<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Chamaemelum nobile</span> (L.) All. (Asteraceae), widely known as Roman chamomile, is a perennial herb native to South-Western Europe, but it is cultivated as a medicinal plant all over Europe and in Africa as well. Dried flowers of the cultivated, double-flowered variety of the species are official in the European Pharmacopoeia (
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">European Pharmacopoeia, 2008</a>). Incorporating the plant in traditional herbal medicinal products has been acknowledged by the European Medicines Agency. The comminuted herbal substance (as tea) and a liquid extract of the plant (extraction solvent: ethanol 70% 
  <span class="italic">v/v</span>) may be used for the symptomatic treatment of mild, spasmodic gastrointestinal complaints including bloating and flatulence. The British Herbal Pharmacopoeia indicates its use as carminative, anti-emetic, antispasmodic, and sedative (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">British Herbal Pharmacopoeia, 1971</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Roman chamomile (RC) has been used as a medicinal plant from the middle ages. The cultivation of the plant started in England in the 16th century (
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Hiller and Melzig, 1999</a>). The double variety of the flower, which now serves as the main commercial drug, has certainly been known since the 18th century (
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">Evans, 1989</a>). The plant gained the name “nobile” (Latin, noble) to illustrate its superior therapeutic efficacy over 
  <span class="italic">Matricaria recutita</span> L. (German chamomile) (
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Hiller and Melzig, 1999</a>). The plant was first listed in the Pharmacopoeia of Württemberg (1741) as a carminative, painkiller, diuretic, and digestive aid (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Lukacs, 1990</a>). In the folk medicine of different regions of Europe, RC has been used for numerous conditions, including dyspepsia, flatulence, nausea and vomiting, anorexia, vomiting of pregnancy, dysmenorrhoea, and specifically for gastrointestinal cramps and flatulent dyspepsia associated with mental stress (
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">Augustin et al., 1948</a>; 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">Rápóti and Romváry, 1974</a>; 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">Melegari et al., 1988</a>; 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">Rossi et al., 1988</a>; 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">Bradley, 1992</a>). In the Mediterranean region, RC tea is consumed to improve appetite and also after meal to prevent indigestion (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Rivera and Obon, 1995</a>; 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">Menendez-Baceta et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">Alarcün et al., 2015</a>). Traditional use of RC is largely related to its supposed smooth muscle-relaxant activity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of the secondary metabolites described from the plant belong to the aliphatic esters (essential oil) (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">Fauconnier et al., 1996</a>), sesquiterpene lactones (
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Bisset, 1994</a>) and flavonoids (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">Herisset et al., 1971</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">1973</a>; 
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">Abou-Zied and Rizk, 1973</a>; 
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Pietta et al., 1991</a>). The polysaccharide content of the dried flower is noteworthy, 3.9% (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Lukacs, 1990</a>). The supposed smooth muscle-relaxant activity of the plant might be attributed to its flavonoid content. Apigenin and luteolin possess remarkable smooth muscle relaxant effects on guinea pig ileum (
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">Lemmens-Gruber et al., 2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although several studies on the bioactivities of RC are available, the majority of these studies were carried out using the essential oil, which is not used medicinally, or the observed activities are not related to the traditional use of the plant. Several studies demonstrate the antimicrobial effects of RC essential oil against different bacterial and fungal strains (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Hänsel et al., 1993</a>; 
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">Piccaglia et al., 1993</a>; 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">Chao et al., 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">Bail et al., 2009</a>), and antifungal activity was demonstrated also for the aqueous extracts of RC (
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Magro et al., 2006</a>). The anti-inflammatory capacity and heat shock protein modulating effects of the flavonoids apigenin and quercetin, as well as the anti-inflammatory activities of α-bisabolol, guajazulene, and chamazulene have been reported in preclinical studies (
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">Viola et al., 1995</a>; 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Baghalian et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">2011</a>; 
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Hernández-Ceruelos et al., 2010</a>). The polysaccharides of RC exerted antiphlogistic effect 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Lukacs, 1990</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the use of RC extract for gastrointestinal problems seems to be related to its presumptive smooth muscle-relaxant effect, interestingly no 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> or 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> studies have been carried out so far to assess this bioactivity. However, in an 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> study an aqueous extract of 
  <span class="italic">C. nobile</span> was demonstrated to induce a vasorelaxant effect through the NO-cGMP pathway or possibly through a combination of Ca
  <span class="sup">2+</span> channel inhibition plus NO-modulating and phosphodiesterase inhibitory mechanisms. After the oral administration of RC aqueous extract, significant hypotensive effect was observed in an animal study on spontaneously hypertensive rats (
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">Zeggwagh et al., 2009</a>), which may be related to the flavonoid content of the plant (
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">Jouad et al., 2001</a>). The clinical efficacy of orally applied preparations has not been studied yet, only the effects of external application (
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">Schrader et al., 1997</a>) and aromatherapeutic use (
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">Wilkinson et al., 1999</a>) have been reported.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of the current study was to assess the effects of a hydroethanolic RC extract, its fractions and essential oil on gastrointestinal and urogenital smooth muscles, including preparations of human jejunum, in order to clarify the rationale for the use of this plant for smooth muscle relaxation. Experiments were carried out with an extract conforming to the monograph of the European Medicines Agency (see in section “Preparation of Herbal Extracts and Isolation of Reference Standards”), and also with the fractions of this extract and with the essential oil of the plant.</p>
</sec>
