<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of NGS technology has expanded the knowledge about the correlation between the human gut microbiota and omega-3 PUFAs. However, the literature in this topic is still in the initial stages. The current literature is listed below and summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="ijms-18-02645-t001">Table 1</xref>. The first report in the literature about the impact of omega-3 fatty acids on human gut microbiota of adults came from a clinical study carried out in 60 overweight (BMI &gt; 25) healthy people, between 40 and 60 years old. In this study, a commercially available probiotic with high concentrations of 
 <italic>Bifidobacteria</italic>, 
 <italic>Lactobacilli</italic>, and 
 <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic> (named VSL#3) was provided in combination with and without an omega-3 nutraceutical supplementation of 180 mg EPA and 120 mg of DHA for six weeks. This study failed to elucidate differences between the probiotic group and the probiotic plus omega-3 group. However, the limitation of this analysis was that the evaluation of microbiota changes was only completed using colony counting on anaerobic or aerobic selective media [
 <xref rid="B12-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Subsequent studies focused more on food and diet impact instead of nutraceutical use of omega-3 PUFAs, likely because omega-3 fatty acids integrated in a food matrix can have a higher positive impact on gut microbiota. Supporting this hypothesis, a randomized crossover trial was completed on 20 middle-aged healthy individuals by administering a high daily dose (4 g) of a mixed DHA/EPA supplement for eight weeks [
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The supplementation was performed using two different formulations: as a nutraceutical in the form of capsules, and as functional drink that was EPA- and DHA-rich. In this study, a taxonomy classification of the whole microbiota of the samples was completed with NGS technology. In this case, no statistically significant changes were observed in the 
 <italic>Firmicutes</italic>/
 <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> phyla ratio for both types of supplementations. On the contrary, analyzing the data at family and genus levels revealed consistent differences associated with both omega-3 PUFA supplementations. In particular, increases in the 
 <italic>Clostridiaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Sutterellaceae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Akkermansiaceae</italic> families were recorded, and these changes were reverted by the washout period. A statistically increased abundance of 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic> and 
 <italic>Oscillospira</italic> genera, associated with a reduction of 
 <italic>Coprococcus</italic> and 
 <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, were found after both omega-3 PUFA supplementations in comparison with before the study and after washout. Instead, an increase in 
 <italic>Lachnospira</italic> and 
 <italic>Roseburia</italic> genera was prominent only after the functional omega-3 drink feeding. So, as previously anticipated, the functional drink had a greater impact on gut microbiota in comparison with nutraceutical supplementation. This study highlighted the increased abundance of butyrate-producing bacterial genera after omega-3 PUFA supplementation [
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Acetate, propionate, and butyrate are the most abundant (&gt;95%) short-chain fatty acids (SCFA) present in gut lumen, as end products of the fermentation of dietary fibers by the gut microbiota. Among the dominant butyrate-producing bacterial taxa, the following genera belonging to the 
 <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic> family of the phylum 
 <italic>Firmicutes</italic> were found: 
 <italic>Eubacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Roseburia</italic>, 
 <italic>Anaerostipes</italic>, and 
 <italic>Coprococcus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The importance of butyrate, and SCFAs in general, are linked to anti-inflammatory properties. Indeed, they have been shown to ameliorate IBD, although their exact mechanism of action is still not completely clear [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
