<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first evidence of the correlation between infant microbiota and omega-3 PUFAs came from the randomized, non-blinded, 2 × 2 intervention study by Nielsen and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In this study, 114 nine-month-old infants were included and randomized to receive cow’s milk or infant formula with or without 5 mL/day of fish oil until the 12th month. In 65 of the 114 infants, the gut microbiota were analyzed in faeces by fingerprint profiles generated by the V3 and V6-8 PCR-DGGE (Denaturing Gradient Gel Electrophoresis). The study revealed that consumption of fish oil in cow’s milk groups created a differential fingerprint profile, and this difference was not found in the infant formula groups. The authors explained that difference with the fact that cow’s milk contains considerably less omega-3 PUFAs in comparison with infant formula, so omega-3 PUFAs can have a dose-response effect in changing the gut microbiota profile [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Subsequently, the same research group performed a double-blinded randomized parallel intervention in 132 nine-month-old infants, to analyze microbiota differences after nine months of daily supplementation with 5 mL fish oil (1.6 g EPA and DHA) or sunflower oil (3.1 g linolenic acid, C18:2 omega-6) [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Differences between groups were analyzed in faeces using fingerprint profiles generated analyzing Terminal Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphism (T-RFLP). Interestingly, the authors found that fish oil caused significant changes in the microbiota in comparison with sunflower oil, but only among children who had stopped breastfeeding before the study. The authors determined that the cessation of breastfeeding opened the infant microbiota to new bacteria. Therefore, breastfeeding likely causes a delay in gut microbial maturation. Indeed, they found that the T-RFLP pattern of non-breastfed infants at the 9th month was more similar to those at the 18th month than that of the partial breastfed nine-month-old infants [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
