<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, the first deeper analysis in infants using NGS technology was a randomized controlled trial, where 32 infants born premature with enterostomy were randomized to receive either the usual nutritional therapy or an enteral supplementation of a fish and safflower blend oil until bowel reanastomosis, for a maximum of 10 weeks [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The experimental PUFA group showed greater bacterial diversity combined with lower abundance of some pathogenic bacteria, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Streptococcus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium</italic>, and some genera of the 
 <italic class="italic">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> family, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Pantoea</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Serratia</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Citrobacter</italic> [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. In a population-based prospective human cohort study [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], 81 maternal-neonate dyads were studied to understand whether a maternal high-fat diet can influence the neonatal and infant gut microbiota. Stool and meconium were collected from neonates until six weeks of age, and a dietary questionnaire was completed by the mothers to estimate fat, sugar, and fiber intakes. From the questionnaire, two different groups were identified: a high-fat maternal diet group, with a 43.1% fat intake, above the recommended limit of 20–35%, and a low-fat maternal diet group, with a 24.4% fat intake. This cohort analysis revealed that a maternal high-fat diet during gestation influenced the neonatal microbiota, resulting in a significant depletion of 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroides</italic> in the high-fat maternal diet group that persists beyond delivery, in infants four to six weeks old [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-18-02645" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. In that study, fatty acid types were not differentiated. However, considering that the levels for sugar and fiber intakes were not in line with the recommended range (i.e., sugar mean 59.6%, recommended &lt;25%; fiber mean 24.9%, recommended &gt;25%), the main fat intake was assumed to be from saturated fatty acids, common in the Western American diet. Therefore, as discussed above, the omega-3 PUFAs favor the butyrate-producing bacterial genera, whereas a diet rich in saturated fats can depauperate the gut microbiota of these commensal bacteria.
</p>
