<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="st1">
  <title>Aim:</title>
  <p>The study investigated the chemical composition, antioxidant content, and antioxidant activity of 
   <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> honey (TVH) and 
   <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> essential oil (OVEO) and their mixture effect on carbon tetrachloride (CCl
   <sub>4</sub>)-induced toxicity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st2">
  <title>Materials and Methods:</title>
  <p>The study conducted physicochemical characterization and chemical analysis of TVH and OVEO with the use of gas chromatography–mass spectrometry and high-performance liquid chromatograph (HPLC). The antioxidant activity of TVH and OVEO was done with the use of 1,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical scavenging activity. The study used nine groups of rats to investigate the effect of TVH, OVEO, and a mixture of TVH and OVEO (HEM) on CCl
   <sub>4</sub>-induced toxicity. Intraperitoneal injection of CCl
   <sub>4</sub> (1 mL/100 g) was used to induce toxicity. The doses of TVH and OVEO were 1 mg/kg.b.wt, and 50 mg/kg.b.wt, respectively. HEM contains TVH (1 mg/kg.b.wt) and OVEO (50 mg/kg.b.wt).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st3">
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p>TVH has a high content of phenols, flavonoids, and flavanols. HPLC analysis showed that TVH contains, for the 1
   <sup>st</sup> time, epicatechin gallate, and at a high concentration. OVEO includes a high percentage of carvacrol and thymol. With the use of DPPH, OVEO was more potent than TVH. CCl
   <sub>4</sub> caused significant liver and kidney damage and lipid disorders, which were alleviated by HVT, OVEO, and HEM. HVT was more potent than OVEO (p&lt;0.05), and HEM was more potent than HVT and OVEO (p&lt;0.05).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st4">
  <title>Conclusion:</title>
  <p>The study identified high content of epicatechin gallate for the 1
   <sup>st</sup> time in TVH, and OVEO contains a high percentage of thymol and carvacrol. Epicatechin gallate might be useful as a marker for TVH. Mixing OVEO and TVH significantly potentiated their protection against CCl
   <sub>4</sub>-induced liver and kidney toxicity.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
