<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Even, if significant changes were made to the structures of ar-turmerone, could ameliorate their anticancer effects. Initially, a study explained that the structural changes of ar-turmerone exhibits remarkable anticancer activities by the reduction of size at aromatic ring and their analog formation at the 6-position as observed by a decrease in effective dose-50% value (ED
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>) against lymphocytic leukemia (L1210) cell study [
 <xref rid="B42-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Baik et al. further explained that the orthogonal arrangement between the side chain and aromatic ring of ar-turmerone is responsible for its cytotoxic activities. For this, they considered various substituents on the 1 (or 2) naphthyl group and phenyl ring rather than phenyl group of ar-turmerone and with the help of bioassay compared their cytotoxic activities of these structural analogs in three different cell lines (L1210, HL-60 and K562). The ED
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values were observed to be more for HL-60 and K-562 cells than L 1210 which stated that the flat structure of aromatic ring was responsible for its enhanced cytotoxic activities. The reason behind this was attributable to the enlargement of aromatic ring and the restricted rotation of single bond between aromatic ring and C-6 due to the introduction of various substituents at the ortho position of the phenyl ring [
 <xref rid="B43-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Another study identified that changes in morphological characters in ar-turmerone triggered apoptosis in human myeloid leukemia HL-60 cells in a concentration-dependent manner, as it produced internucleosomal DNA fragmentation of approximately 200 bases-pair multiples [
 <xref rid="B44-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Collectively, these studies elucidate that the anticancer activities of turmerones and their isomers on different cell lines trigger cell cycle arrest, apoptosis and their mechanism of action is comparable to curcuminoids. Additionally, the combination of turmerones with curcumin would enhance the bioavailability of curcumin tremendously. Therefore, these studies shape this bioactive component as a novel and potent anticancer tool.
</p>
