<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Only a few studies have directly compared the potential medicinal properties of stingless bee products (
 <xref rid="biomolecules-10-00923-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In a study by Ismail et al., each of SBH, SBP, and beebread (fermented bee pollen by lactic ferments [
 <xref rid="B131-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]) extracts were compared for their antioxidant and anticancer effects [
 <xref rid="B16-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. SBP, SBH and beebread all contained phenolic content and displayed antioxidant capacity relating to the levels of phenolic content, respectively, with SBP showing the highest antioxidant capacity [
 <xref rid="B16-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Additionally, treatment with SBP showed the highest growth inhibition in human breast adenocarcinoma cells, compared to SBH and beebread extracts, respectively [
 <xref rid="B16-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Another study examined the cytotoxic activity of crude extracts of SBP, SBH, and bee pollen from different stingless bee species against human breast, lung, liver, gastric and colon cancer cell lines [
 <xref rid="B14-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The SBP and SBH showed higher cytotoxic activities than bee pollen, with SBP exhibiting the highest overall cytotoxic activity against all cell lines, particularly from bee species 
 <italic>T. incisa</italic> and 
 <italic>Trigona fuscobalteata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B14-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Furthermore, the potential immunomodulatory effect of SBP and SBH has been examined in a murine 
 <italic>S. typhi</italic> infection model [
 <xref rid="B129-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. Both SBH and SBP increased FoxP3 mRNA expression (transcription factor of regulatory T cells) following infection, with the highest increase seen in the SBP treated group [
 <xref rid="B132-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>].
</p>
