<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The competitive advantage of sweet potato over 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> could be used to reduce 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> growth and reproductive ability in tropical and subtropical agricultural regions suitable for cultivation of sweet potato. Both plants have similar growth forms and climatic requirements, and sweet potato is a high value crop, and thus we recommend planting sweet potato in areas infested by 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic>, perhaps as part of a rotation involving more vulnerable crops. Sweet potato could even be planted in habitats such as waste areas not currently cultivated in order to reduce 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> populations. Our results showed that various components of reproduction for 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> were significantly reduced by suppression of plant growth; the original data is available online [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Flowering phenology was impacted by sweet potato competition, and delayed flowering phenology, reduced duration of flowering and fruiting and increased duration of bud formation resulted in reduced pollinator visits and seed set for 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic>. Finally, high cover of sweet potato shading 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> plants also reduced pollinator visits, seeds number, and seedling populations of 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic>. Thus the mechanism by which sweet potato reduced sexual reproduction in 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> was essentially twofold: causing a delay in flowering phenology and reducing pollinator visits. In addition to utilizing sweet potato, research in this study and other recent studies revealed that control of 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> ideally should take place during the seedling period when 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> is most vulnerable and should be comprehensive for optimal results, employing both chemical and cultural control. Thus in the case of our study region in southern Asia, the most effective timing of control is in the peak of sexual seedling emergence in May–June. The potential for utilizing a crop like sweet potato to compete with an invasive plant may well apply to many other agronomic settings where other management techniques (e.g., chemical control, mechanical control or classical biological control) are unreliable or are associated with environmental concerns. The scenario of controlling 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> by utilizing a crop with a similar growth form may provide a useful model for similar management strategies in other systems.
</p>
