<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>FIV-RT is a heterodimeric protein consisting of two subunits, p51 and p66. The p66 subunit contains N-terminal RNA-dependent DNA polymerase (RDDP) and C-terminal RNaseH domains, while the p51 subunit contains only RDDP domain. The RDDP domain of both subunits contains four subdomains which are fingers, palm, thumb, and connection, but the arrangement of these subdomains is different [
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The inhibition of RT has mainly focused on the catalytic site on the RDDP domain of p66 and the non-nucleotide binding pocket (NNBP) which is located approximately 10 Å from the catalytic site. Two types of drugs have been used to inhibit FIV-RT by binding to these pockets. The first type of inhibitors is nucleotide analog or nucleoside analog reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NtARTIs or NARTIs). These inhibitors are widely used as antiviral drugs to treat viral infections in both human and cats. They share structural similarities to the natural substrates of the enzyme, therefore, both inhibitors bind at the active site of FIV-RT. Zidovudine (3´-azido-2´,3´-dideoxythymidine or AZT) was the first antiviral drug used to treat HIV infection in humans, and it was then applied to cure FIV infection in cats [
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In human, 1-5 mg/kg AZT was injected intravenously every 4-8 h for 2 weeks, and then, 2-10 mg/kg AZT was given orally for another 2 weeks. All doses used could elevate number of helper-inducer lymphocyte and patient’s weight [
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In cats, AZT could inhibit FIV replication in Crandell-Rees feline kidney cells and could improve the clinical status of the infected cats [
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Application of AZT on infected cats at a dose of 2.5 mg/kg of body weight every 12 h for 3 weeks could improve general clinical status and CD4/CD8 ratio at average degrees of 0.6 and 0.2, respectively [
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Although AZT could inhibit FIV replication 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and could improve the CD4/CD8 ratio, long-term treatment of FIV infection in cats could cause FIV mutation [
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Moreover, the viral load was slightly increased in some cats after discontinuing the treatment [
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Other NARTIs introduced to treat FIV-infected cats were 9-(2-phosphonylmethoxyethyl) adenine (PMEA) which showed more potent anti-FIV-RT activity than AZT. However, PMEA showed more severe side effects than AZT, which limits the use of PMEA for the treatment of FIV infection in cats [
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The second type of antiviral drug is non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs). NNRTIs are hydrophobic compounds with diverse structures [
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The binding of NNRTIs at the NNBP, which is located in close proximity to the active site, causes conformational change of the catalytic site leading to inhibition of viral replication [
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Nevirapine, is one of the FDA-approved NNRTIs anti-HIV drugs, has shown to be ineffective against FIV [
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Thus, the finding of new NNRTIs against FIV-RT will be a major breakthrough for the treatment of FIV-infected cats.
</p>
