<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-medicines-04-00001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-medicines-04-00001" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Essential Oil Compositions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils obtained by the different isolation procedures are characterized by the presence of cyclic and acyclic monoterpenes, which may or may not possess oxygen atoms in their structures (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00001-t001" href="#medicines-04-00001-t001">Table 1</a>). All of oil components are divided into eight groups, including cyclic monoterpene hydrocarbons (I), acyclic monoterpene hydrocarbons (II), acyclic oxygenated monoterpenoids (III), aldehydes (IV), cyclic oxygenated monoterpenoids (V), sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (VI), oxygenated sesquiterpenoids (VII), and coumarins (VIII).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-medicines-04-00001" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Antimicrobial Activity of Fingered Citron Oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MICs of three fingered citron oils against Gram-positive bacteria, Gram-negative bacteria, and fungi, are reported in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00001-t002" href="#medicines-04-00001-t002">Table 2</a>. In particular, the ultrafiltration oil showed notable in vitro antimicrobial activity against 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (MIC = 156 μg/mL), 
   <span class="italic">Bacillus cereus</span> (MIC = 156 μg/mL), 
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> (MIC = 39 μg/mL), and 
   <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span> (MIC = 20 μg/mL).The vacuum distillation oil was only marginally active against 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (MIC = 625 μg/mL), 
   <span class="italic">Bacillus cereus</span> (MIC = 313 μg/mL), and 
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> (MIC = 625 μg/mL), but was also strongly active against 
   <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span> (MIC = 156 μg/mL).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-medicines-04-00001" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Antioxidant Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity of essential oils is another biological property of great interest for potential utilization in cosmetic supplements or functional food products. The use of a DPPH· scavenging assay is the most routinely practiced method for the assessment of anti-radical properties of different samples. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="medicines-04-00001-f002" href="#medicines-04-00001-f002">Figure 2</a>, the antioxidant efficiency of the tested essential oils primarily relies on their concentration, and their free radical scavenging effectiveness was as follows, given in descending order and based on the increasing median inhibitory concentration (IC
   <sub>50</sub>) values: vacuum distillation oil (1.02 mg/mL) &gt; hydrodistillation oil (1.19 mg/mL) &gt; ultrafiltration oil (1.42 mg/mL).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
