<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nutrition of laying hens, the characteristics of the feed (composition in nutrients, energy content, but also feedstuff texture and presentation), and the mode of feed delivery throughout the day affect, not only egg weight, but also to a lesser extent, egg-yolk and egg-white proportion [
 <xref rid="B137-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>]. The quality of the diet for pullets will influence the egg weight essentially at the onset of lay but it is much less significant when considering the whole period of lay [
 <xref rid="B137-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>]. The dietary characteristics include the level of calcium supply as well as its particular size. Dietary calcium in a particular form allow hens to express a specific appetite for calcium at the end of the day, that is stored and further assimilated during the night when the shell formation take place [
 <xref rid="B138-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">138</xref>]. The egg weight is influenced by the daily energy consumption of hens. High energetic diet and the dietary supply of linoleic acid increase the egg weight. This effect is particularly relevant at the onset of laying (22–32 weeks) and much less pronounced in older hens [
 <xref rid="B139-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>]. Egg weight is also increased by the level of dietary proteins, and some studies have revealed that methionine was the main limiting amino acid as its presence in the hen’s diet is positively correlated with egg weight [
 <xref rid="B140-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>]. Additionally, energy intake depends on the protein source considering that laying hens are traditionally fed corn, wheat, and soybean meal. The presence of antinutritional factors in the diet (protease inhibitors and proteins that are highly resistant to digestive proteases such as convicilin, glycinin, cruciferin [
 <xref rid="B141-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">141</xref>]) may affect the overall digestibility of the feed by the hens and subsequent egg weight. However, the content in major egg components is relatively stable and the variability depends essentially on the proportion of the albumen to the yolk, which exhibit very contrasted composition (See 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-nutrients-11-00684" class="xref">Section 2</xref>). In contrast, the fatty-acid profile of the yolk and the content of micronutrients such as vitamins and trace minerals (See 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot2-nutrients-11-00684" class="xref">Section 2.2</xref>) or of carotenoids are very variable and directly rely on diet composition [
 <xref rid="B137-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>].
</p>
