<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The fatty-acid profile of an egg, incorporated in triglycerides and phospholipids, directly reflects the composition of fatty acids in the hen’s diet. In contrast, the enrichment of the hen’s diet with saturated fatty acids has less influence of the yolk lipid profile. The saturated and unsaturated fatty-acid content of the hen’s diet can be modified by the inclusion of oil or feedstuffs showing a high degree of unsaturated fatty acid such as fish, chia, flaxseeds [
 <xref rid="B142-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">142</xref>,
 <xref rid="B143-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">143</xref>], olive, or soy oils (see Reference [
 <xref rid="B144-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">144</xref>] for a review). For instance, including olive oil in a hen’s diet favors the incorporation of mono-unsaturated fatty acids (in particular, oleic acid content) in the yolk, while soil oil increases that of unsaturated n-6 fatty acids (linoleic acid) [
 <xref rid="B144-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">144</xref>]. More recently, results obtained with an enrichment of the diet with microalgae or linseeds have revealed the potential of these compounds to increase the content of yolk in n-3 fatty acids (more than 3- and 4-fold increase, respectively) [
 <xref rid="B145-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">145</xref>]. A similar trend in increasing the polyunsaturated content of yolk was observed with marigold extract powder [
 <xref rid="B146-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">146</xref>], Schizochytrium microalgae [
 <xref rid="B147-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">147</xref>], prebiotic and probiotic combination [
 <xref rid="B148-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">148</xref>], etc. To conclude, it is relatively easy to enrich the egg in some unsaturated fatty acids, of interest for human health. The challenge remains to identify animal and vegetable sources of polyunsaturated fatty acids that increase the content of these fatty acids in yolk without affecting its technological and/or sensorial quality, to suit both the food industry requirements (egg products) and consumer demand.
</p>
