<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Caco-2 cell monolayer permeability model has emerged as the leading 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> tool for the assessment of potential bioavailability of drugs in the human body. Established by Fogh in 1974,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>
 </sup> this model has been extensively used in predicting 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> oral absorption of natural and synthetic products in humans.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>
 </sup> Caco-2 cells provide an excellent physical and biochemical mimic of the human intestinal epithelial membrane.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>
 </sup> When the cells are cultured following specific protocols
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>
 </sup> and they reach expected differentiation and confluency, they express all the major transport proteins present in the human small intestine such as active transporters including sugar transporters, e.g., SGLT1, GLUT2, and GLUT5,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> thus allowing passive diffusion as well as active and passive transport to be investigated.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup> They also express efflux proteins such as P-glycoprotein (P-gp), breast cancer resistance protein (BCRP), and multidrug resistance-associated protein 2 (MRP-2).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup> This model enables both apical to basolateral and basolateral to apical transport to be studied, with the apical compartment mimicking the intestinal lumen and the basal compartment mimicking the bloodstream. This model assesses the apparent permeability coefficient (
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>app</sub>) values of molecules, which is a measure of the rate at which a compound can cross an area of the cell monolayer. The 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>app</sub> of a number of passively diffused drugs was plotted against the absorbed fraction of these drugs after oral administration in humans and a clear correlation emerged, suggesting that this assay can be used to predict the absorption in humans, provided that factors such as the drug solubility and metabolism can be accounted for with the help of other assays.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>
 </sup> These advantages made this model our first choice to investigate the potential bioavailability of compounds isolated from 
 <italic>G. pentaphyllum</italic>.
</p>
