<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The biosynthesis of lignans in plants has been reviewed [
 <xref rid="B236-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>,
 <xref rid="B237-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>], but no current review focusing on sesame is available. Lignans of sesame and other plant species originate from the oxidative dimerization of two molecules of coniferyl alcohol, which is the central metabolite of the phenylpropanoids pathway [
 <xref rid="B238-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. The condensation of coniferyl alcohol yields pinoresinol through a laccase enzyme while the stereoselectivity of the reaction is controlled by a dirigent protein [
 <xref rid="B85-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B239-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00883-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Dirigent proteins are widespread in land plants. They are involved in the dimerization of molecules through radical-radical coupling [
 <xref rid="B240-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>,
 <xref rid="B241-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>]. In the case of pinoresinol formation, the first step consists of the formation of radicals of substrate coniferyl alcohol, which is presumably catalyzed by a laccase enzyme, producing free monolignol radicals (CA·). Two CA· molecules bind to a dirigent protein, which enables stereospecific dimerization to either (+) or (-)-pinoresinol, depending on the plant species [
 <xref rid="B239-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>]. Dirigent proteins form pockets with conserved amino acid residues that control the orientation of the substrate [
 <xref rid="B239-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>]. In the case of 
 <italic>S. indicum</italic>, there is a putative dirigent protein, XP_011080883 [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], in which most of the differing amino acids match those of the (+) enantiomer, in line with the predicted (+)-pinoresinol in this plant species.
</p>
