<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first two glucosylation steps of (+)-sesaminol were previously identified in 
 <italic>S. indicum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B247-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">247</xref>]. Only recently, the last missing step was discovered by Ono and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B248-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">248</xref>]. The first step is the 2-
 <italic>O</italic>-glycosylation of (+)-sesaminol to produce sesaminol monoglucoside (SMG) by the enzyme UGT71A9. Homologs of UGT71A9 were found in 
 <italic>S. radiatum</italic> (UGT71A10) and 
 <italic>S. alatum</italic> (UGT71A8) [
 <xref rid="B247-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">247</xref>], evidencing the conservation of these steps in 
 <italic>Sesamum</italic> spp. The glucosylation of SMG leads to diglucoside SDG(β1→6) [(+)-sesaminol 2-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucosyl-(1→6)-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucoside] or SDG(β1→2) through consecutive glucosylation of the 6′ or 2′ -hydroxyl group of the sugar moiety by the enzyme UGT94D1 or UGT94AG1, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00883-f009">Figure 9</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B248-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">248</xref>]. Until recently, it was not known which glucosylation step of SMG occurs first, β1→6 or β1→2 glucosylation. Ono and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B248-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">248</xref>] showed that β1→2 followed by β1→6 glucosylation is the major pathway. With this discovery, the missing last step for STG biosynthesis was established. The same authors found an enzyme similar to UGT94D1, called UGT94AA2, which interacts with UGT71A9, UGT94AG1, and, interestingly, also with CYP81Q1 (the piperitol/sesamin synthase) producing, what the authors called, an STG metabolon. In this proposed metabolon for STG biosynthesis, CYP81Q1 acts as a membrane bound protein, which increases the efficiency of sequential glucosylation steps by recruiting three UGT enzymes (UGT71A9, UGT94AA2, and UGT94AG1).
</p>
