<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0012">Membrane-free air cathode single-chamber MFCs (SC-MFCs) were constructed in cylindrical tubes made by polymethyl methacrylate (PMMA) (cell sizing ID = 54 mm, 
 <italic>L</italic> = 95 mm) with the working volume of ca. 230 mL (i.e.,
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg">
   <mfrac>
    <mrow>
     <mi>π</mi>
     <msup>
      <mrow>
       <mo>(</mo>
       <mn>5.4</mn>
       <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
       <mi mathvariant="normal">c</mi>
       <mi mathvariant="normal">m</mi>
       <mo>)</mo>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mn>2</mn>
      </mrow>
     </msup>
    </mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mn>4</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mfrac>
   <mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mo>
   <mrow>
    <mo>(</mo>
    <mrow>
     <mn>9.5</mn>
     <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
     <mn>2</mn>
     <mo linebreak="badbreak">×</mo>
     <mn>0.3</mn>
    </mrow>
    <mo>)</mo>
   </mrow>
   <mi>c</mi>
   <mi>m</mi>
   <mo>≈</mo>
   <mn>231.3</mn>
   <mi>m</mi>
   <mi>L</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>). Porous carbon cloth (CeTech) (without waterproofing catalyst) with a projected area of ca. 22.9 cm
 <sup>2</sup> (i.e., π × 2.7
 <sup>2</sup>) on one side was used as anode electrodes. The air cathode was almost identical to the anode in size and consisted of a polytetrafluoroethylene (PTFE) diffusion layer (CeTech) on the air-facing side. Detailed procedures of bacterial cultures for MFCs (e.g., bacterial acclimation, cell immobilization, bioelectricity stimulation) were described elsewhere [
 <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. To guarantee stable and reproducible electrochemical characteristics to be fully expressed, seeding microbe- 
 <italic>Shewanella haliotis</italic> was used to inoculate open system LB-based MFCs for at least 1 month acclimation. Then, two domesticated microbial cultures (i.e., consortia A and consortia B) with high electricity-generating capacities were adopted as study MFC platforms for comparison. To explore the electrochemical influences of different 
 <italic>Camellia</italic> GT extracts on the same MFC, the same microbial culture (e.g., consortia A) was seeded to two blank MFCs for comparison (e.g., marked as MFC-A1 and MFC-A2).
</p>
