<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par52" class="p">As the critical line, the intestinal barrier can protect against pathogenic agents and luminal antigens. In the current study, dietary inclusion of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae up-regulated the expression of intestinal barrier genes expression in the colonic mucosa, such as 
 <italic class="italic">ZO-1</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">occludin</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">mucin-1</italic>, suggesting that 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae may enhance the integrity of the mucous layer, and then generate a host-friendly gut environment which can defend against pathogen infection. To the best of our knowledge, our study is the first to test partially 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion in the diets of finishing pigs, and the available information on the effect of dietary 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae inclusion on mucosal response involved in colonic health is very limited. A previous study has shown that SCFAs, especially butyrate can maintain the gut integrity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>]. As mentioned above, diet inclusion of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae increased the concentrations of total SCFAs and butyrate, and correlation analysis also revealed that the total SCFAs and butyrate concentrations and SCFA-producing bacteria were positively correlated with mRNA expression levels of 
 <italic class="italic">ZO-1</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">occludin</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">mucin-1</italic>. Therefore, the high total SCFAs and butyrate concentrations and the abundance or counts of SCFA-producing bacteria after the 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae treatment may lead to up-regulation of intestinal barrier genes expression, but further studies will be required to clarify the underlying mechanisms. Nonetheless, these findings suggest that diet inclusion of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae down-regulated the expression of pro- inflammatory genes, while up-regulated the expression of anti-inflammatory and intestinal barrier genes.
</p>
