<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0210">There is not enough available literature data on spectrophotometrically determined PAC for the six Lamiaceae species that we have studied. However, the results of PAC analysis presented in this paper showed that these compounds have higher values in both methanolic and aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>Ov</italic> in comparison with 
 <italic>Tv</italic> methanolic and aqueous extracts, which is coherent with the results reported by 
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Skendi et al., (2017)</xref> for 
 <italic>Ov</italic> and 
 <italic>T. capitatus</italic> extracts. Moreover, their HPLC analysis showed that the most abundant phenolic acid in these extracts was rosmarinic acid (12.36 and 3.26 mg/g for 
 <italic>Ov</italic> and 
 <italic>T. capitatus</italic> methanolic extracts, respectively, and 0.98 and 0.73 mg/g for 
 <italic>Ov</italic> and 
 <italic>T. capitatus</italic> aqueous extracts, respectively), however these results are not in accordance with our results, since we have obtained similar values of rosmarinic acid in these samples (about 60.00 mg/g for the methanolic extracts and about 30.00 mg/g for the aqueous extracts). Furthermore, 
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Roby et al. (2013)</xref> reported a rather low amount of rosmarinic and caffeic acids in methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>Om</italic> and especially in 
 <italic>Tv</italic> from Egypt, which is different from the results reported in this study. This discordance might be present due to the different climate conditions and geographic locations where these plants were growing. In support of this it goes the fact that 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Vladimir-Knežević et al. (2014)</xref> after analyzing 
 <italic>Ov</italic>, 
 <italic>Tv</italic>, 
 <italic>Tc</italic> and 
 <italic>Tm,</italic> among other species from the Lamiaceae family from Croatia, reported similar value ratios for rosmarinic, caffeic and chlorogenic acids in their ethanolic extracts to the ones from the 
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.
</p>
