<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A number of secondary metabolites in many classes, such as monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, diterpenes, triterpenes, iridoid glycosides, flavonoids, and phenylethanoid glycosides, have been isolated and identified in the fruits, flowers, leaves, stems and roots of 
 <italic>L. camara</italic> [
 <xref rid="B61-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The biological activity of some of those compounds has been associated with anti-microbial, anti-fungal, anti-herbivore, and pharmacological activities. The allelopathic activity of most of the identified compounds in 
 <italic>L. camara</italic> has not yet been determined. However, some of those compounds may possess phytotoxic activity [
 <xref rid="B61-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Phytotoxic substances in plants can be released into the rhizosphere soil under the plants and neighboring environments either by rainfall leachates and volatile compounds from living plant parts of 
 <italic>L. camara</italic> or by decomposition of plant residues and act as allelochemicals [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-10-01028" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. As described the previous section, the leachates from the plant parts of 
 <italic>L. camara</italic>, residues, and rhizosphere soil 
 <italic>L. camara</italic> suppressed the germination and growth of several other plant species. Therefore, allelochemicals of 
 <italic>L. camara</italic> are probably released into its rhizosphere soil under the canopy and neighboring environments.
</p>
