<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0040">Improving the yield of active ingredients by optimizing the processing methods is a good way to achieve the above goals (
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Mishra et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">Nabet et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018a</xref>). Typically, the active ingredients in medicinal plants are secondary metabolites that are closely related to cultivation methods, field management, harvest time, primary processing in the producing area, deep processing, storage, and transportation, etc. (
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">Kessler and Kalske, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Canter et al., 2005</xref>). Specifically, the processing methods including removing impurities, stacking, steaming, slicing, and drying have significant effects on the contents of active ingredients of Chinese medicinal materials (
 <xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">Nozad et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Azizi, 2008</xref>). The primary processing in the producing area is the first key step for the quality formation of Chinese medicinal materials. Previous studies have demonstrated that primary processing in the producing area have a great influence on the yield, quality, and efficacy of the medicinal materials (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2009</xref>). In the traditional technology of primary processing, it is specified that post-harvest treatment and processing of medicinal materials in the producing area should follow the natural rules of the formation of active ingredients. Meanwhile, the specific characteristics of raw materials during the process of storage and transportation should be carefully considered to ensure the quality of medicinal materials (
 <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
