<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The slide-dip method recommended by Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] and the Chinese Agricultural Standard NYT 1154.12-2008 (Guideline for laboratory bioassay of pesticides, Part 12: Slide-dip method immersion) [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] was used for bioassays. The adult mites was picked up with a fine brush and the dorsal surface of the mite was attached to one end of a glass slide by a double-sided adhesive tape. Each slide contained approximate 40 mites and was maintained at 25 ± 1 °C and 65–80% relative humidity for 4 h, following which the mites were examined under a binocular microscope to remove any dead or unanimated ones, thereby leaving only the vivid adults as the original number. The test compounds were diluted to different concentrations by water with 9% acetone and 1% Tween-80. Then each slide with mites was dipped into the given solution for 3 s. The mites dipped into water with 9% acetone and 1% Tween-80 served as controls. The extra solution at the edge of the slides was carefully absorbed by filter paper. Mite mortality was determined under a binocular microscope 24 h after treatment based on movement of the legs or abdomen when prodded by a fine brush. All treatments were replicated 4 times. The mortality had to be corrected by applying Abbott’s formula as follows [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]: 
 <disp-formula id="FD1-molecules-22-01873" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mtext class="mtext">Corrected mortality</mtext>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">test </mi>
       <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
       <mi class="mi">mortality</mi>
       <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
       <mo class="mo">%</mo>
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <mi class="mi">control</mi>
       <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
       <mi class="mi">mortality</mi>
       <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
       <mo class="mo">%</mo>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mn class="mn">100</mn>
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <mi class="mi">control</mi>
       <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
       <mi class="mi">mortality</mi>
       <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
       <mo class="mo">%</mo>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo class="mo">×</mo>
     <mn class="mn">100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
