<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Policosanol is a mixture of long-chain (C20 to C36) aliphatic primary alcohols exhibiting various beneficial effects on the human health. It was originally isolated from sugar cane wax and is also found in a number of other natural sources such as beeswax and vegetable oils [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Policosanol may be effective in the treatment of hypercholesterolemia by inhibiting hepatic cholesterol biosynthesis, enhancing LDL catabolism and increasing high density lipoprotein levels in serum [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. These aliphatic alcohols have also been shown to possess anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Octacosanol (C28-OH), the main active policosanol, has gained attention due to its health benefits including anti-parkinsonian, antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Triacontanol (C30-OH) is able to induce anti-inflammatory responses in animals, prevent oxidative stress and inhibit lipid peroxidation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Millán et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] revealed that the nutraceutical combination containing policosanol, berberine, and red yeast rice induced significant improvements in plasma lipids. Therefore, there is growing interest in the identification of natural sources of policosanol for the functional foods and nutraceutical applications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Contents and compositions of policosanol in different plant sources such as rice bran, wheat bran, sugar cane wax, corn kernel, green tea leaves, grain sorghum, perilla seeds and grape seed have been reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].
</p>
