<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Three principal means are generally utilized to control the alligator weed, being physical
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>, chemical
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> and biological removal
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Physical methods are mainly to remove invasive plants by manual and mechanical methods; chemical methods are to spray chemical herbicides such as glyphosate to cause plant death; biological methods are mainly to control plant growth by natural enemies, soil animals and soil microorganisms. These methods are usually suffering from expensive costs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>, lack of durability
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>, risks of accelerating invasion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> and producing herbicide-resistant weeds
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>, leading to poor efficiency of invasion control. However, allelopathy found its role in successful replacement control of invasive weeds
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>, consequently being introduced to combat the challenges of environmental pollution and herbicide resistance development
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. Simultaneously, allelochemicals could be produced and degraded under natural conditions, avoiding the risks of secondary contamination during chemical control. A diverse array of allelochemicals are produced by plants, such as phenolic compounds, terpenoids, glycosteroids and alkaloids
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. These chemicals are released by volatilization, leaching, root exudation and decomposition
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. Rhizosphere biochemistry that is shaped by allelopathy may drive geographic co-evolutionary trajectories, affecting the coexistence of species and the development of plant communities, ultimately resulting in an invasion control
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
