<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Biological invasions are an important aspect of anthropogenic global change and are considered to be one of the major threats to biodiversity worldwide (Sala et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). A well‐documented impact of species invasions is to reduce native biodiversity, species abundances, change community patterns, and ecosystem processes such as nutrient cycling in invaded communities (Dogra et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Ehrenfeld, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Vilà et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>)⁠. However, it is difficult to disentangle cause and effect of an invasion. An alien species can invade an intact ecosystem and cause changes there, thus be the “driver” of the changes (Bauer, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Didham et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; MacDougall &amp; Turkington, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>)⁠. Alternatively, invasion may be facilitated by earlier ecosystem changes, such as global warming, land use change, or disturbances. Then the invasion is only a symptom, and the invader a “passenger” of the underlying change (Bauer, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Didham et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; MacDougall &amp; Turkington, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>)⁠. Drivers and passengers are the extreme positions of a continuum, and several invasive species rather fall in‐between those categories (Bauer, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>)⁠. Such “back‐seat drivers” benefit from previous changes, but once established they become drivers of further changes (Bauer, 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Another challenge in assessing the impact of an invader are context‐dependencies. Invasion can, for example, depend on ecosystem, invasion stage, or species traits (Kueffer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37135-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>)⁠. The more an invader is a passenger of changes, characteristics of the native ecosystem such as habitat conditions and species composition of the receiving community should influence the outcome of invasion and lead to differences between habitats. Invasion of a passenger is rather unlikely the more it relies on previous ecosystem changes. Knowledge about driver and passenger characteristics of an invader and context‐dependencies is important to understand invasion processes and to develop more targeted management plans.
</p>
