<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, this was not enough to deduce that the protein was spanning the membrane. For example, Gramicidin could be acting as a rapid carrier, shuttling ions across the lipid bilayer, as is the case for ionophores like valinomycin. Alternatively, the protein could be modifying the membrane in some defined way that facilitates the passage of ions, akin to the ideas presented in the past, e.g., the Davson–Danielli model. To get to the idea of actual integral membrane proteins with defined structures, parallel efforts in membrane protein biochemistry were pivotal. It was long known that biological cell membranes were composed of proteins in high amounts; however, purification of these proteins led to an interesting result. Proteins obtained from the membrane fractions were mainly insoluble in water and often aggregated (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Richardson et al., 1963</xref>). This suggested that the proteins that associated with membranes were somehow different in their physical nature compared with the vast number of soluble proteins studied so far. The next big piece of evidence came from electron microscopy freeze-fracture studies that split the lipid bilayer between the two leaflets. This directly showed that there were defects in the membrane that would appear as a positive signal in one leaflet, while leaving a negative impression, or hole, in the opposite layer (
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moor and Mühlethaler, 1963</xref>). This provided the necessary evidence that proteins associated with membranes were in fact embedded in the lipid bilayer. With all of this accumulating evidence, Singer and Nicolson proposed the mosaic part of their fluid mosaic model (
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singer and Nicolson, 1972</xref>), the idea of integral membrane proteins that are hydrophobic in nature and reside stably within the hydrophobic lipid bilayer. With further research in purification of membrane fractions and functional reconstitution (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Miller and Racker, 1979</xref>), the idea of integral membrane proteins acting as ion channels, transporters, active pumps, and receptors soon became accepted.
</p>
