<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell-based toxicity results</div>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the cell viability assay for the Vero E6 line, it was shown in the first reading after 24 h of exposure that there was toxic activity at concentrations of 4.4 mg/mL and 2.2 mg/mL of oil, inducing cell death at 93.91% and 2.32%, respectively. However, the lower oil concentrations of 1.1 mg/ml, 0.55 mg/ml, and 0.275 mg/ml did not affect the viability of the cells. In the second reading, after 48 h of exposure, cell toxicity occurred only at the highest concentration, 4.4 mg/mL, which killed 94.26% of cells. For the other concentrations of 2.2 mg/mL, 1.1 mg/mL, 0.55 mg/mL and 0.275 mg/mL, cell viability was not affected by the oil. However, statistically, there was no significant difference between the cellular viability values at 24 h and 48 h (
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.7972 (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05), indicating that the oil only inhibits Vero E6 cells at the highest concentration, 4.4 mg/mL. The results are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Percentages Vero cell viability. Treated with differing concentrations of 
     <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil after 24 h (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and after 48 h (
     <span class="bold">b</span>). GC: growth control
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12906_2017_1918_Fig1_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After treating HeLa strain for 24 h, we observed that the largest 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> oil concentrations had a greater inhibitory effect on tumor cell proliferation. Accordingly, the oil showed inhibitions from 11% to 21% between the doses of 1.1 mg/mL and 4.4 mg/mL. After treatment for 48 h, concentrations of 2.2 mg/mL and 4.4 mg/mL showed a greater inhibition of proliferation – 32.4% and 44.3%, respectively. This suggests that, although there was no statistically significant difference between the viabilities observed after 24 h and 48 h (
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.8085; 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05), the oil had notable antitumor activity after 24 h that intensified over longer exposure times, as shown in the 48 h reading, which slightly decreased cell viability at all concentrations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>HeLa cell viability. Treated with different concentrations of 
     <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil for 24 h (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and 48 h (
     <span class="bold">b</span>). GC: growth control
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12906_2017_1918_Fig2_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the non-tumor cell strain HEK-293, we observed that the oil exerted no toxic effects. At 24 h, cell proliferation occurred at levels near or above those of the untreated control cells. At 48 h we observed the same result. The statistical analysis showed that there was no difference between cell viability percentage in 24 h and 48 h, and these were statistically the same, since the 
  <span class="italic">p</span> value obtained from the Wilcoxon test was 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 1 (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>HEK-293 cell viability. Treated with different concentrations of 
     <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil for 24 h (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) and 48 h (
     <span class="bold">b</span>). GC: growth control
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12906_2017_1918_Fig3_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
