<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cytotoxicity assay</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Having shown antibacterial activity, 
  <span class="italic">Myracrodruon urundeuva</span> essential oil was evaluated for its cytotoxicity to Vero E6 (renal epithelial 
  <span class="italic">Cercopithecus aethiops</span>), HeLa (human cervical adenocarcinoma) and HEK-293 (human kidney embryonic) cell lines obtained from the Culture Collection of the Federal University of Rio de Janeiro, and cultured in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), and 1% antibiotic (penicillin/streptomycin). The cells were maintained in an incubator at 37 °C in an atmosphere of 5% CO
  <sub>2</sub>. To assess the viability and proliferation rate of the cell lines in the presence of the oil, a colorimetric assay based on the tetrazolium salt MTT (3- (4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl) -2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide) (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany) was performed as described by Mosmann (1983) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. This technique evaluates the metabolic activity of the cells by quantifying the MTT reduction by NADPH and NADH-associated dehydrogenases that results in the production of formazan crystals within the cells, giving the characteristic coloration to the medium. For this study, cells were placed in 96 well plates with a density of 5 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> cells/well. After 24 h under the culture conditions, serum deprivation was performed, and, after another 24 h, we applied 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil at concentrations of 0.275 mg/mL, 0.55 mg/mL, 1.1 mg/mL, 2.2 mg/mL and 4.4 mg/mL to the cell strains. After the cells were treated for 24 h or 48 h, 100 μL/​​well of MTT (5 mg/mL) was added and incubated for 4 h. After this, the medium was removed and 100 μL of ethanol was added to each well. The plates were shaken and the absorbance obtained in a microplate reader (Epoch - BioTek Instruments Inc., USA) at 570 nm, using Gen5 Data Analysis version 2.0 software (BioTek Instruments Inc., USA). The growth control consisted only of cell culture in the culture medium. The assays were assessed in triplicate and the cell viability percentage was calculated as follows:
  <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">1</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ CV\%=\left( Abs\ sample/ Abs\ growth control\right)\ x100 $$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
     <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">CV</span>
     <span class="mo">%</span>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div close=")" open="(" class="mfenced">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">Abs</span>
       <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mtext">sample</span>
       <span stretchy="true" class="mo">/</span>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">Abs</span>
       <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mtext">growth control</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
     <span class="mi">x</span>
     <span class="mn">100</span>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12906_2017_1918_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
