<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mitochondria can produce adenosine triphosphate (ATP) from products of the fatty acid β-oxidation. At the mitochondrial inner membrane, electrons from NADH and FADH2 are transferred from electron donors to electron acceptors, passing through ETC to oxygen eventually (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jonckheere et al., 2012</xref>). The above process can release energy, namely oxidative phosphorylation, which is used to form ATP by a series of protein complexes within the inner membrane of the cell’s mitochondria in eukaryotes (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Voet et al., 2008</xref>). This response was largely driven by the expression of genes encoding subunits of Complex I (NADH dehydrogenase). As we can see from the results, KO and SO diets significantly up-regulated the expression level of Complex I. Some previous studies also provided evidences that krill oil supplementation may stimulate mitochondrial respiratory activity (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mootha et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burri et al., 2011</xref>). Previous study had found that a coordinated upregulation of nuclear-encoded genes regulating mitochondrial electron transport, and metabolic rate changes were in associated with the content of PUFA in diet (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hulbert et al., 2005</xref>). In addition to an increase of gene expression for subunits of complex I, a change of upregulation in the gene expression of 
 <italic class="italic">sirt3</italic> was observed in KO and SO diets in present study. Sirt3 deacetylates and activates various target substrates used in oxidation of fatty acids. Sirt3 is a regulator of mitochondrial energy metabolism, particularly Complex I (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ahn et al., 2008</xref>). It is important for maintaining basal ATP levels (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ahn et al., 2008</xref>). Aside from Sirt3 modulation and changes in gene expression, mitochondrial membrane fatty acid compositions and membrane fluidity have been proposed to play a role in β-oxidation and energy metabolism (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morash et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Longo et al., 2016</xref>). The unsaturated degree of membrane lipids affects the fluidity of membrane structure and transmembrane transports (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Longo et al., 2016</xref>). The result showed that KO diet had the highest unsaturated degree of mitochondrial membrane, which partly explain the higher mRNA expression levels of transmembrane transports proteins. Furthermore, nuclear respiratory factor 1, also known as 
 <italic class="italic">nrf1</italic>, encodes a protein that homodimerizes, directly regulates the expression of nuclear genes encoding subunits of the respiratory complexes and indirectly regulating the three mitochondrial-encoded COX subunit genes for respiration, mitochondrial DNA transcription and replication (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gleyzer et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2006</xref>). High expression of 
 <italic class="italic">nrf1</italic> in KO and SO diets demonstrated a marked effect of KO and SO on the upregulation of genes and pathways involved in hepatopancreas energy metabolism. What’s more, the energy produced by mitochondrial could used to maintain a steady state after molting of crabs, which can partly explain the reason why KO diet has the highest molting ratio among all diets when all of these results were considered together.
</p>
