<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The genus 
 <italic class="italic">Cyphostemma</italic> (Planch.) Alston (Vitaceae) includes about 150 species distributed in eastern and southern Africa and Madagascar [
 <xref rid="pone.0214594.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Some species from this genus are used in traditional medicine, e.g. roots of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">junceum</italic> to treat snake bites [
 <xref rid="pone.0214594.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Interestingly, Ochawang’i 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214594.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] described the use of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">serpens</italic>, alone or in association with other plants, in traditional medicine for the care of breast cancer. Udegbunam 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214594.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] used root extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">vogeli</italic> to investigate its anti-inflammatory effect on sore throat, cough and pneumonia in mice. The antiproliferative effects of water and methanolic extracts of four 
 <italic class="italic">Cyphostemma</italic> spp. (
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">flaviflorums</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">lanigerum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">natalitium</italic>, and one unidentified species) on HepG2 cell line have been studied by Opoku 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214594.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], but no chemical analyses of the matrices were performed. Cao 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0214594.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] found that 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">greveana</italic> showed antiproliferative activities against the A2780 ovarian cancer cell line and identified one macrolide, lasiodiplodin, three sesquiterpenoids, and a new diterpenoid. Although from a chemical point of view 
 <italic class="italic">Cyphostemma</italic> spp. have been investigated by solvent extractions, to the best of our knowledge no studies have been carried out on hydrodistillated essential oils and their possible biological activities.
</p>
