<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For this study, we used the Cultural Food Significance Index (CFSI) to evaluate the cultural significance of wild leafy vegetable species. The CFSI, developed by Pieroni in 2001 [
 <xref rid="B52-foods-09-01748" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], is the sum of seven measures of food importance and is calculated as:
 <disp-formula>CFSI = QI × AI × FUI × PUI × MFFI × TSAI × FMRI × 10
  <sup>−2</sup>
  <label>(1)</label>
 </disp-formula> where QI = quotation index; AI = availability index; FUI = frequency of utilization index; PUI = plant parts used index; MFFI = multi-functional food use index; TSAI = taste score appreciation index; and FMRI = food-medicinal role index [
 <xref rid="B52-foods-09-01748" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-foods-09-01748" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. To determine the QI, the number quotation of each useful species for particular use was counted. The interviewees were asked “How many of these vegetables can be found in the forest?” to determine the AI with the following categories: rare, medium, common, and very common. The FUI values were determined by asking about the frequency of eating these species. The PUI values express the multiple uses of a plant part. If multiple parts were collected, the value will be higher than the use of single plant part. The MFFI values were obtained by asking interviewees “How do you consume this vegetable?” High values were allocated to raw consumption or cooked alone species, and low values were obtained by using with other ingredients or condiments. The TSAI values were assessed by asking how much interviewees like these vegetables on the following scale: terrible, poor, fair, good, very good, and best. Some vegetable species had medicinal benefits in different roles. High values of FMRI were allocated with food as medicine, while low values were obtained from species that had no specification of therapeutic action, or where it was not recognized. All sub-indices were evaluated using Pieroni’s scales [
 <xref rid="B52-foods-09-01748" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Wild leafy vegetable species with CFSI ≥ 300 in the Karen and Lawa communities were selected to analyze the proximate and mineral components.
</p>
