<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>DeVerse et al. examined IRF-1 and TNF-α-induced VCAM-1 in human aortic endothelial cells (HAECs) stimulated by TRL through immunofluorescence in a microfluidic device. It was found that TRL isolated from human plasma after HFM regulated TNF-α-induced VCAM-1 expression by regulating the IRF-1-dependent transcription mechanism, which indicated that postprandial TRL plays a direct role in regulating the expression of IRF-1 and downstream inflammatory reaction, affecting endothelial function and producing an atherogenic effect (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). The adhesion of monocytes in the arterial wall is associated with AS. Gower et al. detected the blood of healthy subjects with standardized HFM by flow cytometry and found that the expression of CD11c on monocytes increased at 3.5 h after a meal, and the degree of upregulation was related to postprandial TG. The purified monocytes internalized TRL isolated from postprandial blood through LDL receptor associated protein-1, which also caused the upregulation of CD11c. These results suggest that mononuclear cells in the postprandial state can internalize lipids, upregulate CD11c, increase adhesion to VCAM-1, and increase the risk of atherosclerosis (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Gorzelak-Pabis et al. studied the effects of a single high-fat diet on the barrier function and inflammatory status of human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs). Serum from healthy volunteers was extracted before and 3 h after a meal to induce HUVECs. The integrity of HUVECs was measured in the RTCA-DP-xCELLigence system. Fasting and postprandial TG were measured. The expression of proinflammatory cytokine mRNA was detected by RT-PCR. Postprandial TG level increased, and postprandial serum decreased the integrity of HUVECs. The mRNA expression of IL-33, IL-32, MCP-1, and CX3C chemokines was significantly increased, which revealed that a single HFM could aggravate the inflammatory process and destroy the endothelial barrier (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Herieka et al. reviewed 57 studies on HFM-induced postprandial inflammation and found that the increase in systemic inflammation promoting the development of AS can be explained, at least in part, by frequent consumption of excess dietary fat. The results of postprandial inflammation markers were compared with the highly consistent low-grade human endotoxemia model, which showed that plasma-borne inflammatory markers such as, cytokines and soluble adhesion factors did not continuously increase after HFM, while the level of proinflammatory leukocyte surface markers increased in almost all measured studies. It was proposed that the study of inflammation induced by postprandial lipemia could be carried out by focusing on leukocytes in the future (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Recently, a study has shown that the formation of proatherogenic endothelial phenotype is promoted by postprandial metabolism changes in TRL characterized with oxylipin signature in dyslipidemic subjects (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>).
</p>
