<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While the use of 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-limonene as a green solvent may sound like a valuable alternative, the fact that it is an unsaturated terpene that oxidizes easily under exposure to air makes it less attractive, especially as the formed oxidation products are labelled as allergens [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-02170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Logically, we considered that a total hydrogenation of 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-limonene could produce 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-menthane, a stable saturated terpene, which would not be oxidizable. Such an approach seems particularly relevant if we consider the scarcity of saturated terpenes in natural essential oils compared with the abundance of 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-limonene in 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> by-products. This study thus aims to synthesize 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-menthane (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-02170-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) and evaluate its performances under the green analytical chemistry concept as a toluene replacement for moisture determination. The green alternative performance was also compared to that of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane for the extraction of natural substances such as carotenoids, aromas, and vegetable oils using Soxhlet or the conventional single step procedure. The idea was to develop an ecological process that takes economical issues into consideration and presents itself as a competitive potential process for natural substance efficient extraction in cosmetic, food, or agrochemical applications. This was completed with a theoretical solubility analysis of targeted secondary and primary metabolites in 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-menthane and 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane using a computational predictive method (conductor-like combination of quantum chemistry (COSMO) coupled with statistical thermodynamics (RS)). A comparison of 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-menthane has also been done with toluene for moisture determination in Dean–Stark distillation apparatus.
</p>
