<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Interest in fuel and chemical production from lignocellulosic biomass has increased as an alternative to food crop feedstocks within biorefineries. By-product streams, such as those from food and drink production or food waste from households and supermarkets, are currently under investigation as renewable and more sustainable feedstocks. When easily fermentable sugars are extracted from raw material, the remaining substrates, such as proteins, lipids, cellulose, and hemicellulose, require a hydrolysis process that usually liberates a mixture of sugars and other compounds. Current research has focused on either studying organisms that can co-utilise these mixtures or controlling the specificity of the bioprocess. For example, Patel et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-00978" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] investigated the production of lipids from brewers’ spent grains as an oil substitute for biodiesel production. An organosolv- or microwave-assisted alkaline pretreatment was evaluated to release insoluble carbohydrates, which was later used by the oleaginous yeast 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodosporidium toruloides</italic>, capable of co-utilising xylose and glucose. The organosolv pretreatment, together with an optimized C/N ratio of 500 during cultivation, achieved a product with more than 56% of lipid content. The profile of the biodiesel obtained also satisfied the criteria for use as a transportation fuel. In contrast, De Groof et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-00978" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] reviewed the operational conditions necessary for a mixed culture fermentation to produce medium-chain carboxylic acids (MCCA), that can be used as antibiotic replacements in animal feed or further processed into bulk fuels or solvents. Contrary to single-culture processes, these systems allow the treatment of more complex and variable substrates as food waste; however, their yields, selectivity, and, accordingly, economical viability, become more challenging to control. The review states that the production of MCCA is enhanced when substrates contain or easily produce ethanol or lactic acid, which are intermediate substrates; furthermore, mesophilic temperatures, an acid to neutral pH (5–7) and a higher substrate–inoculum ratio in comparison with AD (F/M &gt; 5) are required. In addition, the process is enhanced with high loading rates, which benefits concentrated substrates that cannot be treated by AD.
</p>
