<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Introduction</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">Fish feed formulations are constantly evolving to improve the quality of diets for farmed fish and to ensure the sustainability of the aquaculture sector. Nowadays, insect, microalgae and yeast are feedstuff candidates for new feeds. However, the characterization of aquafeed is still based on proximate and targeted analyses which may not be sufficient to assess feed quality.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objectives</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">Our aim was to highlight the soluble compounds that specifically differ between selected plant-based feeds complemented with alternative feedstuffs and discuss their origin and potential for fish nutrition.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">A growth trial was carried out to evaluate growth performances and feed conversion ratios of fish fed plant-based, commercial, insect, spirulina and yeast feeds. 
   <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR metabolomics profiling of each feed was performed using a CPMG sequence on polar extracts. Spectra were processed, and data were analyzed using multivariate and univariate analyses to compare alternative feeds to a plant-based feed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">Fish fed insect or yeast feed showed the best growth performances associated with the lowest feed conversion ratios compared to plant-based feed. Soluble compound 
   <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR profiles of insect and spirulina alternative feeds differed significantly from the plant-based one that clustered with yeast feed. In insect and spirulina feeds, specific differences compared to plant-based feed concerned glycerol and 3-hydroxybutyrate, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par5" class="p">This strategy based on compositional differences between plant-based and alternative feeds can be useful for detecting compounds unsuspected until now that could impact fish metabolism.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p class="p">The online version of this article (10.1007/s11306-018-1454-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
