<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>In order to investigated diversity and geographic distribitution of rhizobia associated with invasive 
  <italic>Mimosa</italic> species, 
  <italic>Mimosa</italic> nodules and soils around the plants were sampled from five provinces in southern China. In total, 361 isolates were obtained from 
  <italic>Mimosa pudica</italic> and 
  <italic>Mimosa diplotricha</italic> in 25 locations. A multi-locus sequence analysis (MLSA) including 16S rRNA, 
  <italic>atpD</italic>, 
  <italic>dnaK</italic>, 
  <italic>glnA</italic>, 
  <italic>gyrB</italic>, and 
  <italic>recA</italic> identified the isolates into eight genospecies corresponding to 
  <italic>Paraburkhleria mimosarum</italic>, 
  <italic>Paraburkholderia phymatum</italic>, 
  <italic>Paraburkholeria carbensis</italic>, 
  <italic>Cupriavidus taiwanensis</italic>, 
  <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> sp., 
  <italic>Rhizobium altiplani</italic>, 
  <italic>Rhizobium mesoamericanum</italic>, and 
  <italic>Rhizobium etli</italic>. The majority of the isolates were 
  <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> (62.6%), followed by 
  <italic>Paraburkholderia</italic> (33.5%) and 
  <italic>Rhizobium</italic> (2.9%). 
  <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> strains were more predominant in nodules of 
  <italic>M. diplotricha</italic> (76.2) than in 
  <italic>M. pudica</italic> (59.9%), and the distribution of 
  <italic>P. phymatum</italic> in those two plant species was reverse (3.4:18.2%). Four symbiotypes were defined among the isolates based upon the phylogeny of 
  <italic>nodA</italic>-
  <italic>nifH</italic> genes, represented by 
  <italic>P. mimosarum</italic>, 
  <italic>P. phymatum</italic>–
  <italic>P. caribensis</italic>, 
  <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> spp., and 
  <italic>Rhizobium</italic> spp. The species affiliation and the symbiotype division among the isolates demonstrated the multiple origins of 
  <italic>Mimosa</italic> rhizobia in China: most were similar to those found in the original centers of 
  <italic>Mimosa</italic> plants, but 
  <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> sp. might have a local origin. The unbalanced distribution of symbionts between the two 
  <italic>Mimosa</italic> species might be related to the soil pH, organic matter and available nitrogen; 
  <italic>Cupriavidus</italic> spp. generally dominated most of the soils colonized by 
  <italic>Mimosa</italic> in this study, but it had a particular preference for neutral-alkaline soils with low fertility whereas. While 
  <italic>Paraburkholderia</italic> spp. preferred more acidic and fertile soils. The 
  <italic>Rhizobium</italic> spp. tended to prefer neutral–acidic soils with high fertility soils.
 </p>
</abstract>
