<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An investigation of the antibacterial potential of two extracts, one alcoholic and one lipophilic (with hexane), found that the alcoholic had the lowest MIC for 
 <italic>Staphyllococcus aureus</italic>, whereas the lipophilic one for 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B134-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. The MIC values varied between 2.95 and 11.8 mg/mL for the ethanolic; for the hexane extract, MIC was 3.5 mg/mL for 
 <italic>Staphyllococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphyllococcus faecalis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, and higher than 3.5 mg/mL for the other microorganisms tested [
 <xref rid="B134-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Although values lower than 16 mg/mL have been considered sometimes as showing a strong antibacterial effect [
 <xref rid="B135-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>], other authors have used more stringent criteria: MIC values &lt; 100 μg/mL have been proposed to be highly active, those between 100 and 500 μg/mL active, those between 500 and 1000 μg/mL moderately active, those between 1000 and 200 μg/mL of low activity, and those with MIC &gt; 2000 μg/mL inactive [
 <xref rid="B136-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. It has also been suggested that in order to “be considered a promising activity, a crude extract must demonstrate a MIC under 100 μg/mL” (and a pure compound less than 16 μg/mL) [
 <xref rid="B138-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Other studies have also assessed various extracts for their antimicrobial effects, but MIC or MBC (minimal bactericidal concentration) was also for most species higher than 2000 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="B139-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="B141-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]. In the light of these criteria from the literature, the activities observed in this study are not “promising” and because they are higher than 2000 μg/mL, should rather be considered inactive.
</p>
