<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Other than 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> spp., EOs from 
 <italic>Lavandula</italic> spp. have also been studied for the treatment of AD. 
 <italic>L. luisieri</italic> has been found to comprise high contents of oxygen-containing monoterpenes, mainly necrodane derivatives, which are absent from any other oil. This oil was tested on the endogenous beta-site APP-cleaving enzyme 1 (BACE-1) in cultured cells, being responsible for a reduction in Aβ production, with no significant toxicity. Although the study was conducted in vitro, the low molecular weight and high hydrophobicity of terpenoids are properties that provide a good chance for them to cross cellular membranes and the blood–brain barrier, an essential attribute for BACE-1 inhibition in vivo [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. However, EO from 
 <italic>L. angustifolia</italic> did not give a required finding because it enhanced the Aβ aggregation based on the thioflavin T method; this effect was further confirmed by atomic force microscope (AFM) imaging. EO of 
 <italic>L. angustifolia</italic> was also showed to counteract the increase in intracellular reactive oxygen species production and the activation of the pro-apoptotic enzyme caspase-3 induced by Aβ1–42 oligomers [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Meanwhile, EO from 
 <italic>L. pubescens</italic> exhibited strong anti-AChE and anti-BChE effects at IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.9 μL/mL and 6.82 μL/mL, respectively. Carvacrol (CAR, 2-methyl-5-isopropylphenol) was also found to be higher in 
 <italic>L. pubescens</italic>. Carvacrol was found to be abundant among EOs of the Lamiaceae family, and is known for various benefits including antibacterial, antifungal, antioxidant, antinociceptive, anti-inflammatory, anti-apoptosis, and anti-cancer activities [
 <xref rid="B201-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>]. Several studies on EOs have reported that carvacrol exerts some actions on the neuronal system, including AChE inhibition [
 <xref rid="B104-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B202-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>], anxiolytic [
 <xref rid="B203-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>], and antidepressant [
 <xref rid="B204-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>] properties. In addition, carvacrol has the ability to modulate central neurotransmitter pathways, such as dopaminergic, serotonergic and γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA)-ergic systems [
 <xref rid="B201-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>].
</p>
