<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a study conducted by Ayuob et al. [
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>], 
 <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> up-regulated the serum corticosterone level, the hippocampal protein glucocorticoid receptor, and the brain-derived neurotropic factor (BDNF); however, it down-regulated the neurodegenerative and atrophic changes induced in the hippocampus, which decreased after exposure to chronic unpredictable mild stress (CUMS). According to the data collected by Avetisyan and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B216-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>], the major components of 
 <italic>O. basil</italic> includes methyl chavicol and linalool. Interestingly, many linalool-producing plants are commonly used in folk medicine and aromatherapy to alleviate symptoms and treat multiple acute and chronic diseases [
 <xref rid="B217-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>,
 <xref rid="B218-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>]. Linalool is frequently used in the manufacture of fragrances for shampoos, soaps, detergents, and in pharmaceutical formulations [
 <xref rid="B219-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="B220-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>]. Research conducted by Sabogal-Guáqueta et al. [
 <xref rid="B221-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>] found that oral administration of monoterpene linalool to elderly mice (21–24 months old) with a triple transgenic form of AD (3x Tg-AD) at 25 mg/kg for three months at an interval of 48 h resulted in enhanced learning and spatial memory and increased risk assessment activity in the elevated plus maze. Hippocampi and amygdalae from 3x Tg-AD linalool-treated mice also showed a large reduction in extracellular β-amyloidosis, tauopathy, astrogliosis, and microgliosis, as well as pro-inflammatory marker levels of p38 MAPK, NOS2, COX2 and IL-1β. Thus, linalool is suitable as an AD prevention candidate for pre-clinical studies. Based on the articles that we have selected, linalool is a major volatile component of EOs in a number of aromatic plant species, such as 
 <italic>L. angustifolia Mill.</italic>, 
 <italic>M. officinalis L</italic>., 
 <italic>R. officinalis L</italic>., and 
 <italic>C. citrate DC</italic>. The presence of linalool can also help to reduce the deposits of Aβ, based on a study conducted by Gradinariu et al. [
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>] where Aβ1–42-treated rats exhibited the following: a decrease in exploratory activity (crossing number); smaller percentage of time spent and fewer entries in the open arm in the elevated plus-maze test; increase in swim time; and decrease in the immobility time within the forced swimming test.
</p>
