<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1090</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biodiversity</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environmental Sciences</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Competitive interactions between a nonmycorrhizal invasive plant, <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, and a suite of mycorrhizal grassland, old field, and forest species</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>Gary T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Maherali</surname><given-names>Hafiz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/><email>maherali@uoguelph.ca</email></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><institution>Department of Integrative Biology, University of Guelph</institution>, <addr-line>Guelph, ON</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="editor-1" contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>Gwilym</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2015-07-07"><day>7</day><month>7</month><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e1090</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2015-04-14"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2015-06-17"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 Poon and Maherali</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Poon and Maherali</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/1090"/><abstract><p>The widespread invasion of the nonmycorrhizal biennial plant, <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> in North America is hypothesized to be facilitated by the production of novel biochemical weapons that suppress the growth of mycorrhizal fungi. As a result, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is expected to be a strong competitor against plant species that rely on mycorrhizal fungi for nutrient uptake services. If <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is also a strong competitor for soil resources, it should deplete nutrients to levels lower than can be tolerated by weaker competitors. Because the negative effect of losing the fungal symbiont for mycorrhizal plants is greatest when nutrients are low, the ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> to simultaneously suppress fungi and efficiently take up soil nutrients should further strengthen its competitive ability against mycorrhizal plants. To test this hypothesis, we grew 27 mycorrhizal tree, forb and grass species that are representative of invaded habitats in the absence or presence of competition with <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in soils that had previously been experimentally planted with the invader or left as a control. A history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in soil reduced plant available forms of nitrogen by &#x0003e;50% and phosphorus by 17% relative to control soil. Average mycorrhizal colonization of competitor species was reduced by &#x0003e;50% in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history versus control soil. Contrary to expectations, competition between <italic>A. petiolata</italic> and other species was stronger in control than history soil. The invader suppressed the biomass of 70% of competitor species in control soil but only 26% of species in history soil. In addition, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass was reduced by 56% in history versus control soil, whereas the average biomass of competitor species was reduced by 15%. Thus, our results suggest that the negative effect of nutrient depletion on <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was stronger than the negative effect of suppressing mycorrhizal colonization on competitor species. These findings indicate that the inhibitory potential of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> on competitor species via mycorrhizal suppression is not enhanced under nutrient limitation.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Competition</kwd><kwd>Garlic mustard</kwd><kwd>Mycorrhizal fungi</kwd><kwd>Functional traits</kwd><kwd>Invasive species</kwd><kwd>Nutrient limitation</kwd><kwd>Mechanisms of invasion</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>Ontario Early Researcher Award program</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Canada Foundation for Innovation</funding-source></award-group><award-group id="fund-3"><funding-source>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by grants from the Ontario Early Researcher Award program, the Canada Foundation for Innovation and the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Invasions by exotic species are common and can negatively influence the structure and function of invaded communities and ecosystems (<xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Pimental et al., 2000</xref>). Designing effective control and eradication programs to limit the spread of an invasive species, however, requires identifying the specific mechanism that facilitated invasion (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Mack et al., 2000</xref>). Numerous mechanisms have been identified to explain successful invasions (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Catford, Jansson &#x00026; Nilsson, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Gurevitch et al., 2011</xref>). For example, successful invaders may have high propagule production (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Colautti, Grigorovich &#x00026; MacIsaac, 2006</xref>), possess or evolve superior competitive ability for limiting resources (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Blossey &#x00026; Notzold, 1995</xref>), be released from specialist antagonists in their native range (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Callaway et al., 2004</xref>), possess the ability to acclimate to a wide variety of conditions (<xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Parker, Rodriguez &#x00026; Loik, 2003</xref>), or secrete novel biochemical compounds that reduce the performance and survival of native inhabitants (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Callaway &#x00026; Ridenour, 2004</xref>).</p><p>Recent reviews suggest that successful invasions rarely occur because of a single mechanism (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Catford, Jansson &#x00026; Nilsson, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Gurevitch et al., 2011</xref>). At least three explanations for weak effects of any one mechanism have been proposed (<xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Gurevitch et al., 2011</xref>). First, the efficacy of a particular mechanism may depend on ecological context, where differences in resource availability and the functional attributes of resident species can either facilitate or increase resistance to invasion (<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Funk et al., 2008</xref>). Second, the importance of a particular mechanism could differ between phases of an invasion (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Dietz &#x00026; Edwards, 2006</xref>). For example, allelopathy may effectively suppress resident species in the initial phases of invasion (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Callaway &#x00026; Ridenour, 2004</xref>), but its effects can diminish as resident species acclimate or evolve resistance to the novel biochemicals (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Lankau et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Lankau, 2011</xref>). Third, multiple mechanisms could act synergistically, as observed in situations where invasion is facilitated by both competitive suppression of resident species and reduced palatability to herbivores (<xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Lau &#x00026; Schultheis, 2015</xref>). Simultaneous empirical assessments of multiple causes of invasion, however, are infrequent (<xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p>The widespread invasion of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> ((M. Bieb.) Cavara &#x00026; Grandem, Brassicaceae), a biennial species native to Europe that was introduced to North America in the late 19th century (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Cavers, Heagy &#x00026; Kokron, 1979</xref>), has been attributed to several factors (<xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers, Stinson &#x00026; Finzi, 2008</xref>). Of these mechanisms, the ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> to produce allelopathic phytochemicals has received considerable attention. <italic>A. petiolata</italic> phytochemicals are present in leaf litter and also released as root exudates (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Cipollini et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers, Stinson &#x00026; Finzi, 2008</xref>), but have limited direct negative effects on neighboring plant species (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">McCarthy &#x00026; Hanson, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Roberts &#x00026; Anderson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Prati &#x00026; Bossdorf, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Cipollini, Stevenson &#x00026; Cipollini, 2008</xref>). Instead, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> phytochemicals tend to suppress the growth of mycorrhizal fungi (<xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Roberts &#x00026; Anderson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Stinson et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Callaway et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers, Stinson &#x00026; Finzi, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Cantor et al., 2011</xref>), though the effect is variable (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Burke, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Lankau et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Lankau, 2011</xref>). Because <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is non-mycorrhizal, whereas most plant species rely on mycorrhiza for nutrient uptake services (<xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">Wang &#x00026; Qiu, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Brundrett, 2009</xref>), the suppression of mycorrhizal fungi is expected to advantage <italic>A. petiolata</italic> relative to other species during establishment (<xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Stinson et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Callaway et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Hale &#x00026; Kalisz, 2012</xref>), though this effect can diminish over time (<xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Lankau et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Lankau, 2011</xref>).</p><p>The successful establishment and persistence of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> may also be influenced by the joint effects of novel biochemical weapons and the ability to acquire soil resources more effectively than potential competitors (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Blossey &#x00026; Notzold, 1995</xref>). Resource competition theory predicts that the strong competitors deplete limiting resources to levels lower than weaker competitors (<xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">Tilman, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">Tilman &#x00026; Wedin, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Bever et al., 2010</xref>). If <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is a strong resource competitor, it should deplete soil nutrients below tolerable limits for other species, suppressing other species more than itself. The ability to efficiently take up nutrients as well as survive and reproduce under limited soil nutrients could explain <italic>A. petiolata</italic>&#x02019;s ability to colonize habitats that vary widely in nutrient availability (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers et al., 2008</xref>) as well its ability to suppress native vegetation (e.g., <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Stinson et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers, Stinson &#x00026; Finzi, 2008</xref>). Moreover, if <italic>A. petiolata</italic> can suppress mycorrhizal fungi while simultaneously depleting soil nutrients, this should result in even stronger suppression of mycorrhizal competitors. This is because the negative effect of losing the fungal symbiont is greatest when mycorrhizal plants are grown in low soil nutrients (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Hoeksema et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Johnson, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Despite the potential for <italic>A. petiolata</italic> to modify the soil environment in a way that enhances its own competitive ability, resident species may still be able to resist invasion. Such resistance could depend on the morphological and physiological traits that influence acquisition of soil nutrients and light, which most often limit plant growth (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Grime, 1977</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet &#x00026; Keddy, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg &#x00026; Landa, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr">Wardle et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Funk et al., 2008</xref>). The potential for depletion of soil nutrients and the suppression of mycorrhizal fungi by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> suggests that resident species which resist competitive suppression should have thin roots that maximize absorptive root surface area for resource uptake (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Casper &#x00026; Jackson, 1997</xref>). In addition, species that successfully resist invasion by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> could also be effective at acquiring light (<xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">Stinson &#x00026; Seidler, 2014</xref>), particularly by accelerated height growth, which would allow them to overtop neighbors, and by having high photosynthetic light use efficiency (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet &#x00026; Keddy, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg &#x00026; Landa, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Rosch, Van Rooyen &#x00026; Theron, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Keddy et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). The competitive ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> against other species has been tested in pairwise competition trials (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Meekins &#x00026; McCarthy, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers, Stinson &#x00026; Finzi, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Lankau, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Leicht-Young, Pavlovic &#x00026; Adams, 2012</xref>), but whether growth in previously invaded soils enhances its competitive ability against mycorrhizal plant species is not known (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Hale &#x00026; Kalisz, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Smith &#x00026; Reynolds, 2014</xref>).</p><p>To test the hypothesis that nutrient depletion in the first year of an invasion enhances the competitive ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> against resident mycorrhizal plant species in subsequent years, we grew <italic>A. petiolata</italic> with and without multiple competitor species in forest soil that had either been left intact or previously planted with <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. This latter treatment simulates a reduction in soil nutrient availability because <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is expected to take up resources during growth. However, the experiment does not strictly mimic the entire process of invasion in the field because the high decomposability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> leaves is expected to return nutrients to soil in the longer term (e.g., <xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers et al., 2008</xref>). The experimental design nonetheless allows us to address whether the competitive ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> can be influenced by changes in overall resource availability. Because <italic>A. petiolata</italic> occurs in a wide variety of habitats, including old fields, road sides, forest edges and forest understories (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Cavers, Heagy &#x00026; Kokron, 1979</xref>; <xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">Stinson &#x00026; Seidler, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Smith &#x00026; Reynolds, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2015</xref>), we quantified competition between <italic>A. petiolata</italic> and 27 native and non-native mycorrhizal competitor species that represent these different habitats (e.g., <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Cavers, Heagy &#x00026; Kokron, 1979</xref>). We predicted that soil nutrient reduction and the potential for inhibition of mycorrhizal fungi by previous growth of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in soil (&#x02018;history soil&#x02019;) inhibits the growth of mycorrhizal plant species. As a result, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> should more strongly suppress the growth of, and resist growth suppression by, competitor species in the history soil treatment than in control soil. We predicted that competitor species with finer roots, greater height extension, and higher photosynthetic efficiency would be more likely to resist competition against <italic>A. petiolata</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>To examine competitive interactions between resident species and <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, we grew 27 target species with and without the presence of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref>). Competitor species included forest trees, forest understory herbs, old field herbs and grasses that are commonly found in areas typically invaded by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in southern Ontario (e.g., <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Biswas et al., 2015</xref>). <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> seeds were bulk collected from the Wild Goose Woods, a mixed hardwood forest in the University of Guelph Arboretum (43&#x000b0;32&#x02032;N, 80&#x000b0;12&#x02032;W) in July 2009. <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> can be found in dense patches along the periphery of the forest throughout this site. Seeds for each competitor species were harvested within the Guelph Arboretum as well as purchased from suppliers (Acorus Restoration, Walsingham, Ontario, Canada; Angelgrove Seed Company, Harbour Grace, Newfoundland and Labrador, Canada; Ontario Tree Seed Facility, Angus, Ontario, Canada; Richter&#x02019;s Herbs, Goodwood, Ontario, Canada (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref>)).</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>List of competitor species used in the study, along with information on their plant family affiliation, growth form, status in North America (18 native, 9 introduced), and whether plants are arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM), ecto-mycorrhizal (ECM), or ambiguous (both mycorrhizal and non-mycorrhizal states reported in the literature).</title><p>Mycorrhizal state was determined from <xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">Wang &#x00026; Qiu (2006)</xref>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latin name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth form</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Status</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mycorrhizal state</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acer saccharum</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aceraceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Juglans nigra</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Juglandaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pinus strobus</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pinaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Prunus virginiana</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rosaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Quercus macrocarpa</italic> Michx.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fagaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Thuja occidentalis</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cupressaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tree</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn3"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Achillea millefolium</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asteraceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn4"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aquilegia vulgaris</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ranunculaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn4"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aster umbellatus</italic> Miller</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asteraceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Daucus carota</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apiaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fragaria virginiana</italic> Miller.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rosaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brassicaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ambiguous</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Hypericum perforatum</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clusiaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Leucanthemum vulgare</italic> Lam.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asteraceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Lobelia siphilitica</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campanulaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Plantago lanceolata</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plantaginaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn4"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lamiaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Rudbeckia hirta</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asteraceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Sambucus nigra spp. canadensis</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caprifoliaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ambiguous</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Solidago canadensis</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asteraceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Taraxacum officinale</italic> F.H. Wigg.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asteraceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trifolium pratense</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fabaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biennial Forb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bromus inermis</italic> Leyss.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Grass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn5"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Elymus canadensis</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Grass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Elymus riparius</italic> Wiegand.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Grass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Elymus virginicus</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Grass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Panicum virgatum</italic> L.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poaceae</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perennial Grass</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native<xref ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AM</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p>
<bold>Notes.</bold>
</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1"><label>a</label><p>Seeds obtained from Acorus Restoration.</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn2"><label>b</label><p>Seeds obtained from Angelgrove Seed Company.</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn3"><label>c</label><p>Seeds obtained from Ontario Tree Seed Facility.</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn4"><label>d</label><p>Seeds obtained from Richters Herbs, or field collections.</p></fn><fn id="table-1fn5"><label>e</label><p>Seeds obtained from University of Guelph Arboretum.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To simulate a soil environment that <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is likely to encounter upon invasion, we grew plants in a forest soil without a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. In November 2009, soil was collected to a depth of 30 cm from a mixed deciduous forest dominated by <italic>Acer saccharum</italic> in the Koffler Scientific Reserve (44&#x000b0;03&#x02032;N, 79&#x000b0;29&#x02032;W, Newmarket, ON). Prior to soil collection, live aboveground vegetation and macro-organic matter (leaves and twigs) were removed. Soil was sieved onsite to remove roots and stones and placed into 30, 35L tubs (60.7 cm long &#x000d7; 40.4 cm wide &#x000d7; 22.1 cm deep; Roughneck Storage Box #2214; Newell Rubbermaid Inc., Atlanta, Georgia, USA). Tubs had holes drilled in the bottom to facilitate drainage. Soils were stored at 4 &#x000b0;C prior to the beginning of experiments. To experimentally create a treatment where the presence of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> has modified the soil, we grew <italic>A. petiolata</italic> plants in half of the field collected soil (e.g., <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Callaway et al., 2008</xref>). The remaining soil was left intact in the tubs. To create the <italic>A. petiolata</italic> soil history treatment, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> seeds were cold stratified at 4 &#x000b0;C for 120 days on moist filter paper placed inside 10 cm diameter parafilm sealed petri dishes. In January 2010, 100 germinating <italic>A. petiolata</italic> seeds were transplanted into each of 15 randomly selected tubs. After 6 weeks, seedlings were thinned to a density of 80 plants/m<sup>2</sup>, which approximates the upper end of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> density in field populations (<xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Meekins &#x00026; McCarthy, 2002</xref>). Tubs containing <italic>A. petiolata</italic> seedlings and those containing intact control soil were randomly arranged on the greenhouse bench and watered to maintain field capacity. Germinating seedlings from other species were periodically removed from all tubs. <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> plants were harvested 5 months after germination to simulate the approximate active growing season for first year rosettes of this species in southern Ontario and to allow roots to fully explore the soil in the tubs. At harvest, the aboveground portion of plants was removed and discarded, and soil was sieved to remove roots and homogenized within each soil treatment.</p><p>To quantify the effect of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history on soil nutrients, we sampled 500 mL of soil from the post-harvest homogenized soil mixture for each treatment and analyzed it for plant available nutrients, including <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-i001.jpg"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${\mathrm{NO}}_{3}^{-}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-6"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NO</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-i002.jpg"/><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${\mathrm{NH}}_{4}^{+}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-7"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NH</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, P (Olsen), Mg, and K in mg per unit mass (kg) or volume (L) of soil (University of Guelph Laboratory Services; <uri xlink:href="http://www.guelphlabservices.com/AFL/plants.aspx">www.guelphlabservices.com/AFL/plants.aspx</uri>). Soil that had been left without <italic>A. petiolata</italic> contained 160 mg/kg <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-i003.jpg"/><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${\mathrm{NO}}_{3}^{-}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-8"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NO</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, 18.3 mg/kg <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-i004.jpg"/><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${\mathrm{NH}}_{4}^{+}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-10"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NH</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, 23 mg/L P, 77 mg/L Mg, and 52 mg/L K. In soil with <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history, these amounts were reduced to 29.2 mg/kg for <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-i005.jpg"/><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${\mathrm{NO}}_{3}^{-}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-11"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NO</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> (&#x02212;82% decrease), 8.56 mg/kg for <inline-formula><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-i006.jpg"/><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}${\mathrm{NH}}_{4}^{+}$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="mml-ieqn-12"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">NH</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> (&#x02212;53% decrease), 19 mg/L for P (&#x02212;17% decrease), 53 mg/L for Mg (&#x02212;31% decrease) and 40 mg/L for K (&#x02212;23% decrease).</p><p>To study the effects of soil treatment, interspecific competition and competitive species identity on the growth of either <italic>A. petiolata</italic> or the competitor, we used a three-factor design. To quantify competition, we grew each competitor species in the presence and absence of an <italic>A. petiolata</italic> individual in the same pot (e.g., <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet &#x00026; Keddy, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>) in both soil treatments. We also grew <italic>A. petiolata</italic> alone as a reference to calculate its response to competition with the other species. Each treatment combination ((27 species + <italic>A. petiolata</italic>) &#x000d7; 2 soil treatments &#x000d7; 2 competition treatments) was replicated 6 times for a total of 744 pots. Pots (650 mL volume, 6.4 cm wide &#x000d7; 25 cm deep; D40 R; Stuewe and Sons Inc., Tangent, Oregon, USA) were filled with either <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history or untreated field soil and were randomly arranged in a checkerboard pattern across 53 trays (57 N25T; Stuewe and Sons Inc., Tangent, Oregon, USA) to minimize competition for light between pots. To induce germination, all seeds were cold stratified for 30&#x02013;120 days based on information provided by seed suppliers. Cold stratification times were staggered to ensure all species germinated at the same time. After stratification, seeds were moved to the University of Guelph Phytotron greenhouse and germinated in a medium of 2/3 top soil and 1/3 silica sand and then transplanted into experimental treatments. Because of slow germination in some species, they were planted in two groups separated by two weeks. All plants were grown for the same number of days and were completely randomized across the greenhouse benches. 100 mL of 1/4 strength 18-9-18 N:P:K fertilizer (Plant Products, Leamington, Ontario, Canada) was added once to all pots in both soil treatments to promote seedling establishment. Because an equal amount of fertilizer was added to all pots, nutrient differences between the <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history and control soil treatments remained. After 63 days, when herbaceous competitor plants had reached reproductive maturity, the aboveground parts of plants were harvested, separated according to species, dried at 60 &#x000b0;C for 48 h and weighed.</p><p>To determine if <italic>A. petiolata</italic> soil history suppressed arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi, we harvested the roots of a subset of competitor species when grown alone in both history and control soil. To quantify root colonization by AM fungi, we selected eight species that represented the range of growth forms in the experiment. Root cell contents were cleared with potassium hydroxide and AM fungi were stained with Chlorazol black E (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Brundrett, Piche &#x00026; Peterson, 1984</xref>). Samples were mounted on glass slides and viewed under a compound microscope at 250&#x000d7; magnification. To quantify fungal colonization by AM hyphae, arbuscules, and vesicles, we used the gridline intersection method (<xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">McGonigle et al., 1990</xref>). Colonization was quantified as the presence or absence of well-stained structures at 50 intersections per root sample.</p><p>To determine whether morphological and physiological traits could explain the ability of competitive species to either resist suppression by, or suppress <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, we measured aboveground traits on all plant species in the absence of competition in both soil treatments. We measured leaf chlorophyll concentration and photosynthetic efficiency of up to 6 individuals from each species in each soil treatment at 5 and 9 weeks growth. Height at 5 weeks on these individuals was recorded as the vertical distance from the soil surface to the tip of the tallest leaf. We measured chlorophyll concentration on the three youngest fully expanded leaves per plant using a portable chlorophyll meter (SPAD 502; Minolta Inc., Ramsey, New Jersey, USA), and calculated an average value per plant. We measured photosynthetic efficiency as instantaneous fluorescence yield under saturating light conditions (1,500 &#x000b5;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), a measure of the light use efficiency of photosystem II (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Maxwell &#x00026; Johnson, 2000</xref>). The three youngest fully expanded leaves per plant were measured using a light-adapted fluorometer (PAM-2500; Heinz Walz APbH, Effeltrich, Germany) and an average value per plant was calculated.</p><p>To determine if root traits co-varied with competitive ability, we grew 5 replicates of all plant species in a separate experiment in a sterilized mixture of 2/3 silica sand and 1/3 topsoil for 35 days. Root architecture could not be measured in the main experiment because roots could not be effectively separated from the higher organic matter containing field soil, and because roots were becoming pot bound by the time of harvest. The shorter growing period and silica sand-topsoil mixture prevented plant roots from becoming pot bound and facilitated the harvest of intact root systems. Plants were grown individually in 650 mL pots (D40 R; Stuewe and Sons Inc., Tangent, Oregon, USA). At harvest, roots were cleaned and preserved in 50% ethanol. For analysis, roots were stained with 0.05% Toluidine Blue O to improve the visibility of fine roots, spread out in water to minimize overlap and photographed with a high resolution (6,400 dpi) scanner (Epson V700; Epson Canada Limited, Markham, Ontario, Canada). Root images were analyzed with WinRhizo software (version 2009a; Regent Instruments 2009, Quebec City, Quebec, Canada) using the automatic pixel classification setting to assess the length and average root diameter of each root system. After scanning, roots were dried at 60 &#x000b0;C for 48 h and weighed. In addition to average root diameter, we also calculated specific root length (SRL), or the ratio of root length to root mass, which is indicative of the amount of surface area available for nutrient absorption (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Craine et al., 2001</xref>).</p><p>To assess the magnitude and variation in resistance of competitor species to <italic>A. petiolata</italic> competition and whether the magnitude of resistance is influenced by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> soil history, we analyzed aboveground biomass of competitor species with a three-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with competition, soil history and competitor species identity and all interactions as factors. Planned orthogonal single degree of freedom (1-df) contrasts were used to determine whether each competitor species biomass differed between competition treatments within each soil history treatment. We also used 1-df contrasts to test whether growth forms (trees, forbs, grasses) differed as a whole between competition treatments in each soil history treatment.</p><p>To assess the magnitude and variation in the ability of competitor species to influence <italic>A. petiolata</italic> aboveground biomass, and whether this species effect was influenced by soil history, we used a two-way ANOVA with competitor species identity, soil history and their interaction as factors. To test whether growth with a competitor species suppressed the biomass of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in each soil treatment, we used planned orthogonal 1-df contrasts to compare the biomass of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> grown alone relative to its growth (i) with each competitor, (ii) with each growth form in aggregate, and (iii) across all competitor species in aggregate. The effect of soil treatment on fungal colonization of roots was determined with a two-way ANOVA with soil and species as factors. The statistical significance of soil treatment on fungal colonization for each species was determined by comparing 95% confidence intervals for overlap. The effect of growth form and soil treatment on plant traits was tested with a two-way ANOVA using species means for each trait as the replicate. Differences among growth forms were determined by comparing the 95% confidence intervals for each growth form for overlap following a significant main effect. All ANOVAs and 1-df contrasts were done with SPSS 22.0 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY).</p><p>To quantify variation in the ability of competitor species to either resist suppression by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> or suppress <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, we calculated two indices of competition. The ability of a competitor species to resist suppression is defined as competitive response (CR, <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>), and was quantified as ln (biomass under competition/biomass alone). The ability of each competitor species to suppress <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is defined as competitive effect (CE, <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet &#x00026; Keddy, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>), and was quantified as &#x02013;ln (<italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass under competition/<italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass alone). When calculated this way, greater values reflect stronger competitive ability.</p><p>To determine whether morphological and physiological traits of competitor plants were associated with competitive ability, we used phylogenetic generalized least squares (PGLS) multiple regression, with competitive ability (either CR or CE) as the dependent variable and traits as independent variables. Growth form of plants was used as a covariate in the analysis. Because root traits were assessed in a different experiment, multiple regression analyses were run separately for aboveground and belowground traits. To analyze data, we used the time calibrated phylogenetic tree from <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Davies et al. (2004)</xref> in Phylomatic (<xref rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr">Webb, Ackerly &#x00026; Kembel, 2008</xref>), pruned to include the competitor species. In PGLS regression, the phylogenetic variance&#x02013;covariance matrix is incorporated into the calculation of coefficients (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>) for either a univariate or multiple regression model (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Martins &#x00026; Hansen, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Pagel, 1999</xref>). To calculate the magnitude of phylogenetic effects on the regression, maximum likelihood is used to estimate <italic>&#x003bb;</italic>, an index which varies from 0, indicating complete independence between variation in the regression residuals and phylogeny, and 1, indicating complete dependence between residual variation with Brownian model of evolution (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Freckleton, Harvey &#x00026; Pagel, 2002</xref>). When <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0, the PGLS regression is identical to ordinary least squares regression. PGLS regression and estimates of <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> were done in R version 3.12 (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">R Core Team, 2014</xref>) using the &#x02018;pgls&#x02019; command in the package caper, version 0.5.2 (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Orme et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The average aboveground biomass of competitor species was reduced by the presence of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> compared to when they were grown alone (significant competition main effect, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table 2</xref>). However, competition was weaker in soil with a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> relative to control soil (significant soil history &#x000d7; competition interaction, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). The average biomass of competitor species was reduced by 59% in control soil compared to 27% in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil. The influence of soil history on competition also varied among species (significant species &#x000d7; soil history &#x000d7; competition interaction, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). For example, the aboveground biomass of 19 species (70%; 13/18 native, 6/9 introduced) was suppressed by competition in control soil whereas only 7 species (26%; 4/18 native, 3/9 introduced) were suppressed by competition in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil. On a growth form basis, trees (&#x02212;38%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01), forbs (&#x02212;62%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.000001) and grasses (&#x02212;56%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.000001) were all suppressed by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in control soil, whereas the biomass of forbs (&#x02212;32%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.000001) and grasses (&#x02212;14%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.007), but not trees (<italic>P</italic> = 0.228), was significantly reduced by competition in the <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>, insets).</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Biomass of competitor species in response to competition with <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in control (A) or soil with a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (B).</title><p>Biomass within each growth form are shown in the insets. Black bars indicate plants grown alone and grey bars indicate plants grown in competition with <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. Statistically significant differences were determined using planned orthogonal 1-df contrasts, and are indicated with an asterisk.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>A three-way ANOVA table describing the effects of species identity, competition with <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, soil history and their interactions on dry mass of competitor species.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g008"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type III sums of squares</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean square</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1141.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.29 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;144</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Soil history</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Competition</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">319.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;55</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species &#x02217; Soil history</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species &#x02217; Competition</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;25</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Soil history&#x02217; Competition</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species &#x02217; Soil history &#x02217; Competition</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Error</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">326.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">497</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The average biomass of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in competition was not significantly different from its average biomass when grown alone in either soil treatment (<italic>P</italic><sub>history</sub> = 0.284, <italic>P</italic><sub>control</sub> = 0.602; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> biomass varied in response to competition with different competitor species (significant species effect, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-3">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). In most cases, these species effects were not consistent between control and history soils (significant species &#x000d7; soil history interaction, <xref ref-type="table" rid="table-3">Table 3</xref>). For example, relative to its biomass when alone, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was significantly smaller in competition with <italic>H. matronalis, B. inermis, E. canadensis, E. riparius</italic>, and <italic>E. virginicus</italic> in control soil but significantly smaller in competition with <italic>Q. macrocarpa, H. matronalis</italic> and <italic>E. canadensis</italic> in history soil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>). In some cases, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass was higher when grown with a competitor species than when grown alone. This response occurred with <italic>P. strobus</italic> and <italic>T. occidentalis</italic> in control soil and <italic>H. perforatum</italic> in history soil. <italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass response to competition also varied with growth form, and this effect differed between soil treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig. 2</xref>, insets). In control soil, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass was 27% higher (<italic>P</italic> = 0.041) when grown with trees than when grown alone, 43% lower (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001) when grown with grasses than when grown alone, and not influenced by forbs (<italic>P</italic> = 0.61). In history soil, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass was not affected by competition with trees (<italic>P</italic> = 0.96) or forbs (<italic>P</italic> = 0.38), but was 62% lower (<italic>P</italic> = 0.033) when grown with grasses than when grown alone.</p><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Biomass of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> alone or in response to competition with other species in control (A) or soil with a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (B).</title><p>Biomass of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> alone versus in competition with members of different growth forms are shown in the insets. Statistically significant differences were determined using planned orthogonal 1-df contrasts, and are indicated with an asterisk.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>A two-way ANOVA table describing the effects of competitor species identity, soil history and their interaction on the dry mass of <italic>A. petiolata</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g009"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type III sums of squares</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean square</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>F</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;17</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Soil history</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">341.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.51 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;48</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species &#x02217; Soil history</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;06</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Error</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">236</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>On average, competitor species grown alone in soil with a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> were 15% smaller than plants grown in control soil (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,261</sub> = 21.991, <italic>P</italic> = 0.000004, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). Competitor species also differed in their response to <italic>A. petiolata</italic> soil history (<italic>F</italic><sub>26,261</sub> = 3.042, <italic>P</italic> = 0.000003), though a majority showed no significant difference between treatments. Significant negative effects of soil history were found for <italic>Q. macrocarpa</italic> (&#x02212;37%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.041), <italic>H. matronalis</italic> (&#x02212;29%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.041), <italic>R. hirta</italic> (&#x02212;43%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.000001), <italic>E. riparius</italic> (&#x02212;20%, <italic>P</italic> = 0.048), and <italic>P. virgatum</italic> (&#x02212;33%, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.000001). The strongest negative response to soil history was observed for <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, whose biomass was 56% lower in soil in which it had been previously planted than in control soil (<italic>P</italic> = 0.004).</p><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>The log response ratio of plant biomass without competition in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history relative to control soil.</title><p>Statistically significant differences between soil treatments were determined using planned orthogonal 1-df contrasts, and are indicated with an asterisk.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g003"/></fig><p>Plants grown in soils with a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> had reduced levels of arbuscular mycorrhizal colonization of roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>). On average, plants in the soil history treatment had 57% reduced hyphal colonization (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,60</sub> = 20.47, <italic>P</italic> = 0.000029), 53% reduced arbuscular colonization (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,60</sub> = 4.97, <italic>P</italic> = 0.029), and 57% reduced vesicular colonization (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,60</sub> = 4.95, <italic>P</italic> = 0.030) than plants grown in control soils. These effects were strongest in <italic>Q. macrocarpa</italic>, <italic>F. virginiana</italic> and <italic>E. canadensis</italic> for hyphae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4A</xref>), <italic>H. perforatum</italic> for arbuscles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4B</xref>) and <italic>F. virginiana</italic> for vesicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4C</xref>). We note that <italic>Q. macrocarpa</italic> is not typically colonized by AM fungi (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table 1</xref>), and so the levels of fungal colonization reported for this species may reflect a non-functional symbiosis. The average sizes of the soil history effect on colonization with <italic>Q. macrocarpa</italic> removed from the dataset were &#x02212;53% for hyphae (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,51</sub> = 14.7, <italic>P</italic> = 0.000353), &#x02212;52.5% for arbuscles (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,51</sub> = 4.63, <italic>P</italic> = 0.036) and &#x02212;54.5% for vesicles (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,51</sub> = 3.38, <italic>P</italic> = 0.072).</p><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>The effect of soil history with <italic>A. petiolata</italic> on the colonization of roots by arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) hyphae (A) AM arbuscules (B), and vesicles (C).</title><p>Statistically significant differences between soil treatments are indicated with an asterisk.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g004"/></fig><p>Morphological and physiological traits of competitor plants grown alone differed among growth forms, but were not generally affected by growing in soil with a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref>). Quantum yield of photosystem II [Y(II)] measured at week 5 was significantly higher in herbs and grasses relative to trees. In week 9, Y(II) was significantly higher in herbs compared to grasses and trees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5A</xref>). The quantum yield of photosystem II did not differ between soil treatments in week 5, but was lower in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil than control soil in week 9. Chlorophyll concentration in week 5 was significantly higher in herbs and grasses than trees, but did not differ among growth forms in week 9, and did not differ between soil history treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5B</xref>). At week 5, grasses were significantly taller than trees and herbs, but height was not influenced by soil history treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5C</xref>). Trees had significantly larger root diameter than either herbs or grasses, which did not differ significantly from each other. Trees also had significantly lower SRL than herbs, whereas grasses had intermediate SRL that did not differ significantly from that of trees or herbs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Figs. 5D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">5E</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/fig-5</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The effect of growth form and exposure to either control or <italic>A. petiolata</italic> soil history on quantum yield of PSII at weeks 5 and 9 (A), leaf chlorophyll concentration at weeks 5 and 9 (B) and plant height at week 5 (C).</title><p>The effect of growth form on root diameter (D) and specific root length (E). Different letters above bars, when present, represent statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) among groups within each treatment, as determined by a comparison of 95% confidence limits among groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g005"/></fig><p>Though above and belowground functional traits varied among growth forms, these traits were generally not associated with their ability to compete in either soil environment, measured as either the ability to resist suppression from (competitive response, CR) or suppress (competitive effect, CE) <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table 4</xref>). The only exception to this pattern was the nearly significant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.06) positive relationship between Y(II) @ 5 weeks and competitive response in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil. In addition, even though species varied in their response to soil history, this variation was also not correlated with competitive ability. The ln response ratio of growth in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history versus control soils (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>) was not associated with either competitive response (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,25</sub> = 0.07, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.003, <italic>P</italic> = 0.79, <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0.978) or competitive effect (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,25</sub> = 0.57, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.022, <italic>P</italic> = 0.45, <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0.266).</p><table-wrap id="table-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/table-4</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Partial correlation coefficients (<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>) indicating relationships between competitive response (CR) or competitive effect (CE) in control or history soil, and plant functional traits, including height at 5 weeks, quantum yield of PS II in the light [Y(II)] at 5 and 9 weeks, leaf chlorophyll content at 5 and 9 weeks, mean root diameter and specific root length (SRL).</title><p>Because traits differed between trees, forbs and grasses, plant growth form was included as a covariate in the analysis, but only <italic>&#x003b2;</italic> and significance values for traits are shown. The degree to which residuals from the multiple regression were correlated with phylogeny is indicated by <italic>&#x003bb;</italic>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g010"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependent variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CR control soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CR history soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.040</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CE control soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CE history soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y(II) @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 5 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chl @ 9 wks</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CR control soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root diameter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CR history soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root diameter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0.981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CE control soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root diameter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CE history soil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root diameter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SRL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Metrics of competitive ability were not strongly correlated across soil treatments. Specifically, CR in control soil only explained 5.7% of the variation in CR in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil, and CE in control soil only explained 12% of the variation in CE in history soil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6</xref>). CR and CE were positively correlated in control soil (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,25</sub> = 7.44, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.229, <italic>P</italic> = 0.01, <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 1), but were not correlated with each other in history soil (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,25</sub> = 2.73, <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.098, <italic>P</italic> = 0.11, <italic>&#x003bb;</italic> = 0).</p><fig id="fig-6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/fig-6</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Relationships between competitive response (A) or competitive effect (B) across control and <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soils.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-g006"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results indicate that <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is a strong competitor against a range of common mycorrhizal grassland, old field and forest species in soils which had no previous history with its conspecifics, but contrary to expectation, this competitive advantage weakens in soil with a history of conspecific growth. In uninvaded control soil, for example, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> suppressed the biomass of a majority of competitor plant species by an average effect size that exceeded 50% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). By contrast, the suppression of competitor species&#x02019; biomass by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was weaker in history soil, with an effect size that was less than half of that observed in control soil. Moreover, 70% of species responded negatively to the presence of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in control soil, but only 26% of species responded negatively in conspecific history soil. Because the soil history treatment reduced plant available nutrients in soil and reduced mycorrhizal colonization of roots, differences in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> competitive ability between treatments could be caused by these factors acting independently or in combination. Nevertheless, our findings suggest that the competitive ability of newly introduced <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is sufficient to displace competitor species in previously uninvaded sites in the short term, but modification of the soil environment by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> may not enhance its competitive ability.</p><p>The weaker competitive effect of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> on other species in history soil occurred despite suppression of mycorrhizal fungi. Mycorrhizal colonization in soils with <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4">Fig. 4</xref>) was reduced by levels comparable to that observed in the field (e.g., <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Barto et al., 2011</xref>), with concomitant reductions in competitor plant growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). However, competitor species were still better able to resist competition from <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in soils with a history of the invader than control soils. Though we cannot separate the individual effects of nutrient depletion and reduced mycorrhizal colonization on the outcome of competition in the present study, we note that <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was suppressed in the soil history treatment at a level that was more than three times the average level of suppression across all competitor species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig. 3</xref>). Because <italic>A. petiolata</italic> is nonmycorrhizal, the strong negative effect of growth in conspecific soil on its biomass was most likely caused by lower nutrients. We suggest, therefore, that the most likely explanation for weaker competitive ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in history soils is that the negative effect of nutrient depletion on <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was stronger than the negative effect of suppressing mycorrhizal colonization on competitor species. <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Davis et al. (2012)</xref> also observed weak effects of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> soil history on the biomass of competitor species. The observation that competition was weaker overall in history soil is also consistent with the hypothesis that when plant growth is suppressed by environmental stress or low fertility, limited overall demand for resource uptake reduces the strength of competition (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Grime, 1977</xref>; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Lamb, Shore &#x00026; Cahill, 2007</xref>).</p><p>Our findings imply that the negative effect of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> on mycorrhizal fungi as a mechanism of competition during invasion may be weaker than previously expected. Though this interpretation is supported by weaker competition in the <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil, where colonization of roots by AM fungi was reduced, it is tentative for two reasons. First, we did not quantify AM fungal colonization of roots for all competitor species, and it is possible that these effects were not the same in unmeasured species. Second, though the reduction in AM fungal colonization of roots is consistent with the presence of fungal inhibiting secondary chemicals produced by <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, we did not directly quantify the concentration of these compounds in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil. Though secondary chemicals produced by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> likely reduced fungal populations during the 5 month soil conditioning period (<xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Roberts &#x00026; Anderson, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">Stinson et al., 2006</xref>), they may have been absent in the main experiment because of a short half-life (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Barto &#x00026; Cipollini, 2009</xref>).</p><p>We hypothesized that <italic>A. petiolata</italic>&#x02019;s strong competitive ability is caused by the capacity to deplete limiting resources to levels lower than resident species, as expected from resource competition theory (<xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">Tilman, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">Tilman &#x00026; Wedin, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Bever et al., 2010</xref>). However, simulated nutrient depletion of soils by <italic>A. petiolata</italic> more strongly suppressed its own growth relative to competitor species. The ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> to suppress other species may therefore be caused by other traits, such as fast growth rate and high allocation to leaf area (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Grime, 1977</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Funk et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Engelhardt &#x00026; Anderson, 2011</xref>). The tendency for decomposing <italic>A. petiolata</italic> leaf litter to increase soil nutrient availability in the years following successful invasion (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers et al., 2008</xref>) also suggests that this species has evolved to compete effectively at high, rather than low, soil resources. In addition, we note that our experiment simulates competition between first year individuals of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> and competitor species. In the field, competition also takes place between spring flowering <italic>A. petiolata</italic> plants that have over wintered as rosettes and newly germinating plants of competitor species, which can further advantage <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Herold et al., 2011</xref>). The observation that nutrient depletion caused by conspecifics reduces individual plant performance, however, corroborates previous findings that <italic>A. petiolata</italic> experiences relatively strong intra-specific competition (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Meekins &#x00026; McCarthy, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Davis et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Leicht-Young, Pavlovic &#x00026; Adams, 2012</xref>), which would limit the net reproductive rate of established populations. The possibility of nutrient-limitation mediated density-dependent population regulation is consistent with recent demographic analyses showing that in situations where other biotic factors such as herbivory are excluded, established <italic>A. petiolata</italic> populations decline towards extinction (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Knight et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Kalisz, Spigler &#x00026; Horvitz, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Growth form was the best predictor of the ability of competitor species to either resist or suppress <italic>A. petiolata</italic>, but this effect varied with soil history and competition metric. For example, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> suppressed the growth of all three growth forms in control soil, but this effect was more modest in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history soil. By contrast, grasses suppressed invader biomass in both soil treatments, whereas forbs had no effect, and trees appeared to facilitate the growth of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in control soils. The ability of grasses to suppress <italic>A. petiolata</italic> may have occurred because they were taller than other growth forms at a young age, which would increase light acquisition (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Grime, 1977</xref>; <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet &#x00026; Keddy, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg &#x00026; Landa, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Rosch, Van Rooyen &#x00026; Theron, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Keddy et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). Grasses also had relatively fine roots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref>), which would increase nutrient uptake capacity (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Aerts, Boot &#x00026; Van der Aart, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Goldberg, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Casper &#x00026; Jackson, 1997</xref>). Nonetheless, height may be the most important factor because grasses and forbs had similar photosynthetic capacity and root architecture, yet forbs did not suppress <italic>A. petiolata</italic> biomass. <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Meekins &#x00026; McCarthy (1999)</xref> also found that <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was a weaker competitor against tall relative to short species. Though the ability of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> to suppress tree growth has been previously observed (<xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr">Stinson et al., 2007</xref>), the observation that trees might facilitate <italic>A. petiolata</italic> growth was unexpected. This effect may be due to aspects that were unique to the two tree species, <italic>P. strobus</italic> and <italic>T. occidentalis</italic>, which had the strongest beneficial effect on <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. These species were the only conifers in the sample and also ranked lowest in terms of growth rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig. 1</xref>). The relatively strong growth form effects of competitor species on <italic>A. petiolata</italic> we report here may not be universal however. Other studies suggest that trees can be strong competitors (<xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Meekins &#x00026; McCarthy, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Smith &#x00026; Reynolds, 2014</xref>) and grasses can be weak competitors (<xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Smith &#x00026; Reynolds, 2014</xref>) against <italic>A. petiolata</italic>.</p><p>Functional trait variation, beyond that associated with growth form, did not predict either the ability of competitor species to resist suppression by, or their ability to suppress, <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. When growth form was included in multiple regressions between traits and competitive response or competitive effect, no significant relationships were found, regardless of soil treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table 4</xref>). There was also limited trait plasticity in response to <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history in soil (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref>), despite strong effects on plant biomass. These findings are consistent with those of <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2010)</xref>, who also reported weak relationships between trait values and competitive ability. The inability to detect specific relationships between traits and competitive ability could be caused by the possibility that competitive ability depends on combinations of several traits or traits that were not measured (<xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr">Wardle et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>), or because functionally alternate strategies, such as efficient resource acquisition or resource storage, can result in similar competitive abilities (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Grime, 1977</xref>).</p><p>Our findings have implications for recent hypotheses about how competitive response and competitive effect should be correlated across environments (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Keddy, Twolan-Strutt &#x00026; Wisheu, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Keddy et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). Specifically, competitive response is expected to be context specific, varying with resource availability or other ecological and environmental factors, and is not expected to be correlated across environments. By contrast, competitive effect is expected to be a general property of a species, such that it is positively correlated across environments (<xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). Our results are generally consistent with these predictions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6</xref>), but the relationship between competitive effect in control and history soils was weaker than (i.e., <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.12, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-6">Fig. 6B</xref>) found in other studies (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Keddy, Twolan-Strutt &#x00026; Wisheu, 1994</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Keddy et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). Observing such context dependency in the competitive effect of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> was not unique to our study. For example, <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Smith &#x00026; Reynolds (2014)</xref> found that <italic>A. petiolata</italic> could suppress other species under high light conditions, but had much weaker effects in the shade. Our findings suggest the ability of competitor species to either resist suppression by, or suppress, <italic>A. petiolata</italic> cannot be confidently predicted from one ecological context to another.</p><p>In conclusion, our findings suggest that <italic>A. petiolata</italic> has the potential to displace resident species in a community upon initial invasion via a relatively strong competitive ability. However, its competitive ability is weakened, rather than strengthened, by conspecific soil history effects. Like previous studies, we observed that soil with a history of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> reduces the ability of mycorrhizal fungi to colonize the roots of competitor species. However, this negative novel weapons effect on mycorrhizal plant species did not appear overcome the negative history effects of soil nutrient depletion on <italic>A. petiolata</italic>. These findings suggest that the inhibitory potential of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> on competitor species via mycorrhizal suppression may not be as strong as previously suggested. In addition, because longer term effects of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> invasion include an overall increase in plant available soil nitrogen and phosphorus (<xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Rodgers et al., 2008</xref>), mycorrhizal suppression is unlikely to be a strong mechanism of competition in the years following invasion. This is because the effect of losing the fungal symbiont approaches neutrality when mycorrhizal plants are grown with supplemental nutrients (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Hoeksema et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Johnson, 2010</xref>). The potential for weak mycorrhizal suppression effects suggests that eradication or control measures based on minimizing novel biochemical weapons effects in <italic>A. petiolata</italic> may be less successful than other approaches. As suggested by other studies, reducing propagule pressure by removal of flowering individuals (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Herold et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Phillips-Mao, Larson &#x00026; Jordan, 2014</xref>) and suppressing browsing by deer (<xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Kalisz, Spigler &#x00026; Horvitz, 2014</xref>) could be more effective strategies to counteract the invasion of <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in North America.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title>Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1090/supp-1</object-id><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Raw biomass and plant trait data listed by species and treatments.</p></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-03-1090-s001.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank A Benoit, E Bothwell, CM Caruso, E Pacey, P Rekret, R Rivkin and three anonymous reviewers for comments on the manuscript. N Sokol and AM Benscoter assisted with various phases of the project.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Gary T. Poon</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Hafiz Maherali</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Aerts, Boot &#x00026; Van der Aart (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aerts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boot</surname><given-names>RGA</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Aart</surname><given-names>PJM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relation between above- and belowground biomass allocation patterns and competitive ability</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1991</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00320419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Barto et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barto</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Antunes</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi communities associated with sugar maple seedlings in and outside of invaded <italic>A. petiolata</italic> forest patches</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1627</fpage><lpage>1639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-011-9945-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Barto &#x00026; Cipollini (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barto</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Half-lives and field soil concentrations of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> secondary metabolites</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2009</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2009.02.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19269670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Bever et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bever</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickie</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Facelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Facelli</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rillig</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibbett</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zobel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rooting theories of plant community ecology in microbial interactions</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source><year>2010</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2010.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20557974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Biswas et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotanen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kambo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Context-dependent patterns, determinants and demographic consequences of herbivory in an invasive species</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-014-0715-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Blossey &#x00026; Notzold (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Notzold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of increased competitive ability: a hypothesis</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>1995</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2261425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Brundrett (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brundrett</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycorrhizal associations and other means of nutrition of vascular plants: understanding the global diversity of host plants by resolving conflicting information and developing reliable means of diagnosis</article-title><source>Plant and Soil</source><year>2009</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-008-9877-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Brundrett, Piche &#x00026; Peterson (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brundrett</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Piche</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new method for observing the morphology of vesicular-arbuscular mycorrhizae</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Botany</source><year>1984</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>2128</fpage><lpage>2134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b84-290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Burke (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Brassicaceae&#x02013;garlic mustard) on mycorrhizal colonization and community structure in three herbaceous plants in a mixed deciduous forest</article-title><source>American Journal of Botany</source><year>2008</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1416</fpage><lpage>1425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.0800184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21628149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Callaway et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Prati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel weapons: invasive plant suppresses fungal mutualists in America but not its native Europe</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2008</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/07-0370.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18481529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Callaway &#x00026; Ridenour (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridenour</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel weapons: invasive success and the evolution of increased competitive ability</article-title><source>Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/1540-9295(2004)002[0436:NWISAT]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Callaway et al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Holben</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil biota and exotic plant invasion</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>427</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14973484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Cantor et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Traw</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalisz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low allelochemical concentrations detected in <italic>A. petiolata</italic>-invaded soils inhibit fungal growth and AMF germination</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3015</fpage><lpage>3025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-011-9986-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Casper &#x00026; Jackson (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant competition underground</article-title><source>Annual Review of Ecology &#x00026; Systematics</source><year>1997</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.28.1.545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Catford, Jansson &#x00026; Nilsson (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Catford</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reducing redundancy in invasion ecology by integrating hypotheses into a single theoretical framework</article-title><source>Diversity and Distributions</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-4642.2008.00521.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Cavers, Heagy &#x00026; Kokron (1979)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavers</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Heagy</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokron</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology of Canadian weeds.: 35. <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (M. Bieb.) Cavara and Grande</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Plant Science</source><year>1979</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4141/cjps79-029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Cipollini et al. (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbagwu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillstrom</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Enright</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of constitutive and inducible chemical defenses in native and invasive populations of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>2005</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-005-5284-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16222770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Cipollini, Stevenson &#x00026; Cipollini (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasting effects of allelochemicals from two invasive plants on the performance of a nonmycorrhizal plant</article-title><source>International Journal of Plant Sciences</source><year>2008</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/526470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Colautti, Grigorovich &#x00026; MacIsaac (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colautti</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigorovich</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>MacIsaac</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Propagule pressure: a null model for biological invasions</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2006</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-005-3735-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Craine et al. (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craine</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Froehle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tilman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapin</surname><given-names>FS</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>The relationships among root and leaf traits of 76 grassland species and relative abundance along fertility and disturbance gradients</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2001</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0706.2001.930210.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Davies et al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barraclough</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Darwin&#x02019;s abominable mystery: insights from a supertree of the angiosperms</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>1904</fpage><lpage>1909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0308127100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Davis et al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Colehour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Macmillen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Merrill</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dosch</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The population dynamics and ecological effects of garlic mustard, <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, in a Minnesota oak woodland</article-title><source>American Midland Naturalist</source><year>2012</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1674/0003-0031-168.2.364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Dietz &#x00026; Edwards (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition that causal processes change during plant invasion helps explain conflicts in evidence</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2006</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1359</fpage><lpage>1367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9658(2006)87[1359:RTCPCD]2.0.CO;2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16869409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Engelhardt &#x00026; Anderson (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenological niche separation of an invasive species <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic></article-title><source>Journal of the Torrey Botanical Society</source><year>2011</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3159/TORREY-D-11-00019.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Freckleton, Harvey &#x00026; Pagel (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freckleton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analysis and comparative data: a test and review of evidence</article-title><source>American Naturalist</source><year>2002</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/343873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Funk et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Suding</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavaleta</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Restoration through re-assembly: plant traits and invasion resistance</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2008</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2008.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18951652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Gaudet &#x00026; Keddy (1988)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaudet</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Keddy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative approach to predicting competitive ability from plant traits</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/334242a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Goldberg (1996)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competitive ability: definitions, contingency and correlated traits</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>1996</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>1377</fpage><lpage>1385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.1996.0121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Goldberg &#x00026; Landa (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Landa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competitive effect and response: hierarchies and correlated traits in the early stages of competition</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>1991</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1013</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2261095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Grime (1977)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grime</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for the existence of three primary strategies in plants and its relevance to ecological theory</article-title><source>American Naturalist</source><year>1977</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1169</fpage><lpage>1194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/283244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Gurevitch et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurevitch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Inderjit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taub</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergent insights from the synthesis of conceptual frameworks for biological invasions</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2011.01594.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21513009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Hale &#x00026; Kalisz (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalisz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives on allelopathic disruption of plant mutualisms: a framework for individual-and population-level fitness consequences</article-title><source>Plant Ecology</source><year>2012</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>1991</fpage><lpage>2006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11258-012-0128-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Herold et al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Borowicz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the effect of early and late removal of second-year garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>) on first-year plants and deciduous forest spring and summer dominant herbaceous groundlayer species in central Illinois, USA</article-title><source>Ecological Restoration</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3368/er.29.3.225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Hoeksema et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoeksema</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Karst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Koide</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabinski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bever</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GWT</given-names></name><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Umbanhowar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A meta-analysis of context-dependency in plant response to inoculation with mycorrhizal fungi</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2009.01430.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20100237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Johnson (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resource stoichiometry elucidates the structure and function of arbuscular mycorrhizas across scales</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2010</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03110.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19968797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Kalisz, Spigler &#x00026; Horvitz (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalisz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spigler</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvitz</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In a long-term experimental demography study, excluding ungulates reversed invader&#x02019;s explosive population growth rate and restored natives</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>4501</fpage><lpage>4506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1310121111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24616522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Keddy et al. (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keddy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neilsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relative competitive performance of 63 species of terrestrial herbaceous plants</article-title><source>Journal of Vegetation Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1654-1103.2002.tb02018.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>Keddy, Twolan-Strutt &#x00026; Wisheu (1994)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keddy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Twolan-Strutt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisheu</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competitive effect and response rankings in 20 wetland plants: are they consistent across three environments?</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>1994</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2261270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Knight et al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalisz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deer facilitate invasive plant success in a Pennsylvania forest understory</article-title><source>Natural Areas Journal</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3375/043.029.0202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Lamb, Shore &#x00026; Cahill (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water and nitrogen addition differentially impact plant competition in a native rough fescue grassland</article-title><source>Plant Ecology</source><year>2007</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11258-006-9222-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Lankau (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lankau</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soil microbial communities alter allelopathic competition between <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> and a native species</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2059</fpage><lpage>2068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-009-9608-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Lankau (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lankau</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance and recovery of soil microbial communities in the face of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> invasion</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2011</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03481.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20958303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Lankau et al. (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lankau</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuzzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Spyreas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary limits ameliorate negative impact of an invasive plant</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>15362</fpage><lpage>15367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0905446106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19706431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Lau &#x00026; Schultheis (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultheis</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>When two invasion hypotheses are better than one</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2015</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>958</fpage><lpage>960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25580651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Leicht-Young, Pavlovic &#x00026; Adams (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leicht-Young</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlovic</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competitive interactions of garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>) and damesrocket (<italic>Hesperis matronalis</italic>)</article-title><source>Invasive Plant Science and Management</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/IPSM-D-11-00025.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Mack et al. (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Simberloff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonsdale</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Clout</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazzaz</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotic invasions: causes, epidemiology, global consequences, and control</article-title><source>Ecological Applications</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/1051-0761(2000)010[0689:BICEGC]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Martins &#x00026; Hansen (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenies and the comparative method: a general approach to incorporating phylogenetic information into the analysis of inter-specific data</article-title><source>American Naturalist</source><year>1997</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/286013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Maxwell &#x00026; Johnson (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chlorophyll fluorescence&#x02014;a practical guide</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2000</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jexbot/51.345.659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>McCarthy &#x00026; Hanson (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An assessment of the allelopathic potential of the invasive weed <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Brassicaceae)</article-title><source>Castanea</source><year>1998</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>McGonigle et al. (1990)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGonigle</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Swan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new method which gives an objective measure of colonization of roots by vesicular-arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>1990</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.1990.tb00476.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Meekins &#x00026; McCarthy (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meekins</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competitive ability of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Garlic Mustard, Brassicaceae), an invasive, nonindigenous forest herb</article-title><source>International Journal of Plant Sciences</source><year>1999</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/314156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Meekins &#x00026; McCarthy (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meekins</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of population density on the demography of an invasive plant, <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, (Brassicaceae) population in a Southeastern Ohio forest</article-title><source>American Midland Naturalist</source><year>2002</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1674/0003-0031(2002)147[0256:EOPDOT]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Orme et al. (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="software"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orme</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Freckleton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Petzoldt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaac</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearse</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caper: Comparative analyses of phylogenetics and evolution in R</article-title><edition designator="0.5.2">R package version 0.5.2</edition><year>2013</year><comment><italic>Available at <uri xlink:href="http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=caper">http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=caper</uri></italic></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Pagel (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring the historical patterns of biological evolution</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>401</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>884</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/44766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10553904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Parker, Rodriguez &#x00026; Loik (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Loik</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evolutionary approach to understanding the biology of invasions: local adaptation and general-purpose genotypes in the weed <italic>Verbascum thapsus</italic></article-title><source>Conservation Biology</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1523-1739.2003.02019.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Phillips-Mao, Larson &#x00026; Jordan (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips-Mao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of native herbs and light on garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>) invasion</article-title><source>Invasive Plant Science and Management</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1614/IPSM-D-13-00003.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Pimental et al. (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pimental</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lach</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuniga</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental and economic costs of nonindigenous species in the United States</article-title><source>Bioscience</source><year>2000</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/0006-3568(2000)050[0053:EAECON]2.3.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>Prati &#x00026; Bossdorf (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossdorf</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allelopathic inhibition of germination by <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Brassicaceae)</article-title><source>American Journal of Botany</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.91.2.285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>R Core Team (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab><institution>R Core Team</institution></collab></person-group><source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><comment><italic>Available at <uri xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/">http://www.R-project.org/</uri></italic></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-60"><label>Roberts &#x00026; Anderson (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of Garlic Mustard [<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Beib. Cavara &#x00026; Grande)] extracts on plants and arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi</article-title><source>American Midland Naturalist</source><year>2001</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1674/0003-0031(2001)146[0146:EOGMAP]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-61"><label>Rodgers, Stinson &#x00026; Finzi (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Finzi</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ready or not, Garlic Mustard is moving in: <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> as a member of eastern North American forests</article-title><source>Bioscience</source><year>2008</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1641/B580510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-62"><label>Rodgers et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Werden</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Finzi</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The invasive species <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Garlic Mustard) increases soil nutrient availability in northern hardwood-conifer forests</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2008</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-008-1089-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-63"><label>Rosch, Van Rooyen &#x00026; Theron (1997)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Rooyen</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Theron</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting competitive interactions between pioneer plant species by using plant traits</article-title><source>Journal of Vegetation Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3237200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-64"><label>Smith &#x00026; Reynolds (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light, allelopathy, and post-mortem invasive impact on native forest understory species</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-013-0567-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-65"><label>Stinson et al. (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Prati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Klironomos</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Invasive plant suppresses the growth of native tree seedlings by disrupting belowground mutualisms</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e1090</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-66"><label>Stinson et al. (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responses of a New England forest community to increasing levels of invasion by garlic mustard (<italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>)</article-title><source>Northeastern Naturalist</source><year>2007</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1656/1092-6194(2007)14[73:IOGMIO]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-67"><label>Stinson &#x00026; Seidler (2014)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidler</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological constraints on the spread of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> populations in Massachusetts</article-title><source>Ecosphere</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e1090</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/ES14-00164.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-68"><label>Tilman (1988)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plant strategies and the dynamics and structure of plant communities</source><year>1988</year><publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-69"><label>Tilman &#x00026; Wedin (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tilman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of nitrogen competition between successional grasses</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1991</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1940604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-70"><label>Wang &#x00026; Qiu (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic distribution and evolution of mycorrhizas in land plants</article-title><source>Mycorrhiza</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00572-005-0033-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-71"><label>Wang et al. (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stieglitz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are competitive effect and response two sides of the same coin, or fundamentally different?</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2435.2009.01612.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-72"><label>Wardle et al. (1998)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonner</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can comparative approaches based on plant ecophysiological traits predict the nature of biotic interactions and individual plant species effects in ecosystems?</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>1998</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2745.1998.00268.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-73"><label>Webb, Ackerly &#x00026; Kembel (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackerly</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kembel</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylocom: software for the analysis of phylogenetic community structure and trait evolution</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2098</fpage><lpage>2100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btn358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18678590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-74"><label>Wolfe et al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stinson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The invasive plant <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Garlic Mustard) inhibits ectomycorrhizal fungi in it introduced range</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>2008</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>783</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2745.2008.01389.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-75"><label>Zheng et al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Valiente-Banuet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Z-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Barclay</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-Pereyra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrating novel chemical weapons and evolutionarily increased competitive ability in success of a tropical invader</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2015</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>1350</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25367824</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>