<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>GC–MS analysis revealed that the main components of 
 <italic>Zingiber ottensii</italic> (ZO) Valeton essential oil were sesquiterpenes of which zerumbone was the major compound (24.73%), followed by monoterpenes including terpinene-4-ol (18.75%), sabinene (15.19%), and β-Pinene (7.95%) (
 <xref rid="toxics-09-00102-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These findings are in line with the phytochemical compositions of ZO cultivated in Johor, Malaysia, and Phetchaburi Province, Thailand, where major constituents have been reported to be zerumbone (25.63% and 40.14%), terpinene-4-ol (16.81% and 11.17%), sabinene (7.20% and 6.48%), and β-Pinene (5.08% and 4.32%) [
 <xref rid="B17-toxics-09-00102" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-toxics-09-00102" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The most abundant compound of ZO cultivated in Bandung, Indonesia, however, is terpinene-4-ol (16.55%), followed by zerumbone (14.23%) with some other phytochemical components including longifolenaldehyde (1.33%) and 2,5,9-trimethyl-cycloundeca-4,8-dienone (1.00%) [
 <xref rid="B32-toxics-09-00102" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The differences in the amounts and phytoconstituents of the essential oil may be due to differences in cultivation areas, growing seasons, harvest times, and environmental conditions [
 <xref rid="B33-toxics-09-00102" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Interestingly, zerumbone and terpinene-4-ol have been reported to possess a broad spectrum of beneficial biological effects, e.g., anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects [
 <xref rid="B34-toxics-09-00102" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-toxics-09-00102" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Those effects make it attractive to develop pharmaceutical products from ZO essential oil, which can could potentially increase the value of the herbs as well as local farmers’ income. However, an important initial step in the development of any drug or herbal product is to confirm its safety, generally by in vivo toxicity studies. In particular, there is still a lack of scientific evidence demonstrating the safety profile of ZO essential oil in terms of embryonic and teratogenic toxicity and acute oral toxicity. The zebrafish model can also be used in high throughput and valid screening models to study the embryotoxic and teratogenic effects. Such studies require only small amounts of test substances, short duration of study, are low cost and are not so complicated to perform, compared with toxicity models in rats. On the other hand, models to study the development toxicity in rats require higher amounts of test substances, longer duration of study, are higher cost and are very complicated to perform. Due to these reasons, zebrafish models were used, instead of models to study the development toxicity in rats, as the screening models to study the embryotoxic and teratogenic effects of ZO essential oil. The acute oral toxicity in rats is also another well-known model. It is used to provide information on health hazards likely to arise from short-term exposure by the oral route of any test substance and is a step in establishing a dosage regimen in subchronic and other toxicity studies.
</p>
