<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the high profile of health risks arising from the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic there remains substantial concerns regarding the likely levels of compliance (even among medical workers) should an effective vaccine become available [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Similarly, the effective management of pest animals, weeds, and agricultural pathogens is becoming increasingly difficult. At least two global trends will challenge existing approaches to the management of invasive alien species, including human and livestock diseases. The first trend is the increasing resistance of invasive alien plants, invertebrates, vertebrates, and pathogens to methods of chemical control, whether in the form of pesticides, fungicides, herbicides, or antimicrobials [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C67" ref-type="bibr">67–71</xref>]. Strategies to combat resistance to chemical control strategies are vital to ensure the sustainability of current invasive alien species management, and this requires research to find alternative mode-of-action synthetic chemical pesticides and other nonchemical approaches. However, the rate at which new pesticides and antimicrobials are being registered is slower than the rate at which active ingredients are being removed from the market and may limit the ability to control pests, weeds, and pathogens [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The second trend is the social resistance to the tools used to combat pests, weeds, and pathogens. The management of vertebrate pests depends on the use of traps, pesticides, repellents, and other methods, each of which can cause varying levels of pain and other negative experiences to animals. Increasingly the humaneness of control techniques is viewed as more important than its effectiveness resulting in humane but less efficient tools being available for pest control [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. The public are increasingly resistant to pesticides in the environment and in their food, putting increasing pressure on pest control to apply more environmentally acceptable alternatives and/or reduce rates of application [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. At the same time, there remains a growing social movement of public health vaccine opposition [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. In the United States, an increasing number of antivaccine activities are being established in major metropolitan areas, rendering select cities vulnerable for vaccination-preventable diseases [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. This is a particularly alarming development since urban areas are likely to be hotspots for the emergence of new zoonotic diseases. The consequences of these two global trends is that post-border biosecurity management will become increasingly complex, challenging scientists to develop new tools to replace currently unacceptable approaches and compelling society to appreciate the cost and benefits of pest and disease control. Given the parallels in these trends facing both human and animal health as well as plant and environmental health, a unified approach under the banner of One Biosecurity would certainly bring benefits.
</p>
