<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ukrainian researchers have conducted a study evaluating antimicrobial activity of 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> L. herb extracts, including 
 <italic>A. abrotanum</italic> extract. Therefore, the team has prepared ethanol extracts of 
 <italic>A. abrotanum</italic>, 
 <italic>A. vulgaris and A. absinthium</italic> with three concentration of the solvent: 40%, 70% and 90%. Micromethod of diffusion in agar has been employed in antimicrobial activity assessment. Moderate inhibition of the growth of bacteria: 
 <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus agalactiae</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus gordonii</italic>, 
 <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Citrobacter freundii</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>; methicilin suseptible: 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus and Staphylococcus epidermis</italic>; methicillin resistant: 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus haemolyticus</italic> and macrolides resistant: 
 <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> strains under influence of 
 <italic>A. abrotanum</italic> herb ethanolic extract has been noted. The strongest bacteriostatic activity of the 70% ethanol extract has been displayed against 
 <italic>Propionibacterium acnes</italic> MLS (8.71 mm. = inhibition zone) in comparison with the control (70% ethanol). The results also showed a decrement of the growth of 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and 
 <italic>Candida tropicalis</italic> colonies as well as a significant inhibition of 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> spore germination (13.32 mm.). Moreover, the study has also evaluated a synergistic action of 
 <italic>A. abrotanum</italic> ethanol herb extract with erythromycin against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> with efflux mechanism of MLS-resistance. Only extract with 90% ethanol displayed a synergistic action with erythromycin. The results demonstrated inhibition zone 6.83 mm. with 1.95 µg/mL concentration of erythromycin and 7.48 mm. with 31.25 µg/mL of erythromycin. Of note, erythromycin alone didn’t exhibit any action against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> with efflux mechanism of MLS-resistance so did medium without erythromycin [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-02503" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
