<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Detailed information on the mechanisms of antimicrobial actions of EOs is not fully understood yet. However, various researchers have proposed several plausible mechanisms of antimicrobial activity (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-13-00575-f011">Figure 11</xref>). Most of the EOs increase the bacterial cell wall permeability. The increase in the permeability of the cell wall can be related to the dissolution of the lipid structures that compromises the integrity of the microbial cell wall [
 <xref rid="B47-polymers-13-00575" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. This consequently results in the leakage of the intracellular contents, thereby resulting in bacterial cell death. In addition to the cell wall damage, the EOs can induce damage to the cell membrane proteins and cytoplasmic membrane. Hence, the EOs exhibit greater activity against the Gram-positive bacteria, which contains a peptidoglycan layer on the external surface of the outer membrane. The presence of the lipopolysaccharides in the Gram-negative bacteria prevents the internalization of the EOs within the bacterial cells. The activity of the quorum sensing response regulator of the genus 
 <italic>Vibrio</italic> is inhibited by certain components of EOs (e.g., cinnamaldehyde and its derivatives), which considerably reduces their virulence [
 <xref rid="B47-polymers-13-00575" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Coagulation of the cytoplasm and reduction in proton motive force have also been reported in the presence of EOs. EOs that contain trans-cinnamaldehyde can significantly reduce the intracellular ATP levels in some bacteria (e.g., Escherichia coli and Salmonella Typhimurium) [
 <xref rid="B47-polymers-13-00575" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The reduction in the ATP levels can be accounted for by the combined effect of hydrolysis of the ATPs and hampering their synthesis. Interestingly, carvone can only disrupt the cell wall functionality and does not have any effect on the intracellular ATP levels in the bacteria. Many researchers have proposed the use of whole EOs for better antimicrobial activity as compared to the use of purified active antimicrobial components of EOs. This has been reasoned to the synergistic activity of the different antimicrobial components that are present in the EOs. The synergistic activity increases the potency of the EOs without inducing any toxic effects [
 <xref rid="B47-polymers-13-00575" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. 
</p>
