<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For thousands of years, different studies have introduced 
 <italic>Allium species</italic> as potential medicinal agents [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. There are several reports of multiple biological activities including antioxidant, antibacterial, antiviral, anti-inflammatory, and prevention of cardiovascular disorders from the 
 <italic>Allium</italic> species such as garlic (
 <italic>A. sativum</italic>) and onion (
 <italic>A. cepa</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Although there are many subtypes and extraction method differences, the biological effects of 
 <italic>Allium</italic> species may be attributable to various compounds including dietary fibers and polyphenolic contents [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. For example, it is reported that bulbs of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> contain hundreds of phytochemicals including sulfur-containing compounds such as ajoenes (
 <italic>E</italic>-ajoene, 
 <italic>Z</italic>-ajoene), thiosulfinates (allicin), vinyldithiins (2-vinyl-(4H)-1,3-dithiin, 3-vinyl-(4H)-1,2-dithiin), sulfides (diallyl disulfide (DADS), diallyl trisulfide (DATS), and others that accounted for 82% of the overall garlic sulfur content [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Though Shin et al. reported several distinct peaks including 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid, chlorogenic acid, and rutin as major peaks compared with their respective standards in the HPLC analysis of A.S., the chemical composition and the biological effect of other 
 <italic>Allium</italic> species have not been adequately investigated in different diseases [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00035" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
</p>
