<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Protea caffra</italic> is a dicotyledonous shrub (3 m) that grows in different parts of Mozambique, South Africa and Zimbabwe [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The plant is native to South Africa where it is locally known as the common sugarbush, Natal sugarbush (English), 
 <italic>gewone suikerbos</italic>, 
 <italic>waboom</italic> (Afrikaans), 
 <italic>isadlunge</italic>, 
 <italic>indlunge</italic>, 
 <italic>isiqwanwe</italic> (Isixhosa), 
 <italic>uhlinkihane</italic> (isiZulu), 
 <italic>tshididiri, tshidzungu</italic> (TshiVhenda), 
 <italic>mahlako</italic>, 
 <italic>mogalagala</italic>, 
 <italic>segwapi</italic>, 
 <italic>sekila</italic> and 
 <italic>tshidzungu</italic> (Sotho) [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. As applicable with other members of the genus 
 <italic>Protea</italic>, it has characteristic large beautiful flower heads which have made it an important ornamental plant in southern Africa and other parts of the world [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Apart from having important horticultural purposes, 
 <italic>Protea caffra</italic> has several ethnomedicinal applications. For instance, the aqueous infusions of the root and stem barkare used to manage bleeding stomach ulcers, diarrhoea or as enemas [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. According to Zukulu [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], the roots of the plant are used to prepare 
 <italic>umhlabelo</italic>, a decoction used to help heal broken bones. The fruit and stem bark are also used to manage dizziness, while decoctions of dried seeds are used to manage different psychological disorders [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. A study by Semenya et al. [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-09-01331" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], revealed that the Bapedi traditional healers of South Africa use 
 <italic>Protea caffra</italic> seed infusions to manage chlamydia, a sexually transmitted bacterial infection. However, the scientific basis for the majority of its traditional uses are currently lacking or limited. In addition, the phytochemical and toxicological evaluations of 
 <italic>Protea caffra</italic> remain pertinent to contribute toward its wider acceptance. The present study investigated the antibacterial (against drug-sensitive and -resistant strains), mutagenic and phytochemical properties of different parts of 
 <italic>Protea caffra</italic>.
</p>
