<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) and other free radicals cause oxidative damage in cells under biotic and abiotic stress. Endophytic microorganisms reside in the internal tissues of plants and contribute to the mitigation of such stresses by the production of antioxidant enzymes and compounds. We hypothesized that the endophytic actinobacterium 
  <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. strain DBT34, which was previously demonstrated to have plant growth-promoting (PGP) and antimicrobial properties, may also have a role in protecting plants against several stresses through the production of antioxidants. The present study was designed to characterize catalase and superoxide dismutase (SOD), two enzymes involved in the detoxification of ROS, in methanolic extracts derived from six endophytic actinobacterial isolates obtained from the traditional medicinal plant 
  <italic>Mirabilis jalapa</italic>. The results of a preliminary screen indicated that 
  <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. strain DBT34 was the best overall strain and was therefore used in subsequent detailed analyses. A methanolic extract of DBT34 exhibited significant antioxidant potential in 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and 2,2′-azino-bis-3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulphonic acid (ABTS) assays. The cytotoxicity of DBT34 against liver hepatocellular cells (HepG2) was also determined. Results indicated that methanolic extract of 
  <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. strain DBT34 exhibited significant catalase and SOD-like activity with 158.21 U resulting in a 55.15% reduction in ROS. The IC
  <sub>50</sub> values of a crude methanolic extract of strain DBT34 on DPPH radical scavenging and ABTS radical cation decolorization were 41.5 µg/mL and 47.8 µg/mL, respectively. Volatile compounds (VOC) were also detected in the methanolic extract of 
  <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. strain DBT34 using GC-MS analysis to correlate their presence with bioactive potential. Treatments of rats with DBT34 extract and sitagliptin resulted in a significant (
  <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.001) reduction in total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, and VLDL-cholesterol, relative to the vehicle control and a standard diabetic medicine. The pancreatic histoarchitecture of vehicle control rats exhibited a compact volume of isolated clusters of Langerhans cells surrounded by acinies with proper vaculation. An in-vivo study of 
  <italic>Streptomyces</italic> sp. strain DBT34 on chickpea seedlings revealed an enhancement in its antioxidant potential as denoted by lower IC
  <sub>50</sub> values for DPPH and ABTS radical scavenging activity under greenhouse conditions in relative comparison to control plants. Results of the study indicate that strain DBT34 provides a defense mechanism to its host through the production of antioxidant therapeutic agents that mitigate ROS in hosts subjected to biotic and abiotic stresses. 
 </p>
</abstract>
