<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phenolic compounds present in 
 <italic>F. ammoniacum</italic> and other plants serve as antioxidants due to its hydroxyl groups, which have exhibited strong antioxidant potential and have been reported to cause cholinesterase inhibition as well as they are capable of reacting with active oxygen radicals such as hydroxyl radicals. Flavonoids are polyphenolic compounds found in fruits and vegetables, and are highly effective scavengers of most oxidizing molecules, including singlet oxygen, and various free radicals implicated in several diseases including AD. Flavonoids can provide protection to the brain cells by modulating intracellular signals and promoting cellular survival [
 <xref rid="B41-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In the current study highest contents of total phenolic (88.23 ± 1.13) and flavonoids (85.93 ± 0.67) were detected in Fa.EtAc followed by Fa.Chf extract (TPC: 75.12 ± 1.58 and TFC: 77.83 ± 2.16). Phenolics and flavonoids are free radical scavengers responsible for the observed high antioxidant and anticholinesterase activities, thus having protective effects in many neuro degenerative diseases such AD. The inhibition of cholinesterase enzymes is considered as a promising strategy in the management of neurological and neurodegenerative disorders such as AD, where a deficit in cholinergic neurotransmission is often observed. Several pharmacological effects of the plant extract such as antioxidant, anticholinesterase, free radical scavenging, antidiabetic, and hypolipidemic activities regarding the essential oil and crude extract of roots and aerial parts of Dorema species have also been associated with the presence of phenolic and flavonoid compounds [
 <xref rid="B23-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
