<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Essential oils are highly demanded substances worldwide due to their large number of chemical and biological properties [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The limit for the use of these metabolites is their low yield. The yield and extraction time of essential oil depends on the plant species and the part of the plant used for the extraction: leaves, trunk, fruits, roots, etc. [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]; for this reason, the yields are very varied with values &lt; 0.01% up to values &gt; 3%. For common genera such as Eucalyptus, yields have been reported to range from 0.2 to 2.5% for fresh plant material (leaves) [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Considering that essential oil is a commercially important substance, several efforts have been made to improve yields and reduce extraction times; research includes use or treatment with enzymes [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], microwave [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], supercritical carbon dioxide [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], steam explosion [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], etc. Extraction times by hydrodistillation range from two to four hours [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and from one to two hours if microwave-assisted hydrodistillation is used [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-09-01658" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The short extraction times in the present investigation are because the essential oil was previously released from the plant matrix. The release prior to the hydrodistillation process makes it possible to obtain the majority (95%) of the essential oil in the first hour of distillation. The authors propose that the optimal extraction time would be 1.5 h, with which it would be possible to obtain an optimal extraction amount of 98% of essential oil; 470 mL (47 mL/Kg) from fresh and 1107 mL (111 mL/Kg) from dried fruit.
</p>
