<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the case of the aforementioned thermal treatment, some volatile compounds are lost and the flavour of the resulting product may be different from the starting components. By now, due to the fragrant food additives, we are able to restore these aromas to a certain extent. The addition of some synthetic or natural aromas to food products increases their tastiness and sensory attractiveness. These substances are not always friendly to our health. It happens that during the heat treatment of processed foods a Maillard reaction occurs, resulting in melanoidine molecules (the pigment responsible for the colour of bread crust or roasted meat) and by-products, e.g., furfuryl aldehyde 
 <bold>11</bold>, hydroxymethylfurfural HMF 
 <bold>12</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02473-f002">Figure 2</xref>), propene aldehyde H
 <sub>2</sub>C=CHCHO, acrylamide H
 <sub>2</sub>C=CHCONH
 <sub>2</sub> and others, depending on the pH, substrates and temperature. Most of the low-molecular substances formed at that time have high reactivity, including potential carcinogenicity, such as acrylamide [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Nowadays, due to a greater socio-consumer awareness regarding food preservatives, consumers prefer to choose products that are enriched with natural fragrances or processed without the addition of artificial preservatives, e.g., osmotic dehydration [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In addition, Piekut [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-02473" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] proved that besides the olfactory experience, the presence of common spices, such as ginger, dill, lovage and thyme, have very strong antibacterial (on 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (Migula) Castellani and Chalmers, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> Rosenbach, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (Schröter) Migula, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (Ehrenberg) Cohn) and antifungal (on 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (C.-P. Robin) Berkhout) properties.
</p>
