<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0011">To assess the electrochemical characteristics of tea extracts, comparative CV analysis upon these candidate redox mediators was carried out through electrochemical workstation (ALS/DY2325 BI-POTENTIOSTAT, Taiwan). A glassy carbon electrode (0.07 cm
 <sup>2</sup>; CH Instruments Inc., SA) polished with 0.05 μm alumina polish was used as the working electrode. Quadrate platinum electrode (6.08 cm
 <sup>2</sup>) was served as the counter electrode and was soaked in hydrogen peroxide (H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>) prior to use. As the reference electrode, a Hg/Hg
 <sub>2</sub>Cl
 <sub>2</sub> electrode was filled with saturated KCl
 <sub>(aq)</sub> to maintain electrochemical stability and reproducibility. Prior to analysis, the test solutions were purged with nitrogen 15 min for removal of residual oxygen. The symmetric scan range from −1.5 to + 1.5 V were carried out with a scanning rate of 10 mV 
 <italic>s</italic> 
 <sup>−</sup> 
 <sup>1</sup>. As the direct parameter to assess the redox capacity, closed curve area of redox potential 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg">
   <mrow>
    <mo>(</mo>
    <mrow>
     <mi mathvariant="normal">i</mi>
     <mo>.</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="normal">e</mi>
     <mo>.</mo>
     <mo>,</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mspace width="0.33em"/>
      <mtext>Area</mtext>
     </mrow>
     <mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mo>
     <munderover>
      <mo>∫</mo>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mi>V</mi>
        <mi>L</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <msub>
       <mi>V</mi>
       <mi>H</mi>
      </msub>
     </munderover>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>h</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mo>
       <msub>
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>l</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mtext>dV</mtext>
    </mrow>
    <mo>)</mo>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> were determined with Origin 8. Considering data calculation, V
 <sub>H</sub>, V
 <sub>L</sub> represented the CV scanning voltages of +1.5 V and −1.5 V, respectively; 
 <italic>i
  <sub>h</sub>, i
  <sub>l</sub>
 </italic> denoted the oxidation currents and the reduction currents at specific scan voltage, respectively. Moreover, 100 cycles of CV scan were conducted to verify the electrochemical reversibility and stability of redox-mediating characteristics.
</p>
