<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5-ijerph-15-00651" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Palm Oil and Saturated Fatty Acids: Effects on Children</div>
 <sec id="sec5dot1-ijerph-15-00651" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.1. The First Six Months of Life</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dietary fats represent the main energy source during the first years of life, and they perform a crucial role in nurslings’ growth and development, especially for premature neonates, because they are among the constituents of the nervous and retinal tissue.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The newborn must immediately switch the main source of calories form glucose (placenta) to fats (breast milk) [
   <a rid="B24-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-15-00651">24</a>]. The composition of human milk is adapted to the needs of newborns and thus represents the gold standard on which to base infant formulas. In the absence of breast milk, formulas play a crucial role in ensuring the correct intake of nutrients.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In human milk, unsaturated fatty acids, including optimal percentages of essential fatty acids (α-linolenic and linoleic), are more prevalent than saturated fatty acids. Saturated fatty acids, 50% of which consist of palmitic acid, account for 40% of total fat. Moreover, the particular stereospecific distribution of the different fatty acid triglycerides guarantees advantageous absorption. The differences between breast milk versus bovine milk are essentially qualitative; this is the reason why bovine milk is enriched with oleic acid and saturated lauric, myristic and palmitic acids [
   <a rid="B24-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-15-00651">24</a>]. In breast milk, palmitic acid is esterified at the sn-2 position, while in formulas it is often found in the sn-1 and sn-3 positions, leading to less absorption and more solid faeces, which are typical in artificial breastfeeding.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vegetal oils that are rich in saturated fatty acids, including some tropical oils (such as palm and coconut oils), are used for formulas in order to increase their energetic value [
   <a rid="B25-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-15-00651">25</a>]. In addition, the inter-esterification process induces favourable effects in infant formula, as the absorption of palmitic acid increases [
   <a rid="B25-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-15-00651">25</a>]. Recently, Sanders has demonstrated that palmitic acid in sn-2 can reduce postprandial lipemia, confirming the joint FAO/WHO study of 2008 [
   <a rid="B8-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-15-00651">8</a>,
   <a rid="B26-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-15-00651">26</a>]. A valid nutritional alternative for premature newborns, in the absence of breast milk, is the human milk bank, which has been shown to be a better alternative than formula milk. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec5dot2-ijerph-15-00651" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.2. Six Months–Two Years </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Weaning is an important dietary change: the caloric contribution of lipids decreases from 50 to 35–40% at 24 months owing to a progressive increase in the amount of carbohydrates, which will continue into adulthood [
   <a rid="B27-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-15-00651">27</a>]. To date, there is no evidence of any link between dietary fat consumption before 2 years of age and later health conditions, particularly for non-transmissible chronic pathologies such as diabetes, metabolic syndrome or cardiovascular disease [
   <a rid="B28-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-15-00651">28</a>]. It is difficult, however, to determine the specific metabolic effects of a particular fatty acid and how much it influences the lipid profile in subsequent life phases. It is still difficult to understand the roles of various factors (i.e., gender, degree of excessive weight, distribution of body fat, level of motor activity, composition of macronutrients in the diet) on the optimal dietary lipid profile [
   <a rid="B29-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-15-00651">29</a>]. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec5dot3-ijerph-15-00651" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.3. Three Years–Eighteen Years </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 3 years old onwards, the nutritional recommendations regarding fats are the same as those for adults. It is necessary to pay greater attention to one’s lifestyle during these years, as the consumption of baked goods, snacks, cookies and chips is especially widespread in this age range [
   <a rid="B4-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-15-00651">4</a>]. Desserts and other such products contain refined oils, enhanced flours, chemical yeast, synthesized vitamins, sugars, high salt content, toxic products deriving from high-temperature cooking, and palm oil as well. This is the reason why palm oil cannot be considered the only culprit for the ill health effects of this junk food [
   <a rid="B30-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-15-00651">30</a>]. 
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
