<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">The conventional manufacturing method includes collecting stems and leaves, soaking, producing coarse indigo, refining, and drying (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The manufacturing process is very interesting, including microbial action, component transformation, adsorption and precipitation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Firstly, the stems and leaves from 
 <italic>Baphicacanthus cusia</italic> (Nees) Bremek, 
 <italic>Polygonum tinctorium</italic> Ait or 
 <italic>Isatis indigotica</italic> Fort are soaked in water until rot. Under the action of microorganisms, indole glycosides and endogenous polyglucosidases are released from stems and leaves. In soaking processing, the most important chemical change is that endogenous polyglucosidases hydrolyzes indole glycoside to produce indole phenol, which is the source of indigo and indirubin. Then, stems and leaves are removed and lime slurry is added. Indole phenol combines with oxygen to form indole phenol free radical in an alkaline environment. Some indole phenol radicals condense to form indigo, and some indole phenol radicals are further oxidized to indole ketone and combine with indole phenol to form indirubin. Simultaneously, Ca(OH)
 <sub>2</sub> in lime reacts with CO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>2−</sup> in the soaking solution to form the CaCO
 <sub>3</sub> nucleus, which provides carriers for adsorbing indigo, indirubin and other compounds. With the continuous deposition of the compound on the surface of CaCO
 <sub>3</sub>, the gravity of the polymer exceeds the buoyancy, and the solid-liquid separation is realized at the bottom of the water. These polymers are the original indigo naturalis and commercial indigo naturalis is obtained from the further separation, purification and drying of the original indigo naturalis. In fact, the process of soaking and adding lime is not only the conversion of indole phenol, as well as the transformation of other substances. However, the transformation of other substances needs further researches.
</p>
