<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Torreya grandis</italic> Fort. ex Lindl. are plants belonging to the Taxaceae family, which are also known as “chiguo”. Six different species and two varieties of
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya</italic> have been reported to date. Three of these species (
 <italic class="italic">Torreya fargesii</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya fargesii </italic>var. yunnanensis, and
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis</italic>) and two varieties (
 <italic class="italic">Torreya jackii and Torreya grandis </italic>var. Jiulongshanensis) can be found in China; one species (
 <italic class="italic">Torreya nucifera</italic>) can be found in Japan; and two species (
 <italic class="italic">Torreya taxifolia </italic>and
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya californica</italic>) can be found in America [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>].
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis</italic>, which has been cultivated in China for more than 1500 years, is a rare and unique species, which is mainly distributed across the hilly areas of subtropical China, which is located in Zhejiang, Fujian, Anhui, Jiangxi, Jiangsu, Hunan, Hubei, Guizhou, and other places in China; vast territories were distributed, among them,
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis </italic>Fort. ex Lindl is mainly distributed in Zhuji, Zhejiang province. In recent years, a large number of ancient trees of
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis </italic>Fort. ex Lindl have been found in this area; among them, there are 42 ancient trees over a thousand years old, and the oldest one has reached 1500 years [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>].
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis</italic> cv. Merrillii is the only grafted and thoroughbred species of
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis </italic>Fort. ex Lindl, which has a wide variety of seedling species because of its broad range of characteristics.
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis </italic>Fort. ex Lindl is well known for its edible seeds of
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis,</italic> which have a unique nutty flavor and high nutritional value, leading to their use in traditional Chinese medicine [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. It is noteworthy that there are still four kinds of
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis</italic> of wild mutation variety of Zhimafei, Cunguangfei, Xiangyafei, and Dayuanfei, in China, and that the seeds of these wild species have comparable flavor and quality characteristics to those of cultivated
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis</italic>. However, the seeds of these wild plants are unsuitable for human consumption, and these species have consequently been abandoned without reasonable utilization. Previous studies have demonstrated that
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis</italic> seeds have multiple biological properties including antioxidative, anti-inflammatory, antiatherosclerosis, antiviral, antifungal, antitumor and antihelminthic activities, because of their rich nutritional content and numerous bioactive fatty acid, protein, vitamin, and mineral components [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. With this in mind, we investigated the inhibitory activities of TGSO and four wild
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis </italic>seed oils (TGSOs) towards tyrosinase to provide a platform for the rational utilization of wild
 <italic class="italic"> Torreya grandis.</italic>
</p>
