<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The methanol extracts of yellow leaves, green leaves, and debarked stems of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> were evaluated by analyzing potential anti-cancer activity for different tumor cell lines, including COLO-205, HOS, SNU-245, SNU-308, Huh-BAT, and Huh-7. In particular, the authors investigated the possible mechanism of action behind the impact of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> extracts on the most vulnerable cell line Huh-7. Based on the investigation, 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> extracts at 50 µg/mL caused an increase in apoptotic and triggering p53 and p16 in Huh-7 cells. Moreover, the extracts of the green leaf and the debarked stems of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> significantly inhibited the activation of ERK and Akt levels, resulting in the suppression of Huh-7 cell proliferation [
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Aceituno et al. demonstrated that novel synthesis of silver nanoparticles (Ag-NPs) using leaves extract of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> showed cytotoxicity in the cell lines A549 and HepG2. Cells treated with synthesized Ag-NPs at 25 µg/mL displayed significant increases in ROS production, reduction in cell migration, and cell apoptosis in both cell lines. Moreover, synthesized Ag-NPs treatment resulted in significant modulation of the EGFR/p38 expressions in A549 cells [
 <xref rid="B70-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Elsewhere, Lee et al. evaluated the proapoptotic activities of ethanol extracts of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> stem bark on human leukemia U937 cells. The extracts of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> at various concentrations of 0, 20, 40, 60, 80, and 100 µg/mL exhibited decreased cell growth, due to inhibited cell proliferation, the induction of cell apoptosis, and the downregulation of anti-apoptotic IAP family proteins, and together with the subsequent inhibition of Bcl-2 and Bcl-xL protein expression levels, the loss of MMP, and bid cleavage, suggesting that the apoptosis of U937 cells occurred through both intrinsic and extrinsic pathways [
 <xref rid="B71-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. In the study by Jin et al., oleifolioside-B, a triterpene glycoside compound isolated from the stem of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic>, was evaluated in A549 cells. Here, oleifolioside-B exposure at 30 µM induced caspase activation and typical apoptotic features. Subsequently, oleifolioside-B treatment increased autophagy, as indicated by an increase in the levels of the autophagy-specific gene MAP1LC3 and Atg3, which was associated with the inhibition of Nrf2 expression [
 <xref rid="B83-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Similar studies have also reported on oleifolioside-A, a new anticancer agent isolated from 
 <italic>D. morbifera,</italic> and found that the mechanisms of oleifolioside-A exhibited activities of potentially induced caspases activation and apoptotic features in HeLa cells. In addition, oleifolioside-A administration induced the up-regulation of the loss of MMP, Bad, AIF, and EndoG factors, and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B84-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Meanwhile, Lee et al. evaluated the anticancer activity of dendropanoxide isolated from the leaves and stems of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> and the results study indicated treatment with 60 µM could modulate the autophagy through ERK1/2 activation in human osteosarcoma (OS) cells and induce apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B29-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Recently, using an in vivo tumor xenograft model, the administration of 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> 25 mg/kg orally daily for 10 days achieved renoprotective properties against cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity without blocking the chemotherapeutic efficacy. The authors suggested that 
 <italic>D. morbifera</italic> might be combined with cisplatin therapy to protect renal function during the treatment of solid tumor patients [
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. 
</p>
