<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lavender is also used in many countries as complementary therapy for painful and inflammatory conditions (
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Djenane et al., 2012</xref>). Several clinical studies have reported that aromatherapy massage or inhalation with lavender produces pain relief in patients with different types of acute pain states, including pediatric pain (
 <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soltani et al., 2013</xref>), dysmenorrhea (
 <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ou et al., 2012</xref>), cesarean postoperative (
 <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Olapour et al., 2013</xref>), labor (
 <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yazdkhasti and Pirak, 2016</xref>), and in inflammatory disorders, such as osteoarthritis (
 <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nasiri et al., 2016</xref>). However, the capability of lavender essential oil to relieve neuropathic pain and its potential mechanisms has never been elucidated. This study aims to investigate the antineuropathic properties of lavender in a mouse model of neuropathic pain. Mood disorders, such as depression and anxiety, are frequently experienced by patients suffering from neuropathic pain (
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Langley et al., 2013</xref>). Epidemiologic studies reported approximately 34% mean prevalence rate for major depressive disorder in neuropathic patients (
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gustorff et al., 2008</xref>) and clinical studies have indicated strong comorbidity between chronic pain and anxiety (
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Scott et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tsang et al., 2008</xref>). The induction of an antidepressant/anxiolytic action, along with an anti-allodynic activity, might improve the overall condition of patients and produce important clinical benefits. The capability of LEO to induce antidepressant/anxiolytic effects at analgesic doses is, thus, here investigated.
</p>
