<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Kaempferol has a wide variety of pharmacological activities including antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, anticancer, cardioprotective, neuroprotective, antidiabetic, anti-osteoporotic, estrogenic/antiestrogenic, anxiolytic, analgesic, and antiallergic activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. In fact, many studies demonstrated the beneficial effects of dietary kaempferol in reducing the risk of chronic diseases by augmenting the body’s antioxidant defense against free radicals, which reinforces body immunity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. Kaempferol with its strong anti-inflammatory, anti-oxidant properties decreased lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced TNF-α and IL-1β expression by increasing the number of activated macrophages and inhibited NF-κB translocation to the nucleus, which blocks the inflammatory cascade pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. Kaempferol was established to have a high antiviral activity on both influenza viruses, H1N1 and H9N2 where kaempferol acts on the virus neuraminidase protein and its specific functional groups [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. Kaempferol is considered as an effective drug in vitro and in vivo for the potential treatment of H9N2 influenza virus-induced inflammation and lung injury. Kaempferol treatment attenuated pulmonary edema, pulmonary capillary permeability, myeloperoxidase (MPO) activity, and the numbers of inflammatory cells. Kaempferol reduced ROS and Malondialdehyde (MDA). In addition, kaempferol also reduced of ROS, MDA, TNF-α, IL-1β and IL-6 production and significantly inhibited the upregulation of toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4), myeloid differentiation factor 88 (MyD88) and phosphorylation of NF-κB and MAPKs pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Moreover, kaempferol showed an antiviral activity against influenza A replication and its spread through modulating cell-autonomous immunity through MAPK signaling pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Kaempferol derivatives such as kaempferol glycosides and acylated kaempferol glucoside showed comparable antiviral activities against the 3a channel protein of SARS coronavirus that may become expressed in the infected cells. Therefore, inhibition of virus production and allowing the infected body to build up or strengthening its own immune system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Likewise, a docking study indicated that kaempferol derivatives effectively reduced the proteolytic activity of Middle East respiratory syndrome‐coronavirus (MERS‐CoV) by its ability to occupy the S1 and S2 sites of MERS‐CoV 3CLpro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Therefore, Kaempferol and its derivatives might be selected as alternatives to fight COVID‐19 infection possibly through targeting coronavirus proteases.
</p>
