<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Recent years, the plant derived essential oil has got increased attention to use as active biomedical agents that can be incorporated into biodegradable active films (
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">López-Meneses et al., 2018a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">López-Meneses et al., 2018b</xref>). The well-known effects of potential biological activities against various infections are received from various aromatic plant and spices in liquid form. Plant essential oils have more phenolic and flavonoid content, which have the excellent anti-oxidant properties. Also, terpenoid content of essential oils has increased anti-oxidant activity (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2020</xref>). Essential oils have excellent anti-oxidant activity with increased biological activity such as antimicrobial, anti-cancer, antiviral and larvicidal. Previously more bioactive compounds with different biological activity such as anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory and wound healing properties were screened from essential oil contents (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Jahed et al., 2017a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Jahed et al., 2017b</xref>). Some of the essential oil compounds have anti-diabetics activity. The purification of essential oils from degradation affected by extreme processing conditions is their encapsulation (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Jahed et al., 2017a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Jahed et al., 2017b</xref>). To increase the essential oil properties, recent studies are concentrated encapsulation methods. Among the various encapsulations, the biopolymers mediated encapsulation was applied more in biomedical research. Among the biopolymer mediated encapsulation, chitosan is a naturally derived biopolymer, which has the ability to decrease the water vapor due to the increased permeability in essential oils (
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Mohammadi et al., 2015</xref>). Chitosan mediated encapsulation of essential oils not only protects the environment, thereby extending the shelf life of the product but also enables a controlled release of active compounds. Nanoencapsulation of essential oil into the chitosan is an emerging route of encapsulation. In this route of encapsulation, the nanomaterial is loaded to envelop or reservoirs where nanomaterial are trapped and released from large surface area. Based on the above facts, the present study was focused on chitosan loaded Guava leaves essential oil against multi drug resistant 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>.
</p>
