<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_BTRE559 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEgr7 jpg ?><?FILEgr8 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 xlsx ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biotechnol Rep (Amst)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biotechnol Rep (Amst)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biotechnology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2215-017X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7733000</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2215-017X(20)30670-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.btre.2020.e00559</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e00559</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of methyl jasmonate and salicylic acid on the production of metabolites in cell suspensions cultures of <italic>Piper cumanense</italic> (Piperaceae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0005"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>Laura Katherine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0010"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Bernal</surname><given-names>Jorge Enrique</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0015"><name><surname>Santamar&#x000ed;a-Torres</surname><given-names>Mary Andrea</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0020"><name><surname>Marqu&#x000ed;nez-Casas</surname><given-names>Xavier</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0025"><name><surname>Cuca-Su&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>Luis Enrique</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0030"><name><surname>Prieto-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>Juliet Ang&#x000e9;lica</given-names></name><email>juliet.prieto@javeriana.edu.co</email><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0035"><name><surname>Pati&#x000f1;o-Ladino</surname><given-names>Oscar Javier</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Research Group &#x02018;Qu&#x000ed;mica de Productos Naturales Vegetales Bioactivos QuiProNaB&#x02019;, Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogot&#x000e1;, 11001, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>&#x02018;Sistem&#x000e1;tica biol&#x000f3;gica &#x02013; SisBio&#x02019;, Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogot&#x000e1;, 11001, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>&#x02018;Grupo de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Fitoqu&#x000ed;mica Universidad Javeriana GIFUJ&#x02019;, Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, Pontificia Universidad Javeriana, Bogot&#x000e1;, 110231, Colombia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>juliet.prieto@javeriana.edu.co</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><elocation-id>e00559</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0005"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="lis0005"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0005">MeJA and SA induced a differential metabolic production in elicited cell suspensions.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0010">Production of metabolites was dependent on the type and the concentration of elicitor.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0015">Elicitation with SA produced the greatest changes in the metabolic profile.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0020">5-hidroximetilfurfural, (Z)-9-octadecenamide and phenol were induced by elicitation.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Elicitation of cell suspensions culture is a strategy that could increase the production of secondary metabolites under controlled conditions. This research evaluated the effect of methyl jasmonate-MeJA and salicylic acid-SA as elicitors on the production of metabolites in cell suspensions of <italic>P. cumanense</italic>. The type of elicitor (MeJA or SA), the concentration of elicitor (10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M and 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M), and time of exposition (3, 12, 24&#x0202f;h) on cell suspension were evaluated. Metabolic profiles of intracellular and extracellular extracts were analyzed by UHPLC-DAD and GC&#x02013;MS. Differential production of metabolites was dependent on the type of elicitor, its concentration, and the time of exposition. Treatments with 100 &#x003bc;M SA were conducted to high production of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural (6.3 %), phenol (6.5 %), and (Z)-9-octadecenamide (8.8 %). This is the first report of elicitation on cell suspensions in the <italic>Piper</italic> genus and contributes to understanding the effect of MeJA and SA on metabolite production in plant cell culture.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Abbreviations</title><kwd>2,4-D, 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic</kwd><kwd>BAP, 6-benzyladenine</kwd><kwd>GC&#x02013;MS, Gaschromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry</kwd><kwd>MeJA, Methyl jasmonato</kwd><kwd>MS, Murashige &#x00026; Skoog medium</kwd><kwd>PCA, Principal Component Analysis</kwd><kwd>PDVF, Polyvinylidene fluoride</kwd><kwd>SA, Salicylic acid</kwd><kwd>SI, Similarity index</kwd><kwd>UHPLC-DAD, Ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography coupled to a diode array detector</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="kwd0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Elicitation</kwd><kwd>Methyl jasmonate</kwd><kwd>Salicylic acid</kwd><kwd><italic>Piper</italic></kwd><kwd>Plant cell culture</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="par0025"><italic>Piper</italic> is the richest genus of the Piperaceae family with around 2000 species, and one of the most diverse lineages of basal angiosperms [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. <italic>Piper</italic> species are characterized by producing a great diversity of metabolites of agricultural, medicinal, and ecological importance, such as alkaloids and amides, propenylphenols, lignans, neolignans, and terpenes, several of them with anticancer, antiparasitic, and antibacterial activity [<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p id="par0030"><italic>Piper cumanense</italic> is a species of the genus. It is distributed in Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, and Venezuela, and produces metabolites of interest, such as, benzoic acid derivates and chromones. The extracts or isolated compounds of this species have antifungal activity, insecticidal activity, and activity against leishmaniasis amastigotes. However, the low yield in the obtention of its compounds has prevented further research at an experimental or commercial level, which has encouraged the evaluation of strategies to increasing the production of its metabolites in controlled, permanent, and sustainable conditions [<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>].</p><p id="par0035">One of the most widely used biotechnological strategies to increase the production of secondary metabolites is the elicitation of cell suspensions [<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Elicitation refers to the induction of metabolite biosynthesis using compounds or environmental conditions that trigger the expression of defense genes that promote the production of secondary metabolites [<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The most commonly used elicitors in this type of strategy are methyl jasmonate (MeJA), which, for example, has increased the production of vindoline, catharantine and ajmalicine in suspensions of <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (Apocynaceae), and salicylic acid (SA), which use has increased taxol production in <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures of <italic>Taxus baccata</italic> (Taxaceae) [<xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p id="par0040">In the genus <italic>Piper</italic>, some biotechnological strategies focus on increasing the production of compounds of interest are in preliminary stages. There are important advances in the establishment of <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures (micropropagation, callogenesis, and cell suspensions) in some species of the genus. Furthermore, the elicitation is seen as an important strategy to increase the production of secondary metabolites of interest [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>].</p><p id="par0045">Due to the potential of the metabolites present in <italic>P. cumanense</italic> and the interest to increase the production of their compounds, the objective of this study was to determine the effect of methyl jasmonate and salicylic acid on the production of metabolites in cell suspensions of <italic>P. cumanense</italic> (Piperaceae).</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Chemicals</title><p id="par0050">Plant growth regulators 6-benzyladenine and 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic and elicitors methyl jasmonate 95 % and salicylic acid were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich Chemicals. Ethyl acetate 96 % and methanol for HPLC&#x0202f;&#x02265;&#x0202f;99.9 % were purchased from Merck.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Callus culture</title><p id="par0055">Petioles of 1&#x0202f;cm length were excised from <italic>in vitro</italic> plants of 45 days after <italic>in vitro</italic> germination and were placed horizontally to MS medium supplemented with the following components at a final concentration of 1&#x0202f;mg/L of thiamine, 100&#x0202f;mg/L of inositol, 30&#x0202f;g/L of sucrose, 7.5&#x0202f;g/L of agar and a combination of 2,4-D (2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic) and BAP (6-benzyladenine). The media were adjusted to pH 5.8 with 0.1&#x0202f;M HCl and 0.1&#x0202f;M NaOH and then autoclaved at 120&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x0202f;min. Every 15 days, callus white and friable obtained, were sub-cultured for its maintenance. Cultures were incubated at 25&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;2&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C in constant light under white-fluorescent light bulbs with an intensity of 4500&#x0202f;lx.</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Plant cell suspensions establishment</title><p id="par0060">Cell suspensions were initiated by transferring 2&#x0202f;g of white and friable callus to 100&#x0202f;mL Erlenmeyer flasks which were cultured for 30 days. These bottles contained 20&#x0202f;mL of MS medium supplemented with the following components at a final concentration of 1&#x0202f;mg/L of thiamine, 100&#x0202f;mg/L of inositol, 30&#x0202f;g/L of sucrose, 1&#x0202f;mg/L of 2,4-D, and 0.5&#x0202f;mg/L of BAP. The liquid medium was adjusted to pH 5.8 with 0.1&#x0202f;M HCl and 0.1&#x0202f;M NaOH and then autoclaved at 120&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x0202f;min. On the 15th day, the medium was changed by removing 10&#x0202f;mL of old medium and then adding 10&#x0202f;mL of fresh MS medium supplemented with the components described before. Cell suspensions were placed in continuous orbital agitation at 110&#x0202f;rpm, under constant white light at 25&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;2&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C [<xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Cell suspensions elicitation</title><p id="par0065">Cell suspensions previously established were homogenized in a flask and aliquots of 10&#x0202f;mL were taken. Each aliquot was added to 100&#x0202f;mL Erlenmeyer flasks contained 10&#x0202f;mL of MS liquid medium, supplemented with the components described in sub section <xref rid="sec0025" ref-type="sec">2.3</xref>. Each suspension had an initial concentration of 90&#x0202f;g of fresh weight per liter (FW/L). On the 15th day, MeJA and SA were added, separately, to the cell suspensions at a final concentration of 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M and 100 &#x003bc;M. Elicitor solutions were prepared in a 1&#x0202f;mL of a 0.25 % ethanol solution and filtered on a 0.22&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m membrane filter. The effect of elicitors was evaluated at 3&#x0202f;h, 12&#x0202f;h, and 24&#x0202f;h after its addition to cell suspensions. Controls were suspensions without elicitors added. At times of evaluation (6&#x0202f;h, 12&#x0202f;h, and 24&#x0202f;h) suspensions were harvested and cells were separated from the medium by vacuum filtration. Cells were stored at &#x02212;80&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C and medium at -20&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C to further metabolites extraction. All experiments were carried out in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Metabolites extraction</title><sec id="sec0040"><label>2.5.1</label><title>Intracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0070">Cells were pulverized in presence of liquid nitrogen and lyophilized at Labconco FreeZone&#x000ae;-2.5&#x0202f;L. From the powder obtained, 150&#x0202f;mg was separated, extracted with 2&#x0202f;mL of ethyl acetate, and ultrasonicated for 10&#x0202f;min. This solution was placed in continuous orbital agitation at 110&#x0202f;rpm for 12&#x0202f;h at 25&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;2&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C. Then, it was centrifuged at 8500&#x0202f;rpm for 8&#x0202f;min, the supernatant was separated, and its solvent was removed by distillation under reduced pressure. This extraction process was repeated three times. The extract obtained was solubilized in 500&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L methanol, for HPLC, using ultrasound. Finally, the resulting solution was filtered on 0.22&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m polyvinylidene fluoride (PDVF) polymer membrane filters of 0.22&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m and stored at &#x02013; 20&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>2.5.2</label><title>Extracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0075">Medium (20&#x0202f;mL) was extracted with 20&#x0202f;mL of ethyl acetate and vortexed for 2&#x0202f;min. The mixture was put in a separatory funnel and the organic phase was separated, dried with anhydrous sodium sulfate, and filtered with a qualitative filter paper grade (11&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m). Then, the solvent was removed by distillation under reduced pressure. This extraction process was repeated three times. The extract obtained was solubilized in 500&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L methanol for HPLC using ultrasound, filtered, and stored as described in section <xref rid="sec0040" ref-type="sec">2.5.1</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0050"><label>2.6</label><title>Analysis of metabolic profiles</title><p id="par0080">Intracellular and extracellular metabolites were tentatively identified and analyzed using UHPLC-DAD and GC&#x02013;MS chromatographic techniques as described below.</p><sec id="sec0055"><label>2.6.1</label><title>UHPLC-DAD analysis</title><p id="par0085">Metabolic profiles of intracellular and extracellular extracts were analyzed by ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography (UHPLC) using the Thermo Fisher Scientific UPLC Ultimate 3000 equipment coupled to a diode array detector (UHPLC-DAD) and a C18 Kinetex column (50&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;2.1&#x0202f;mm d.i; 2.6&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m). Solvents used as mobile phase were methanol (MeOH): water (0.1 % formic acid) with a gradient elution of 60&#x02013;100 % MeOH in 30&#x0202f;min and 100 % MeOH in 10&#x0202f;min and the temperature of the oven was 30&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C. The injection volume was 2&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L with a constant flow of 0.2&#x0202f;mL/min. Chromatograms were recorded at 254&#x0202f;nm and UV spectra were obtained in a range between 200 and 380&#x0202f;nm. The number of peaks, area, and retention time from each sample were analyzed and compared with data (retention time and UV spectra) of peaks from compounds previously isolated and identified by the research group QuiProNaB on the extract of inflorescences and infructescences from wild individuals of <italic>P. cumanense</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><label>2.6.2</label><title>GC&#x02013;MS analysis</title><p id="par0090">Metabolic profiles of intracellular and extracellular extracts were obtained by direct injection without derivatization on a Shimadzu GC 2010 Plus chromatograph coupled to a Shimadzu GCMS-TQ 8040 selective mass detector, equipped with a split/splitless injection port (250&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C, 1:5 Split ratio), a Shimadzu AOC-20i autoinjector and Shimadzu AOC-20&#x0202f;s autosampler. A HP-5MS capillary column with a stationary phase of 5% -phenyl-poly (methylsiloxane), 60&#x0202f;m &#x000d7; 0.25&#x0202f;mm, ID &#x000d7;0.25&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m, df, was used. The carrier gas used was helium, with an inlet pressure at the top of the column of 117.6&#x0202f;kPa, a linear velocity of 25.7 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and a constant flow of 1&#x0202f;mLmin<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The oven temperature was programmed from 50&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C (5&#x0202f;min) - 20&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C&#x0202f;min up to 150&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C (3&#x0202f;min) and finally at 4&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C/min up to 310&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C (5&#x0202f;min). The mass spectra were obtained by electron impact (EI) with an energy of 70&#x0202f;eV. The temperatures of the ionization chamber and transfer line were maintained at 290&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C and 310&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C, respectively. The mass spectra and total ion chromatogram (TIC) were obtained in a quadrupole, by automatic frequency scanning (full scan), in the mass range of m / z 45&#x02013;600.</p><p id="par0095">Peaks obtained were tentatively identified by comparing their mass spectrum with the library of the National Institute of Standards and Technology 14 (NIST, USA). Compounds with a similarity index (SI) &#x02265; 90 % were selected and peaks such as silanes and siloxanes related to column bleeding were excluded.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0065"><label>2.7</label><title>Analysis of metabolite distribution (statistical analysis)</title><p id="par0100">To analyze the effect of elicitors on cell suspensions Venn diagrams were performed with the InteractiVenn program [<xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and multivariate statistical analysis like PCA biplot and heatmap were constructed in RStudio version 1.2.1335 using the prcomp, factoextra, and pheatmap packages [<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The heatmap was clustered by Euclidean distance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0070"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec0075"><label>3.1</label><title>UHPLC-DAD analysis</title><p id="par0105">Cell suspensions (control and treated) are shown in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, there were no appreciable differences in color or viscosity. Intracellular and extracellular extracts from cell suspensions were analyzed by UHPLC-DAD. Chromatograms obtained were compared considering the presence/absence and relative area of selected peaks. Additionally, it was determined if previously isolated and identified compounds from wild <italic>P. cumanense</italic> plants were present in the extracts obtained in this study.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Cell suspensions of <italic>P. cumanense</italic>: <bold>A</bold>. Control. Elicited with <bold>B</bold>. methyl jasmonate (MeJA) and <bold>C</bold>. Salicylic acid (SA).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0140">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><sec id="sec0080"><label>3.1.1</label><title>UHPLC-DAD: intracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0110"><xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> shows the chromatographic profiles of intracellular extracts obtained from suspensions elicited with MeJA and SA. The chromatographic profiles showed that in all the samples analyzed there was a production of metabolites of different polarities. However, most of the compounds eluted in the first 15&#x0202f;min and the largest number of metabolites eluted between minutes 25 and 33. The samples of both controls and treatments had similar chromatographic profiles. The most representative signals were selected and highlighted in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> and their retention times and maximum absorbance were summarized in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Additionally, the table includes the retention times and maximum absorbance of the compounds previously isolated and identified from wild <italic>P. cumanense</italic> individuals. However, those compounds were not detected in the chromatographic profiles either of the control nor the treatments, indicating that the cells in suspensions did not produce this type of compounds under the evaluated <italic>in vitro</italic> culture conditions.<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>UHPLC-DAD chromatographic profiles of intracellular extracts from elicited cell suspensions with SA and MeJA at an exposure time of 6&#x0202f;h, 12&#x0202f;h, and 24&#x0202f;h recorded at 254&#x0202f;nm. At the concentration of elicitor evaluated <bold>A.</bold> 10 &#x003bc;M and, <bold>B.</bold> 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0145">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Retention times and absorption maximums of selected peaks of intracellular profiles, as well as patterns of compounds previously isolated of <italic>P. cumanense</italic> inflorescences and infructescences analyzed by UHLPC-DAD. <bold>RT:</bold> Retention time. <bold>SEM:</bold> Standard error of the mean. Peaks from intracellular profiles were not identified.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0180">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Peak No. / Compound</th><th align="left">RT (min) &#x000b1; SEM</th><th align="left">Absorption maximums (nm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="16">Peaks of intracellular profile</td><td align="left">Peak 1</td><td align="left">0.62&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.00</td><td align="left">200.0<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 258.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 2</td><td align="left">1.32&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">200.9; 273.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 3</td><td align="left">2.39&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.04</td><td align="left">205.0; 239.7; 313.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 4</td><td align="left">13.55&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.03</td><td align="left">279.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 5</td><td align="left">14.38&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.03</td><td align="left">233.3<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 277.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 6</td><td align="left">25.82&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">200.0<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 226.2; 276.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 7</td><td align="left">26.43&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">216.0, 252.9<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 8</td><td align="left">28.04&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">245.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 9</td><td align="left">28.56&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">238.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 10</td><td align="left">28.75&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">251.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 11</td><td align="left">29.35&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">237.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 12</td><td align="left">31.69&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">242.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 13</td><td align="left">31.82&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.01</td><td align="left">242.1<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 321.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 14</td><td align="left">31.97&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.01</td><td align="left">285.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 15</td><td align="left">32.39&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">242.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 16</td><td align="left">32.58&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.02</td><td align="left">241.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="4">Patterns</td><td align="left">Oxocumenic acid</td><td align="left">15.85&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.61</td><td align="left">204.0; 236.0<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 327.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gaudichaudianic acid</td><td align="left">20.50&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.60</td><td align="left">247.0<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 284.0; 367.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cumenic acid</td><td align="left">23.11&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.35</td><td align="left">203.0; 242.0<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 270.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caryophylene oxide</td><td align="left">24.86&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.38</td><td align="left">201.0<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 288.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0005"><label>a</label><p id="npar0005">Corresponds to the maximum absorption in the spectrum.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="par0115">Elicited cells with SA at the two concentrations evaluated tended to increase the area of some peaks: Exposition to 10 &#x003bc;M SA for 24&#x0202f;h increased the area of peak 6 (2.6 times) concerning the control, while 6&#x0202f;h and 12&#x0202f;h exposition increased the intensities of the peaks 7 (7.6 and 11 times, respectively) and 9 (2.5 and 2.7, respectively). Treatments with 100 &#x003bc;M SA and 6&#x0202f;h exposition increased the area of peaks 6 (2.7 times) and 7 (8.7 times), while 24&#x0202f;h exposition only increased the intensity of peak 7 (8.6 times) regarding control.</p><p id="par0120">On the other hand, MeJA treatments also increased the area of some peaks in the chromatographic profiles. Elicitation with 10 &#x003bc;M MeJA and an exposure time of 12&#x0202f;h increased the area of peak 2, 2.9 times compared to the control. Treatments with 100 &#x003bc;M MeJA and 6&#x0202f;h of exposition caused increases in peak 13, in this case, 3 times more than the control. A 24&#x0202f;h exposition of this elicitor (100 &#x003bc;M MeJA) caused an increase in peak 7 (13.7 times), which is higher compared with the observed in SA treatments.</p></sec><sec id="sec0085"><label>3.1.2</label><title>UHPLC-DAD: extracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0125">The chromatographic profiles from media of suspensions are shown in <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>. A peak with a high polarity was detected in 0.62&#x0202f;min which represented around 85 % of the total relative area. However, the greatest number of peaks eluted between 24 and 34&#x0202f;min. As well as the observed in intracellular extracts, the samples of media of both controls and treatments had similar chromatographic profiles. The most representative peaks are highlighted in <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and their retention times and maximum absorbance are listed in <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Likewise, in this table, the data of the compounds previously isolated of <italic>P. cumanense</italic> are presented. However, those compounds were not detected in the profiles of media under the evaluated conditions which indicates cells neither produced those compounds nor expulsed them to media after its contact with the elicitors.<fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>UHPLC-DAD chromatographic profiles of extracellular extracts from cell suspensions elicited with SA and MeJA at an exposure time of 6&#x0202f;h, 12&#x0202f;h, and 24&#x0202f;h recorded at 254&#x0202f;nm. At the concentration of elicitor evaluated: <bold>A-B.</bold> 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M and, <bold>C-D.</bold> 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M. Chromatograms shown in <bold>B.</bold> and <bold>D.</bold> are presented from retention time: 4&#x0202f;min. In media, peak 2 is only observed in treatments with elicitors at a concentration of 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0150">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Retention times and absorption maximums of selected peaks of extracellular profiles, as well as patterns of compounds previously isolated of <italic>P. cumanense</italic> inflorescences and infructescences analyzed by UHLPC-DAD. <bold>RT:</bold> Retention time. <bold>SEM:</bold> Standard error of the mean. Peaks from intracellular profiles were not identified.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0185">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Peak No. / Compuesto</th><th align="left">TR (min) &#x000b1; SEM</th><th align="left">Absorption maximums (nm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="8">Peaks of extracellular profile</td><td align="left">Peak 1</td><td align="left">0.62&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.00</td><td align="left">208.3<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 262.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 2</td><td align="left">0.94&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.00</td><td align="left">202.4<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 205.5<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 235.4; 303.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 3</td><td align="left">25.62&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.01</td><td align="left">200.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 250.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 4</td><td align="left">25.26&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.01</td><td align="left">252.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 5</td><td align="left">25.92&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.01</td><td align="left">200.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 224.5; 281.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 6</td><td align="left">28.66&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.01</td><td align="left">240.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 7</td><td align="left">32.49&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.01</td><td align="left">242.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peak 8</td><td align="left">33.23&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.00</td><td align="left">200.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 212.5; 272</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="4">Patterns</td><td align="left">Oxocumenic acid</td><td align="left">15.85&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.61</td><td align="left">204.0; 236.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 327.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gaudichaudianic acid</td><td align="left">20.50&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.60</td><td align="left">247.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 284.0; 367.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cumenic acid</td><td align="left">23.11&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.35</td><td align="left">203.0; 242.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 270.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caryophylene oxide</td><td align="left">24.86&#x0202f;&#x000b1;&#x0202f;0.38</td><td align="left">201.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>; 288.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0010"><label>a</label><p id="npar0010">Corresponds to the maximum absorption in the spectrum.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="par0130">Some peaks in the profiles from the media of elicited suspensions with SA decreased or increased its area. Treatment with 100 &#x003bc;M SA increased the area of peak 2, while in suspensions elicited with 10 &#x003bc;M SA peak 8 decreased (0.4 times) compared with control. It is highlighted that peak 2 was produced only by suspensions treated with 100 &#x003bc;M SA and exposed to it during 6&#x0202f;h, 12&#x0202f;h, and 24&#x0202f;h.</p><p id="par0135">On the other hand, MeJA treatments reduced the relative areas of some peaks. Elicitation with 100 &#x003bc;M MeJA during 6&#x0202f;h caused a decrease in peak 8 (0.4 times) compared with control. Suspensions exposed to 10&#x003bc;M MeJA caused a decrease in peaks 1 and 8, 0.9, and 0.5 times, respectively. Furthermore, the exposure of the suspensions to 10&#x003bc;M MeJA during 12&#x0202f;h generated the greatest increases in peak areas of extracellular extracts. It was detected increases of 2.5, 3.1, and 2.0 times in peaks 5, 6, and 7, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec0090"><label>3.1.3</label><title>UHPLC-DAD: Comparison between intracellular and extracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0140">Compounds previously isolated and identified from <italic>P. cumanense</italic> wild individuals were found neither in intracellular nor in extracellular extracts from suspensions elicited. This could be because the type of elicitor and times of exposure used in treatments did not induce the production of those compounds, at least not in amounts detectable by the UHPLC-DAD equipment. Furthermore, the production of these secondary metabolites may be associated with the state of differentiation of specific tissues, such as leaves or inflorescences, from which the compounds were isolated in wild plants.</p><p id="par0145">It has been found that the state of cell differentiation is an important factor for the activation of biosynthetic pathways to produce specific secondary metabolites. For example, Langhansov&#x000e1; &#x00026; Mar&#x00161;&#x000ed;k (2005) found that root cultures of <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> led to the production of a greater variety of ginsenosides (saponins) compared to callus or cells <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures. This tissue-dependent production is related to the state of tissue differentiation that could be due to differential expression of genes involved in the biosynthesis of compounds [<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p id="par0150">On the other hand, the absence of compounds previously identified in <italic>P. cumanense</italic> in the cell suspensions could also be due to the absence of endophytes, a term that refers to microorganisms such as bacteria or fungi that are closely associated with tissues of some plants in a symbiotic relationship. It has been found that endophytes produce intermediate molecules that use plants to synthesize some secondary metabolites or even produce them. For example, taxol, an important compound used for cancer treatment, was first isolated from the plant species <italic>Taxus brevifolia</italic>. However, taxol production has been discovered also in a wide variety of fungal species like the endophytic fungi <italic>Pestalotiopsis microspora</italic> and <italic>Stemphylium sedicola</italic> which have been isolated from plant species of the genus <italic>Taxus</italic> and <italic>Taxodium</italic>. Likewise, the compounds azadirachtin A and B, which are widely used as natural insecticides and traditionally isolated from neem tree, <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic>, are also produced by the endophytic fungus <italic>Eupenicillium parvum</italic> isolated from neem tree [<xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>].</p><p id="par0155">Furthermore, the UHPLC-DAD profiles obtained (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) show greater changes in peaks areas in extracts of media compared to extracts of cells. This indicates that under the stress conditions evaluated cells tended to excrete metabolites to medium rather than keep them internally. The expulsion of the metabolites to the medium is desirable in this type of strategy because it favors the extraction procedure and, cells can continue growing in new media. In some species, it has been possible to induce cells to excrete secondary metabolites of interest to medium. For example, cell suspensions of <italic>Vitis labrusca</italic> elicited with methyl jasmonate tended to expulse predominantly trans-resveratrol, pallidol, &#x003b4;-viniferin, and &#x003b5;-viniferin to the medium [<xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0095"><label>3.2</label><title>GC&#x02013;MS analysis</title><p id="par0160">GC&#x02013;MS analysis of intracellular and extracellular extracts led to tentatively identify a total of 121 compounds. These metabolites correspond mostly to primary metabolites, mainly to hydrocarbons and esters. Also, some secondary metabolites such as terpenes, amides, and phenol were detected (see supplementary file).</p><sec id="sec0100"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Analysis of metabolites distribution: PCA of intracellular and extracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0165"><xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> shows the principal component analysis (PCA) of intracellular and extracellular extracts. PCA explains in the first two dimensions 54 % of the variance. Intracellular samples are grouped (orange color) and present a low variance. On the other hand, extracellular samples are grouped separately (aquamarine color) and have greater variance. This could be due to the number of metabolites present and their relative areas. PCA shows that intracellular and extracellular extracts have divergent characteristics.<fig id="fig0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>PCA biplot of the relative areas of the metabolites tentatively identified in intracellular and extracellular extracts from cell suspensions elicited with MeJA and SA.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0155">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="par0170">However, some samples, particularly controls of both types of extracts, are overlapped. This suggests that compounds present in controls are mainly constitutive while compounds in samples, within the groupings, could be produced by the effect of treatments with elicitors.</p></sec><sec id="sec0105"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Analysis of metabolites distribution: venn diagram</title><p id="par0175">Venn diagrams were constructed to determine the distribution of the metabolites present in the intracellular and extracellular extracts (<xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). A greater number of compounds were found in media (87) in comparison with cells (74), which indicates that cells tended to excrete the metabolites (<xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>.A). Some metabolites (40) were present in both types of extracts, which represents about 50 % of the total metabolites present in each type of extract.<fig id="fig0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Venn diagrams with the distribution of metabolites in intracellular and extracellular extracts from cell suspensions elicited with MeJA and SA. <bold>A</bold>. Total metabolites in cells and medium. <bold>B</bold>. Exclusive metabolites of the medium. <bold>C.</bold> Exclusive metabolites of the cells. <bold>D</bold>. Metabolites shared by cells and medium.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0160">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="par0180"><xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>.B shows the distribution of the exclusive metabolites of extracellular extracts (media). Some metabolites were excreted to media when cell suspensions were exposed to the elicitors. Treatments with</p><p id="par0185">MeJA induced the exclusive production of 4 compounds, with SA of 6 compounds, and 10 compounds were produced by both elicitors. Moreover, 12 metabolites were present only in controls and 15 in controls and media of elicited suspensions. This distribution suggests that the elicitors induced the synthesis of compounds that were excreted to the media. Additionally, the presence of some metabolites only in controls indicate that elicitors may be inhibiting the production of some compounds, causing their degradation or transformation into new metabolites [<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p id="par0190"><xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>.C shows the distribution of metabolites present exclusively in intracellular extracts (cells). In this case, MeJA induced the biosynthesis of 8 compounds, SA of 7 compounds, and the number of metabolites induced by both elicitors was lower compared with media extracts (5 <italic>versus</italic> 10 in the media). Furthermore, only 1 metabolite was exclusive of control, and 13 were produced in both, elicited cells, and controls.</p><p id="par0195">Finally, <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>.D shows the distribution of the 40 metabolites shared between intracellular and extracellular extracts. Most of the metabolites were present in both controls and samples of elicited suspensions. Furthermore, only 3 compounds were present in both MeJA and SA treatments, and no compound was exclusive to controls, MeJA, or SA. This indicates that metabolites shared by cells and media were mostly constitutive because they were present in control and treatments with at least one elicitor.</p></sec><sec id="sec0110"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Analysis of metabolites distribution: PCA biplot of intracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0200">PCA's biplot of the intracellular (cells) and extracellular (media) extracts were done to determine the most relevant compounds in each set of data. PCA biplot of cell samples is shown in <xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>. In this diagram, the first two dimensions expressed 64.6 % of the total variability, samples were displayed as points, and the most important variables (compounds) as vectors. The first principal component had the highest variability with 52.3 %, and the variables with the highest weight were dodecane and 2,4-dimethyldodecane. On the other hand, in the second principal component, with 12.3 % of the total variability, campest-4-en-3-one, tetradecane, and eicosanal were the most important variables.<fig id="fig0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>PCA biplot of intracellular extracts. The letters of the sample labels refer to, in order of appearance: <bold>C</bold> to Cell extract. Next letter: <bold>C, M</bold>, or <bold>S</bold> to Control samples (C) or treated with methyl jasmonate (M) or salicylic acid (S). Finally, <bold>1</bold> or <bold>2</bold>: Concentration of 10 or 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M, respectively, and <bold>6&#x0202f;h</bold>, <bold>12&#x0202f;h</bold> or <bold>24&#x0202f;h</bold> to the exposure time.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0165">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p><p id="par0205">Based on the biplot diagram, it was observed that the elicited samples tended to present a higher relative area percentage of dodecane and 2,4-dimethyldodecane, highlighting the samples exposed to 100&#x003bc;M SA. Also, there was an overlap between control and cells exposed to 10 &#x003bc;M SA for 6 and 12&#x0202f;h, which indicates that SA at low concentration and exposure time equal to or less than 12&#x0202f;h does not generate changes in the production of metabolites compared to the control. Moreover, the overlap between samples treated with MeJA and SA may indicate a similar effect of these elicitors at certain concentrations and exposure times.</p></sec><sec id="sec0115"><label>3.2.4</label><title>Analysis of metabolites distribution: PCA biplot of extracellular metabolites</title><p id="par0210">The first two dimensions of the PCA biplot of media samples expressed 60.1 % of the total variability (<xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). The compounds with the highest weight in the second principal component were 5-hydroxymethylfurfural and (Z)-9-octadecenamide, and in the first principal component were the compounds named above and phenol. Elicited suspensions with SA had a high relative area percentage of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural, (Z)-9-octadecenamide and phenol, especially those exposed to 100 &#x003bc;M SA. In contrast, control and mainly of MeJA treatments had a low relative area percentage of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural and phenol.<fig id="fig0035"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>PCA biplot of extracellular extracts. The letters of the sample labels refer to, in order of appearance: <bold>M</bold> to Media extract. Next letter, <bold>C, M</bold> or <bold>S</bold> to Control samples (C) or treated with methyl jasmonate (M) or salicylic acid (S). Finally, <bold>1</bold> or <bold>2</bold>: Concentration of 10 or 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M, respectively, and <bold>6&#x0202f;h, 12&#x0202f;h</bold> or <bold>24&#x0202f;h</bold> to the exposure time.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0170">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="par0215">The results obtained in this study allow us to understand the effect of MeJA and SA on the production of metabolites in <italic>P. cumanense</italic>. However, although species of the genus <italic>Piper</italic> produce compounds with potential for use in industry (<italic>e.g.</italic> agricultural and medicinal), research focused on increasing their production using plant biotechnology tools is scarce. It is highlighted the establishment of cell suspensions of some <italic>Piper</italic> species in which a production of metabolites has been found, such as phenylethylamines dopamine and tyramine (<italic>P. cernuum</italic>), and alkamides (<italic>P. crassinervum</italic>) [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Also, suspensions of <italic>P. solmsianum</italic> have been established finding a greater diversity of metabolites in the medium suggesting that cells excreted those compounds, the same as found in this study in elicited suspensions of <italic>P. cumanese</italic> [<xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, to our knowledge, this study is the first report of elicitation in <italic>Piper</italic> genus cell suspension which can serve as a basis to the understanding of the production of secondary metabolites in <italic>Piper</italic> species.</p></sec><sec id="sec0120"><label>3.2.5</label><title>Analysis of metabolites distribution: Heatmap</title><p id="par0220">A heatmap was constructed to analyze the production of the metabolites concerning the relative percentage area in the different treatments (<xref rid="fig0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). To construct this diagram, the 121 compounds tentatively identified were classified into 14 groups according to the main functional group. Two large groupings defined by the type of sample (cells or medium) were obtained in this diagram. The group of cells had a cluster established mainly by elicited cells, and another cluster composed mainly of controls of cells and media samples. Finally, there was a third, poorly defined grouping composed of media from suspensions exposed to elicitors and characterized by the presence of the highest relative areas of some compounds.<fig id="fig0040"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Heatmap of metabolites present in intracellular and extracellular extracts from cell suspensions elicited with MeJA and SA.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0175">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig></p><p id="par0225">In this diagram, it was observed that the samples were composed mainly of primary metabolites such as hydrocarbons and esters, although secondary metabolites like terpene, phenol, and amide were also detected. Hydrocarbons were characteristic of all samples and formed blocks that defined the groupings in cells and media. For example, in the listing of compounds from dodecane to 2,610-trimethyl-pentadecane (on the right of <xref rid="fig0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>), those metabolites defined the grouping of elicited cell samples. Moreover, dodecane was an important metabolite with a high weight in the biplot of cells (<xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>), the same as seen in this heatmap, in which this compound had a high relative area in elicited cells with SA.</p><p id="par0230">On the other hand, media from elicited suspensions were characterized by having a higher intensity in some metabolites, mainly secondary metabolites. It indicates that elicitors induced the activation of secondary metabolic pathways in cell suspensions, and in this case, cells tended to preferentially excrete these metabolites to media. It is highlighted the compounds 5-hydroxymethylfurfural and phenol which were mainly detected in media from elicited suspension with SA, and (Z)-9-octadecenamide which were present in elicited suspensions with both, MeJA and SA treatments. The production of this amide is interesting because the biosynthesis of this compound has been reported in <italic>Piper</italic> species like <italic>P. boehmeriaefolium</italic>, <italic>P. maclueri</italic>, and <italic>P. guineense</italic> [<xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, the production of (Z)-9-octadecenamide has not been reported yet in <italic>P. cumanense</italic> wild species, but interestingly in this study, the biosynthesis of this compound was induced by MeJA and SA elicitors under <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions. The study of the effect of these and other elicitors in various concentrations and exposure times could contribute to the understanding of the factors that cause the production of metabolites in <italic>P. cumanense</italic> and the implementation of strategies focused on obtaining compounds of interest in larger scales.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec0125"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="par0235">This research represents the first report on cell suspensions elicitation in <italic>Piper</italic> genus. Cell suspensions elicited with MeJA and SA had a differential production of metabolites dependent on the type and concentration of elicitor as well as the time of exposition to the cell suspension. Treatments with SA 10 &#x003bc;M and 100 &#x003bc;M induced the greatest metabolic changes highlighting the production of 5-hidroximetilfurfural, (Z)-9-octadecenamide, and phenol. However, under the elicitation conditions evaluated, the production of any of the secondary metabolites isolated from wild <italic>P. cumanense</italic> species was not achieved. This research can serve as a basis for understanding the effect of abiotic elicitors on <italic>Piper</italic> cell suspensions and on the application of strategies to improve metabolite production in cell suspensions culture.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec0130"><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="par0240">Supplementary material related to GC&#x02013;MS data is provided.</p></sec><sec id="sec0135"><title>Funding</title><p id="par0245">This research was funded by <funding-source id="gs0005"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100002753</institution-id><institution>Universidad Nacional de Colombia</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, <funding-source id="gs0010"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100009543</institution-id><institution>Pontificia Universidad Javeriana</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, and <funding-source id="gs0015">MINCIENCIAS</funding-source> (Ministry of Science, Technology, and Innovation of Colombia), grant No. 110171250886 through the project with contract 380-2016.</p></sec><sec id="sec00005"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="par00005"><bold>Laura Katherine Rodr&#x000ed;guez-S&#x000e1;nchez:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing - original draft. <bold>Jorge Enrique P&#x000e9;rez-Bernal:</bold> Methodology, Software, Validation, Investigation, Data curation. <bold>Mary Andrea Santamar&#x000ed;a-Torres:</bold> Methodology, Formal analysis, Data curation. <bold>Xavier Marqu&#x000ed;nez-Casas:</bold> Validation, Formal analysis, Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Luis Enrique Cuca-Su&#x000e1;rez:</bold> Methodology, Formal analysis. <bold>Juliet Ang&#x000e9;lica Prieto-Rodr&#x000ed;guez:</bold> Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Writing - review &#x00026; editing, Supervision. <bold>Oscar Javier Pati&#x000f1;o-Ladino:</bold> Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Writing - review &#x00026; editing, Supervision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="par0250">The authors report no declarations of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Callejas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Current perspectives on the classification and phylogenetics of the genus <italic>Piper</italic> L.</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Piper</italic> A Model Genus Stud. Phytochem. Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>198</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Plant Systematics. An Integrated Approach</chapter-title><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Science Publishers</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/CBO9781107415324.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title><italic>Piper</italic>: a Model Genus for Studies of Phytochemistry, Ecology, and Evolution</chapter-title><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Kluwer Academic/Plenum Publishers</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13398-014-0173-7.2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mgbeahuruike</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yrj&#x000f6;nen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuorela</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive compounds from medicinal plants: focus on <italic>Piper</italic> species</article-title><source>S. Afr. J. Bot.</source><volume>112</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2017.05.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pati&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>O.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuca</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new benzoic acid derivative isolated from <italic>Piper</italic> cf. <italic>Cumanense</italic> Kunth (Piperaceae)</article-title><source>Phytochem. Lett.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytol.2013.07.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuca</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cumanensic acid, a new chromene isolated from <italic>Piper</italic> cf. <italic>cumanense</italic> Kunth</article-title><source>Piperaceae), Phytochem. Lett.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytol.2011.04.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuca</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Coloma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal and phytotoxic activity of benzoic acid derivatives from inflorescences of <italic>Piper cumanense</italic></article-title><source>Nat. Prod. Res.</source><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786419.2019.1662010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garavito</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arteaga</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourdy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimenez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinz&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deharo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial activity of some Colombian medicinal plants</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>107</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>460</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.03.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuura</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Costa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousefzadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirjalili</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhambra</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strnad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfill</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fett-Neto</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specialized plant metabolism characteristics and impact on target molecule biotechnological production</article-title><source>Mol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>60</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12033-017-0056-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochoa-Villareal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loake</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant cell culture strategies for the production of natural products</article-title><source>BMB Rep.</source><volume>49</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5483/BMBRep.2016.49.3.264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26698871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paek</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of secondary metabolites from cell and organ cultures: strategies and approaches for biomass improvement and metabolite accumulation</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult.</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-014-0467-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of &#x003b2;-cyclodextrin and methyl jasmonate on the production of vindoline, catharanthine, and ajmalicine in <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> cambial meristematic cell cultures</article-title><source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>99</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>7035</fpage><lpage>7045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-015-6651-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25981997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarmadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaz&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghassempour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirjalili</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of salicylic acid and glucose on biochemical traits and taxane production in a <italic>Taxus baccata</italic> callus culture</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><volume>132</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2018.09.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30240989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgado-Paredes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Massuo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojas-Idrogo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular suspension and production of secondary metabolites in <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures of <italic>Piper</italic> sp</article-title><source>Bolet&#x000ed;n Latinoam. y Del Caribe Plantas Med. y Arom&#x000e1;ticas.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>282</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balbuena</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santa-Catarina</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Floh</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> morphogenesis and cell suspension culture establishment in <italic>Piper solmsianum</italic> C. DC</article-title><source>Piperaceae), Acta Bot. Brasilica.</source><volume>23</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-33062009000100029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazal</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Piper nigrum</italic>: micropropagation, antioxidative enzyme activities, and chromatographic fingerprint analysis for quality Control</article-title><source>Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol.</source><volume>169</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>2004</fpage><lpage>2015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12010-013-0104-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23354497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makwana</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>De novo</italic> organogenesis from leaf explants in <italic>Piper longum</italic> L</article-title><source>J. Pharmacogn. Phytochem.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>485</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szabados</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mroginski</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suspensiones celulares: descripci&#x000f3;n, manipulaci&#x000f3;n y aplicaciones, in: cultiv</article-title><source>Tejidos En La Agric. Fundam. y Apl., Centro Int</source><year>1991</year><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heberle</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meirelles</surname><given-names>G.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>F.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Telles</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Minghim</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>InteractiVenn: A Web-based Tool for the Analysis of Sets Through Venn Diagrams</chapter-title><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-015-0611-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>RStudioTeam</surname></name><name><surname>RStudio</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Integrated Development for R. Studio</chapter-title><year>2020</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rstudio.com" id="intr0010">http://www.rstudio.com</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaheer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical elicitors versus secondary metabolite production <italic>in vitro</italic> using plant cell, tissue and organ cultures: recent trends and a sky eye view appraisal</article-title><source>Plant Cell, Tissue Organ Cult.</source><volume>126</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-016-0985-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian-liang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bing</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng-Jian</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu-ping</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plant cell suspension cultures: pharmaceutical applications and high-yielding strategies for the desired secondary metabolites</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Biotechnol.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24963701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamshoeft</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiteller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An endophytic fungus from <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss. That produces azadirachtin</article-title><source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source><volume>28</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1287</fpage><lpage>1294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-011-0876-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22805849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludwig-M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants and endophytes: equal partners in secondary metabolite production</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Lett.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-015-1814-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorentino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant bioactive metabolites and drugs produced by endophytic fungi of spermatophyta</article-title><source>Agriculture</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>918</fpage><lpage>970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agriculture5040918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subban</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Priya</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnpaul</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayabaskaran</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Salicylic acid as an effective elicitor for improved taxol production in endophytic fungus <italic>Pestalotiopsis microspora</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0212736</pub-id><comment>February</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rustamova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozorov</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Efferth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yili</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel secondary metabolites from endophytic fungi: synthesis and biological properties</article-title><source>Phytochem. Rev.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11101-020-09672-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kastell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knorr</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smetanska</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exudation: an expanding technique for continuous production and release of secondary metabolites from plant cell suspension and hairy root cultures</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-011-1165-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21987121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaire</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Auger</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guilleret</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynaud</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cl&#x000e9;ment</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Courot</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taidi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimize, modulate, and scale-up resveratrol and resveratrol dimers bioproduction in<italic>Vitis labrusca</italic> L. cell suspension from flasks to 20 L bioreactor</article-title><source>Plants</source><volume>8</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/plants8120567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narayani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elicitation: a stimulation of stress in <italic>in vitro</italic> plant cell/tissue cultures for enhancement of secondary metabolite production</article-title><source>Phytochem. Rev.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1227</fpage><lpage>1252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11101-017-9534-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danelutte</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantin</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Braz-Filho</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergence of secondary metabolism in cell suspension cultures and differentiated plants of Piper cernuum and P. Crassinervium</article-title><source>J. Braz. Chem. Soc.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1425</fpage><lpage>1430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-50532005000800022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0160"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hieu</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thang</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoi</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogunwande</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of essential oils from four vietnamese species of <italic>Piper</italic> (Piperaceae)</article-title><source>J. Oleo Sci.</source><volume>63</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5650/jos.ess13175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24712088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kpomah</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Monday</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kpomah</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GCMS analysis of leaves and seeds of <italic>Piper guineense</italic> shumach &#x00026; thoon</article-title><source>African Sci.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>138</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0145" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="par0265">The following is Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="upi0005"><media xlink:href="mmc1.xlsx"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="par0255">Professor Eddy Herrera from Pontificia Universidad Javeriana for her help in multivariate analysis of GC&#x02013;MS results. Biologist Sebastian S&#x000e1;nchez for his help on graphing in RStudio. Ph.D Jorge Parra for giving the patterns of the compounds isolated from wild <italic>P. cumanense</italic> individuals.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="sec0140" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="par0260">Supplementary material related to this article can be found, in the online version, at doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.btre.2020.e00559" id="intr0005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.btre.2020.e00559</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>