<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">The mountains in the western part of High Atlas and northern slopes of the western Anti-Atlas, which are exposed to Atlantic influences are characterized by the presence of the thuya (
 <italic>Tetraclinis articulata</italic> (Vahl) Masters the holm oak 
 <italic>Q. ilex</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>rotundifolia</italic>, the Juniper (
 <italic>J. phoenicea</italic>) and the development of lavender matorrals (
 <italic>Lavandula dentata</italic> L. and 
 <italic>Lavandula pedunculata</italic> (Miller) Cav.), 
 <italic>Cistus</italic> (
 <italic>C. creticus</italic> L. and 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>salviifolius</italic> L.) broom (
 <italic>Genista tricuspidata</italic> Desf.) and Cytise (
 <italic>Teline segonnei</italic> (Maire) C. Raynaud endemic to Kerdous and Ifni massif. The thuya formations grow in the N and NW exposures of the High western Atlas from 600 m altitude in the Ida Ou Tanane massif, the regions of Tamanar, Ait Daoud, and Jbel Amsittene (Fennane 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">1988</xref>). Depending on ecological conditions, the main trees associated to the thuya are 
 <italic>A. spinosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Ceratonia siliqua</italic> L., and 
 <italic>Q. ilex</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>rotundifolia</italic>. In the Western Anti-Atlas, in the Lakhsass massif, the thuya tree associated to argan tree and 
 <italic>E. officinarum</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>echinus</italic> constitute the southernmost association of thuya in Morocco (Fennane 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">1988</xref>). Ecologically, it is the most xerophilic association of thuya in Morocco which is located in an arid bioclimate with 250 to 300 mm precipitation per year. Although higher in altitude, the holm oak (
 <italic>Q. ilex</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>rotundifolia</italic>) appears and participates in several plants associations. In the Western Anti Atlas (Jbels Bou Timezguida 1250 m, Bou Krat 1217 m, Touwala 1222 m in Ifni Massif, Lkest 2374 m, Ighchene 2041, Mkorn 2340 m in Kerdous Massif) relinked sites of holm oak, which constitute the most southern holm oak formations of Morocco are found (Peltier 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">1982</xref>; Msanda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2002</xref>). These massifs are well known by their plant biodiversity and endemism (Mathez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1973</xref>; Peltier 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">1982</xref>; El Aboudi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1987</xref>).
</p>
