<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella</italic> spp. are Gram-negative rod shaped bacteria that cause bacterial pneumonia with a high fatality rate if infection remains untreated in the clinical setting [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Globally, the vast majority of 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella</italic> infections are hospital-acquired. Nosocomial 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella</italic> infections are mainly caused by 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, the medically most important species of the genus which primarily attacks immune-compromised individuals who are hospitalized and suffer from severe underlying diseases such as diabetes mellitus, chronic pulmonary obstruction or even cancer. It is estimated that 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella</italic> spp. cause 8% of all nosocomial bacterial infections in the United States and Europe, with 50.1% of these cases being caused by 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> placing 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella</italic> spp. among the eight most important infectious pathogens in hospitals [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. In 1983, the first report of a plasmid-mediated extended spectrum beta-lactamases (
 <italic class="italic">ESBLs</italic>) capable of hydrolyzing extended-spectrum cephalosporins was discovered [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Carbapenems are one of the last lines of antibiotic treatment for severe drug-resistant bacterial infections, and are now the treatment of choice for serious infections caused by pathogens carrying the 
 <italic class="italic">ESBL</italic> gene. This has led to an increased reliance on carbapenems in clinical practice [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. In tandem with this, the first carbapenemase producing 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pneumoniae</italic> isolate was reported in North Carolina in 2001. This enzyme was termed 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pneumoniae</italic> carbapenemase (KPC) and conferred resistance to carbapenem antibiotics [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. KPCs are encoded by the gene 
 <italic class="italic">bla</italic>KPC, whose potential for inter-species and geographic dissemination is largely explained by its location within a Tn3-type transposon, Tn4401 that is capable of inserting itself into diverse plasmids of Gram-negative bacteria. Although 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pneumoniae</italic> remains the most prevalent bacterial species carrying KPCs, the enzyme has been identified in several other Gram-negative bacilli such as 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella enterica</italic> due to horizontal gene transfer [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. To worsen this issue, KPC-producing 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pneumoniae</italic> (KPC-KP) possesses innate antibiotic resistance in the form of an efflux pump, which generally removes the antibiotics that have penetrated the bacterial membrane, from the cytoplasm into the extracellular environment. Membrane permeability can also be altered in the presence of antibiotics; preventing the access of antibiotics into the cells, which when coupled to the other mechanisms, enables resistance against higher concentrations of antibiotics [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>].
</p>
