<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In order to address to this particular issue, there had been constant efforts to discover novel antimicrobials for clinical use. Natural products such as essential oil consisting a plethora of chemical compounds, are becoming a popular mainstream platform for researchers in drug discovery [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Numerous studies have also demonstrated the efficacy of essential oils from curry plant (
 <italic class="italic">Helichrysum italicum</italic> (Roth) G. Don fil.), peppermint (
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> x 
 <italic class="italic">piperita</italic> L.), tea tree (
 <italic class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia</italic> (Maiden &amp; Betche) Cheel.) and marjoram (
 <italic class="italic">Origanum majorana</italic> L.) as promising antimicrobials. Multiple studies have shown the synergistic effects between various essential oils and antibiotics, potentially solving the antibiotic resistance issue in the clinical setting [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Despite this, only a few studies have been carried out to elucidate the mode of action of several essential oils on different bacteria; most of these studies have postulated that essential oils exert their antimicrobial activities by disrupting bacterial cell membrane and/or their efflux systems through various assays [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. For example, de Souza et al. (2009) postulated that 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> L. essential oil affects the membrane permeability of 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> by studying potassium ion efflux and scanning electron microscopy [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Similarly, Silva et al. (2011) hypothesized that coriander essential oil exerts its bactericidal activity towards both Gram-positive and Gram–negative bacteria via membrane damage by measuring their efflux activity, respiratory activity and membrane potential [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. To further support and understand the antimicrobial activity of essential oils, mass spectrometry-based proteomics analysis has become the tool of choice offering the identification and quantification of the proteome of an organism. There has been a tremendous improvement in instrument performance and the computational tools used in proteomic studies in recent years, which facilitates the understanding of the mechanisms of action of potential antimicrobial agents in the clinical setting. In the most widely used “bottom-up” approach to proteomics, liquid chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS), enables a complex mixture of proteins to be first subjected to enzymatic cleavage; the resulting peptide products are separated based on chemical or physical properties and analyzed using a mass spectrometer. The proteome can then be analyzed, quantified and compared by using third party analytical software such as Progenesis QI (Progenesis Group Sdn. Bhd.) or Perseus (Max Planck Institute of Biochemistry). For instance, Xu et al. (2015) identified the mode of action of paclitaxel as chemotherapeutic drugs in HeLa cells by tampering with the abundance of tumor suppressor PDCD4 via LC-MS/MS proteomic profiling [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Similarly, Kawatani et al. (2016) also revealed the role of collismycin A as an iron chelator antagonizing cancer cells, using a proteomic approach [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>].
</p>
