<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In our previous study, we have successfully shown that cinnamon bark (
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomon verum</italic> J. Presl) essential oil (CBO) is, in fact, an effective antimicrobial when used against KPC-KP with an extremely low minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 0.16% (v/v) [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Furthermore, combinations of CBO and antibiotic meropenem further reduced the MIC of CBO to 0.08% (v/v) which makes it a putative candidate to be used as an antimicrobial in the clinical setting [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Other studies showed that CBO with a low MIC value is effective against a variety of Gram-positive and Gram–negative pathogens. Zamirah and colleagues (2013) demonstrated that CBO is effective against oral pathogens such as 
 <italic class="italic">Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Fusobacterium nucleatum</italic>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porphyromonas_gingivalis" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">Porphyromonas gingivalis</italic>
 </ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Streptococcus_salivarius" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">Streptococcus salivarius</italic>
 </ext-link>, 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">mitis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">mutans</italic> with a low MIC ranging from 0.02 to 0.06% (v/v) [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Kaskatepe et al (2016) also showed that CBO is highly effective against other opportunistic pathogens, including 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and multidrug-resistant 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA), with a MIC ranging from 0.009% to 0.078% (v/v) [
 <xref rid="pone.0214326.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. As already mentioned above, preliminary studies had postulated that essential oils affect bacterial membrane and/or their efflux system via numerous assays. Nevertheless, none had explained or gave an overview on the overall changes that the bacterial cells undergo when exposed to essential oils, especially in the perspective of proteomics. Thus, this study was carried out to understand and possibly bridge the missing links among previous studies regarding the mode of action of essential oils as an antimicrobial agent from the proteomic perspective, using CBO and KPC-KP as a model of study.
</p>
