<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The secretory cells of lateral and median nectaries of 
 <italic>B. orientalis</italic> share several typical features with the nectary glands of other plant species, i.e. small size, large nuclei, small vacuoles and dense, intensely staining cytoplasm with several organelles including numerous mitochondria and ribosomes. In the secretory stage, the glandular parenchyma of both lateral and median glands contained several plastids, and in each plastid zero, one, or two starch grains were detected. Our results, strong chlorophyll autofluorescence on examination under UV light, indicate that the nectariferous tissue of 
 <italic>B. orientalis</italic> can be directly involved in production of nectar carbohydrates via a photosynthesis process. According to Lüttge (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2013</xref>), in sun-adapted green nectaries, photosynthesis can make a quantitatively significant contribution to the production of nectar sugar. The arrangement of floral parts in 
 <italic>B. orientalis</italic> makes its nectaries only partly accessible to sunlight, and thus, their possible photosynthetic activity cannot explain the total sugar secreted in nectar. The presence of photosynthetic cells as components of floral nectaries has been described for several species (Pacini and Nepi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2007</xref>), and this phenomenon is chiefly associated with lowering the cost of reproduction and further fruit development. However, in the nectary parenchyma with chlorophyll, small quantities of starch are produced directly by photosynthesis and are stored for only few hours (Pacini et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2003</xref>). Recent quantitative studies have shown that starch accumulation plays only a minor role in nectar production (Ren et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2007</xref>; Nepi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2011</xref>), and this is a characteristic of floral nectaries with a short period of secretory activity (Paiva and Machado 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2008</xref>). The scarcity of starch in combination with small quantities of secreted nectar per flower indicates that floral nectaries of 
 <italic>B. orientalis</italic> depend also on products of photosynthesis by other plant organs. Indeed, transport of nectar carbohydrates from other floral or vegetative parts has been demonstrated in a number of plant species (see Pacini and Nepi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2007</xref>). In lateral nectaries of 
 <italic>B. orientalis</italic>, nectar carbohydrates are probably uploaded from phloem elements situated at the nectary base then transported to the secretory cells and stored temporarily as starch in plastids. Carbohydrates for nectar synthesis may also originate from vascular bundles associated with the closely located sepal bundles which may be evidenced by the presence of starch in the secretory parenchyma of median nectaries and is congruent with the observations of other species (e.g. Davis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1986</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>; Ren et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2007</xref>; Konarska 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2011</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2015</xref>). However, the role of starch in nectar formation cannot be completely excluded for the species studied, as partly hydrolyzed starch grains have been observed in the plastids of secretory parenchyma cells.
</p>
