<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The nonsignificant difference in alkaloid and tannin contents observed in the water extracts of the wild and cultivated plants might be due to the polarity of solvent used; hence, the significant difference observed in acetone and methanol extracts of wild and cultivated plants may depend on the ability of the solvents to extract some key constituents. (Umpathy et al. [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]). The variation in phytochemical as shown in 
 <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, thus, confirmed that variation between wild and cultivated plants may be due to the influence of agronomic parameters such as shading or sunlight exposure and water supply which had impact on chemical composition. The findings of this study were in line with Ahmed et al. [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] in which bioactive compounds from herbal medicine may be affected by physiological response (circadian rhythm and phenology) of plants and agronomic conditions. It has also been reported that growing conditions, such as warm weather, increase the synthesis of secondary metabolites but wet weather conditions can inhibit alkaloid production in many species [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Alkaloids have been used medically as analgesic and antiseptic [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The presence of alkaloid in both wild and cultivated 
 <italic>A. amatymbica</italic> shows that the plant could be a potential source of antispasmodic, antimalarial, antiseptic, and antibacterial agents [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. This could explain the use of 
 <italic>A. amatymbica</italic> by traditional healers for the treatment of the above ailments. The presence of tannins in wild and cultivated 
 <italic>A. amatymbica</italic> makes the plant a good source of tannin and could be useful for the prevention of cancer as well as treatment of inflamed ulcerated tissue. It can also act as a natural antibiotic by preventing lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
