<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30" class="p">The final biosynthetic products from the non-mevalonate pathway of isoprenoid biosynthesis, geranyl pyrophosphate and farnesyl pyrophosphate, are precursors to linear mono-, di- and sesquiterpenes, called prenyl groups, which are frequently isolated as natural products with some additional modifications. The monoterpene alcohol linalool (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>), present in hundreds of plant species, exists as a mixture of two enantiomers to which numerous biological activities have been ascribed, including significant toxicity against transformed cells (cf. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>]). Linalool, presumably the racemate, has recently been put forward as a chemical starting point for anthelmintic drug development, along with other natural products [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">73</xref>]. The compounds in this study were selected from phytochemical databases and filtered chemoinformatically for favourable ADME and drug-like properties. Compounds were further screened computationally for binding to a modelled structure of glutathione S-transferase (GST) from the filarial worm 
 <italic class="italic">Brugia malayi</italic>, and the best hits were biochemically tested at 1 µg/ml against a crude GST preparation from the heartworm 
 <italic class="italic">Dirofilaria immitis</italic> (due to a lack of access to 
 <italic class="italic">B. malayi</italic>). Linalool inhibited DiGST by 98% at 1 µg/ml (~ 6.5 µM) in this assay, and it was thereby assumed to possess anthelmintic efficacy, although this was not directly tested, a problem when interpreting the results. Linalool is sensitive to an extensive metabolism that generates multiple derivatives with biological activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>] and its purported biological target in nematodes and insects, GST, is usually present as a family of multiple isoenzymes in metazoans; the 
 <italic class="italic">H.</italic> 
 <italic class="italic">contortus</italic> genome, for example, has at least 8 distinct genes encoding GST isozymes (ParaSite@WormBase; release 11) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">74</xref>]. Presently, it is unknown whether any of these enzymes is singularly essential and thus represents a good anthelmintic target, or how many functionally redundant isozymes can be simultaneously inhibited to a sufficient extent by a single compound. These are some of the biological and chemical questions that need to be addressed ahead of a drug development effort with these compounds. 
</p>
