<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While cinnamon and mustard EOs were effective to inhibit 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7, 
 <italic>Pseudomanas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic>, 
 <italic>Pectobacterium carotovorum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>enterica</italic> individually, their synergistic action was only found on 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 and 
 <italic>Pseudomanas putida</italic>. The highest antimicrobial activity was observed on mustard EO [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In a study performed by our research group, while cardamom, cumin, and dill weed EOs were effective inhibitors individually against 
 <italic>Campylobacter</italic> spp. [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], their mixtures showed the highest antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Campylobacter</italic> spp. and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Similarly, the antibacterial activities of cinnamon and clove EO were tested not only individually but also in combination. Clove EO was more effective than cinnamon EO to inhibit microorganisms, which might be a result of its higher eugenol concentration (53.9%). Their combination showed better antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomanas aeruginosa</italic>, and 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> compared to their individual applications [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. However, in another study, cinnamon EO had higher antibacterial activity than clove EO against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomanas aeruginosa</italic>, and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The different results obtained might be due to the differences in the composition of EOs. Lavandula species are well-known for their wide variety of biological activities. Although it is commonly used in the cosmetic industry, depending on the linalool, 1,8-cineole, and camphor content, the antibacterial activity of 
 <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> EO is also noteworthy. This significant antibacterial activity was proved against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pseudomanas aeruginosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Moreover, the EO from 
 <italic>Lavandula mairei</italic> Humbert that was predominated by carvacrol had different levels of antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Listeria innocua</italic>, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Proteus vulgaris</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pseudomanas aeruginosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Peppermint (
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L.) EO, which was mainly characterized by menthol and menthone, showed significant levels of antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Micrococcus flavus</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella enteritidis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Furthermore, peppermint EO was active against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
