<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">In addition, variations in soil nutrient properties (e.g. available carbon, total nitrogen, available potassium) commonly cause shifts in soil microbial communities with short-term fertilisation treatments
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. Fertilisation may be a contributing factor favouring a more active, copiotrophic microbial community, thus shifting the predominant microbial life history strategies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>. Soil organic matter is a critical index of soil fertility due to its capacity to affect plant growth indirectly or directly
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. Organic fertiliser is a source of organic components
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>, promoting the growth of microbes in soil. Dynamics of soil organic carbon and total nitrogen storage in soils determine microbial activity and nutrient cycles, improves soil physical properties, promotes water retention capacity, and decreases erosion
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. A great number of genes involved in the function of carbon metabolism were enriched in the associated microbial communities. Proteobacteria, which is known to play critical role in the global cycles of carbon, nitrogen, iron, and sulphur
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>, was the most abundant group in soil. Actinobacteria were overrepresented with fertiliser treatments in this study. Actinobacteria are believed to contribute to the global carbon cycle by breaking down plant biomass
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>, and due to their ability to decompose organic matter in soils
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup>, they are capable of producing cellulases, hemicellulases, chitinases, glucanases, and amylases
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
