<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Maize weevil (
 <italic class="italic">Sitophilus zeamais</italic> Motsch.) has a nearly cosmopolitan distribution. Occurring throughout the warmer parts of the world, it is one of the most destructive primary insect pests of stored cereals [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. It is an internal feeder, and infestations of this weevil not only cause significant losses due to the consumption of grains, they also result in elevated temperature and moisture conditions that lead to an accelerated growth of molds, including toxigenic species [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Booklice (
 <italic class="italic">Liposcelis bostrychophila</italic> Badonnel) have also a worldwide distribution, infesting domestic premises, raw material stores, manufacturing factories, and historical documents in museums [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Currently, psocids are perhaps the most important emerging pests in stored grains and related commodities, due to their small size and resistance to chemicals [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Control of the stored product insects is currently mainly based on the application of synthetic insecticides/fumigants [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. However, these insecticides and fumigants are often associated with residues that are dangerous for the consumer and the environment. In addition, repeated use of those fumigants/insecticides for decades has led to resurgence of stored-product insect pests, sometimes resulting in the development of resistance [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. These problems have pushed researchers to find alternative insecticides. In recent years, global research has focused on the possible use of plant secondary metabolites, especially essential oils, for the protection of stored agricultural products. Essential oils and their major constituents, often monoterpenoids, are among the best known substances to have attracted research attention in recent years as potential alternatives to classical fumigants. Investigations in several countries confirm that some plant essential oils not only repel insects, but also possess contact and fumigant toxicity against stored product pests, as well as exhibiting feeding inhibition or harmful effects on the reproductive system of insects [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
