<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">During our mass screening program for new agrochemicals from Chinese medicinal herbs and wild plants, the essential oil of the aerial parts at a flowering stage of 
 <italic class="italic">Stachys riederi</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">japonica</italic> (Miq.) H. Hara (syn. 
 <italic class="italic">Stachys japonica</italic> Miq.) were found to possess strong insecticidal activity against maize weevils and booklice. The genus 
 <italic class="italic">Stachys</italic> is considered as one of the largest genera of the family Lamiaceae, with nearly worldwide distribution [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. It comprises about 300 species of annual or perennial herbs and shrubs, and 18 species were found in China [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Chinese woundwort (
 <italic class="italic">S. riederi</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">japonica)</italic> is a perennial, rhizomatous herb distributed only in some areas of China (e.g., Anhui, Fujian, Hebei, Henan, Jiangsu, Jiangxi, Liaoning, Inner Mongol, Shandong, and Zhejiang province), and Russia and Japan. It is distributed in wet areas of ravines and riverbanks, and was used in Chinese traditional medicine for tonsillitis, sore throats, and dysentery [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In Korea, this plant has also been used for centuries as traditional medicine to treat homorrhage, coughs, and skin diseases [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Chinese woundwort contains caffeic acid, 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-methoxybaicalein, palustrine, and palustinoside [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. In the previous studies, several phenylethanoid glycosides and oleanane-type triterpene saponins were isolated and identified from this plant [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-01200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. However, a literature survey showed that there are no reports on the volatile constituents and insecticidal activity of 
 <italic class="italic">S. riederi</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">Japonica</italic> aerial parts. Thus, we decided to investigate insecticidal activities of the essential oil against two grain storage insects. Also, this paper deals with the isolation and structure determination of bioactive constituents from the essential oil, as well as their insecticidal activities.
</p>
