<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An important consequence of a biologically realistic, mixed lipid bilayer is the tendency for these systems to demonstrate phase separation. In the 1990s, membrane fragments were identified 10–200 nm in size, rich in cholesterol and sphingolipids as well as membrane proteins (
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Simons and Ikonen, 1997</xref>). These fragments were called “rafts,” proposed to be self-assembled domains that were important in regulating membrane signaling and function. Because of the challenges in imaging such small structures at the time, the study of rafts has been under ongoing debate. Yet, there is substantial evidence that mixed lipid systems exhibit immiscible liquid phase separation and critical point behavior (
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Veatch et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Honerkamp-Smith et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sezgin et al., 2017</xref>). Furthermore, it is apparent that receptors and membrane lipids may cluster and aggregate together and that this may affect physiological signaling. Therefore, mixed membranes offer a way of regulating membrane physiology beyond the activity of each individual protein, and this can be modulated by changes in lipid synthesis or metabolism (
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Siliakus et al., 2017</xref>). As we learn that lipids have a significant and intimate relationship with membrane proteins, it becomes clear that we require a quantitative understanding of how membrane proteins physically behave in more complex membrane systems. This requires multiple pathways of research studying membrane protein structure and function in membranes, the physical properties of these complex lipid bilayers by methods such as small angle x-ray or neutron scattering, and superresolution microscopy imaging. Although complicated, there is an enormous amount of information to learn that is sure to have an effect on the complexities of cell membrane physiology.
</p>
