<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">Interesting data were observed on the variation of the total phenol content under water stress conditions and at increasing concentrations of ABA. Total phenolic content increased under drought conditions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>). Exposure to some environmental stress, such as drought often increases the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) (Sánchez-Rodríguez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2011</xref>). ROS can produce antioxidants and secondary metabolism such as phenolic compounds which play an important role in the detoxification of ROS (Ksouri et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2007</xref>). Shikimate is the main phenolic compounds biosynthesis pathway (Parida et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2004</xref>) and phenylalanine ammonium lyase (PAL, EC 4.3.1.5) is a key enzyme. Some data reports that the PAL activity increases in drought conditions by increasing the plant phenolic compounds (Keleş and Öncel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2002</xref>; Oh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2009</xref>). Moreover, exogenous ABA can induce an increase in the biosynthesis of flavonoids and carotenoids in conditions of water stress (Gai et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2020</xref>). Indeed, phenolic content improved with increasing in ABA concentration in well-watered and severe drought conditions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>). In addition, ABA increased total phenolic content up to 20 µM concentration in moderate drought (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>). Shen et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2016</xref>) reported that ABA could improve the expressions of PAL and tyrosine aminotransferase (TAT) genes that are key enzymes in the phenolic biosynthesis pathway. From these data, it can be assumed that the increase in phenolic compounds can be induced up to certain levels of water stress in 
 <italic>D. moldavica</italic>. Indeed, severe drought decreases the production of these secondary metabolites in both years. Doses higher than 20 µM of exogenous ABA are no longer efficient in increasing phenolic compounds in conditions of moderate drought in 
 <italic>D. moldavica</italic>. We can hypothesize that to counteract plant stress, exogenous ABA induces an enzymatic mechanism for the synthesis of new phenolic compounds which is regulated by the increase in ABA levels. When the exogenous ABA exceeds the concentration of 20 µM it has an inhibitory effect (negative feedback) on the action of the enzyme (or even on the expression of the enzyme itself).
</p>
