<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Food Sci Nutr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2048-7177</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">FSN3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2048-7177</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7684585</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1924</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">FSN31924</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
<italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> L. flower extract inhibits cell growth and metastatic properties in human colon and lung cancer cell lines</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">SEO et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="fsn31924-cr-0001" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Jina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31924-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31924-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Jungjae</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31924-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31924-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Hyi Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31924-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="fsn31924-cr-0004" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Jihyeung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="fsn31924-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>jujihg@gmail.com</email><email>jujih@chungbuk.ac.kr</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="fsn31924-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Food and Nutrition</named-content>
<institution>Chungbuk National University</institution>
<city>Cheongju</city>
<country country="KR">Korea</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Jihyeung Ju, Department of Food and Nutrition, Chungbuk National University, 1 Chungdae&#x02010;ro, Seowon&#x02010;gu, Cheongju 362&#x02010;763, Korea.<break/>
Emails: <email>jujihg@gmail.com</email>; <email>jujih@chungbuk.ac.kr</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.v8.11</issue-id><fpage>6259</fpage><lpage>6268</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright">&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors. Food Science & Nutrition published by Wiley Periodicals LLC.<copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors. <italic>Food Science &#x00026; Nutrition</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals LLC</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:FSN3-8-6259.pdf"/><abstract id="fsn31924-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>Snapdragon <bold>(</bold>
<italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> L.) flowers are one of the most frequently used edible flowers in different preparations of foods and drinks. In this study, we examined inhibitory effects of snapdragon flower extract (SFE) against distinctive properties of cancer cells, stimulated growth, and activated metastasis, using H1299 lung cancer and HCT116 colon cancer cell lines. SFE treatment at 100&#x02013;1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 24&#x02013;72&#x000a0;hr resulted in a time&#x02010; and dose&#x02010;dependent growth inhibition in H1299 and HCT116 cells. Cell cycle analysis and Annexin V staining assay further revealed that SFE caused cell cycle arrest at G2/M phase and induction of apoptosis, indicating the growth inhibition by SFE is attributed to its G2/M cell cycle&#x02010;arresting and apoptosis&#x02010;inducing activities. SFE dose&#x02010;dependently enhanced generation of intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) and reduced mitochondrial membrane potential in H1299 cells but had no effect on intracellular ROS levels in HCT116 cells, suggesting that the type of apoptosis induced by SFE in H1299 cells is different to that in HCT116 cells. Furthermore, SFE alleviated invasion, levels of matrix metalloproteinases, migration, and adhesion in H1299 and HCT116 cells. These results indicate that SFE not only inhibits cell growth by cell cycle arrest at G2/M and apoptosis induction but also alleviates metastatic properties such as invasion, migration, and adhesion in lung and colon cancer cells.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="fsn31924-abs-0002"><p>Snapdragon flower extract not only inhibits cell growth by cell cycle arrest at G2/M phase and induction of apoptosis but also alleviates metastatic properties such as invasion, migration, and adhesion in human lung and colon cancer cells.
<boxed-text position="anchor" content-type="graphic" id="fsn31924-blkfxd-0001" orientation="portrait"><graphic xlink:href="FSN3-8-6259-g006.jpg" position="anchor" id="nlm-graphic-1" orientation="portrait"/></boxed-text>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="fsn31924-kwd-0001">adhesion</kwd><kwd id="fsn31924-kwd-0002">cancer</kwd><kwd id="fsn31924-kwd-0003">growth</kwd><kwd id="fsn31924-kwd-0004">invasion</kwd><kwd id="fsn31924-kwd-0005">migration</kwd><kwd id="fsn31924-kwd-0006">snapdragon flower</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Research Foundation of Korea </institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/501100003725</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>NRF&#x02010;2015R1D1A1A01059139</award-id></award-group><award-group id="funding-0002"><funding-source>the Research Year of Chungbuk National University</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="5557"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>November 2020</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:5.9.4 mode:remove_FC converted:24.11.2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-1001">
<string-name>
<surname>Seo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ju</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>
<italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> L. flower extract inhibits cell growth and metastatic properties in human colon and lung cancer cell lines</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Sci. Nutr.</source>
<year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>6259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6268</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1924</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body id="fsn31924-body-0001"><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Cancer is a major disease burden around the world. Among cancers at different organ sites, lung cancer is the most prevalent and leading cause of death in most countries, while colorectal cancer ranks second in both incidence and mortality in more developed countries (Siegel et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Carcinogenesis is a multi&#x02010;stage process of cancer development, whereby normal cells evolve progressively to a tumorigenic and ultimately malignant state. Sustaining stimulated growth and activating metastasis are the most distinctive properties that cancer cells must acquire during the multi&#x02010;stage carcinogenesis (Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Stimulated growth is the fundamental characteristics of cancer cells, which is achieved by dysregulated cell cycle and resisted programmed cell death, called apoptosis. Metastasis, the major cause of treatment failure and the death of cancer patients, is the ultimate step of the multi&#x02010;stage carcinogenesis where secondary tumors are formed at the sites distant from the site of primary lesion (Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Siegel et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).</p><p>Diet has been recognized as a major determinant in the cancer etiology (Grosso et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The most consistent finding on diet and cancer is an association between adequate consumption of plant&#x02010;based foods, such as fruits, vegetables, and whole grains, and reduced risk of several cancers, including cancers of digestive and respiratory tracts (Grosso et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The benefits from consuming plant&#x02010;based foods have been attributed to different phytochemicals (Johnson,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). However, evidence that an isolated compound can entirely explain the cancer&#x02010;preventive activity of a particular plant&#x02010;based food has been insufficient (Liu,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). Therefore, it would be still important to investigate anticancer activities of plant&#x02010;based foods as a mixture containing a large number of different classes of phytochemicals.</p><p>Snapdragon <bold>(</bold>
<italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic> L.) belongs to the family Plantaginaceae and is native to northern Africa and southern Europe (Al&#x02010;Snafi,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). The flowers and leaves of snapdragon have been used as traditional herbal medicine for treating several symptoms and diseases, including watery eyes, gum scurvy, hemorrhoids, ulcers, liver disorder, and tumors (Al&#x02010;Snafi,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). The flowers, particularly, are among the most popular edible flowers and frequently introduced in different preparations of foods and drinks, such as salad, desserts, soups, teas, and liquors, for decorative and flavor&#x02010;enhancing purposes (Rop et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Despite rich uses of the flower in medicinal and food products, only a small number of studies have reported its antioxidant, antimicrobial, hemolytic, and wound&#x02010;healing activities (Al&#x02010;Snafi,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Saqallah et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>); information on other biological activities remains limited.</p><p>In the current study, we investigated the potential inhibitory effects of snapdragon flower extract (SFE) against stimulated growth and activated metastasis using two human cancer cell lines representing highly proliferative and metastatic properties (Li, Huang, et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Wang et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>), H1299 nonsmall cell lung carcinoma cells and HCT116 colorectal carcinoma cells. The results presented herein will be helpful to provide basic knowledge on the cancer&#x02010;inhibitory activities of SFE and scientific evidence for further development and application of functional food and medicinal products using SFE.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials-and-methods" id="fsn31924-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec sec-type="materials" id="fsn31924-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Materials</title><p>RPMI and Macoy's 5A media were purchased from Gibco. Fetal bovine serum (FBS) was purchased from Thermo Scientific. Streptomycin and penicillin were purchased from Welgene Inc. Sodium carbonate, Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu's reagent, gallic acid, diethylene glycol, sodium hydroxide, quercetin, (+)&#x02010;catechin, dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), <italic>N</italic>&#x02010;acetylcysteine (NAC), 3&#x02010;[4,5&#x02010;dimethylthiazol&#x02010;2&#x02010;yl]&#x02010;2,5&#x02010;diphenyl tetrazolium bromide (MTT), RNase, propidium iodide (PI), 2&#x02032;,7&#x02032;&#x02010;dichlorofluorescein diacetate (DCFH&#x02010;DA), 3,3&#x02032;&#x02010;dihexyloxacarbocyanine iodide (DiOC<sub>6</sub>), Matrigel, crystal violet, sodium dodecyl sulfate, and gelatin were purchased from Sigma&#x02010;Aldrich (St. Louis). Multi&#x02010;well plates were purchased from Corning Inc. All other chemicals and solvents (LC grade) were purchased from Fisher Scientifics.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Snapdragon flower extract</title><p>Snapdragon flowers were purchased from a local farm (Seoul, Korea), sorted by colors (red and yellow), and washed. Freeze&#x02010;dried (PH1316, IshinBioBase, Yangju, Korea) red and yellow flowers were separately ground into powder and extracted with 80% ethanol (40&#x02010;fold volume) for 6&#x000a0;hr at room temperature. After centrifugation at 1,500&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> for 5&#x000a0;min (A320101, Gyrozen), the solvent was evaporated using a speed vacuum concentrator without additional heating applied (NB&#x02010;503CIR, N&#x02010;bioteck). The remaining dried extract of red and yellow flowers (RSFE and YSFE, respectively) was weighed to calculate the extraction yield and stored in deep freezer for further use.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Phytochemical compositions</title><p>The total polyphenol content was determined using Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu method (Margraf et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Briefly, SFE reconstituted in ethanol (4&#x000a0;mg/ml), 8% sodium carbonate, distilled water, and Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu's reagent were mixed in a ratio of 6:20:10:3 (v/v) and then incubated for 30&#x000a0;min at room temperature. The resulting absorbance was read at the wavelength of 650&#x000a0;nm using a microplate reader (Bio&#x02010;Rad Laboratories). Total polyphenol content was calculated as mg gallic acid equivalent (GAE) per g of dried extract.</p><p>The total flavonoid content was determined according to previous report (Csepregi et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) with minor modification. Briefly, SFE reconstituted in ethanol (4&#x000a0;mg/ml), diethylene glycol, and 1&#x000a0;N sodium hydroxide were mixed in a ratio of 3:10:5 (v/v) and then incubated for 1&#x000a0;hr at room temperature. The resulting absorbance was read at the wavelength of 415&#x000a0;nm using a microplate reader (Bio&#x02010;Rad Laboratories). Total flavonoid content was calculated as mg quercetin equivalent (QE) per g of dried extract.</p><p>Proanthocyanidin content was determined according to previous report (Aastrup,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1985</xref>) with minor modification. Briefly, SE reconstituted in ethanol (4&#x000a0;mg/ml), 2% vanillin, and 8&#x000a0;N HCL was mixed in a 1:1:1 ratio (v/v). After incubation for 20&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000b0;C, the absorbance was read at the wavelength of 495&#x000a0;nm in a microplate reader (Bio&#x02010;Rad Laboratories). Proanthocyanidin content was calculated as mg (+)&#x02010;catechin equivalent (CE) per g of dried extract.</p><p>Carotenoid content was determined according to previous report (Scolnik et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">1980</xref>). SFE was dissolved in DMSO, and the absorbance was read at 470&#x000a0;nm (<italic>A</italic>
<sub>470</sub>), 647&#x000a0;nm (<italic>A</italic>
<sub>647</sub>), and 663&#x000a0;nm (<italic>A</italic>
<sub>663</sub>). Total carotenoid content was calculated by the equation of (1,000<italic>A</italic>
<sub>470</sub>&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;333.4837<italic>A</italic>
<sub>663</sub>&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;1,343.057<italic>A</italic>
<sub>647</sub>)&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;1.136 and shown as mg per g of dried extract.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Cell culture and general scheme of treatment</title><p>H1299 human lung cancer cells and HCT116 human colon cancer cells (Korean Cell Line Bank, Seoul, Korea) were cultured in RPMI and Macoy's 5A media, respectively, at 37&#x000b0;C with 95% humidity and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Each medium was premixed with 10% FBS, 0.1&#x000a0;mg/ml streptomycin, and 100&#x000a0;units/ml penicillin. DMSO was used as a vehicle to deliver SFE, and its final concentration was less than 0.2% (v/v) in all experiments. Serum&#x02010;free media were used to treat SFE unless indicated otherwise.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Cell viability</title><p>H1299 and HCT116 cells were seeded in 96&#x02010;well plates at a density of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>4</sup> cells/well. After overnight incubation, cells were treated with SFE at 0, 100, 500, and 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 72&#x000a0;hr. In another experiment, H1299 cells were pretreated with 2&#x000a0;mM NAC for 2&#x000a0;hr and then cotreated with 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml SFE and 2&#x000a0;mM NAC for 72&#x000a0;hr. After aspiration of medium, cells were washed with PBS twice and then incubated with MTT at 0.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 4&#x000a0;hr. The formazan dye formed by viable cells was solubilized by DMSO, and the absorbance was monitored at 540&#x000a0;nm using a microplate reader (Bio&#x02010;Rad Laboratories).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Cell cycle</title><p>H1299 and HCT116 cells at a density of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well were starved for 24&#x000a0;hr in serum&#x02010;free media and then treated with SFE at 500 &#x000b5;g/ml (for H1299) or 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml (for HCT116) in serum&#x02010;complete media for 72&#x000a0;hr. Cells were trypsinized, washed with PBS, and fixed with 70% of methanol. Cells were incubated with 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml RNase and 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml PI for 30&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000b0;C. For each determination, 10,000 cells were counted, and cells at different phases such as sub&#x02010;G1, G1/G0, S, and G2/M were analyzed using flow cytometer (BD Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0009"><label>2.7</label><title>Apoptosis</title><p>Apoptotic cells were quantified by Annexin V/PI double staining assay using apoptotic detection kit (BioVision). H1299 cells were seeded in 6&#x02010;well plates at a density of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. After overnight incubation, cells were treated with SFE at 0 or 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml in serum&#x02010;complete media for 72&#x000a0;hr. Cells were then gently detached by brief trypsinization, washed, and stained with annexin V&#x02010;FITC and PI for 10&#x000a0;min in the dark. The stained cells were analyzed using flow cytometer (FACS Calibur&#x02010;S System, BD Biosciences). Annexin V&#x02010;positive/PI&#x02010;negative cells and annexin V&#x02010;positive/PI&#x02010;positive cells were identified as early and late apoptotic cells, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0010"><label>2.8</label><title>Intracellular reactive oxygen species</title><p>H1299 and HCT116 cells were seeded in 96&#x02010;well black plates at a density of 3&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. After overnight incubation, cells were treated with SFE at 0, 100, 500, and 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 72&#x000a0;hr. In another experiment, H1299 cells were pretreated with 2&#x000a0;mM NAC for 2&#x000a0;hr and then treated with 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml SFE in the presence of NAC for 72&#x000a0;hr. After aspiration of medium, cells were incubated with 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M DCFH&#x02010;DA in the dark for 30&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000b0;C. Intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) oxidize DCFH&#x02010;DA to 2&#x02032;,7&#x02032;&#x02010;dichlorofluorescin (DCF), which was monitored at the excitation and emission wavelength of 485&#x000a0;nm and 528&#x000a0;nm, respectively, using a fluorescence microplate reader (FLx800, Biotek Instrument).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0011"><label>2.9</label><title>Mitochondrial membrane potential</title><p>H1299 cells were seeded in 6&#x02010;well plates at a density of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. After overnight incubation, cells were treated with SFE at 0, 100, 500, and 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 72&#x000a0;hr. After aspiration of medium, cells were then incubated with 100&#x000a0;nM DiOC<sub>6</sub>, a dye selective for the mitochondria of live cells, in the dark for 30&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000b0;C. Relative fluorescence intensity was measured using a flow cytometer (BD Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0012"><label>2.10</label><title>Cell invasion and migration</title><p>Invasion and migration assays were performed using a transwell insert with 8&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m pore size (Sigma&#x02010;Aldrich). H1299 and HCT116 cells (1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well) containing SFE at 0&#x02013;500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml in serum&#x02010;free media were loaded on the insert. For the invasion assay, the insert was precoated with Matrigel (20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/well) to simulate a human basement membrane. After 24&#x000a0;hr, invasive or migratory cells moving through the insert toward the outer well containing serum&#x02010;complete media were fixed with methanol for 10&#x000a0;min and stained with 0.1% crystal violet for 30&#x000a0;min. After gentle wash, the dye was dissolved by adding 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate and quantified spectrophotometrically using a plate reader (Bio&#x02010;Rad Laboratories) at the wavelength of 540&#x000a0;nm.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0013"><label>2.11</label><title>Matrix metalloproteinases</title><p>H1299 cells were seeded in 24&#x02010;well plates at a density of 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells/well. After overnight incubation, cells were treated with SFE at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 24&#x000a0;hr. The media were collected and analyzed for matrix metalloproteinases&#x02010;2, &#x02010;7, &#x02010;9, and &#x02010;10 levels using enzyme&#x02010;linked immunosorbent assay kits (Koma Biotech Inc.) following the manufacturer's instruction.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0014"><label>2.12</label><title>Cell adhesion</title><p>H1299 and HCT116 cells were suspended at a density of 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>4</sup> cells/well in serum&#x02010;complete media containing SFE at 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml and plated into 96&#x02010;well plates precoated with 0.5% gelatin. After 2&#x000a0;hr, 0.5&#x000a0;mg/ml of MTT in the fresh media was added to cells adherent to gelatin. Gelatin is a hydrolyzed collagen and frequently used for mimicking major component of extracellular matrix (Plant et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Further analysis was performed as described for the determination of cell viability.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0015"><label>2.13</label><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>All data were presented as the mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SEM</italic> of at least triplicates. Two&#x02010;tailed Student <italic>t</italic> test was used for comparing two groups. One&#x02010;way ANOVA followed by Duncan test was used for comparing more than two groups. Regression analysis was used for determining time&#x02010; and dose&#x02010;dependent response. Significance was reached at <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0016"><label>3</label><title>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</title><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0017"><label>3.1</label><title>Phytochemical contents of SFE</title><p>A recent study has reported that the snapdragon flowers are rich in diverse phytochemicals (Gonzalez&#x02010;Barrio et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). To confirm the richness of phytochemicals, we first determined the content of major classes of phytochemicals, such as polyphenols, flavonoids, proanthocyanidins, and carotenoids, in SFE used in our study. Polyphenols, secondary metabolites widely distributed in higher plants, are a large class of compounds containing multiples of phenol units. Flavonoids, belonging to polyphenols, are characterized by two phenyl and one heterocyclic ring structure. Proanthocyanidins are an oligomeric flavonoid. Carotenoids are a class of naturally occurring pigments and structurally characterized by the presence of tetraterpenoids containing 8 isoprenes. These classes of phytochemicals are ubiquitously found in plants, and their wide range of health benefits, including cancer&#x02010;inhibitory activities, have been extensively studied (Krzyzanowska et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).</p><p>Total polyphenol and flavonoid contents of RSFE were 15.4&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;GAE/g and 43.2&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;QE/g, resp<bold>e</bold>ctively, which were similar to those of YSFE, 12.8&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;GAE/g and 48.1&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;QE equivalent/g, resp<bold>e</bold>ctively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The total polyphenol content of SFE found in our study was similar to those of snapdragon flowers reported previously (10&#x02013;28&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;GAE/g) (Gonzalez&#x02010;Barrio et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) and within the range of other edible flowers (Kaisoon et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Li et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Song et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The total flavonoid contents found in our study were much higher than those of snapdragon flowers reported previously (1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;CE/g) (Gonzalez&#x02010;Barrio et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) but within the range of other edible flowers (11&#x02013;68&#x000a0;mg rutin equivalent/g) (Kaisoon et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The differences in the contents are likely due to different botanical origins, extraction protocols, and other experimental conditions used for different studies. RSFE contained significantly higher proanthocyanidin levels (312.6&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;CE/g) but lower total carotenoid levels (8.6&#x000a0;mg/g) than YSFE (182.3&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;CE/g and 243.6&#x000a0;mg/g, respectively). These results were consistent with previous reports showing that the flowers with distinct colors, especially red, purple, or blue, contain high amounts of anthocyanidins, while the flowers with pale colors, like yellow or white, contain low amounts of anthocyanidins but high amount of carotenoids (Garzon et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Vukics et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Our results indicated the richness of phytochemicals in SFE, which allowed us to further evaluate its potential cancer&#x02010;inhibitory activities.</p><table-wrap id="fsn31924-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" content-type="TABLE" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Phytochemical content of SFE</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phytochemicals</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSFE</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YSFE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extraction yield (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total polyphenols (mg gallic acid equivalent/g dried extract)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fsn31924-note-0002">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total flavonoids (mg quercetin equivalent/g dried extract)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proanthocyanidins (mg catechin equivalent/g dried extract)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">312.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;13.6*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;30.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotenoids (mg/g dried extract)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot id="fsn31924-ntgp-0001"><title>Note</title><fn id="fsn31924-note-0001"><p>Asterisks mean difference between RSFE and YSFE (*<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.001).</p></fn><fn id="fsn31924-note-0002"><label><sup>&#x02020;</sup></label><p>Mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;<italic>SEM</italic> of &#x02265;3 determinations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0018"><label>3.2</label><title>SFE inhibited the growth of human lung and colon cancer cells</title><p>Stimulated growth is the most essential trait of cancer cells (Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). To determine the growth&#x02010;inhibitory activities of SFE in human lung and colon cells, cell viability assay was performed. As shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, the treatment with SFE at 100, 500, and 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 24&#x02013;72&#x000a0;hr inhibited the growth of H1299 and HCT116 cells in a time&#x02010; and dose&#x02010;dependent manner (<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;0.9, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.001). Particularly at the 72&#x000a0;hr time point, SFE at all concentrations, even at the lowest concentration (100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml), exhibited significant growth&#x02010;inhibitory effects in both H1299 (with estimated IC<sub>50</sub> values of 800&#x02013;820&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) and HCT116 cells (with estimated IC<sub>50</sub> values of 260&#x02013;305&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml).</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31924-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>SFE suppressed the growth of H1299 human lung cancer cells and HCT116 human colon cancer cells. H1299 (a) and HCT116 cells (b) were treated with SFE (0&#x02013;1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) for 24&#x000a0;hr, 48&#x000a0;hr, and 72&#x000a0;hr, and viable cells were shown as % of control. Different letters (a&#x02010;g) indicate significance (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="FSN3-8-6259-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0019"><label>3.3</label><title>SFE induced cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in human lung and colon cancer cells</title><p>Uncontrolled cell cycle progression is a cardinal feature of cancer cells (Evan &#x00026; Vousden,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Apoptosis is a vital process for normal cell turnover. Defective apoptosis represents a major causative factor in the development and progression of cancer. Impediment of cell cycle progression and induction of apoptosis in cancer cells, therefore, are recognized as an effective preventive and therapeutic approach against cancers (Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Pan &#x00026; Ho,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). To examine possible alteration in cell cycle distribution and induction of apoptosis by SFE, cell cycle analysis was performed. SFE significantly elevated the percentage of cell population at G2/M phase to 1.8&#x02010;fold to 1.9&#x02010;fold of the control H1299 cells (at 500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) and to 1.6&#x02010;fold to 1.8&#x02010;fold of the control HCT116 cells (at 1,000&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2a,b</xref>), indicating G2/M arrest&#x02010;inducing activities of SFE. SFE also significantly elevated the percentage of cell population at sub&#x02010;G1 phase to 2.2&#x02010;fold of the control H1299 cells (at 500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) and to 1.6&#x02010;fold to 2.1&#x02010;fold of the control HCT116 cells (at 1,000&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2a,b</xref>). Since the cells at sub&#x02010;G1 phase are apoptotic (Evan &#x00026; Vousden,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>), these results indicate apoptosis&#x02010;inducing activities of SFE. To confirm the induction of apoptosis by SFE, Annexin V/propidium iodine double staining assay was performed using H1299 cells. SFE at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml increased the percentage of both early and late apoptotic cells to 3.7&#x02010;fold to 5.5&#x02010;fold and 1.6&#x02010;fold to 1.8&#x02010;fold of the control cells, respectively, resulting in increased percentage of total apoptotic cells to 2.3&#x02010;fold to 3.3&#x02010;fold of the control (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Since dysregulated cell cycle and evaded apoptosis are important contributors to the stimulated growth of cancers (Evan &#x00026; Vousden,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), our results suggest that the growth&#x02010;inhibitory activities of SFE found in this study (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) are attributed to the cell cycle arrest at G2/M and induction of apoptosis.</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31924-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>SFE induced G2/M cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in H1299 and HCT116 cells. H1299 (a) and HCT116 cells (b) were treated with SFE (500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml and 1,000&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml, respectively) for 72&#x000a0;hr, and the cells at G2/M (M2) and sub&#x02010;G1 (M4) phases (%) were counted by flow cytometry. Additionally, H1299 cells were treated with SFE (500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/ml) for 72&#x000a0;hr, stained with Annexin V&#x02010;FITC and PI, and analyzed by flow cytometry (c). Total apoptotic cells were calculated by summing early (Annexin V+/PI&#x02212;) and late apoptotic cells (Annexin V+/PI+). Different letters (a&#x02010;c) indicate significance (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="FSN3-8-6259-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0020"><label>3.4</label><title>SFE enhanced intracellular ROS generation and reduced mitochondrial membrane potential in human lung cancer cells</title><p>Cells induce apoptosis by sensing different stress stimuli, including ROS. Mitochondria play an integral role in generating endogenous ROS by incomplete metabolism of consumed oxygen and electron leakage. Mitochondrial ROS induces sequential events, including collapse of mitochondrial membrane potential, and further activates intrinsic apoptotic signaling (Lowe &#x00026; Lin,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). Increased production of intracellular ROS and disruption of mitochondrial membrane integrity, therefore, are regarded as early events in mitochondrial intrinsic apoptosis (Marchi et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Redza&#x02010;Dutordoir &#x00026; Averill&#x02010;Bates,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). To determine whether SFE&#x02010;treated cells were subjected to intracellular ROS&#x02010;mediated mitochondrial intrinsic apoptosis, intracellular ROS levels, and mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP) were measured. The treatment of H1299 cells with SFE at 100, 500, and 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml for 72&#x000a0;hr resulted in increased intracellular ROS levels and decreased MMP in a dose&#x02010;dependent manner (<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;0.9, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.001, Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3a,c</xref>). The increases in intracellular ROS level, however, were not found in HCT116 cells at 72&#x000a0;hr time point (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>) and other earlier time points (24&#x000a0;hr and 48&#x000a0;hr; data not shown). These results suggest that the type of apoptosis induced by SFE in H1299 cells is different to that in HCT116; the SFE&#x02010;induced apoptosis in H1299 cells is mitochondria&#x02010;mediated intrinsic while the SFE&#x02010;induced apoptosis in HCT116 cells is not mediated by intracellular ROS.</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31924-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>SFE enhanced intracellular ROS generation and reduced MMP in H1299 cells. H1299 (a, c) and HCT116 cells (b) were treated with SFE (0&#x02013;1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) for 72&#x000a0;hr, and intracellular ROS levels (a, b) and MMP (c) were present as % of control. H1299 cells were pretreated with NAC (2&#x000a0;mM) and then treated with SFE (500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) in the presence of NAC for another 72&#x000a0;hr. Intracellular ROS levels (d) and cell viability (e) were present as % of control. Different letters (a&#x02010;e) indicate significance (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="FSN3-8-6259-g003"/></fig><p>To further investigate the role of SFE&#x02010;induced intracellular ROS in the inhibition of H1299 cell growth, cells were treated with SFE at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml in the presence of NAC, a cell&#x02010;permeable ROS scavenger. NAC completely prevented the SFE&#x02010;induced elevation of intracellular ROS and inhibition of cell growth (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3d,e</xref>). These results suggest that SFE&#x02010;induced intracellular ROS is responsible for the SFE&#x02010;induced inhibition of H1299 cell growth. Cancer cells are not capable of adapting to oxidative stress due to decreased capacity for ROS metabolism, and therefore, pro&#x02010;oxidants exacerbating oxidative stress in cancer cells often exert cytotoxic effects or enhance the efficacy of chemotherapeutic agents (Schumacker,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Many phytochemicals have been shown to exhibit both antioxidant and pro&#x02010;oxidant activities. The mode of action may depend on the extent of oxidative stress, the concentrations of compounds, and the types of cancers (Chikara et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Further studies are needed to verify whether such pro&#x02010;oxidant effects of SFE found in H1299 cells are still responsible for the growth&#x02010;inhibitory effects of SFE against lung carcinogenesis in vivo.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0021"><label>3.5</label><title>SFE inhibited invasion in human lung and colon cancer cells</title><p>Invasion is a process of cells grown in the primary tumor penetrating into surrounding stroma, which is a critical step of cancer metastasis (Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Matrix metalloproteinases, a family of zinc&#x02010;dependent endoproteases degrading various proteins in the extracellular matrix, act as major contributors in the invasion and further malignant progression during metastasis (Conlon &#x00026; Murray,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Treatment with SFE significantly inhibited invasion of H1299 (to 45%&#x02013;47% of the control, at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) and HCT116 cells (to 30%&#x02013;68% of the control, at 100&#x02013;500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) in a Matrigel&#x02010;coated transwell assay (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4a,b</xref>). Concomitantly, SFE decreased levels of matrix metalloproteinase&#x02010;2, &#x02010;7, &#x02010;9, and &#x02010;10 in H1299 cells (to 74%&#x02013;90% of the control, at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml, Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). Matrix metalloproteinase&#x02010;2 and &#x02212;9 are categorized into gelatinases which major substrate are gelatin and type IV collagen. Matrix metalloproteinase&#x02010;7 is a membrane&#x02010;type matrilysin degrading fibronectin, laminin, type VI collagen, and gelatin. Matrix melloproteinase&#x02010;10 is a stromelysin with a broad range of substrates (Conlon &#x00026; Murray,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Our results indicate that SFE possesses inhibitory activities against invasion, and such activities appear to be associated with suppressed levels different matrix metalloproteinases.</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31924-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>SFE inhibited invasion in H1299 and HCT116 cells. H1299 (a, c) and HCT116 (b) cells were treated with SFE (0&#x02013;500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) for 24&#x000a0;hr. Invasive cells (a, b) and matrix metalloproteinases&#x02010;2, 7, 9, and 10 levels (c) were shown as % of control. Different letters (a&#x02010;d) indicate significance (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="FSN3-8-6259-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0022"><label>3.6</label><title>SFE alleviated migration and adhesion of human lung and colon cancer cells</title><p>Migration of cancer cells through extracellular matrix to reach blood or lymph vessels and alteration in adhesion of cell&#x02010;extracellular matrix are inevitable events during cancer metastasis (Hanahan &#x00026; Weinberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). In both H1299 and HCT116 cells, SFE substantially alleviated migration (to 45%&#x02013;68% of the control, at 100&#x02013;500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) and adhesion to gelatin (to 37%&#x02013;63% of the control, at 1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). YSFE is slightly more effective than RSFE in inhibiting migration consistently in both H1299 and HCT116 cells (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5a,b</xref>). Since lutein, a major carotenoid found in Snapdragon flowers (Gonzalez&#x02010;Barrio et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), is presumably present in the extract used in our study (Craft &#x00026; Soares,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>) and has been reported to inhibit migration of breast cancer cells ( Li, Zhang, et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), the greater activities of YSFE than HSFE may be ascribed to lutein contained in YSFE; further study is needed.</p><fig fig-type="FIGURE" xml:lang="en" id="fsn31924-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIGURE 5</label><caption><p>SFE alleviated migration and adhesion in H1299 and HCT116 cells. H1299 (a) and HCT116 cells (b) were treated with SFE (0&#x02013;500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) for 24&#x000a0;hr, and migratory cells were quantified as % of control. H1299 (c) and HCT116 cells (d) suspended in media containing SFE (1,000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) were plated into gelatin&#x02010;coated 96&#x02010;well plate, and after 2&#x000a0;hr, adherent cells were quantified as % of control. Different letters (a&#x02010;d) indicate significance (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="FSN3-8-6259-g005"/></fig><p>The inhibitory activities of SFE against invasion (at 24&#x000a0;hr time point, Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), migration (at 24&#x000a0;hr time point, Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5a,b</xref>), and adhesion (at 2&#x000a0;hr time point, Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5c,d</xref>) were observed at noncytotoxic conditions where significant changes in cell viability were not found in SFE&#x02010;treated cells (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Therefore, these activities are likely independent of the growth&#x02010;inhibitory activity of SFE. Our results (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="fsn31924-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) collectively suggest the antimetastatic activities of SFE against lung and colon cancer cells.</p><p>To the extent of our knowledge, this is the first study demonstrating inhibitory effects of SFE against cell growth and metastatic properties of human cancer cells. Further studies are warranted to standardize SFE and then verify whether such effects are demonstrated in laboratory animals and finally humans. Since a recent study has reported that snapdragon flowers are rich in different bioactive phytochemicals, including flavonol glycosides and anthocyanin (Gonzalez&#x02010;Barrio et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="fsn31924-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), it needs to be clarified whether the inhibitory activities of SFE observed in the present study are ascribed to an isolated single constituent or more than one constituents in combination. Detailed molecular mechanisms of the inhibitory action of SFE against lung and colon cancers also remain to be elucidated.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="fsn31924-sec-0023"><label>4</label><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>SFE effectively not only inhibits cell growth by cell cycle arrest at G2/M phase and induction of apoptosis but also alleviates metastatic properties such as invasion, migration, and adhesion in lung and colon cancer cells. These results will be helpful for understanding health benefits of SFE and developing relevant medicinal and functional food products.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="fsn31924-sec-0025"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests.</p></sec><sec id="fsn31924-sec-0026"><title>ETHICAL APPROVAL</title><p>This study does not involve any human or animal studies.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="fsn31924-sec-0024"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>This work was funded by the Research Year of Chungbuk National University in 2017 and National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF&#x02010;2015R1D1A1A01059139).</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="fsn31924-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Aastrup</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1985</year>). <article-title>A test for presence or absence of proanthocyanidins in barley and malt</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Carlsberg Research Communications</source>, <volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>37</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02910536</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Al&#x02010;Snafi</surname>, <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>The pharmacological importance of <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic>&#x02010;a review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Asian Journal of Pharmaceutical Science and Technology</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Chikara</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nagaprashantha</surname>, <given-names>L. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Singhal</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Horne</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Awasthi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Singhal</surname>, <given-names>S. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Oxidative stress and dietary phytochemicals: Role in cancer chemoprevention and treatment</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Cancer Letters</source>, <volume>413</volume>, <fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2017.11.002</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29113871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Conlon</surname>, <given-names>G. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Murray</surname>, <given-names>G. I.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Recent advances in understanding the roles of matrix metalloproteinases in tumour invasion and metastasis</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">The Journal of Pathology</source>, <volume>247</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>640</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.5225</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30582157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Craft</surname>, <given-names>N. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Soares</surname>, <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Relative solubility, stability, and absorptivity of lutein and beta&#x02010;carotene in organic solvents</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Agriculture and Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>40</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>434</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00015a013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Csepregi</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kocsis</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hideg</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>On the spectrophotometric determination of total phenolic and flavonoid contents</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Acta Biologica Hungarica</source>, <volume>64</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>500</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>509</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/ABiol.64.2013.4.10</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24275595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Evan</surname>, <given-names>G. I.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Vousden</surname>, <given-names>K. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Proliferation, cell cycle and apoptosis in cancer</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Nature</source>, <volume>411</volume>(<issue>6835</issue>), <fpage>342</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35077213</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11357141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Garzon</surname>, <given-names>G. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Manns</surname>, <given-names>D. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Riedl</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Schwartz</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Padilla&#x02010;Zakour</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Identification of phenolic compounds in petals of nasturtium flowers (<italic>Tropaeolum majus</italic>) by high&#x02010;performance liquid chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry and determination of oxygen radical absorbance capacity (ORAC)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Agriculture and Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>63</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1803</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1811</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf503366c</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Gonzalez&#x02010;Barrio</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Periago</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Luna&#x02010;Recio</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Garcia&#x02010;Alonso</surname>, <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Navarro&#x02010;Gonzalez</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Chemical composition of the edible flowers, pansy (<italic>Viola wittrockiana</italic>) and snapdragon (<italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic>) as new sources of bioactive compounds</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>252</volume>, <fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>380</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.01.102</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29478556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Grosso</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bella</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Godos</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sciacca</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Del Rio</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ray</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Galvano</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Giovannucci</surname>, <given-names>E. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Possible role of diet in cancer: Systematic review and multiple meta&#x02010;analyses of dietary patterns, lifestyle factors, and cancer risk</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Nutrition Reviews</source>, <volume>75</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>419</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nutrit/nux012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28969358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Hanahan</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Weinberg</surname>, <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Hallmarks of cancer: The next generation</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Cell</source>, <volume>144</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>646</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>674</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.02.013</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21376230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Johnson</surname>, <given-names>I. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Phytochemicals and cancer</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">The Proceedings of the Nutrition Society</source>, <volume>66</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0029665107005459</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17466103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Kaisoon</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Siriamornpun</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weerapreeyakul</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Meeso</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Phenolic compounds and antioxidant activities of edible flowers from Thailand</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Functional Foods</source>, <volume>3</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2011.03.002</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Krzyzanowska</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Czubacka</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Oleszek</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Dietary phytochemicals and human health</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Advances in Experimental Medicine and Biology</source>, <volume>698</volume>, <fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4419-7347-4_7</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21520705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>A. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>H. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xu</surname>, <given-names>D. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xu</surname>, <given-names>X. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Total phenolic contents and antioxidant capacities of 51 edible and wild flowers</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Functional Foods</source>, <volume>6</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>330</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jff.2013.10.022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Lutein inhibits proliferation, invasion and migration of hypoxic breast cancer cells via downregulation of HES1</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">International Journal of Oncology</source>, <volume>52</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>2119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2129</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ijo.2018.4332</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29620169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Li</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Shen</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ding</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Luo</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>SIRT6 drives epithelial&#x02010;to&#x02010;mesenchymal transition and metastasis in non&#x02010;small cell lung cancer via snail&#x02010;dependent transrepression of KLF4</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Experimental &#x00026; Clinical Cancer Research</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>323</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13046-018-0984-z</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30577808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Liu</surname>, <given-names>R. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Potential synergy of phytochemicals in cancer prevention: Mechanism of action</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Nutrition</source>, <volume>134</volume>(<issue>12 Suppl</issue>), <fpage>3479S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3485S</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/134.12.3479S</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Lowe</surname>, <given-names>S. W.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lin</surname>, <given-names>A. W.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Apoptosis in cancer</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Carcinogenesis</source>, <volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>485</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/21.3.485</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Marchi</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Giorgi</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Suski</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Agnoletto</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bononi</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bonora</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>De Marchi</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Missiroli</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Patergnani</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Poletti</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rimessi</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Duszynski</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wieckowski</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Pinton</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Mitochondria&#x02010;ros crosstalk in the control of cell death and aging</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Signal Transduction</source>, <volume>2012</volume>, <fpage>329635</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/329635</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22175013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Margraf</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Karnopp</surname>, <given-names>A. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rosso</surname>, <given-names>N. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Granato</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Comparison between Folin&#x02010;Ciocalteu and Prussian Blue assays to estimate the total phenolic content of juices and teas using 96&#x02010;well microplates</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Food Science</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>C2397</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>C2403</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.13077</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26448565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Pan</surname>, <given-names>M. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ho</surname>, <given-names>C. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Chemopreventive effects of natural dietary compounds on cancer development</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Chemical Society Reviews</source>, <volume>37</volume>(<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>2558</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2574</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b801558a</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18949126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Plant</surname>, <given-names>A. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bhadriraju</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Spurlin</surname>, <given-names>T. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Elliott</surname>, <given-names>J. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Cell response to matrix mechanics: Focus on collagen</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>, <volume>1793</volume>(<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>902</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2008.10.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19027042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Redza&#x02010;Dutordoir</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Averill&#x02010;Bates</surname>, <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Activation of apoptosis signalling pathways by reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>, <volume>1863</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>2977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2992</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2016.09.012</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27646922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Rop</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mlcek</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Jurikova</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Neugebauerova</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Vabkova</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Edible flowers &#x02013; A new promising source of mineral elements in human nutrition</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Molecules</source>, <volume>17</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>6672</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6683</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules17066672</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22728361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Saqallah</surname>, <given-names>F. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hamed</surname>, <given-names>W. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Talib</surname>, <given-names>W. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>In vivo evaluation of <italic>Antirrhinum majus</italic>' wound&#x02010;healing activity</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Scientia Pharmaceutica</source>, <volume>86</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>45</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/scipharm86040045</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Schumacker</surname>, <given-names>P. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Reactive oxygen species in cancer cells: Live by the sword, die by the sword</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Cancer Cell</source>, <volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2006.08.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16959608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Scolnik</surname>, <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zannoni</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Marrs</surname>, <given-names>B. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Spectral and functional comparisons between the carotenoids of the two antenna complexes of <italic>Rhodopseudomonas capsulata</italic>
</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>, <volume>593</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0005-2728(80)90061-4</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7236633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Siegel</surname>, <given-names>R. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname>, <given-names>K. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Jemal</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Cancer statistics, 2019</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">CA: A Cancer Journal for Clinicians</source>, <volume>69</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21551</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30620402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Song</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>, <given-names>X.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Huang</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Polyphenolic antioxidant profiles of yellow camellia</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Food Chemistry</source>, <volume>129</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>357</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.04.083</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30634237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Vukics</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kery</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Guttman</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Analysis of polar antioxidants in Heartsease (<italic>Viola tricolor</italic> L.) and Garden pansy (Viola x wittrockiana Gams.)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Journal of Chromatographic Science</source>, <volume>46</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>823</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>827</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/chromsci/46.9.823</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19007486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="fsn31924-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="fsn31924-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Wang</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gao</surname>, <given-names>X. Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yang</surname>, <given-names>S. Q.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sun</surname>, <given-names>Z. X.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dian</surname>, <given-names>L. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Qasim</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Phyo</surname>, <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Liang</surname>, <given-names>Z. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sun</surname>, <given-names>Y. F.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Jatrorrhizine inhibits colorectal carcinoma proliferation and metastasis through Wnt/beta&#x02010;catenin signaling pathway and epithelial&#x02010;mesenchymal transition</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Drug Design, Development and Therapy</source>, <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>2235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2247</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DDDT.S207315</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>