<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Plant micropropagation is proposed to be the most promising system for the efficient production of useful secondary metabolites under controlled cultivation conditions. In vitro culture allows rapid production of genetically identical pathogen- and contaminant-free plants through clonal propagation, using relatively small amounts of space, supplies, and time. In this study, tansy 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> culture was established from seeds collected from natural populations, whose composition of secondary metabolites in essential oils and methanol extracts were determined in our previous study (Devrnja et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>). Successful multiplication of plantlets was conducted through shoot tips that exhibited potent apical growth and regeneration capacities on BM without the addition of any PGRs. It has been previously reported that exogenously applied PGRs, especially from the cytokinin and auxin groups, may impair genetic stability and lead to somaclonal variation (Rani and Raina 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2000</xref>; Bairu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2007</xref>), which is considered to be undesirable in the production of plant material via in vitro culture, especially if it will be used for secondary metabolite isolation (Bairu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2007</xref>; Passinho-Soares et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>). Moreover, for the establishment and propagation of tansy in vitro root cultures, PGR supplementation was also unnecessary, and roots increased their mass 3 times in 4 weeks in PGR-free liquid BM. For roots detached from the spontaneously rooted micropropagated shoots and further in vitro maintenance, auxins were considered a necessary treatment. Roots that were excised and propagated in PGR-free medium, often turned brown and died soon after being removed from the “mother” plant (Stanišić et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2019</xref>).
</p>
