<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">A review of the available literature found no data referring to phytochemical analyses of EOs from in vitro tansy cultures. Essential oil constituents of native tansy, of which the seeds were taken for the establishment of in vitro cultures presented in this study, were predominantly oxygenated monoterpenes, with 
 <italic>trans</italic>-chysantenyl acetate as a dominant compound (Devrnja et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>). Interestingly, in vitro cultivation significantly affected EO composition that may be favored by the high chemical plasticity reported for tansy (Lawrence 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>). Like in some other reports (Arumugam et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2020</xref>), in EO obtained from in vitro cultivated plants, a significantly greater number of chemical compounds was detected, as compared to that of wild-grown tansy (88 vs. 65, respectively). In vitro cultivation conditions also enhanced the accumulation of sesquiterpenes with respect to EO from field-grown “mother” plants, with a similar portion of identified monoterpene and sesquiterpene compounds. Although EO chemistry is genotype determined, the plasticity of secondary metabolism allows plants to alter their defenses in response to environmental and/or physiological-stress circumstances (Usano-Alemany et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2016</xref>; Kirimer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2017</xref>). Strikingly, the dominant sesquiterpene from in vitro tansy, neryl-isovalerate, present with 20.6% in total EO, was not detected in native tansy plants. Neryl-isovalerate is a registered food flavoring agent and adjuvant (Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1997</xref>; EU Commission 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2012</xref>). Additionally, the dominant compounds in the EO of in vitro tansy, 
 <italic>trans</italic>-thujone and camphor, were identified in a much higher portion (22.7% and 10.1%, respectively) than in the oil of native tansy (9.04% and 4.9%, respectively). At this point, the observed differences in EO metabolite production in tansy trichomes affected by cultivation practice are hard to explain. Several authors have reported that these quantity-quality variations induced by in vitro culture conditions could be accounted for by the requirement of some metabolites for a specified environmental factor, such as light or temperature, for highly differentiated in vitro cells/tissues or for cells/tissues in a specified stage of development (Dörnenberg and Knorr 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1997</xref>; Avato et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2005</xref>; Batista et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2016</xref>; Passinho-Soares et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>). Variation in EO composition could also be the consequence of different ontological stages, with in vitro plants being in the juvenile-stage by definition and mature native tansy plants in the flowering stage. The elevated prevalence of camphor in micropropagated plants, compared to field-grown plants, was also observed in 
 <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> (Avato et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2005</xref>), which was explained by the correlation of camphor levels with juvenile stages of development of micropropagated plants relying on earlier works by Croteau et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1981</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1987</xref>), who have shown that the presence of camphor in the oil decreases with the age of the plant. Although the specific growing conditions could alter the chemotype of “mother” plants, in vitro cultivation could offer a supply of constant EO, unrelated to environmental conditions, time of the year, and presence of unwanted biotic interactions. Biotechnological interventions on secondary metabolites production taking place in trichomes could further enhance the production of some important metabolites in tansy EO. Guided by a similar goal, Sultana et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2015</xref>) used the 
 <italic>Tanacetum cinerariifolium</italic> promoter of chrysanthemol synthase (TcCHS), coding for the first enzyme in the pyrethrum biosynthesis pathway, fused to a GFP (Green Fluorescent Protein) and GUS (β-glucuronidase) reporter genes, to transform 
 <italic>Chrysanthemum morifolium</italic> and 
 <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> plants. The accumulation of pyrethrum was detected only in glandular trichomes of both species.
</p>
