<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Concerns were raised that Figs 1 and 2 report data that were generated by other researchers and reported previously in Figures 10 and 12 of [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The journal office did not receive documentary evidence to confirm that the authors had permissions from the data owners to include these results in the 
   <italic>PLOS ONE</italic> article. According to the first author, the spectra obtained by the authors were of poor resolution but were similar to those in [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], so the representative spectra from [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] were included in [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The names of the researchers who generated the data were included in Figs 1 and 2, but neither the Results section text nor the figure legends indicate that the data in Figs 1 and 2 were obtained by researchers outside the author group. The first author apologized for not citing the prior work as the source of these results.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Similarities were noted between chemical analysis data reported for 26 compounds in the Methods section (#6, 10–23, 26–36) and data reported previously in [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In response to this issue, the first author commented that the 
   <italic>PLOS ONE</italic> article [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] presented a new methodology (sonochemical synthesis) to synthesize compounds which have been reported previously, and compared compounds synthesized using this method to compounds generated using previously reported methods. According to the first author, the Methods section ought to have cited [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] for the conventional method of synthesizing triazole based Schiff bases, and similar spectroscopic data were obtained in [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and in [
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
   <xref rid="pone.0238168.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] because the same compounds were analyzed in these articles. Underlying data were provided to support some of the results for which similarities were raised, but the first author stated that the full dataset is not accessible at this time due to the current coronavirus-related lockdown situation in Pakistan. Without the full original dataset to support the results in question the 
   <italic>PLOS ONE</italic> Editors cannot fully clarify this issue.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
