<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For extraction of sugars, plant tissues were homogenized in 50% (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) acetonitrile. The method described by Hamad et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-jof-06-00168" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] was applied to identify the individual sugars in the plant extract by using high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC), then comparing their retention time with those of a standard mixture. Quantification of the sugar samples was achieved based on peak area comparison with a calibration curve of the corresponding standards. Organic acids were extracted in phosphoric acid (0.1% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) supplemented with butylated hydroxyanisole (3 g/L) and then analyzed using HPLC with a SUPELCOGEL C-610H column coupled to a UV detection system set at 210 nm (LaChromL-7455 diode array, LaChrom, Tokyo, Japan). The concentration of each organic acid was calculated by using a calibration curve [
 <xref rid="B24-jof-06-00168" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. For extraction of amino acids, a known weight of plant tissues was vigorously homogenized in 80% aqueous ethanol. Amino acids were measured using a Waters Acquity UPLC-tqd system (Milford, Worcester County, MA, USA) equipped with a BEH amide 2.1 × 50 column. The lipophilic fraction of plant samples was obtained by extraction in chloroform/methanol (2:1, 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>). Thereafter, fatty acids were detected, according to Hassan et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-jof-06-00168" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], by using GC/MS analysis (Hewlett Packard, Palo Alto, CA, USA) with an HP-5 MS column (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 mm). Fatty acids were quantified using NIST 05 database and Golm 
 <italic/> Metabolome Database (
 <uri xlink:href="http://gmd.mpimp-golm.mpg.de" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://gmd.mpimp-golm.mpg.de</uri>). Phenolic acids and flavonoids were extracted in acetone-water solution (4:1 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) for 24 h. The method outlined in Hamad et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-jof-06-00168" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] was followed up for determination of Phenolic acids and flavonoids using an HPLC system (SCL-10A vp, Shimadzu Corporation, Kyoto, Japan). The concentration of each compound was calculated with a calibration curve of the corresponding standard. For extraction of volatile oils, two hundred gm of fresh plant material were subjected to steam distillation with about 500 mL of water, where the volatiles were collected [
 <xref rid="B26-jof-06-00168" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The levels of volatiles were determined using gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS) according to the method outlined by El Hattab et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-jof-06-00168" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
