<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Light conditions strongly affected plant metabolism, especially the accumulation of polyphenol compounds including flavonoids. The combination of blue and red light in BR significantly improved the percentage of total flavonoid in 
 <italic>A. roxburghii</italic> plants, about 1.81 mg/g compared to 1.56, 1.24, and 1.43 mg/g fresh leaves in the FL, LED red, and LED blue, respectively. The reason might be the factors involved in the flavonoid biosynthesis pathway were regulated by both blue and red wavelengths. Liu et al., 2019, indicated that blue or red light had opposite effects on different flavonoid compounds in 
 <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> Osbeck. Meanwhile, the blue light promoted Diomestin 6-8-di-C-glucosie, Neoeriocitrin, Apigenin-6,8 di glucosise, Narirutin; red light enhanced the accumulation of Diosimin, Rhoifolin-4′-O-glusoside, Eriocitrin, Didymin, and Hesperidin [
 <xref rid="B52-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. On the other hand, the supplement of white diodes in the LED matrix caused the decline of total flavonoids in plants cultured under BRW151 and BRW142, compared to the control and BR lights (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-09-01344-f005">Figure 5</xref>c). Besides blue or red wavelengths, there was the presence of yellow and green wavelengths in these lamps, which were initially from white light emitting diodes in the matrix. Ye et al., 2017, showed that yellow light (generated with a light filter) led to a decrease in total phenolic compounds and flavone in 
 <italic>A. roxburghii</italic> [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Likewise, Wang et al. (2018) also found that the lowest total flavonoid content was in the formula yellow light, and the total polyphenol content was the lowest in the green light treatment [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01344" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Consequently, the total biomass of plants slightly affected to compare to BR light (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-09-01344-f005">Figure 5</xref>a,b). These phenomena might be influenced by the effects of the white LED ratio in BRW142 lamps (approximate 28%) compared to BRW151 (about 14%). In addition, the reduction in red diodes in this lamp also might be the reason (about 58% red diodes) as compared to the BR lamp with up to 80% red diodes.
</p>
