<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ιn comparison with other species, similar antioxidant biological activity has been reported for the essential oils of 
 <italic>Sideritis raeseri</italic> subps. 
 <italic>raeseri, Citrus sinensis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Citrus latifolia</italic>. 
 <italic>Sideritis raeseri</italic> essential oil possessed weak radical scavenging activity but demonstrated substantial cytoprotective activity against H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative stress and DNA damage in HaCaT cells. The main components of the oil were geranyl-
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene (25.08%), geranyl-
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene (15.17%), and geranyl-linalool (14.04%), but α-pinene (2.13%) and caryophyllene (2.88%) are common with mastic essential oil [
 <xref rid="B63-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The essential oils of 
 <italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>Citrus latifolia</italic> were found to efficiently decrease apoptosis in HaCaT cells following exposure to H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and to lower intracellular superoxide ion. R-(+)-limonene, 
 <italic>β</italic>-thujene, α-myrcene, and 
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene were identified as their major components [
 <xref rid="B64-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. However, α-pinene and myrcene are also present, but are found in minimal abundance in the 
 <italic>Citrus</italic> essential oils. In another study by Haghdoost et al., the essential oil of 
 <italic>Pistacia atlantica</italic> resin extract demonstrated a concentration-dependent effect on the healing of burn wounds through increasing basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) and platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF) and enhancing angiogenesis. Quite interestingly, 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene (46.57%) was identified as the main constituent of the essential oil [
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Detailed studies on the potencies and the capacities of the single components of essential oils, as well as their synergy effects, are required to reach more accurate conclusions on the relation between biological activity and chemical composition. 
</p>
