<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) is a permeabilizing agent that has been successfully used in cell and root cultures to promote the release of secondary metabolites from the cells to the culture medium. The excretion of target compounds to the culture medium facilitates the downstream processes to increase overall production. Cell suspensions of 
 <italic>C. blumei,</italic> when maintained with the addition of 0.1% DMSO, presented a cell death rate lower than 15% in relation to the total cells, with a doubling time of 10.7 h and a RA production of 1.0–1.1 g L
 <sup>−1</sup>. This shows that this concentration of the permeabilizing agent is not harmful for the cells [
 <xref rid="B151-antioxidants-09-01273" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. The response of the preconditioned cells (previously treated with 0.1% DMSO) was an improved cell growth and RA production when they were later treated with higher DMSO concentrations (0.5%). They reached a maximum of 2.85 g RA 100 g DW
 <sup>−1</sup> in the culture medium, which represented 66.4% of the total RA produced. Immobilization is a plant cell culture technique that fixes the cells in a suitable matrix and prevents their movement into the culture medium. The first successful immobilization of plant cells was reported by Brodelius et al. [
 <xref rid="B152-antioxidants-09-01273" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>], who entrapped 
 <italic>Catharathus roseus</italic> and 
 <italic>Daucus carota</italic> cells in alginate beads. Immobilization was proposed as a strategy to enhance the overall production of SMs in plant cell cultures. Immobilized cell cultures of 
 <italic>C. blumei</italic> were developed to study the effect of the permeabilizing agent DMSO and growth regulators on biomass and RA production. Cells were immobilized in a support matrix composed of the fibrous skeleton of Luffa fruits. Immobilized conditions reduced the growth rate and RA production of cell cultures by half. The absence of growth regulators decreased the cell biomass and did not increase RA production. In this case, preconditioning treatment with 0.1% DMSO did not improve the cell adaptability to higher concentrations (0.5%) of the permeabilizing agent [
 <xref rid="B151-antioxidants-09-01273" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>].
</p>
