<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Having this in mind, Balaure et al. [
 <xref rid="B227-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">227</xref>] recently developed a collagen dressing containing orange essential oil functionalized ZnO nanoparticles (
 <italic class="italic">d</italic> = 20 nm) inserted into a three-dimensional (3D) matrix. As was described above, ZnO nanoparticles present antimicrobial activity, and their incorporation into collagen to impart biocidal properties is a strategy that has also been followed by other authors [
 <xref rid="B228-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">228</xref>,
 <xref rid="B229-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">229</xref>]. In this particular case, for the preparation of the dressing, suitable amounts of previously synthesized ZnO nanoparticles, collagen, and glutaraldehyde solution (crosslinker) were added so that collagen–ZnO gels were formed. For the antibacterial activity, collagen–ZnO gels (with three different ZnO contents) were placed in petri dishes and inoculated with 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> bacteria strains. For the sake of comparison, antibiotic disks were used as a control. After 24 h of incubation, the diameters of the inhibition zone were measured and compared with the control disks. The results revealed that the collagen–ZnO wound dressings presented a remarkable antimicrobial activity against the 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strain, as the growth inhibition zones were 11.5 mm and comparable to the diameter of the inhibition zones obtained for the control antibiotics. When analyzing antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, the influence of the ZnO content was evidenced. Besides the antimicrobial activity, the developed collagen dressings showed great regenerative capacity. This combination of outstanding properties makes this bio-based sustainable material a potential candidate for wound healing applications.
</p>
