<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Periderm and rhytidome tissues of stem and root bark play an essential role in the protection against 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> invasion. When the advancing fungal mycelia reach phellogen in the healthy bark, it induces a series of anatomical changes to limit the growth of the pathogen and replace infected meristems and other tissues. The activated defence response leads to the development of lignified impervious tissue (IT), necrophylactic periderm formation (NP) and callus tissue generation, which is then involved in the compartmentalization of infected tissue and formation of new vascular cambium inside the host plant [
 <xref rid="B175-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B192-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>]. Different patterns in cambial damage and xylem compartmentalization reflected the susceptibility levels of plant species towards the 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> pathogens [
 <xref rid="B175-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>]. At similar levels of inoculations, both 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic> and 
 <italic>A. sinapina</italic> were found equally pathogenic on Douglas-fir, western hemlock and western redcedar; however, based on using inoculum blocks with fungal exudates, 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic> mycelia were advancing more virulently than those of 
 <italic>A. sinapina</italic> [
 <xref rid="B102-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Equal levels of inoculation, using vegetative fungal mycelia, indicated that both species have a comparable pathogenic potential in contacting and invading their hosts. In contrast, inoculum blocks with fungal exudates, possibly exposing all secreted protein-based and metabolic factors, enforced the real virulent abilities of 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic> towards host tissues. 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic> inoculations with exudates appeared to cause lesions on the roots, IT and NP developed in the bark at higher frequencies than 
 <italic>A. sinapina</italic> inoculations, and large proportions of the roots showed no signs of host response. Furthermore, as an indication of possible host-specific communication, 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic> induced more intense host responses in western redcedar than those following infections by 
 <italic>A. sinapina</italic> [
 <xref rid="B102-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>].
</p>
