<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tussilagone (
 <bold>6</bold>), a sesquiterpene compound isolated from the dried flower buds of 
 <italic>Tussilago farfara</italic> L. has been identified as the major bioactive component of the plant (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2020</xref>). IL-6 is a type of cytokine that is also an important key component in the pathophysiology of AR. The aggravation of the inflammatory symptoms may be induced by the mast cells. This is caused by the recruitment of various inflammatory cells to the nasal mucosa by cytokines including IL-6 and TNF-α (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Bernstein et al., 2002</xref>). Apart from reducing the levels of histamine and OVA-specific IgE in an 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> study, tussilagone administered intraperitoneally at the dose of 50 and 25 mg/kg has shown a significant decrease (p&lt; 0.01) in cytokine IL-6 levels OVA-sensitized guinea pigs. The inhibitory effect of tussilagone at 50 mg/kg was as good as clarityne, the positive control, at the dose of 10 mg/kg (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2020</xref>). Another study has also shown a significant decrease in LPS-stimulated production of IL-1β, and IL-6 mRNA through the inhibition of MAPK and NF-ƙB pathways (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2018</xref>). The phosphorylation of MAPKs may upregulate the gene expression of multiple inflammatory cytokines by transcription factor activation (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Passante and Frankish, 2009</xref>). An 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study conducted on RBL-2H3 cells, a histamine-releasing cell has also shown an obvious suppression of p38 MAPK in a concentration-dependent manner after the treatment with tussilagone (
 <bold>6</bold>) at the doses of 1, 10, 100, 500 µM with a significant value of p&lt; 0.01 given at the highest dose (500 µM). The inhibition of the MAPK pathway in the mast cells has been identified to be one of the mechanisms to alleviate AR symptoms in this study (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
