<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0100">In methanolic extracts, total phenolic content of 
 <italic>L. adoensis</italic> was the highest followed by 
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic>, 
 <italic>Piper capense</italic>, 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> and 
 <italic>T. ammi</italic>. The amount of total phenolic and flavonoid contents obtained from the same spice was also varied by the type of solvent used. For example, total phenolic content was higher in methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>L. adoensis</italic> and 
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic> than in aqueous extracts. This indicates that phenolic compounds in these two spices are extractable more by less polar solvent than by highly polar aqueous solvent. Whereas the reverse is true in 
 <italic>P. capense</italic>, 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> and 
 <italic>T. ammi</italic> as total phenolics measurement was higher in aqueous extracts than methanolic extracts. Solvents of different polarity have different potential of extracting compounds (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Egigu et al., 2010</xref>). Excepting 
 <italic>P. capense</italic>, total flavonoid content was also higher in methanolic extracts than aqueous extracts with the highest value measured for 
 <italic>L. adoensis</italic> followed by 
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic>, 
 <italic>T. ammi</italic>, 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> and 
 <italic>P. capense</italic>. In 
 <italic>L. adoensis</italic>, 
 <italic>T. schimperi</italic> and 
 <italic>P. capense</italic> total phenolic content was 1.5–1.8-fold and 1.7–2.4-fold higher than total flavonoids content in methanolic and aqueous extracts, respectively. In methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic>, total phenolics content was equivalent to flavonoids, whereas total phenolics content was lower than flavonoids in 
 <italic>T. ammi</italic>. In aqueous extracts, however, values were 2-3-fold higher. Here it is noteworthy that in seed spices, the ratio of total phenolics to flavonoids content were lower as compared to leafy spices in methanolic extracts. This may be due to less extractability of some phenolic compounds, for example phenolic acids, that account for total phenolic values by methanol. It is also possible that since spice seeds were obtained from shop where they have been stored for some time, some phenolic compounds other than flavonoids that could have contributed to total phenolic content and able to be extracted by methanol might have been lost or transformed. In general, our test plants showed variation in their total phenolic contents. Results of the antioxidant assays were also varied between the test plants. From correlation analysis, we noticed strong positive correlation between total phenolic contents of our test plants and the different antioxidant assays, suggesting that differences of antioxidant capacities between our test plants can be ascribed to phenolic contents of the spices. Previously, several researchers (e.g., 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Takao et al., 2015</xref>) showed the presence of strong correlation between antioxidant capacities and plants' total phenolic contents that confirms phenolic compounds as important contributors to antioxidant activities.
</p>
