<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Support parameters</div>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical analysis of the Troll C crude oil used in this exposure confirmed that all 16 EPA PAHs were present, their sum was 1.6 g/L. The most abundant PAHs present were 2- and 3-ring PAHs and the highest concentrations were found for those of 2-methylnaphthalene and 3-methylnaphthalene. The PAH profile of the seawater in the header tank also showed presence of both low and high molecular weight PAHs. Chemical analysis results for Troll C crude and header tank are summarized in additional files [see Additional files 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM4">4</a>, respectively].
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Morphometric parameters (CI and HSI) and concentrations of PAH metabolites in fish bile, reported for the three individuals used for GI microbial community analysis, were intended to give an overall description of the effect of oil on the exposed fishes. Moreover, concentrations of PAH metabolites in fish bile were used as support parameter for the GI microbial community analysis.</p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CI and HSI values, reported in additional tables [see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM5">5</a>], showed no differences between fish exposed to crude oil and the control group. The lack of significant difference between exposure groups was confirmed by statistical analysis using data from all exposed fishes (data not shown).
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of both FF and GC-MS analysis of PAH metabolites in bile confirmed the uptake and biotransformation of PAHs after exposure and results can be seen in additional files [see Additional files 
  <a rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM6">6</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM7">7</a>, respectively]. Distribution pattern of PAHs found in Troll C crude oil was reflected through the distribution pattern of PAH metabolites in the bile analysed by FF. Highest concentrations were measured for 2–3-ring PAH metabolites, while 4-ring and 5-ring PAH metabolites were present in lower concentration. GC-MS results further confirmed these observations, showing C
  <sub>2</sub>-OH-, and C
  <sub>3</sub>-OH-naphthalene to be found in the highest concentrations in bile from crude oil exposed fish. The level of PAH metabolites revealed a grouping of samples according to exposure level when using multi-variate analyses (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). A non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) plot showed a distinct clustering of control and low oil concentration exposed fish, clearly separated from the cluster of medium and high oil concentration exposed individuals.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Differences in oil exposure levels in Atlantic cod. Oil exposure was assessed by multivariate analysis of PAH metabolite concentrations using non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS). The analysis is based on standardized polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) metabolite levels in fish bile, generated using Euclidean distances between samples. Fish subjected to the same oil exposure level are coloured identically. Ctrl = control, Low = low oil concentration, Med = medium oil concentration, High = high oil concentration. Numbers indicate sample (individual fish) numbers</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12866_2018_1171_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variation among individual fish was highest for the high exposure group as revealed by the scattering. The plot indicates a dose-response effect. Moreover, PERMANOVA analysis confirmed a significant difference between the control and low oil concentration exposed fish when compared to the medium and high oil concentration samples (
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.002, R2 = 0.59, Pseudo-F = 14.2, DF = 11) [see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM8">8</a>]. This, together with the NMDS plot, indicated a dichotomy between the lower (control + low) and upper (medium + high) exposure levels in the dataset.
 </p>
</sec>
