<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Since the most commonly applied method of hydrodistillation is usually performed at the laboratory scale using a Clevenger apparatus, thus representing a complete and effective extraction method for volatile compounds, HD oil might be regarded as the traditional product for vetiver root, as acknowledged by the current market. The experimental results indicated that although the number of total components of CXE oil was close to HD oil, the chemical composition exhibited a slight difference, most possibly due to the fact that CXE extraction depends on the solubility of the extracts in the specific solvent, whereas hydrodistillation obtains extracts based on the reduction of the co-boiling point while mixing and then heating the root matrix with the water. Literally, IVD, namely, indirect vapor distillation, implies that the water does not need to be in direct contact with the root matrix before distillation, and instead live steam is employed directly to penetrate the matrix for the extraction of volatile compounds, which is generally more intensive than the direct distillation (HD) performed in an ordinary laboratory [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Therefore, the result showed the similar chemical composition of IVD and HD, merely representing the distillation of different magnitudes. Both CXE and SFE belong to the green solvents recently recommended by many researchers, but remarkable differences between the two pressurized fluids were displayed when they were used in the extraction of natural products. Notably, for the extraction of vetiver oil from the root material, less components could be obtained by SFE, because supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> might preferentially extract solutes of relatively low polarity. In other words, the polarity range of SFE might not fit that of the polarity of vetiver oil. However, different from pure supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, the ethanol pressurized by compressed CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> was a perfect solvent, exhibiting a more extensive polarity range, which was achieved by mixing the common polar solvent, ethanol, and the nonpolar solvent, supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. As far as the polarity was concerned, CXE was more suitable to extract the vetiver root oil, whose chemical composition was more complex than that of other general plant essential oils.
</p>
