<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Despite plants being a rich source of useful chemical compounds with different pharmacological properties, some of these compounds may be toxic to humans. 
  <italic>Parinari curatellifolia</italic>, among its other important pharmacological activities, has been shown to have significant antiproliferative activity on cancer cell lines. Toxicity studies are required to determine the safety profile of 
  <italic>P. curatellifolia</italic> in the consideration of its potential pharmaceutical benefits as a source of lead compounds in cancer therapy. The effects of 
  <italic>P. curatellifolia</italic> on both the integrity of the erythrocyte membrane and on normal cells were determined. The dried leaf powder of 
  <italic>P. curatellifolia</italic> was used in serial exhaustive extraction procedures using hexane, dichloromethane, ethyl acetate, acetone, ethanol, methanol, and water as solvents in addition to extraction using DCM: methanol in equal ratio. Alkaloids, flavonoids, and saponins were isolated from the ethanol extract. The leaf extracts were tested for haemolytic activity on sheep erythrocytes at concentrations of 0.625 to 5 mg/ml. The extracts were also tested for toxicity activity on normal mammalian cells such as the BALB/c mice peritoneal cells using the MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide) at the concentrations of 6.3 to 50 
  <italic>μ</italic>g/ml. In the haemolysis assays, none of the plant extracts had a significant haemolytic activity with the saponin-enriched extract having the maximum haemolytic activity of 12.2% for a concentration of 5 mg/ml. In the MTT cell viability assay, none of the 11 plant extracts had significant cytotoxicity. The water extract, however, had significant (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) proliferative activity towards the murine immune cells at all concentrations
  <italic>. P. curatellifolia</italic> leaf extracts were, therefore, not toxic to both erythrocytes and immune cells, and the water extract may have immunostimulatory effects. It is concluded that 
  <italic>P. curatellifolia</italic> leaf extracts are not toxic 
  <italic>in vitro</italic> and, therefore, our results support the use of the plant for ethnomedicinal use.
 </p>
</abstract>
