<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">The findings of some researchers [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] have shown that Gram-positive bacteria were more susceptible to extracts from plants than the Gram-negative bacteria. Gao 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] reported that the ability of Gram-negative bacteria to resist plant extracts is an attribute of the lipopolysaccharides in their external membrane. However, a recent work done by Ajiboye and Oyejobi [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] using an agar-well diffusion method showed that most of the extracts used inhibited the growth of Gram-negative bacteria. Taahir [
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] observed in his work, where he used direct bioautography method, that Gram-negative bacteria (
 <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 700603, and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 27853) were more inhibited than Gram-positive bacteria (
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>aureus</italic> ATCC 33591) by BGN extracts from red and brown hulls confirming the work of Ajiboye and Oyejobi [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The ability of BGN extracts from red and brown hulls was attributed to the high phenolic content of the hulls as red and brown BGN hulls correlated well with high flavonoid and tannin content [
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Klompong and Benjakul [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] observed that BGN seed coat extracts exhibited antimicrobial properties against bacteria (
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>), yeast (
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>) and mold (
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>), in a dose-dependent manner using agar diffusion method. Anthony [
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] found out that BGN nut extracts exhibited inhibitory properties against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas auriginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> using the Kirby-Baurer diffusion method. In sum, BGN can be considered as an efficient antimicrobial agent that can inhibit the proliferation of both prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells. A typical antimicrobial agent's mechanism of action is through the penetration of the cytoplasmic membrane, disruption of the permeability of the membrane leading to the destruction of the membrane [
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Consequently, cytoplasm leakage and coagulation occur causing the deformation, lysis and death of the cell [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In fungi, this agent prevents mycelial growth and spore germination [
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The hydrophilicity and hydrophobicity of BGN phytochemicals enhance its accumulation in cell membranes leading to the change in permeability of the membrane, seepage of intracellular components, weakening enzyme systems of microbes and consequently, their death [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Clearly, the antimicrobial activities of BGN depend on the concentration of the extract and nature of tested organisms. However, no study has so far quantified the dosage of BGN extracts for treatment of any human disease in sub-Saharan Africa.
</p>
