<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30" class="p">The assignments of metabolites in the 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR spectra were based on chemical shifts, signal multiplicities, intensity ratios, comparison with database values (HMDB, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hmdb.ca" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.hmdb.ca</ext-link>, BMRB, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bmrb.wisc.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bmrb.wisc.edu</ext-link> and ChenomX NMR Suite 8.3 library (ChenomX Inc., Edmonton, Canada)) and with spectra of authentic compounds recorded in the same solvent conditions (in-house library) and by spiking the samples with corresponding compound standards when doubt remained. 2D NMR experiments (COSY, Correlation SpetroscopY; HSQC, Heteronuclear Single Quantum Correlation; HMBC, Heteronuclear Multiple Bond Correlation) with non-uniform sampling (NUS percent at 25% and 128 points for COSY and HSQC and 512 points for HMBC) were performed for selected samples for assignment verification. COSY experiment observed 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H nuclei in both direct and indirect dimensions where 16 dummy scans preceded a 64-scan series of 8.97 µs 90° pulse in each dimension. Spectral width was 6000 Hz for each dimension, with 4K data points in f2 and 1K in f1. The HSQC experiment observed 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H in direct dimension and 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C in indirect dimension, 16 dummy scans preceded a 128-scan series of 8.97 µs 90° pulse in direct dimension and 14.50 µs 90° pulse in indirect dimension. Spectral width was 20,000 Hz in indirect dimension and 6,000 in the direct one, 2K data points were recorded in the direct dimension and 1K in the indirect one. The HMBC experiment observed 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H in direct dimension and 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C in indirect dimension, 16 dummy scans preceded a 128-scan series of 8.50 µs 90° pulse in direct dimension and 14.50 µs 90° pulse in the indirect dimension. Spectral width was 30,000 Hz in indirect dimension and 6000 in the direct one, 4K data points were recorded in the direct dimension and 2K in the indirect one. The 2D spectrum was reconstructed using the recursive multidimensional decomposition available within the Bruker software.
</p>
