<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fish oil and the related actives, such as omega-3 and omega-6 PUFAs, have been proved helpful for maintaining skin homeostasis and ameliorating cutaneous abnormalities. The fatty acids in fish oil can improve skin barrier function, inhibit UV-induced inflammation and hyperpigmentation, attenuate dry skin and pruritus elicited by dermatitis, accelerate skin wound healing, and prevent skin cancer development. All the benefits can be achieved by different administration routes, including oral supplementation, topical application, and intravenous injection. Despite the evidence indicating the successful application of fish oil and omega-3 PUFAs on skin disorders, there have been conflicting reports from meta-analysis and systematic review regarding the clinical benefit of using fish oil over the control or other lipids. Fish oil is a crude extract with very complex ingredients. It is difficult to control fish oil contents well. The abundant sources of the fish genus also complicate the quality control. The specific fish type and the PUFA percentage in the fish oil are the important factors that should be considered for the benefits on the skin. Another issue that should be considered is that not only PUFAs but also vitamin A, vitamin D, retinol, selenium, and other components may contribute to the bioactivity of fish oil. The most commonly raised concern for omega-3 PUFA administration is the potential to raise the risk of bleeding via the anti-platelet effect. Gastrointestinal disturbance by dietary fish oil is also reported in some cases. Caution should be used in optimizing the benefits of fish oil or omega-3 fatty acids to ensure a balance between damage or toxicity and the effectiveness. Although many fish oil products and PUFAs are developed for testing in cell- and animal-based studies, clinical trials for skin application are still limited. This may be because of the high cost of clinical trials and some unknown side effects that should be identified and explored first. Further clinical studies are encouraged for future application of improved therapy.</p>
