<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Atmospheric chemical transport models have considered the dissolution rates for mineral dust from laboratory experiments as a kinetic process, which is dependent on the pH, the mineral composition of Fe-containing particles, organic species (as Fe-reducing agents), and solar radiation (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">4</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">15</italic>
 </xref>). The Fe dissolution scheme was improved on the basis of laboratory studies considering the types of Fe species associated with mineral dust source materials (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">20</italic>
 </xref>). Following these studies, three Fe pools were characterized as follows: labile Fe (e.g., ferrihydrite and nanosized Fe oxides), less labile Fe (e.g., heterogeneous inclusion of nano-Fe grains in aluminosilicates), and refractory Fe (e.g., crystalline and micrometer-sized iron oxides). The labile Fe fraction in aerosols is regarded as the most readily bioavailable form of Fe and often used as the input from atmospheric models to ocean biogeochemistry models. The fraction of less labile Fe in aerosols may be regarded as potentially bioavailable forms that can be photochemically transformed to labile forms in the atmosphere or after deposition into the ocean. “Less labile Fe” may be operationally distinguished from “labile Fe” by using specific leaching agents (
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">21</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">23</italic>
 </xref>), which do not access the refractory Fe fraction (
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">23</italic>
 </xref>). Therefore, the labile and less labile content in aerosols may set the upper and lower limits for aerosol Fe solubility, respectively, as it applies to the marine environment.
</p>
