<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The bark of the oak has much importance and is used extensively in medicine as an antiseptic and an energizer. The decoctions from the barks of 
 <italic>Q. robur</italic> and 
 <italic>Q. petraea</italic> were recognized to have anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, and antihemorrhagic activities [
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Indeed, it has been suggested for the treatment of patients with high levels of blood sugar [
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and treatment of sore throat [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The leaves of 
 <italic>Q. virginiana</italic> have been used as antimicrobial agent. As well as, can be employed for the treatment of gastrointestinal disorders [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The galls of 
 <italic>Q. infectoria</italic> are used to restore the elasticity of the uterine wall, as well as to treat many inflammatory disorders [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Also, they are used in Malay traditional medicine commonly to treat wound infections after childbirth [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In India, they are employed traditionally as dental applications such as that in treatment of toothache and gingivitis. In Asia, it has been widely used for the treatment of infection diseases, skin disorders, and inflammatory ailments [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The traditional system of medicine is an integral part of Kumaun and Garhwal regions of Uttarakhand, and others states in India used 
 <italic>Quercus leucotrichophora A. Camus</italic> for treatment of urinary infection [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], stomach pain [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], gonorrhea, asthma, hemorrhages, diarrhea, dysentery [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], urinary disorder [
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], and diuretics [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Besides, in Korean medicine folk, they are widely used for their dysentery, antidiarrhea, and antidermatitic proprieties [
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].
</p>
