<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0165">The contradictions between harvesting years and contents of active ingredients have long been the primary issue for the industrial production of medicinal crops (
 <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">Saha and Basak, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). At present, the medicinal materials of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> used in pharmaceutical industry are mostly collected from cultivation resources. According to our field investigation as of May 2020, the cultivated area of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> is more than 26,000 ha in China, with an annual production of about 60,000 tons for raw materials. However, an emerging challenge faced by herbalists and pharmaceutical enterprises is how to obtain the maximum yield of active ingredients from limited medicinal materials. For 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, its root gradually grows thicker, and the production of medicinal materials increases with cultivation years. However, the yield of active ingredients showed different regular patterns changing with growth years (
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2018</xref>). In this study, the contents of four main medicinal active ingredients (baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, and wogonin) showed a changing trend of "V" type from 1-year-old to 15-year-old 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, indicating that the contents of 2 or 3 growth years and 15 growth years were higher than those of 4 or 5 growth years. The main reason is mostly due to the age of plant tissues. As the growth year increases, the phenotypic, biochemical, and physiological characters (e.g. leaf area, chlorophyll content) of plants change gradually. Previous studies have found that leaf area as well as chlorophyll content have critical effects on the contents of primary and secondary metabolites of crops (
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">Munz et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">Senger et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">Hudina and Štampar, 2002</xref>). For 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, its capacity of sugar biosynthesis increases with growing leaf area and chlorophyll content, thereby increasing the contents of secondary metabolites (e.g. the four main active ingredients). However, the increasing leaf area will also lead to more consumptions of organic matters through cellular respiration. Thus, there exists a trade-off between accumulation of secondary metabolites and consumption of organic matters. This is rational to explain the “V” type trend of active ingredients of 1-year-old to 15-year-old 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. In addition, another reason is probably the significant differences of the contents of active ingredients between cortex and stele in roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. In 2-year and 15-year old 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, the contents of baicalin, wogonoside, scutellarin, scutellarein, baicalein, and wogonin in the part of cortex were significantly higher than those of stele (
 <italic>P</italic> ≤  0.01, 
 <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Previous studies have shown that baicalein and wogonin are mainly distributed in cortex, while baicalin and wogonoside are evenly distributed in both cortex and stele (
 <xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2015</xref>). Meanwhile, it is found that the contents of baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, and wogonin in roots of 2-years-old 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> is higher than that of 1.5-year and 3-year-old 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Hu, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2008</xref>). After growing for more than 3 years, the part of stele in the whole root will gradually decay, and the proportion of cortex will increase year after year. Therefore, the contents of five medicinal active ingredients in roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> older than 4 growth years are significantly higher than those of 2 growth years. Considering only land use efficiency and product yield, the contents of active ingredients, and the yield of medicinal materials in perennial 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> (more than 3 years) were both higher than those of 2 years. However, the increment of yield per hectare and per year significantly reduced in 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> growing over three years (
 <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, the increment of economic benefit per unit area and per year significantly reduced with growing years of land utilization. In addition, for 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> growing more than 3 years, the part of stele in the whole root will gradually rot and the proportion of cortex will increase. The contents of baicalin, wogonoside, scutellarin, baicalein, and wogonin in cortex were significantly higher than those in stele (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt;  0.001) (
 <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Thus, the contents of active ingredients in roots (with decayed stele) growing more than 3 years is significantly higher than that of roots (without decayed stele) growing less than 3 years. Taken together, the best harvesting year of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> is determined as cultivated 2–3 years based on comprehensive evaluation of the content of medicinal active ingredients, the increment of annual yield, and the efficiency of land utilization. Collectively, the above results not only gave interpretations for the differences of medicinal active ingredients in different growing years and different parts of roots, but also provided valuable references that old 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> (rotten or hollow stele) was best quality of Chinese medicinal materials in ancient pharmacopoeia.
</p>
