<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The usage of silver as an antimicrobial agent spans a century. Silver was used as a disinfectant by Greeks and Romans to decontaminate their water and food supplies. Silver was also used in ancient times to treat burns and wounds (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Alexander, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Barillo and Marx, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adhya et al., 2015</xref>). Studying silver nanoparticles against biofilms has gained immense recognition. Silver nanoparticles exert an inhibitory effect against fungal biofilms by damaging cell wall mostly by distortion and disruption of the outer surface of the fungal cell wall (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Lara et al., 2015</xref>). In subsequent experiments, AgNPs when used to functionalize medical and environmental surfaces, demonstrated biofilm inhibition (&gt;50%) at relatively low concentrations (2.3 to 0.28 ppm) (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Lara et al., 2020</xref>). Combination therapy of Fluconazole with silver nanoparticles has also shown a substantial decrease in the MIC (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Longhi et al., 2016</xref>). The resistance to fluconazole (FLC) in 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> is strongly associated with overexpression of genes encoding efflux pumps or lanosterol 14α-demethylase (
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr">Sagatova et al., 2016</xref>). Subsequently, with the disruption of the cell wall and cytoplasmic membrane of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> by AgNPs, these silver particles cause an increase in reactive oxygen species and hydroxyl radical production, which can also contribute to cell membrane damage (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Hwang et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">Monteiro et al., 2012</xref>). Recently, researchers have identified bismuth oxide (BiO
 <sub>3</sub>) nanoparticles with potent antimycotic activity against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> growth. Moreover, when these nanoparticles were compared to commercially available antifungal drugs like chlorhexidine, nystatin, they completely eradicated the biofilm formation (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Hernandez-Delgadillo et al., 2013</xref>). In another study, magnesium oxide nanoparticles (MgO NP) were used to investigate their antifungal and antibiofilm property against 
 <italic>C. albican</italic>s. The study revealed that MgO nanoparticles effectively inhibited 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm formation. Furthermore, adhesion experiments showed that MgO NPs repressed the preliminary adhesion of 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Kong et al., 2020</xref>). In another study, when gold nanoparticles (Au-NP) were tested on the biofilms formed due to 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, these particles showed robust inhibitory activity. Additionally, these Au-NPs increased the host immune response activity against these pathogenic organisms (
 <xref rid="B188" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Nani et al., 2019</xref>). From previous studies, chitostan and its nanoparticle (ChNPs) were already known for their antifungal property (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Ing et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Mohammed et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Gondim et al., 2018</xref>). Therefore, to establish its antibiofilm activity, ChNPs were investigated, and it was found that ChNPs significantly inhibited the biofilm formation causing very less changes in the acrylic resin surface (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Gondim et al., 2018</xref>). Likewise, another study conducted with selenium nanoparticles (Se-NP) showed strong inhibition on 
 <italic>Candida</italic> biofilm formation as these particles out compete sulfur in biological process due to their similar chemical properties. Also, these nanoparticles enter into the cell to shrink and disrupt the outer membrane structure of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> cell (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Guisbiers et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
