<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Transcriptome sequencing is a powerful tool for screening gene expression patterns and identifying candidate genes. In the current study, high-throughput RNA sequences were generated to analyze the transcriptomes of 
 <italic>M. canadensis</italic> undergoing a 24 h darkness treatment followed by exposure to light for 24 h. Approximately 72 million high-quality clean reads were generated, and a total of 95,579 unigenes, with an N50 of 1260 bp and average length of 754 bp, were obtained. In a previous study, nine of the orthologous genes involved in the menthol synthesis pathway were identified. Darkness for 24 h downregulated the expression levels of 
 <italic>McGpps-L</italic>, 
 <italic>McGpps-s</italic>, 
 <italic>McLs</italic>, 
 <italic>McL3OH</italic>, 
 <italic>MciPD</italic>, 
 <italic>MciPR,</italic> and 
 <italic>McPR</italic> genes. The RNA-Seq study showed that the expression levels of these genes were upregulated after light exposure, and RT-PCR confirmed these results. Among the transcriptional profiles, 14 of the DEGs involved in the monoterpene pathway and 15 of the DEGs involved in the sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis pathways showed the same transcription patterns, except for unigene0051735 and unigene001095. The significant downregulation of genes involved in the MEP pathway may explain the reduced essential oil metabolite production. Furthermore, changes in the monoterpene profiles show that low light intensity leads to an accumulation of the branchpoint intermediate pulegone and the side product piperitone. In fact, under conditions of salinity and osmotic stresses, pulegone accumulated in 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-00930" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-00930" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00930" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-00930" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This intermediate compound is considered an undesirable component under harsh growth conditions. The downregulation of the gene encoding pulegone reductase (PR), and the consistent expression of the gene encoding (−)-menthol dehydrogenase (MR), may explain the reduced proportions of menthone and menthol. Mahmoud and Croteau [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00930" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] reported that high levels of menthofuran reduced pr transcript levels in immature leaves, consequently increasing pulegone content in peppermint. These results suggest that the flux of (+)-pulegone is controlled at the transcriptional level of pr, and they are consistent with the results of our present research. However, our data are presently insufficient to explain the accumulation of piperitone under low light conditions.
</p>
