<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The essential oils (EOs) are complex mixtures of volatile components with intensive odor and various colors [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These components have different biological functions for plants such as the attraction of pollinators or protection against herbivores or microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. EOs are stored in specialized structures such as secretory glands, cavities, channels, and glandular trichomes. In the Lamiaceae family, EOs are stored in glandular trichomes. These trichomes are found on the surface of stems, leaves, calyces, and corollas of plants from the 
 <italic>Satureja</italic> genus [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. They are roughly divided into two groups—peltate and capitate glandular trichomes. Peltate glandular trichomes are composed of one basal epidermal cell, one wide stalk cell, and a multicellular head consisting of 8, 12 or 16 cells. Two types of capitate trichomes are described, type 1 (C1) composed of one basal epidermal cell, one stalk cell, and unicellular secretory head, and type 2 (C2) which are the smallest and have one basal cell, one or two stalk cells, and a unicellular head [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Peltate glandular trichomes are also found on all organs, while capitate trichomes show organ preference [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Previous research showed that 
 <italic>S. montana</italic> has more peltate trichomes on the outer side of calyx than 
 <italic>S. subspicata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], but the distribution of trichomes varies between species and organs. Non-glandular trichomes are found on all organs, 
 <italic>S. montana</italic> has a denser indumentum compared to the other two species. 
 <italic>S. subspicata</italic> and 
 <italic>S. kitaibelii</italic> have fewer non-glandular trichomes on the leaves and calyces, while on the stem, these trichomes are present only on two opposite sides [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00511" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
