<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Qualitative analysis of aqueous and organic extracts of guava leaves revealed the presence of phenolic acids, flavonoids, terpenoids, glycosides, and saponins, in which their presence is positively correlated with antimicrobial activity. HPLC–TOF–ESI/MS analysis of fermented GLs confirmed the presence of gallic acid, chlorogenic acid, rutin, isoquercitrin, avicularin, quercitrin, kaempferol, morin, and quercetin. These compounds have the property of inhibiting ergosterol, which is a fungal cell membrane component, and glucosamine, which is a fungal cell growth indicator. Similarly, water-soluble tannins present in GLs act as bacteriostatic agents, with mechanisms of actions like withholding substratum, hampering oxidative phosphorylation, and extracellular enzyme inhibition. They have been demonstrated to have an inhibitory effect on antibiotic-resistant clinical isolates of 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B72-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Another study, by Hirudkar et al. [
 <xref rid="B73-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], identified quercetin as one of the most predominant flavonoids of GLs with the highest pharmacological activity. Additionally, activity against bacterial and fungal pathogens was traced to triterpenoids like betulinic acid and lupeol [
 <xref rid="B74-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. A methanolic GL extract demonstrated antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> with a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 0.79 μg/mL, a minimum bactericidal concentration of 51 μg/mL, and a reasonable antifungal activity with a minimum inhibitory concentration of 12.6 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="B75-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. A decoction of GLs at various concentrations (1%, 5%, and 10%) exhibited an inhibitory effect on bacterial colonization and binding of bacterial enterotoxins on epithelial cells, thus altering the inflammatory response. Guava extract showed higher activity of the antioxidant enzymes peroxidase, catalase, and polyphenol oxidase [
 <xref rid="B76-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Biogenic production of silver nanoparticles (40 nm in size) using GL extract showed antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> owing to high antiradical activity against DPPH radicals and ABTS radical cations [
 <xref rid="B77-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The role of the cytokine interleukin-7 (IL-7) as an immune booster against microbial infections is well studied. It is hypothesized that GL extracts act on the intestinal mucosal cells and aid the upregulation of IL-7 synthesis and help in the development of B and T cells [
 <xref rid="B78-foods-10-00752" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Ongoing investigations on the antimicrobial activity of plant bioactive compounds encourage the utilization of GL extract in the treatment of microbial infections, oxidative stress-related diseases, and unraveling more prophylactic compounds from GLs. An overall presentation of all the bioactivities demonstrated by GLs is presented in 
 <xref rid="foods-10-00752-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-10-00752-f003">Figure 3</xref>.
</p>
