<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alkaloids are a large and structurally diverse group of amino acid-derived heterocyclic nitrogen compounds of low molecular weight, widely distributed across plant kingdoms, microorganisms and animals and deriving their name from their alkaline chemical nature [
 <xref rid="B164-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. Due to the complexity of alkaloids, no single taxonomic principle could completely classify them [
 <xref rid="B165-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>]. Alkaloids can be grouped into classes based on their natural and biochemical origin, as well as by chemical structures (heterocyclic and non-heterocyclic alkanoids). Structurally, they can be divided into classes such as quinolines, isoquinolines, indoles, pyrrolidines, pyridines, pyrrolizidines, tropanes and terpenoids and steroids [
 <xref rid="B166-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>]. Presently, over 18,000 alkaloids have been reported in different plant species [
 <xref rid="B167-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>] including those of 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic>. While alkaloids have been utilized pharmaceutically because of their therapeutic activities such as anti-microbial, anti-hypertensive, anti-cancer, anti-inflammatory, anti-human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and many others, some alkaloids are highly toxic to humans and animals [
 <xref rid="B164-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>]. They may contribute to undesirable sensory qualities such as bitterness in food crops such as yams [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Alkaloids have been reported in several species of yams (
 <italic>D. alata</italic>, 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic>, 
 <italic>D. hamiltonii</italic>, 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic>, 
 <italic>D. pubera</italic>, 
 <italic>D. pentaphylla</italic>, 
 <italic>D. wallichii</italic>, 
 <italic>D. glabra</italic> and 
 <italic>D. hispida</italic>) at values between 7.2 and 16 mg per 100 g dry weight [
 <xref rid="B123-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>] (
 <xref rid="foods-09-01304-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). A study from West Africa characterized the antinutritional factors in flour samples from four 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species and reported alkaloid levels ranging between 0.02 and 0.11 mg/100 g [
 <xref rid="B169-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. Similarly, Senanyake et al. [
 <xref rid="B170-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>] recorded alkaloid levels of 0.94, 1.64 and 1.89 mg/100 g in 
 <italic>D. alata</italic> (Rajala), 
 <italic>D. alata</italic> (Hingurala) and 
 <italic>D. esculenta</italic> (Kukulala), respectively. Alkaloid has also been reported in 
 <italic>D. belophylla</italic> (Prain) Haines at a concentration of 0.68 mg/100 g [
 <xref rid="B125-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. 
</p>
