<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) is the key enzyme involved in the hydrolysis of the acetylcholine in the neuromuscular junction and synapse which results in termination of the nerve impulse transmission (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>). The impairments in cholinergic transmission are associated with the severity of AD (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>). High level of AChE is found in the brain of AD patients (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>). Previous reports suggested that activity of the AChE increases, which lead to a decrease in acetylcholine level in the brain of AD patients (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>). Neurotoxic effect of aluminum significantly increases AChE activity which is responsible for hydrolysis of acetylcholine (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>). The increase in activity of AChE by aluminum could be due to the allosteric interaction between cation (Al
 <sup class="sup">+3</sup>) and anionic sites of acetylcholinesterase enzyme which lead to alteration in secondary structure of AChE in the brain (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>). Inhibition of acetyl-cholinesterase (AChE) serves as an important strategy in the development of anti-Alzheimer's drugs. Natural products like essential oils have been reported for their strong acetylcholinesterase (AChE) inhibitory activity (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>). In our study, increased in AChE activity was observed in aluminum chloride treated group when compared to normal control rats. Treatment with cardamom oil showed decrease in AChE activity significantly, due to its main chemical constituent 1,8 cineole which has been reported to inhibit AChE enzyme 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>).
</p>
