<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>In vitro</italic> assays showed that 
 <italic>C. alnifolia</italic> had interesting antioxidant potential, and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> assays using cell lines showed that, in general, the six extracts were neither cytotoxic to 3T3 nontumour cell lines nor to Hela, SiHa, PC-3, B16-F10, and PANC tumour cell lines. On the other hand, Tsuboy et al. [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] observed that root extracts from 
 <italic>C. mollis</italic> were more cytotoxic than leaf extracts against HTC tumour cell lines. He et al. [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] showed that vitexin and isovitexin are excellent antioxidant molecules and have a wide spectrum of antioxidant, antiproliferative, anti-inflammatory, and other properties. Moreover, it has been verified that extracts from 
 <italic>C. uvifera</italic> and 
 <italic>C. cereifera</italic> have proinflammatory activity and may act on tumour necrosis factor-
 <italic>α</italic> (TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The bioinformatics approach used here, considering the presence of vitexin and isovitexin, proposes that 
 <italic>C. alnifolia</italic> extract may act on TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> and prostaglandin-endoperoxide synthase (PTGS or COX). Habtemariam [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] mentioned that extracts are a mixture of bioactive molecules that may act synergistically or alone. Furthermore, it has been observed that natural products may act on signalling pathways, for example, the NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B signalling pathway [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Bioinformatics data using vitexin and isovitexin showed that some gene targets were anti-inflammatory genes such as NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B and COX-2.
</p>
