<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with OASIS Tables v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing-oasis-article1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharm Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharm Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IPHB</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">iphb20</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pharmaceutical Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1388-0209</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1744-5116</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6130702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27927070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13880209.2016.1258424</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1258424</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of antioxidant and hepatoprotective effects of white cabbage essential oil</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">J. Morales-L&#x000f3;pez et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morales-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>Javier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Centeno-&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>M&#x000f3;nica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nieto-Camacho</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003"><sup>c</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>Mercedes G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004"><sup>d</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0005"><sup>e</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>Nury</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>Eduardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0006"><sup>f</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><label>a</label><institution>Escuela Nacional de Medicina y Homeopat&#x000ed;a, Programa Institucional de Biomedicina Molecular, Instituto Polit&#x000e9;cnico Nacional</institution>, <country>M&#x000e9;xico</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>b</label><institution>Centro de Investigaci&#x000f3;n en Ciencia Aplicada y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a Avanzada del Instituto Polit&#x000e9;cnico Nacional</institution>, <country>M&#x000e9;xico</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>c</label><institution>Instituto de Qu&#x000ed;mica Universidad Nacional Aut&#x000f3;noma de M&#x000e9;xico</institution>, <country>M&#x000e9;xico</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0004"><label>d</label><institution>Unidad Irapuato, Centro de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y de Estudios Avanzados del IPN</institution>, <country>M&#x000e9;xico</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0005"><label>e</label><institution>IMSS, Hospital de Ortopedia "Dr. Victorio de la Fuente Narv&#x000e1;ez"</institution>, <country>M&#x000e9;xico</country>; </aff><aff id="AF0006"><label>f</label><institution>Laboratory of Medicinal Chemistry and Pharmacology. Centro de Investigaci&#x000f3;n en Biolog&#x000ed;a de la Reproducci&#x000f3;n, &#x000c1;rea Acad&#x000e9;mica de Medicina, Universidad Aut&#x000f3;noma del Estado de Hidalgo</institution>, Pachuca Hidalgo, <country>M&#x000e9;xico</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">CONTACT <addr-line>Eduardo Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Mart&#x000ed;nez</addr-line><email>efernan@uaeh.edu.mx</email>; <email>tomedyfm@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage seq="29">233</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2016 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s).</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/Licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/Licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/Licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="iphb-55-1258424.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><bold>Context:</bold> There have been no reports of the extraction of essential oil (EO) from white cabbage [<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> L. var. <italic>capitata</italic> (L.) Alef. f. <italic>alba</italic> DC. (Brassicaceae)] (Bocfal) or its chemical composition, antioxidant activity, or hepatoprotective effects.</p><p><bold>Objective:</bold> To extract Bocfal EO, to identify and quantify its chemical components, to assess their antioxidant capacity, and to evaluate the hepatoprotective properties of Bocfal EO.</p><p><bold>Materials and methods:</bold> Bocfal EO was obtained using hydrodistillation (200&#x02009;mm Hg/58&#x02009;&#x000b0;C). The chemical composition was analyzed using GC-MS and was quantified using GC-FID. The antioxidant activity of Bocfal EO and its main constituents was evaluated using TBARS in rat brain homogenates. A Bocfal EO hepatoprotective effect (192&#x02009;mg/kg) on acute carbon tetrachloride (CT)-induced liver damage was determined in rats using biochemical markers and histological analysis. Diallyl disulphide (DADS) (1&#x02009;mmol/kg) was used as a control for comparison.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> Bocfal EO contained organic polysulphides (OPSs), such as dimethyl trisulphide (DMTS) 65.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.92% and dimethyl disulphide (DMDS) 19.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.16% as major constituents. Bocfal EO and DMTS were found to be potent TBARS inhibitors with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 0.51 and 3&#x02009;mg/L, respectively. Bocfal EO demonstrated better hepatoprotective properties than did DADS (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), although both slightly affected the hepatic parenchyma <italic>per se</italic>, as observed using histopathology.</p><p><bold>Discussion and conclusion:</bold> The antioxidant properties of Bocfal EO and DMTS may be the mechanism of hepatoprotective action; the parenchymal disturbances by Bocfal EO or DADS alone may be related to the high doses used.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var. <italic>capitata</italic> f. <italic>alba</italic></kwd><kwd>organic polysulphides</kwd><kwd>hepatoprotection</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Instituto Polit&#x000e9;cnico Nacional</named-content><named-content content-type="funderidentifier">10.13039/501100003069</named-content></funding-source><award-id>Proyectos SIP 20120526 and 20141449.</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="7309"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>The liver is one of the largest internal organs in the human body, and it controls the flow and safety of substances absorbed from the digestive system into the systemic circulation. The main liver functions include the production of energy by protein, carbohydrate and lipid metabolism, the synthesis of bile salts, the storage of vitamins, and the production of lipoproteins, angiotensin and coagulation factors among others. Therefore, hepatic diseases such as fatty liver disease, hepatitis and cirrhosis highly impact the homeostasis of the body (Arias et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Hepatopathies are caused by toxic chemicals, drugs, alcoholism, viral infections and glutathione exhaustion, among others; thus, numerous animal models of liver injury have been used to test the hepatoprotective potential of natural products (Jaeschke et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The hepatotoxic carbon tetrachloride (CCl<sub>4</sub>, CT) model is widely used for the experimental induction of acute or chronic liver damage; the metabolism of CT involves the homolytic cleavage of C&#x02013;Cl bonds, which lead to the formation of free radicals (CCl<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02022;</sup>) that bind covalently to a series of molecular structures, in particular to membrane lipids, during the peroxidation process (Muriel <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In this regard, the genus <italic>Brassica</italic> (Brassicaceae) comprises diverse vegetable species that contain bioactive compounds such as glucosinolates and phenolic compounds. Many of these compounds are famous for their antioxidant activity, via preventing carcinogen bioactivation and increasing the detoxification of reactive oxygen species (ROS) (Wagner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; &#x00160;amec et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>The research on the aromas from cruciferous vegetables (i.e., cabbages and related vegetables, <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> Linn. spp.) and, in consequence, their bioactive compounds, represents a real challenge because of the scarce yields of these aroma compounds, which have been described to contain isothiocyanates (ITCs) and organic polysulphides (OPSs) as major components (Stoewsand <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). The OPSs or sulfane sulphur compounds contain a labile, highly reactive sulphur atom in a reduced oxidation state with a valence of 0 or &#x02212;1, covalently bound to another sulphur atom (R&#x02013;S<sub>n</sub>&#x02013;R&#x02032;) (Iciek et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and this chemical characteristic makes OPSs good antioxidants (Toohey &#x00026; Cooper <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Moreover, cruciferous vegetables contain other antioxidant compounds; for instance, polyphenols from dry cabbage powder have exhibited moderate antioxidant activity in chemical assays. In addition, the anthocyanin-rich extract from red cabbage [<italic>B. oleracea</italic> L. var. <italic>capitata</italic> (L.) Alef. f. <italic>rubra</italic> DC.] has been shown to attenuate cardiac and hepatic oxidative stress in atherogenic rats (Sankhari et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Likewise, the genus <italic>Allium</italic> (Amaryllidaceae) contains OPSs such as allyl sulphides (Calvo-G&#x000f3;mez et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). The biological properties of the diallyl disulphide (DADS) found in garlic (<italic>Allium sativum</italic> L.) have been widely studied, and they include modulation of cellular oxidative stress, involvement in signal transduction and post-translational modification of proteins by the formation of mixed disulphides (Iciek et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) and hepatoprotective effects, which were observed on the model of CT-induced liver damage (Zhu et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>Currently, there are no published reports concerning the extraction, identification and quantification of the chemical constituents of white cabbage essential oil (<italic>B. oleracea</italic> var. <italic>capitata</italic> f. <italic>alba,</italic> Bocfal EO), its antioxidant capacity or its hepatoprotective activity. Therefore, the aim of this study was to obtain Bocfal EO via hydrodistillation (at low pressure/temperature), to identify and quantify its chemical constituents (OPSs content), to assess their antioxidant capacity through an <italic>in vitro</italic> assay, and to evaluate Bocfal EO hepatoprotective properties by comparing them with those of DADS in an acute, CT-induced liver damage rat model.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0003"><title>Chemicals</title><p>All reagents were of analytical grade. Dichloromethane of chromatographic grade and diallyl disulphide (DADS) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St Louis, MO). Dimethyl trisulphide (DMTS) and dimethyl disulphide (DMDS) (purity 98%) were supplied by Natural Advantage (Oakdale, LA).</p></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Vegetable material</title><p>The aerial parts of fresh Bocfal were collected in parcels at the &#x02018;Ejido de San Vicente Chicoloapan, Estado de M&#x000e9;xico&#x02019; in August 2015. The Bocfal showed edible maturity and was harvested within 24&#x02009;h period. The identity of the plant was confirmed by Dr N. Ival&#x000fa; Cacho and a voucher specimen (1420213MEXU) was deposited at the Herbario Nacional de M&#x000e9;xico (MEXU).</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Essential oil (EO) extraction</title><p>Distillation is the traditional method for EO extraction (Amorati et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), but hydrodistillation is the most used because it allows the application of low-pressure conditions (200&#x02013;150&#x02009;mm Hg) and low temperatures (55&#x02013;58&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) to avoid chemical changes that are induced by thermal shock in the EO at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Kim et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Bocfal EO was extracted by hydrodistillation as reported previously (Calvo-G&#x000f3;mez et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>); in brief, 12&#x02009;kg of vegetable was ground with 4&#x02009;L of water for 20&#x02009;min in an industrial blender (Santos model Miss Blend, Mexico). Then, the plant material was introduced into a distillation apparatus and heated for 12&#x02009;h in a double boiler until the temperature reached 58&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The pressure was then slowly reduced from 200 to 150&#x02009;mm Hg. The Bocfal EO was stored in Pyrex glass flasks at &#x02212;20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s0006"><title>EO chemical composition by gas chromatography &#x02013; mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis and gas chromatography &#x02013; flame ionization detector (GC-FID) quantification</title><p>GC-MS analyses of the EO samples was performed using an AutoSystem XL-GC equipped with a polar capillary column coated with free fatty acid phase (HP-FFAP, 30 m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.32&#x02009;mm ID &#x000d7;0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m film thickness) and coupled to a selective quadrupole TurboMass-MS detector with an electron impact ionization system at 70&#x02009;eV and 215&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Perkin-Elmer, Norwalk, CT). The oven temperature started at 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and was gradually increased up to 130&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at a rate of 6&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min, where it was maintained for 3&#x02009;min. A second program was used, where the temperature was increased to 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at a rate of 8&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min, where it was maintained for 8&#x02009;min. The injector temperature was 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and the flow rate of helium was 1.0&#x02009;mL/min at 8&#x02009;psi. The EO samples were diluted (1.0&#x02009;&#x003bc;L) in dichloromethane 1:25 v/v, and they were then manually injected in split mode.</p><p>The linear retention indices (RI) of the volatile compounds were calculated with a series of <italic>n</italic>-alkanes (C<sub>10</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>26</sub>), and DMDS, DMTS and allyl isothiocyanate (AITC) as standards. The identification of each detected compound was accomplished by comparing its retention time and mass spectra with those of authentic injected compounds as well as with information available from a computerized spectral database (NIST MS Search 1.7) and from published literature. Relative percentage amounts of the separated compounds in the Bocfal EO were expressed as percentages by peak area normalization of the total ion chromatogram (TIC) from the average value for each of three GC-MS iterations (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9).</p><p>The quantification of the major EO constituents was performed using a GC-FID on an Agilent Technologies 6890 plus GC (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA) equipped with a single injector, the same HP-FFAP polar capillary column was used. The flow of the carrier gas (N<sub>2</sub>) was 0.8&#x02009;mL/min. The initial column temperature was 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and it programmed as in the GC-MS equipment. Split injection was conducted with a split ratio of 1:100. A volume of 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of EO and standard samples diluted with dichloromethane was injected. The amounts of DMTS, DMDS and AITC, the three most abundant compounds in the Bocfal EO, were calculated using the linearity of the responses tested and the preparation of standard curves for each pure control compound in the following volume ranges (&#x003bc;L): DMTS 0.04&#x02013;0.01; DMDS 0.015&#x02013;0.005; AITC 0.005&#x02013;0.002. The final diluted sample of Bocfal EO was 0.04&#x02009;&#x003bc;L.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Animals</title><p>Male Wistar rats weighing approximately 180&#x02013;200&#x02009;g were housed in standard plastic cages at a temperature of 22&#x02013;24&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, under a 12&#x02009;h light&#x02013;dark cycle. They had free access to food (standard Purina chow diet, USA) and purified water. All the animals received humane care according to the respective institutional guidelines, the Mexican Official Norm (NOM-062-ZOO-999) regarding technical specifications for the production, care and use of laboratory animals, and the criteria outlined in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals (National Institutes of Health 1985).</p></sec><sec id="s0008"><title>Effect of Bocfal EO on lipid peroxidation inhibition in rat brain homogenates</title><p>The capacity to inhibit the products of lipid peroxidation was determined using thiobarbituric acid reactive substance (TBARS) quantification in homogenized rat brain samples according to the procedure described in the literature, with minor modifications (Ohkawa et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>). In brief, the rats were sacrificed by CO<sub>2</sub>, and their brains were rapidly dissected and homogenized in cold phosphate-buffered saline (9.5&#x02009;mM) at pH 7.4, 1:10 (w/v). The homogenate was centrifuged at 3400&#x02009;rpm for 10&#x02009;min, the supernatant was recovered, and its protein content was measured and adjusted at 2.66&#x02009;mg of protein/mL in PBS according to the method described by Bradford (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>). Then, in an ice bath, 375&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of supernatant was added to 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;M EDTA, and this mixture was incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min in the absence or presence of 25&#x02009;&#x003bc;L aliquots of the different dilutions of each test sample; the screened concentration ranges were the following: Bocfal EO 0.15&#x02013;4.7; DMTS 1.40&#x02013;14.06; DMDS 1.05&#x02013;10.56; AITC 1.12&#x02013;6.34 and DADS 17.78&#x02013;1000&#x02009;mg/L.</p><p>Lipid peroxidation was initiated by the addition of 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M FeSO<sub>4</sub> (final concentration 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;M). This blend was incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h, and 0.5&#x02009;mL of TBA reagent (0.5% TBA in 0.05 N NaOH and 30% TCA, 1:1 v/v) was added. The mixture was cooled by ice for 10&#x02009;min, centrifuged at 10,000&#x02009;rpm for 5&#x02009;min, and heated at 75&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min. After the mixture had cooled to room temperature, the absorbance was measured at 540&#x02009;nm using a Bio-Tek model ELx808 microplate reader. Butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) and &#x003b1;-tocopherol were used as synthetic controls. TBARS content was calculated using 1,1,3,3-tetramethoxypropane (TMP) for the standard curve. The lipoperoxidation inhibition percentage was calculated as the inhibition ratio (IR) as follows:</p><p>IR (%)&#x02009;=&#x02009;[(<italic>C</italic>&#x02013;<italic>E</italic>)/<italic>C</italic>]&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100, where <italic>C</italic> is the absorbance of the control sample, and <italic>E</italic> is the absorbance of the test sample.</p></sec><sec id="s0009"><title>Effect of Bocfal EO on acute, CT-induced liver damage <italic>in vivo</italic></title><sec id="s0010"><title>Experimental groups, treatment and doses</title><p>To assess the hepatoprotective properties of Bocfal EO on CT-induced liver damage, the rats were divided into six groups with <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7 animals in each group. The first group was the normal control group (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) that received two p.o. doses that were 12&#x02009;h apart of 1&#x02009;mL of olive oil as the vehicle (VE) for the Bocfal EO or DADS, which was used as a positive control because its hepatoprotective properties have been previously demonstrated and because it is a sulfane sulphur, or OPS, compound. In addition, 2&#x02009;h after the first administration of VE, the rats were orally given 1&#x02009;mL of mineral oil as the vehicle for CT (VCT). All the remaining groups underwent the same administration schedule. The second (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) and third (DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) groups received Bocfal EO and DADS, respectively, twice orally dissolved in their vehicles and also received the VTC p.o.; thus, both were control groups intended to show any adverse effects of Bocfal EO or DADS <italic>per se</italic> on normal rats. The fourth group was the damaged control (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT), wherein rats received the VE twice orally and a single dose of 4&#x02009;g/kg CT dissolved in its vehicle (1:1 v/v). Finally, the fifth (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT) and sixth (DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT) groups were administered their respective substances and were injured by CT.</p><p>Regarding the Bocfal EO dose, it was considered an amount of EO that contained 1&#x02009;mmol/kg of DMTS (192&#x02009;mg/kg of EO), which was later determined to be its main constituent at 65.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.92%, as well as 1&#x02009;mmol/kg of DADS (146&#x02009;mg/kg). These doses were based on a previous report wherein this moderate dose of pure OPSs, including DADS, was used in Wistar rats (Siess et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>).</p><p>All the animals were sacrificed by exsanguination under light ether anaesthesia 24&#x02009;h after CT administration; hence, blood was collected by cardiac puncture using a syringe containing sodium heparin as an anticoagulant. The liver was rapidly removed and rinsed in saline. All the samples were either kept on ice for immediate use or frozen at &#x02212;70&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="s0011"><title>Plasma enzyme activities and bilirubin determinations</title><p>Plasma was obtained for the determination of the canalicular membrane enzyme activities of cholestasis markers, such as alkaline phosphatase (AP) and &#x003b3;-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGTP), and for the cytosolic activity of the necrosis indicator alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Mart&#x000ed;nez et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) as well as for the quantification of the total bilirubin (TB) concentration (TECO Diagnostics kit, CA).</p></sec><sec id="s0012"><title>Glycogen determination</title><p>Small liver pieces (0.5&#x02009;g) were separated for glycogen measurement using anthrone&#x02013;sulphuric acid reagent (Seifter, et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">1950</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0013"><title>Assessment of lipid peroxidation</title><p>The extent of lipid peroxidation (LP) was estimated in the liver homogenates by measuring malondialdehyde (MDA) formation using the thiobarbituric acid method (Ohkawa et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>). Protein was determined according to the method described by Bradford using bovine serum albumin as a standard (Bradford <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0014"><title>Catalase as an oxidative stress indicator</title><p>For hepatic catalase (CAT) activity, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> consumption was measured at 480&#x02009;nm (Cohen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">1970</xref>). In brief, 5&#x02009;mL of cold 6&#x02009;mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was added to 0.5&#x02009;mL aliquots of the 10% liver homogenate. After 3&#x02009;min, the reaction was stopped with 1.0&#x02009;mL of 6 N H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>. The H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> reacted with a standard excess of 0.01 N KMnO<sub>4</sub>, and the residual KMnO<sub>4</sub> was measured at 480&#x02009;nm. CAT activity was calculated as the first-order reaction rate constant of the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> decomposition (k &#x000d7; 10<sup>2</sup>/min).
</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><title>Histology</title><p>Liver samples were taken from all the animals and fixed with 10% formaldehyde in phosphate-buffered-saline for 24&#x02009;h. Then, they were washed with tap water, dehydrated in alcohols and embedded in paraffin. Sections of 6&#x02013;7&#x02009;&#x003bc;m were mounted on glass slides covered with silane; the paraffin was previously eliminated. They consequently were used for haematoxylin/eosin staining for histological examinations using light microscopy.</p></sec><sec id="s0016"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>TBARS data underwent a one-way variance analysis (ANOVA), and the significant differences were obtained using Dunnett&#x02019;s test. For the hepatoprotective assessment, an ANOVA with the Student&#x02013;Newman&#x02013;Keuls test was used to compare groups. The resulting data are expressed as the means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM and were analyzed using Sigma Stat software version 3.1 (Systat Software Inc., San Jose, CA). In all cases, a difference was considered significant when <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s0017"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0018"><title>Extraction yields, constituents and quantification of Bocfal essential oil (EO)</title><p>The Bocfal EO extraction yield was 37.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.71&#x02009;mg/kg (33.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.29&#x02009;&#x003bc;L/kg) (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). The extraction process was repeated until the amount of EO was enough to carry out the biological tests. The GC-MS permitted the identification of 28 volatile compounds in the Bocfal EO, accounting for approximately 99% of the total amount (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). They were categorized into six chemical families, which are listed according to their relative abundance. The first family includes OPS compounds (R-S<sub>n</sub>-R, <italic>n&#x02009;=</italic>&#x02009;1&#x02013;4 and R&#x02009;=&#x02009;CH<sub>3</sub>) at 88.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.11% as follows: DMTS (65.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.92%) is the most abundant OPS, and DMDS (19.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.16%) is the second most abundant compound. The second family includes the ITCs and indoles at 6.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.09%, including AITC (4.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.70%), 3-butenyl isothiocyanate (0.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16%), and phenylethyl isothiocyanate (0.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15%), among others. The third family is the nitriles family (2.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33%); five compounds were identified in this study, with 3-butenenitrile (1.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23%) being the most abundant, followed by 2-pentenenitrile (0.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06%) and three more compounds. The fourth family is the alcohol family (1.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.53%) with 1-hexanol (1.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34%), 2-hexen1-ol (0.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10%), and some others. Aldehydes (0.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11%) form the fifth family, including 2-hexenal (0.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05%) and others. Finally, miscellaneous compounds constitute the sixth family at 0.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04%.</p><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Major components of <italic>B. oleracea</italic> var. capitata F. <italic>alba</italic> essential oil (Bocfal EO) obtained by hydrodistillation at low pressure (200&#x02013;150&#x02009;mmHg) and low temperature (55&#x02013;58&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) conditions.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Peak(#)</th><th align="center">RT (Min)</th><th align="center">RI</th><th align="center">Compound</th><th align="center">Content (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Organopolysulphanes (OPS)</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(1)</td><td align="char" char=".">2.26</td><td align="char" char=".">1224</td><td align="left">Dimethyl disulphide (DMDS)</td><td align="char" char=".">19.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(11)</td><td align="char" char=".">6.24</td><td align="char" char=".">1544</td><td align="left">Dimethyl trisulphide (DMTS)</td><td align="char" char=".">65.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(13)</td><td align="char" char=".">7.12</td><td align="char" char=".">1595</td><td align="left">Methyl pentyl disulphide</td><td align="char" char=".">0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(17)</td><td align="char" char=".">10.07</td><td align="char" char=".">1750</td><td align="left">Allyl methyl trisulphide</td><td align="char" char=".">0.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(19)</td><td align="char" char=".">11.39</td><td align="char" char=".">1818</td><td align="left">Methyl methylthiomethyl disulphide</td><td align="char" char=".">1.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(20)</td><td align="char" char=".">12.89</td><td align="char" char=".">1893</td><td align="left">Dimethyl tetrasulphide</td><td align="char" char=".">1.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Isothiocyanates and indoles</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(10)</td><td align="char" char=".">5.94</td><td align="char" char=".">1527</td><td align="left">Allyl isothiocyanate (AITC)</td><td align="char" char=".">4.31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(14)</td><td align="char" char=".">7.59</td><td align="char" char=".">1621</td><td align="left">3-Butenyl isothiocyanate</td><td align="char" char=".">0.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(22)</td><td align="char" char=".">17.64</td><td align="char" char=".">2109</td><td align="left">Indole</td><td align="char" char=".">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(23)</td><td align="char" char=".">18.04</td><td align="char" char=".">2125</td><td align="left">1-Methoxyindole</td><td align="char" char=".">0.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(24)</td><td align="char" char=".">19.38</td><td align="char" char=".">2181</td><td align="left">3-(Methylthio)propyl isothiocyanate</td><td align="char" char=".">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(26)</td><td align="char" char=".">25.62</td><td align="char" char=".">2511</td><td align="left">Butyl isothiocyanate</td><td align="char" char=".">0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(28)</td><td align="char" char=".">27.67</td><td align="char" char=".">2731</td><td align="left">Phenylethyl isothiocyanate</td><td align="char" char=".">0.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Nitriles</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(3)</td><td align="char" char=".">3.21</td><td align="char" char=".">1336</td><td align="left">3-Butenenitrile</td><td align="char" char=".">1.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(6)</td><td align="char" char=".">4.03</td><td align="char" char=".">1415</td><td align="left">4-Methylpentanenitrile</td><td align="char" char=".">0.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(7)</td><td align="char" char=".">4.48</td><td align="char" char=".">1441</td><td align="left">2-Pentenenitrile</td><td align="char" char=".">0.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(8)</td><td align="char" char=".">4.83</td><td align="char" char=".">1462</td><td align="left">Hexanenitrile</td><td align="char" char=".">0.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(25)</td><td align="char" char=".">22.04</td><td align="char" char=".">2352</td><td align="left">Benzene;propanenitrile</td><td align="char" char=".">0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Alcohols</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(2)</td><td align="char" char=".">2.94</td><td align="char" char=".">1306</td><td align="left">Penten-3-ol</td><td align="char" char=".">0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(5)</td><td align="char" char=".">3.84</td><td align="char" char=".">1404</td><td align="left">2-Pentenol</td><td align="char" char=".">0.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(9)</td><td align="char" char=".">5.76</td><td align="char" char=".">1516</td><td align="left">1-Hexanol</td><td align="char" char=".">1.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(12)</td><td align="char" char=".">6.73</td><td align="char" char=".">1556</td><td align="left">2-Hexen1-ol</td><td align="char" char=".">0.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Aldehydes</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(4)</td><td align="char" char=".">3.67</td><td align="char" char=".">1388</td><td align="left">2-Hexenal</td><td align="char" char=".">0.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(18)</td><td align="char" char=".">10.71</td><td align="char" char=".">1783</td><td align="left">Heptanal</td><td align="char" char=".">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(21)</td><td align="char" char=".">14.43</td><td align="char" char=".">1970</td><td align="left">2,4-Decadienal</td><td align="char" char=".">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>Miscellaneous</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(15)</td><td align="char" char=".">8.00</td><td align="char" char=".">1642</td><td align="left">3,3-Dimethylallylbromide</td><td align="char" char=".">0.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(16)</td><td align="char" char=".">8.60</td><td align="char" char=".">1673</td><td align="left">Camphor</td><td align="char" char=".">0.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">(27)</td><td align="char" char=".">26.93</td><td align="char" char=".">2601</td><td align="left">Eugenol</td><td align="char" char=".">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p>RI: retention index; RT: retention time.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The quantifications of DMTS, DMDS and AITC amounts, the three most abundant compounds in the Bocfal EO, were calculated using the linearity of the responses. This was conducted by preparing standard curves in a concentration range of pure volatile controls for comparison and using the equation from the linear regression obtained from each curve with the GC-FID equipment. The results indicate that each 1000&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of Bocfal EO contains 575&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;125&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of DMTS, 483&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;88&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of DMDS and 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;39&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of AITC. The correlation coefficients of the three standard curves were values higher than 0.95.</p></sec><sec id="s0019"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> antioxidant activity by TBARS assay</title><p><xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the antioxidant activity of Bocfal EO through a TBARS assay with rat brain homogenates; which showed an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x02009;mg/L. Bocfal EO showed a very similar antioxidant capacity when compared with that of the synthetic controls, BHT and &#x003b1;-tocopherol (0.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 and 2.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.93&#x02009;mg/L, respectively). Additionally, in this assay, the pure compounds, DMTS and AITC exhibited IC<sub>50</sub> values almost equal to that of &#x003b1;-tocopherol. In contrast, DMDS seemed to be inactive, resembling DADS; its IC<sub>50</sub> was 444.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;49.57&#x02009;mg/L, the highest value in this test. Indeed, the TBARS assay seems to be more suitable to quantify the antioxidant capacity of OPSs, because Bocfal EO, DMTS and DMDS were ineffective as antioxidants in the usual <italic>in vitro</italic> tests with DPPH and FRAP (data not shown), wherein polyphenolic compounds are very active.</p><table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Antioxidant activity by TBARS assay.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="80pt" align="left"/><col width="80pt" align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Tested compound</th><th align="center">TBARS &#x02013; IC<sub>50</sub> (mg/L)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left">Bocfal EO</td><td align="center">0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DMTS</td><td align="center">3.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DMDS</td><td align="center">No activity</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AITC</td><td align="center">3.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DADS</td><td align="center">444.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;49.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">BHT</td><td align="center">0.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Tocopherol</td><td align="center">2.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.93</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><p>Results are expressed as the mean value&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM of experiments performed in duplicate with samples of rat brain homogenates from at least five animals.</p></fn><fn id="TF3"><label>a</label><p>Different from Bocfal EO, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, ANOVA, Dunnett&#x02019;s test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s0020"><title>Effect of Bocfal EO on acute CT-induced liver damage <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref> depicts the plasma enzyme activities of AP and GGTP as well as TB concentration. Due to CT-provoked injury, the AP activity was increased twofold in the damaged group (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT) when compared with that of the normal control group (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT). In addition, the administration of Bocfal EO and DADS elevated that marker, though neither resulted in a significant difference in contrast with VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT. However, the treatment with Bocfal EO significantly decreased the enzyme activity (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) during the liver injury compared with VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT, which shows an anticholestatic effect. In addition, DADS did not modify the CT-induced AP elevation.</p><fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Plasma cholestasis markers: enzyme activities of alkaline phosphatase (AP) and &#x003b3;-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGTP); total bilirubin determined in the plasma from control rats treated with their respective vehicles (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VTC), with Bocfal EO (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) or with DADS (DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) as well as those administered the hepatotoxicant CT (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT) but treated with the same compound, respectively (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT and DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT). Each bar represents the mean value of experiments performed in duplicate with samples from at least four animals&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. (a) Difference from the VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT group and (b) from the VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT group, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, Student&#x02013;Newman&#x02013;Keuls test.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1258424_F0001_B"/></fig><p>GGTP enzyme activity was increased almost fivefold by CT administration (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) with respect to that in VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VTC control group; conversely, the Bocfal EO or DADS administrations slightly reduced the normal levels, but not in a significant manner. Regarding the CT-injured groups treated with the respective compounds, their GGTP activity increases were completely prevented; again, Bocfal EO was more effective as an anticholestatic agent than was DADS.</p><p>TB in the experimental groups showed a pattern very similar to that of AP because CT-induced liver damage increased the TB concentration, but in a statistically significant way; furthermore, the Bocfal EO and DADS control groups also exhibited a small degree of elevated TB concentration. However, although DADS lowered this marker, this change was not statistically significant. In contrast, Bocfal EO completely lowered the TB level (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref> shows the markers of liver injury: ALT, glycogen, LP and CAT. ALT is a cytoplasmic enzyme marker of necrosis; its activity was slightly diminished by Bocfal EO but significantly lowered by DADS administration. As expected, CT induced a notable increment in ALT activity (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), while treatments with both Bocfal EO and DADS abolished such elevation of activity, indicating their antinecrotic properties during oxidative damage, particularly for Bocfal EO.</p><fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Plasma and liver markers of necrosis, functionality and oxidative stress: alanine aminotransferase enzyme activity (ALT) determined in the plasma, hepatic levels of lipid peroxidation (LP) and glycogen, and catalase activity (CAT) quantified in the livers of control rats treated with their respective vehicles (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VTC), with Bocfal EO (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) or with DADS (DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) as well as those administered the hepatotoxicant CT (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT) but treated with the same compound, respectively (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT and DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT). Each bar represents the mean value of experiments performed in duplicate with samples from at least four animals&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. (a) Difference from the VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT group and (b) from the VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT group, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, Student&#x02013;Newman&#x02013;Keuls test.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1258424_F0002_B"/></fig><p>The Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT and DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT groups showed normal levels of glycogen with respect to the control group, while the CT-damaged group exhibited depleted glycogen content (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). However, Bocfal EO treatment completely prevented the depletion of glycogen; DADS did as well but to a much lesser extent.</p><p>LP represents the oxidative stress of cellular membranes. This hepatic indicator was augmented several-fold through CT administration in contrast with the VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT and the control groups of Bocfal EO and DADS, which did not alter the normal level of LP <italic>per se</italic>. In contrast, Bocfal EO treatment partially prevented the CT-induced oxidative injury by lowering the LP level approximately 70%; in addition, DADS maintained this marker at normal levels.</p><p>The normal liver CAT activity was augmented by Bocfal EO administration; conversely, DADS administration lowered it, and both of these results were significant (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). In addition, treatment with either Bocfal EO or DADS completely prevented the CT-induced CAT activity elevation in a similar way.</p><p>Liver damage was also evaluated by a histological approach through haematoxylin/eosin staining, which stains nuclei a black/dark blue colour and parenchymal hepatocyte cytoplasm a pink/magenta colour (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>). A normal hepatic cell population and tissue homogeneity are shown in a representative liver sample from the VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT normal control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3(a)</xref>). In contrast, type CT-injured liver sample showed important damage zones, diffuse ballooning necrosis, pyknotic nuclei and high hepatic steatosis with hepatocyte vacuolization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3(b)</xref>). Bocfal EO administration provoked diffuse hepatocyte ballooning by itself (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3(c)</xref>); thus, when Bocfal EO was administered concomitantly with CT, the liver presented an increased diffuse ballooning degeneration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3(d)</xref>). The treatment with the OPS standard resulted in a similar case, as the DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT group demonstrated focal swollen hepatocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3(e)</xref>). Furthermore, liver samples from animals damaged by CT and treated with DADS showed individual and zonal necrosis accompanied by high neutrophil infiltration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3(f)</xref>). Moreover, despite the apparent hepatoprotective properties, the mortality in groups treated with the substances was higher (up to 30%) than the regular mortality observed for the acute CT model was (less than 10%); thus, perhaps hepatoprotection was achieved in the stronger rats. Additionally, the administration of Bocfal EO or DADS caused weight loss (data not shown), piloerection and diminished activity in the rats.</p><fig id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Haematoxylin/eosin staining of representative liver sections from: (A) normal control rats administered vehicle (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT); (B) damaged control rats administered CT (VE&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT); (C) control rats administered Bocfal EO (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT); (D) damaged rats administered Bocfal EO (Bocfal EO&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT); (E) control rats administered DADS (DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;VCT) and (F) damaged rats administered DADS (DADS&#x02009;+&#x02009;CT). Central vein (CV), original magnification: 10&#x000d7;.</p></caption><graphic content-type="color" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1258424_F0003_C"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s0021"><title>Discussion</title><p>The Bocfal EO extraction yield was limited (37.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.71&#x02009;mg/kg), considering that there are few studies on the extraction of volatile compounds from <italic>Brassica</italic> spp. using a Likens&#x02013;Nickerson-type apparatus for hydrodistillation (Hifnawy et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Since yield values of 2&#x02009;mg/kg for broccoli, cabbage and cauliflower have been described (Buttery et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>), this work reports an unprecedented yield of volatile compounds in Bocfal EO, in comparison with those other <italic>Brassica</italic> vegetables. It has been strongly suggested that variations in type, presence and abundance of compounds within EO from the same cultivars depend on the genetic and ecological growth factors (Charron et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) as well as the extraction method and temperature (Kim et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The main reason for the limited amount of data about concentrated extracts of the volatile compounds present in <italic>Brassica</italic> is that ITCs and OPSs have glucosinolates and <italic>S</italic>-methyl-<sc>l</sc>-cysteine sulphoxide as precursors, which exist in low concentrations in the vegetable tissues (Macleod &#x00026; Macleod <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Stoewsand <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>).</p><p>The volatile compounds in Bocfal EO were identified and classified into six chemical families, listed according to their relative abundance. DMTS (65.43%) was the most abundant OPS, in agreement with many works on <italic>Brassica</italic> species (Maruyama <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">1970</xref>; Hifnawy et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). DMDS (19.29%) was the second most abundant OPS, and it is more frequently reported than DMTS in <italic>B. oleracea</italic> (Valette et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Fernandes et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Variations in composition and amount may be due to the extraction method used (Valette et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The ITC and indole family includes AITC, which was the third most abundant compound and has been described in some publications as the major volatile constituent in the varieties of <italic>B. oleracea</italic> spp. (Stoewsand <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). Five nitriles were identified and have previously been described in <italic>Brassica</italic>; they are considered ITC subproducts, which are generated under higher temperatures and more aggressive distillation methods than those used in this work (Valette et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Additionally, all the alcohols identified herein have been reported previously (Macleod &#x00026; Macleod <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Valette et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Many aldehydes have been described for Brussels sprouts (Van Langenhove et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>), and these compounds are considered high-temperature reaction markers, which are usually observed in extractions at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Buttery et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">1976</xref>); in this case, only three aldehydes were identified in EO, which may be due to the low extraction temperature applied. The sixth family included miscellaneous compounds in trace amounts.</p><p>The antioxidant activity of Bocfal EO assessed using a TBARS assay showed an antioxidant capacity very similar to that of the synthetic controls, BHT and &#x003b1;-tocopherol. Similarly, DMTS and AITC exhibited IC<sub>50</sub> values almost equal to that of &#x003b1;-tocopherol. Conversely, DMDS seemed to be inactive, resembling DADS inactivity. This could be because lipids in brain are good targets for OPSs, which inhibit TBARS formation as products of brain lipid peroxidation; in addition, the number of sulphur atoms contained in a molecule has been directly related to its antioxidant capacity (Wang et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p><p>DADS, diallyl sulphide (DAS), and diallyl trisulphide (DATS) are the principal constituents of garlic EO (Calvo-G&#x000f3;mez et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) and have been demonstrated to be antioxidants as well as hepatoprotective agents in a CT model (Hosono-Fukao et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Lee et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zhu et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). On this rationale, DADS was used as a control OPS because it possesses anticholestatic, antinecrotic and antioxidant effects, which were corroborated in this study. Furthermore, the dose-dependent protective effects of DADS and DATS against CT-induced hepatotoxicity possibly involve mechanisms of inducing antioxidizing or detoxifying enzymes by activating nuclear factor E2-related factor 2 (Nrf2) and blocking the metabolic activation of CCl<sub>4</sub> by suppressing CYP2E1 (Hosono-Fukao et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Many authors have achieved significant liver damage amelioration through the use of doses of DADS (with 50 and 100&#x02009;mg/kg, and even 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol/kg) lower than the dose administered in this study.</p><p>Cholestasis is defined as the mechanical or functional stoppage of bile flow in the intrahepatic or extrahepatic bile ducts, with bile components passing into the blood (Kuntz &#x00026; Kuntz <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). AP and GGTP are indicators of cholestasis, because they leak from damaged hepatocellular membranes by lipid peroxidation. Bilirubin is a breakdown product of haem catabolism; indeed, its increase in plasma may be a sign of impaired excretory hepatic functions such as cholestasis (Kuntz &#x00026; Kuntz <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Bocfal EO administration consistently showed a better anticholestatic effect than did DADS administration; these results are in agreement with various reports of anticholestatic effects by the administration of <italic>Brassica</italic> extracts in diverse liver damage animal models. Although polar extracts rich in flavonoids were used in those studies (John <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Rajamurugan et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), Bocfal EO may have similar cholagogue effects, perhaps through activating canalicular membrane transporters to improve the excretion of bile products.</p><p>CT induced a notable increase of the necrosis marker ALT (Hosono-Fukao et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Zhu et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>); however, Bocfal EO and DADS showed antinecrotic properties during the oxidative damage. These results are in accordance with those of various authors who prevented the ALT increase using <italic>Brassica</italic> extracts and DADS as antioxidant treatments (John <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Rajamurugan et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Lee et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Additionally, the inhibition on the nuclear factor NF-&#x003ba;B, with the activation of Nrf2, seems to provoke immunomodulatory effects by diminishing the proinflammatory cytokine TNF-&#x003b1; (Wagner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In this regard, hepatic glycogen is perhaps the main source of energy in an organism and is indicative of metabolism and functionality. Glycogen synthesis and glycogenolysis are affected by TNF-&#x003b1;; therefore, this marker is very sensitive to liver stress (Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Mart&#x000ed;nez et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Interestingly, Bocfal EO treatment completely prevented the CT-induced depletion of stored glycogen, even better than did by DADS.</p><p>Several hepatotoxic chemicals cause liver damage by inducing free radicals that, in turn, provoke oxidative stress, which is defined as a strong imbalance between antioxidant defences and an excessive production of oxidative species. The liver is an important source of free radicals, as these reactive species are metabolic products of exogenous or endogenous antioxidants that involve a variety of enzymatic and non-enzymatic mechanisms, which induce oxidation and electron uncoupling (Zhu et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Bocfal EO and DADS prevented the CT-induced LP; this antioxidant effect was associated with the OPS content in the Bocfal EO as well as to the recognized antioxidant activity of DADS (Lee et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Nevertheless, those results in the liver did not match those of the <italic>in vitro</italic> TBARS assay in the brain, where DADS was not as effective as the mixture with Bocfal EO. These results suggest an influence of the <italic>in vivo</italic> experiment or the tissue-type assessed.</p><p>CAT is an endogenous antioxidant enzyme involved in the elimination of ROS, particularly hydrogen peroxide. CAT activity was significantly augmented by CT and Bocfal EO, while it was lowered by DADS; nevertheless, the treatment with either Bocfal EO or DADS during the CT-induced injury diminished CAT activity elevation. In contrast, most reports have found a CT-induced decrease in the activity of CAT that reflects an impaired antioxidant defence system, whereas the administration of DADS or <italic>Brassica</italic> extracts promotes its recovery and inhibits the LP (Sankhari et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Lee et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). This contradictory result may be explained by a liver that is still functional enough to respond by elevating antioxidant enzymes during oxidative damage, where the whole antioxidant system is not exhausted. In addition, DADS has been reported to significantly inhibit CAT activity (Truong et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), as was detected in the DADS control group.</p><p>A histopathological analysis was performed; despite the hepatoprotective properties demonstrated by the biochemical markers for Bocfal EO and DADS, both substances produced hepatic parenchymal damage. These deleterious effects may be related to the 1&#x02009;mmol/kg dose of Bocfal EO or DADS, which is higher than the majority of pharmacological doses used by others. The LC<sub>50</sub> of DADS is 1&#x02009;mM in hepatocytes. Additionally, garlic fed to rats, cats, dogs and sheep causes haemolytic anaemia along with liver and lung toxicity (Truong et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Thounaojam et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) evaluated the effect of high doses of red cabbage (<italic>B. oleracea</italic> L.) ethanolic extract in mice and found that it caused an elevation of AP and TB, as well as weight loss, in a manner similar to that observed herein. Concerning the adverse effects of <italic>Brassica</italic> in humans, there is only one report of liver toxicity due to excessive broccoli juice drinking (Ekiz et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). It has been assumed that garlic and many other antioxidants (such as OPSs) might act as potent prooxidants when used in high concentrations and, consequently, cause harmful effects (Iciek et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>Bocfal EO or DADS administration resulted in inhibitory effects on the enzyme activities of liver damage markers, particularly ALT, and ALT activity in rats treated with Bocfal EO was even lower during CT-induced injury; the effects on GGTP activity exhibited a similar pattern. These inhibitory properties on the enzymatic liver damage markers may mask adverse hepatic outcomes and mislead the true biochemical diagnosis. OPSs are perhaps capable of either inhibiting the intrinsic enzyme activity or the <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis, considering that diverse OPSs suppress CYP2E1 activity in the rat liver (Melega et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Because GGTP is indispensable for the resynthesis of the most important non-enzymatic endogenous antioxidant in the cell, reduced glutathione (GSH), it is considered an antioxidant enzyme; however, it can also be classified as a prooxidant enzyme, due to the product of GSH hydrolysis, Cys-Gly. For this reason, the inhibition of GGTP activity may lead to a cysteine deficit in the cell and a consequent decline in the level of GSH, as well as to the elimination of a physiological source of oxidative stress (Kwiecien et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0022"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This is the first report regarding the extraction, chemical constituent analysis, and evaluation of the antioxidant and hepatoprotective activities of the EO obtained from Bocfal. Thus, at the right dose, the edible OPSs in white cabbage are suggested as hydrogen sulphide donors that may serve as useful tools for the research of a variety of diseases. In addition, they might be economical and promising drug candidates for restoring endogenous organic sulphur compounds.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to express gratitude to the following individuals: Mrs Vivian Esquivo-Rechy for providing facilities; Brian Byrne, Ph.D. (Natural Advantage, NJ, USA), for supplying DMTS and DMDS; N. Ival&#x000fa; Cacho-Gonz&#x000e1;lez, Ph.D., for identifying taxonomies; Ver&#x000f3;nica Ju&#x000e1;rez-Jaimes, M.Sc., for guiding the preparation of the herbarium specimen (MEXU, Instituto de Biolog&#x000ed;a, UNAM, Mexico); Claudia Rivera-Cerecedo and H&#x000e9;ctor Malag&#x000f3;n-Rivero (Instituto de Fisiolog&#x000ed;a Celular, UNAM, Mexico) for providing the rats; and Alma Lilia Garc&#x000ed;a-Ortiz, Ph.D, for analyzing the GC-FID. The authors thank the Instituto Polit&#x000e9;cnico Nacional (IPN), Mexico, for the financial support (Proyectos SIP 20120526 and 20141449) and M.C.E. Luis Carlos Romero-Quezada for the administrative support.</p></sec><sec id="s0023"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amorati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foti</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valgimigli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Antioxidant activity of essential oils</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>10835</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10847</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24156356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fausto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolkoff</surname><given-names>AW.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year>
<source>The liver: biology and pathobiology</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken (NJ)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year>
<article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buttery</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guadagni</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year>
<article-title>Additional volatile components of cabbage, broccoli, and cauliflower</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>832</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calvo-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morales-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>MG.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year>
. <article-title>Solid-phase microextraction-gas chromatographic-mass spectrometric analysis of garlic oil obtained by hydrodistillation</article-title>. <source>J Chromatogr A</source>. <volume>1036</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15139418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saxton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sams</surname><given-names>CE.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year>
<article-title>Relationship of climate and genotype to seasonal variation in the glucosinolate&#x02013;myrosinase system. I. Glucosinolate content in ten cultivars of <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> grown in fall and spring seasons</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agr</source>. <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>681</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dembiec</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year>
<article-title>Measurement of catalase activity in tissue extracts</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekiz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuksel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kertmen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yuksel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year>
<article-title>Liver toxicity due to broccoli juice</article-title>. <source>Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>. <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>898</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>900</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guedes de Pinho</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valent&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>PB.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>Volatile constituents throughout <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> L. var. <italic>acephala</italic> germination</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>6795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6802</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19606906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-&#x000c1;lvarez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shibayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muriel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>
<article-title>Chronic bile duct obstruction induces changes in plasma and hepatic levels of cytokines and nitric oxide in the rat</article-title>. <source>Exp Toxicol Pathol</source>. <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16617007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hifnawy</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salam</surname><given-names>RMA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rabeh</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aboseada</surname><given-names>MA.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Glucosinolates, glycosidically bound volatiles and antimicrobial activity of <italic>Brassica oleraceae</italic> var. botrytis, (soultany cultivar)</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosono-Fukao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ariga</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>Diallyl trisulfide protects rats from carbon tetrachloride-induced liver injury</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>2252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2256</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iciek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwiecien</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wlodek</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
. <article-title>Biological properties of garlic and garlic-derived organosulfur compounds</article-title>. <source>Environ Mol Mutagen</source>. <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19253339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaeschke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGill</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Models of drug-induced liver injury for evaluation of phytotherapeutics and other natural products</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23353004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>AA.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>
<article-title>Hepatoprotective activity of <italic>Brassica juncea</italic> (L) Czern against carbon tetrachloride induced hepatotoxicity in albino rats</article-title>. <source>Pharmacologyonline</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>621</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>
<article-title>Volatile distribution in garlic (<italic>Allium sativum</italic> L.) by solid phase microextraction (SPME) with different processing conditions</article-title>. <source>Food Sci Biotechnol</source>. <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>782</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuntz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuntz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>
<source>Hepatology: principles and practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Heidelberg, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Medizin Verlag</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwiecien</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iciek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wlodek</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
<article-title>Acceleration of anaerobic cysteine transformations to sulfane sulfur consequent to &#x003b3;-glutamyl transpeptidase inhibition</article-title>. <source>Scientific World J</source>. <volume>2012</volume>:<fpage>253724</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JC.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year>
<article-title>The involvement of Nrf2 in the protective effects of diallyl disulfide on carbon tetrachloride-induced hepatic oxidative damage and inflammatory response in rats</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24246655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1990</year>
<article-title>The glucosinolates and aroma volatiles of green kohlrabi</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry</source>. <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1187</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>FT.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1970</year>
<article-title>Identification of dimethyl trisulfide as a major aroma component of cooked brassicaceous vegetables</article-title>. <source>J Food Sci</source>. <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>543</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melega</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Canistro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnotta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iori</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sapone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paolini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Effect of sprout extract from Tuscan black cabbage on xenobiotic-metabolizing and antioxidant enzymes in rat liver</article-title>. <source>Mutat Res</source>. <volume>751</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23183052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muriel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>Role of free radicals in liver diseases</article-title>. <source>Hepatol Int</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>536</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19941170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohishi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1979</year>
<article-title>Assay for lipid peroxides in animal tissues by thiobarbituric acid reaction</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajamurugan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suyavaran</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaganabathy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramamurthy</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sujatha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thirunavukkarasu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
<article-title><italic>Brassica nigra</italic> plays a remedy role in hepatic and renal damage</article-title>. <source>Pharm Biol</source>. <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1488</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1497</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22978659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#x00160;amec</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salopek-Sondi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year>
<article-title>White cabbage (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> var. <italic>capitata</italic> f. <italic>alba</italic>): botanical, phytochemical and pharmacological overview</article-title>. <source>Phytochem Rev</source>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11101-016-9454-4</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sankhari</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thounaojam</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jadeja</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devkar</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>AV.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
. <article-title>Anthocyanin-rich red cabbage (Brassica oleracea L.) extract attenuates cardiac and hepatic oxidative stress in rats fed an atherogenic diet</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric</source>. <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1688</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1693</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22228433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dayton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muntwyler</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1950</year>
<article-title>The estimation of glycogen with the anthrone reagent</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siess</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Canivenc-Lavier</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suschetet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year>
<article-title>Modification of hepatic drug-metabolizing enzymes in rats treated with alkyl sulfides</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett</source>. <volume>120</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9461037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoewsand</surname><given-names>GS.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year>
<article-title>Bioactive organosulfur phytochemicals in <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> vegetables-a review</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>543</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7797181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thounaojam</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jadeja</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sankhari</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devkar</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>AV.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>
<article-title>Safety evaluations on ethanolic extract of red cabbage (<italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> L.) in mice</article-title>. <source>J Food Sci</source>. <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>T35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>T39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21535729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toohey</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year>
<article-title>Thiosulfoxide (sulfane) sulfur: new chemistry and new regulatory roles in biology</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>. <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>12789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12813</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25153879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hindmarsh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>PJ.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year>
<article-title>The molecular mechanisms of diallyl disulfide and diallyl sulfide induced hepatocyte cytotoxicity</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol Interact</source>. <volume>180</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19428347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valette</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poulain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loiseau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lizzani-Cuvelier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Levieil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Restier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>
<article-title>Volatile constituents from romanesco cauliflower</article-title>. <source>Food Chem</source>. <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Langenhove</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cornelis</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schamp</surname><given-names>NM.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1991</year>
<article-title>Identification of volatiles emitted during the blanching process of Brussels sprouts and cauliflower</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agr</source>. <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>487</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terschluesen</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rimbach</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2013</year>
<article-title>Health promoting effects of brassica-derived phytochemicals: from chemopreventive and anti-inflammatory activities to epigenetic regulation</article-title>. <source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source>. <volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>964539</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24454992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>LY.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year>
<article-title>Allyl sulfides inhibit cell growth of skin cancer cells through induction of DNA damage mediated G2/M arrest and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>7096</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7103</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20459099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year>
<article-title>Oxidative stress and liver disease</article-title>. <source>Hepatol Res</source>. <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>749</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22489668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year>
<article-title>Diallyl trisulfide attenuates carbon tetrachloride-caused liver injury and fibrogenesis and reduces hepatic oxidative stress in rats</article-title>. <source>Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch Pharmacol</source>. <volume>387</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>455</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24557053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>