<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Heat stress indices were fitted based on experiments that indicated that isolate growth and disease on plant material was impaired at temperatures above 30°C 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Werres2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier5" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Davidson1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Brasier et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier5" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> found that 37% of EU1 isolates and 80% of NA1 isolates grew at 30°C, but that neither lineage of isolates grew at 31°C. Similarly, Tooley et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> found that chlamydospores of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> held in moist sand showed a high rate of recovery at 30°C, but at 35°C recovery declined steadily with time, and over a seven-day period there was no recovery of the pathogen at 40°C. Likewise, when Tooley et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> tested recovery of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> from infected 
 <italic>Rhododendron</italic> tissue they found high recoveries at 20 and 30°C after seven days, but at a constant 35°C recoveries declined within two days, and there was no recovery by four days. However, Tooley et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> also found that 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> was able to survive several weeks of maximum temperatures of 31°C and 32°C in a variable temperature growth chamber experiment, designed to represent temperature minima and maxima of an average summer in Lewisburg, Tennessee in the USA. Collectively, the results of these experiments indicate that heat stress (TTHS) for 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> is likely to begin accumulating at or above approximately 31°C. The heat stress accumulation rate (THHS) was therefore set to accumulate at a rate of 0.03 week
 <sup>−1</sup>, to allow for a survival rate of at least 50% of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> under the conditions described by Tooley et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, as those representative of a summer in Lewisburg, TN. A survival rate at or near 100%, as reported by Tooley et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, was not calculated for as the methods used to break potential dormancy of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> in the Tooley et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> study (where dry leaf disks were rehydrated for one hour prior to plating) are not considered likely to occur systematically and regularly under natural field conditions.
</p>
