<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The optimization in this review does not merely focus on drug distribution and release manner but also emphasizes the design of multifunctional materials. Utilizing nanotechnology to realize inhibiting cancer cells and osteoclasts simultaneously is a great optimization and improvable. When metastatic bone destruction occurs, it is not enough to anti-cancer and anti bone resorption, promoting bone regeneration is also important to improve the quality of life. In tissue engineering and regenerative medicine, many implantable biomaterials have been designed with good biocompatibility and osteoconductive ability to promote bone tissue regeneration (Sarigol-Calamak &amp; Hascicek, 
 <xref rid="CIT0105" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Martin &amp; Bettencourt, 
 <xref rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Calcium phosphate (Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), CS (Kozusko et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), collagen (Cruz-Neves et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), hyaluronic acid, nHA (Cruz-Neves et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), polymers (Olthof et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0088" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Sarigol-Calamak &amp; Hascicek, 
 <xref rid="CIT0105" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), metal and some composites (Newman &amp; Benoit, 
 <xref rid="CIT0083" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) were often used to fabricate bionic scaffolds with osteogenesis drugs, factors or even cells carried on, like bone morphogenetic protein-2 (BMP-2) (Holzapfel et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Martin &amp; Bettencourt, 
 <xref rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Olthof et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0088" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). These implanted bone tissue engineering or bone regeneration materials can be explored as multifunctional materials to carry anti-osteolysis drugs or anti-osteolysis drug delivery systems. Multifunctional materials also are characterized by multi drugs and multi delivery systems. The integration of different drugs and different systems (target delivery systems, PTT systems, local delivery systems) can be realized by tactfully designed nanomaterials and novel fabrication nanotechnology. During the treatment of osteolysis, reducing bone pain is another therapy goal. Designed materials should also be tested for their bone pain alleviating ability, such as mechanical allodynia and thermal hyperalgesia test on cancer metastasis model (De Felice et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Wei et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0135" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Zhou, Chen, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0151" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).
</p>
