<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nanofibers of alginates were created by electrospinning in the presence of various synthetic polymers and surfactants [
 <xref rid="B154-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">154</xref>]. The electrospinning process has been used inexpensively by an efficient technique for the production of nanofibers with the use of biopolymers and other organic substances used in medicine and pharmaceuticals [
 <xref rid="B93-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">155</xref>]. This technique is used to create dressings, drug delivery systems and scaffolds in tissue engineering. The electrospinning creates ultrathin fibers, collected in a random set [
 <xref rid="B156-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">156</xref>]. The mats that are created during this process are used as wound dressings, catalytic carriers and nanocomposites with many applications [
 <xref rid="B99-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>]. The versatility of the electrospinning technique is so developed that it allows for its use in drug delivery systems and the creation of poly (lactide-co-glycolide) scaffolds, which allows the permanent release of the drug from nanofibres while maintaining their structure and biological activity [
 <xref rid="B86-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">157</xref>]. Nanofibres have also been used in the chemical field as catalysts, sensors and chemical and physical adsorbents. Still, most popular is the use of unique properties of nanofibers prepared using different biopolymers via electrospinning [
 <xref rid="B158-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">158</xref>]. Several materials have been commercialized under different trademarks such as Coalgan from Brothier Laboratories (France), which is sold as an haemostatic fibers pad for nosebleeds; Algosteril
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> or Sorban
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> are also non-woven dressing absorbing rapidly and retains wound fluid resulting in haemostasis and accelerates wound healing. Alginate based hydrogels were also synthesized and used as novel platform for in situ preparation of metal–organic framework [MOF] [
 <xref rid="B159-nanomaterials-09-00404" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>]. In order to establish the feasibility of the synthesis technique, the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology-1 [HKUST-1] –alginate composite was selected as a model system. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00404-f008" class="xref">Figure 8</xref> shows the schematic for the preparation of the MOF–alginate composite and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nanomaterials-09-00404-f009" class="xref">Figure 9</xref> displays the cross-section backscattered electron images. It was concluded from the study that MOF particles can be incorporated into the alginate substrates and for in situ MOF growth, the metal ion cross-linked alginate hydrogels provided outstanding templates. 
</p>
