<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The traditional usage of MO is generally considered to be well tolerated and safe, as it is assigned to the Food and Drug Administration GRAS (Generally Recognized as Safe) list in the United States. Up until now, no serious adverse effects have been reported following lemon balm usage. Because of insufficient information about lemon balm usage in sensitive populations such as pediatrics or during pregnancy or lactation, theoretically, in these cases it may be marked as possibly unsafe. 
 <italic>Per os</italic> usage of MO has been reported to be well tolerated, with no adverse events when taken at less than 8 weeks. To date, sporadic minor side effects have been reported such as electroencephalographic changes in doses of 1,200 mg, reduced alertness with caution to driving in dose of 900 mg, possible increase of intraocular pressure, thyroid hormone inhibition, palpitations, headache, diarrhea, and vomiting (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Ulbricht et al., 2005</xref>). Increased appetite was also reported as a side effect in a clinical trial investigating MO effects on heart palpitations (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Alijaniha et al., 2015</xref>). On the other hand, topical administration of MO preparations might cause local redness, burning sensation, or irritation. It is considered that MO has no toxic effects on the liver, as proven in cell cultures (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Carocho et al., 2015</xref>). Toxic effects of MO essential oil on the stomach, duodenum, liver, and kidneys have been described when applied in a dose of 1 mg/kg 
 <italic>per os</italic>. The calculated LD50 (median lethal dose) for BALB/c mice is 2.57 g/kg, and this is thought to be moderately toxic for human usage (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Stojanović et al., 2019</xref>). These findings are contrary to the previous study by 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Bounihi et al. (2014)</xref>, which reported absence of toxicity after 2 g/kg MO essential oil of MO.
</p>
