<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Analysis of EOs’ chemical composition in this study revealed that both tested essential oils are in accordance with the requirements prescribed by Ph. Eur. 10 (2020) [
 <xref rid="B38-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] for thymol type of thyme EOs, with thymol ranging from 37 to 55% and carvacrol from 0.5 to 5.5%. According to the pharmacopoeia, the official biological source of 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> EO is only the flowering aerial parts of 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>, 
 <italic>T. zygis</italic>, or a mixture of both species, while 
 <italic>T. serpyllum</italic> is the biological source of 
 <italic>Serpylli herba</italic>. However, the content of thymol in the wild thyme EO is higher (54.17%) than in the common thyme EO (45.22%). Unlike thymol, the content of carvacrol is reversed (3.86% in common thyme and 0.81% in wild thyme). There is a notable difference between the tested EOs in the content of 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene in common thyme (23.83%) and wild thyme (16.66%), but both EOs meet the quality criteria prescribed by the pharmacopoeia (14–28%). On the other hand, the content of γ-terpinene (3.12% for common thyme and 22.18% for wild thyme) does not comply with the pharmacopoeia requirements (4–12%). According to the prescribed content of linalool (1.5–6.5%) and terpinen-4-ol (0.1–2.5%) established by the pharmacopoeia, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> EO meets the requirements related to the chemical composition for thymol type EO (2.55% for linalool and 1.42% for terpinen-4-ol). The results for 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> EO composition are also in line with previously published data [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. However, because, in the wild thyme EO, several chemotypes are described [
 <xref rid="B26-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], this oil could be defined as a thymol chemotype.
</p>
