<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding that fact, the EOs tested in our study showed notable antioxidant potential, similar to the results of other authors [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], although the general comparison of the results obtained in different labs is sometimes difficult because of different experimental conditions and presentation of the results, different methods of antioxidant potential evaluation, and so on. In addition, in the case of various 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> species EOs, the chemical composition plays a significant role in antioxidant effects as thymol and carvacrol are the main compounds responsible for RSC and inhibition of peroxidation of different lipids and biological membranes [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Both thymol and carvacrol demonstrate the ability to achieve a resonantly stable radical structure after donation of hydrogen atom or electrons to ROS, thus neutralizing the cascade of free radical reactions [
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Hence, different chemotypes, especially of different species of wild thyme (
 <italic>T. serpyllum</italic>, 
 <italic>T. marschallianus</italic>, 
 <italic>T. jankae</italic>, 
 <italic>T. longicaulis</italic>, 
 <italic>T. lonidens</italic>, 
 <italic>T. pannonicus,</italic> and so on), can show significantly weaker antioxidant effects [
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. As different plant-derived products have less toxicity and side effects compared with synthetic antioxidants, they can play an important role in the prevention of various diseases and syndromes where reactive oxygen species are involved [
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. They have also found their place as natural preservatives in the pharmaceutical, food, and cosmetic industry [
 <xref rid="B43-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. ROS production is linked with the inflammatory process and is provided by netrophils in milk [
 <xref rid="B46-antibiotics-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].
</p>
