<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">Prepared stimulus sets were shown to members of an extended family group living at Buluhkaduru Outstation. A total of 13 Kune speakers participated in the study, which represents almost all the adult residents at the outstation at the time of data collection. A larger sample size was not possible because the total number of Kune speakers is itself small, and speakers often travel between widely dispersed settlements. Two stimulus sets were used in this study. The first was a set of plant photographs taken from the book Top End Native Plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], which catalogues many common and culturally important plants found at the study site. The second set was audiovisual in nature, and consisted of bird photographs with accompanying recordings of the birds’ calls or songs (if any). Birds were selected on the basis of local occurrence data obtained from the website Atlas of Living Australia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. This ensured that the species represented in the stimulus set could indeed be observed in the study area. Bird calls and songs were obtained from the website Xeno-Canto [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], while pictures were sourced from online databases, such as Avibase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. This approach has been used successfully in previous ethnobiological studies carried out within the context of a language documentation project (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]), and has yielded rich linguistic and cultural information, as well as reproducible results. The plant and bird stimulus sets included approximately 80 and 100 species respectively. It was intended that the stimulus sets be used to investigate naming patterns in multiple language communities of north-central Arnhem Land, and so, species that could be found in both coastal and inland habitats were included in the sets. Therefore, there was no expectation than any single respondent would be able to name all the species in a stimulus set, as at least some of the species would only be found in habitats not normally encountered on his/her traditional lands. Kune speakers, for instance, were not expected to provide names for mangrove plants or coastal birds.
</p>
