<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> was reported to display insect repellent action [
 <xref rid="B132-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. The characteristic odor of the plant makes it essential as an insect repellent and this action is linked to absinthin (sesquiterpene lactone) secretion, which suppresses the growth of neighbouring plants [
 <xref rid="B133-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. In addition to that, the plant can repel the larvae of the insect when applied to cultured media containing these larvae. It has also been applied as a repellent to moths and fleas. Several studies have shown that 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> and its essential oil possess acaricidal [
 <xref rid="B134-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>], insecticidal [
 <xref rid="B135-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>], and repellent properties against flies, fleas, mosquitoes, and ticks [
 <xref rid="B136-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. They showed that ethanolic 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> extract displayed 100% inhibition against cattle tick (
 <italic>Rhipicephalus microplus</italic>) eggs hatching in vitro, proposing that the plant could serve as a substitute to commercially available synthetic acaricides. Consistently, alcoholic 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> extracts exerted high antifeedant activity rate on 
 <italic>Leptinotarsa decemnlineata</italic>, 
 <italic>Rhopalosiphum padi</italic> [
 <xref rid="B138-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> essential oils were reported to cause toxicity to adults of granary weevil 
 <italic>Sitophilus granarius</italic> L. (Coleoptera). Additionally, 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> essential oil exerted toxic effect on adult 
 <italic>R. dominica</italic>, a stored product pest, with an LC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 18.23 µL/L and LC
 <sub>90</sub> value of 41.74 µL/L. The essential oils from 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> showed significant fumigant activity on 
 <italic>S. littoralis</italic> (a furthermost hazard pests of crops) with an LC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 10.59 µL/L and LC
 <sub>90</sub> value of 17.12 µL/L [
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Govindarajan et al. [
 <xref rid="B139-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>] registered the larvicidal action of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> essential oils against 
 <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Culex tritaeniorhynchus</italic>, 
 <italic>Anopheles subpictus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>, 
 <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic>, and 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>. Few pharmacological effects of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> related to infectious diseases are shown in 
 <xref rid="antibiotics-09-00353-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. Some of the mechanisms of action related to these activities are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antibiotics-09-00353-f002">Figure 2</xref>.
</p>
