<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0165">An important requirement in the synthesis of essential oil based nanoemulsion is that the encapsulation system protects the active ingredients from chemical degradation and that the encapsulation process does not alter the bioactivity of the components. Although EOs are complex mixtures, their bioactivity is mainly dependent on a few molecules present at high concentrations. However, the compounds contained at low percentages are useful to enhance the effectiveness. Most of the actually studies that evaluate the functionality of nanoemulsions are conducted in simple model solutions, while the information regarding possible effects of the encapsulation process on the EO chemical components is scarce. For this reason, we evaluate the effect of encapsulation process on EO volatile compounds. GC-MS analysis showed no significant differences between EO and NE profile. Only few studies have evaluated changes on essential oil constituents after encapsulation. 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Donsì et al. (2012)</xref> reported that high-pressure homogenization (HPH) as well as high shear homogenization (HSH), results in decomposition of active constituents of EO particularly p-cymene, terpinenes, carveol, carvacrol and others. During emulsification by HPH there is an intrinsic increase in the temperature of the sample, which must be taken into account, especially when it comes to the production of nanoemulsions incorporating heat-sensitive active compounds (
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Salvia-Trujillo et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Shukat and Relkin (2011)</xref> observed a substantial degradation of α-tocopherol in palm oil nanoemulsions produced with HPH. 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al. (2020)</xref> studied the effect of nanoencapsulation on volatile constituents of Algerian 
 <italic>Origanum glandulosum</italic> Desf. EO that was encapsulated via HSH at 18000 rpm and via HPH. The results reported a significant decrease for carvacrol as the process intensity increased from HSH to HPH and showed that the volatiles profile of oil nanocapsules generated by HSH is still similar to that of the oil and corresponds to the thymol and/or carvacrol chemotype. In the present work, we used a lower homogenization speed than the previous reported works (approximately 8000 rpm for 5 min), only a slight percentage (~2.5%) of pulegone was affected.
</p>
