<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SIRT6 can act as both a cancer promoter and a cancer suppressor. The reduction of SIRT6 expression is linked to the progression of different types of cancers such as colorectal, breast, ovarian, hepatocellular, and lung cancers. It has been exhibited that SIRT6 promotes tumor suppression inhibiting the hypoxia-inducible factor-1α (HIF-1α), which prevents the glycolytic metabolism of cancer cells [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Downregulation of SIRT6 expression has been detected in liver cancer, whereas SIRT6 is found to be overexpressed in chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) in patients with liver cancer and CLL, respectively [
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Besides, SIRT6 modulation has been suggested to play a pivotal role in the tumor microenvironment of various cancers [
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. SIRT6 overexpression has been found to be associated with prostate cancer and skin cancer [
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].Downregulation of the lethal-7 (let-7) family of miRNAs suppresses myc target oncofetal proteins Lin28 and Lin28b, which cause SIRT6 knockdown and contribute to progression and metastasis of mouse and human pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC)[
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. SIRT6 suppression is regulated via the c-Fos pathway in hepatic cancer. Inhibition of histone H3K9 acetylation and nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) activation results in suppression of survivin, and thus c-Fos induces SIRT6. Upregulation of SIRT6 arrests cancer development through survivin’s anti-apoptotic activity [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Studies have also reported tumor-promoting activity of SIRT6. SIRT6 provides its oncogenic effect through chromatin remodeling. Deacetylation of H3K9 by SIRT6 inhibits B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl-2)-associated X protein (Bax) transcription; thus, it increases p53 gene and E2F-1 transcription factor chromatin accessibility, and eventually, apoptosis is inhibited [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Since SIRT6 plays a significant role in tumorigenesis, SIRT6 specific modulators with therapeutic and chemo-preventive potential would be of great interest in pharmacology [
 <xref rid="B50-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
