<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ecological consequences of the invasion of certain non‐native plant species are well‐supported throughout the literature, with direct, negative effects documented on a wide range of native taxa. These impacts occur when invasive plants directly reduce available habitat and survival of native plant species (Vilá et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) or directly affect availability of plant material used by birds and invertebrates for food, shelter, and oviposition (Ballard, Hough‐Goldstein, &amp; Tallamy, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Bultman &amp; DeWitt, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Burghardt &amp; Tallamy, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Heleno, Ceia, Ramos, &amp; Memmott, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Meyer, Schmidt, &amp; Robertson, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Mollot, Pantel, &amp; Romanuk, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Beyond directly impacting both the behavior and density of other taxa, invasive plant species can also cause negative indirect effects mediated through alteration of the behavior and density of other, often herbivorous, species (Vilá et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; White, Wilson, &amp; Clarke, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Nevertheless, there exists an expanding literature detailing both direct and indirect impacts considered positive or beneficial for a species or ecological community resulting from non‐native plant invasion (McCary, Mores, Farfan, &amp; Wise, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Tymkiw, Bowman, &amp; Shriver, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Some invading plant species, often with large and showy inflorescences, can increase floral density and food availability for pollinators throughout the season and potentially at times of reduced floral availability (Davis, Kelly, Maggs, &amp; Stout, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Russo, Nichol, &amp; Shea, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The complex and novel architecture of many invasive plant species can also provide enhanced structure for primary consumers to effectively hide from predators (Dutra, Barnett, Reinhardt, Marquis, &amp; Orrock, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Malo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Contrastingly, changes in plant structure can also directly benefit actively hunting predators (Loomis, Cameron, &amp; Uetz, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) or those that use passive hunting techniques (Dudek, Michlewicz, Dudek, &amp; Tryjanowski, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Several examples exist whereby predator populations are augmented due to the change in plant structure caused by the invading plant species, ultimately causing indirect suppression of plant consumer populations. These aforementioned studies examined impacts of common invasive plant species of the United States (U.S.): 
 <italic>Centaurea maculosa</italic> (spotted knapweed) in the West, 
 <italic>Microstegium vimineum</italic> (Japanese stiltgrass) in the South, and 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (garlic mustard) in the Northeast, respectively. However, these examples focused on pairs of morphologically similar predator species (DeVore &amp; Maerz, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) or on specific predatory functional guilds (Smith‐Ramesh, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) and not on predatory communities of the forest understory as a whole.
</p>
