<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because of rapidly emerging and spreading antibiotic-resistant bacteria, initial treatment of impetigo with topical antibiotics has been discontinued in remote areas in Australia and, instead, intramuscular (IM) benzathine penicillin G (BPG) alongside oral co-trimoxazole syrup (known by the brand names Bactrim and Septrin) are being employed as the current first-line impetigo treatments [
 <xref rid="B22-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The use of oral and injectable antibiotics for uncomplicated impetigo alter systemic levels of host-protective bacteria, and they are also associated with adverse effects (particularly gastrointestinal) [
 <xref rid="B40-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In the long run, given the rapid emergence of community-associated methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (CA-MRSA) in remote areas [
 <xref rid="B67-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], exhausting currently available systemic antibiotics for the treatment of diseases, such as impetigo, can have serious ramifications [
 <xref rid="B40-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Based on a seven-year descriptive study conducted in New South Wales [
 <xref rid="B70-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], 33.4% of Aboriginal children were found to have skin infections with CA-MRSA, indicating that CA-MRSA is a significant public health problem in these settings. According to the 2019 Antimicrobial Use and Resistance in Australia (AURA) report [
 <xref rid="B25-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], about 85–90% of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains are now resistant to penicillin. Further, about 50% of MRSA are resistant to erythromycin and ciprofloxacin, and 15% are resistant to co-trimoxazole, tetracycline and gentamicin. In a report from the Kimberley region (North Western Australia), one of Australia’s most remote areas, MRSA resistance to co-trimoxazole showed an increase from 9% to 18% over a 12-month period, and following this, the local antimicrobial resistance committee recommended removing co-trimoxazole as the first-line oral alternative for these skin infections [
 <xref rid="B69-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Given the rapid emergence of these resistant bacteria to the current topical antibiotics, a post-antibiotic era is fast approaching, requiring alternative means of treatments with an intension to break the cycle, and prevent further resistance.
</p>
