<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">Microsatellite loci enabled the first insights on the demographic dynamics of this introduced wild bee. By better quantifying population genetic structuring, indirect measurements of gene flow revealed striking differences between populations within Europe. As the SSR-GBAS was applied in a relatively early invasion stage before the expected admixture between European populations took place, we were able to find tremendous genetic patterns. This east–west differentiation as well as fine-scale genetic patterns are best explained by multiple colonization events in Middle Europe. Such multiple colonization events can partly explain its invasion success in Europe. Further, it is a possible explanation for its adaptation potential to its new environment. To confidently determine the number of colonization events, future studies with larger sampling from all invaded regions of Europe will be necessary. By implementing genetic landscape modelling, we are planning to estimate the probability of migration between geographic separated populations and to test the degree of connectivity more explicitly. Furthermore, specimens from its native origin and North America will be included to produce a synthetic view of its global invasion patterns and potential. By including North American samples for genetic structure analyses, we will be able to test if European individuals are bridgehead populations, those from a previously-invaded region rather than the native range, as are often found in other hymenopterans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. If the primary exotic habitat contains substantial genetic diversity, it may act as a particularly potent source for another, second translocation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>], making it crucial that we quickly better our understanding of this species ‘ invasive dynamics.
</p>
