<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies were conducted to identify areas of blueberry bush invasions. The first studies were done by [
 <xref rid="B9-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] covering up to 12.5 km
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm31">
   <mrow>
    <msup>
     <mrow/>
     <mn>2</mn>
    </msup>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> with estimations of blueberry bush coverage areas. Another study focusing on the invasive blueberry species was presented by [
 <xref rid="B15-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], studying an area of 4.7 ha, which is nine times smaller than the area that was studied in our work. Reference [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] studied an area of 230 ha and characterised the blueberry invasion. The author conducted 11 days of fieldwork in order to capture the information regarding the cover area of blueberry bushes. The study area is less in our work with 63 ha, but, in comparison to the manual fieldwork, image capturing only took half a day. The pre-processing step needed the longest time, about 4 to 5 h per orthomosaic, since manual annotations were done in the beginning of the work. Therefore, the presented workflow of our study reduces the amount of time for gathering information significantly. The characteristics that were provided by [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] are mainly focused on the blueberry bush cover area, which were 16% of the 230 ha. Other characteristics were provided by general statements about average heights and clustering behaviours. Our study provided height and area measurements for each blueberry bush, which has not been done in previous studies. Based on the orthomosaics, further measures, like hot spot analysis, density calculations, and spread measures, could be performed in order to characterise the blueberry invasion in much more detail than previous studies have shown [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Furthermore, refs. [
 <xref rid="B10-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] stated a high probability of loss of identification during fieldwork due to the density of the bushes in certain areas near former blueberry plantations, which were therefore predominantly investigated. In comparison to the mentioned studies, our work presents an objective grading, a precise cover area and each bush was detected in the captured high-resolution images. This information is essential in order to compare both the invasion and monitoring in different areas.
</p>
