<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The hot plate is one of the oldest and frequently used animal models to quantify “pain-like” behaviors in rodents [
 <xref rid="B53-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Based on the species and strain of rodents used in clinical studies, nearly 12 different behaviors, including grooming, freezing, sniffing, licking, stamping of the legs, leaning, and jumping, have been measured in the hot plate assay [
 <xref rid="B54-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In the present study, hot plate analgesic assay of saffron extracts demonstrated a time-dependent activity. Among all the saffron extracts, SEE exhibited the highest analgesic value in delaying the mean paw licking time (13.50 ± 0.28 s) by suppressing nociception in paws. PEE also delayed the onset time of licking response (11.13 ± 0.35 s). However, CEE and LEE exhibited weak analgesic activity of 22% and 29% at 2 h, respectively. Good analgesic drugs suppress the activity of nociceptors and exhibit the least number of lickings in animals. As per findings, SEE, and PEE thus were found as potent analgesic agents. The maximum analgesic activity of SEE might be due to the presence of carotenoids such as crocetin, crocin, picrocrocin, and safranal, as carotenoids have been reported to suppress the synthesis of prostaglandin synthetase [
 <xref rid="B55-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. This speculation is supported by another study where 0.1 and 0.2 g/kg crocin showed significant anti-edematogenic potential in histamine-induced paw edema in rats [
 <xref rid="B56-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. However, according to Hosseinzadeh and Younesi [
 <xref rid="B48-plants-09-01414" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], aqueous and ethanolic stigma and petal extracts of saffron at any dose exerted no significant analgesic effect in mice. They suggested that the extracts might not act through central mechanisms, although drugs that alter the animal’s motor ability may enhance the licking duration on the hot plate method without affecting the central nervous system.
</p>
