<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">C. maritimum</italic> L. produces a high amount of viable fruits that can germinate without any inconvenience, especially in distilled water [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-07-00092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Nonetheless, despite the fact that this halophyte usually grows near the seawater, seed germination is inhibited when salinities exceed 50 mM NaCl [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-07-00092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-07-00092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. In the natural habitat, sea fennel fruits are always exposed to several ions such as Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>, Mg
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>, Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>, Cl
 <sup class="sup">−</sup>, and SO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>
 <sup class="sup">2−</sup>. Sodium salts adversely affect seeds germination firstly via the osmotic effect; it is not the case that a high germination recovery can be observed if seeds are transferred in distilled water [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-07-00092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Therefore, it is possible to speculate that in nature, although sea fennel seeds remain viable with high salinity conditions, the germination starts at the beginning of the spring, only after salt leaching which is due to the winter precipitations [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-07-00092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Another interesting aspect regarding sea fennel seed germination is the fact that it’s fruits can be considered a dispersal unit [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-07-00092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Both secretory envelope and spongy coat can protect sea fennel seeds from the damage due to potential Na+ and Cl− accumulation. Furthermore, the high floating capacity together with the germination recovery for explaining the long-distance seed dispersal and the consequent plants growth should also be considered [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-07-00092" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
