<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants have continued to play an important role in providing primary healthcare needs across the African region particularly during sudden outbreak of deadly diseases like COVID-19. Emerging technologies, including the mining of plant-derived chemical libraries and application of computational techniques including ligand docking and other methods in computer-aided drug design (CADD), are increasingly deployed in rapidly selecting candidate screening compounds for a fast-tracked drug discovery process particularly during emergency situations like the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic. 
 <italic>In silico</italic> analysis reduces the investigational time-line to identify “hits” and the analysis of their suitability in combating pathogenic diseases and thus shortens the drug discovery pipeline (
 <xref rid="B259" ref-type="bibr">Terstappen and Reggiani, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B212" ref-type="bibr">Pascolutti and Quinn, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B264" ref-type="bibr">Ubani et al., 2020</xref>). Documented hits compounds which have demonstrated interesting 
 <italic>in silico</italic> activities against SARS-CoV-2 and isolated from African plants (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>) include amaranthin 
 <bold>(134)</bold> (
 <italic>Amaranthus tricolor</italic> L.- Amaranthaceae), myricitrin 
 <bold>(32)</bold> (
 <italic>Myrica cerifera</italic> (L.) Small - Myricaceae), isoflavones 
 <bold>(30)</bold> (
 <italic>Psorothamnus arborescens</italic> (A.Gray) Barneby - Fabaceae), nigellicine 
 <bold>(21)</bold>, nigellidine 
 <bold>(22)</bold>, nigellone 
 <bold>(28)</bold>, carvacrol 
 <bold>(24)</bold>, hederin 
 <bold>(25)</bold>, thymol 
 <bold>(26)</bold>, thymoquinone 
 <bold>(27)</bold>, thymohyroquinone 
 <bold>(29</bold>) (
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L.), Calceolarioside B 
 <bold>(135)</bold> (
 <italic>Fraxinus sieboldiana</italic> Blume - Oleaceae), Licoleafol 
 <bold>(137)</bold> (
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza uralensis</italic> Fisch. ex DC - Fabaceae), methyl rosmarinate 
 <bold>(31)</bold> (
 <italic>H. atrorubens</italic> Poit), myricetin 3-O-beta-D glucopyranoside 
 <bold>(136)</bold> (
 <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> L. Kuntze - Theaceae). 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents a full list of these compounds and the plants producing them while 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> presents the chemical structures of the compounds. These 
 <italic>in silico</italic> findings with limited evidence should form the basis for future in-depth 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and clinical studies rather than indiscriminate application of preliminary data which could constitute a public health concern.
</p>
