<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The EO of 
 <italic class="italic">F. vulgare</italic> was purchased from KOS srl (Carmignano, PO, Italy); the EO of 
 <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic>, methyl chavicol type, was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Milan, MI, Italy); the EO of 
 <italic class="italic">P. lentiscus</italic> was purchased from Efit srl (Terni, TR, Italy). The EOs were diluted to 0.5% in HPLC-grade 
 <italic class="italic">n-</italic>hexane and then injected into a gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS) apparatus. Gas chromatography–electron impact mass spectrometry (GC–EIMS) analyses were performed with an Agilent 7890B gas chromatograph (Agilent Technologies Inc., Santa Clara, CA, USA) equipped with an Agilent HP-5MS (Agilent Technologies Inc.) capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm; coating thickness 0.25 μm) and an Agilent 5977B single quadrupole mass detector (Agilent Technologies Inc.). Analytical conditions were as follows: Injector and transfer line temperatures 220 and 240 °C, respectively; oven temperature programmed from 60 to 240 °C at 3 °C/min; carrier gas helium at 1 mL/min; injection of 1 μL (0.5% HPLC grade 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane solution); split ratio 1:25. The acquisition parameters were as follows: Full scan; scan range: 30–300 
 <italic class="italic">m/z</italic>; scan time: 1.0 s. Identification of the constituents was based on a comparison of the retention times with those of the authentic samples, comparing their linear retention indices relative to the series of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hydrocarbons. Computer matching was also used against commercial (NIST 14 and ADAMS) and laboratory-developed mass spectra library built up from pure substances and components of known oils and MS literature data [
 <xref rid="B21-insects-10-00114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-insects-10-00114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-insects-10-00114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-insects-10-00114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-insects-10-00114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-insects-10-00114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>].
</p>
