<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phytochemicals are plant-derived chemicals, and some of these compounds help inhibit cell damage and improve immune function. To date, more than 10,000 species have been identified and they have varying efficacies depending on their type [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Phytochemical compounds are particularly abundant in edible and medicinal crops, such as vegetables and fruits. Representative examples include anthocyanins and carotenoids. 
 <italic>Polygonum multiflorum</italic> contains the anthraquinone compounds chrysophanol, rhein, physcion, and emodin, as well as 2,3,5,4′-tetrahydroxystilbene-2-
 <italic>O</italic>-
 <italic>β</italic>-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucoside (TSG), a glycoside of anthraquinone compounds. TSG compounds are the largest group of phytochemical components in 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Furthermore, antioxidative compounds can be derived from chrysophanol, rhein, physcion, emodin, and TSG. Apart from their antioxidative activities, these compounds have been shown to reduce cholesterol [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and blood sugar [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] levels, have a whitening improvement effect by inhibiting melanin production [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], and reduce oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. They also inhibit microorganisms that cause food poisoning, such as 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-01280" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Therefore, 
 <italic>P. multiflorum</italic> has various beneficial activities and is a potential high value-added medical food material.
</p>
