<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055" class="p">At 12 weeks of age, all rabbits were weighed at the experimental farm. Ten representative rabbits (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 10) from each group were selected for carcass and meat quality analysis representing the average weight and variability of each group. The slaughter procedure was conducted at the Department of Animal and Poultry Production research abattoir, Faculty of Agriculture, South Valley University, Egypt. The animals were humanely slaughtered according to halal slaughter procedure. The procedure involved severing the carotid artery, jugular vein, trachea and oesophagus. The slaughtered rabbits were bled, and then the skin, genitals, urinary bladder, gastrointestinal tract, and the distal part of legs were removed. Carcasses (with head, lungs, liver, kidneys, heart, perirenal and scapular fat) were weighed (warm carcass), then chilled at 4 °C for 24 h in a ventilated room and the chilled carcasses were weighed again. The head, heart, lungs, liver and kidneys were removed from each carcass to obtain the reference carcass, which included meat, bones and fat depots. The internal organs included heart, lungs, liver and kidneys were weighed and the outer shape examined. The carcasses were then cut between the 7th and 8th thoracic vertebra and between the 6th and 7th lumbar vertebra to obtain the fore, mid, and hind parts, which were weighed separately. Also, scapular and perirenal fat was dissected and weighed. The carcass yield, chilled carcass percentage and the ratio of the organs and carcass parts to the chilled carcass weight were calculated as required. The fore, mid, and hind muscle (i.e., meat) of both sides of randomly selected 5 rabbits per experimental group were separated and individually packed in polyethylene bags, sealed, ice-cooled in portable refrigerators and transported to the Department of Food Science and Technology, Faculty of Agriculture, South Valley University, Egypt for meat quality analysis.
</p>
