<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Regeneration of natural forests is a very important ecological process in order to protect biodiversity and ecosystem balance. Autotoxicity is more common in coniferous forests, but some examples of it are also known for deciduous trees and forest plantations [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. An important regulator of stand structure is the autotoxicity of tree allelochemicals [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. The main reason for problems with natural regeneration in forest ecosystems is related to the litter, which falls intensively and can accumulate over years being the source of allelochemicals, particularly phenolics, which penetrate soil after degradation and leachation [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. There are several potential mechanisms to avoid autotoxicity, including modification of allelochemicals, detoxification, sequestration, exudation, and resistance to the molecular target site, but yet there are no examples for the latter method available [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The most common methods are various postproduction modifications, such as glycosylation, methylation, and acylation, which not only reduce their toxicity by blocking reactive groups, but also increase stability and enhance water solubility, thus enabling transportation and/or storage in subcellular compartments [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. The example of such protection in trees is the glycosylation of juglone [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Another method is the sequestering of toxins in vacuoles or in other specialized plant structures, such as trichomes or hairy glands [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. This kind of protection is found in eucalypts: monoterpenes occur in secretory trichomes, and then they are released after volatilization. The detoxication of its own allelochemical is a relatively rare case. It is assumed that it is present in the seedlings of 
 <italic class="italic">Leucaena leucocephala</italic>, which detoxifies mimosine into 3,4-dihydroxypyridine and then converts it into non-toxic metabolites [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The way of tree protection, when tree secrets a compound almost as quickly as it is produced, has also not yet been described. In addition, some inactive allelochemicals released by plants can be converted into active forms after degradation, for example, by soil microbes in some cases [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] or environmental factors (temperature, light, oxygen, etc.), for example, the toxic juglone is produced by oxidation of the non-toxic hydrojuglone.
</p>
