<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Taking into account the widely highlighted significance of the trifluoromethyl group in pharmacologically active compounds and drugs
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1–5</sup>
 </xref>, the search for new non-toxic or low-toxic trifluoromethylated drug candidates is an important goal in current medicinal chemistry. Hence, we recently developed eight new 8-substituted-3-(trifluoromethyl)-7,8-dihydroimidazo[2,1-
 <italic>c</italic>][1,2,4]triazin-4(6
 <italic>H</italic>)-ones
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6–8</sup>
 </xref> (
 <bold>I–VIII</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>) – belonging to innovative antimetabolites that can act as suicide substrates (mechanism-based irreversible inactivators of specific enzymes). They revealed strong antiproliferative effects (which – in the future – may be useful in the treatment of human solid tumours of the breast, cervix and lung) as well as protective effects on erythrocytes exposed to some reactive oxygen species
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6–8</sup>
 </xref>. In addition, it has been observed that they show lipophilicity indices providing 
 <italic>inter alia</italic> an optimal intestinal absorption, an effective permeability and a binding with albumin in human serum
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>. Most of the title trifluoromethylated molecules have been shown to possess stronger anticancer activities and better selectivity indices than that of pemetrexed (a clinically approved anticancer agent, belonging to the class of folate antimetabolites). In addition, three compounds of this novel class – containing the 
 <italic>ortho-</italic>methyl
 <italic>, ortho-</italic>methoxy and 
 <italic>ortho-</italic>chloro substituent at the phenyl moiety (
 <bold>II</bold>, 
 <bold>IV</bold> and 
 <bold>V</bold>, respectively) – proved to be the most selective, displaying 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> less toxic effects to normal cells than pemetrexed
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>. Therefore, a whole set of these pharmacologically important and bioavailable molecules
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6–8</sup>
 </xref> – with the anticipated resistance to metabolic deamination
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> and bearing the valuable trifluoromethyl group (
 <italic>inter alia</italic> resistant to 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> oxidation
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>) – seems to be the most appropriate for further 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies.
</p>
