<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Extensive previous research exists on different varieties and cultivars of sweet basil under the influence of beneficial fungi such as AMF, with respect to the biosynthesis and composition of essential oils, and the generation of biomass and plant fitness (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Copetta et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Toussaint et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zuccarini and Okurowska, 2008</xref>). AMF are particularly important to improve the quality of medicinal plants such as sweet basil. The symbionts can be used to enhance nutrient uptake and alter secondary metabolite content (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Harrier, 2001</xref>). The AM fungus 
 <italic class="italic">Rhizophagus irregularis</italic> (formerly known as 
 <italic class="italic">Glomus intraradices</italic> (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Krüger et al., 2012</xref>)) is widely used in research on AM symbiosis, in particular on how it supports plant fitness (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Smith and Read, 2008</xref>). Going one step further, 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Battini et al. (2016)</xref> described the impact of dual inoculation with AMF and its associated bacteria and found an improvement of nutraceutical value of sweet basil. Nevertheless, little research has been initiated on the impact of beneficial fungi on sweet basil under heavy metal stress. However many investigations of the responses of other plants to heavy metal stress inoculated with AMF exist and different plant mechanisms, including the role of mycorrhizal fungi for heavy metal tolerance are surveyed by 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hall (2002)</xref>. 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ingle et al. (2017)</xref> showed that AMF play an important role in the alleviation of cadmium stress in chickpea plants. In sweet basil, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prasad et al. (2011)</xref> discovered that 
 <italic class="italic">R. irregularis</italic> enhance the metal concentration in shoot tissues grown in soil with a low dose of metals, whereas this effect was reciprocal in soil with a high amount of heavy metals.
</p>
