<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In fish and fish oils, LC omega-3 PUFAs are mainly found as triacylglycerides and free fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B167-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">168</xref>]. In Krill oil phospholipids are also an important fraction of these fatty acids (30–65% of EPA and DHA), mainly phosphatidylcholine [
 <xref rid="B167-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>,
 <xref rid="B169-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">169</xref>,
 <xref rid="B170-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">170</xref>,
 <xref rid="B171-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">171</xref>]. EPA and DHA represent approximately 18% and 12%, respectively, of the content of naturally occurring fish oils [
 <xref rid="B167-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>]. However, due to the transesterification process, oil blends often contain much more of both EPA and DHA. This process is related to the substitution of the removed glycerol backbone with ethanol, resulting in the formation of ethylesters (EE), which can then be converted to re-esterified TG (rTG)-ethanol is enzymatically removed, resulting in free fatty acids being released, then attached by enzymes back to the glycerol backbone [
 <xref rid="B167-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">168</xref>]. An example of a drug in which the content of EPA (DHA) is increased as a result of transesterification is Lovaza [
 <xref rid="B168-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B172-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">172</xref>]. Another method to increase the content of EPA and DHA has been used in Epanova. Glycerol is removed and replaced with a hydrogen atom, which, in combination with the released fatty acid, forms a carboxylic acid. Ethylesters (of which Lovaza is composed) require the hydrolysis of the ester bond by pancreatic lipase before they release the free fatty acids that can be absorbed in the small intestine. This step is not required by the carboxylic acids. Interestingly, EPA and DHA-EE are also absorbed unchanged. However, this form accounts for &lt; 1% of the total pool of EPA and DHA in circulation after ingestion of omega-3 acids EE [
 <xref rid="B168-nutrients-10-01662" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">168</xref>]. 
</p>
