<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>C. erythraea</italic> is relatively easily manipulated in the in vitro culture, where it can even complete its life cycle. Centaury’s manageability and developmental plasticity in vitro made it not only the most investigated species of the 
 <italic>Centaurium</italic> genus but an emerging model in plant developmental biology. The diversity of morphogenetic paths that 
 <italic>C. erythraea</italic> can undergo in vitro has been compiled recently [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The vigorous morphogenic potential of the explants favors the use of centaury for genetic transformations [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], interspecific hybridization in vitro [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], functional studies on secondary metabolite synthesis in vitro [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and stress physiology studies [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Overall, different aspects of 
 <italic>C. erythraea’s</italic> in vitro development, physiology, pharmacology, and ecology have been studied for over20 years at the Department for Plant Physiology, Institute for Biological Research “Siniša Stanković”, University of Belgrade, resulting in 38 journal papers, 8 book chapters, and 9 masters and doctoral theses. Similarities and differences between two in vitro systems for the induction of SE in centaury that have been extensively studied in our lab—spontaneous DSE from root culture and induced ISE from leaf explants—are the focus of this review. A newly developed system for secondary and cyclic SE is also described [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00070" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and will be submitted as an accompanying article in this issue.
</p>
