<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">While data composition did not have a significant impact on model performance, it did affect model area estimates. The area of predicted suitable habitat varied particularly under the warmest climate conditions (e.g., 2070s for both RCP 6.0 and 8.5, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). For example, among the 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> models, the difference between data set source was relatively smaller under current climate conditions (maximum 33,108 km
 <sup>2</sup>, minimum 24,055 km
 <sup>2</sup>) compared to the warmest scenario (maximum 129,630 km
 <sup>2</sup>, minimum 44,534 km
 <sup>2</sup>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). This may reflect the occurrence data used to train models for this species; private and other non-public data make up a large proportion (~ 40%) of all available occurrence points for 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Supplemental Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Private and other non-public data make up a similarly large portion (~ 44%) of occurrence data for 
 <italic>R. multiflora</italic>, which also demonstrates apparent differences between models constructed using public data only and those trained using public + private or all available data (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). These differences may be due to the large proportion of non-public occurrence data for these species having a different distribution pattern or a varying amount of sampling bias relative to public data (Supplemental Figs. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>). These results may suggest that differences in model predictions which may be relatively minor under contemporary environmental conditions could become more pronounced if projections are made for changing environmental conditions. This can be a concern because, as demonstrated here, there may be species for which much of the available spatial data is scattered across different sources, some of which may be from public agencies, ecological professionals, or herbaria, but some may come from volunteer citizen groups, private companies, the general public, or may even be listed in a database but have unattributed sourcing. We find that models constructed with different subsets of these data can yield the same broad, overall result (i.e., increase or decrease in predicted suitable habitat over time and climate scenarios), though the magnitude and specific areal predictions may vary (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).
</p>
