<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">The models produced here performed well by all available metrics (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), demonstrating good capacity for prediction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup>. There are, however, limitations inherent to species distribution modeling and making projections under future climate scenarios. While distribution modeling is generally performed using data from the realized niche of a species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, factors important to shaping the realized niche, particularly biotic interactions and population dynamics, are not considered in standard species distribution modeling approaches. Moreover, because the four species we analyzed are exotic invasives, the spatial data available for model construction may not reflect equilibrium range limits
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>
 </sup>; there is, however, a growing set of literature demonstrating the utility of distribution modeling approaches for invasive species ecology and management despite this concern
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>
 </sup>. Another important caveat is that this study models the distribution of these four invasive plants using regional occurrence data and does not incorporate data from the species’ native range or non-regional invaded range. This was done because Minnesota represents a leading edge of the invasive range for each of these species, and in working with local managers, we were interested in identifying habitats similar to those already invaded in Minnesota. We were particularly interested in locally-relevant habitats following several recent studies demonstrating that local adaptations and niche shifts may be more common than previously thought among invasive species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>
 </sup>. A limitation of this approach, however, is that if these species exhibit realized niche conservatism, we may be underestimating total suitable habitat.
</p>
