<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Soybean (
 <italic class="italic">Glycine max</italic> (L.)) seed protein content is 35–50% of its total dry weight and is a major source of protein in the human diet and for animal nutrition. Soybean protein also has a well-balanced amino acid profile and is rich in many essential amino acids. Soybean meal has been used extensively to make popular food products such as tofu, soy milk, soybean paste (miso), green soybeans (edamame), boiled beans (nimame), fermented soybeans (natto), soy sauce (shoyu), soybean sprouts (moyashi), and roasted soybean flour (kinako). Soybean consumption has been limited in the western world due to the beany flavor present in soy meal products. Enzymatic oxidation of linoleic acid and linolenic acid by lipoxygenase genes (Lox) is reported as a major cause of the beany flavor [
 <xref rid="B1-biosensors-09-00066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-biosensors-09-00066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>], and in soybeans there are three separate genes, Lox1, Lox2 and Lox3 controlling this trait [
 <xref rid="B2-biosensors-09-00066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Hexanal is commonly associated with the grassy flavor; hexanol; 1-octen-3-ol; 1-octen-3-one; 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>,
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2,4-decadienal; and 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>,
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-2,4-nonadienal are other aromatic compounds linked with the beany taste in soy meal products [
 <xref rid="B3-biosensors-09-00066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Odor compounds of soybean products depend on the soybean cultivars and can change in each variety depending on growing season, storage conditions and processing technologies. Boiling the seeds at 100 °C deactivates the lipoxygenase enzymes and is the common method used for reducing the beany flavor. Breeding soybean lines with reduced beany flavor is another approach that can be used for minimizing the off-flavors in soybeans. In order to establish such breeding programs, establishing a reliable and fast screening method for testing beany flavor is necessary. Plant volatile compounds such as beany flavor are overlooked in plant phenotyping. Novel molecular techniques and marker assisted breeding can be used to map the QTLs controlling these traits and find the loci/genetic mechanisms regulating these compounds which can then be exploited for developing soybean lines with reduced off-flavor traits. 
</p>
