<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various studies investigated compositions and biological activity of essential oils and presented valuable results, which encourages the development of products with them. The isolation yield and chemical composition of the essential oils depend on many factors; therefore biological activity can vary. Thyme essential oil can contain 36–55% of thymol. Thyme essential oil has several chemotypes named according to the major compound: thymol, carvacrol, terpineol, and linalool. The concentration of thymol in Romanian thyme essential oil was 47.59% and its activity against
  <span class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Salmonella typhimurium</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Escherichia coli</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Klebsiella pneumoniae</span>,
  <span class="italic"> Enterococcus faecalis</span>, and
  <span class="italic"> Candida albicans</span> was observed at concentrations from 5 to 20 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL of the essential oil [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>]. Iranian thyme essential oil had 54.14% of thymol and it inhibited
  <span class="italic"> Candida albicans</span> at 0.1–20 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL of the essential oil [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. Other researches have detected effective MIC to be 4 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL of essential oil containing 47.9% of thymol [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>] and 2.4 mg/mL of essential oil containing 47.2% of thymol [
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>]. Essential oil containing 70.3% of carvacrol showed 0.32 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL MIC against
  <span class="italic"> Candida albicans </span>[
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>]. Antimicrobial activity of this study was determined for 0.05–0.30% of essential oil containing oleogel, while concentration of thymol was 9.6 mg/mL and that of carvacrol was 0.07 mg/mL. Thyme essential oil is convenient to insert in oil medium; therefore a lipophilic gel was formulated. Technology process of oleogels is simple; system does not contain water; its physical, microbiological, and chemical stability is much more as compared to conventional topical bases; the lipids of oleogels support skin hydration by reducing transepidermal water loss [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. Despite the convenience of technology, the amount of thymol decreased by 30% and it can be related to the compound volatility or other investigation aspects in future. 0.1% concentration of thyme essential oil was chosen as active substance regarding the above-mentioned aspects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the modeling of oleogel, the colloidal silica performed gelators role. The liquid paraffin and olive oil were mixed to compose mineral and herbal oil mixture for the oleogel formulation. The response surface central composite design was applied in order to formulate optimal composition of preparation and to investigate the relationship between ingredients and texture analysis. The influence of concentration of colloidal silica on textural parameters including firmness, cohesiveness, and consistency was found to be significant (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05), except on index of viscosity (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05). Previous studies of other researches presented high correlation between instrumental analysis and sensory evaluation of texture attributes of various skin care products [
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>, 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. Oleogels have a lot of valuable properties for skin care, but texture characteristics should be acceptable for the consumers as well. Oleogel with thyme essential oil can be recommended as a skin care product with general skin protection purposes and as a natural antiseptic with pharmaceutical application.
 </p>
</sec>
