<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interestingly, the strength and direction of PSFs may change during succession (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Jing et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al., 2018</xref>). The early-successional plants are generally fast growing and poorly defend against natural enemies, tend to have negative PSFs by its species-specific pathogens. Contrastingly, late-successional plants tend to more depend on mycorrhizal associations and have neutral to positive PSFs (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Kardol et al., 2006</xref>). Alternatively, negative feedbacks may allow for early-successional species rather than late-successional species to coexist in early-successional plant communities as a result of the suppression of dominant species. On the contrary, our findings suggested that the late-successional non-mycorrhizal species (i.e., 
 <italic>H. cochinchinensis</italic>) had consistent negative conspecific PSFs [i.e., log (Con/Heter)] and the highest survival rates in 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plantations since planting, whereas the early-successional NF plants had consistent positive conspecific PSFs and the lowest survival rates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The importance of different mycorrhizal types for increasing plant diversity is conventionally linked to the complementary use of soil resources such as soil N and P (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al., 2018</xref>). Mixed plantations of 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> and NF trees is considered to enhance stand productivity by increase soil carbon and nitrogen pool (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Santos et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2019</xref>). We found that there was no significant difference on AN content in the species-specific soil of nine focal species. However, the content of P was relatively low in 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> soil (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). Soil P is the key limiting nutrient for plant growth in both tropical and subtropical forests (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Condit et al., 2013</xref>). It also has a substantial impact on limiting 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> seedling growth in natural forest soil (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Tng et al., 2014</xref>). Mycorrhizal association is an important strategies to enhance P acquisition by plants (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Read, 2008</xref>). The variable pattern of AM and EM plants when inoculated with the soil community from different mycorrhizal types may increase plant diversity. Our previous study demonstrated that AM symbiosis can promote positive effects for native tree growth by counteracting the allelopathic inhibition of 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Qin and Yu, 2019</xref>). Interestingly, non-mycorrhizal species survived best in the 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plantation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). It has been demonstrated that non-mycorrhizal plants, such as 
 <italic>Proteaceae</italic>, which may release large amounts of nutrient-mobilizing exudates from their cluster roots, tend to be common in a P-impoverished habitat (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Lambers et al., 2006</xref>). We speculated that non-mycorrhizal plants had more efficient P acquisition due to their specialized cluster roots partitioning of soil P with other mycorrhizal plants.
</p>
