<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-antioxidants-07-00006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Almond is the most important tree nut crop in terms of commercial production [
  <a rid="B1-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-antioxidants-07-00006">1</a>]. An adaptation to harsh climates combined with an ability to develop a deep and extensive root system has allowed almond to exploit a wide range of ecological niches. Almond is well-adapted to the Mediterranean climate, characterized by mild winters and dry, hot summers. This adaptation has led to early bloom and rapid early shoot growth because of the low chilling requirements of almond. Almond also shows high tolerance to summer drought and heat. Almond has traditionally been the earliest temperate fruit tree crop to bloom, which limited growing to areas relatively free from spring frosts before the release of late-blooming cultivars by different breeding programs, since frosts at bloom or early fruit development can reduce, and even completely nullify, the crop. Since almond is naturally self-incompatible, it often requires cross-pollination, which further acts to promote genetic variability and adaptability to diverse environments [
  <a rid="B2-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-antioxidants-07-00006">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The edible part of the almond nut is the kernel, considered an important food crop with a high nutritional and medicinal value. The oldest and most extensive medical system that first recorded the health uses for almonds derives from ancient Greeks and then the Persians, and later in traditional Chinese medicine and Indian Ayurvedic medicine [
  <a rid="B3-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-antioxidants-07-00006">3</a>]. From medieval times to the 18th century, almond nuts were a source of substitute “milk” [
  <a rid="B4-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-antioxidants-07-00006">4</a>], and also it was used as thickener before starch was “discovered” [
  <a rid="B3-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-antioxidants-07-00006">3</a>]. Almond consumption has almost doubled in the last 20 years [
  <a rid="B5-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-antioxidants-07-00006">5</a>], a fact that highlights how this consumption has evolved from a convenient snack food and component of a high number of confectioneries, to an important food which is increasingly recognized as essential for maintaining and increasing human health. Recent nutritional and medical studies have associated the regular consumption of almonds with a wide range of health benefits, including protection from cancer [
  <a rid="B6-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-antioxidants-07-00006">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-antioxidants-07-00006">7</a>], obesity [
  <a rid="B8-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-antioxidants-07-00006">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-antioxidants-07-00006">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-antioxidants-07-00006">10</a>], diabetes [
  <a rid="B11-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-antioxidants-07-00006">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-antioxidants-07-00006">12</a>], and heart diseases [
  <a rid="B13-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-antioxidants-07-00006">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-antioxidants-07-00006">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-antioxidants-07-00006">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-antioxidants-07-00006">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-antioxidants-07-00006">17</a>]. Almond kernels may be consumed in many different ways, blanched or unblanched, raw or combined, and/or mixed with other nuts. They can also be transformed to produce marzipan, nougat, almond milk, and almond flour, incorporated in many pastries and ice creams. Almonds may also be combined in other products and gastronomic specialties [
  <a rid="B18-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-antioxidants-07-00006">18</a>]. The high nutritive value of almond kernels is mainly due to their high lipid content. This lipid fraction, even constituting an important source of calories, does not contribute to cholesterol formation because of their high level of unsaturated fatty acids, mainly mono-unsaturated fatty acids [
  <a rid="B19-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-antioxidants-07-00006">19</a>]. Although almond kernels are high in energy, humans compensate their effect with their high satiety value [
  <a rid="B20-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-antioxidants-07-00006">20</a>]. The absorption of energy from almond kernels is rather inefficient, having been suggested that their chronic consumption may raise resting energy expenditure [
  <a rid="B21-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-antioxidants-07-00006">21</a>]. Acute and longer-term almond ingestion may help in regulating body weight [
  <a rid="B17-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-antioxidants-07-00006">17</a>], modulating fluctuations of blood glucose [
  <a rid="B22-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-antioxidants-07-00006">22</a>], total low density/high density lipoprotein cholesterol ratio, and triglycerides [
  <a rid="B23-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-antioxidants-07-00006">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Almond kernel quality must be high in order to fulfill not only the industry requirements, but also to be attractive for the consumers [
  <a rid="B24-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-antioxidants-07-00006">24</a>]. Until recently only the kernel physical traits were considered when trying to establish almond quality [
  <a rid="B18-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-antioxidants-07-00006">18</a>], but the kernel chemical composition appears to be essential when establishing the best raw material for the different industrial applications and the high diversity of almond confectioneries [
  <a rid="B24-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-antioxidants-07-00006">24</a>]. In view of the high lipid fraction in the almond kernel, the quality of the almond oil is considered as the most important feature in the evaluation of almond quality. Different parameters related to the lipid fraction have been suggested for quality evaluation of the almond kernels, such as the amount of oil content in the kernel (fat percentage over the kernel dry weight), the percentage of oleic acid of the total fatty acids, the ratio of the percentages of oleic/linoleic acids (O/L), and, especially, the tocopherol concentration in the almond oil [
  <a rid="B24-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-antioxidants-07-00006">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-antioxidants-07-00006">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early reviews on the composition of the almond nuts [
  <a rid="B18-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-antioxidants-07-00006">18</a>,
  <a rid="B26-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-antioxidants-07-00006">26</a>] did not include tocopherols as an important component of almond kernels. More recently tocopherols were already included in several reviews [
  <a rid="B27-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-antioxidants-07-00006">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-antioxidants-07-00006">28</a>], but most of them were primarily descriptive without attempts to assess quality, particularly as it relates not only to industrial requirements, but also to breeding goals and approaches. Extensive variability in the chemical composition has been demonstrated among cultivars; additionally the importance of differences in geographical origins, as well as climatic and growing conditions have also been demonstrated. Despite this extensive information, little is known concerning the genetic control and inheritance of biochemical components of almond quality. For all these reasons, this review summarizes the current knowledge of the almond kernel tocopherol composition and factors affecting its variability.
 </p>
</sec>
