<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It has been estimated that around 70 million tons of lignin in the paper-making industry are available per year [
 <xref rid="B31-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. However, only 2% of it is processed and utilized as lignin, the rest is added into fuels [
 <xref rid="B53-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Commercially available lignin obtained from industrial delignification methods is called technical lignin (
 <xref rid="polymers-11-00751-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). One main source of technical lignin is provided by the paper-making industry with two major lignins: Kraft lignin and lignosulfonates [
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Kraft lignin (KL) constitutes about 85% of total world lignin production, but lignosulfonates are the most important commercially available lignin whose yield is approximately 1 Mt yr1 [
 <xref rid="B53-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. The category comprises almost the total market of commercially available lignin [
 <xref rid="B71-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. The second main lignin source is mainly related to the soda pulping process and Organosolv pulping processes. The category is closer to the native structure of lignin because it is sulfur-free. Today, the soda process is utilized primarily to extract cellulose from low lignin content of non-wood crops such as wheat straw, bagasse, hemp, kenaf or sisal. However, it is generally hard to recover soda lignin through centrifugation or filtration due to its high content of carboxylic groups arising from aliphatic hydroxy group oxidation. This causes lignin to be highly hydrophilic and renders lignin a potential dispersant. Organosolv lignin is a less modified lignin. The homogeneity of Organosolv lignin is higher than that of lignosulphonates or KL. Organosolv lignin has the lowest molecular weights among the technical lignin and can be dissolved in certain solvents, which facilitates their further processing [
 <xref rid="B72-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>]. In addition, there is ionic liquid lignin, steam explosion lignin, enzyme lignin etc. [
 <xref rid="B73-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. Since lignins originate from different sources and separation processes, they differ from each other in terms of chemical structure, composition, and reactivity to a significant extent. As a result, each lignin type needs to be considered individually [
 <xref rid="B72-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>]. The first proportion of this section mainly covers the direct use of lignin with starch, protein, cellulose, PLA and PHB in bioplastics. In the second part, the field of modified lignin reinforced bioplastics is addressed.
</p>
