<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Non-pharmaceutical strategies such as zinc, vitamin C, lysine, and a diet low in arginine have shown some beneficial effects for managing HSV infections, but results are modest and inconsistent.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr5-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr17-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr18-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr19-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr20-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr21-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 </sup> In 2 studies, the application of a zinc-containing cream for treatment of herpes labialis outbreaks was found to modestly reduce severity of associated symptoms and healing time.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr5-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, topical treatment with a strong ascorbic acid-containing solution was found to shorten the persistence of scabs caused by HSV by 2.5 days.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr17-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 </sup> An older study found herpes labialis outbreaks to be cleared in 4.2 days on average after oral administration of a water-soluble bioflavonoid-ascorbic acid complex.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr18-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup> More recently, a pilot study used an oral combination of pine cone lignin and ascorbic acid to treat active HSV-1 lesions and found subjects did not develop characteristic lesions when treatment was initiated within the first 48 hours of symptoms.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr19-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> If treatment was initiated later, subjects reported a reduction in symptoms and healing time compared to previous outbreaks.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr19-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> These studies shed light on the idea that combination therapies for managing HSV infections could be more effective than single therapies.
</p>
