<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The root and shoot extracts are effective in treating a broad range of diseases caused by Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Salep was found to be highly effective against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Shigella flexinerai,</italic> which often show resistance to synthetic medicines [
 <xref rid="B82-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Different extracts of 
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> prepared with petrol, ether, chloroform, methanol, and water were tested against five different bacteria for the determination of zone of inhibition (ZOI) and minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) [
 <xref rid="B83-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Petroleum ether extract and chloroform extract of the aerial part and methanolic extract of the rhizome of 
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> showed significant activity against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli.</italic> The chloroform extract showed the best inhibitory action against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, while these extracts show similar effects for 
 <italic>Shigella flexinerai</italic>. The results indicate that the rhizome part is more effective than the aerial parts against all tested organisms. Besides this, 
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> extract exhibits greater ZOI than ciprofloxacin against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. 
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> exerts equal effect to that of norfloxacin for 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. For 
 <italic>E. coli,</italic> the ZOI of the aerial part of 
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> was found to be almost equal to ciprofloxacin. For 
 <italic>S. flexinerai</italic>, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa,</italic> and 
 <italic>B. subtilis,</italic> the ZOI is equal for tuber extract and ciprofloxacin [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The antibacterial activity of root and shoot ethanol and methanolic extracts of 
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> against 
 <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> showed MIC at lower values [
 <xref rid="B84-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Its ability to exert an effect that is comparable to the available regimes of medicines reflects its potential for use as effective antibacterial agent.
</p>
