<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Endophytes, especially those that are found from ethnopharmacologically noteworthy medicinal plants have attracted attention due to their diverse bioactive metabolites of pharmacological importance.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">This study aimed at isolating endophytic bacterium from the leaves of 
   <italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> CIX1 for its bioactive metabolites. The endophytic isolates were identified by 16S rRNA sequence and investigated for antibiotic sensitivity using different antibiotics. The secondary metabolites were evaluated for antibacterial activity against four bacterial strains. The 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and 2, 2′-azinobis (3- ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) (ABTS) methods were used to assess their scavenging activities. The chemical components were analysed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">Out of 13 isolates, Isolate 1 was identified as 
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> CP043328.1. It was resistant to clindamycin, ertapenem, penicillin G, amoxicillin, cephalothin and kanamycin but sensitive to imipenem, meropenem, and gentamycin. Its extract demonstrated antibacterial activity with minimum inhibitory concentration value of 0.098 against 
   <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102) and 
   <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925) and 0.391 mg/ml against 
   <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) and 
   <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic> (ATCC 25933). The extract revealed DPPH and ABTS scavenging activities with half maximal inhibitory concentration value of 0.650 mg/ml and 0.15 mg/ml, respectively. The GC-MS revealed a total of 15 compounds with diisooctyl phthalate (50.51%) and [1, 2, 4] oxadiazole, 5-benzyl-3 (10.44%) as major components.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4">
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP043328.1 produced secondary metabolites with antibacterial and antioxidant activities.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
