<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Malaria, a widespread disease in tropical and subtropical regions (including much of sub-Saharan Africa, Asia, and the Americas), can cause symptoms that include fever, headache, vomiting, and even progress to coma or death [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. As the World Health Organization (WHO) estimated, there were 216 million documented cases and more than 445,000 deaths from malaria in 2016 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. As a mosquito-borne infectious disease, malaria can be caused by a bite from an infected mosquito, which can introduce the malaria parasites into the circulatory system of the human and ultimately to the liver, where they mature and reproduce [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among mosquitoes, 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles</span> is the only vector of human malaria [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>] and, of these, 30–40 species commonly transmit parasites of the genus 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles anthropophagus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles sinensis</span> have been chosen as the test target mosquito species in this research, because they are rife and harmful in China. The mosquito 
  <span class="italic">An. sinensis</span> is a member of the 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles hyrcanus</span> group, distinguished from other series by the presence of pale bands (usually four) on the palpi and a tuft of dark scales on the clypeus on each side. 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles anthropophagus</span> is a major vector in central China, able to spread malaria 18–20 times better than 
  <span class="italic">An. sinensis</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. The larvae of 
  <span class="italic">An. anthropophagus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">An. sinensis</span> live on the surface of water. Compared to adults, the ability of larvae to escape the insecticide is limited, so the time from larvae to adult is an important period to control mosquitoes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, mosquito larval control is carried out by conventional synthetic insecticides, which have high efficiency and low cost. Their efficacy may decay gradually because mosquitoes develop resistance against insecticides [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. By contrast, plant essential oils, often obtained from the plant by steam distillation or hydrodistillation, constitute a rich source of bioactive compounds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>], and have emerged as a good alternative larvicidal or adulticidal agents with fewer insect resistance problems [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Biodegradable and nontoxic, they can be used as an eco-friendly tool as well as an economical agent in vector control [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum acanthopodium</span> is a shrub or small tree in the 
  <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum</span> genus of 
  <span class="italic">Citrus</span> family, native to southern China, Bangladesh, Bhutan, northern India, Nepal, Laos, Burma, northern Thailand Vietnam, Indonesia, and Peninsular Malaysia. It has 5–13 alternate leaves with serrated edge (3–8 cm long and 1–2 cm wide) and axillary inflorescences with densely globose clusters of unisexual flowers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Much like the closely related 
  <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum piperitum</span>, it has similar tongue-numbing characteristic seed pericarps, which are often used as spices in cooking, and traditional Chinese medicine reported great effect on contraception, relieving pain and killing parasites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Additionally, the hydrodistilled essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum acanthopodium</span>, with many active ingredients, is a novel agent with special effect. In the present study, the chemical composition of the essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum acanthopodium</span> was determined and its larvicidal activity was evaluated against 
  <span class="italic">An. anthropophagus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">An. sinensis</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
