<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the South of France, fennel is an insect-pollinated aromatic plant of great economic interest. It is largely cultivated for its seeds, which are the richest part of the plant regarding the load in volatile aromatic compounds. Among them, 
 <italic>trans</italic>-anethole, a monoterpene with an anise flavor, is the main constituent of the essential oil extracted from fennel fruits [
 <xref rid="B13-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. To our knowledge, few studies have described the flower-visitor community of fennel, and the results arising from the literature are widely heterogeneous. For example, as most papers present the managed honeybee 
 <italic>Apis</italic> as the main fennel pollinator [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], a small part of the literature showed a striking importance of wild pollinators in fennel reproduction [
 <xref rid="B20-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Among those, few authors explored the importance of these pollinators for the yield of fennel crops [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and most of these studies mainly relied on the seed set as the yield measurement. Salami’s study [
 <xref rid="B13-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] is the only one which attempted to link 
 <italic>trans</italic>-anethole production and pollination, yet it considered only self- vs. cross- pollination with no regard for phytometabolite variations according to insects’ abundance and richness, or the structure of the surrounding habitats.
</p>
