<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antidiabetic or antihyperglycaemic effects of ASLs and their constituents have been studied in animal models. Panda and Kar [
 <xref rid="B49-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] isolated quercetin-3-O-glucoside (Q3G) from ASL, evaluated its antidiabetic potential in alloxan-induced diabetic rats, and observed that Q3G significantly improved insulin secretion and reduced the level of glucose in the blood. The authors also observed an increase in antioxidant enzyme activity, such as superoxide dismutase (SOD) and catalase (CAT), in renal and hepatic cells. Ranjana and Tripathi [
 <xref rid="B53-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] studied the antidiabetic properties of different extracts of ASL and found that among the methanol and water extracts of ASL, hexane extract showed a better antihyperglycaemic response. Authors reported that hexane extract (400 mg/kg) showed significant intestinal α-glucosidase inhibition with 75.69 ± 1.7% compared to acarbose (10 mg/kg) with 53.60 ± 1.45% and improved the serum insulin level with 16.26 ± 1.20 µU/mL compared to glimepiride (1 mg/kg) with 17.36 ± 0.90 µU/mL, which demonstrated the secretagogue nature of the extract. Davis et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] implied that leaves exert their action by promoting glucose uptake as well as by modulating insulin signalling events via inhibition of protein tyrosine phosphatase 1B (PTP1B) and stimulation of the phosphorylation of insulin receptor-β (IR-β) and insulin receptor substrate-1 (IRS-1) accompanied by upregulation of glucose transporter type 4 (GLUT4) and phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3 kinase) mRNA expression in vitro. The authors also revealed that oral administration of hexane extract showed a significant reduction of 30.5% in the levels of triglyceride (TG) compared to the antidiabetic drug rosiglitazone (33.5%). Gupta et al. [
 <xref rid="B64-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] evaluated the effects of an ethanol extract of ASLs in alloxan and streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic mice. The authors determined that a dose of 350 mg/kg body weight significantly decreased the fasting blood glucose (FBG) level by 26.8%, reduced the triglyceride (TG) by 28.7%, significantly reduced the low-density lipoprotein (LDL) or “bad cholesterol” by 71.9% along with total cholesterol (TC) by 49.3%, and favourably increased high-density lipoprotein (HDL) or “good cholesterol” by 30.3% in diabetic mice. In several studies, researchers investigated the hypoglycaemic and antidiabetic effects of ASLs and reported that these extracts exerted antidiabetic potential through (i) increasing the amount of insulin by stimulating pancreatic β-cells, (ii) increasing glucose uptake in the muscle, (iii) inhibiting intestinal enzymes such as α-glucosidase responsible for glucose metabolism [
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], and (iv) inhibiting glucose output from the liver and consequently improving the lipid profile in diabetic mice [
 <xref rid="B52-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The abovementioned findings suggested that ASLs could be useful to maintain or control normal blood sugar levels and cholesterol levels and could be an effective alternative as a herbal medicine to control diabetes. Antidiabetic and various other bioactivities of ASL extract is presented in 
 <xref rid="biomolecules-11-00614-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. 
</p>
