<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Harvesting time has an obvious effect on 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic>’s essential oil yield. On the other hand, harvesting time effect on 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil composition is variable. Four studies reported that the highest essential oil yields were obtained when 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> was harvested during the summer [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. For 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> essential oil composition variation, both thymol and carvacrol were reported to be higher in summer during the flowering period in two studies [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Another study found that wild 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> leaves produced a higher level of thymol and cultivated 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> leaves produced a higher level of carvacrol in June after flowering [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Thymol level was observed to be increased in May in one study [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], while in two studies thymol levels were higher when 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> was harvested in early spring before flowering and during winter and autumn, and the levels of carvacrol were higher when 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> was harvested in spring and summer [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. For γ-terpinene and p-cymene levels, two studies reported that they were higher when 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> was harvested in spring between February and May [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], while one study reported that p-cymene and thymoquinone levels were higher after the flowering stage from January to July [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. It was found in one study that the level of myrsitic acid was the highest after flowering in June, and for α-linolenic acid and palmitic acid, levels were the highest in April before flowering. Additionally, the mineral content obtained from cultivated 
 <italic>O. syriacum</italic> was higher in April after flowering [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-01001" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].
</p>
