<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="s2001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>The leaves of 
   <italic>Hagenia abyssinica</italic> (Rosaceae) have been used traditionally for the management of diabetes mellitus. Thus, this study aimed to evaluate the antidiabetic and anti-hyperlipidemic activity of 
   <italic>Hagenia abyssinica</italic> leaves crude extract in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Antidiabetic and anti-hyperlipidemic activity of the crude extract of 
   <italic>Hagenia abyssinica</italic> was studied in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice. The effects of the extract on fasting blood glucose level, body weight, and serum lipid profiles were analyzed. One-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s post hoc test was used for data analysis and p&lt;0.05 was considered as statistically significant.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Hagenia abyssinica leaves crude extract showed significant (p&lt;0.05-p&lt;0.001) blood-glucose-lowering activity. Moreover, the crude extract of 
   <italic>H. abyssinica</italic> reduced the fasting blood glucose level by 23.21%, 38.20%, 43.53%, and 58.99%, respectively, for CE100, CE 200, CE 400, and GLC 5 mg/kg on the 14th day of treatment. After diabetic mice were treated with 
   <italic>H. abyssinica</italic> (100, 200 and 400 mg/kg) for 14 days, there was a significant decrease in serum total cholesterol, very-low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein cholesterol, and serum triglyceride and a significant increase in body weight, and HDL-cholesterol level as compared to diabetic control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2004">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>The present findings revealed that 
   <italic>H. abyssinica</italic> leaves could be useful for the management of diabetes mellitus and other abnormalities related to this metabolic disorder. Thus, the present study may support the traditional use of 
   <italic>H. abyssinica</italic> for diabetes mellitus treatment.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
