<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The EO screened in this study can be classified according to their main active compound as phenolic compounds (anis star, black pepper, capsicum, cassia, ginger, thyme, and turmeric oils) and monoterpenes (coriander, geraniol, lemongrass, limonene, and tea tree). Both phenolic and monoterpene compounds have exhibited effective antimicrobial activity in vitro [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Phenolic compounds have been shown to have antimicrobial activity due to the presence of a hydroxyl group in the phenolic structure [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These molecules have a wide spectrum of activity against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, in our study, the addition of phenolic compounds at low, medium, or high doses did not improve rumen fermentation profile in the desired direction (increasing propionate and decreasing acetate and the A:P ratio) except for thyme oil which tended to increase total VFA and butyrate proportion, and anise star oil that had a small effect only on butyrate molar proportion. Our results agree with previous studies that used thyme oil at doses ranging between our low and medium doses (at 100 or 200 mg/L) or its main active compound (thymol at 200 mg/L) in in vitro dairy cow rumen microbial fermentation conditions [
 <xref rid="B20-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, Castillejos et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] used thymol at higher doses (500 and 5000 mg/L) and observed a decrease in total VFA and an increase in the A:P ratio, but such an effect is not beneficial for improving the energy efficiency. Busquet et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] used anise oil and its main active compound (anethol) at 300 and 3000 mg/L, and observed a decrease in total VFA, propionate, and acetate molar proportions. However, Chaves et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] used anethol at low dose (20 mg/L) and did not find effect on rumen microbial profile. The results obtained from capsicum in this study agree with those of Busquet et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] that used capsicum at different doses (3, 30, 300, and 3000 mg/L) and did not find effect on total VFA and the A:P ratio. Moreover, Busquet et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and Nanon et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] tested ginger oil in vitro at similar or higher doses and did not find any effect. In this study, cassia oil did not affect total and individual VFA. Busquet et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] used cinnamaldehyde, one of the main active compounds of cassia at 3000 mg/L and observed a decrease in total VFA and an increase in propionate molar proportion. The same active compound was used in another in vitro study at 200 mg/L and had no effect on total and individual VFA [
 <xref rid="B27-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In this study, black pepper and turmeric did not have any effect on total and individual VFA. Moreover, we did not find any study that used black pepper and turmeric oils or their main active compound (piperine and curcumin) in in vitro dairy cow rumen microbial fermentation conditions to compare with. 
</p>
