<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">DNA from isolate purified colonies was extracted using Microlysis kit (Labogen, London, United Kingdom) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. The isolates were screened by randomly amplified polymorphic DNA-polymerase chain reaction (RAPD-PCR) using the single stranded oligonucleotides primer RAPD2 (5′-AGCAGCGTGG-3′) (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rebecchi et al., 2015</xref>) and GTG-5 (5′-GTG GTG GTG GTG GTG-3′) (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Versalovic et al., 1994</xref>). The PCR fragment profiles were digitally captured using the BioImaging System Gene Genius and pattern analysis was performed with the Fingerprinting II software (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, United States). The similarity in the profiles of bands was based on the Pearson correlation coefficient and the cluster analyses were performed by unweighted pair group method with arithmetic mean (UPGMA). A correlation coefficient of 70% was arbitrarily selected to distinguish the clusters, and one representative for each cluster was amplified using the primers P0 (5′-GAG AGT TTG ATC CTG GCT-3′) and P6 (5′-CTA CGG CTA CCT TGT TAC-3′) (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Di Cello and Fani, 1996</xref>). PCR products were visualized by electrophoresis on 2.5% agarose gel in Tris-Acetate-EDTA (TAE). The PCR amplicons of approximately 1.5 kb, corresponding to the size of the full 16S rRNA gene were purified using the NucleoSpin gel and PCR clean-up according to the package insert (Macherey-Nagel, DE) and sequenced at the GATC Biotech (Germany). The taxonomical identification of sequences was performed using BLAST (Basic Local Alignment Search Tool) (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Altschul et al., 1997</xref>) and by alignment against the Ribosomal Database Project (RDP) database using the Naïve Bayesian Classifier (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
