<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">In Europe, USA and Japan, plant-based medicines got immense importance for the treatment of diseases for which no readymade medicine or treatment is directly available. As a result, in last one decade there has been a massive increase in utilization of such plant derived medicines in advanced western countries specifically like France and Germany [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. The inventions under modern herbal healthcare practices in developing countries like India are still under process. It is a common fact that the origins of maximum regularly used drugs under modern and traditional medicine are from plant sources. Almost 1% of the plant species from 250000 higher plants have been identified with medicinal properties and among them, some were specifically recognized for antidiabetic properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Such herbs have been identified by large potential of hypoglycemic activity but their effectiveness were not equally proved against all forms of diabetes and related complications. 
 <italic>Swertia Chirayita,</italic> which is one among such ayurvedic plant, is well-known for its immense herbal and pharmaceutical applications. Value for the plant in national and global market has been constantly increasing. 
 <italic>S. Chirayita</italic> from Indian origin and 
 <italic>S. japonica</italic> and 
 <italic>S. pseudochinensis</italic> from Japanise origin are considered under “elite” classes due to their huge therapeutic importance and revenue making possibilities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. Utilization of such plant in the form of crude drug has received growing demand in the Indian subcontinent (almost 400 tons/year) and such demand is predicted to increase 10% annually [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. Still now the plant extract has been successfully implemented in the form of different compositions for remedial purposes of diabetics and other related disorders. Powdered form of the drug is normally utilized as a constituent of ‘sudarshan churna’, an ayurvedic tonic used in herbal medicinal method for management of all types of fevers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. So far no toxicity or serious side effects have been reported during various application of 
 <italic>Swertia Chirayita</italic> plant extract although further extensive toxicological researches are necessary to establish total safety of the plant for human applications. Detail and time to time investigation of toxicological and mutagenic properties of different plant derivative compounds from 
 <italic>Swertia Chirayita</italic> are also necessary as mutagenic and cytotoxic properties can be induced in such medicinal plants especially during long period utilization [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. Despite of the long term recognition for various potent pharmacological activities, the pant does not possess enough scientific evidences regarding safety evaluation. In some cases, herbal formulations generated with active ingredients from such plant extract to defend specific diseases, were not well executed or established. Extensive investigation on antidiabetic mechanism, developed during application of diverse animal models is also absent for such plant species. In order to standardize the plant extract as medicinally valuable product and to analyze its therapeutic efficiency, proper identification of active components with their molecular interaction is highly necessary. Antidiabetic effectiveness and sensitivity evaluation of such plant extract against humans can be established by some extensive screening practices like oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT), fasting plasma glucose (FPG) test and random capillary blood glucose (RCBG) test. Even more specifically with RCBG test, Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) tests are also necessary to identify the condition of liver when the patient is under treatment with such plant extract. A series of histopathological studies of patient are needed to confirm the effect of plant extract on recovery of beta cells activity in terms of normal insulin production. Techniques like pre-fractionation of plant extracts can reduce the difficulties associated to the standardization of some screening methods [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>].
</p>
