<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study evaluates the performances of seven algorithms in mapping 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> distribution and fractional cover abundance. We chose five MLAs: two different implementations of gradient boosting machine (GBM and GBM‐BRT), random forest (RF), support vector machine (SVM), and deep (learning) neural network (DNN), an ensemble model composed of the four best‐performing tested algorithms, and a generalized linear model (GLM) for comparison reasons. All model calculations and model performance assessments were implemented in R programming (R Core Team, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0080" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). A comprehensive overview of the R packages and the different parameter settings are provided in the Supporting information (Table 
 <xref rid="ece34919-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). We checked collinearity of explanatory variables before applying to any model and those having high variable inflated factors (VIF) were removed. In this study, we used a threshold level of VIF &gt; 10 to exclude variable(s) from any model (Bruce &amp; Bruce, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Gareth, Witten, Hastie, &amp; Tibshirani, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Accordingly, three variables, the blue, green and second shortwave‐infrared (SWIR 2) bands were removed from all models as they had high VIF (Dormann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). We then assessed the influence (importance) of variables in each model by using the method described by Natekin and Knoll (
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Furthermore, 10‐fold cross‐validation was applied to assess model performance (Fushiki, 
 <xref rid="ece34919-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Finally, the predictive power of all tested MLAs was evaluated using several performance parameters (Table 
 <xref rid="ece34919-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The general functionality of each tested model is described below.
</p>
