<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Limitations of this study warrant mention. Polyphenol bioavailability is known to be low, given that, depending on their chemical structure, polyphenols are poorly absorbed through the intestinal tract and extensively catabolized by the gut microflora into microbial metabolites. Previously, we contributed to identifying the parent polyphenols quercetin, caffeic, chlorogenic, and gallic acids in urine samples that were collected from humans after the intake of polyphenol-rich beverages, demonstrating their ability to be absorbed in in vivo condition [
 <xref rid="B80-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. In parallel, literature data [
 <xref rid="B32-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and our previous studies [
 <xref rid="B81-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>] led to detect ferulic, 3,4-dihydroxyphenylpropionic, 3,4-dihydroxyphenylacetic, 3-hydroxyphenylacetic, 3-hydroxybenzoic and hippuric acids as circulating metabolites in rats and humans after consumption of polyphenols like caffeic, chlorogenic and gallic acids, quercetin, and procyanidins. When considering the presence of such polyphenols on the medicinal plant extracts we used here, it was relevant to assess the effect of their related circulating metabolites on cerebral endothelial cells. Importantly, our data show, for the first time, that the polyphenol circulating metabolites tested improve ROS production, NFκB transcriptional activity, IL-6 secretion, and NO levels in cerebral endothelial cells during the hyperglycemic condition. This result emphasizes their possible involvement in the capacity of medicinal plant polyphenols to improve redox, inflammatory, and vasoactive markers in in vivo condition. It will be of interest to determine the molecular mechanism implicated in the bioactivity of polyphenol circulating metabolites. Another limitation of the present study is that polyphenol uptake mechanism by cells remains poorly understood. Literature data indicate that the uptake of polyphenols, such as flavonoids, depends on cellular types. Rather than different levels of passive diffusion, this may be explained by a greater level of intracellular metabolism and faster rate of export from different cells [
 <xref rid="B84-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. It is also assumed that polyphenol transport through the BBB is limited and associated with the inhibition of efflux transporters, such as P-glycoprotein [
 <xref rid="B86-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Absorbed phenolic acids, like caffeic acid, were found to accumulate in the brain at nanomolar concentrations [
 <xref rid="B88-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>] and exert neuroprotective effects during cerebral ischemic injury [
 <xref rid="B89-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Our recent study conducted on a mouse stroke model co-exposed to hyperglycemia and 
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic> plant polyphenols or pure caffeic acid, led to demonstrate the presence of caffeic acid and its circulating metabolite ferulic acid in the infarcted hemisphere. Moreover, we found that the capacity of polyphenols to decrease cerebral infarct volume and hemorrhagic transformation aggravated by hyperglycemia was associated with an improvement of the production of vascular endothelial-cadherin used as a BBB integrity marker, and with a reduction of neuroinflammation [
 <xref rid="B40-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Further work will be needed in order to assess the gut absorption, metabolism, and ability of other medicinal plant polyphenols to target cerebrovascular cells in in vivo diabetic and ischemic conditions. Given that UPLC-ESI-MS-MS analysis identified polyphenols such as quercetin, caffeic, chlorogenic and gallic acids in medicinal plant extracts, the biological effects of standard molecules were assessed. It will be relevant to evaluate their role as active principles after fractionation and purification from medicinal plants. However, it is not excluded that other phytochemicals detected like kaempferol, trimethoxyflavone, ellagic acid or ellagitannins may be involved. Literature data provided evidence for their antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B38-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In our study, polyphenol-rich plant extracts were prepared through a pharmacological approach based on aqueous acetonic extraction. The most traditionally employed method for preparation of herbal remedies is infusion, which consists of soaking the plant part in very hot water [
 <xref rid="B50-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Recently, 
 <italic>A. borbonica</italic> plant infusion was shown to exert antioxidant properties on in vitro and in vivo models exposed to glycoxidative condition [
 <xref rid="B90-antioxidants-09-00573" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. It will be of interest to evaluate the benefits of infusions that were prepared from the medicinal plants tested here, during cerebrovascular complications related to diabetes.
</p>
