<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="bdi459-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">The aim of this study was to optimize the extraction of 
  <italic class="italic">p</italic>‐menthadienol isomers and aristolone from the essential oil of 
  <italic class="italic">Elyonurus hensii</italic> by hydrodistillation. The study of the seasonal variation in the chemical composition has shown that the plant material has been subject to a natural selection regarding the biosynthesis of the 
  <italic class="italic">p</italic>‐menthadienol isomers: during periods of water stress, the extracts are rich in 
  <italic class="italic">cis</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">trans‐p</italic>‐mentha‐1(7),8‐dien‐2‐ol and poor in 
  <italic class="italic">cis</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">trans‐p</italic>‐mentha‐2,8‐dien‐1‐ol. Regarding the modeling, eight experiments were carried out by considering three easily interpretable factors (the extraction duration, the residual water content and the state of the division of the plant material). The average yield was 1.33% for the aerial part and 0.74% for the roots. The residual water content is the most important factor, which significantly influences the average yield of the essential oil and the content of the major constituents. Regarding the aerial part, a low residual water content of the plant material varies the essential oil yield (from 0.40% to 2.11%) and the content of 
  <italic class="italic">cis</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">trans</italic>‐
  <italic class="italic">p</italic>‐mentha‐2.8‐dien‐1‐ol (from 15.87% to 23.24%). At the root level, the samples that have a very low residual water content provide extracts richer in aristolone. The combined effects of the extraction duration, the state of division, and the residual water content influence greatly the extraction of aristolone (from 36.68% to 54.55%). However, these interactions are more complex and difficult to assess.
 </p>
</abstract>
