<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A total of 29 differentially expressed proteins involved in the sugar metabolism and tricarboxylic acid (TCA) were identified by 2D-DIGE (
 <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="other">Table 
  <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="other">4</xref>
 </xref>), of which 15 proteins were expressed (13 were upregulated and 2 were downregulated) in ME-treated 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, and 28 proteins were expressed in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with SE (26 downregulated and 2 upregulated). The expression of some TCA- and glycolytic-pathway enzymes was upregulated in 
 <italic>E.coli</italic> treated with ME, and some enzymes related to the glycerol metabolism, glycolysis, or gluconeogenesis had a significant role in antimicrobial stress. One of the most sensitive pathways to ROS response is the TCA cycle.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>
 </sup> TCA produces and scavenges ROS under oxidative stress, which might explain ROS upregulation under antimicrobial stress in the present study, thereby suggesting that some TCA pathways have a vital role in managing oxidative stress.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>
 </sup> Upregulation of the expression of glycolysis enzymes and downregulation of the expression of TCA enzymes have been noted in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> under the stress of iron limitation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref>
 </sup> Aconitate hydratase B is a TCA enzyme that appeared in three locations and showed different expression patterns in the present study. The expression of aconitate hydratase B was downregulated in all three locations in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with SE but was upregulated in one location after treatment with ME. Aconitate hydratase B is sensitive, and SE appeared to damage it. The expression of aconitate hydratase B is downregulated in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> suffering from cadmium stress.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>
 </sup> Glycerol kinase is an enzyme involved in glycerol uptake and lipolysis, and its expression was upregulated and downregulated in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with ME and SE, respectively. Glycerol kinase participates in the energy metabolism, and the downregulation we observed might have occurred to reduce cell-energy consumption under stress conditions to conserve energy for cell survival. Pyruvate dehydrogenase is responsible for acetate formation, and its expression was upregulated after ME exposure in contrast with 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with SE. Downregulation of the expression of pyruvate dehydrogenase has also been reported for 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> tested in an alkaline environment.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>
 </sup> The expression of an enzyme involved in the electron-transport chain and TCA cycle, succinate dehydrogenase, was upregulated in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with ME but downregulated in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with SE. However, the expression of succinate dehydrogenase is enhanced in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> under zinc stress.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>
 </sup> Malate dehydrogenase is vital for control of oxidative stress. Its expression was downregulated in SE-treated 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> but was not affected significantly by ME. Several mechanisms are used by bacteria for carbohydrate uptake.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>
 </sup> The important transport system for carbohydrates is the phosphotransferase system (PTS), and the enzyme involved in this system is phosphoenolpyruvate-protein phosphotransferase. The expression of the latter was not affected in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with ME, but in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with SE, it was upregulated. The expression of the glucose-specific EIIA component and galactofuranose transporter ATP-binding protein YtfR was downregulated and upregulated, respectively, in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with SE. The expression of phosphoenolpyruvate-protein phosphotransferase is downregulated in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> under alkaline conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>
 </sup> The proteins involved in the nonoxidative part of the pentose phosphate pathway, transaldolase B and transaldolase B1, responded differently in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> to ME treatment compared with that upon SE treatment, with downregulation being observed in the latter treatment. Downregulation of the transketolase expression has been recorded for 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> under alkaline conditions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>
 </sup> It appears that ME enhanced the tryptophanase expression for the tryptophan catabolism; this was in contrast to SE, which downregulated the tryptophanase expression and revealed no vital role for tryptophanase in the antimicrobial response to SE.
</p>
