<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> tracer technique [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] can be used to make estimations of methane emissions either by eructation or expiration from animals that can easily select their diet in a way characteristic of farmed livestock especially in grazing. The SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub>, a gas is easily measurable and traceable at low concentrations. In addition, it is synthetic in origin and not produced as part of any sort of biological process. The SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> is also idyllic as its background concentration, which is naturally very low (6 pmol/day) [
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>], while its concentration as a tracer typically ranges from 0.01 to 0.03 mmol/day [
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. In the gas technique, SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> tracer gas is delivered via a permeation tube, which is positioned in the rumen, and the ratio of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> to SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> in the breath of an animal is measured and corrected with reference to the background concentration. Though the concentration of the tracer is known, the rate of production of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> can be calculated [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. The assessments have challenged the accuracy of the SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> technique for estimating CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>], with greater between-animal variation compared to RC [
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. The SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> technique has also delivered variable estimates of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission from animals on diverse herbages that have not been supported by RC measurements [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>–
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. There was also some problem with halter and collection canisters, placed on the animal for CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> estimates can affect during grazing [
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>], especially in young animals, and a lower than predicted feed dry matter intake (DMI) will overestimate CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> yields (g/kg DMI). Administration of rumen SF
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> boluses and frequent handling of animal is needed which can be troublemaking to normal behavior and is relatively laborious. Though this technique is challenging to use in practice, standard operating techniques have been established [
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>].
</p>
