<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The face-masks method is one of the oldest technique for “spot-sampling” of respiratory exchange and CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission from cattle, sheep, and goats. Face mask is only useful for short-term measurements of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission rate for screening of large numbers of animals, however may cause marked discomfort and distress which can change animal behaviors, and affect the gas measurements [
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. The sniffer method, first reported by Garnsworthy et al. [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>], is the measurement of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> concentration in air eructed by cattle during milking. In this technique, air in the manger is continuously sampled, analyzed, and logged at 1-second intervals using data loggers in order to measure CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations in close proximity to the muzzle of the animal. Garnsworthy et al. [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>] also reported a good relationship (r = 0.79) between RC technique and CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission rate using this method. The hand laser CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> detector (LMD) has been proposed to measures enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> concentrations in the air near the nose or mouth of an animal in normal environment [
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>]. The methane hood (MH) system, a novel method to quantify CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission from cattle during group feeding in housed environment. This system measures CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> concentrations exhausted from underneath a hood designed to partially enclose the volume above a feed bin. The principle is almost similar to GF system except that there is no requirement to offer extra feed supplements needed to influence the visit of cattle into GF system [
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. There are also some other indirect approaches have been suggested and so far used to measure enteric CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions from animal however, associated with lower accuracy and greater uncertainty in the emission data [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>].
</p>
