<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0015">We have retrieved research articles (80 in total) about TCM against COVID-19 which were based on database-based strategy from PubMed and CNKI as of June 15, 2020. The results of database usage frequency were shown in 
 <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, in which 73 of 80 articles were used TCMSP for further analysis, the following were ETCM (12 of 80) and TCMID (9 of 80), but none of them were updated earlier than November 2018. It was found that many studies have attempted to determine the anti-COVID-19 activity of ingredients from TCM solely by the binding ability of ingredients with angiotensin-COnverting enzyme 2 (ACE2) through molecular docking, since the increased expression of ACE2 were reported to facilitate infection with COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, most of the active ingredients screened out in these studies are widely present in most Chinese herbs, such as quercetin (PubChem CID: 5280343), kaempferol (PubChem CID: 5280863), luteolin (PubChem CID: 5280445), rutin (PubChem CID: 5280805) and β-sitosterol (PubChem CID: 222284), etc., which seem not the characteristic compound and have yet to validate their anti-COVID-19 activities. Moreover, in these studies, the main focus is on constructing the interaction of herb-ingredient-target protein (Homo sapiens) to predict and analyze the effect of TCM against COVID-19, but it ignores whether these ingredients have a direct antiviral effect on SARS-COronavirus 2 (SARS-COV-2). Subsequently, a total of 56 kinds of Chinese medicines (including Chinese patent medicine, TCM formula/decoction, herb pair, and single herb, etc.) were involved in these articles (Table S1), however, only a few of them (such as Lianhua Qingwen capsules, Qingfeipaidu decoction, Ma Xing Shi Gan decoction, and Shufengjiedu capsules etc.) have been recommended by the National Health Commission of China (NHCC) for the treatment of COVID-19 clinically [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Importantly, 36 kinds of Chinese medicines have not been validated experimentally or clinically in the treatment of COVID-19, indicating that database-based strategy to repurpose these Chinese medicines for the clinical management of COVID-19 should be more cautious. Compared with Chinese patent medicines, these TCM formulas/decoctions consist of several or even dozens of herbs without corresponding quality criteria, which may pose a challenge to their quality control and database-based mechanistic investigations.
</p>
