<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> species are soilborne pathogens that use root-like rhizomorphs as persistent propagative structures in the soil and to colonize roots and fallen logs. The networks of rhizomorphs represent territorially expanding, often vastly extended and long-lived, clonal individuals or genets [
 <xref rid="B78-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Population-level studies corroborated that genets of the same species maintain discrete territories, possibly by the prevalence of somatic incompatibility between adjacent colonies [
 <xref rid="B79-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Genets of different species, representing either apparently non-competing saprotrophic (
 <italic>A. cepistipes</italic>) and pathogenic (
 <italic>A. ostoyae</italic>) species, or others (
 <italic>A. altimontana</italic> and 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic>) showing signs of competitive in situ exclusion, may occur sympatrically with significant spatial overlaps between them [
 <xref rid="B80-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. For the evaluation of the genetic structures of two spatially distinct 
 <italic>A. cepistipes</italic> populations, neutral genetic traits as single sequence repeats (SSR) and single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have proven to offer distinctive tracking of inherent genetic variabilities either within indigenous (50–100 km) or between distant (1000 km) fungal populations [
 <xref rid="B82-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. In contrast to the prevalence of extended genets in native forests, a newly established ornamental landscape with trees infected by 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic> mycelia, representing a high proportion of unique genotypes in single trees, suggested a significant role of local spore dispersal in 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic>-related ecology [
 <xref rid="B83-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>].
</p>
