<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The super-resolution revolution in optical microscopy offers even inexperienced users up to 10-fold increased resolution on commercial systems that have become commonly available through imaging facilities. However, established sample preparation protocols that were previously acceptable may be inadequate for super-resolution microscopy, as the inaccuracies are no longer masked by the diffraction limit. While the importance of careful sample preparation is readily accepted, its assessment remains challenging. Neglecting to recognize this cost associated with increased resolution could render imaging results useless or worse might incorrectly inform researchers about a biological system. To demonstrate sample preparation inadequacies in imaging regimes, we took advantage of NanoJ-Fluidics (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>) and NanoJ-SQUIRREL (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>) to compare the pre- and post-fixation actin structures and CD4 cellular organization, in the same cells. We asked what would be the influence of chemical fixation using different imaging regimes with increasing resolution (TIRF, SIM and SMLM) by correlating pre- and post-fixation images. The actin cytoskeleton acts as a supporting scaffold that orchestrates the organization of the plasma membrane (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>). However, while actin filaments are strongly affected by chemical fixation conditions, the plasma membrane itself is affected to a lesser extent. Chemical fixation is usually fast and even a simple protocol can achieve structural preservation of the organization of transmembrane proteins in the plasma membrane. Despite the availability of chemical fixation protocols that preserve the actin cytoskeleton, the predominant approach for studying protein organization is fixation with 4% PFA in PBS. Our data suggests this is insufficient to produce reliable imaging data on receptor distributions for imaging modalities that break the diffraction limit. The chemical fixation protocol used was shown to play a crucial role on the introduction of artifacts. We applied SQUIRREL, a recently developed quality metric tool (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>), to quantify how much cytoskeletal structures are distorted by chemical fixation at exemplary conditions. Our approach is widely applicable to determine the impact of any fixation protocol beyond those tested. Of course, a correlation between pre- and postfixation structures is required which, albeit greatly facilitated by NanoJ-Fluidics (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>), is still a time-consuming quality control approach. However, in our opinion, the benefit of increased confidence in light microscopy data is worth the added effort. The increase in cluster size and density we observed could be due to: (1) disruption of the actin cytoskeleton organization that could affect to CD4 membrane organization via protein-protein interaction; (2) fixation-induced changes in membrane properties, which would cause artificial reorganization of membrane proteins; (3) a combination of both factors. Using super-resolution microscopy we could show that the changes in CD4 organization coincided with a disrupted actin cytoskeleton profile. The cluster size in optimal conditions suggests CD4 may be organized in dimers (as seen by the mean cluster size of ~60 nm), which is consistent with its suggested capacity to homo-dimerize, a process that may increase the avidity of its binding to MHCII (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>). The differences observed between temperatures regarding CD4 cluster size are negligible (~6 nm) and likely related to the high number of data points skewing the statistical analysis. This is something the reader should always have in mind when analyzing statistical significance, as in this case the ~6 nm is significantly below the resolution our setup can provide and within the linker error introduced by using antibodies (~10 nm). The cluster density suggests a homogeneous distribution consistent with COS7 non-native CD4 expression. It is important to highlight that the considerable differences in cluster density are in a system where CD4 does not normally exist, hence lacking the regulatory machinery or native interactions that may normally regulate CD4 distribution. Presumably, the observed differences would be more striking in CD4-positive immune cells where CD4 is linked to p56/LCK (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>). Interestingly, the degree of actin cytoskeleton disruption is consistent with the extent of the changes we observe in CD4 membrane organization. After chemical fixation at 4°C we observed almost complete disruption whereas at 23°C the cell displays a mixture of regions with disrupted and non-disrupted actin structures. This suggests that despite CD4 not existing in COS7 cells in native conditions, CD4 organization may be affected by the structure of the dense actin cortex (possibly through its cytoplasmic domain). Consequently, inadequate actin chemical fixation regimes can affect CD4 membrane organization and influence the biological information extracted from SMLM CD4 analysis. Challenging fields, such as the spatial distribution of immunomodulatory receptors require rigorous controls. For example, actin cytoskeleton dynamics affect clustering in immunological synapses (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>). Our approach could be employed to quantify the effects of actin perturbing drugs used on these cells.
</p>
