<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">These results are further supported by single-particle tracking experiments. Single-particle tracking of transmembrane proteins and a GPI-anchored protein showed that the size and orientation in the plasma membrane was more important than fixation conditions. GPI-anchored proteins that reside in the outer leaflet of the plasma membrane with only indirect interaction with the submembrane cytoskeleton (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>) remain largely mobile in ideal actin-preserving conditions. Any distribution or clustering analysis must rule out post-fixation aggregation, e.g., by the use of single-binders such as nanobodies. This is in agreement with STED and FRAP data showing that appropriate fixation is critical for imaging of microclusters (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>). In contrast, transmembrane proteins with a cytosolic domain such as CD4 or our artificial transmembrane probe are quickly immobilized, indicating an interaction with the submembrane cytoskeleton. During single-particle tracking of membrane probes at 45 Hz, we observed a trend toward faster immobilization in the first few seconds after addition of the pre-warmed chemical fixative. During phase contrast imaging at 0.066 Hz cellular motion was halted within 30 s for both conditions tested. The increased fluctuations in correlation analysis after addition of ice-cold fixative was likely due to thermal effects on sample structure and microscope optics and not diffusion or reaction rate of the fixative. Our observation that CD4 membrane organization is affected by poor actin chemical fixation should serve as a cautionary tale for sample preparation approaches to study membrane proteins. Optimal fixation approaches preserve the cortical actin cytoskeleton structure and the organization of transmembrane proteins in a near-native state (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" class="xref">Figure 6</xref>). Conversely, suboptimal fixation conditions induce deformations of membrane and cytoskeleton that can result in artifacts that can influence the organization of membrane proteins, such as CD4 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" class="xref">Figure 6</xref>). Although, we and others (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>–
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>) suggest that the actin cytoskeleton, protein-protein interactions and the physiological context (e.g., temperature) are important for membrane proteins organization, many studies using SMLM focus on imaging unknown structures and distributions of proteins that do not have a known organization. It is important to highlight that this work does not intend to suggest a direct correlation between the actin cytoskeleton and CD4 surface organization (or other surface proteins). Rather that when performing essential protocol optimization, preservation of the overall cellular structure and physiological context should be a priority. This work also aims to highlight that there are already established protocols that serve as excellent starting points (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>), hardware that permits the optimization of such protocols to be streamlined (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>) and tools that allow for seamless analysis of possible bottlenecks (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>). In conclusion, to extract the most from SMLM experiments it is essential to use reliable and repeatable imaging protocols that preserve, as much as possible, the overall cellular structure.
</p>
