<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Other studies have also investigated the activity of zingerone, a phenolic alkanone found in 
 <italic>Z. officinale</italic>, using 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> models. In particular, zingerone has been shown to inhibit the production of HMGB-1 and TGFBIp in LPS-induced human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs), as well as in CLP-induced septic mice [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Both HMGB-1 and TGFBIp are proinflammatory mediators that promote vascular leakage in sepsis [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Zingerone was able to inhibit HMGB-1- and TGFBIp-induced endothelial dysfunction through the suppression of hyperpermeability, cell adhesion molecules (CAMs) expression, and adhesion and transendothelial migration of neutrophils [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Most importantly, zingerone's therapeutic effect is evidenced by its ability to decrease sepsis-related mortality and to reverse organ damage such as hepatic, renal, and pulmonary injury in CLP-induced septic mice at a dose of 0.72 mg/kg via intravenous injection [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Similar improvements in the survival rate and tissue damage were also observed in TGFBIp-induced CLP mice injected with zingerone (0.36 and 0.72 mg/kg) intravenously [
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. These findings are in line with other reports that described the ability of zingerone to alleviate lung and kidney injury in LPS-induced mice upon intragastric and intraperitoneal administration, respectively [
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. These studies cumulatively suggest that 
 <italic>Z. officinale</italic> or ginger has great therapeutic potential for sepsis by suppressing sepsis-related mediators and organ damage.
</p>
