<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is immense interest in unravelling the role of bioactive compounds present in nature. Some medicinal plants with antimicrobial attributes are capable of evading the activity of multi-drug resistant (MDR) microbes, which helps in withstanding antimicrobial resistance [
 <xref rid="B63-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Distinct morphological parts of the mango plant like leaves, stem, kernel, seeds, and bark have been manifested to show antimicrobial activities against microbes like 
 <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis, Escherichia coli, Candida albicans, Proteus vulgaris, Pseudomonas fluorescens, Shigella flexneri, Klebsiella pneumoniae,</italic> and 
 <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic>. MLs extract is the most studied part for antibacterial effects. Bharti [
 <xref rid="B64-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] observed that hexane and hexane/ethyl acetate extracts of MLs exhibit favorable antibacterial effects against 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and 
 <italic>Enterobacter aerogenes</italic>. Antimicrobial investigation of the essential oils extracted from leaves of five Egyptian mango cultivars to be used as preservatives materials has been demonstrated by Ouf et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> sp. (Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC): 62.5 μg/mL), Bacillus subtilis (MIC: 125 μg/mL), 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (MIC: 125 μg/mL), 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (MIC: 500 μg/mL), Aspergillus flavus (MIC: 1000 μg/mL), and Salmonella typhi (MIC: 1000 μg/mL). The major phytochemicals responsible for the antimicrobial activity in mango leaves include phenolics, alkaloids, saponins, glycosides, terpenes, and tannins. The concentration of the aforementioned compounds were measured as follows: flavonoid content was the highest at 11.25 mg/100 g; there was 3.23 mg/100 g of saponins; phenolic content was 0.08 mg/100 g; and tannins in leaves was at 0.46 mg/100 g [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Polyphenols and phenolic acids present in ML extract include protocatechuic acid, gallic acid, hyperin, catechin, quercetin, kainic acid, ethyl digallate, ellagic acid, and shikimic acid, which can inhibit the growth of pathogens [
 <xref rid="B8-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The mechanism of exertion of antimicrobial activity by these compounds involves depleting intracellular ATP levels, depolarization of plasma membrane, cytoplasm leakage, damaging genetic material, and declining the concentration of microbial protein [
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Anti-microbial activity of mangiferin is schematized in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antioxidants-10-00299-f004">Figure 4</xref>. Additionally, an adequate level of antibacterial activity of leaf extract was found against Gram positive bacteria, but no or less activity against Gram-negative bacteria was observed [
 <xref rid="B66-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The study indicated that MLs extract exhibited diameter of zone of inhibition in the range of 7.0‒11.5 mm against Gram-positive bacteria like 
 <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> and 
 <italic>Bacillus</italic> sp., but no activity was seen against gram-negative 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> spp. Additionally, Mangiferin, a xanthone C-glycosyl compound extracted from MLs extract, has also shown to possess strong iron chelating activity, which favors antimicrobial activity. Furthermore, chemical analysis of MLs extract for antimicrobial activity indicated the presence of five major flavonoid compounds including epicatechin-3-O-β-glucopyranoside, 5-hydroxy-3-(4-hydroxyl phenyl) pyrano chromene-4 (8H)-one, 6-(phydroxybenzyl) taxifolin-7-O-β-D-glucoside, quercetin-3-O-α-glucopyranosyl-(1-2)-β-D-glucopyranoside, and epicatechin(2-(3,4dihydroxyphenyl)-3,4-dihydro-2H-chromene-3,5,7-triol [
 <xref rid="B67-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. These compounds are identified to be synthesized immediately after a fungal attack, and a concentration of 1000 ppm has curtailed the growth of target fungal species like 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and 
 <italic>Alternaria</italic> from 56‒97% [
 <xref rid="B67-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. A myriad of terpenes identified from MLs extract including α-pinene, β-pinene, δ-elemene, taraxerol, β-elemene, camphene, γ–cadinene, lupeol, friedelin, linalool, α-guaiene, humulene, α-farnesene, myrcene, limonene, β-ocimene, γ–terpinene, and α-terpinolene exhibit bacteriostatic and bactericidal effects against different pathogens [
 <xref rid="B8-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. HPLC-TOF-ESI/MS analysis of leaf extract to identify hydrolyzable tannins revealed the presence of gallatotannins. Antimicrobial properties of gallatotannins have been associated with their ability to hinder the enzymes of the pathogen, disintegrate lipid bilayer membranes, and promote chelation of metal ions [
 <xref rid="B68-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. The MIC of MLs extract is reported to be in the range 11–52 mg/mL [
 <xref rid="B69-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] and the MIC values were greatest against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> with 36.3 mg/mL. The aforementioned phytocompounds purified from ML extract can be directly used as food additives to enhance the shelf-life of foods, and as an alternative for the synthetic antimicrobial agents, owing to their broad biological and pharmacological activities [
 <xref rid="B70-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].
</p>
