<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we also aimed at analysis of the mutual genetic relationship between 
 <italic>S. abrotanoides</italic> and 
 <italic>S. yangii</italic> rather than their taxonomical position within the 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> subgenera. To our knowledge, no previous work has done that with using DNA barcoding. Usually, a single-entry representative of 
 <italic>Perovskia</italic> subgenus was used for phylogenetic tree reconstructions of 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B11-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. There are two reports of employing molecular markers (ISSR markers) to investigate genetic variability among populations from subgenus 
 <italic>Perovskia</italic> growing wild in Iran [
 <xref rid="B71-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Heshemifar and Rahimmalek [
 <xref rid="B72-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] analysed 63 accessions of 
 <italic>S. abrotanoides</italic> from 16 populations and four accessions of 
 <italic>S. yangii</italic>. Thirteen ISSR markers were shown to have a relatively high efficiency in the assessment of population diversity, which was in most cases confirmed by morphological classifications. In the study of Pourhosseini at al. [
 <xref rid="B71-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], twelve 
 <italic>S. abrotanoides</italic> populations were analyzed and a cultivated population of 
 <italic>S. yangii</italic> was used as an outgroup. The authors have shown that nine ISSR markers are able to genetically distinguish between all studied populations and that the 
 <italic>S. yangii</italic> population was clearly separated from 
 <italic>S. abrotanoides</italic> populations, proving the effectiveness of this DNA fingerprinting method in studying the genetic relationship within the 
 <italic>Perovskia</italic> subgenus. Despite the suitability of the ISSR markers for studying genetic variation among species within subgenus 
 <italic>Perovskia</italic>, we have chosen DNA barcoding as it is regarded as a more sophisticated, standardized, and worldwide acknowledged method, recommended for genetic relationship analysis of land plants [
 <xref rid="B73-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-cells-10-00112" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].
</p>
