<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CAR-T cell infusion is administered after a brief course of chemotherapy. The aim of such chemotherapy is to control, at least in part, the disease during the period between lymphocyte collection and the final infusion of the CAR-T cell product (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). However, it is advisable that the treatment with CAR-T cells might be performed before the achievement of disease complete remission, since the target molecules of CAR-T cells might be no longer detectable. “Bridge” chemotherapy plays an important role in acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) as leukemic blast burden at the time of CAR-T cell infusion correlates with an increased risk of cytokine release syndrome (CRS). The overall tumor burden and the involved sites are additional factors to be considered also in lymphoma patients: many regimens are indicated in this phase, and the choice must take into account the type of histology, the burden of disease, previous treatments, and the fragility of the patient. However, the “bridge” chemotherapy should be given only after leukapheresis in order not to affect the quality of CAR-T cell product (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Two to seven days before CAR-T cell infusion, patients receive a lymphodepleting conditioning regimen to get rid of immune cells and factors endowed with immune suppressive properties and to enhance CAR-T cell functions and engraftment (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). The optimal conditioning regimen has not been defined yet, but the majority of studies employed a combination of fludarabine and cyclophosphamide. Experiences at the NCI (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>) and Fred Hutchinson Cancer Center (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) demonstrated that aggressive lymphodepleting regimens are associated with the increase of both CAR-T cell expansion and toxicity. Of note, certain drugs such as check point inhibitors or other biological drugs (
 <italic>i.e.</italic>, alemtuzumab, daratumumab, and brentuximab vedotin) should be avoided since they may interfere with expansion and persistence of CAR-T cells after infusion (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Infectious complications and organ toxicities should be minimized during bridging chemotherapy (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>).
</p>
