<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Various authors (Dobrynin et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Muranyi et al., 
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Miao and Yun, 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Tseng et al., 
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Tian et al., 
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) have identified the mechanical or oxidative damage caused to cellular envelopes as the main cause of death after NTAP treatments. The mechanical erosion of cellular envelopes could be due either to the impact of plasma energy particles, such as electrons and excited atoms (Butscher et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), or to the accumulation of charges in certain parts of the cell surface, which would lead to its permeabilization through the formation of pores, in a phenomenon known as electroporation (Laroussi et al., 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>). Moreover, damage at this level would facilitate the release of important intracellular components and the invasion of reactive species which would attack other cellular components, such as DNA and proteins, thus accelerating the inactivation process. In addition to this mechanical effect, neutral reactive species generated in plasma, such as atomic oxygen, hydroxyl and peroxyl radicals, metastable oxygen or ozone, are capable of causing oxidative damage to various cellular structures and macromolecules. If this damage is very intense and exceeds the physiological repair capacity, it will lead to microbial death (Leipold et al., 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). In fact, the use of substances that chelate reactive species has been shown to reduce the antimicrobial efficacy of NTAP. Thus, several sequestering agents of various reactive oxygen species, such as catalase, superoxide dismutase, dimethyl sulfoxide, thiourea, sodium azide, and various antioxidants (glutathione, ascorbic acid, sodium pyruvate, mannitol, histidine, or tocopherol) have been reported to protect microorganisms, such as 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> (Joshi et al., 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Yost and Joshi, 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) or 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic> (Takamatsu et al., 
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), from the action of NTAP. Yost and Joshi (
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) showed that previous incubation of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> with catalase provided a greater protective effect than vitamin E and thiourea, concluding that peroxides such as H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> could be the major chemical species responsible for microbial inactivation by NTAP. On the other hand, Takamatsu et al. (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) observed that the presence of dimethyl sulfoxide or sodium azide resulted in lower 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic> inactivation rates than those observed when catalase or superoxide dismutase were used, suggesting that hydroxyl radicals and singlet oxygen were the main agents involved in microbial inactivation.
</p>
