<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mango is known for its pleasant aroma, which varies with the place of origin, variety, and climatic conditions. Hydro distillation method is generally used to extract the essential oil from MLs, and its chemical profile was analyzed by gas chromatography coupled with a mass spectrophotometer. MLO was found to contain monoterpenes (46.98%), sesquiterpenes (38.17%), minor quantities of their analogues (10.67%), and trace amounts of non-terpenoid hydrocarbons and oxygenated hydrocarbons (4.19%). MLO profile showed the presence of seven chemical compounds camphene, α-pinene, α-copaene, pinene, α-gurjunene, β-elemene, and α-humulene [
 <xref rid="B15-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. MLO extracted through hydro-distillation method was rich in sesquiterpenes (70.3%) and dominant compounds δ-3-carene (20.5%), α-gurjunene (19.2%), β-selinene (13.9%), and β-caryophyllene (13.7%) [
 <xref rid="B16-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Studies were also conducted to analyze the chemical composition of MLO from different varieties. MLO extracted from Tommy Atkins cultivar showed β-selinene (29.64%), caryophyllene oxide (12.40%), and humulene epoxide II (8.66%) as the main constituent, while MLO from Rosa, Moscatel, and Jasmim cultivars showed caryophyllene oxide and humulene epoxide II as the main constituent. Other constituents that were common in all the four varieties were spathulenol, italicene epoxide, caryphyllene oxide, cyclocolorenone, and humulene epoxide II. This study also reported sesquiterpenoids as the major compound of MLO [
 <xref rid="B17-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The essential oil from MLs also possesses bacteriostatic properties and contains several antimicrobial constituents such as gurjunene, trans-caryophyllene, humulene, selinene, and camphor. However, varietal variation was also found in context of oil composition, where five Egyptian mango cultivars leaves, Alphonso, Sidik, Ewase, Zebda, and Fagrikalan, were evaluated for their antibacterial activities and possibility to be used as food preservatives. The chemical constituents of the MLO were identified using GC–MS spectrometry and showed the presence of several biologically active compounds, such as humulene-4-hydroxy-4-methyl-2-pentanone, elements, and trans-caryophllene, which was common in all five cultivars of mango [
 <xref rid="B18-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In another study, volatile compounds of MLs (
 <italic>Mangifera indica</italic> var. Coquinho) were extracted using head space solid phase micro extraction (HS-SPME) and hydro-distillation (HD) methods. Gas chromatography–mass spectroscopy (GC–MS) analysis showed a presence of as many as 100 compounds in both leaves and fruit of mango. It was observed that HS-SPME has great potential in isolation of volatiles rich in monoterpenes, whereas these compounds are most likely lost during HD. HD extracts were exclusively detected with oxygenated compounds, viz. carotol, terpineol, cadinol, humulene epoxide II, caryophyllene oxide, and guainol, which may be due to the thermal oxidation of products during distillation. The major compounds found in immature leaves were cyperene, α-humulene, E-caryophyllene, and terpnolene, whereas the main compounds in the mature leaves were cyperene, α-gurjunene, E-caryophyllene, β-cedrene, and α-humulene [
 <xref rid="B19-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The volatilome of MLs demonstrates the presence of very active terpenes, which have health promoting functionalities in the human body. Therefore, volatile compounds can find an important application in the food and nutraceutical industries. The nutritional profile of the MLs, including proteins, components of essential oil, and fatty acid profile, is presented in 
 <xref rid="antioxidants-10-00299-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.
</p>
