<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since allelopathy is specific, it offers interesting applications for biological pest control. In fact, plants producing essential oils have been used extensively for growth regulation, herbicidal, insecticidal, or other agricultural applications (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bajalan et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Cheng and Cheng, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Skrzypek et al., 2015</xref>). Biocontrol by essential oils has a long history—for instance, these oils were the first food preservatives used by humans (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Thompson, 1989</xref>), and often already the crude extracts have been found to exert efficient antifungal, antimicrobial, cytostatic, and insecticidal activities (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Sivropoulou et al., 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Mkaddem et al 2008</xref>). In some cases, the bioactivity has already been broken down to individual compounds. For instance, oil from 
 <italic>Artemisia scoparia</italic> can inhibit germination and seedling growth of three weeds, and this allelopathic effect could be attributed to its major constituent, β-myrcene (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2009</xref>). Components from 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> essential oil, such as eucalyptol, α- and β-pinene, camphene and camphor were reported to inhibit cell proliferation in roots by interfering with DNA synthesis in organelles and nucleus of the 
 <italic>Brassica campestris</italic> root meristem (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Nishida et al., 2005</xref>). Monoterpenes (camphor and menthol) have been found to affect stomatal opening through cytoskeletal changes as a response to the monoterpenes and have effects on the growth of 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedlings (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Kriegs et al., 2010</xref>). Similarly, citral was found to be a strong inhibitor of seed germination in 
 <italic>Triticum sativum</italic>, 
 <italic>Amaranthus palmeri</italic> and 
 <italic>Brassica nigra</italic> (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Dudai et al., 1999</xref>). However, in many cases, it has remained unclear which compound or which mixture of compounds is responsible for the alellopathic effect of a given essential oil, such that the mechanisms behind the specificity of allelopathy have remained fairly elusive.
</p>
