<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antibacterial activity of 
 <italic>Quercus</italic> has been investigated against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria including multidrug-resistant bacterial pathogens. An aqueous extract of leaves from four species of white oaks (
 <italic>Q resinosa, Q laeta, Q grisea, and Q obtusata</italic>) was investigated for antimicrobial activities against a range of bacteria (
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>S. epidermidis</italic>, 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>, 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic>, 
 <italic>P. hauseri</italic>, 
 <italic>P. vulgaris</italic>, and 
 <italic>E. aerogenes</italic>) and yeast (
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>). They further reported that all aqueous extracts of oak tested showed susceptibility to 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> (
 <italic>ATCC 13883</italic>). These researchers also reported that 
 <italic>Q. resinosa</italic> and 
 <italic>Q. grisea</italic> denoted antimitotic activity against these organisms [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], whereas Bahador and Baserisalehi [
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] tested the antibacterial activity against Gram-negative bacteria (
 <italic>E. coli, Salmonella typhimurium, Shigella dysenteriae, and Yersinia enterocolitica</italic>) of the fruit of 
 <italic>Q. castaneifolia</italic>. According to their finding, 
 <italic>S. dysenteriae</italic> was more sensitive with a zone of inhibition of 18 mm, and he MIC value was 2.5 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup>. The lowest MIC values were found for extracts for 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>. In a study carried out by Sarwar et al. [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], the antibacterial activity of the gold nanoparticle synthesized from the leaves of 
 <italic>Quercus incana</italic> was evaluated against the human pathogens (
 <italic>Pseudomonas pickettii, Salmonella setubal, Staphylococcus aureus, Bacillus subtilis, Aspergillus flavus,</italic> and 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>). The results showed enhanced antibacterial activity against all bacterial pathogens. Besides, the ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>Q. persica</italic> have been also tested against 
 <italic>S. aureus, B. subtilis, E. coli, and K. pneumoniae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>].
</p>
