<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">After the outbreak of SARS-CoV-2, there is an abundance of literature on plant-based materials such as traditional Chinese herbs as a possible cure for symptoms related to SARS like fever control and faster chest clearing. Nonetheless, further clinical trials are needed in treating acute respiratory tract infections (
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Wu 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>). It remains important to recognize new therapeutic and functional agents of infectious diseases using natural sources (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Cragg and Newman, 2013</xref>). During the last decade, scientists have made significant efforts to classify several polyphenols with anti-SARS-CoV activity. However, because of SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 homology, these earlier findings regard naturally occurring substances could capable of inhibiting SARS-CoV-2. A 3CLpro is essential for virus replication and is thus a potential drug goal for the production of therapeutic materials for SARS-CoV as well as SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Yang 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). It could be explained that bioactive compounds extracted from herbs were effectively inhibited the enzymatic activity of SARS-3CLpro in a dose-dependent matter. Rhubarb extracts (an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 13.76±0.03 μg mL
 <sup>-1</sup>) water extract (
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Luo 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009
 </xref>), 
 <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic> water extract (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Lau 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>), litchi seeds-flavonoid extracted (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Gong 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>), and extracted from 
 <italic>Isatis indigotica</italic> root (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Lin 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>) were efficiently effective against CoVs. Further, subsequent herb-derived occurring complexes-includes herbacetin, -rhoifolin, pectolinarin (Jo 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020), sinigrin (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 217 μM), indigo (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 752 μM), -aloe-emodin (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 366 μM), hesperetin- (IC
 <sub>50</sub>:8.3-μM) (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Lin 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>), quercetin- (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 73 μM), epigallocatechin-gallate- (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 73 μM), and gallocatechin-gallate (IC
 <sub>50</sub>: 47 μM) (
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>), inhibited SARS 3CLpro effects. In addition, flavonoids, including isobavaschalcone, herbacetin, helichrysetin, and quercetin 3-β-D-glucoside, could inhibit the enzymatic action of MERS-CoV 3CLpro (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Jo 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019
 </xref>). Helicase protein is often thought to be a possible focus for the production of anti-HCoV agents. Yu 
 <italic>et al.</italic> stated that myricetin and scutellarein had a strong inhibition of nsP13 (SARS-CoV-helicase-protein) 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> by influencing the function of ATPase (
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Yu 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>). Wu 
 <italic>et al.</italic> conducted a massive-scale review of emerging medicines, natural products, and synthetic substances (&gt;10000 substances) to classify successful anti-SARS-CoV agents via a cell-based technique of SARS-CoV and Vero-E6-cells. Ginsenoside Rb1 extracted from 
 <italic>Panax-ginseng</italic>, aescin extracted from horse chestnut, reserpine in the eucalyptus, Rauwolfia genus extracts, and 
 <italic>Lonicera japonica</italic> blocked SARS-CoV replication at non-toxic concentrations (
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Wu 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004
 </xref>). Same as SARS-CoV and HCoV-NL63, SARS-CoV-2-uses the ACE2-host receptor for cellular entry (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Letko 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). Thus, traditional Chinese medicine with ACE
 <sub>2</sub> goal capability keeps a pledge to avoid SARS-CoV-2 infection. In addition, disruption of the 3a receptor by kaempferol-juglanin derivatives may avoid viral release from contaminated cells (
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Schwarz 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>). Significantly, in compromised patients with SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2 infections, the overpowering inflammatory responses have remarkably occurred. As a consequence, anti-inflammatory drugs are expected to reduce the incidence and mortality risk (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Lu, 2020</xref>). In addition, a variety of anti-CoV agents have been reported from natural herbs, but the mechanisms of action have not yet been explained. Recently, the Chinese Health Commission has officially confirmed that natural medicinal herbs could be used in combination with traditional medicine for the treatment of COVID-19 patients (
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Yang 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). Currently, experimental research on the efficacy of natural and medicinal plants focuses on the therapeutic potential of polyphenols against SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Yang 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). As the homogeneity of SARS-CoV is closely similar to SARS-CoV-2, many experiments demonstrating the anti-SARS-CoV-2 behavior of polyphenols or are planned to be released in the immediate future. Medicinal plants provide helpful and preventive treatments but are still desperately needed for the care of patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection, and experience with polyphenols is certainly worth researching. More analysis of polyphenols may contribute to the discovery of innovative anti-CoV compounds that could probably prove effective in the treatment of SARS-CoV-2 or other evolving lethal viral diseases as traditional therapeutic agents. Experimental searching with medicinal plant fields still has some risks and needs massive and further experiments. Polyphenols therapies traditionally used to treat the viral respiratory infection can include specific anti-SARS-CoV-2 substances. This research described many medicinal plants labeled as antiviral/pneumonia-effective which could specifically inhibit SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Zhang 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Letko 
  <italic>et al.</italic> (2020)
 </xref> confirmed how dissimilar lineage B-viruses can recombine to increase passage into human cells and have agreed that human ACE
 <sub>2</sub> is the receptor for the recent SARS-CoV-2 development. However, polyphenols including flavonoids as antiviral agents against MERS, SARS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2 are not hardly investigated and more practical experiments are required. 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref> . illustrated the role of polyphenols against MERS, SARS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
