<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the seven pure EOs extracted from MAPs and tested herein, those being phenolic/carvacrol-rich were the most effective against 
 <italic>A. veronii</italic> bv. 
 <italic>sobria</italic>. More specifically, the EOs from savoury, Spanish oregano and Greek oregano were the most effective growth inhibitors of this particular fish pathogen. In addition, their antibacterial activities were greater than those found for the majority of the 127 combinations of EOs tested and they were ranked in the top-10 most potent agents overall. The enhanced potency of those three pure EOs was most likely due to their greater abundance in highly effective compounds, such as carvacrol (32.8% to 72.0%), γ-terpinene (5.3 to 34.0%) and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene (6.5 to 11.9%) [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].Among the bi- or tripartite mixtures, the combination of Greek oregano with wild carrot in 1:1 ratio (blend #10) showed the best antibacterial activity, exhibiting stronger inhibitory effects compared to the single EOs, as also indicated by the ratio of theoretical IC
 <sub>50</sub> to the measured one. More specifically, the presence of wild carrot in this carvacrol-rich blend seems to play a synergistic role in antibacterial potency, implying a possible positive interaction of its individual constituents such as α-pinene, isoeugenol methyl ether and β-himachalene (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-26-02731">Table S1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="molecules-26-02731-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), with those of Greek oregano. This was also the case for blend #38, where the combination of Greek oregano with Spanish oregano and wild carrot (1:1:1) resulted in a highly effective mix, which showed higher inhibitory activity than the pure individual EOs (i.e., synergistic effects). The antibacterial properties of 
 <italic>Daucus carota</italic> EO against both Gram positive and negative bacteria, as well as fungi, have already been investigated [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], with some studies [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] reporting isoeugenol methyl ether as one of the most active compounds. Moreover, it has been reported that the simultaneous presence of high levels of both hydrophobic and hydrophilic compounds, such as hydrocarbons and phenols, can more readily affect the integrity and permeability of the cell membrane of microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Further studies on the antimicrobial properties of the individual EO components in pure form and in combination are warranted to elucidate the efficacy observed in the above-mentioned EOs mixtures.
</p>
