<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. is reported with an array of ethnobotanical applications due to its extensive pharmacological properties. The plant was chiefly used for the treatment of wounds, as it possesses healing and antiseptic properties [
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Usage of its aerial parts for fumigation, treating skin and respiratory diseases in ancient Europe deliberates on the anti-infective property of the plant [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Besides, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. was used in monasteries in food preparations. These properties depict its efficacy as a culinary and medicinal plant as well. It is believed that Romans and Greek fumigated their surroundings by burning the entire plant [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Treatment of skin diseases like Black Death during the 1340s and several foodborne illnesses was also done using the 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. aqueous extract [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This is supported by modern studies, which have proved the antibacterial efficacy using both normal and MDR strains of virulent bacteria and fungi [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In the 1980s, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. was recommended for treating respiratory disorders raised due to the inflammation of upper respiratory tract mucous membranes, including whooping cough, bronchitis, and catarrh [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, application of thyme (
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L.) and primrose (
 <italic>Primula vulgaris</italic>) extract has demonstrated beneficiary in clinical trials against bronchitis and other respiratory disease related symptoms [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Experts have also recommended the use of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. in cases of bacterial and fungal infections. The plant is expected to render a possible inhibition of bacterial adsorption and biofilm matrix formation [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. was believed to possess antiseptic, astringent, carminative, tonic, and anthelminthic properties. The plant has gained much popularity due to the profound activity shown towards intestinal infections and infestations caused by ascarids, hookworms, fungi, yeast, and bacteria. It has also found its importance in dermatological issues like acne, oily skin, dermatitis, bug bites as well as sciatica and rheumatic aches. In support of this, modern pharmacological investigations have come up with several findings that satisfactorily decipher the antifungal nature of different extracts and compounds of the plant [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. It is reported that, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. relieves bites and stings, and the neurological issues associated with it. In aromatherapy, red 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. oil and white 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. oil are used to treat skin disorders as well as body pains [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Modern anti-inflammatory investigations have revealed the efficacy of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. in the amelioration of oxidative stress and cell mediated immune response [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].
</p>
