<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains were grown in tryptic soy broth (TSB) and biofilm ability was studied using a semi-quantitative adherence assay on 96-well tissue culture plates (Nunc, Roskilde, Denmark) as described previously [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-23-02672" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. After incubation for 24 h at 37 °C, the absorbance at 570 nm (OD
 <sub class="sub">570</sub>) was recorded as a measure of total growth. An overnight culture grown in TSB (Biorad, Marnes la Coquette, France) at 37 °C was diluted to 1:100 in TSB with 2% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) glucose to maximize 
 <italic class="italic">ica</italic> operon induction [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-23-02672" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. A total of 200 µL of these cell suspensions was transferred in a U-bottomed 96-well microtiter plate. Each strain was tested in triplicate. Wells with sterile TSB alone was served as controls. 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> ATCC 25,923 and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> ATCC 43,300 were used as a positive control. The plates were incubated aerobically for 24 h at 37 °C. Furthermore, the culture was removed, and plates were washed three times with 200 µL of phosphate-buffered saline (7 mM Na
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>HPO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, 3 mM NaH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>PO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and 130 mM NaCl at pH 7.4) to remove non-adherent cells and dried in an inverted position. Adherent biofilm was fixed with 95% ethanol and was stained with 100 µL of 1% (wt vol
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) crystal violet (Merck, Lyon, France) for 5 min. Then, unbound crystal violet was removed and the wells were washed three times with sterile distilled water. The water was then absorbed and the microtiter plate was air dried for 30 min. The optical density (OD) of each well was measured at 570 nm using an automated Multiskan reader (Gio De Vita, Rome, Italy). Biofilm formation was categorized as highly positive (OD
 <sub class="sub">570</sub> ≥ 1), low-grade positive (0.1 ≤ OD
 <sub class="sub">570</sub> &lt; 1), or negative (OD
 <sub class="sub">570</sub> &lt; 0.1).
</p>
