<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and reagents</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The milk thistle (
   <span class="italic">Silybium marianum</span> L.) seeds were collected from plants growing in region of Sousse (Centre of Tunisia), during April and June, 2012. The seeds were authenticated at the National Botanical Research Institute Tunisia (INRAT). Seeds were selected according to external color; green seeds were chosen as immature stage, mahogany brown seeds as the intermediate stage and dark brown seeds as the last stage of maturity (mature stage).
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chloroform, methanol and petroleum ether were purchased from Lab-Scan analytical Sciences (Poland). Ethanol, diethyl ether and n-hexane were obtained from Scientific Limited (Northampton, UK). 2, 7-Dichlorofluorescein, DPPH (2, 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl radical) and the standard 1-eicosanol were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, Co. (St. Louis, MO, USA). Potassium hydroxide pellets and anhydrous sodium sulfate were obtained from AppliChem (Darmstadt, Germany). ABTS, 2,29-azinobis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6- sulfonic acid) diammonium salt, and potassium persulfate (di-potassium peroxdisulfate) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Poole, Dorset, UK).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seed oil extraction, saponification and thin layer chromatography</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oils were extracted by the method of Folch et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Seeds (2.5 g) were washed with boiling water for 5 min and then crushed in a mortar with chloroform/methanol (2:1, 
   <span class="italic">v</span>/v). The mixture was centrifuged at 3000 g for 15 min and the lower chloroformic phase containing the total lipids was kept and dried in a rotary evaporator at 40 °C.
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The saponification and the Thin layer chromatography analysis of unsaponoifiables were done according to the previous reports [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. The unsaponifiable fraction and the authentic 1-eicosanol were spotted on preparative silica gel thin-layer plates (silica gel 60G F254) and developed with hexane–diethyl ether (65:35, 
   <span class="italic">v</span>/v). After development, the plate was sprayed with 2,7-dichlorofluorescein and viewed under UV light. The band corresponding to aliphatic alcohols was scraped, extracted three times with chloroform–diethyl ether (1:1, v/v), filtered to remove the residual silica, dried in a rotary evaporator and stored at − 10 °C.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of policosanol by GC-MS</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC-MS analyses were performed using a capillary HP-5MS column (30 m × 0.25 mm I.D., 0.25 μm film thickness; Agilent Technologies) with gas chromatography (Agilent Technologies 7820A) coupled directly to the mass detector (Agilent Technologies 5975 series MSD). Helium was used as carrier gas, with a constant flow rate of 1 ml/ min. The injector and detector temperatures were 230 °C. The oven temperature was programmed from 150 to 320 °C at 10 °C·min − 1 from 150 to 250 °C and at 5 °C·min − 1 from 250 to 320 °C. Manual injection of 1 μL of the aliphatic alcohol solution was performed in the split mode at a 10:1 split ratio. The policosanol compounds were identified by comparing their mass spectra with the Wiley 275.L Mass Spectral Library.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of in vitro antioxidant activity</div>
  <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DPPH test</div>
   <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity of seed oil samples was determined using DPPH radicals as described by Kozłowska et al. [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. Fifty mg of oil was dissolved in 3 mL of ethyl acetate and then 1 mL of oil solution was diluted with 2.75 mL ethyl acetate. 0.25 mL of DPPH solution (1 mM) was added and the mixture was shaken vigorously for 10s in a vortex apparatus. After 20 min, the absorbance was measured at 515 nm using UV/Vis scanning spectrophotometer (Model 2650, Labomed, Inc. U.S.A) and the percent of inhibition was calculated using this formula:
   </p>
   <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inhibition (%) = {(Absorbance of the control – Absorbance of sample)/Absorbance of the control}/ × 100.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ABTS antioxidant assay</div>
   <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ABTS radical scavenging capacity of the oil was measured using the method described by Rubalya and Neelamegam [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. The ABTS
    <span class="sup">+</span> radical was generated by oxidation of 2.5 ml of ABTS solution (7 mM) with potassium persulfate (14.7 mM). The mixture is kept in the dark for 16 h at room temperature (25 °C). Before usage, the mixture was diluted with water to obtain an absorbance of 0.70 ± 0.05 at 734 nm. The radical scavenging activity is assessed by mixing 2 ml of this diluted ABTS+ solution with different oil samples dissolved in benzene. After 30 min, the percentage inhibition at 734 nm was calculated for each sample relative to blank absorbance. The percentage inhibition of ABTS radical by the oils was calculated using the equation described in the DPPH assay.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of in vitro anti-arthritic activity</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vitro anti-arthritic activity was evaluated using bovine serum protein denaturation method and egg albumin denaturation method [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>] with some modifications [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
  </p>
  <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bovine serum albumin (BSA) denaturation method</div>
   <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Test solution (0.5 ml) consisted of 0.45 ml bovine serum albumin (0.5% 
    <span class="italic">w</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span> aqueous solution) and 0.05 ml of oil samples. Then the samples were incubated at 37 °C for 20 min followed by incubation at 57 °C for 3 min. After cooling the samples, 2.5 ml phosphate buffer (pH 6.3) was added to each tube. UV-Visible spectrophotometer was used to measure the absorbance at 660 nm. The control represents 100% protein denaturation. For test control solution (0.5 ml) 0.05 ml distilled water was used instead of oil sample while for product control (0.5 ml) 0.45 ml distilled water and test solution (0.05 ml) were used. The percentage inhibition of protein denaturation was calculated by the following formula:
   </p>
   <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Percentage inhibition = {(Absorbance of test solution- Absorbance of the control)/Absorbance of the control}/ × 100.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Egg albumin denaturation method</div>
   <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reaction mixture (5 ml) was comprised of 0.2 ml of fresh hen’s egg albumin, 2.8 ml of phosphate buffered saline (PBS, pH 6.4) and 2mlof oil samples. Similar volume of double distilled water served as control. Then the mixture was incubated at 37 °C in the incubator for 15 min and then heated at 7°0 C for 5 min. After cooling, their absorbance was measured at 660 nm by using pure blank. The percentage inhibition of protein denaturation was calculated as mentioned in Bovine serum albumin (BSA) denaturation method.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of the studied samples was performed in triplicate and the results were expressed as means± standard deviation (SD). Statistical analysis was performed by using the Proc ANOVA in SAS (Software version 8). Duncan’s Multiple Range Test was applied. The Pearson correlation coefficient (r) was used to examine the relation between the main parameters.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
