<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">idr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">idr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7723237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">277295</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S277295</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>In-vitro Antimicrobial Activity of Essential Oils and Spices Powder of some Medicinal Plants&#x000a0;Against <italic>Bacillus</italic> Species Isolated from Raw and Processed Meat</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Hetta et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Hetta et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8541-7304</contrib-id><name><surname>Hetta</surname><given-names>Helal F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kh Meshaal</surname><given-names>Ahmed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5580-1559</contrib-id><name><surname>Algammal</surname><given-names>Abdelazeem M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yahia</surname><given-names>Ramadan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6430-7541</contrib-id><name><surname>Makharita</surname><given-names>Rabab R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0006"><sup>6</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0007"><sup>7</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marraiki</surname><given-names>Najat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0008"><sup>8</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3471-184X</contrib-id><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Muhammad Ajmal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0009"><sup>9</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Hebat-Allah M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Batiha</surname><given-names>Gaber El-Saber</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0010"><sup>10</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Internal Medicine, <institution>University of Cincinnati, College of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Cincinnati</addr-line>, <addr-line>OH</addr-line>
<addr-line>45267-0595</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, <institution>Assuit University</institution>, <addr-line>Assuit</addr-line>
<addr-line>71515</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Botany and Microbiology, Faculty of Science, <institution>Al-Azhar University</institution>, <addr-line>Assiut</addr-line>
<addr-line>71524</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Department of Bacteriology, Immunology and Mycology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, <institution>Suez Canal University</institution>, <addr-line>Ismailia</addr-line>
<addr-line>41522</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Pharmacy, <institution>Deraya University</institution>, <addr-line>Minia</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label>Biology Department, Faculty of Science and Arts Khulais, <institution>University of Jeddah</institution>, <addr-line>Jeddah</addr-line>, <addr-line>21959</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label>Botany Department, Faculty of Science, <institution>Suez Canal University</institution>, <addr-line>Ismailia</addr-line>
<addr-line>41522</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label>Department of Botany and Microbiology, <institution>College of Science, King Saud University</institution>, <addr-line>Riyadh</addr-line>
<addr-line>11451</addr-line>, <country>Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="aff0009"><label>9</label>Department of Pharmacognosy, Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences, <institution>Government College University</institution>, <addr-line>Faisalabad</addr-line>, <country>Pakistan</country></aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>10</label>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, Faculty of Veterinary Medicines, <institution>Damanhour University</institution>, <addr-line>Damanhour</addr-line>
<addr-line>22511</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Helal F Hetta <institution>Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, Assuit University</institution>, <addr-line>Assuit</addr-line><addr-line>71515</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country> Email helalhetta@aun.edu.eg</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><fpage>4367</fpage><lpage>4378</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Hetta et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hetta et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#x02013; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="s2001"><title>Background and Aim</title><p><italic>Bacillus</italic> species are widely distributed microorganisms in nature that are responsible for outbreaks of food poisoning and a common cause of food spoilage. This study aimed to isolate and identify foodborne <italic>Bacillus</italic> species from meat and to determine the antimicrobial activities of commercial essential oils and spices powder extracted from certain medicinal plants.</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p>Sixty meat samples were collected in Assiut city and subdivided into raw meat and processed meat. <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp were isolated and identified according to their cultural characters, biochemical reactions, serological typing, and 16S rRNA gene sequencing. The antibacterial activity of essential oils and spices powder was measured by using well-diffusion and microbial count techniques.</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>The prevalence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in the examined raw meat samples and processed meat samples was 13.34%, and 26.67%, respectively. There was a marked decrease in the total <italic>Bacillus</italic> species count after treatment of minced beef with essential oils and spices powder compared to the untreated one. Black seed oil was the most potent antibacterial essential oil among the tested oils present in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Essential oils and spices powder of certain medicinal plants (cumin: <italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic>, black seeds: <italic>Nigella sativa</italic>, cloves: <italic>Syzygium aromaicum</italic>, cinnamon: <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic>, and Marjoram: <italic>Origanum majorana</italic>) have a potential in vitro antimicrobial activity against <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. Furthermore, <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> oil exhibited the most potent antibacterial activity against <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Bacillus</italic> spp.</kwd><kwd>essential oils</kwd><kwd>processed meat</kwd><kwd>fresh meat</kwd><kwd>sequencing</kwd><kwd>antibacterial activity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="11"/><ref-count count="61"/><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Meat is a daily part of the internationally human diet. It contains proteins (with all the essential amino acids), vitamins (A, B12, B6, D, and E), and minerals (iron and zinc), which are very important to human growth and well-being.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Because of its nutrient content, meat is a highly perishable food since it represents good media for microorganism proliferation.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> According to the World Health Organization, 30% of the inhabitants in industrialized countries suffer every year from foodborne diseases<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> with most of the cases attributed to the consumption of meat.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p><italic>Bacillus</italic> species are widely distributed microorganisms in nature. They have often been found to be responsible for outbreaks of food poisoning and are a common cause of food spoilage.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> is the most frequently isolated of naturally occurring bacilli. However, accurate identification for these bacterial species in many cases is difficult since they share many important morphological and biochemical properties.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></p><p>Different types of culture media such as MYP (mannitol&#x02013;egg yolk&#x02013;phenol red&#x02013;polymyxin&#x02013;agar) and PEMBA (polymyxin&#x02013;pyruvate&#x02013;egg yolk&#x02013;mannitol&#x02013;bromthymol blue-agar) were used for detection and the selective isolation of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. from food. The selectivity of these media is based on the hydrolysis of egg yolk lecithin and the absence of the use of mannitol by <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. besides the presence of selective compounds like polymyxin.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>Several previous studies reported the emergence of multidrug-resistant bacterial pathogens that call for the need of natural herbal alternatives to the commonly used antimicrobial agents.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9&#x02013;14</xref></p><p>Several molecular techniques that rely on DNA sequencing have been used to reveal the genetic relationship of bacillus strains.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Enterobacterial repetitive intergenic consensus-PCR (ERIC-PCR) was used to screen for genetic relatedness. On the other hand, the application of pulsed-field gel electrophoresis (PFGE) has been proven to be useful for the discrimination and epidemiological characterization of <italic>B. cereus</italic> group strains.<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p><p>The 16S rRNA gene sequencing will continue to be the gold standard for identifying bacteria. The automation of this technique could enable it to be used routinely in clinical microbiology laboratories to replace the traditional phenotypic tests.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p><p><italic>Bacillus oceanisediminis</italic> H2T was first isolated from sediment of the South Sea in China<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and was found to be most closely related to <italic>Bacillus firmus</italic><xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and <italic>Bacillus infantis</italic><xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> by 16S rRNA gene analysis. Recently, <italic>Bacillus oceanisediminis</italic> species is a rod-shaped aerobic bacterium, Gram-positive and spore-forming, and first isolated from marine sediment of the South Korean coast.<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p><p>The genus <italic>Brevibacillus</italic> was reported by Shida<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> with the reclassification of 10 species of the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic>. A recent study reported that, 25 bacterial isolates were identified by 16S rRNA sequences analysis collected from public tap water in India, from the 25 isolates, 5 were of <italic>Bacillus</italic> (<italic>B. pumilus, B. flexus, B. megaterium, B. marisflavi and B. oceanosediminis</italic>).<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p><p>In a recent study, Fancello et al reported that 72 isolates were purified from olive samples collected in Italy and according to the 16S rDNA sequencing analysis, the bacterial isolates primarily fitting to <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp., <italic>Brevibacillus</italic> spp., <italic>Micrococcus</italic> spp., <italic>Pantoea</italic> spp., <italic>Kocuria</italic> spp., <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> spp., <italic>Lysinibacillus</italic> spp. and <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> spp. From them 17 isolates belonging to <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. as follows: 11 strains as <italic>B. amyloliquefaciens</italic>, 5 strains as <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and 1 strain as <italic>B. megaterium</italic>. Also, 18 isolates belonging to <italic>Brevibacillus</italic> spp. as follows: 9 strains as <italic>Br. agri</italic>, 6 strains as <italic>Br. invocatus</italic> and 3 strains as <italic>Br. parabrevis</italic>.<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> This study aimed to isolate and identify the foodborne <italic>Bacillus</italic> species by using conventional and molecular techniques and to determine the antimicrobial activities of commercial essential oils and spices powder extracted from certain medicinal plants (cumin: <italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic>, black seeds: <italic>Nigella sativa</italic>, cloves: <italic>Syzygium aromaicum</italic>, cinnamon: <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic>, and Marjoram: <italic>Origanum majorana</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Sample Collection and Processing</title><p>Sixty meat samples (n = 60), including raw meat (n = 15), and processed meat (n = 45), were collected from butchery and markets in Assiut city, Egypt. The collected samples were transferred to the microbiology laboratory at the Faculty of Science (Al-Azhar University, Assiut Branch, Egypt) as soon as possible. The obtained samples were immediately cut and minced aseptically with a grinder through a 4 mm sterilized plate diameter (AC110V, China). All samples were kept at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;C for further analysis. The raw meat samples included beef, mutton meat, veal meat and chicken, while the processed meat samples included beef burgers, beef luncheon, ground beef, ground chicken, beef sausage, basterma, chicken luncheon and chicken burgers.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Isolation and Identification of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp</title><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3001"><title>Isolation of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp</title><p>Three media were used for the isolation, and identification of <italic>Bacillus species</italic>; nutrient agar (Difco), Mannitol Egg Yolk Polymyxin agar (MEYP) (Difco, USA) (It depends on 1) selective inhibitory agent; polymyxin that inhibit the growth of other bacterial pathogens and contaminants. 2) Indicator systems; mannitol and phenol red, and egg yolk)<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and trypticase soy agar (Difco, USA) (support the growth of a wide variety of fastidious microorganisms).<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Twenty-five grams from each sample have been aseptically weighed and added to 225 mL of peptone water and overnight incubation at 37 &#x000b0;C in a shaker incubator. After 24 hours of enrichment, 0.1 mL of the broth was streaked on nutrient agar, MEYP agar, and trypticase soy agar plates and incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 24&#x02013;48 hours. The characteristic colonies on MEYP agar are pink in color and were surrounded by a precipitate zone with the same color.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3002"><title>Phenotypic Identification of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp</title><p>The obtained pure suspected colonies were identified according to their culture characters on nutrient agar, MEYP agar, and trypticase soy agar, morphological characters using Gram&#x02019;s stain, and biochemical reactions including oxidase test, urease test, catalase test, indole production test, Voges&#x02013;Proskauer test, citrate utilization test, and sugar fermentation pattern.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002-s3003"><title>Molecular Typing of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp</title><p>A single pure colony of the isolate was taken and streaked on a nutrient agar plate and incubated overnight at 37 &#x000b0;C until a good colony morphology and size were obtained. DNA extraction was carried out according to the QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (Qiagen, USA). The 16S rRNA gene was amplified as described by Lane,<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> using the universal primers 27F and 1492R. The PCR conditions were as follows: initial denaturation at 94 &#x000ba;C for 5 min, then 30 cycles of denaturation at 94 &#x000ba;C for 40 sec., annealing at 52 &#x000ba;C for 30 sec., and extension at 72 &#x000ba;C for 1 min., and final extension at 72 &#x000ba;C for 7 min.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p><p>The PCR amplicon was purified by the QIAquick gel extraction kit (Qiagen, USA) and sequenced using the same pair of primers. The sequence of the PCR amplicon was visualized and annotated using the Applied Biosystem Automated 3730XL DNA sequencer (Solgent Company, Daejeon, South Korea).</p><p>The BLAST tool from the National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI) website has been used to analyze the sequence obtained. Phylogenetic analysis of sequence was constructed using the software MEGA 6.0.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>Assessment of Antibacterial Activity of Some Medicinal Plants</title><sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001"><title>Plant Samples Collection and Preparation</title><p>Five plant samples including cumin (<italic>Cuminumcyminum</italic>), black seeds (<italic>Nigella sativa</italic>), cloves (<italic>Syzygium aromaicum</italic>), cinnamon (<italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic>), and marjoram (<italic>Origanum Majorana</italic>) have been used in the treatment of beef meat samples. The powder samples were collected from the local market in Assiut city. The plant volatile oil samples were collected from National Research Center&#x02014;Unit of oils extraction.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003-s3002"><title>Treatment of Minced Beef Meat Samples with Both the Spices Powder and Essential Oils of the Plant Samples Separately for the Bacterial Count</title><p>Minced beef samples were mixed in a sterile mixer with spices powder (0.5% and 1% of minced beef meat as weight/weight), and the essential oils (0.25% and 0.5% of minced beef meat as volume/weight). Three groups were made from the samples; the first group was treated with either 0.5% or 1% spices, the second group was treated with either 0.25% or 0.5% essential oils, and the third group was kept as a control group. Each sample was packed in polyethylene bags and stored at 4 &#x000b0;C &#x000b1; 1, and the bacterial count was done at intervals of 0, 3, 6, 9, 12, and 15 days.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003-s3003"><title>Antimicrobial Activity of Essential Oils and Spices Powder of the Plant Samples Using the Well-Diffusion Assay</title><p>The antibacterial activity of essential oils and spices powder was examined in a well-diffusion assay, by adding the essential oils or the powder extract into the well of agar plates inoculated with the isolated strain that was confirmed to be <italic>Bacillus species</italic> based on culture characteristics, biochemical reactions, and 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p>The agar plates were prepared as follows: a pure culture of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. was grown in nutrient broth at 37 &#x000b0;C for 18&#x02013;24 hours in shaker incubator until the final concentration was 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL. Twenty millilitres of plain nutrient agar was poured into each sterile petri dish. A 6 mm well punched in the solid agar plates via a sterile cork borer. Each plate was surface inoculated by 0.2 mL of the culture of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. broth in triplicates.</p><p>Serial concentrations of each tested essential oil were made (% w/v) in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) (10% aqueous) solvent as follows: 50 and 100 mg/mL and sterilized by filtration by passing through a 0.22-&#x003bc;m membrane filter. DMSO without the essential oil was used as a control. For spices powder, 100 g of the powder was dissolved in 500 mL ethyl alcohol<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> and left for 72 hours at room temperature on a shaker,<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> then the extract was dried by rotary evaporator with a vacuum at 25 &#x000b0;C. The residues obtained were weighed and reconstituted by ethyl alcohol and sterilized by filtration by passing through a 0.22-&#x003bc;m membrane filter. The concentrations made from each residue were as follows: 50 and 100 mg/mL. Fifty microlitres of each tested sample was pipette to the wells of the inoculated agar plates aseptically.<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35&#x02013;37</xref> The plates were incubated at 35 &#x000b0;C for 24 hours. After incubation, the inhibitory zones were measured in millimeters.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>GraphPad Prism program version 8.0.1 (244) (San Diego, CA, USA) was used for statistical analysis. <italic>P</italic>-values less than 0.05 were considered significant. Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test was used when groups compared to the control group to analyze the results for statistically significant differences.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Isolation and Identification of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp</title><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3001"><title>Conventional Methods (Cultural and Biochemical Methods)</title><p>Only 14 isolates out of 297 presumptive isolated colonies have been characterized as <italic>Bacillus species</italic> among all the examined samples. The details are as follows: <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. have been detected in 2 out of 6 fresh chicken meat samples (33.34%), 3 out of 12 beef luncheon samples (25.0%), 5 out of 12 ground beef samples&#x000a0;(41.67%), only 1 out of 6 basterma samples(16.67%), and 3 out of 3 beef burger samples (100.0%), while <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. has not been detected in fresh veal meat, fresh mutton meat and chicken luncheon samples (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Occurrence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in Samples Collected During the Three Periods</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Food Sample</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">First Season</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Second Season</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Third Season</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Samples Tested</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Presumptive Colonies</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occurrence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in Samples</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in Samples</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Samples Tested</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Presumptive Colonies</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occurrence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in Samples</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in Samples</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Samples Tested</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Presumptive Colonies</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occurrence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in Samples</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in Samples</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh veal meat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh chicken meat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh mutton meat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef luncheon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken luncheon</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ground beef</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basterma</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef burger</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 isolate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 isolates</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>Regarding the phenotypic characteristics; <italic>Bacillus oceanisediminis</italic> is a Gram-positive, rod-shaped, aerobic, motile, catalase-positive, and endospore-forming microorganism. The optimal growth temperature was 37 &#x000b0;C; the optimal pH was 7.0. Also, according to the results obtained from the API 50 CHB/E medium, the characteristics strongly confirmed that the isolate belongs to the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic>. Concerning the phenotypic characteristics of <italic>Brevibacillus invocatus</italic>; it is a Gram-positive, motile, rod-shaped, strictly aerobic microorganism. The growth at 30 &#x000b0;C is initially slow, with a more rapid increase in growth rate following 24 hours&#x02019; incubation; after 3&#x02013;4 days, the slightly umbonate colonies are 1&#x02013;8 mm in diameter, with slightly irregular margins. Colonies are brownish yellow, some with a single whitish concentric zone at the margin, and they are butyrous and have silky surfaces; the centers are opaque and the edges are translucent. <italic>Brevibacillus invocatus</italic> is catalase-positive. Nitrate reduction-negative. Casein, gelatin, starch, and urea are not hydrolyzed and indole is not produced) (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Biochemical Reaction Results of Selected Strains</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>Bacillus oceanisedimins</italic></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>Brevibacillus invocatus</italic></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Test</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Result</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolation source</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minced beef</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolation source</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minced beef</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motility</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Motility</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morphology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spore forming<break/>rods</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morphology</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spore-forming rods</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gram-stain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gram-stain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature for growth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth temperatures range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#x02212;35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature optimum range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x02013;45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;8.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH for growth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH optimum range</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indole</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl for growth (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#x02013;12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate reduction</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indole</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Casein hydrolysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl red</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gelatin hydrolysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Voges-Proskauer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea hydrolysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch hydrolysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycerol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assimilation of:</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ribose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Alanine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Alanine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Aspartate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Fructose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mannitol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fumarate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Gluconate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saccharose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DL-Glycerate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strach</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactulose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gelatin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ve</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-ve</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> +ve, positive; -ve, negative.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2001-s3002"><title>Molecular Identification of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. Using 16S rRNA Gene Sequencing</title><p>Two isolates (AKM5 &#x00026; AKM6) from those, which identified to be <italic>Bacillus species</italic>, were chosen to be additionally confirmed via 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis using the BLASTn tool of the National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI). The isolate AKM5 was related to <italic>Bacillus oceanisedimins</italic> and the isolate AKM6 was related to <italic>Brevibacillus invocatus</italic>. Our sequences were submitted to the GenBank database with the accession numbers KX863513 for AKM5 isolate and accession number KX863514 for AKM6 isolate (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Sequence Analysis of the 16S rDNA Gene by BLASTn Tool</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolates</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name Of Closely Associated Strain</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identity %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Bank Accession Number of Closely Associated Strain</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AKM5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus oceanisediminis</italic> strain C22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.18%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT457440.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AKM6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brevibacillus invocatus</italic> strain B32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.23%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MH587029.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>A phylogenetic tree based on the assessment of the 16S rRNA sequence with reference strains was created. The phylogenetic analysis was made with 1,500 bp and 2000bp sequences for <italic>Bacillus</italic> using the software MEGA 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>).<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic dendrogram based on 16S rRNA gene sequences showing the site of strain AKM5 &#x00026; AKM6 between members of diverse genus species. The evolutionary history was inferred using the UPGMA method.<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> The optimal tree with the sum of branch length = 0.13321378 is shown. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths in the same units as those of the evolutionary distances used to infer the phylogenetic tree. The evolutionary distances were computed using the Kimura 2-parameter method<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> and are in the units of the number of base substitutions per site. The analysis involved 21 nucleotide sequences. All positions containing gaps and missing data were eliminated. There were a total of 258 positions in the final dataset. Evolutionary analyses were conducted in MEGA6.<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref></p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-13-4367-g0001"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Assessment of Antibacterial Activity of Some Medicinal Plants</title><sec id="s0003-s2002-s3001"><title>Treatment of Minced Beef with Plant Samples for the Microbial Count</title><p>The results show that the treatment of minced beef with a level of 0.50% essential oil has more antibacterial activity than 0.25% essential oils of the same plant on <italic>Bacillus species</italic> and the same matter for spices powder. The differences between the control group and each treated minced beef sample after 15 days&#x02019; storage were statistically significant, except for samples treated with 0.25% essential oil of marjoram it was non-significant. Generally, the essential oils have better antibacterial activity than spices powder of the same plants. The details of the results were as follows:</p><p>Changes in <italic>Bacillus</italic> species Log<sub>10</sub> count (CFU/g) in minced beef samples treated with essential oils during storage at 4&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C up to 15 days:</p><p><italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. was counted in different minced samples contain essential oils of cumin, black seeds, cloves, cinnamon, and marjoram under levels of 0.25% and 0.50% and control sample during storage at 4&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C up to 15 days. The results revealed that <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. counts increased in the control sample; thus, its counts at zero time were (3.333 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g) and reached to (3.439 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g) at the end of storage periods. However, for the treated samples, after 12 days of the refrigerated storage, the microbial count reached zero except samples treated with marjoram oil 0.25%, it reached zero count after 15 days of storage. After 15 days of storage, the difference between the control group and the samples treated with 0.25% essential oil of cumin, black seeds, cloves and cinnamon was statistically significant (p = 0.0138, 0.0011, 0.0052 and 0.0088, respectively). Moreover, after 15 days of storage, the difference between the control group and all samples treated with 0.5% essential oil of cumin, black seeds, cloves, cinnamon and marjoram was statistically significant (p = 0.0010, 0.0001, 0.0013, 0.0037 and 0.0047, respectively). However, the difference was non-significant between the control group and the samples treated with 0.25 essential oil of marjoram (p = 0.1412) after 15 days of storage (<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Changes in <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. Log<sub>10</sub> Count (CFU/g) of Minced Samples Treated with Essential Oils During Storage at 4&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C Up to 15 Days</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean&#x000b1;SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.349</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.372</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.379</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.405</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.380&#x000b1;0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin 0.25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.978</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.904</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.654</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.940&#x000b1;1.509</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0138</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.813</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.532</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.399&#x000b1;1.541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds 0.25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.876</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.749</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.708</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.389&#x000b1;1.522</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.557</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77&#x000b1;1.207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves 0.25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.939</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.881</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.579</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.857&#x000b1;1.444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0052</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.929</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.827</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.613</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.395&#x000b1;1.531</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0013</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon 0.25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.898</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.807</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.699</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.933&#x000b1;1.506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0088</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.153</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.807</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.510&#x000b1;1.659</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0037</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram 0.25%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.162</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.793</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.545&#x000b1;1.256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1412</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.072</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.893</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.518&#x000b1;1.665</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0047</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Note:</bold> P: Significance between control group and each tested spices powder.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> S.D, std. deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Changes in <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. Log<sub>10</sub> counts (CFU/g) of treated minced samples with essential oils during storage at 6&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C for up to 15 days.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-13-4367-g0002"/></fig></p><p>Changes in <italic>Bacillus</italic> species Log<sub>10</sub> counts (CFU/g) in minced beef samples treated with spices powder throughout storage at 4&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C up to 15 days:</p><p><italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. was counted in different minced samples contain spices powder of cumin, black seeds, cloves, cinnamon, and marjoram under levels of 0.5% and 1.0% and control sample during storage at 4&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C up to 15 days. The results revealed that <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. count increased in the control sample; thus, its counts at zero time were (3.333 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g) and reached to (3.439 log<sub>10</sub> CFU/g) at the end of storage periods. Concerning the treated samples, the microbial count reached zero after 12 days of the refrigerated storage, except samples treated with cinnamon and marjoram spices powder under the level of 0.5%, which reached zero count after 15 days of storage. After 15 days of storage the difference between the control group and the samples treated with 0.5% spices powder of cumin, black seeds, cloves, cinnamon and marjoram was statistically significant (p = 0.0229, 0.0082, 0.0136, 0.0114 and 0.0184, respectively). Furthermore, the difference between the control group and the samples treated with 1% spices powder of cumin, black seeds, cloves, cinnamon and marjoram was statistically significant (p = 0.0029, &#x0003c;0.0001, 0.0014, 0.0044 and 0.0049) after 15 days of storage (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Changes in <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. Log<sub>10</sub> Count (CFU/g) of Minced Samples Treated with Spices Powders During Storage at 4&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C Up to 15 Days</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean&#x000b1;SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.349</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.372</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.379</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.405</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.380<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>0.038</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.327</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.634</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.046<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>1.602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0229</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin 1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.717</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.526<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>1.682</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0029</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.188</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.833</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.506</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.929<bold>&#x000b1;</bold>1.512</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0082</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds 1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.448</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.923&#x000b1;1.444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.272</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.935</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.613</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.991&#x000b1;1.558</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0136</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves 1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.959</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.458&#x000b1;1.608</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0014</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.935</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.569</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.265&#x000b1;1.168</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0114</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon 1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.974</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.634</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.872&#x000b1;1.484</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0044</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram 0.50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.291</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.833</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.592</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.343&#x000b1;1.198</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0184</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram 1.0%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.949</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.654</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.463</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.888&#x000b1;1.487</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0049</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Note:</bold> P: Significance between control group and each tested spices powder.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> S.D, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Changes in <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. Log<sub>10</sub> counts (CFU/g) of treated minced samples with spices powder throughout storage at 6&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C for up to 15 days.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-13-4367-g0003"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002-s3002"><title>Antimicrobial Activity of Essential Oils and Spices Powder Using the Well-Diffusion Assay Technique</title><p>The growth inhibition zones were measured are listed in <xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. The black seeds had the highest antibacterial activity followed by marjoram then cloves then cumin and finally the least antibacterial activity for cinnamon. Generally, the antibacterial activity of essential oils is stronger than the spices powder for the same plant (<xref rid="t0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Antibacterial Activities of Some Essential Oils and Spices Powder Against <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Essential Oil of the Plant</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibition Zone (mm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spices Powder of the Plant</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibition Zone (mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin oil 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin oil 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumin 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds oil 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds oil 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black seeds 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves oil 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves oil 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cloves 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon oil 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon oil 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinnamon 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram oil 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram 50 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram oil 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marjoram 100 mg/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>The uncontrolled widespread use of antibiotics in veterinary and health sectors as well as the bacterial antibiotic-resistant genes are incriminated in the development of such multidrug-resistant strains.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38&#x02013;41</xref> The emergence of multidrug-resistant bacteria call for the need of natural herbal alternatives to the commonly used antimicrobial agents.<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42&#x02013;51</xref> The foodborne diseases resulting from the consumption of Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria-contaminated food have been of vital concern to public health. Good hygiene practices, adequate preservative techniques for processed foods and the use of antimicrobial substances such as antibiotics are the various control and treatment methods in developed countries.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></p><p>Many studies stated that food analysis is a useful tool for identifying bacterial species including <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. which cause foodborne diseases.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Our results showed that 14 isolates were identified as <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. by cultural, biochemical, and serological characteristics. <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. was not recognized in fresh veal meat samples, 2 of 6 fresh chicken meat samples (33.34%), not recognized in fresh mutton meat, 3 of 12 beef luncheon (25.0%), not recognized in chicken luncheon, 5 of 12 ground beef (41.67%), only 1 of 6 basterma (16.67%), and 3 of 3 beef burger (100.0%). These results assure the fact that <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. are associated with food from animal sources either fresh or processed and not specifically with beef.</p><p>In light of our results, we found that the highest occurrence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. is in beef burger samples, which may indicate that the prevalence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. is higher in processed meat than in fresh meet. According to 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis, the two identified isolates are <italic>Bacillus oceanisedimins</italic> and <italic>Brevibacillus invocatus</italic>; thus to our knowledge, this is the first report isolating both <italic>Bacillus oceanisedimins</italic> and <italic>Brevibacillus invocatus</italic> from both fresh and processed meat samples, and more investigations are required to identify their roles in meat samples.</p><p>The results of the treatment of minced beef with essential oils of cumin, black seeds, cloves, cinnamon, and marjoram under levels 0.25% and 0.50% during storage showed that statistically significant decrease in <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. counts in comparison to control samples during storage except for essential oil of marjoram under levels 0.25%, accordingly we recommend the use of marjoram essential oil not less than 1% (volume/weight). Furthermore, there was an increase in <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. count in the control sample. Moreover, after storage for 6 days <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. disappeared in minced beef samples contained black seeds essential oils with level 0.50%. After 15 days of the refrigerated storage, there were no any <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in all studied samples except the sample contained marjoram oil at 0.25% and 0.50% and the control.</p><p>The disappearance of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in samples treated with essential oils of black seeds, cloves, cumin, and cinnamon meanwhile increased the <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. count in a control sample, after 15 days of storage, indicates that the disappearance of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. in treated samples may be attributed to the antimicrobial activity of these essential oils. One of the most important findings of the current study was the reduced effectiveness of the major components of essential oil compared with whole oil mixtures. Many reports of the antibacterial activity of essential oil components have tested their efficacy against vegetative bacterial cells.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55&#x02013;57</xref></p><p>The results of antimicrobial activity of essential oils and spices powder using Well-diffusion assays showed that the black seeds essential oil had the strongest antibacterial activity (biggest inhibition zone), while the Cumin oil had the least antibacterial activity (smallest inhibition zone) among the essential oils present in this study. The results also showed that the Marjoram spices power has the strongest antibacterial activity among spices powder tested in this study, while Cumin spices powder had the least antibacterial activity among the spices powder tested in this study. Therefore, it is obvious that the cumin plant had the least antibacterial among plants present in this study. These results are in agreement with &#x000d6;zcan et al, which reported that essential oils of some spices may be used as antimicrobial agents to prevent the spoilage of food products.<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref></p><p>Study limitation and future recommendations: The small sample size is the main limitation of this study. As part of the antimicrobial activity of essential oils, it is better to evaluate the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and the minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC).</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p><italic>Bacillus</italic> species are commonly associated with food from animal sources that is considered a public health threat. The highest prevalence of <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. was observed in processed meat, especially beef burger. Essential oils and spices powder of certain medicinal plants (black seeds: <italic>Nigella sativa</italic>, cloves: <italic>Syzygium aromaicum</italic>, cinnamon: <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic>, and Marjoram: <italic>Origanum majorana</italic>) have a potential in vitro antimicrobial activity against <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. Furthermore, <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> oil exhibited the most potent antibacterial activity against <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp., while Cumin (<italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic>) showed the least antibacterial activity.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors extend their appreciation to the researchers supporting project number (RSP-2020/201), King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</p></ack><sec id="s0006" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest for this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zerabruk</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Retta</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muleta</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tefera</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessment of microbiological safety and quality of minced meat and meat contact surfaces in selected butcher shops of Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Food Qual</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>2019</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Holck</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Axelsson</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McLeod</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rode</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heir</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Health and safety considerations of fermented sausages</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Food Qual</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<fpage>2017</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mouafo</surname>
<given-names>HT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baomog</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adjele</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sokamte</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mbawala</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ndjouenkeu</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Microbial profile of fresh beef sold in the markets of ngaound&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;, cameroon, and antiadhesive activity of a biosurfactant against selected bacterial pathogens</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Food Qual</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>2020</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Salifou</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boko</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahounou</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Diversit&#x000e9; de la microflore initiale de la viande et s&#x000e9;curit&#x000e9; sanitaire des consommateurs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Biol Chem Sci</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1369</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Goepfert</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spira</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elshafie</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Technology</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bacillus cereus: food poisoning organism. A review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Milk Food Technol</italic></source>. <year>1972</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Camele</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elshafie</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caputo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sakr</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Bacillus mojavensis: biofilm formation and biochemical investigation of its bioactive metabolites</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Res/Bollettino della Societ&#x000e0; Italiana di Biologia Sperimentale</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kwon</surname>
<given-names>G-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>H-A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>J-Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development of a RAPD-PCR method for identification of Bacillus species isolated from Cheonggukjang</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Food Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>287</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19157616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hendriksen</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Diagnostic properties of three conventional selective plating media for selection of Bacillus cereus, B. thuringiensis and B. weihenstephanensis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Folia Microbiologica</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>535</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>539</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22083787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Kholy</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riad</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genes encoding the virulence and the antimicrobial resistance in enterotoxigenic and shiga-toxigenic E. coli isolated from diarrheic calves</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Toxins</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins12060383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Sayed</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Youssef</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence, the antibiogram and the frequency of virulence genes of the most predominant bacterial pathogens incriminated in calf pneumonia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AMB Express</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-020-01037-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32472209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Enany</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Tarabili</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghobashy</surname>
<given-names>MOI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Helmy</surname>
<given-names>YA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence, antimicrobial resistance profiles, virulence and enterotoxins-determinant genes of MRSA isolated from subclinical bovine mastitis in Egypt</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathogens (Basel, Switzerland)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohamed</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tawfiek</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hozzein</surname>
<given-names>WN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El Kazzaz</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mabrok</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular typing, antibiogram and PCR-RFLP based detection of aeromonas hydrophila complex isolated from oreochromis niloticus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathogens (Basel, Switzerland)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Enany</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nasef</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The occurrence of the multidrug resistance (MDR) and the prevalence of virulence genes and QACs resistance genes in E. coli isolated from environmental and avian sources</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AMB Express</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>192</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-019-0920-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31797067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Sayed</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abouel-Atta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mabrok</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Emam</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathogenicity, genetic typing, and antibiotic sensitivity of Vibrio alginolyticus isolated from Oreochromis niloticus and Tilapia zillii</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Med Vet</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>170</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Koeck</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Njanpop-Lafourcade</surname>
<given-names>B-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cade</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Evaluation and selection of tandem repeat loci for Streptococcus pneumoniae MLVA strain typing</article-title>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>66</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gdoura-Ben Amor</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Siala</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zayani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Isolation, identification, prevalence, and genetic diversity of Bacillus cereus group bacteria from different foodstuffs in Tunisia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>447</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29593691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Woo</surname>
<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheung</surname>
<given-names>EY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leung</surname>
<given-names>K-W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuen</surname>
<given-names>K-Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Identification by 16S ribosomal RNA gene sequencing of an Enterobacteriaceae species with ambiguous biochemical profile from a renal transplant recipient</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0732-8893(01)00206-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11248520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bacillus oceanisediminis sp. nov., isolated from marine sediment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2924</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2929</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20118297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Manzo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D&#x02019;Apuzzo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coutinho</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cutting</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henrissat</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ricca</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Carbohydrate-active enzymes from pigmented Bacilli: a genomic approach to assess carbohydrate utilization and degradation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>198</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ko</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oh</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bacillus infantis sp. nov. and Bacillus idriensis sp. nov., isolated from a patient with neonatal sepsis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2544</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>Y-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jeong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Draft genome sequence of Bacillus oceanisediminis 2691</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>.<year>2012</year>;<volume>194</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>6351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6352</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shida</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takagi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kadowaki</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komagata</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <collab>Microbiology E</collab>. <article-title>Proposal for Two New Genera, Brevibacillus gen. nov. and Aneurinibacillus gen. nov.</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>.<year>1996</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>939</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>946</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kesavan</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaur</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular characterization and antimicrobial susceptibility of bacterial isolates present in tap water of public toilets</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/inthealth/ihz074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31693132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fancello</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Multineddu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santona</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Bacterial biodiversity of extra virgin olive oils and their potential biotechnological exploitation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microorganisms</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8010097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mossel</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koopman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jongerius</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Enumeration of Bacillus cereus in foods</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>1967</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>650</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>653</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.15.3.650-653.1967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4291956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolff</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Atlas</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>General probability-matched relations between radar reflectivity and rain rate</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Meteorol</italic></source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/1520-0450(1993)032&#x0003c;0050:GPMRBR&#x0003e;2.0.CO;2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Cowan</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steel</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cowan and Steel&#x02019;s Manual for the Identification of Medical Bacteria</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge university press</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Hadedy</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Nour</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Identification of Staphylococcus aureus and Escherichia coli isolated from Egyptian food by conventional and molecular methods</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Genetic Eng Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jgeb.2012.01.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>16S/23S rRNA sequencing</chapter-title> In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acid Techniques in Bacterial Systematics</italic></source>. <year>1991</year>:115&#x02013;175.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yahia</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanora</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fahmy</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aly</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quorum sensing signal production by sponge-associated bacteria isolated from the Red Sea, Egypt</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Afr J Biotechnol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>32</issue>):<fpage>1688</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1698</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJB2017.16078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tamura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stecher</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filipski</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Biol Evol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2729</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elshafie</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caputo</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De Martino</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Biological investigations of essential oils extracted from three Juniperus species and evaluation of their antimicrobial, antioxidant and cytotoxic activities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Applied Microbiology</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1271</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.14723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32445616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rajasekar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkinson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sekar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bridge</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medina-Roldan</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moy</surname>
<given-names>CKS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biomineralisation performance of bacteria isolated from a landfill in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can J Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>953</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/cjm-2018-0254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30148972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alam</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmad</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pranaw</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mishra</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khare</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Asparaginase conjugated magnetic nanoparticles used for reducing acrylamide formation in food model system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioresour Technol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2018.08.095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30157443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adiguzel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ozer</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>KiliC</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>CetiN</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Screening of antimicrobial activity of essential oil and methanol extract of Satureja hortensis on foodborne bacteria and fungi</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Czech J Food Sci</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17221/753-CJFS</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>De</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>De</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><given-names>Banerjee</given-names>
<surname>AB</surname></string-name>. <article-title>Screening of spices for antimicrobial activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Spices Aromatic Crops</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>135</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mostafa</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Askar</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Almaary</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawoud</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sholkamy</surname>
<given-names>EN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bakri</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of some plant extracts against bacterial strains causing food poisoning diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Saudi J Biol Sci</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2017.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29472791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elkelish</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA): one health perspective approach to the bacterium epidemiology, virulence factors, antibiotic-resistance, and zoonotic impact</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>3255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3265</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S272733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33061472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mabrok</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sivaramasamy</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Emerging MDR-Pseudomonas aeruginosa in fish commonly harbor oprL and toxA virulence genes and bla(TEM), bla(CTX-M), and tetA antibiotic-resistance genes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15961</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-72264-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32994450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rangel-L&#x000f3;pez</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zaragoza-Bastida</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valladares-Carranza</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>In vitro antibacterial potential of salix babylonica extract against bacteria that affect oncorhynchus mykiss and oreochromis spp</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Animals</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10081340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Makharita</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdelaziz</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagagy</surname>
<given-names>FI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Algammal</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antibiogram and genetic characterization of carbapenem-resistant gram-negative pathogens incriminated in healthcare-associated infections</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>Volume 13</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3991</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4002</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S276975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saleh</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morshdy</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Manakhly</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of olive leaf extracts as natural preservative on retailed poultry meat quality</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Foods</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1017</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods9081017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abd El-Baky</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farhan</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mahran</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antimicrobial resistance pattern and molecular epidemiology of ESBL and MBL producing Acinetobacter baumannii isolated from hospitals in Minia, Egypt</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Alexandria J Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20905068.2019.1707350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abd El-Baky</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masoud</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohamed</surname>
<given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and some possible mechanisms of colistin resistance among multidrug-resistant and extensively drug-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>332</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S238811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32099423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abd El-Baky</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandle</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>John</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gea</surname>
<given-names>A-R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A novel mechanism of action of ketoconazole: inhibition of the NorA efflux pump system and biofilm formation in multidrug-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1703</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1718</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S201124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31354319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abd Ellah</surname>
<given-names>NH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdel-Aleem</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdo</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abou-Ghadir</surname>
<given-names>OF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zahran</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Efficacy of ketoconazole gel-flakes in treatment of vaginal candidiasis: formulation, in vitro and clinical evaluation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pharm</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>567</volume>:<fpage>118472</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2019.118472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31252146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Abo-Shama</surname>
<given-names>UH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Gendy</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mousa</surname>
<given-names>WS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Synergistic and antagonistic effects of metal nanoparticles in combination with antibiotics against some reference strains of pathogenic microorganisms</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>362</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S234425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32104007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohamed</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nosocomial vancomycin and methicillin resistant staphylococcal infections in intensive care units in Assiut University Hospitals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Egypt J Med Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Al-Kadmy</surname>
<given-names>IMS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibrahim</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Saryi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aziz</surname>
<given-names>SN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Besinis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of genes involved in colistin resistance in Acinetobacter baumannii: first report from Iraq</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microbial Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>616</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>622</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2019.0243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Kazzaz</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Metwally</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yahia</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Harbi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Taher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antibiogram, prevalence of OXA carbapenemase encoding genes, and RAPD-genotyping of multidrug-resistant acinetobacter baumannii incriminated in hidden community-acquired infections</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antibiotics (Basel, Switzerland)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Mokhtar</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetta</surname>
<given-names>HF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ambulance vehicles as a source of multidrug-resistant infections: a multicenter study in Assiut City, Egypt</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S151783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29731647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0052"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aboaba</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olude</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antibacterial effect of edible plant extract on Escherichia coli 0157: H7</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pak J Nutri</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>327</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0053"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>El-Helow</surname>
<given-names>ERJFML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Identification and molecular characterization of a novel Bacillus strain capable of degrading Tween-80</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">FEMS Microbiol Letters</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>196</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0054"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Whittaker</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fry</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curtis</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Use of fatty acid profiles to identify food-borne bacterial pathogens and aerobic endospore-forming bacilli</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Agr Food Chem</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3742</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15853428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0055"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bakkali</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Averbeck</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Averbeck</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Idaomar</surname>
<given-names>MJF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Toxicology c. Biological effects of essential oils&#x02013;a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Food Chem Toxicol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>446</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>475</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0056"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mann</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markham</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gustafson</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warmington</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wyllie</surname>
<given-names>SGJM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Determining the antimicrobial actions of tea tree oil</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Molecules</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0057"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dorman</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deans</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antimicrobial agents from plants: antibacterial activity of plant volatile oils</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>316</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10736000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0058"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>&#x000d6;zcan</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sa&#x001e7;d&#x00131;&#x000e7;</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>&#x000d6;zkan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Inhibitory effects of spice essential oils on the growth of Bacillus species</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Food</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>421</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17004909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0059"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Sokal</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Numerical Taxonomy</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Freeman</publisher-name>; <year>1973</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0060"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kimura</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Mol Evol</italic></source>. <year>1980</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7463489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0061"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tamura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stecher</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filipski</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0.</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Biol Evol</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2729</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>