<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is known that EOs can act on the gut microbiota selectively. For instance, a cocktail of carvacrol, cinnamaldehyde, and capsicum oleoresin increased the population of 
 <italic>Lactobacilli</italic> and the ratio of 
 <italic>Lactobacilli</italic> to 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> in the jejunum and cecum of early-weaned piglets [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The way EOs active substances can modify microbial composition is very important as it is known that the microbiota plays a fundamental role in the induction, training, and functioning of the host immune system [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. It also actively participates in the digestion process. Bacteria belonging to phylum Firmicutes are able to digest long-chain carbohydrates and thus provide the host with additional sources of nutrients [
 <xref rid="B31-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In addition to its positive role, microbiota has a potential in the development of irritable bowel disease and some other diseases, as well as obesity [
 <xref rid="B32-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. It may also elaborate toxic products from food residues such as genotoxic hydrogen sulphide [
 <xref rid="B33-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. As the microbiota has the potential to play different roles in the gut of the host, it is very important to explore the key elements influencing the domination of beneficial bacteria over the pathogenic ones or those that may have a negative impact on health. Different EOs have been investigated regarding their antimicrobial and functional properties. The previous investigations proved that the potential of activity of different EOs is not equal [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]; therefore, the selection of an appropriate EOs with the aim to obtain the most active (or optimal) composition is very important.
</p>
