<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Methyleugenol (4-allyl-1,2-dimethoxybenzene) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-23-01061-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>), a phenylpropanoid derivative, is a natural constituent isolated from EOs of many plants, such as Chinese herb 
 <italic class="italic">Asari Radix et Rhizoma</italic>, having multiple biological effects including anticonvulsant, antinociceptive, and anesthetic activities. The anesthetic property of methyleugenol has been demonstrated by a loss of the righting reflex and decreased sensitivity to a tail pinch in rats and mice, and a loss of the corneal reflex in rabbits [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The antinociceptive and anesthetic effects of methyleugenol resulted from the inhibitory action of methyleugenol on peripheral Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> channels [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Yano et al. [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>] tested the effects of methyleugenol on antinociception using the formalin test in mice in vivo. They found that the antinociceptive effect of methyleugenol on the second phase of formalin-induced pain might be due to the inhibition of NMDA receptor-mediated hyperalgesia via GABA
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> receptors. Ding et al. [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>] tested the action of methyleugenol on GABA
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> receptors. At lower concentrations (~30 μM), methyleugenol significantly potentiated GABA-induced currents in cultured hippocampal neurons [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. Similarly, methyleugenol potentiated GABA-induced currents mediated by recombinant α
 <sub class="sub">1</sub>β
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>γ
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> or α
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>β
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>γ
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> GABA
 <sub class="sub">A</sub>Rs in human embryonic kidney (HEK) cells. In addition to the blockade of Na
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> channels [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], this study adds GABA
 <sub class="sub">A</sub>R activation to the list of molecular targets of methyleugenol [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>].
</p>
