<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Ulva lactuca</italic> polymorphism dependent upon the environment led to the proposal that different species may exist, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva armoricana, rigida, prolifera, pertusa, fasciata</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">rotundata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B1-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. However, genetic analysis revealed that the different phenotypes observed were not based on genetic variations that would justify the existence of different species other than 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva lactuca</italic> [
 <xref rid="B13-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Taxonomy is challenging for the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic>, which belongs to the phylum of 
 <italic class="italic">Chlorophyta</italic>, constituting four traditional classes (
 <italic class="italic">Ulvophyceae</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Trebouxiophyceae</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Chlorophyceae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Chlorodendrophyceae</italic>) that evolved from unicellular marine planktonic prasinophyte algae in the Neoproterozoic [
 <xref rid="B1-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Trebouxiophyceae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Chlorophyceae</italic> are found mainly in fresh water while 
 <italic class="italic">Ulvophyceae</italic> colonize mainly shallow marine environments, similar to the Australian 
 <italic class="italic">Collerpa</italic> that has colonized the Mediterranean Sea since 20 years ago. Linnaeus was the first to observe that 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva lactuca</italic> could have different phenotypes with a tubular or a sheet-like tail, but taxonomists in the nineteenth century proposed that the tubular green algae were a distinct genus called 
 <italic class="italic">Enteromorpha</italic>. However, molecular approaches demonstrated that Linnaeus was correct—
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Enteromorpha</italic> are not distinct genera [
 <xref rid="B13-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Different 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> species are still described in the literature [
 <xref rid="B14-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>], but it turns out that reproduction is possible between these different “species”, which therefore should be described as 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva lactuca</italic> variants or clades.
</p>
