<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1) has a vital role in metabolizing heme to biliverdin, carbon monoxide and free iron. Biliverdin is immediately conversed to bilirubin, as catalyzed by biliverdin reductase containing two isozymes, i.e., biliverdin reductase A and B. Free iron is released to blood circulation by ferroportin and further carried to bone marrow (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Kovtunovych et al., 2010</xref>). Therefore, HO-1, biliverdin reductase and ferropotin are considered as the main target enzymes in determining the iron recycling in macrophages. Jujube extract at different concentration (0–3.0 mg/ml) was applied onto cultured macrophages for 24 h. The applied jujube extract stimulated the mRNA expressions of HO-1, biliverdin reductase A and B, and ferropotin in dose-dependent manners, giving the highest response by ∼2.0, 2.0, 3.0, and 4.0 folds, respectively (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen J. et al., 2016</xref>). In good agreement with this finding, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al. (2016)</xref> reported that the intake of jujube extract showed an improvement in iron deficiency anemia rats. In parallel, the extract of jujube significantly increased serum iron, iron saturation, total iron binding capacity in anemia rats, indicating the supply of circulation iron for erythropoiesis. Nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2 (Nrf2), a transcription factor, was found to regulate HO-1 expression (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Motohashi and Yamamoto, 2004</xref>). Nrf2 directly binds to anti-oxidant response element (ARE) in the promoter region of 
 <italic>HO-1</italic> gene resulting in the transcription. In pARE-Luc-expressed cells treated with jujube water extract, the luciferase assay was activated in a dose-dependent manner (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen J. et al., 2016</xref>). The activation by two folds was confirmed under application of jujube extract at 3.0 mg/ml (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Chen J. et al., 2016</xref>). This result suggests the involvement of Nrf2/HO-1 signaling in jujube-treated cells. In support of this notion, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Almeer et al. (2018)</xref> revealed the effects of jujube extract on gene expressions of Nrf2 and HO-1 in colitis rats, as induced by treating intrarectally with acetic acid. Compared with model group, the pre-treatment with jujube extract at different doses (100, 200, and 400 mg/kg/day) in colon of rats for 5 days by oral gavage significantly induced mRNA expressions of Nrf2 and HO-1, giving the highest response by seven and two folds, respectively (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Almeer et al., 2018</xref>). These studies however need further confirmation as no observation has been found in a physiology model of iron recycling. For instance, a cellular model of erythrophagocytosis using artificially-aged RBCs and macrophages may be designed to investigate mRNA and protein expressions of target enzymes relating to iron recycling.
</p>
