<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">In spite of being rich in these beneficiary components and activities, it is still underutilized because of its unavailability throughout the year. The ripe fruits are available only from March to June (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Hazra et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Baliga et al., 2013</xref>). After harvesting, the shelf life of bael fruit is normally two weeks at room temperature (27–32 °C). The shelf life can be enhanced to twelve weeks by preserving it at 9 °C (85–90% relative humidity), but it is highly sensitive to spoilage (chilling injury) below 9 °C (
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Pal et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Roy et al., 2011</xref>). The possible solution we found is to convert it into fruit leather which is one of the prominent methods, mainly used to preserve fully ripe unconsumed or excess fruit pulp for a long period of time without adding any preservative, and can be consumed as snacks or, dessert for a long. Bael leather can be utilized in the fruit bar industry, fruit cake industry, and importantly as ayurvedic medicine. The traditional way of making leather is to dry the pulp in the sun, which is one of the easiest and cheapest methods. However, the main problems associated with this are uncertain climatic conditions, microorganisms, dust, dirt and insect infections that produce an inferior quality product in terms of hygiene (
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Uribe et al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, it is better to focus on other possible alternatives, mainly industrial methods like, microwave drying, hot air drying, and freeze drying which gives better yields in terms of production rate and quality of the leather. In this study, the quality of fresh and differently dried 
 <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) fruit leathers in terms of nutraceutical components, compositional changes, and medicinal activities was evaluated.
</p>
