<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Myristic acid is a naturally occurring fatty acid and abundantly found in milk fat, nutmeg, palm kernel, and butter [
 <xref rid="B129-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Myristic acid has been shown to be a competitive inhibitor of SIRT6 demyristoylation where the free fatty acid (FFA) and peptide-conjugated myristoyl chain compete for the same hydrophobic pocket of SIRT6 protein [
 <xref rid="B109-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. To test the theory that myristic acid ties in a similar site as the unsaturated fat chain of a myristoylated lysine peptide, SIRT6 demyristoylase movement was estimated within sight of expanding myristic acid at a fixed peptide substrate concentration. In addition, a detailed steady-state analysis was performed to prove further that myristic acid and the fatty acid chain of a myristoylated peptide share the same binding site on SIRT6. This study clearly showed their competitive inhibition of SIRT6, as H3K9Myr peptide concentration was varied at several fixed concentrations of myristic acid [
 <xref rid="B95-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Myristic acid had restrained the demyristoylase action of SIRT6 with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 190 ± 10 μM. Previously there was a perception that SIRT6 demyristoylation was entirely unrelated to FFA; however, it has been proven that expanded cell levels of explicit fatty acids (FAs) trigger a change from SIRT6-subordinate demyristoylation to actuated histone deacetylation. SIRT6 attenuates NF-κB signaling through H3K9Ac deacetylation and also improves a supportive proinflammatory reaction by advancing the emission of TNF-α through lysine demyristoylation. Therefore, myristic acid plays a critical role as an inhibitor of SIRT6 by inhibiting inflammation [
 <xref rid="B95-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Myristic acid is a competitive inhibitor of SIRT6. Thus, it might have anticancer activity since SIRT6 has essential capacities in cell procedures, such as gene expression, genome stabilization, and DNA fix [
 <xref rid="B119-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>].
</p>
