<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experimental data on the pharmacological activity of
 <italic> breu</italic> essential oils administered by inhalation, in a similar manner as used in Amazon
 <italic> quilombola</italic> traditional communities, are presented for the first time. Nebulization of formulations containing
 <italic> breu</italic> essential oils provides a mixture of major
 <italic> breu</italic> components similar to those found in the pure essential oil and proved to be an efficient method of administration. Depending on the type and concentration of the components, the
 <italic> breu</italic> essential oils may present antinociceptive properties without sedation when inhaled after nebulization. The presence of monoterpenes, such as 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene,
 <italic> p</italic>-cymene, 
 <italic>α</italic>-phellandrene, limonene, 
 <italic>β</italic>-pinene, and 
 <italic>α</italic>-terpineol, may play important roles in these bioactivities. Formulation E, which contains a high concentration of 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene, appeared to be the most promising formulation since it was the only formulation with significant activity in both phases of the formalin test. It is interesting to note that, with the exception of Formulation E (which suppressed licking time by 60.2% in the late phase), no activity was greater than 50% in the models tested. However, it is necessary to remember that
 <italic> breu</italic> essential oil formulations were administered by inhalation and not by common routes, such as oral or intraperitoneal routes, that present more pronounced effects. It is possible that, when administered by inhalation, the effects are not as prominent due to rapid elimination (via respiration). In this work, we demonstrated that formulations containing essential oils from
 <italic> breu</italic> samples can produce
 <italic> in vivo</italic> antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory activities when inhaled by nebulization.
</p>
