<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vector-borne diseases remain a major public health concern in tropical areas [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Poor drainage systems in urban areas, especially during rainy seasons, and irrigation ditches in farmland provide abundant mosquito breeding places [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Tanzania spends a low share of its gross domestic product (7.2%) on health, with a meagre public expenditure of 39% for health costs [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. Vector-borne diseases affecting people in Tanzania are malaria, filariasis, dengue, chikungunya and other arboviruses [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. Malaria remains the deadliest vector-borne disease despite long-term control efforts [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]. Among the mosquito-borne vectors, 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> (L.), a vector of dengue fever, is prevalent in the tropics and sub-tropics and is closely associated with human habitats outside its native range of Africa [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Culex pipiens pallens</span> (Coquillett) is a vector of the western Nile virus and is distributed throughout Africa, the Middle East and Asia [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. The complex sibling species of 
  <span class="italic">An. gambiae</span> which transmit malaria worldwide have been described [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. All of these vector-borne diseases occur mainly in tropical countries where more than two billion people live in endemic regions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. The approaches to combating vector-borne diseases relies on the interruption of the disease transmission cycle by either targeting the adult or larvae through spraying breeding sites or targeting adults using insecticides [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Synthetic pesticides have been extensively used for mosquito control by either killing the vectors, preventing adult mosquitoes from biting humans or by killing mosquito larvae at breeding sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. However, the development of resistance to different classes of synthetic insecticides such as pyrethroids, organophosphates, organochlorides and carbamates has drawn attention to the search of alternative methods of control [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. The toxicity of the available chemical insecticides, their high operational cost and the subsequent environmental pollution have caused the need for developing alternative approaches to control vector-borne diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Plant extracts with proven mosquito control potential can be used in place of synthetic insecticides, either as insecticides for killing larvae or adult mosquitoes or as repellents for protection against mosquito bites. Amongst them, essential oils have gained a special interest due to their insecticidal properties [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>] andin recent years, have proved to be potentially useful sources of bioactive compounds against mosquito larvae [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]
  <span class="italic">.</span> Essential oils are composed of isoprenoid compounds, mainly monoterpene carriers of smell in the aromatic plants, such as sesquiterpenes alcohols identified from 
  <span class="italic">Chamaecyparis obtusa</span> leaf oil and various monoterpene components derived from 
  <span class="italic">Thuja orientalis</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of studies have been conducted on essential oils to determine their larvicidal and repellency activities. 
  <span class="italic">Cinnamon umzeylanicum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cymbopogon citrates</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Tanacetum vulgare</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Rubdosia melissoides</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Eugenia caryophyllata</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Ocimum</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Gaultheria procumbens</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cuminum cymium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Bunium persicum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Trachyspermum ammi</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Foeniculum vulgare</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Abelmoschus moschatus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cedru</span>s spp. and 
  <span class="italic">Piper</span> spp. have been found to be effective for pest control [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Other essential oils such as lemon grass (
  <span class="italic">Cymbopogon winteriana</span>), eucalyptus (
  <span class="italic">Eucalyptus globules),</span> rosemary (
  <span class="italic">Rosemarinus officinalis</span>), vetiver (
  <span class="italic">Vetiveria zizanoides</span>), clove (
  <span class="italic">Eugenia caryophyllus</span>) and thyme (
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris)</span> are known for their pest control properties [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Another study, conducted on the repellent effect of essential oils from 
  <span class="italic">Cymbopogon</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Ocimum</span> spp., and 
  <span class="italic">Eucalyptus</span> spp. showed their strong repellency against malaria vectors and other mosquitoes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from essential oils, extracts prepared from Tanzanian plants have been evaluated for their larvicidal activity. For instance, extracts from 
  <span class="italic">Annona muricata</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Annona senegalensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Annona squamosa</span> were active against 
  <span class="italic">Culex quinquefasciatus</span>, which demonstrated that extracts of 
  <span class="italic">Annona</span> species grown in Tanzania could be potential anti-mosquito agents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. In spite of the anti-mosquito activities of several studied species of plants, relatively little work has been done on the larvicidal activities of essential oils extracted from spices, such as clove and cinnamon. A recent study carried out in Nigeria assessed the activity of clove essential oils against 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Cx. quinquefasciatus</span> and achieved over 85% larval mortality within 24-hourspost-exposure [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Meanwhile, in Thailand, lemongrass and clove essential oils were effective in causing mortality for all larval stages of 
  <span class="italic">An. dirus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study was to determine the active ingredients, and larvicidal activities of clove (Family: Myrtaceae) and cinnamon (Family: Lauraceae) essential oils and their blend against insectary-reared 
  <span class="italic">Anopheles gambiae</span> (
  <span class="italic">s.s</span>.) larvae and 
  <span class="italic">An. arabiensis</span> larvae from wild populations.
 </p>
</sec>
