<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are a good number of other medicinal plants which have shown good to moderate immunomodulation and antiviral activities in various 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> models. For instance, oleanolic acid in rosemary (
 <italic>Salvia rosmarinus</italic>) has been proven to have good effect against herpes, HIV, influnza, and hepatitis A viruses (
 <xref rid="B229" ref-type="bibr">229</xref>). Sambucus, licorice, ginger, ginseng, and dandelion showed dominant antiviral activities in many laboratory experiments. Glycyrrhizin and lycorine from 
 <italic>G. glabra</italic> and 
 <italic>Lycoris radiate</italic>, respectively, showed good activity against SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B230" ref-type="bibr">230</xref>). Glycyrrhizin has even showed good potential against the COVID-19 virus SARS-CoV-2 and may emerge as an alternative drug for its treatment (
 <xref rid="B231" ref-type="bibr">231</xref>). Based on these findings, a novel combination of vitamin C, curcumin and glycyrrhizic acid (VCG plus) was proposed for the treatment of coronavirus infections (
 <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>). This combination is believed to regulate the innate immune response. Many other plants such as 
 <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, 
 <italic>Zingeber officinale</italic>, 
 <italic>Andrographis paniculate</italic>, 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic>, 
 <italic>Trigonella foemnum graecum</italic>, 
 <italic>Picrorhiza scrophulariiflora</italic>, 
 <italic>Phyllanthus debilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Baliospermum montanum</italic>, 
 <italic>Tinospora cordifolia</italic>, 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pouteria cambodiana</italic> reportedly displayed either immunostimulant or immunosuppressive properties by modulating acquired or innate immune responses (
 <xref rid="B199" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>). A number of single and compound drugs are advised in the Unani medicine based on the medicinal plants which are claimed to be antiviral, antipyretic, blood purifier, cardioprotective and expectorant activities and can be effective in the treatment and management of viral infections including COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B233" ref-type="bibr">233</xref>).
</p>
