<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>“Muicle”, “micle” and “moyottli” are some names used by the people in Michoacán, Tabasco, Nayarit, Jalisco, San Luis Potosi, Chiapas, Morelos, Tlaxcala, Veracruz and Yucatan state to identify the 
 <italic>Justicia spicigera</italic> plant. It is a plant belong to the Acanthaceae family and has been used since Aztec times as an infusion of the leaves, branches, and flowers for consumption as a common drink throughout the day. Its infusions are indicated to treat inflammation, anemias, leukemias, pulmonary tuberculosis, diarrhea, hemorrhoids, parasites, rheumatism, arthritis, bone disease and diseases of the eye [
 <xref rid="B164-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. Furthermore, its properties have been used since pre-Hispanic times to obtain indigo dye for paintm food, baskets, crafts and clothes. Concerning its ethnopharmacology, preclinical assays have demonstrated the anticonvulsant properties induced by aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>J. spicigera</italic> and its derivate kaempferitrin [
 <xref rid="B165-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>], as well as antidepressant [
 <xref rid="B166-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>] and anxiolytic-like effects [
 <xref rid="B167-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. In the same way, the antidiabetic, [
 <xref rid="B168-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>] antitumor, immunomodulatory [
 <xref rid="B169-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B136-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>] and antiparasitic [
 <xref rid="B170-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>] properties of this plant have been demonstrated. Pertaining to the topic of this review, 
 <italic>J. spicigera</italic> has reduced nociception in several inflammatory pain models [
 <xref rid="B171-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>], suggesting that its antinociceptive effect can be attributed to kaempferitrin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00865-f001">Figure 1</xref>), which in turn induces antispasmodic effects through the activation of 5-HT
 <sub>1A</sub> and opioid receptors [
 <xref rid="B172-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>,
 <xref rid="B173-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>]. As a recapitulation, the pharmacological studies support the ancient use of 
 <italic>J. spicigera</italic> to alleviate painful conditions. However, it is important to consider that hexane and chloroform extracts of this plant displayed mortality in mice administrated with 400 mg/kg of those extracts.
</p>
