<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The behavior of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in various lakes, wetlands, and other water bodies of Kashmir is that of a typical invader in terms of forming the monotypic stands, attaining great abundance, and outcompeting native species [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Previous studies that were carried out in 2018 [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] based on field observations reported this species at the stage V (widespread and dominant) on the stage-based hierarchical model (CM model) propounded by Colautti and MacIsaac [
 <xref rid="B46-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Similarly, earlier studies conducted in 2007 [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] reported this species as a South American native and Shah et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] in 2014 reported it as a European native based on published, web-based sources as well as phytogeographical distribution of this species, but substantial molecular evidence for the nativity of this species is lacking. Based on the above evidence, many authors declared that 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> was introduced in India, especially in Kashmir Himalayan region [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. There is hardly any study conducted in Kashmir, India, or elsewhere, that suggests native range of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in this part (Kashmir Himalaya) of Asia. The present study aimed at increasing our understanding of the phenotypic and genetic diversity of invasive populations of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in Kashmir and Quebec. Only one native 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> population in Quebec was identified during field surveys on reported natural distribution of the species across Quebec province and all the populations from Kashmir turned out to be invasive as revealed by cpDNA PCR-RFLP analyses. Such findings indicate that invasive haplotypes are becoming more dominant in the natural distribution range of the species in the sites of study. This is the first study in India, especially in Kashmir Himalaya, that provides molecular evidence regarding the invasive status of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in this region. Such successful invasion of alien haplotypes in their non-native range is due to the fact that invaders usually perform better than natives in terms of life-history traits such as mature plant size and fecundity, thereby reducing the size of, or even replacing, native populations [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-01392" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Further studies in this direction need to be carried out by taking samples from a larger global range, including native European populations of 
 <italic>P. australis</italic>, in order to provide greater understanding of the origin and phylogeography of this species.
</p>
