<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Quantification of the seed and cone essential oil components was carried out based on the measurement of response factors for all of the chemical groups. The application of this analytical procedure allowed the accurate determination of the concentration (g/100 g) of all the tested components to be made. For the calculation of response factors, the standard compounds mentioned below were spiked with nonane as internal standard and injected consecutively for three runs. Once calculated, response factors were used for the absolute quantification of volatiles, based on the commonly known formula. The application of this analytical procedure allowed for the determination of the concentration (g/100 g) of all the 98 compounds identified. For the measurement of response factors, the following chemicals were used: α-pinene, β-pinene, camphene, limonene for monoterpene hydrocarbons (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 0.99 ± 0.050); (
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-caryophyllene and germacrene D, for sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 0.99 ± 0.019); 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, for aromatic hydrocarbons (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 0.99 ± 0.004); octanal, decanal and citral, for aldehydes (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 1.28 ± 0.050); benzaldehyde, for aromatic aldehydes (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 1.24 ± 0.042); heptan-2-one and pulegone, for ketones (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 1.34 ± 0.053); citronellol, terpinen-4-ol, geraniol, 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-hex-3-en-1-ol, borneol, eugenol, thymol, farnesol and carotol for alcohols (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 1.29 ± 0.071), buthyl acetate, neryl acetate, benzyl benzoate for esters (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 1.55 ± 0.045); caryophyllene oxide and safrol, for oxides (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 1.53 ± 0.002); and, ethers (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 1.46 ± 0.009). Response factors for diterpene hydrocarbons were measured as an average of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub>s for monoterpene and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> = 0.99).
</p>
