<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">The list of antibiotics recommended for LD treatment at the early stages of infection is expanding [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" class="xref">102</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" class="xref">108</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" class="xref">109</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" class="xref">114</xref>]. Current antibiotics are efficient in killing the growing replicative form of spirochetes, but they have rather insufficient activity against non-growing persistent forms. It has been confirmed that monotherapy of 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> infection with β-lactam, tetracycline, fluoroquinolone, sulfonamide, macrolide, lipopeptide, glycopeptides, aminoglycoside or antitumor antibiotics are not adequate. Such treatment fails to eliminate spirochetes in 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> culture and leaves viable and effective persisters in treated vertebrates, including humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" class="xref">108</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" class="xref">109</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>]. The obvious need in antibiotics with strong anti-persister activity has led to the identification of drugs that act differently from current LD antibiotics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" class="xref">117</xref>]. However, even anti-persister drugs such as daptomycin, clofazimine or daunomycin cannot kill different persister forms such as cysts, round bodies, micro-colonies or biofilms alone. A combination of two or three drugs from different classes of antibiotics with different mechanisms of action along with the use of sulfa drugs shows significant improvement in eliminating multiple persisters’ forms 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic>. Pulse dosing treatment shows great potential for eradicating persisters and seems to be a promising scheme for LD treatment. The interest in identifying alternative drug candidates with a high activity against multiple persister forms is growing. The other known “agent”, comparable by its strength to triple-combination antibiotics treatment and efficient in eliminating log phase spirochetes as well as reducing persisters (by 94%), is 
 <italic class="italic">Stevia rebaudiana</italic>, the plant widely known as honey leaf or sweet leaf [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138" class="xref">138</xref>]. Most probably the killing power of this “agent”, which is the whole leaf extract of the plant, is the result of the synergy of multiple natural compounds not yet identified. Recently, the screening of wide set of essential oils revealed candidates with an even stronger anti-persister activity than was described for some anti-persister drugs. For example, oregano oil and its active component carvacrol, cinnamon bark or clove bud were more efficient against the stationary phase and biofilms of Lyme disease spirochete than 40 µM daptomycin. For comparison, 0.05% cinnamaldehyde, the active component of cinnamon bark essential oil, sterilized the LD spirochete at stationary phase and garlic essential oil was successful in killing of all forms of 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> at a concentration of 0.05%. These results were confirmed by the absence of bacterial regrowth after 21 days of subculture and correspond to results obtained by culture treatment with 5 µg/ml of triple-drugs daptomycin + doxycycline + cefuroxime [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139" class="xref">139</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140" class="xref">140</xref>]. The majority of published results, dealing with promising or fairly successful anti-
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> drugs or their combinations, were obtained 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic>. There is no doubt that their effect on spirochetes 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> will be different, may be unexpected, and definitely unpredictable. Evaluating the elimination capability of anti-
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> drugs or finding alternative candidates against multiple non-replicating forms of LD spirochetes should be taken to another level. Until the same experiments are conducted 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic>, involving multiple laboratory animal models, concerns about successful LD therapy protocol will remain at the discussion or speculation level. The success of LD therapy depends on how early antibiotic treatment is started. The question is how early is early enough to start antibiotic treatment in order to assure elimination of the replicating forms of spirochetes in an infected host, if a 7–10 day-old 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> culture already contains multiple persistent forms of the pathogen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" class="xref">109</xref>]. If the signature marker of Lyme disease, erythema migrans, does not develop in a person after a tick bite, antibiotic treatment will not be initiated immediately. How much time might the motile form of bacteria need to change its morphology or to hide in vertebrate host tissues 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> when such changes triggered by an unfriendly environment 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> can occur in minutes or hours? Even if antibiotic monotherapy is started shortly after exposure to a tick, the LD treatment paradox could occur anyway: frontline LD antibiotics can trigger the establishment of a persister subpopulation 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> as it has been proven by the confirmation of chronic infection in multiple animal species and humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" class="xref">114</xref>]. Atypical dormant spirochete forms, persisters, survive in a 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic>-infected host for years, regardless of antibiotic treatment. The recurrence of LD likely happens because persisters may convert back into motile replicating infective forms under favorable growth conditions. The treatment of LD requires knowledge of its history and 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> pleomorphism in its natural environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>]. The theory that chronic spirochete infections in humans are examples of symbioses that developed between the host and pathogen over time has been proposed for LD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>]. The human-
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> interaction represents co-evolved spirochete-tick-host relationships highly integrated on genetic, metabolic and behavioral levels. From this point of view LD is a manifestation of long-lasting genetically integrated symbioses, and the disease symptoms are the expression of symbiogenesis to which many aspects of the host immune system respond [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>]. Symbiogenesis means cooperation between species in order to increase their survival. While the benefit of symbiosis to the spirochete is obvious, what is the benefit of this symbiosis to the host? The successful persistence of spirochetes within the host is known to depend on their ability to use the host regulatory proteins to avoid recognition and eradication by its complement. Inability to understand chronic LD as ancient co-evolved host-pathogen symbioses might lead to misdiagnoses and insufficient therapies. The probability that chronic LD arises from a persisting infection is real. Regardless of the cause of chronic LD, i.e. persisting forms hidden in biofilms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">96</xref>], cell-wall deficient forms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>], or round bodies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>], the 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> treatment options for all of them are very limited. Addressing this problem requires a new comprehensive examination of the complex and controversial subject called chronic Lyme disease. 
</p>
