<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">The adult fly can typically live for one to two weeks without the need to feed as it appears it can rely on fat body reserve that was acquired during larval stages and can even live longer when fed with water
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. It does not carry diseases, and actively feeding BSFL secrete an info-chemical that keeps away other species of flies, thereby repelling potential insect pests and disease vectors such as 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">domestica</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. The same authors also reported that BSFL significantly influence the reduction of 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella enterica</italic> presence in cow dung while Liu and colleagues
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup> reported the same influence on 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> in chicken manure. The economic feasibility of the use of insects as feed largely depends on cost effective and readily available organic waste streams, both in the developed and in particular in the developing world. So far, very few studies assessed the holistic nutritional contents of BSFL in terms of quality using experimental diets that were established within the means of the developing world. Unlike rationed diets, organic waste streams in the developing world are heterogeneous in nutritional composition and might be an environment where heavy metals can accumulate. Therefore, the current study sought to perform a comparative holistic analysis of the quality of the nutritional composition of BSFL reared on organic waste streams that are largely and readily available in urban areas of Kenya and the developing world in general. A comparative study that is essential when deciding which organic waste streams are potentially suitable for industrial large-scale BSFL production in Kenya.
</p>
