<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Irrespective of the variable set potential distribution maps place 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>alatum</italic> in the broadly defined mountainous areas. This is also visible in the response curves of the modelling algorithm whose values are associated with this type of environment. Within this habitat some variation exists as it may be seen in the PCA graphs which group locations into few weakly separated assemblages (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0182793.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Obviously exotic sites, which are located only in a narrow area, represent much smaller variation and are placed close to each other. It is likely caused by the founder effect and in the future the plants may follow different scenarios. They will either start to establish populations in new conditions or the slow colonization rate may eventually lead to the shrinkage of the range associated with climate warming. Nevertheless, future spreading of 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>alatum</italic> will be restricted, since irrespective of the scenario, the ecological niche modelling indicates that fewer areas will be suitable for colonization. Scenarios with higher concentration of CO
 <sub>2</sub> predict a lower coverage in the north and higher in the south of Europe, compared to the scenarios with lower CO
 <sub>2</sub> concentrations. Contrary to the non-native range, almost no changes are expected to occur within its native range. Especially, the Dinaric Alps and other mountains in the Balkan Peninsula show different support under varying RCPs where increased CO
 <sub>2</sub> levels will make it more suitable. Notably predictions indicate that favourable habitats in the Balkan Peninsula are separated by only 200 km through the Bosphorus strait from the native range of the species. Thus, in this area the species might be treated not as an invasive plant but rather as a natural component that migrates along almost continuous suitable conditions. Following this hypothesis one may also argue that instead of treating this species as invasive it could be considered as a new element in the European Flora that extends its range due to favourable conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0182793.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>],[
 <xref rid="pone.0182793.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
