<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>BACKGROUND</title>
  <p> Essential oils (EO) extracted from 
   <italic>Cinnamomum verum</italic> has been used as an antimicrobial agents for centuries. The effects of 
   <italic>C. verum</italic> leaf oil against virulence of microorganisms is not well studied yet.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>OBJECTIVES</title>
  <p> This study evaluates the effect of 
   <italic>C. verum</italic> leaf oil against three virulence factors of 
   <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, 
   <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> and 
   <italic>C. dubliniensis</italic> and its 
   <italic>in-vivo</italic> toxicity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>METHODS</title>
  <p> Chemical composition of EO was determined using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was determined using clinical and laboratory standards institute (CLSI) M27-A3 broth microdilution. Effect of EO on initial adhesion was quantified using XTT assay after allowing 
   <italic>Candida</italic> cells to adhere to the polystyrene surface for 2 h. Biofilm formation of 
   <italic>Candida</italic> in the presence of EO was quantified using XTT viability assay. Efficacy on reduction of germ tube formation was evaluated using standard protocol. Visualisation of biofilm formation and progression under the EO treatment were done using scanning electron microscope (SEM) and Time lapses microscope respectively. 
   <italic>In-vivo</italic> toxicity of EO was determined using 
   <italic>Galleria mellonella</italic> larvae. Chlorhexidine digluconate: positive control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p> Eugenol was the main compound of EO. MIC was 1.0 mg/mL. 50% reduction in initial adhesion was achieved by 
   <italic>C. albicans</italic>, 
   <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> and 
   <italic>C. dubliniensis</italic> with 1.0, &gt; 2.0 and 0.34 mg/mL respectively. 0.5 and 1.0 mg/mL significantly inhibit the germ tube formation. MBIC
   <sub>50</sub> for forming biofilms were ≤ 0.35 mg/mL. 1.0 mg/mL prevent biofilm progression of 
   <italic>Candida</italic>. SEM images exhibited cell wall damages, cellular shrinkages and decreased hyphal formation. No lethal effect was noted with 
   <italic>in-vivo</italic> experiment model at any concentration tested.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSION</title>
  <p>
   <italic>C. verum</italic> leaf oil acts against virulence factors of 
   <italic>Candida</italic> and does not show any toxicity.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
