<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig3" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 3</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Evaluation of the synergism of doxycycline in combination with essential oil (EO) of 
   <italic class="italic">A. conyzoides</italic>. Data sets in blue, red and green correspond to doxycycline, EO, combinations, respectively. 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> Dose–response curves of each individual treatment. Doxycycline was evaluated twice, for each of the combinations with EO. The antibacterial effect was determined by measurement of foci size. 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold> Median-effect representation of the dose–response curves for each individual compound, using Eq. (
   <xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="" class="xref">3</xref>). fa is the “fraction affected”, or (% effect) ÷ 100. 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold> Normalised isobologram that represents, for each combination, the normalised dose of each treatment individually required to reach the observed effect in combination (Eq. 
   <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="" class="xref">2</xref>). 
   <bold class="bold">d</bold> CI-effect plot representing the combination index CI, calculated using Eq. (
   <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="" class="xref">1</xref>), of each combination as a function of their associated antibacterial effect. 
   <bold class="bold">e</bold> Log (DRI)-effect plot representing the drug reduction index (DRI) of compounds as a function of their antibacterial effect in combination. The DRI is calculated for each drug in each combination according to Eq. (
   <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="" class="xref">4</xref>) and represents the dilution factor required for a drug to reach the same level of inhibition individually compared with it when in combination. The results are representative of 3 independent experiments
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="13568_2019_780_Fig3_HTML" id="MO7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
