<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Wound infections are important challenges that cause the suffering of patients and economic losses (Vittorazzi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Daemi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2019a</xref>; Farghali et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Skin is a regenerative organ which acts as a barrier between the body and the external environment (Hassan et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). A wound is defined as a disturbance in anatomic structure of skin and its functional integrity (Farghali et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Skin prevents the penetration of bacteria and fungi that are important challenges that induce mortality and morbidity. 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> are opportunistic bacteria that induce infection in patients (Cardona and Wilson 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The bacteria are commonly detected in the upper and deepest region of wound bed (Serra et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Colonization of 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> in the wound site postpones the wound healing process (Farahpour et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Khezri et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The wound healing process comprises several phases, including coagulation, inflammation, epithelialization, granulation tissue formation, and tissue remodelling (Daemi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2019a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>; Farahpour et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Inflammatory phase occurs after activation of inflammatory chemokines (Farahpour et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Interleukin-1β (IL-1β) is significantly synthesized 12–24 h after infliction of the wound, and its level returns to basal level after the proliferative stage is completed (Fahey and Doyle 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Tumour necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) is significantly synthesized by macrophages and T lymphocytes and its level increases under inflammation and infection conditions (Xue and Falcon 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Following the induction of inflammation, proliferative phase occurs in which many genes are involved. Insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1) promotes the production of keratinocyte and fibroblast proliferation and improves the re-epithelialization (Daemi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Decreased endothelial insulin/IGF-1 signal delays in the wound healing process (Aghdam et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) induces angiogenesis and stimulates cell migration and proliferation (Farahpour et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Fibroblast growth factor-2 (FGF-2) is a protein that participates in the wound healing process (Souto et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Interleukin-10 (IL-10) reduces the production of pro-inflammatory cytokine, but tumour growth factor-β (TGF-β) has roles in increasing the proliferative phase improving the proliferation and differentiation of fibroblasts, collagen production, and wound contraction (Khezri et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). On the other hand, oxidative stress increases under wound disorders and increases the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) in the site of wound (Ustuner et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Applying antibacterial and antioxidant agents shortens the inflammatory phase, promotes the proliferative phase and accelerates the wound healing process (Bardaa et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Vittorazzi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Daemi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2019a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>).
</p>
