<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes>
 <p content-type="self-citation">
  <mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece37171-cit-1001">
   <string-name>
    <surname>Muletz‐Wolz</surname>
    <given-names>CR</given-names>
   </string-name>, 
   <string-name>
    <surname>Wilson Rankin</surname>
    <given-names>E</given-names>
   </string-name>, 
   <string-name>
    <surname>McGrath‐Blaser</surname>
    <given-names>S</given-names>
   </string-name>, et al. 
   <article-title>Identification of novel bacterial biomarkers to detect bird scavenging by invasive rats</article-title>. 
   <source xml:lang="en">Ecol Evol</source>. 
   <year>2021</year>;
   <volume>11</volume>:
   <fpage>1814</fpage>–
   <lpage>1828</lpage>. 
   <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.7171</pub-id>
  </mixed-citation>
 </p>
 <fn-group id="ece37171-ntgp-0001">
  <fn id="ece37171-note-1001">
   <p>This article has been contributed to by US Government employees and their work is in the public domain in the USA.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="ece37171-note-0001">
   <p>This research was approved by the US Geological Bird Banding Laboratory (permit no. 22958), the State of Hawaii Dept of Land and Natural Resources Division of Forestry and Wildlife (Protected Wildlife permit no. WL13‐02), the Michigan Technological Univ. Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC, no. 332879‐4), the USDA APHIS WS IACUC Protocol QA‐1776, and Stanford IACUC, no. 1776.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn fn-type="funding" id="ece37171-note-0002">
   <p>
    <bold>Funding information</bold>This project was funded by the University of Maryland‐Smithsonian Seed Grant program to DSG, RCF, JEM, and by Robert and Arlene Kogod support of the Secretarial Scholar Program to CRMW. Additional funding included National Science Foundation grants (DEB‐1020007 to DSG; DEB‐1020412 to T. Fukami &amp; C. Giardina; and DEB‐1019928 to D. Flaspohler), the USDA Forest Service Inst. of Pacific Islands Forestry for support in implementation and maintenance of the larger study. Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. None of the funders had any input into the content of the manuscript. None of the funders required their approval of the manuscript before submission or publication.
   </p>
  </fn>
 </fn-group>
</notes>
