<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In recent years, much consideration has been given to characterizing the polyphenol content and evaluating the antioxidant activity of different plant-based materials, especially nuts because their regular consumption is associated with the reduction of some disease risk such as cancer and cardiovascular diseases (CVDs) [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">Juglans</italic> genus or particularly Juglandaceae family includes several species and is widely distributed all over the world. The Persian, English, common walnut or 
 <italic class="italic">Juglans regia</italic> L. (
 <italic class="italic">J. regia</italic> L.), is its well-known member, comprises significant forms of deciduous trees detected mainly in temperate regions and commercially cultivated in Asia, western South America, the United States, and central and southern Europe [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Walnut is a large arbor tree species which is traditionally cultivated for its valuable wood and fruit, attaining the height of 25–35 m, and a trunk up to 2 m in diameter [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Walnut is an appreciated crop because the nut is very popular and widely consumed. Green walnut, shell, husk, kernel, bark, root, and leaves have been extensively used in the pharmaceutical and cosmetic industries [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">J. regia</italic> L. is recognized as a rich source of different valuable chemicals because the kernel, fresh green fruit, husk, shell, skin, bark, leaves, and root are comprehensively studied to use in food, cosmetic and pharmaceutical industries. In this respect, all parts of walnut tree can be used as an excellent source of various compounds expressing antioxidant and antimicrobial potential, as well as antinociceptive, antihistaminic, antiulcer, antiasthmatic, antidiabetics, immunomodulator, antifertility, hepatoprotective, central nervous system stimulant, anti-inflammatory, wound healing, lipolytic, larvicidal, insecticidal and many others properties positively affecting human health [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Walnut is categorized as a strategic species for human nutrition because the food and agriculture organization (FAO) included it in the group of priority plants [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Not only are walnuts used in human nutrition but also the young green walnuts are much appreciated in the traditional folk medicine of some countries and the preparation of jams and a wholesome alcoholic drink named walnut liqueur which contains high levels of phenolic compounds and vitamins. The fruit is left to steep in food-grade ethanol. This liqueur is made out of fresh walnuts with green husks just before the hardening of the endocarp [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Substantially high amounts of by-products rich in phenolic compounds are produced in agricultural industries, which have gained increasing interest due to their excellent antioxidant properties [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Walnut is recognized as one of the agro-crops that produce more waste-heavy materials. It is estimated that ~70% of the fruit weight is shell and husk, low-value waste materials that are rich in different chemicals, mainly phenolic compounds [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
