<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reverse docking is widely used to model interactions at the atomic level between a small molecule (ligand) and a known macromolecule [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Molecular docking and other bioinformatic tools represent cost-effective approaches to screen potential compounds prior to in vitro cell culture-based assays or chemical modifications to accelerate the overall drug discovery process. The importance of the reverse docking technique was evident in its recent application in the identification of p38-alpha kinase as the molecular target of anti-inflammatory natural products hybrids. This approach was directly linked to the identification of esculentoside A’s target and mode of action [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In this present study, we exploited the existing knowledge of anti-tubercular drug targets to predict the potential modes of action of NPs known to have activity against TB. Seven molecular targets of 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic>—ClpP1P2, DprE1, InhA, KasA, PanK, PknB and Pks13—were selected as these are essential for bacterial survival, and their inhibition will affect mycobacterial metabolism [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-00475" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. We herein predict the binding of the NPs in comparison with the established inhibitor of the molecular target, which was referred to as the control. We show that the specific interactions of the bisbenzylisoquinoline alkaloids 2-nortiliacorinine, tiliacorine and 13’-bromotiliacorinine against PknB and DprE1 and the lignan 
 <italic>α</italic>-cubebin with Pks13 had significantly superior docking scores. The predicted interactions here reported should facilitate in vitro validation studies.
</p>
