<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Natural variants of HLF1 could be identified in specimens of 
 <italic>Hirudo medicinalis</italic>, 
 <italic>Hirudo verbana</italic>, and 
 <italic>Hirudo orientalis</italic>, respectively (M端ller et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>). The several variants of HLF1 differ in the length of the C-terminal tail and in the actual number of acidic amino acid residues (ranging from 13 to 16). In addition, they differ in the number (4 or 5) and the composition of the N-terminal amino acid residues (M端ller et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2017</xref>). Strikingly, HLF1 variants with the N-terminal five amino acid residues IVYGP (HLF1V and HLF1long) exhibited very high anti-coagulatory activities comparable to hirudins. In contrast, variants with either four (IYGP, HLF1) or different five N-terminal amino acid residues, specifically IDYEP (HLF1D), had only very low or no detectable activities (M端ller et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>). These results were in very good accordance with examinations of the N-termini of hirudins like HV1 of 
 <italic>Hirudo medicinalis</italic> (Betz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1992</xref>; Wallace et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1989</xref>; Lazar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1991</xref>) or in HM1 of 
 <italic>Hirudinaria manillensis</italic> (De Filippis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1995</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">1998</xref>). HLF2 could not yet be successfully purified but almost completely precipitated during dialysis. However, the construction and functional characterization of hybrid variants of HLF1 and HLF2 bypassed this limitation and subsequently revealed strong evidence for the crucial importance of the central globular domain of HLFs on the anti-thrombin activity of the whole molecule as well. The central globular domain of HLF1 enabled thrombin-inhibitory potency, whereas the central globular domain of HLF2 did not (M端ller et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>). In the current work, we wanted to apply the same strategy and technical approach to analyze and functionally characterize the hirudin-like factors HLF3 and HLF4.
</p>
