<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the 3 last years, the most documented unhealthy gut condition is related to bariatric surgery. Indeed, after a gastric bypass, which drastically modifies the gut anatomy, amino acid bioavailability may be altered in a paradoxical manner. Significantly, the blood appearance of amino acids from 
 <sup>13</sup>C labelled casein was shown to occur faster after gastric bypass than in normal volunteers [
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 <sup>▪▪</sup>]. This result was also associated with a faster glucose handling by the intestine. It is thus likely that bioavailability of amino acids from ingested protein is not impaired by a gastric bypass. Our team confirmed this hypothesis in a gastric bypass rat model in which we observed that 
 <sup>15</sup>N labelled milk protein was paradoxically more digestible in operated rats than in sham rats [
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This better digestive efficiency was slight (+2%) but significant. In this study, we also evaluated the metabolic bioavailability of dietary nitrogen (N) by measuring the 
 <sup>15</sup>N retention in tissues. We found a lower dietary N retention in organs, especially liver and muscle, a paradox that can be explained by a higher retention of dietary N in intestinal mucosa. Indeed, as previously observed, the mucosa was hypertrophied and the 
 <sup>15</sup>N retention/g of tissue was as high in gastric bypass as in sham rats. Gastric bypass but not sleeve gastrectomy slightly improves digestive amino acid bioavailability but lowers metabolic bioavailability which could thus contribute to protein deficiency [
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Energy absorption was evaluated in children with three types of SBS, differing by the length of the bowel and the presence or not of the colon and ileocaecal valve [
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
 <sup>▪▪</sup>]. The energy absorption was only 60–68% and was linearly linked to the length of the small bowel, with a better efficiency in the presence of a remnant colon. The patient characteristic data indicated that apparent protein digestibility was 57–65%, without any effect of the type of SBS, suggesting a protein malabsorption of about 20–30% in this syndrome.
</p>
