<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Four grams of well-mixed egg yolk were weighed into a 100 mL volumetric flask and 25 mL of a chloroform:absolute alcohol (1:1) mixed solvent was slowly added, after which the sample was shaken constantly until the proteins coagulated. An additional 60 to 65 mL of the mixed solvent was added, and the mixture was allowed to stand for 1 h, during which it was shaken every 5 min. Afterward, the sample was brought up to a volume by the mixed solvent, and the mixture was left to stand until clear. The mixture was then filtered, the mixed solvent was evaporated, and egg yolk lipid was obtained. The fatty acid methyl esters were prepared from lipid extracts [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] and quantified by gas-liquid chromatography (GLC). The fatty acid methyl esters were analyzed using a fused silica CP-Sil 88 capillary column with an inside diameter of 50 × 0.25, installed on a Hewlett Packard 5890 GLC “analyzer” with a flame ionization detector. The GLC was temperature programmed to start at 170 °C and to increase by 1 °C/min until reaching 205 °C. The injector and detector temperatures were set at 250 °C and 270 °C, respectively. Hydrogen was used as a carrier gas at a flow rate of 1 mL/min and the split ratio was 1:50. For the cholesterol analysis, the AOAC [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] method was applied with some modifications. A sample of 10 g egg yolk was transferred to a 250 mL flask. The sample was stirred in an ethanol:methanol:isopropanol (90:5:5) solution, in an amount equivalent to 4 mL/g sample, and 1 mL 60% KOH/g sample. The mixture-containing flask was connected to the water-cooled condenser and refluxed for 1 h. After cooling the digest to room temperature, 100 mL of hexane was added, and the mixture was stirred for 10 min, after which 25 mL of deionized water was added, and the mixture stirred for a further 15 min. The layers were then separated, and the hexane layer was collected in an Erlenmeyer flask. An aliquot of 25 mL from the hexane layer was evaporated in a rotary evaporator at 37 °C. The residue was dissolved in 2 mL hexane and 3 μL was injected into a gas-liquid chromatography, Hewlett Packard 5890 GLC with flame ionization detector. A fused silica SE-30 capillary column (25 × 0.25 inside diameter) was installed and the column temperature was set at 260 °C. The injector and detector temperatures were set at 260 °C and 300 °C, respectively. Hydrogen was used as a carrier at a flow rate of 1.5 mL/min, and the split ratio was 1:150.
</p>
