<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Mycotoxin contamination is of serious concern for food safety and security worldwide. These toxins account for enormous economic losses in agricultural productivity and trade, with more severity in poor and developing countries. It is estimated that about 60–80% of crops worldwide can be contaminated by mycotoxins, thus resulting in significant economic losses (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Eskola et al., 2019</xref>). The toxic effects of mycotoxins are persistent, and they are difficult to completely eradicate once they enter the food/feed chain. In the agricultural industry, mycotoxins cause loss in livestock production due to reduced growth rates, decreased immunity and fertility, reduced eggs, meat and milk production, and increased mortality (
 <xref rid="bib150" ref-type="bibr">Thipe et al., 2020</xref>). Furthermore, the effects associated with mycotoxins cause veterinary and healthcare costs (
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">Marroquin-Cardona et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Kagot et al., 2019</xref>). This contamination of food and feedstuffs by mycotoxins equally reduces the nutritional value, quality and safety of food and feed (
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Luo et al., 2018</xref>). Many countries have established regulatory limits on mycotoxins in agricultural commodities to limit human and animal health risks associated with them (
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">Marroquin-Cardona et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Haque et al., 2020</xref>). Mycotoxins cause a disease known as mycotoxicosis (
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Bennett and Klich, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Liew and Mohd-Redzwan, 2018</xref>). The health effects of mycotoxins are extensive as they potentiate some hepatotoxic, nephrotoxic, mutagenic, genotoxic, carcinogenic, immunosuppressive and teratogenic properties. The most prevalent mycotoxins of agricultural importance include the aflatoxins (AFs), ochratoxins (OTA), fumonisins (FBs), trichothecenes and zearalenone (ZEN). These have been given serious attention due to the health risks that they pose in humans and animals (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Dikhoba et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Celik, 2020</xref>).
</p>
