<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Parasite cultures were synchronized by combination of magnetic enrichment [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-16-08273" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] followed by D-sorbitol lysis (5% of D-sorbitol in sterile water) as described by Lambros and Vanderberg [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-16-08273" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. The antimalarial activity of essential oil was evaluated by a radioactive micromethod described elsewhere [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-16-08273" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Tests were performed in triplicate in 96-well culture plates (TPP) with cultures mostly at ring stages (synchronisation interval, 16 h) at 0.5–1% parasitemia (hematocrit, 1.5%). Parasite culture was incubated with each sample for 48 h. Parasite growth was estimated by [
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>H]-hypoxanthine (Perkin-Elmer, Courtaboeuf, France) incorporation, which was added to the plates 24 h before freezing. After 48 h incubation, plates were frozen-defrosted and each well was harvested on a glass fiber filter. Incorporated (
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>H)-hypoxanthine was then determined with a β-counter (1450-Microbeta Trilux, Wallac-Perkin Elmer). The control parasite cultures, free from any sample, was referred to 100% growth. IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> were determined graphically in concentration versus percent inhibition curves. Chloroquine diphosphate was used as positive control. The antimalarial activity of sample was expressed by IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>, representing the concentration of drug that induced a 50% parasitaemia decrease compared to the positive control culture referred to as 100% parasitaemia [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-16-08273" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. According to the literature concerning plant antiplasmodial activities a sample is very active if IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> &lt; 5 mg/L, active if IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> between 5 and 50 mg/L, weakly active if IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> between 50 and 100 mg/L and inactive if IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> &gt; 100 mg/L [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-16-08273" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
