<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="sec-meta" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="contrib-group">
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hamdouch</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af117-ijms-18-01383" href="#af117-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</a>
   </contrib>
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chebli</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af118-ijms-18-01383" href="#af118-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</a>
   </contrib>
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Idrissi</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">L.M.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af117-ijms-18-01383" href="#af117-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</a>
   </contrib>
   <aff id="af117-ijms-18-01383" class="aff" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>Faculty of science, University Ibnou Zohr, Agadir, Morocco
   </aff>
   <aff id="af118-ijms-18-01383" class="aff" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>School of applied sciences, University Ibnou Zohr Agadir, Morocco
   </aff>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Vitro Antifungal and Antioxidant Activities of Essential Oil, Polar and Apolar Extracts of Pulicaria Mauritanica from South-East of Morocco</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vitro antifungal and antioxidant activities of essential oil, methanol and ether extracts and anticorrosive activity of essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Pulicaria mauritanica</span> (Asteraceae) harvested in the oasis of Tata of south-East of Morocco were investigated. Essential oil was extracted using hydrodistillation method; methanol and ether extracts were obtained using soxhlet apparatus. Essential oil showed a strong inhibition of 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium digitatum</span> mycelium growth (100% at 700 ppm); ether extract gave 46.212 ± 1.543% of inhibition at 30,000 ppm, while methanol extract exhibited no activity against 
  <span class="italic">P. digitatum</span>. Methanol extract showed a strong reduction of DPPH (IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 0.027 ± 0.004 mg/mL), while essential oil and ether extract exhibited median reduction of DPPH, IC
  <sub>50</sub> are successively 0.080 ± 0.005 mg/mL and 0.123 ± 0.0006 mg/mL. Phytochemical investigation of studied organic extracts showed that polyphenolic compounds constitute the major compounds of it. Linear correlation between total polyphenols and total flavonoids contents and antioxidant capacity was obtained; the correlation was positive
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Keywords:</span>
  <span class="italic">Pulicaria mauritanica</span>; antifuangal activity; antioxidant activity; IC
  <sub>50</sub>; insecticidal activity; phytochemical analyses
 </p>
</sec>
