<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="sec-meta" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="contrib-group">
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nasri</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af125-ijms-18-01383" href="#af125-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</a>
   </contrib>
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">El Bouhali</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af127-ijms-18-01383" href="#af127-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</a>
   </contrib>
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bouaz</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">S.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af125-ijms-18-01383" href="#af125-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</a>
   </contrib>
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Boughribil</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">S.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af126-ijms-18-01383" href="#af126-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</a>
   </contrib>
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Benaji</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af125-ijms-18-01383" href="#af125-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</a>
   </contrib>
   <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib" xmlns="">
    <name class="name">
     <span class="surname" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eddouks</span>
     <span class="given-names" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">M.</span>
    </name>
    <a ref-type="aff" rid="af127-ijms-18-01383" href="#af127-ijms-18-01383" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</a>
   </contrib>
   <aff id="af125-ijms-18-01383" class="aff" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>Laboratory of Biochemistry, Environment &amp; Agro Alimentary. Team of Pharmacochemistry. URAC 36. Faculty of Sciences and Techniques. University Hassan II, Casablanca
   </aff>
   <aff id="af126-ijms-18-01383" class="aff" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>Laboratory of Virology, Microbiology and Quality. Faculty of Sciences and Techniques. University Hassan II, Casablanca
   </aff>
   <aff id="af127-ijms-18-01383" class="aff" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>Team of nutritional physiology and endocrine pharmacology, Faculty of Sciences and Technology, University Moulay Ismail, Errachidia. This work was supported by the CNRST under grant number PPR/2015/35
   </aff>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thin Layer Chromatography Fingerprinting of Thymelaea Lythroides Extracts for Pharmacological Screening </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Medicinal plants constitute an important reservoir of active and new biomolecules and wide variety of secondary metabolites. The obtaining of reproducible and reliable extracts ensures the reproducibility of the pharmacological activity. Chromatography fingerprinting is an elegant approach to monitoring the compounds involved.We develop TLC fingerprint to evaluate the chemical stability and identifies biomolecules of the extract before screening pharmacological activity. The TLC fingerprint is constructed from the spots and the area of the compounds by software.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div xlink:href="ijms-18-01383-i001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Thymelaea L.</span> is an endemic plant known for its ethno-pharmacological use in several pathologies in Morocco. After extraction by several solvents and evaporation, the residues were subjected to TLC on silica gel. The chemical reagents in solution, sprayed on TLC chromatograms, are used to complement the visual observations under sunlight and for a specific revelation. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our previous studies differential extraction shows four stable compounds. Three flavonoids (Mtb1, Mtb2 Mtb3) were identified and Tpn is probably a terpene. In this research we are focused on polar fraction for antibacterial and antihypertensive screening. This TLC fingerprint is used in first step for preparative chromatography of polar fraction. The first results show promising pharmacological activity.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TLC fingerprinting localizes easily the secondary metabolites and optimizes the fractions for preparative chromatography. It also provides a simple and fast method to monitor a particular component in the mixture. The demonstration of pharmacological activity of family or single molecule becomes more rational.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Keywords:</span> TLC fingerprints; Thymelaea L.; antihypertensive; antibacterial activity
 </p>
</sec>
