<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Kamran et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-biomolecules-09-00138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] studied the preparation of invasomes using beta-citronellene as a permeation enhancer for transdermal delivery of the antihypertensive olmesartan and observed an increase in the bioavailability of olmesartan from invasomes in Wistar rats compared to the control. Incorporation of isradipine, also an antihypertensive agent, in invasomes containing beta-citronellene was investigated by Qadri et al. [
 <xref rid="B42-biomolecules-09-00138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], who showed a decrease of 20% of blood pressure in rats. The permeation of rhodamine B invasomes through rat skin was evaluated by confocal laser spectroscopy, and fluorescence was detected at a depth of 171.18 mm in the skin. A series of studies focused on the encapsulation of temoporfin in invasomes, aiming to improve its penetration through the skin using several different proportions of cineole, citral, and d-limonene. The findings indicated that the optimal amount of terpenes in formulations should be 1% (v/v), and the formulation containing 1% of cineole alone led to higher permeation of the drug to deeper layers of the skin compared to mixtures of the three terpenes in varied proportions and limonene and citral alone [
 <xref rid="B68-biomolecules-09-00138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-biomolecules-09-00138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-09-00138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. El-Nabarawi et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-biomolecules-09-00138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] prepared dapsone-loaded invasomes for acne treatment, containing different terpenes (limonene, cineole, citral, or fenchone) in varied concentrations in a full factorial design study and compared drug deposition in vivo of optimized formulations with dapsone solution, finding a 2.5-fold increase in dapsone deposition with the invasomes formulation.
</p>
