<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The chemotaxonomy study of some 
 <italic>Zanthoxylum</italic> species such as 
 <italic>Z. acanthopodium</italic>, 
 <italic>Z. nitidum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Z. myriacanthum</italic> are found in Northern Thailand [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] or 
 <italic>Z. budrunga</italic>, 
 <italic>Z. bungeanum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Z. schinifolium</italic>, all have shown anti-inflammatory and antinociceptive action [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. 
 <italic>Zanthoxylum rhetsa</italic> is a pungent plant and a member of the Rutaceae family. Its whole fruit consists of pericarp and seed and is used in the diet in the Northern part of Thailand. Both pericarp and fruit are described in Pra-O-Sod-Pra-Narai scripture and Thai Traditional Household Remedy for muscle spasm, a pain relief from swelling of muscle and tendons and also as pain relief from abscesses and hemorrhoids [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
 <italic>Z. rhetsa</italic> fruit is also extensively used as an anti-inflammatory agent and antiseptic in India [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. 
 <italic>Z. rhetsa</italic> fruit and seed are also used as a pain relief treatment from toothache, digestion problems, inflammation, and infection in Southeast Asia [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. 
 <italic>Z. rhetsa</italic> activity is a mosquito repellent, and its larvicidal, antimicrobial, antioxidant, and antitumor activities have been characterized [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Additionally, major chemical compounds in pericarp, fruit, and seed of 
 <italic>Z. rhetsa</italic> as monoterpenes such as limonene, terpinen-4-ol, sabinene, and 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] have been reported for their anti-inflammatory activity [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
