<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0015" class="p">Aiming to evaluate if there would be differences in the bacterial community over time sampling was carried out in 2008 (FSI and RSI) and 2011 (FSII and RSII) at Schist Industrialization Business Unit (Six) of Petrobras, in São Mateus, Paraná, Brazil (25°52′26″ S, 50° 22′58″ W) in storage piles of shale by-products as described by Goes et al.
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">4</sup>
 </xref> An aliquot of 10 g from four samples of shale by-product were enriched in Luria Bertani (LB),
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">5</sup>
 </xref> J. E. medium
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">6</sup>
 </xref> and dispersed sterile water for 30 days prior DNA extraction using the MoBio Powersoil DNA isolation kit (Geneworks, Australia). Extracting high-purity DNA directly from environmental samples is essential for the study of microbial community composition. Direct DNA extraction was performed from by-products at least three times without success. To allow the proliferation of microorganisms that could grow on the medium provided and then make available extractable DNA; we used an enrichment method.
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">7</sup>
 </xref> The total amount of DNA extracted was quantified and checked for purity with a Qubit™ Fluorometer using Quant-iT™ dsDNA BR assay kit (Invitrogen™). Bacterial DNA was amplified using primers F515 (5′-GTGCCAGCMGCCGCGGTAA-3′) and R806 (5′-GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3′) targeting the V4 region of the SSU rRNA gene.
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">8</sup>
 </xref> Barcoded libraries were sequenced on Ion 314™ Chip (10 Mb.p.) using the Ion Torrent Personal Genome Machine – PGM (Life Technologies, USA). Reads were filtered within the Ion Torrent server to remove low quality and polyclonal sequences. The resulting sequencing data sets were uploaded to the Metagenome Rapid Annotation using Subsystem Technology (MG-RAST) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://metagenomics.nmpdr.org/" id="intr0005" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://metagenomics.nmpdr.org/</ext-link>), checked for low-quality reads prior to dereplication, assigned phylogenetic identification of phylum level using the Ribosomal Database Project (RDP) with 95% identity and the alpha diversity index calculation (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/index.jsp" id="intr0010" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/index.jsp</ext-link>).
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">9</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
