<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, Wright and the team explored the antimicrobial properties of 
 <italic>Terminalia ferdinandiana</italic> Exell (Kakadu plum) extracts against 
 <italic>Shewanella</italic> sp. growth, the main cause of fish spoilage (
 <xref rid="B199" ref-type="bibr">Wright et al., 2019</xref>). Several compounds were identified by LC-MS analysis that displayed this pharmacological application. The aqueous extract of 
 <italic>Terminalia bellirica</italic> (Gaertn.) Roxb. from fruits have been reported to contain glycosides, flavonoids, tannins, phenols, saponin, carbohydrates, and proteins (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Abraham et al., 2014</xref>). Proteins, carbohydrates, and tannins were found in both aqueous, and methanol extracts of 
 <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz. leaves. Alkaloids were present in both aqueous and methanol extracts of the fruit, while flavonoids were detected in both aqueous and methanol extracts of all parts of 
 <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz. except root (
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr">Vemuri et al., 2019</xref>). (8)Terflavin B and (9) chebulinic acid were pure compounds isolated from 
 <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz. fruits (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Cock, 2015</xref>). 
 <italic>Terminalia schimperiana</italic> Hochst. ex Engl. &amp; Diels (synonym of 
 <italic>Terminalia glaucescens</italic> Planch. ex Benth.) root bark was reported to contain flavonoids, tannins, steroids, carbohydrates, and terpenoids in n-hexane, ethylacetate, and methanol as solvents (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2019</xref>). Besides, (10)stigmasterol was a pure compound isolated from the root bark of 
 <italic>Terminalia schimperiana</italic> Hochst. ex Engl. &amp; Diels (synonym of 
 <italic>Terminalia glaucescens</italic> Planch. ex Benth.). The pure compound was a white-yellow crystal, characterized by spectral techniques such as 1H-NMR, 13C-NMR, COSY, HSQC, and HMBC spectral techniques (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2019</xref>). Aqueous and methanol extracts of 
 <italic>Terminalia grandiflora</italic> Benth. nut, fruit, and leaf contained high levels of water-soluble phenolics, moderate to high levels of tannins, and low levels of flavonoids and anthraquinones; while 
 <italic>Terminalia carpentariae</italic> C.T.White (synonym of 
 <italic>Terminalia hadleyana</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>carpentariae</italic> (C.T.White) Pedley), leaf extract showed high levels of water-soluble phenolics and tannins (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Wright et al., 2016</xref>). Furthermore, the methanol extract of 
 <italic>Terminalia grandiflora</italic> Benth. nut and 
 <italic>Terminalia carpentariae</italic> C.T.White [synonym of 
 <italic>Terminalia hadleyana</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>carpentariae</italic> (C.T.White) Pedley], leaf exhibited antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Bacillus anthracis</italic> with MIC at 155 and 74 µg/mL, respectively (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Wright et al., 2016</xref>). Pure compounds including (11) methyl N-hydroxybenzenecarboximidoate; (12) 1-octen-3-ol; (13) 5-hepten-2-one; (14) 6-methyl-, 2-tert-butoxyethanol; (15) 2-ethyl-1-hexanol; (16) dimethyl succinate; (17) isophorone; (18) α-citronellol; (19) nonanal; (20) 4-oxoisophorone; (21) ethyl benzoate; (22) methyl benzeneacetate; (23) α-terpineol; (24) 2-isopropylidene-3-methylhexa-3,5-dienal; (25) lauraldehyde; (26) 2,4-dimethyl-benzaldehyde; (27) 1,3-pentanediol; (28) 2,2,4-trimethyl-, 1-isobutyrate; (29) 2,4-di-tert-butylphenol; (30) ethyl para-ethoxybenzoate; and (31) 2,2,4-trimethyl-1,3-pentanediol diisobutyrate were detected from the methanol 
 <italic>Terminalia carpentariae</italic> C.T.White (synonym of 
 <italic>Terminalia hadleyana</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>carpentariae</italic> (C.T.White) Pedley), leaf extract using GC-MS headspace analysis (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Wright et al., 2016</xref>). It has been highlighted that (32) 2-(1,1-dimethylethoxy)-ethanol; (33) caryophyllene; (31) 2,2,4-trimethyl-1,3-pentanediol diisobutyrate; and (34) butyl octyl phthalate were detected in 
 <italic>Terminalia grandiflora</italic> Benth. methanol extract but they were not found in the 
 <italic>Terminalia carpentariae</italic> C.T.White (synonym of 
 <italic>Terminalia hadleyana</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>carpentariae</italic> (C.T.White) Pedley), leaf extract (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Wright et al., 2016</xref>). Groups of flavonoids, including (35) quercetin, (36) kaempferol, tannins, saponins, and phytosterols presented in the 
 <italic>Terminalia catappa</italic> L. fruit, have been documented (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Cock, 2015</xref>). This information indicates varieties of chemical compounds present in 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> plant species. This study shows that there are several chemical compounds in 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> plant species. As such, assessment and isolation of phytochemicals from 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> sp. could hold promise in the discovery of novel new compounds leading to the development of new drugs for the management and control of diseases.
</p>
