<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Results from HS-SPME/GC-MS Analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All three samples of “Kainari” from Mytilini, Paleochori, and Agiassos in Lesvos were studied for the first time to our knowledge. The rich aroma of the mixture was studied through Headspace Solid-Phase Microextraction (HS-SPME)/GC-MS analyses. Furthermore, the pentane and methanol extracts were also studied through GC-MS with respective results. The major constituents that have been determined through GC-MS analyses were cinnamic aldehyde, eugenol, myristicin, 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, curcumene, and zingiberene, which can be related to the possible contained spices as shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Through analyses of all extracts of the three samples (herbal teas, methanol, and pentane extracts) and the simultaneous use of bibliography we conclude that the main components in all three samples are cinnamon (~6/10) and clove (~3/10) and the remaining part (1/10) corresponds to both nutmeg and ginger.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is remarkable that, according to the analyses of the volatiles in KN3, they were not identified as the main components of ginger
   <span class="italic"> (Zingiber officinale)</span> and consequently we assume that ginger is not included in the mixture or it is included in small quantities. As for the presence of cardamom and pepper, due to the lack of some of their main metabolites (some of them exist in other contained plants at the same time), we conclude that if they are present they will be in small quantities.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Isolation and Determination of Compounds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Six compounds were isolated from the essential oil of sample 
   <span class="italic">Κ</span>N2 by applying a series of liquid-liquid extractions based on acid-base chemical reactions, as well as with preparative TLC: eugenol, cinnamic aldehyde, and myristicin were determined by NMR spectroscopy and GC-MS analysis, while cinnamyl alcohol, alpha-terpinyl acetate, and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene were determined only by GC-MS analysis.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also, two food dyes were isolated and identified as parts of the family of azo colors. Samples KN1 and KN2 contained the same food color azorubine [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>], while sample KN3 contained amaranth [
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The azo colors are compounds bearing the functional group R-N = N-R′, where R and R′ may be either aryl or alkyl. Azo dyes are one of the most important chemical categories of dyes which are used for the coloring of natural and synthetic fibers, candies, and cosmetics but also food and beverages [
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>, 
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>]. Many azo dyes are nontoxic, although some of them have been accused for allergic reactions and increasing hyperactivity in children [
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The two isolated compounds are being referred to EFSA as amaranth (E123) and azorubine or carmoisine (Ε122) and are well-known food dyes [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>, 
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Antioxidant Properties</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total phenolic content (TPC) of the three samples was notably high, probably due to the known rich phenolic concentration of all spices that they contain [
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>, 
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>]. The sample KN3 revealed the higher concentration of phenolic content (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The free radical scavenging activities of herbal teas and methanol extracts were determined by DPPH and ABTS assays (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a>). All extracts showed significant antioxidant activity performing 30–64% inhibition at DPPH assay (50 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL), as well as 26–48% inhibition at ABTS assay (10 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/mL). The herbal tea KN3 performed the higher inhibition at DPPH (64.7%) and at ABTS (46.9%) which is in accordance with the high TPC. Also, the methanol extracts of KN1 and KN3 showed high inhibition.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Antimicrobial Bioassay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to in vitro antimicrobial tests (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>) against two Gram-positive bacteria (
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and
   <span class="italic"> S. epidermidis</span>) and four Gram-negative ones (
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span>,
   <span class="italic"> E. cloacae, K. pneumoniae, </span>and
   <span class="italic"> P. aeruginosa</span>), as well as against oral pathogens
   <span class="italic"> (S. mutans and S. viridans)</span> and three human pathogenic fungi (
   <span class="italic">Candida albicans, C. tropicalis, </span>and
   <span class="italic"> C. glabrata</span>), the herbal teas exhibited a broad spectrum of strong antimicrobial activity, while KN3 herbal tea appeared to be the most active against all tested microorganisms, which can be explained by the high percentage of cinnamic aldehyde and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene that appears in herbal tea of KN3 as shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
