<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The extract of 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>raeseri</italic> also exhibited a dose-dependent tracheorelaxant effect when tested on rabbit tracheal rings precontracted with both CCh and high K
 <sup>+</sup>. CCh- and high KCl-induced contractions are associated with membrane depolarization, leading to an increase in the Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx across the plasma membrane through voltage-dependent channels [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The tracheal smooth muscle contractions are initiated by cholinergic agonists such as CCh and high K
 <sup>+</sup> through stimulation of muscarinic receptors that lead to the opening of L-type Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> channels, and consequently enhancing intracellular calcium levels ([Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub>), therefore, resulting in tracheoconstriction [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Compared to high K
 <sup>+</sup>, which leads to muscle contraction by allowing the influx of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> from the extracellular space into the cytosol through the cell membrane, CCh induces contraction by two pathways, either one leading to influx of external Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> in the cytosol and/or another releasing Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> from intracellular stores, sarcoplasmic reticulum [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Accordingly, the SRE appears to involve these two pathways. Our results are entirely consistent with the findings of the previous study reporting the SRE vasorelaxant effect [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Nonspecific inhibition of both CCh and high K
 <sup>+</sup> by the SR extract indicates that nonspecific tracheorelaxant function, apparently, at least partly is accomplished by calcium channel blockade mechanisms. Similar tracheorelaxant effect was reported in our recent research, but for another medicinal plant species, 
 <italic>Vitex agnus-castus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
