<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chronic inflammation is the underlying pathogenesis of a series of diseases, including numerous types of carcinomas, atherosclerosis, autoimmune diseases and obesity, among others. Following stimulation caused by lipopolysaccharides (LPS), a series of pro-inflammatory cytokines are released including prostaglandin mediators, cytokines (TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6) and nitric oxide (NO) [
 <xref rid="B60-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. It was reported that 
 <italic>IOP</italic> can inhibit the induction of NO and other similar cytokines, a phenomenon that has been associated with COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B62-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Similarly, in another experiment on inflammatory bowel disease, 
 <italic>Inonotus obliquus</italic> polysaccharides (
 <italic>IOP)</italic> were shown to alleviate inflammatory responses by inhibiting JAK-STAT signalling pathways that regulate the release of T Helper subsets [
 <xref rid="B63-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Furthermore, the extract of chaga mushroom was also found to possess anticancer properties; however, the exact mechanism of action of these polysaccharides is still unknown [
 <xref rid="B64-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Additionally, the effect of 
 <italic>IOP</italic> extracts on Hepatitis C and human immunodeficiency disease have also been elucidated [
 <xref rid="B56-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. It was concluded that the bioactive molecules of chaga fungus suppressed the expression of JAK-STAT pathway that led to the activation of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, responsible for inflammation [
 <xref rid="B67-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In addition to the mentioned viral diseases, patients infected with COVID-19 also showed similar inflammatory responses possessing significant levels of plasma cytokines and leucocytes. As 
 <italic>IOP</italic>s have shown promising results in treating various viral diseases, the effect of this mushroom in COVID-19 infection could prove to be beneficial.
</p>
