<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium Corylophilum</span> CBMF1
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> is a fungus that may cause the spoilage of bakery products; for this judgment, the essential oils selected were used to determine their antifungal activity against this mold.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f006" href="#materials-10-00045-f006">Figure 6</a> shows the inhibition manifested by the tested essential oils against 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> growth.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effectiveness of thyme oil as an antifungal agent can be noticed from the data presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f006" href="#materials-10-00045-f006">Figure 6</a>. As can be seen, thyme essential oil is more active than clove essential oil, showing an inhibition rate of 100% at 10 µL, while clove oil was less effective (
  <span class="italic">IR</span> = 47.6%) at a volume of 10 µL. As well, tea tree essential oil has antifungal properties, but when a higher oil volume is used. It produced an inhibition of 89.04% for a quantity of 40 µL. It is considered that the antifungal activity of tea tree oil was significantly affected by the presence of high content of γ-terpinene (16.3%), 4-terpineol (38.7%), and α-terpineol (4.6%). Previous studies showed that tea tree oil has antifungal activity against 
  <span class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Rhizopus stolonifer</span> under in vitro conditions, inhibiting the spore germination and mycelial growth [
  <a rid="B43-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-materials-10-00045">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the highest volume used in this study (60 µL), rosemary oil did not inhibit the fungal growth of 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> CBMF1, the IR being below 10%.
 </p>
</sec>
