<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Antibacterial Inhibition</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antibacterial effect of EOs against the growth of 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> was established by the agar disc diffusion method, and the results are presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f008" href="#materials-10-00045-f008">Figure 8</a>. On Mueller–Hinten (MH) agar plates, the inhibition zones of 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> are 64.7 ± 1.2 mm for thyme oil, 27.8 ± 3.4 mm for tea tree oil, 27.8 ± 4.0 mm for clove oil, and 12.8 ± 4.3 mm for rosemary oil. For 
  <span class="italic">E. coli,</span> the inhibition zones are 35.5 ± 4.6 mm for thyme oil, 27.0 ± 3.4 mm for tea tree oil, 19.5 ± 0.5 mm for clove oil, and 15.1 ± 0.5 mm for rosemary oil. The diameters of the inhibition zones in the case of 
  <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> growth are of 69.5 ± 6.4 mm for thyme oil, 22.0 ± 2.8 mm for tea tree oil, and 28.5 ± 2.1 mm for clove oil. There is no inhibition zone for rosemary.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thyme oil had the highest inhibition zones for the three test strains, followed by tea tree oil, and then by clove oil. Rosemary oil was the least active.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thyme essential oil is strongly antimicrobial, antifungal, antiviral, antiparasitic, mainly due to the high content of thymol [
  <a rid="B49-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-materials-10-00045">49</a>]. This is in accordance with other studies that reported that thyme essential oil is efficient against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [
  <a rid="B29-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-materials-10-00045">29</a>,
  <a rid="B30-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-materials-10-00045">30</a>] and fungi [
  <a rid="B28-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-materials-10-00045">28</a>,
  <a rid="B51-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-materials-10-00045">51</a>,
  <a rid="B52-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-materials-10-00045">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to its antimicrobial, antifungal, antivermin, and antiviral activity [
  <a rid="B34-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-materials-10-00045">34</a>,
  <a rid="B35-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-materials-10-00045">35</a>], clove essential oil is used as a preservative but also exhibits other effects with positive impacts on consumer health, including antiseptic, antihelmintic, anti-inflammatory, antispastic, carminative, anti-neuralgic, antiulcer, anti-thrombotic, anticancerinogenic, and anticoagulant activities. Moreover, it acts as a local analgesic [
  <a rid="B36-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-materials-10-00045">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition zones observed after 24 h were stable and identical after 48 and 72 h of incubation. EOs are less effective in the vapor disc diffusion method compared to the disc diffusion method. Thyme and clove oils had volatile components that had inhibition zones even when the disc with EO had no contact with the bacteria. Thyme had the best effect for all test microorganisms, while clove only had an effect on 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t005" href="#materials-10-00045-t005">Table 5</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimal inhibitory concentration of an antimicrobial agent is the lowest (i.e., minimal) concentration of the antimicrobial agent that inhibits a given bacterial isolate from multiplying and producing visible growth in the test system. This concentration was determined by incubating a known quantity of bacteria with specified dilutions of the antimicrobial agent. Using a similar broth dilution method, Zhang et al. [
  <a rid="B53-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-materials-10-00045">53</a>] found that MIC was 1.0 mg/mL of cinnamon for both 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>. Broth microdilution is the most widely used method in clinical laboratories, but agar diffusion is also used. Due to the oily content of EOs, using solvents is needed to obtain homogeneous dilutions. The results obtained using three solvents namely Tween-20, DMSO, and ethanol by the two test methods (agar MIC testing and the broth microdilution test) are shown in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t006" href="#materials-10-00045-t006">Table 6</a>. There are some differences between the test results, but they all showed that thyme is the most effective EO, with a very low concentration needed to inhibit the growth of 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E. coli,</span> followed by clove and tea tree oils. The thyme oil MIC values with the broth dilution method was approximately 0.39%–3.13% for 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 1.56%–3.13% for 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>. Similarly, clove MIC value range were approximately 3.13%–6.26% for 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 6.25% for 
  <span class="italic">E. coli.</span> A strong antimicrobial activity of thyme was also found by Mith et al. [
  <a rid="B54-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-materials-10-00045">54</a>] when they tested different EOs and determined MIC against both food-borne pathogens and spoilage bacteria with a broth dilution method. The MIC value ranges of tea tree oil were approximately 0.80%–25.00% for 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 12.5%–25.00% for 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TTO has gained attention in the food industry for its antimicrobial [
  <a rid="B41-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-materials-10-00045">41</a>,
  <a rid="B42-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-materials-10-00045">42</a>] and antifungal activity [
  <a rid="B43-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-materials-10-00045">43</a>], and it was successfully used in respiratory or genito-urinary tract infections [
  <a rid="B44-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-materials-10-00045">44</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
