<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot6-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Preliminary Results on the Use of Encapsulated Essential Oils into Chitosan Films as Food Packaging Material</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stability of the chitosan/essential oil emulsions was sustained by dynamic light scattering (DLS) analysis, which showed a main particle population with low dimensions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f011" href="#materials-10-00045-f011">Figure 11</a>), with the distribution showing, in the low dimension range, a single peak and a polydispersity index (PDI)-approached value of 1.0 (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t007" href="#materials-10-00045-t007">Table 7</a>). The chitosan/essential oil emulsions contain two kinds of particle populations: the first one is very small, where 
  <span class="italic">d</span> = 5 nm for the chitosan solution and 11–70 (350) nm for the emulsion containing EOs, and the second contains larger particles of 850 nm for CS and 2500–8800 nm for CS/EOs emulsions. Oils are probably concentrated around CS particles because of aggregation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scanning electron microscopy examination reveals the morphology of the films obtained by the incorporation of essential oils into chitosan films—
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f012" href="#materials-10-00045-f012">Figure 12</a>. The films are relatively homogeneous, and dispersion of the essential oil in the film obtained by solvent casting is homogeneous, as is evident from the SEM images taken at high magnification (2000×).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It can be observed that the surfaces are very smooth, and, by essential oil incorporation, very small particles are evidenced at high magnification. The good homogeneity of the films and the encapsulation of the oils is assured by the presence of a nonionic surfactant and emulsifier T80.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The encapsulation of active (antimicrobial and antioxidant) essential oils into the chitosan matrix leads to a significant decrease in the total number of germs for beef meat packed in such films—from 2400–1020 CFU/cm
  <span class="sup">2</span> for films containing only CS to 700 CFU/cm
  <span class="sup">2</span> for films containing both CS and clove oil. These films proved to have a good antimicrobial activity for delaying the spoilage of beef meat, with both antimicrobial agents acting synergistically [
  <a rid="B56-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-materials-10-00045">56</a>]. This research will be the topic of the subsequent paper.
 </p>
</sec>
