<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on GC-MSD/FID analysis, it has been established that the commercially available thyme, rosemary, clove, and tea tree essential oils correspond to AFNOR/ISO standards.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this study demonstrate the potential of thyme oil, clove oil, and tea tree oil for use as antifungal agents against tested fungi strains (
  <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span> G87, 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> CBMF1, and 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis</span> ATCC 16404) and three potential pathogenic food bacteria: 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</span>. The overall results of the MIC values show that thyme oil is the most effective with a very low concentration used against both on the three fungi and bacteria, followed by clove and tea tree oils, while the rosemary oil is less active or inactive.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the antioxidant activity, the IC50 of the analyzed essential oils is in the μg/mL range that is assigned to a very good antioxidant activity which varies in the following order: clove oil &gt; thyme oil &gt; rosemary oil &gt; tee tree oil, and the clove oil exhibits the highest radical scavenging activity.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Promising results were obtained by their incorporation into chitosan emulsions and films, with potential applications in food packaging that will be detailed in a future paper. Taking into account their biological activity in addition, it is expected that their use can also benefit consumers’ health.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the basis of the obtained results, it can be concluded that these essential oils can be suitable alternatives to chemical additives, satisfying the consumer demand for naturally preserved food products and ensuring their safety at the same time.</p>
</sec>
