<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Chemical Composition</div>
  <sec id="sec2dot1dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.1. Phenolic Content</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The phenolic content of extracts of many plants contributes significantly to their total antioxidant activity. The antioxidant feature of the investigated essential oils was determined by the phenolic compouds presence in their composition by the Folin–Ciocâlteu method [
    <a rid="B20-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-materials-10-00045">20</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total concentration of phenolic compounds found in essential oil samples are presented in 
    <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t001" href="#materials-10-00045-t001">Table 1</a>, and a decrease in phenolic content concentration in the following order was found: clove &gt; thyme &gt; tea tree &gt; rosemary. Excepting the rosemary oil, all oils were found to have different phenolic levels, ranging from 0.034 to 1.136 mg·GAE/g·DW, which can play a vital role in the increase of food shelf-life. The clove oil has the highest content of phenolic compounds.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot1dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.2. GC-MSD and GC-FID Analysis</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The composition (including both main components and those in low amount but with significant biological/therapeutic effects) of the essential oils varies depending on the geographical position, the plant’s origin and species, harvest time, distillation/extraction procedure, etc. [
    <a rid="B17-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-materials-10-00045">17</a>]. Additionally, the composition of the essential oils and consequently their biological/therapeutic activities depend on the combination and ratio of their numerous different components. Gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry (GC-MSD) and flame ionization (GC-FID) detectors was used to determine the quality and quantity of chemical compounds in the essential oils.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chromatograms of studied essential oils are shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f001" href="#materials-10-00045-f001">Figure 1</a>, 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f002" href="#materials-10-00045-f002">Figure 2</a>, 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f003" href="#materials-10-00045-f003">Figure 3</a> and 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f004" href="#materials-10-00045-f004">Figure 4</a>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential thyme oil contains especially thymol, p-cymene, γ-terpinene, linalol, isothymol (carvacrol/biosol), and β-myrcene—
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f001" href="#materials-10-00045-f001">Figure 1</a>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The clove essential oil had the simplest composition, based on eugenol/eugenol acetate and β-/α-caryophyllene, accompanied by several other sesquiterpenes—
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f002" href="#materials-10-00045-f002">Figure 2</a>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rosemary oil is rich in light monoterpenes, containing mainly eucalyptol, camphor, α-/β-pinene, camphene, borneol, and limonene—
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f003" href="#materials-10-00045-f003">Figure 3</a>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tea tree essential oil contained both light monoterpenes and numerous sesquiterpenes. The main compound is 4-terpineol, followed by γ-terpinene, 2-carene, α-terpineol, α-terpinene, α-pinene, o-cymene, limonene, β-caryophyllene, eucalyptol, and β-myrcene—
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f004" href="#materials-10-00045-f004">Figure 4</a>. Standards ask for α-terpinene (5%–13%), which was not found in our tee tree sample, instead 2-carene was found in high amounts of about 10%. Aromadendrene and δ-cadinene, mentioned by standards in amounts varying from traces up to 7%–8% were confirmed in the studied sample.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main classes of compounds identified in the studied essential oils are presented in 
    <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t002" href="#materials-10-00045-t002">Table 2</a>. Under the mentioned analysis parameters, only volatile compounds up to the level of sesquiterpenes were detected.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t003" href="#materials-10-00045-t003">Table 3</a> shows the quantitative composition (based on Gas Chromatographz with Flame Ioniyation Detector (GC-FID) of the analyzed essential oils. The GC-FID analysis was performed on several different samples obtained from the same company, i.e., Fares, Orăştie-Romania, and no relevant difference was found between them. The results are reproducible.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The composition of the four essential oils is within the limits of AFNOR (Association French Normalization Organization Regulation)/ISO standards [
    <a rid="B21-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-materials-10-00045">21</a>,
    <a rid="B22-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-materials-10-00045">22</a>,
    <a rid="B23-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-materials-10-00045">23</a>,
    <a rid="B24-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-materials-10-00045">24</a>,
    <a rid="B25-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-materials-10-00045">25</a>], except for a few differences, which could be considered within the error limits of the analysis. Deviation in the composition from standard values may not interfere with the therapeutic properties of the essential oils; however, if oils respect the standard limits, it is safer to consider them usable according to the general practice.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ORAC index shows the antioxidant capacity of the oils. According to databases, the antioxidant capacity is highest for clove essential oil, followed at a high distance by thyme oil, while the antioxidant capacity for tea tree is smaller than those of other essential oils. These statements are in accordance with results obtained by the Folin–Ciocâlteu method.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the gas chromatography analysis coupled with mass spectrometry and flame ionisation detectors, the commercial essential oils of thyme (
    <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> L.), clove (
    <span class="italic">Eugenia caryophyllus</span>), rosemary (
    <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> L.), and tea tree (
    <span class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia aetheroleum</span>) were found to have compositions within the limits of the AFNOR/ISO standards.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the obtained results related to the composition of the studied essential oils are in accordance with those found by other authors and constitute support for the explanation of their potential biological activity spectrum [
    <a rid="B28-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-materials-10-00045">28</a>,
    <a rid="B29-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-materials-10-00045">29</a>,
    <a rid="B30-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-materials-10-00045">30</a>,
    <a rid="B31-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-materials-10-00045">31</a>,
    <a rid="B32-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-materials-10-00045">32</a>,
    <a rid="B33-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-materials-10-00045">33</a>,
    <a rid="B34-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-materials-10-00045">34</a>,
    <a rid="B35-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-materials-10-00045">35</a>,
    <a rid="B36-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-materials-10-00045">36</a>,
    <a rid="B37-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-materials-10-00045">37</a>,
    <a rid="B38-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-materials-10-00045">38</a>,
    <a rid="B39-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-materials-10-00045">39</a>,
    <a rid="B40-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-materials-10-00045">40</a>,
    <a rid="B41-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-materials-10-00045">41</a>,
    <a rid="B42-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-materials-10-00045">42</a>,
    <a rid="B43-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-materials-10-00045">43</a>,
    <a rid="B44-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-materials-10-00045">44</a>]. Thyme essential oil (TEO) is obtained from 
    <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> L. and exhibits antimicrobial effects due to its constituents. Omidbeygi et al. [
    <a rid="B28-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-materials-10-00045">28</a>] found that the major compounds of TEO are thymol, carvacrol with similar chemical structures, linalool, and ρ-cymene [
    <a rid="B28-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-materials-10-00045">28</a>,
    <a rid="B29-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-materials-10-00045">29</a>]. The presence of thymol (2-Isopropyl-5-methylphenol) and carvacrol enhanced the TEO antimicrobial activity [
    <a rid="B30-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-materials-10-00045">30</a>,
    <a rid="B31-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-materials-10-00045">31</a>,
    <a rid="B32-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-materials-10-00045">32</a>]. Clove essential oil (
    <span class="italic">Caryophylli aetheroleum</span>) (CEO) isolated from the dry floral buds of 
    <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span>, belonging to the 
    <span class="italic">Myrtaceae</span> family has been used for its antimicrobial activity. Goni [
    <a rid="B33-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-materials-10-00045">33</a>], Shao [
    <a rid="B34-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-materials-10-00045">34</a>], and Sebaaly [
    <a rid="B35-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-materials-10-00045">35</a>] established that the CEO is composed mainly of phenylpropanoides such as eugenol, β-caryophyllene, and the eugenyl acetate [
    <a rid="B33-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-materials-10-00045">33</a>,
    <a rid="B34-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-materials-10-00045">34</a>,
    <a rid="B35-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-materials-10-00045">35</a>,
    <a rid="B36-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-materials-10-00045">36</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Jiang et al. [
    <a rid="B37-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-materials-10-00045">37</a>] found that the rosemary essential oil (
    <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> L.) (REO) can be used in the food industry as a flavoring agent and preservative because of its antimicrobial and antioxidant properties [
    <a rid="B37-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-materials-10-00045">37</a>]. Among the terpenes found in the composition of REO, the main components are the following: cineole, camphor, α-pinene, camphene, and α-terpineol [
    <a rid="B38-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-materials-10-00045">38</a>,
    <a rid="B39-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-materials-10-00045">39</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sánchez-González et al. [
    <a rid="B33-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-materials-10-00045">33</a>,
    <a rid="B40-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-materials-10-00045">40</a>] established that the essential oil of 
    <span class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia,</span> also known as tea tree essential oil (TTO) is composed of terpene, mainly monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and tertiary alcohols [
    <a rid="B33-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-materials-10-00045">33</a>,
    <a rid="B40-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-materials-10-00045">40</a>,
    <a rid="B41-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-materials-10-00045">41</a>,
    <a rid="B42-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-materials-10-00045">42</a>,
    <a rid="B43-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-materials-10-00045">43</a>]. The main components of TTO are terpineol, cineol, pinen, and terpinen and demonstrated antimicrobial activity [
    <a rid="B40-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-materials-10-00045">40</a>,
    <a rid="B44-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-materials-10-00045">44</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Antifungal Activity of the Tested Essential Oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antifungal activity of the essential oils against the three fungi strains examined was assessed by the percentage of the inhibition rate (
   <span class="italic">IR</span>%) and minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC). In order to evaluate the quantity of essential oils needed to be used, a preliminary investigation was carried out with a volume of 10 µL and 20 µL of each of them. After this screening, the maximum concentration used was 60 µL, while the minimum volume used was 2.5 µL. The results presented in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f005" href="#materials-10-00045-f005">Figure 5</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f006" href="#materials-10-00045-f006">Figure 6</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f007" href="#materials-10-00045-f007">Figure 7</a> for the antifungal activity of the essential oils tested are the ones from the 7th day of analyses. From all tested oils, the most effective were the essential oils of clove, thyme, and tea tree. The efficacy of these essential oils can be attributed to the terpenes and phenylpropanoides present in their composition. The research studies demonstrated that phenolic compounds are responsible for the antifungal potential of these oils.
  </p>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1. 
    <span class="italic">Fusarium Graminearum</span> G87
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span>, being a plant pathogen, is a fungus commonly found in cereal grains (mostly wheat and barley). This pathogen has the potential to produce mycotoxines (deoxynivalenol and zearalonene) that have a negative impact on human and animal health [
    <a rid="B45-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-materials-10-00045">45</a>]. The contamination of cereals by this toxigenic mold produces major economic impacts in agriculture.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils selected were tested against 
    <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span>, and the results are presented in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f005" href="#materials-10-00045-f005">Figure 5</a>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fungal growth inhibition induced by essential oils, as determined by the disc diffusion assay, was dependent mostly on the volume (varying from 5 µL to 60 µL) and nature of the essential oils. According to the results presented in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f005" href="#materials-10-00045-f005">Figure 5</a>, it can be noticed that the essential oils tested had antifungal activity against 
    <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span> G87, but their efficacy is different. Thyme essential oil was the most effective, with an inhibition rate of over 80% at the lowest volume of essential oil used for the growth inhibition of this fungus, namely, 87.04% for 7 µL. Clove oil was also effective against the tested fungus, with an inhibition rate of 81.64% when using 40 µL. It is assumed that the high antifungal potential of clove essential oil is due to its active principle, eugenol (85.7%). The results are in accordance with the study of Abbaszadeh et al. [
    <a rid="B46-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-materials-10-00045">46</a>] regarding the effectiveness of eugenol against pathogenic fungi, which demonstrated that this phenylpropanoide had antifungal activity against all tested fungi. The antifungal activity was in direct ratio with the concentration of eugenol added to the media. In a study made by Marin et al. [
    <a rid="B47-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-materials-10-00045">47</a>] who tested the efficacy of cinnamon, clove, oregano, palmarosa, and lemongrass oils against the mycotoxines produced by 
    <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span>, it was shown that clove essential oils was the most efficient against zearalenone and deoxynivalenol release.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rosemary essential oil exhibits antifungal activity, but this was very low. For a volume of 60 µL of this oil, the inhibition was below 10%. Tea tree essential oil had an inhibition rate higher than 80% against 
    <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> G87 only for the highest volume used in this study (60 µL).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. 
    <span class="italic">Penicillium Corylophilum</span> CBMF1
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> is a fungus that may cause the spoilage of bakery products; for this judgment, the essential oils selected were used to determine their antifungal activity against this mold.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f006" href="#materials-10-00045-f006">Figure 6</a> shows the inhibition manifested by the tested essential oils against 
    <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> growth.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effectiveness of thyme oil as an antifungal agent can be noticed from the data presented in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f006" href="#materials-10-00045-f006">Figure 6</a>. As can be seen, thyme essential oil is more active than clove essential oil, showing an inhibition rate of 100% at 10 µL, while clove oil was less effective (
    <span class="italic">IR</span> = 47.6%) at a volume of 10 µL. As well, tea tree essential oil has antifungal properties, but when a higher oil volume is used. It produced an inhibition of 89.04% for a quantity of 40 µL. It is considered that the antifungal activity of tea tree oil was significantly affected by the presence of high content of γ-terpinene (16.3%), 4-terpineol (38.7%), and α-terpineol (4.6%). Previous studies showed that tea tree oil has antifungal activity against 
    <span class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</span> and 
    <span class="italic">Rhizopus stolonifer</span> under in vitro conditions, inhibiting the spore germination and mycelial growth [
    <a rid="B43-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-materials-10-00045">43</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the highest volume used in this study (60 µL), rosemary oil did not inhibit the fungal growth of 
    <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> CBMF1, the IR being below 10%.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot2dot3-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.3. 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus Brasiliensis</span> ATCC 16404
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis</span> is a black mold that can spoil food products, especially fruits and vegetables [
    <a rid="B48-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-materials-10-00045">48</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition rate of the tested essential oils (thyme oil, clove oil, rosemary oil, tea tree oil) against 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis</span> ATCC 16404 is presented in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f007" href="#materials-10-00045-f007">Figure 7</a>. The results presented evidenced that thyme oil was effective against 
    <span class="italic">A. brasiliensis</span> ATCC 16404 at a volume of 5 µL (
    <span class="italic">IR</span> = 97.43%), while clove oil shows antifungal activity at a volume of 30 µL (
    <span class="italic">IR</span> = 82.64%). The strong antifungal activity of thyme oil is attributed to phenolic compounds carvacrol (2.75%) and thymol (43.1%), while the antimicrobial effectiveness of clove oil is associated with the activity of eugenol (85.7%), β-caryophyllene (4.5%), and eugenol acetate (7.9%). Similar studies were conducted by Abbaszadeh et al. [
    <a rid="B46-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-materials-10-00045">46</a>], who tested the antifungal efficiency of thymol, carvacrol, eugenol, and menthol on growth inhibition of some important food-borne pathogens. The results showed that thymol and carvacrol inhibited the fungal growth of 
    <span class="italic">Cladosporium</span> spp., 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus</span> spp., 
    <span class="italic">Fusarium oxysporum</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Penicillium</span> spp., 
    <span class="italic">Alternaria alternata</span>, and 
    <span class="italic">Rhizopus oryzae</span>, and the inhibition growth was dependent on the concentration used.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil of rosemary showed an inhibition rate of 14.22% for the volume of 60 µL. Jiang et al. [
    <a rid="B37-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-materials-10-00045">37</a>] tested the antimicrobial activity of rosemary essential oil and its main components, α-pinene and 1.8-cineole, against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria and fungi (
    <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span>). This study showed that the antimicrobial activity of rosemary essential oil was superior to its active compounds, and the essential oil is more active against all the bacteria used in this research compared to the tested fungi, concluding that the synergism between its compounds determine the antifungal activity.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tea tree essential oil inhibited the growth of the tested fungus with an inhibition rate of 88.90% for a volume of 35 µL.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing antifungal activity results of the studied essential oils, the following decreasing order of activity is evident: thyme oil &gt; clove oil &gt; tea tree oil &gt;&gt; rosemary oil. Concerning the sensitivity to various fungi, the thyme oil and tea tree oil are very effective in the inhibition of the 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis,</span> as is clove oil in the inhibition of the 
    <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum.</span> The rosemary oil is less effective as an antifungal agent but shows some activity against 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasiliensis.</span> However, other studies have evidenced that high-quality rosemary oil has antitumor, antifungal, and antiparasitic effects [
    <a rid="B49-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-materials-10-00045">49</a>]. It has also analgesic, anticancer, anticatarrhal, anti-infection, anti-inflammatory, and expectorant properties and stimulates the circulatory system [
    <a rid="B50-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-materials-10-00045">50</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Minimum Inhibitory Concentration</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimum inhibitory concentrations of the tested essential oils (EOs of thyme, clove, rosemary, and tea tree oils) are presented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t004" href="#materials-10-00045-t004">Table 4</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data presented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t004" href="#materials-10-00045-t004">Table 4</a> shows that, from all the essential oils tested in this study, rosemary oil did not show desirable results against the selected fungi.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results evidenced that the most effective essential oil from the tested oils was thyme essential oil, which displayed strong antifungal activity with MIC values between 116.27 and 174.41 ppm. MIC values of clove, rosemary, and tea tree essential oils were found within the range of 465.11–1395.34 ppm.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Antibacterial Inhibition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antibacterial effect of EOs against the growth of 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> was established by the agar disc diffusion method, and the results are presented in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f008" href="#materials-10-00045-f008">Figure 8</a>. On Mueller–Hinten (MH) agar plates, the inhibition zones of 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> are 64.7 ± 1.2 mm for thyme oil, 27.8 ± 3.4 mm for tea tree oil, 27.8 ± 4.0 mm for clove oil, and 12.8 ± 4.3 mm for rosemary oil. For 
   <span class="italic">E. coli,</span> the inhibition zones are 35.5 ± 4.6 mm for thyme oil, 27.0 ± 3.4 mm for tea tree oil, 19.5 ± 0.5 mm for clove oil, and 15.1 ± 0.5 mm for rosemary oil. The diameters of the inhibition zones in the case of 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> growth are of 69.5 ± 6.4 mm for thyme oil, 22.0 ± 2.8 mm for tea tree oil, and 28.5 ± 2.1 mm for clove oil. There is no inhibition zone for rosemary.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thyme oil had the highest inhibition zones for the three test strains, followed by tea tree oil, and then by clove oil. Rosemary oil was the least active.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thyme essential oil is strongly antimicrobial, antifungal, antiviral, antiparasitic, mainly due to the high content of thymol [
   <a rid="B49-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-materials-10-00045">49</a>]. This is in accordance with other studies that reported that thyme essential oil is efficient against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [
   <a rid="B29-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-materials-10-00045">29</a>,
   <a rid="B30-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-materials-10-00045">30</a>] and fungi [
   <a rid="B28-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-materials-10-00045">28</a>,
   <a rid="B51-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-materials-10-00045">51</a>,
   <a rid="B52-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-materials-10-00045">52</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to its antimicrobial, antifungal, antivermin, and antiviral activity [
   <a rid="B34-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-materials-10-00045">34</a>,
   <a rid="B35-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-materials-10-00045">35</a>], clove essential oil is used as a preservative but also exhibits other effects with positive impacts on consumer health, including antiseptic, antihelmintic, anti-inflammatory, antispastic, carminative, anti-neuralgic, antiulcer, anti-thrombotic, anticancerinogenic, and anticoagulant activities. Moreover, it acts as a local analgesic [
   <a rid="B36-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-materials-10-00045">36</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition zones observed after 24 h were stable and identical after 48 and 72 h of incubation. EOs are less effective in the vapor disc diffusion method compared to the disc diffusion method. Thyme and clove oils had volatile components that had inhibition zones even when the disc with EO had no contact with the bacteria. Thyme had the best effect for all test microorganisms, while clove only had an effect on 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t005" href="#materials-10-00045-t005">Table 5</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimal inhibitory concentration of an antimicrobial agent is the lowest (i.e., minimal) concentration of the antimicrobial agent that inhibits a given bacterial isolate from multiplying and producing visible growth in the test system. This concentration was determined by incubating a known quantity of bacteria with specified dilutions of the antimicrobial agent. Using a similar broth dilution method, Zhang et al. [
   <a rid="B53-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-materials-10-00045">53</a>] found that MIC was 1.0 mg/mL of cinnamon for both 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span>. Broth microdilution is the most widely used method in clinical laboratories, but agar diffusion is also used. Due to the oily content of EOs, using solvents is needed to obtain homogeneous dilutions. The results obtained using three solvents namely Tween-20, DMSO, and ethanol by the two test methods (agar MIC testing and the broth microdilution test) are shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t006" href="#materials-10-00045-t006">Table 6</a>. There are some differences between the test results, but they all showed that thyme is the most effective EO, with a very low concentration needed to inhibit the growth of 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">E. coli,</span> followed by clove and tea tree oils. The thyme oil MIC values with the broth dilution method was approximately 0.39%–3.13% for 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 1.56%–3.13% for 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span>. Similarly, clove MIC value range were approximately 3.13%–6.26% for 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 6.25% for 
   <span class="italic">E. coli.</span> A strong antimicrobial activity of thyme was also found by Mith et al. [
   <a rid="B54-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-materials-10-00045">54</a>] when they tested different EOs and determined MIC against both food-borne pathogens and spoilage bacteria with a broth dilution method. The MIC value ranges of tea tree oil were approximately 0.80%–25.00% for 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 12.5%–25.00% for 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TTO has gained attention in the food industry for its antimicrobial [
   <a rid="B41-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-materials-10-00045">41</a>,
   <a rid="B42-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-materials-10-00045">42</a>] and antifungal activity [
   <a rid="B43-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-materials-10-00045">43</a>], and it was successfully used in respiratory or genito-urinary tract infections [
   <a rid="B44-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-materials-10-00045">44</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Antioxidant Activity Evaluation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results obtained by the ABTS method—
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f009" href="#materials-10-00045-f009">Figure 9</a>—are well correlated with those obtained by 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH)—
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f010" href="#materials-10-00045-f010">Figure 10</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the analyzed essential oils, IC50 is in the μg/mL range assigned to a very good antioxidant activity [
   <a rid="B55-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-materials-10-00045">55</a>]. From the selected essential oils, the clove oil is by far the most radical scavenging active, with an IC50 of 8 μg/mL. The antioxidant activity was associated with the presence of phenolic compounds in the composition of essential oils, as determined by the Folin–Ciocâlteu method and the GC-FID technique and ORAC values. The antioxidant activity varies in the following order: clove oil &gt; thyme oil &gt; rosemary oil &gt;&gt; tea tree oil. Based on the radical scavenging tests, the clove oil is the most effective antioxidant is recommended for further such applications.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot6-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Preliminary Results on the Use of Encapsulated Essential Oils into Chitosan Films as Food Packaging Material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stability of the chitosan/essential oil emulsions was sustained by dynamic light scattering (DLS) analysis, which showed a main particle population with low dimensions (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f011" href="#materials-10-00045-f011">Figure 11</a>), with the distribution showing, in the low dimension range, a single peak and a polydispersity index (PDI)-approached value of 1.0 (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="materials-10-00045-t007" href="#materials-10-00045-t007">Table 7</a>). The chitosan/essential oil emulsions contain two kinds of particle populations: the first one is very small, where 
   <span class="italic">d</span> = 5 nm for the chitosan solution and 11–70 (350) nm for the emulsion containing EOs, and the second contains larger particles of 850 nm for CS and 2500–8800 nm for CS/EOs emulsions. Oils are probably concentrated around CS particles because of aggregation.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scanning electron microscopy examination reveals the morphology of the films obtained by the incorporation of essential oils into chitosan films—
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="materials-10-00045-f012" href="#materials-10-00045-f012">Figure 12</a>. The films are relatively homogeneous, and dispersion of the essential oil in the film obtained by solvent casting is homogeneous, as is evident from the SEM images taken at high magnification (2000×).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It can be observed that the surfaces are very smooth, and, by essential oil incorporation, very small particles are evidenced at high magnification. The good homogeneity of the films and the encapsulation of the oils is assured by the presence of a nonionic surfactant and emulsifier T80.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The encapsulation of active (antimicrobial and antioxidant) essential oils into the chitosan matrix leads to a significant decrease in the total number of germs for beef meat packed in such films—from 2400–1020 CFU/cm
   <span class="sup">2</span> for films containing only CS to 700 CFU/cm
   <span class="sup">2</span> for films containing both CS and clove oil. These films proved to have a good antimicrobial activity for delaying the spoilage of beef meat, with both antimicrobial agents acting synergistically [
   <a rid="B56-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-materials-10-00045">56</a>]. This research will be the topic of the subsequent paper.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
