<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Experimental Section</div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Materials</div>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential Oils</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four commercial essential oils used in this study were purchased from the Fares company (Orăştie, Romania): thyme (
    <span class="italic">Thymus Vulgaris</span> L.), clove (
    <span class="italic">Eugenia caryophyllus</span>—from dried floral buds of 
    <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span>), rosemary (
    <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> L.), and tea tree (
    <span class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia aetheroleum</span>) obtained using a distillation apparatus (according to European Pharmacopoeia 7th edition, method 8.2.12).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Folin–Ciocâlteu phenol reagent 2N was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland), and sodium carbonate decahydrate (Na
    <sub>2</sub>CO
    <sub>3</sub>·10H
    <sub>2</sub>O, 
    <span class="italic">M</span> = 286.14) was from Chimopar S.A., Bucuresti, Romania. Methanol and gallic acid (97%, 
    <span class="italic">M</span> = 170.12) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the determination of the antioxidant activity 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH, Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany), 2,2′-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt (ABTS, purity ≥ 98% by HPLC, Sigma-Aldrich, Darmsadt, Germany) and potassium persulfate (KPS, ACS reagent, purity ≥ 99.0%, Fluka, Buchs, Switzerland) were used. High purity solvents such as Tween-20 from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland) containing lauric acid, ≥40% (balance primarily myristic, palmoyic, and stearic acids; dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, Sigma-Aldrich, Buchs, Switzerland), or ethanol (Sigma-Aldrich, Buchs, Switzerland) were used in the antibacterial activity test.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Chitosan</span> (CS) from crab shells, with a dynamic viscosity of &gt;400 mPa·s in 1% acetic acid (20 °C) where 
    <span class="italic">MW</span> = 310,000–375,000 g/mol, was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polysorbate 80 or Tween
    <span class="sup">®</span> 80 (T80) is a viscous, water-soluble viscous yellow liquid, a nonionic surfactant and emulsifier often used in foods and cosmetics. It was offered by Sigma-Aldrich (Buchs, Switzerland) for research purposes.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Microorganisms</div>
  <sec id="sec3dot2dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1. Fungi</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three food-related fungi were used as target microorganisms in this study: 
    <span class="italic">Aspergillus brasilliensis</span> ATCC 16404, 
    <span class="italic">Penicillium corylophilum</span> CBMF1, and 
    <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span> G87, and they were provided from the collection of Faculty of Biotechnology of University of Agronomic Sciences and Veterinary Medicine Bucharest (Bucharest, Romania).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3dot2dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.2. Bacteria</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The three tested bacterial strains were obtained from the Culture Collection at the University of Gothenburg: 
    <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> CCUG 1828, 
    <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> CCUG 10979, and 
    <span class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</span> CCUG 15527. A test culture was prepared by growth on MH agar overnight, and colonies were diluted to a 0.5 McFarland in MH broth.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Methods of Investigation</div>
  <sec id="sec3dot3dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.1. Determination of Total Phenolic Content in Vegetable Oils by the Folin–Ciocâlteu Reagent Method</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amount of total phenols was determined by the Folin–Ciocâlteu reagent method as described by Scalbert et al. [
    <a rid="B18-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-materials-10-00045">18</a>]. A 10 μL volume of essential oil was dissolved in 10 mL of methanol, and 0.1 mL of methanol solution was then transferred into a volumetric flask and diluted with 0.4 mL of double distilled water and used for analysis. A Folin–Ciocâlteu reagent solution 1:10 
    <span class="italic">v</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span> in double distilled water (1 mL) was added to the diluted methanol/oil mixture (0.5 mL), which was then mixed thoroughly and leaved for 10 minutes at room temperature. A 2 mL solution based on 15% sodium carbonate (Na
    <sub>2</sub>CO
    <sub>3</sub>·10H
    <sub>2</sub>O) was added; after 1 h of incubation at room temperature, the absorbance was measured at 740 nm with a UV-Vis 60 Cary spectrophotometer against a blank sample that was concomitantly prepared. The blank sample contained 0.1 mL of methanol without oil, 0.4 mL of water, 1 mL of a Folin–Ciocâlteu reagent solution, and 2 mL of a Na
    <sub>2</sub>CO
    <sub>3</sub>·10H
    <sub>2</sub>O solution. Gallic acid was used as the standard for the calibration curve, which was drawn using solutions of the gallic acid in methanol of different concentrations ranging between 0.01 and 1 mg/mL. Based on the measured absorbance at 740 nm, the concentration of phenolics was read (mg/mL) from the calibration line, and the total phenolics values were then expressed as mg·GAE/g·DW. Each determination was made in triplicate, and average values were reported.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3dot3dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.2. Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry Detector and Flame-Ionized Detector Analysis (GC-MSD/FID)</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils were characterized by gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry detector (GC-MSD) for qualitative analysis and, with a flame ionized detector (GC-FID) (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA), quantitative analysis.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GC analysis was performed on a 6890 Agilent Technologies chromatograph using the following parameters: a Teknokroma TR-520232 (95% dimethyl- and 5% diphenyl-polysiloxane, crosslinked; 30 m × 250 μm × 0.25 μm) capillary column, a 1 mL/min helium flow, an inlet at 175 °C, a 100:1 split ratio, and a temperature program starting at 60 °C, with a heating rate of 7 °C/min up to 200 °C and then 15 °C/min up to 300 °C, followed by isothermal heating at 300 °C for 3.33 min.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MS detection was performed on a 5975 Inert XL Agilent Technologies detector (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA), at 70 eV. Identification of chromatographic peaks was made by reference to Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) database, with a quality of recognition above 90%.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot4-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Fungi Spore Suspension Preparation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate the antifungal activity of the tested essential oils, the selected fungi were grown on a Potato Dextrose Agar (PDA, Scharlau Microbiologi, Barcelona, Spain) medium in 90 mm Petri dishes for 7–9 days and stored at 25 °C. Fungal spore suspension was obtained in aseptic conditions in a laminar flow cabinet after ultraviolet sterilization for 20 min. Fungal spore suspensions were collected from the surface of fungal colonies by gentle scraping with a sterile inoculation loop and suspended in 10 mL of sterile water. Spore population was counted using a hemocytometer (Thoma camera, 0, 100 mm depth, from Hirschmann Techcolor, Eberstadt, Germany). The concentration of spore suspensions was 10
   <span class="sup">6</span> spores/mL.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot5-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Antifungal Assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antifungal activity of the tested oils was determined with the disc diffusion method. Potato dextrose agar medium was poured into 90 mm Petri dishes, and, after its solidifying, in each Petri dish, 100 μL of spore suspensions (containing 10
   <span class="sup">6</span> spores/mL) were spread onto the surface of the media. The dishes were left to facilitate the incorporation of fungi in the PDA medium for 30 min. Subsequently, filter paper discs (6 mm Ø; Whatman) were placed on the surface of the Petri dishes and impregnated with different amounts (volume from 2.5 to 60 µL) of essential oil. All determinations were performed in five replicates. Control plates (without essential oils) were inoculated using the same procedure. Each sample was evaluated by three analysts, and three averages of the five replicates were obtained. The final average is the arithmetic average of the three other averages. Samples were evaluated through estimation of the degree to which the Petri dish surface was covered by fungal mycelium and through an inhibition rate (IR) calculation.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition rate was calculated as follows: 
   <div id="FD1-materials-10-00045" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
    <div id="mm1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">I</span>
       <span class="mi">R</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <span class="mo">%</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">C</span>
         <span class="mo">−</span>
         <span class="mi">S</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mi">C</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">×</span>
       <span class="mn">100</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> where 
   <span class="italic">C</span> is the rate of the fungal mycelium growth of the control, and 
   <span class="italic">S</span> is the rate of the fungal mycelium growth of the samples.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dishes were sealed with parafilm tape to prevent the volatilization of essential oils and incubated for 7 days at 25 °C. The efficacy of the treatment was evaluated after 7 days by the inhibition rate 
   <span class="italic">IR</span> (%).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot6-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6. Determination of the Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of Fungi</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils were screened to determine their minimum inhibitory concentration against the food spoilage microorganisms selected. The same procedure as the one described for the antifungal assay was used to determine the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC). The definition of the MIC differs between various publications [
   <a rid="B57-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-materials-10-00045">57</a>,
   <a rid="B58-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-materials-10-00045">58</a>,
   <a rid="B59-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-materials-10-00045">59</a>], so it was decided that the MIC would be defined as the lowest volume of essential oil that inhibited the growth of the tested fungi with an inhibition rate higher than 80%. The MIC is expressed in different units including mg/mL [
   <a rid="B60-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-materials-10-00045">60</a>], µg/mL [
   <a rid="B61-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-materials-10-00045">61</a>,
   <a rid="B62-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-materials-10-00045">62</a>], µL/L [
   <a rid="B63-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-materials-10-00045">63</a>,
   <a rid="B64-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64-materials-10-00045">64</a>], µL/mL [
   <a rid="B65-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65-materials-10-00045">65</a>], and ppm [
   <a rid="B62-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-materials-10-00045">62</a>,
   <a rid="B66-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66-materials-10-00045">66</a>]. In this study, the MIC of fungi was expressed as ppm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot7-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.7. The Agar Disc Diffusion Method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The protocol of the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) [
   <a rid="B67-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67-materials-10-00045">67</a>,
   <a rid="B68-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68-materials-10-00045">68</a>] was followed with some modifications. The bacterial suspensions were diluted to a McFarland standard of 0.5 (0.5 McFarland standard is prepared by mixing 0.05 mL of 1.175% barium chloride dihydrate (BaCl
   <sub>2</sub>·2H
   <sub>2</sub>O), with 9.95 mL of 1% sulfuric acid (H
   <sub>2</sub>SO
   <sub>4</sub>), and adjusted to about 10
   <span class="sup">4</span>–10
   <span class="sup">5</span> bacteria/mL before use. A 0.1 mL portion from this bacterial dilution was spread on Mueller–Hinten (MH) agar (MHA, Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany). Subsequently, sterile paper discs (Macherey-Nagel, Düren, Germany, LOT: 141112) 6 mm in diameter were placed within 15 min onto the inoculated agar surface containing 10 µL of the essential oil or 10 µL of sterile water as control. Petri dishes were incubated at 37 °C for 24 ± 1 h. After incubation, the inhibition zones were measured as the complete inhibition in mm, as a diameter including the disc. The inhibition zones were measured in triplicate with a vernier caliper. The distance from the colonies closest to the disc to the center of the disc was doubled to obtain a diameter.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot8-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.8. The Vapor Disc Diffusion Method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MH-agar plate surfaces inoculated with 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span> and 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and Tryptone Soya Agar (TSA, CM 0131, Oxoid Ltd., Thermo Fisher Scientific, Basingstoke, Hampshire, UK) with 
   <span class="italic">L. monocytogenes</span> were prepared as described in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot7-materials-10-00045" href="#sec3dot7-materials-10-00045">Section 3.7</a>. A volume of 10 µL of each pure EO was added to sterile filter discs with a diameter of 6 mm, and sterile water was used as control. The discs were placed on the inside center of a Petri dish lid in a sterile working hood. A control was also prepared by adding 10 µL of sterile water to the filter discs.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inoculated agar plate was then placed to fit the lid but with the agar upwards. This created a closed Petri dish with a distance of about 1 cm between the disc and the bacteria inoculated agar surface in accordance with Goni et al. [
   <a rid="B69-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69-materials-10-00045">69</a>]. The Petri dishes were sealed with adhesive tape to prevent volatile components of the essential oils to escape.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot9-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9. Determination of the Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of Bacteria</div>
  <sec id="sec3dot9dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.1. Agar MIC Testing</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The preparation of agar, broth, and bacteria were carried out as described in 
    <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot7-materials-10-00045" href="#sec3dot7-materials-10-00045">Section 3.7</a>. MICs was determined for thyme, clove, and tea tree against 
    <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">E. coli</span> according to the method used by Zhang and Mith [
    <a rid="B53-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-materials-10-00045">53</a>,
    <a rid="B54-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-materials-10-00045">54</a>] with some minor modifications. The original solution of each EO was dissolved in Tween-20 (0.5%), dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, 5%), or ethanol (100%) in a 1:1 ratio to make serial 2-fold dilutions, yielding solutions with a gradient from 100% oil to 0.2% oil (
    <span class="italic">v</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span>). A volume of 10 µL of each oil dilution was added to the 6 mm paper disc and then placed on MH agar plates with a 100 µL bacterial concentration containing a 10
    <span class="sup">4</span>–10
    <span class="sup">5</span> CFU/mL suspension of each tested bacterium. DSMO without bacteria was used as a control.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3dot9dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.2. Broth Microdilution MIC Testing</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar dilutions in either Tween-20 (0.5%), dimethyl sulfoxide (DSMO, 5%), or ethanol (100%) were transferred to sterile microtiter plates (honeycomb plates with 100 wells). Three parallel dilution series were used with 100 µL in each well. The microtiter plates were mounted in a Bioscreen C (Oy Growth Curves Ab Ltd., Helsinki, Finland), an automated growth curve analysis system, programmed to measure absorbance at 600 nm (abs 600 nm) at regular time intervals at 37 ± 0.1 °C. Prior to each measurement, the plates were shaken for 10 s (default setting). Growth curves of both strains were recorded. Time-to-detection (TTD) were defined as 
    <span class="italic">ABS</span>
    <sub>600nm</sub> = 0.2. Lack of absorbance above 0.2 were defined as growth inhibition.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot10-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.10. Antioxidant Activity Evaluation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inhibition concentration of four essential oils (thyme, clove, rosemary, and tea tree) and the stability of natural antioxidant at different concentrations were evaluated using 2,2’-azino-bis 3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (ABTS) and 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical methods.</p>
  <sec id="sec3dot10dot1-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.10.1. ABTS
    <span class="sup">•+</span> (2,2’-Azino-bis 3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulfonic Acid) Radical Cation Scavenging Assay
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ABTS
    <span class="sup">•+</span> scavenging test is used to determine the antioxidant activity of both hydrophilic and hydrophobic compounds. ABTS
    <span class="sup">•+</span> is generated by mixing 2.5 mL of 7 mM ABTS with 2.5 mL of 14.7 mM potassium persulfate (KPS) water solutions and stored in the dark at room temperature for 16 h. The reaction between ABTS
    <span class="sup">•+</span> and potassium persulfate directly generates the blue green ABTS
    <span class="sup">•+</span> chromophore, which can be reduced by an antioxidant, thereby resulting in a loss of absorbance at 750 nm.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant capacity is expressed as percentage inhibition, calculated using the following formula [
    <a rid="B70-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70-materials-10-00045">70</a>]: 
    <div id="FD2-materials-10-00045" class="disp-formula">
     <span class="label">(2)</span>
     <div id="mm2" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">I</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">n</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">h</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">i</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">b</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">i</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">t</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">i</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">o</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">n</span>
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
        <span class="mo">%</span>
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mo">[</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="mfrac">
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">A</span>
             <div class="mrow">
              <span class="mi">control</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <span class="mo">−</span>
            <div class="msub">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">A</span>
             <div class="mrow">
              <span class="mi">sample</span>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">A</span>
             <div class="mrow">
              <span class="mi">control</span>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">×</span>
          <span class="mn">100</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">]</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div> where 
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>control</sub> is the absorbance of the ABTS radical in methanol, and 
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>sample</sub> is the absorbance of an ABTS radical solution mixed with the sample. All determinations were performed in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3dot10dot2-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.10.2. DPPH Radical Scavenging Assay</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DPPH radical scavenging assay for essential oils was measured using the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical. The DPPH is a stable free radical with a violet color that, under the action of proton-donating compounds, is reduced to a light yellow color, and this change can be monitored at 517 nm [
    <a rid="B71-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71-materials-10-00045">71</a>]. Concentrations of the methanolic solution between 0.156 and 20 mg/mL were tested.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The radical scavenging activity was calculated according to the following equation: 
    <div id="FD3-materials-10-00045" class="disp-formula">
     <span class="label">(3)</span>
     <div id="mm3" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">%</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">R</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">S</span>
        <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">A</span>
        <span class="mo">=</span>
        <span class="mn">100</span>
        <span class="mo">×</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mo">(</span>
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="mfrac">
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">A</span>
             <div class="mrow">
              <span class="mi">control</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <span class="mo">−</span>
            <div class="msub">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">A</span>
             <div class="mrow">
              <span class="mi">sample</span>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
           <div class="mrow">
            <div class="msub">
             <span mathvariant="bold-italic" class="mi">A</span>
             <div class="mrow">
              <span class="mi">control</span>
             </div>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div> where 
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>sample</sub> represents the absorbance of the sample solution in the presence of DPPH, and 
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>control</sub> is the absorbance of the standard DPPH solution. For more details, see ref. [
    <a rid="B72-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-materials-10-00045">72</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot11-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.11. The Encapsulation of Essential Oils into the Chitosan Matrix by the Emulsion/Solvent Casting Method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The film forming solutions were prepared using highly viscous chitosan from crab shells where 
   <span class="italic">MW</span> = 310,000–375,000 g/mol, with a dynamic viscosity of &gt;400 mPa·s in 1% acetic acid (20 °C). The chitosan film-forming solution was prepared by dissolving 2 g of chitosan per 100 mL of a 5% acetic acid aqueous solution. Food grade essential oils (clove, thyme, rosemary, and tea tree oils) were incorporated in a proportion of 0.75 mL/g chitosan, and Tween 80 (Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany) (0.125 g/g chitosan) was added as an emulsifying agent. The essential oil-added film-forming solution was homogenized with an ultrasonic processor UP50H (Hielscher—Ultrasound Technology, Teltow, Germany) using a power of 50 W at 30 kHz). The films were obtained by casting 50 mL in glass Petri dishes (153 cm
   <span class="sup">2</span>) and drying first at 25 °C in a forced-air oven for 24 h and then at 40 °C in a vacuum oven to yield a uniform thickness in all cases. Prior to analyses, the films were conditioned in desiccators for 2 days at 22 °C over a saturated solution of NaBr (58% relative humidity) [
   <a rid="B56-materials-10-00045" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-materials-10-00045">56</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot12-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.12. The Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS) Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The DLS analysis of the oils-in-chitosan emulsions was carried out using a Zetasizer NS (Malvern Instruments Ltd., Malvern, UK), according with standard ISO 13321 (1996). This analysis only gives a mean particle size (z-average) and an estimate of the width of the distribution (polydispersity index (PDI)). It is very sensitive to the presence of aggregates due to the inherent intensity weighting. The oil/chitosan ratio was kept at 0.75 mL/1 g chitosan. For DLS, the concentration of the initial solution was 1.5 wt % chitosan and the corresponding concentration of the oils. The chitosan/essential oil emulsions of 1.5 wt % were diluted three times prior to analysis with the 5 wt % acetic acid aqueous solution.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot13-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13. Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SEM examination was carried out using QUANTA 200 scanning electronic microscope (FEI Company, Hillsboro, OR, USA), with an integrated EDX system, GENESIS XM 2i EDAX (FEI Company, Hillsboro, OR, USA) with a SUTW detector and without any further treatments at different magnifications given on the image micrographs.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot14-materials-10-00045" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.14. Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each analysis was performed in five replicates. Data were analyzed statistically with the one-way analysis of variance ANOVA test using the SPSS statistics. Significant differences between tested samples and the control were defined at 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
