<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">A total of 1 × 10
 <sup>4</sup> Vero E6 cells were cultured in a 96-black well plate (Corning, USA) for 24 h at 37 °C in 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> atmosphere. Then, culture supernatant was discarded, and the cells were washed once with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). In the case of post-treatment, the cells were subsequently infected with SARS-CoV-2 at 25TCID
 <sub>50</sub>. After viral adsorption for 2 h at 37 °C, the cells were washed twice to remove the excessive inoculum with PBS, and the fresh culture medium (DMEM with 2% FBS) was added into the wells. Each concentration of drugs, crude extracts, or active compounds was directly inoculated into the culture medium. The cells were then maintained at 37 °C in 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> incubator for 48 h. For pre-entry treatment, the mixture of each drug, crude extract, or active compound and 25TCID
 <sub>50</sub> of SARS-CoV-2 was incubated at 37 °C for 1 h before inoculating it into the cells. Similarly, viral adsorption was allowed for 2 h. After that, the cells were washed twice with PBS, and the fresh culture medium (DMEM with 2% FBS) was added into the cells. The culture was maintained for an additional 48 h. For the pre-treatment experiment, each concentration of drugs, crude extracts, or active compounds was directly inoculated into the cells before viral infection. After incubation at 37 °C for 1 h, drug, crude extract or compound was removed and the cells were washed with PBS. Then, the cells were infected with SARS-CoV-2 at 25TCID
 <sub>50</sub>. Viral adsorption was carried out for 2 h at 37 °C followed by washing with PBS. Fresh medium (DMEM with 2% FBS) was added into the wells, and the culture was maintained for 48 h. Positive convalescent serum (heat-inactivated at 56 °C for 30 min.) of a COVID-19 patient and anti-human IgG-FITC (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, USA) was used as a viral inhibition positive control and negative control, respectively. The experiment was done in triplicate.
</p>
