<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125" class="p">Pyroelectric materials can be used as detectors of infrared radiation. In this regard pyroelectric materials are advantages compare to narrow band-gap semiconductors. The main advantages of LB technique in the application of pyroelectric devices are, - (i) here symmetry of the film structure can be precisely manipulated and controlled through sequential deposition of monolayer. Also monolayers of different materials can be deposited to produced highly ordered heterostructure. (ii) The polarization of an LB film is ‘frozen-in’ during deposition and it is therefore not necessary to subject the film to a poling process. (iii) Amphiphilic organic molecules have low permitivities (
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M4" altimg="si4.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">ε</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>) and LB films are ingeneral prepared using water insoluble amphiphilies. Accordingly the figure of merit for voltage responsivity 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M5" altimg="si5.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mfrac bevelled="true" class="mfrac">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">p</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">ε</mi>
     </mrow>
    </mfrac>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> (where p is the pyroelectric coefficient) is expected to be large. Finally the LB method enables the preparation of much thinner films than usually attained by other normal conventional techniques. The pyroelectric coefficients for multilayer acid/amine LB films can be about 10 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M6" altimg="si6.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">μ</mi>
    <mi class="mi">C</mi>
    <msup class="msup">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">m</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mn class="mn">2</mn>
     </mrow>
    </msup>
    <msup class="msup">
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mi class="mi">K</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mo class="mo">−</mo>
      <mn class="mn">1</mn>
     </mrow>
    </msup>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> and depend on the thermal expansion coefficient of the substrate, indicating that there is a significant secondary contribution to the measured pyroelectric response [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>]. LB films of poly(vinylidene fluoride trifluoroethylene) showed ferroelectric switching with distribution of switching times several decades wide 
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[101]</xref>.
</p>
