<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0130" class="p">Rectifying junctions are the oldest practical semiconductor device and are used as the basic elements of many electronic devices. The rectifying metal-semiconductor junction forms a schottky barier. LB film based polymer p-n junction as well as schottky junction have been investigated extensively 
 <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[102]</xref>. Anion doped polypyrrole/polythophene in LB films have been found to behave as n-type semiconductor 
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[103]</xref>. Various metals have been deposited onto cadmium stearate (CdSt
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) LB films to have metal-insulator-semiconductor (MIS) structures 
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[104]</xref>. LB films of ZnO has been used to fabricate metal-insulator-metal tunnel diode 
 <xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[105]</xref>. This types of diodes have great potential for use in infrared detection and energy harvesting applications. Polypyrrole and polythiophene derivatives assembled onto LB films have been investigated for realization of electrical rectifying devices 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[106]</xref>. Alternating deposition of this two polymers using LB technique have been done to fabricate heterostructure rectifying devices 
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[107]</xref>. Aviram and Ratner predicated that molecule having a donor and an acceptor group connected by a short 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M7" altimg="si7.gif" overflow="scroll" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">σ</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>-bond should exhibit diode characteristics 
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[108]</xref>. Based on their predication several researchers tried to realize LB film based rectifying diode 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[36]</xref>. It has been demonstrated that the rectification behaviour of such diode can be manipulated by changing LB film structure [
 <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>].
</p>
