<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Periodontitis, a chronic inflammatory disease which causes tooth loss and deterioration of gingiva, alveolar bone, and periodontal ligaments, is caused by several microbes including the keystone pathogen 
 <italic>Porphyromonas gingivalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This bacterium is a gram negative, rod-shaped, obligate anaerobe belonging to the 500 bacterial species living in the oral cavity [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It infects periodontal tissues as a secondary infection through interactions with commensal streptococci [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Because of its ability to evade the host immune response and travel from cell to cell as well as via the haematogenous route, 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic> can cause and maintain high levels of chronic inflammation in various peripheral organs [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Infection with 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic> has been associated with cardiovascular disease, diabetes mellitus, respiratory infection, rheumatoid arthritis, osteoporosis, obesity, and preterm birth [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. While potential mechanisms linking periodontal infection with these disease states are not fully understood, several models have been hypothesized and explored, reviewed by Kim and Amar [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. More recently, the link between inflammation and the central nervous system (CNS) has been receiving increasing attention, and many studies have begun to investigate the link between 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic>, inflammation, and the brain. Although the exact cause and effect relationship between this bacteria, peripheral and CNS inflammation, and the brain has yet to be fully elucidated, an increasing volume of clinical and experimental evidence has associated 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic> with Alzheimer’s disease (AD), dementia, and other forms of cognitive decline [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
