<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Van der Wielen et al. [
 <xref rid="B99-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] showed that dietary fibers were fermented in the caecum of birds by faecal microbes which produced end products such as volatile fatty acids (VFAs), an essential compound in decreasing of 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> spp and other pathogenic bacteria. MOS is the main component of PKC and is considered to contain prebiotic properties that can reduce pathogenic bacteria and improve birds’ immunity [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. FPKC in the broiler feeding diet may increase intestinal LAB and lactic acid concentration [
 <xref rid="B58-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]; hence, the interactions between the LAB and the host immune system have been suggested to lead to some immunomodulatory activities [
 <xref rid="B101-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Organic acids, mainly lactic acid in fermented feeds, may increase beneficial bacteria leading to higher production of short-chain fatty acids and ultimately acidify and lower the pH throughout the GIT [
 <xref rid="B89-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Additionally, organic acid can decrease pathogenic bacteria directly through penetration into the bacterial cell wall and produce H
 <sup>+</sup> ions that interfere with bacteria’s enzyme activities or indirectly by changing the intestines’ pH. Thus, a cell must spend more energy to maintain internal pH, and this energy cannot be used for other metabolic processes. It may result in less number of pathogenic bacteria [
 <xref rid="B91-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Moreover, lowering of pH improved organic acids’ antimicrobial activity against pathogens [
 <xref rid="B103-animals-11-00338" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>].
</p>
