<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antimicrobial properties of 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> and 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> have been attributed to their chemical compositions, which are primarily rich with monoterpene hydrocarbons and oxygenated monoterpenes. The principal terpenes identified in oregano and thyme are usually carvacrol, thymol, 
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene, and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene; while terpinen-4-ol, linalool, 
 <italic>β</italic>-myrcene, 
 <italic>trans</italic>-sabinene hydrate, and 
 <italic>β</italic>-caryophyllene are also present. The proportion of these and other components in oils within the same species defines the chemotype [
 <xref rid="B59-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In our study, the chromatographic profiles of both EOs were analyzed by GC/MS using two detectors and two capillary columns of different polarities to avoid the overlapping of signal peaks observed in the chromatogram and to achieve the best possible resolution of compounds. The internal standard was used for quantitative analysis. Compounds belonging to the classes with monoterpene hydrocarbons and oxygenated monoterpenes were the most numerous identified. Carvacrol was the most abundant compound in oregano EO, followed by 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene and 
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene, and the oil is, thus, characterized as a carvacrol chemotype. This finding is in accordance with several previously published studies. For example, Stojkovic et al. [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], Scalas et al. [
 <xref rid="B60-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], and Stoilova et al. [
 <xref rid="B61-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] reported carvacrol as the main component of oregano EO (contributing 64.50%, 62.61%, and 66.20% of the EO, respectively), 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene as the second the most abundant compound (10.90%; 12.36%, and 9.1%, respectively), and 
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene as third most abundant component (10.80%, 7.60%, and 7.30%, respectively). Thymol, on the other hand, has been in our study detected as the most abundant constituent in thyme EO, also followed by its precursors, 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene and 
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene; therefore the present thyme oil belongs to thymol chemotype. This finding is also in accordance with numerous previously published studies [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], where thymol, 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, and 
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene were reported as the first, second, and third most abundant compounds, respectively. The number of components identified in our study (26 and 37 in total in oregano and thyme EOs, respectively) is within the range of numbers of compounds identified in other reported studies, as eight to 38 compounds have been reported for 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], and 16–50 for 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Since the used plant material has been obtained from a commercial supplier, the age of the plants as well as their growing conditions, harvest time, transportation, and storage conditions are unknown. Therefore, the chemical composition of EOs analyzed in this study can be influenced by all the above-mentioned factors [
 <xref rid="B66-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The qualitative differences (numbers of components) between the two columns are in accordance with previously reported studies on GC/MS analysis of EOs using two columns. For example, Anderson and Parnell [
 <xref rid="B68-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], who compared cold-pressed orange oil profiles by GC/MS using polar (Zebron ZB-WAX column) and non-polar (Zebron ZB-1ms) GC columns, identified 22 and 29 components on non-polar and polar compounds, respectively. The higher number of volatile components identified on a polar column might have been caused, similarly as in our case, by the better resolution between compounds that were seen to co-elute on the non-polar column. Similarly, quantitative differences between the polar and non-polar columns have previously been reported as well. In our study, the main compound (thymol) in thyme EO showed the highest proportional difference between two columns (more than 6%), which can be, for example, compared to Fan et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], who analyzed the composition of the EO from 
 <italic>Dendranthema indicum</italic> var. 
 <italic>aromaticum</italic> and detected 
 <italic>α</italic>-thujone as the main compound with a difference of 4.88% between columns. Different amounts of the detected compounds are caused by different polarity and material of the used columns. Besides determining of raw percentages of peak areas, the concentration of components in 1 kg of dry plant material was calculated using predicted relative response factors with an objective to increase the reliability and accuracy of the volatile components’ quantification [
 <xref rid="B70-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. This approach is important in technological processes with various applications in the field of chemical analysis of volatile plant-derived products because it allows the quantification of volatile components by GC/MS with flame-ionization detection when the authentic components are not available, and in addition, it can avoid time-consuming procedures of calibration [
 <xref rid="B71-plants-10-00393" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
