<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">Commercially available fluorine-doped tin oxide (FTO) conductive glass substrates (surface resistivity of 10 Ω/square) were cleaned by ultrasonication in acetone, methanol and then in isopropanol sequentially for 10 minutes at 80 ± 2 °C and finally dried using nitrogen airflow. An electron transporting compact (c-TiO
 <sub>2</sub>) layer solution was prepared by mixing 700 μL of titanium di isopropoxide bis(acetylacetonate) in 7.0 mL of absolute ethanol (1:10 volume ratio) and was filtered through 0.2 μm pore syringe filter. This solution (1200 µl of above solution for 6 samples) was sprayed on the preheated glass/FTO surface followed by annealing at 450 ± 5 °C for 10 minutes. It was then allowed to cool down to room temperature (RT) and sonicated in absolute ethanol for 20 minutes. The purchased dyesol 18 NR TiO
 <sub>2</sub> paste mixed with absolute ethanol (1:3.5 volume ratio) solution and was spin-coated at 4000 rpm for 20 s to form a mesoporous TiO
 <sub>2</sub> (mp-TiO
 <sub>2</sub>) on the top of the c-TiO
 <sub>2</sub> layer. It was then annealed at 450 ± 5 °C for 30 minutes. The overnight heated perovskite solution at 70 ± 2 °C was taken and spin-coated on the top of the pre-heated (80 ± 2 °C) glass/FTO/c-TiO
 <sub>2</sub>/mp-TiO
 <sub>2</sub> film at 2000 rpm for the 30 s. The deposited perovskite film was heated at 120 ± 3 °C for 45 minutes so as to remove the organic solvents and this resulted in a systematic color change in the layer from yellow to black confirming the formation of perovskite active layer. A heterogenous graphitic carbon (EC-GC10) mixed perovskite solution was taken and spin-coated at 3500/1500 rpm for 20 s and was heated at 80 ± 2 °C, and this resulted in the formation of porous graphitic carbon encapsulated perovskite (EC-GC10@CH
 <sub>3</sub>NH
 <sub>3</sub>PbI
 <sub>3−x</sub>Cl
 <sub>x</sub>) thin film with the thickness of 80/150 nm respectively. Finally, the carbon-based hole transporting material (C-HTMs) such as EC-GC4, EC-GC8, EC-GC10, commercial carbon paste (CC) and carbon nickel sulphide composite (C/NiS) was mixed with α-terpineol and chlorobenzene (1:2 vol.%) and coated via brush painting technique on the top of the perovskite layer. The PSC device structure fabricated in the present work are of the form Glass/FTO/c-TiO
 <sub>2</sub>/mp-TiO
 <sub>2</sub>/CH
 <sub>3</sub>NH
 <sub>3</sub>PbI
 <sub>3−x</sub>Cl
 <sub>x</sub>/EC-GC10@CH
 <sub>3</sub>NH
 <sub>3</sub>PbI
 <sub>3−x</sub>Cl
 <sub>x</sub>/EC-GC based HTMs prepared at different annealed temperatures.
</p>
