<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effect of alcoholic extract of 
 <italic>Bacopa</italic> has been evaluated at the dose of 20, 40 and 80 mg/kg on cognitive functions and neurodegeneration in the animal model of AD induced by bilateral intracerebroventricular administration of AF64A. They found that 
 <italic>Bacopa</italic> improved the escape latency in the Morris water maze test and prevented the reduction in cholinergic neuron density [
 <xref rid="B47-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Besides, oral administration of 40 mg/kg/day of the 
 <italic>Bacopa</italic> extract for 5 weeks prevented neurotoxicity in rats exposed to aluminum chloride [
 <xref rid="B83-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Cognitive deficit induced by intracerebroventricular (ICV) injection of cholchicine and ibotenic acid into the nucleus basalis magnocellularis was attenuated by standardized 
 <italic>Bacopa</italic> extract by reversing the depletion of ACh level, reduction in choline acetyl transferase (ChAT) activity and decrease in muscarinic cholinergic receptor binding in frontal cortex and hippocampus [
 <xref rid="B84-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Holcomb et al. [
 <xref rid="B43-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] reported that administration of ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Bacopa</italic> leaves at doses of 40 and 160 mg/kg for 2 and 8 months reduced A
 <italic>β</italic> 1–40 and 1–42 levels in the cortex of PSAPP mice. Bacopa, at the dose of 50 mg/kg, demonstrated the neuroprotective effect in the colchicine model of dementia through its antioxidant effect and restored the activity of Na
 <sup>+</sup>K
 <sup>+</sup>ATPase and AChE [
 <xref rid="B85-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. The neuronal dendritic growth stimulating property of 
 <italic>Bacopa</italic> has also been reported which may be responsible for its memory enhancing property [
 <xref rid="B86-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].
</p>
