<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Custódio et al. [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>] studied the inhibitory effect of leaves and acorns from 
 <italic>Quercus suber</italic> on key enzymes relevant for hyperglycemia (
 <italic>α</italic>-amylase and 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase). Their study showed that the best results were obtained with the water and methanol leaves extracts with values of 97 and 89%, respectively, which could most likely be attributed to their higher phenolic content. Moreover, the extract from the bark of 
 <italic>Q. coccifera</italic> exhibited stronger 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitory activity with an IC50 value of 3.26 ± 0.08 
 <italic>µ</italic>g/mL than that reported for acarbose IC50: 50.45 ± 0.20 
 <italic>µ</italic>g/ml [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. In another work, triterpenoids obtained from acorns of 
 <italic>Quercus liaotungensis</italic> have been studied for their inhibitory activity against 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase, 
 <italic>α</italic>-amylase, and protein-tyrosine phosphatase 1B. The authors found that all the compounds showed strong inhibitory effects on PTP1B and 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase, but inhibition of 
 <italic>α</italic>-amylase was not observed [
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. It was also reported that the polyphenol fraction from acorn leaves (
 <italic>Quercus liaotungensis</italic>) inhibited 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase and PTP1B activity [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Similarly, Yin et al. [
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] reported that 
 <italic>Mongolian oak</italic> cups might be a source of ellagic acid (EA), which possess prominent inhibitory activities against 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase, 
 <italic>α</italic>-amylase, and formation of AGEs. Other authors reported that the chloroform extract from 
 <italic>Quercus dilatata</italic> exhibited maximum antidiabetic activity 
 <italic>α</italic>-amylase inhibition of 21.61 ± 1.53% at 200 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/ml [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In addition, condensed tannin fractions isolated from the leaves of 
 <italic>Quercus phillyraeoides</italic> presented potent 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase inhibitory activities with IC50 values in the range of 2.60 to 3.14 
 <italic>µ</italic>g/ml, respectively [
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>].
</p>
