<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A mixture of the following compounds was added to the pool: 4 amino acids (glycine, 
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-alanine, 
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-aspartic acid, and 
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-valine, 1 gram each), four nucleobases (adenine, cytosine, guanine, and uracil, 1 gram each), sodium phosphate (3 grams), glycerol (2 grams), and myristic acid (1.5 grams). The goal of the experiment was to establish the fate of such compounds in natural hydrothermal conditions. Water samples (50 mL) and samples of the clay lining the pool were taken before addition of the powder, then at 1, 5, 30, 60, 120 min, 24 h, and 9 days later. Later analysis revealed that most of the added organics and phosphate were removed from solution with half times measured in minutes to a few hours. For instance, the two purines―guanine and adenine―disappeared from solution in about 2 h with a half time of 30 min. Even though cytosine was among the compounds added, it could not be detected in the analysis, but uracil was present at twice the expected concentration and disappeared with a half time of 2 h. The loss of cytosine was expected because at acidic pH ranges it readily undergoes deamination to uracil. When clay samples were analyzed, it was found that the organics could be released by addition of NaOH to bring the pH into the alkaline range, showing that with the exception of myristic acid, the organics had been adsorbed to the mineral surfaces at the acidic pH of the pool. This experiment was described in detail [
 <xref rid="B7-life-09-00041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] and inspired David’s later work in other geothermal regions as well as laboratory simulations of hydrothermal environments. The ionic solutes in the pool are summarized in 
 <xref rid="life-09-00041-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. The total concentration of ~2 mM is far below that of seawater, and therefore better able to support processes leading to the emergence of life.
</p>
