<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The current study demonstrates that DNA of ingested seeds from different plant species can be detected in carabid regurgitates for up to 5 days post‐feeding under laboratory conditions. These findings indicate the potential of a sufficiently large time frame in which we can detect and identify food sources in field‐collected carabid beetles, particularly when consumption of a specific prey may date several hours or days prior to collection, as in case of a bad weather period for example. This is highly important when it comes to the analysis of field‐collected beetles, where the feeding frequency and exact time of actual consumption are usually unknown. The present results are in accordance with earlier experiments, showing extended detection periods/high detection rates of both seed (Wallinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) and animal prey in 
 <italic class="italic">P. rufipes</italic> (Monzo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Waldner, Sint, Juen, &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). These long prey DNA detection intervals may be ascribed to the omnivorous feeding mode of 
 <italic class="italic">P. rufipes</italic> (Waldner et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Like in most carabids, the digestive tract of 
 <italic class="italic">P. rufipes</italic> is characterized by the capability to digest many different food sources, rather than being optimized for the effective breakdown of a certain prey type (Holland, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Tooley &amp; Brust, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). These carabids might therefore exhibit slower basal metabolic rates than comparably sized carnivorous arthropods. Moreover, the enzymatic breakdown of ingested plant tissue or seeds seems to be generally slower than that of insect tissue because plant material is harder to digest. Apart from prolonged DNA detection rates, plant food detectability does not generally seem to follow a logistic decline, as usually seen in the digestion of animal prey. In some cases, detection rates of plant food are already low at the beginning and we can see an increase in detection rates at late time points following an initial decrease, as for example in S. vulgaris. These findings are in accordance with earlier feeding experiments with herbivorous insects (Staudacher, Wallinger, Schallhart, &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Wallinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref> ). The differences may be related to the nature of the digestion of plant tissue. Some plant‐specific metabolites could have an inhibitory effect resulting in low initial detection rates which can continue until detectability increases again during advanced digestion and associated lysis of plant cell walls or breakdown of plant secondary compounds. Altogether, this make the finding of appropriate models describing the digestion and DNA detectability of plant food challenging. This also prevented the possibility of fitting a single model describing the data of pure seed consumption together with that of the mixed diet in the present experiment. Based on experiences from former feeding experiments, where it had happened that DNA was still detectable at the end of the experiment and did not reach the base line, we already accounted for long detection rates (observation over five days post‐feeding) and were therefore able to characterize the digestion of most seeds in the pure diet very well. However, the additional consumption of mealworm increased detection rates dramatically. For example, in 
 <italic class="italic">C. bursa‐pastoris</italic>, no seed DNA was detectable after 32 hr or later if only the seed was consumed, but with subsequent consumption of a mealworm, the detection rate remained at around 60% for five days, and again we saw an increase in detection rates following an initial decline. These aspects regarding DNA detection of plant food in arthropods, contrasting the knowledge of animal tissue digestion, clearly require further investigations.
</p>
