<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As might be expected, seed DNA detectability had been negatively affected by time post‐feeding. However, the decrease in seed DNA detection rates in beetles regurgitates turned out to be seed species dependent, thus confirming earlier presumptions that seed identity might play a significant role (Wallinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). The same was true for different plant species in root feeding insects (Wallinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). While the detectability of some species dropped within the first 32 hr, the DNA of others was still detectable at the maximum period tested (i.e., 5 days post‐feeding). Accordingly, there were significant differences when pairwise comparing overall DNA detection rates in the single food‐source experiments. Seed mass and protein content turned out to have a negative effect on the detectability of plant DNA, whereas higher oil content seemed to result in longer detection periods. The latter was in accordance to the findings of Thomas, Jarman, Haman, Trites, and Deagle (
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), who reported enhanced prey detection for lipid‐rich prey as well. This indicates that high lipid content of prey is associated with diminished tissue breakdown and accordingly slower DNA degradation during digestion. That means, in turn, that the ratio of lipid‐rich seeds is likely to be overestimated compared to other ones, an issue that needs to be considered when it comes to the analysis of field‐collected data. However, unlike here where the protein content of seeds was negatively correlated with DNA detectability, in the study of diet estimates of Thomas et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), also protein content was correlated with higher detection rates, which the authors ascribed to the fact that increased body protein is associated with elevated levels of mitochondrial DNA, which had been targeted in their work. This factor does not play a role here, as the study by Thomas et al. (2014) was based on animal tissue, whereas the present study used the 
 <italic class="italic">trn</italic>L exon, part of the chloroplast DNA, to detect DNA from plant tissue. The “meal size” in earlier feeding experiments with 
 <italic class="italic">P. rufipes</italic> referred to the amount of consumed seeds of two plant species with rather similar size, which did not affect plant DNA detection (Wallinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). However, when comparing the effect of “meal size” between different seed species, one should also consider the high variation in size and biomass between seeds. Therefore, in the present experiments, “meal size” refers to the number of consumed seeds * average seed mass. Here, it had a positive effect, indicating the importance of the biomass of a certain prey type consumed by a carabid beetle. We want to point out, that these findings on the influence of seed traits here are based on data from six seed species only, covering just a fraction of the variability of those plant traits. Unfortunately, we have a coincidental correlation of “1,000 seed mass” and “oil content” in the present subset due to three species showing a low (&lt;7%) and the three other ones a high (&gt;26%) oil content, respectively, which would be not the case if a wider range of plant species is considered. Thus, a slight reduction in the predictive power of the discriminant analysis due to multicollinearity could not be excluded and we ran the discriminant analysis also with either one variable excluded (data not shown). As expected, the coefficient of the respective other factor increased in these cases, but overall a decrease in the percentage of correct classifications was observed—especially in the already difficult prediction of negative samples. Thus, we do not think that the results of the presented discriminant analysis are strongly biased by this fact and decided to keep both explanatory variables. Still, it would be highly interesting to extend the knowledge on the influence of different seed traits to better understand digestion of seeds by carabids and thus to improve in the long run the models predicting the digestion and detectability of plant DNA over time.
</p>
