<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It should be taken into account that our conclusions are based on the analysis of a single carabid species so far, tested under laboratory conditions. Still, in choosing, 
 <italic class="italic">P. rufipes</italic> we have selected a species that is not only dominant in ground beetle communities but also a representative, in being omnivorous and a chewing feeder like most carabids in arable land. The detection times observed can serve as guidelines for interpreting field‐derived data, although several factors that are present in the field may additionally influence the detectability of food DNA, such as fluctuating temperatures. High ambient temperatures have been found to effectively decrease detection rates of prey DNA (Hoogendoorn &amp; Heimpel, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Hosseini et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; von Berg, Traugott, &amp; Scheu, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Carabids, however, are surface active and many of them are nocturnal (Thiele, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1977</xref>), which implies that they are hiding during the day and might therefore not be subjected to strong daily temperature fluctuations. Thus, the effect of temperature on DNA detection rates probably might be less important for interpreting molecular trophic data. Still, there are various other aspects that need to be taken under consideration, such as the influence of activity levels, the ontogenetic status on digestion or sex‐specific differences as reported by Lundgren (
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), which might be specifically examined in the field to account for the variability present in natural settings. Future work, testing the detection intervals in mesocosms or a field experiment would represent the next logical step toward a better interpretation of field data based on carabid regurgitates.
</p>
