<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In vertebrate studies, non‐invasive approaches to obtain biological material for molecular analysis have long been preferred (Waits &amp; Paetkau, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>); however, these approaches have only recently been adopted for use in invertebrate studies (Lefort, Boyer, Worner, &amp; Armstrong, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Raso et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Seeber, Rief, Seeber, Meyer, &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Sint, Thurner, Kaufmann, &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Apart from ethical reasons, using carabid regurgitates instead of whole‐body DNA extracts has numerous advantages. First of all, the avoidance of killing the beetles is essential for example in surveys of small populations or when working with beneficial, rare, or endangered species. In addition, the application of this nondestructive approach offers the opportunity to monitor dietary changes in carabid beetles, which can be dependent upon different seasons (Holland, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Hulme, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) or vary ontogenetically (Lundgren et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Thiele, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1977</xref>). In comparisons of fecal, gut content, and regurgitate samples, prey DNA detection rates were the highest for regurgitates (Frei, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Kamenova, Mayer, Coissac, Plantegenest, &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Waldner &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). This indicates that they constitute a good source of prey DNA. Also in terms of fixation and storage, regurgitates are an advantageous sample type, as they can be directly dissolved in lysis buffer or quickly preserved in ethanol, which immediately inhibits the activity of digestive enzymes. Preserving invertebrates as a whole, in contrast, has shown to be less efficient in respect to the quality of prey DNA (Waldner &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). This might be explained by the longer time ethanol needs to penetrate and fixate the gut content. Preserving regurgitates in ethanol will be especially useful for projects conducted in remote areas (e.g., alpine environments, tropics) where freeze‐storage of samples is difficult. Finally, regurgitates contain comparable low concentrations of predator DNA. This is especially beneficial when DNA extraction methods are used where the overall amount of nucleic acids that can be isolated is limited (e.g., all silica‐based methods). Furthermore, large amounts of nontarget DNA and inhibitors present in whole‐body insect extracts can be a particular problem in molecular diet studies, where predator DNA is often present in great excess of food‐derived DNA. The predominance of one DNA template within a single sample can bias or restrict molecular analysis (Polz &amp; Cavanaugh, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>), especially if general primers are employed which might co‐amplify the consumer DNA (Krehenwinkel, Kennedy, Pekár, &amp; Gillespie, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Aside from carabid beetles, regurgitation is also common in other arthropod taxa, such as spiders (Kaestner, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>), grasshoppers (Sword, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>), or soil‐dwelling invertebrate predators (Juen &amp; Traugott, 
 <xref rid="ece34536-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>), indicating a wide applicability of the current approach.
</p>
