<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The unexpected lack of differences in the effect of soil biota from the native and the exotic range on the analyzed traits suggests that there is neither evidence for a release from belowground microbial enemies nor for an enhanced mutualism in the exotic range of 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic>. This contradicts the results of other studies that support the hypothesis of a release from enemies and/or enhanced mutualism in the exotic range as was, for example, shown for several tree (Gundale et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Reinhart &amp; Callaway, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) and forb species (Maron et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; McGinn et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Parepa et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). In contrast, other studies revealed negative feedbacks in exotic forb expansion, for example, of 
 <italic>Centaurea solstitialis</italic> (Andonian et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Apparently, there seem to be some differential effects on plant–soil feedbacks depending on the life‐form. In their meta‐analysis, Meisner et al. (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) concluded that plant–soil feedbacks based on the provenances' own soils could bring about the full suite of positive, negative, and neutral effects, with native plants rather displaying negative and exotics showing positive feedbacks. In addition, origins differed in their responses by life‐form with exotic forbs displaying positive effects and native forbs rather showing negative plant–soil feedbacks, whereas for trees, this trend was reversed. An absence of soil biota origin effects as found in our study was also shown by Beckstead and Parker (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>) for the European beach grass 
 <italic>Ammophila arenaria</italic>. In their study, seedlings were grown in two greenhouse experiments in the home and exotic range. Comparisons with settings in sterilized soil revealed that their performance was reduced both in the native and in the exotic range, thus failing to find a release from natural enemies. Hence, the absence of effects of soil biota origin on overall plant performance is not uncommon.
</p>
