<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The index of similarity between the vegetation and the seed banks of the roadsides and reference areas analyzed in this work was higher at the roadsides than in the reference areas. When the roadsides and reference areas were compared, similarity was greater in the vegetation than in the seed banks. The high similarity between the roadside vegetation and seed bank may be due to the abundance of annual exotic and native species. Annual species have traits (short life cycles, rapid growth and long-distance dispersal) [
 <xref rid="pone.0246657.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>], which allow them to persist in very disturbed environments [
 <xref rid="pone.0246657.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>] such as roadsides. These species produce numerous small, long-lived seeds that are easily incorporated into the soil [
 <xref rid="pone.0246657.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] contributing to the similarity between aboveground vegetation and the soil seed banks. The low similarity found between the vegetation and seed bank in the reference area follows a pattern which is common in other perennial grasslands [
 <xref rid="pone.0246657.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246657.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. The dominant shrubs and perennial grasses in the reference area vegetation have predominantly vegetative reproduction, and usually have large seeds [
 <xref rid="pone.0246657.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>] with dispersal structures that make it difficult for them to become buried in the soil, making them easy predation targets [
 <xref rid="pone.0246657.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Also, some ruderal species (e.g., 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>paronychioides</italic> and 
 <italic>V</italic>. 
 <italic>thapsus</italic>) were found only in the seed bank, contributing to the high dissimilarity. The presence of perennial herbs and grasses only in the vegetation of the roadsides and reference areas contributed to greater similarity in the vegetation than in the seed banks.
</p>
