<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">The model used in this study is very simple, with individual plants being identical except for differences in dispersal strategies. Competition is not explicitly parameterized in the model, but implicitly there is some form of density dependence due to the role of kin avoidance. Multi-scale dispersal strategies emerge as optimal in a wide range of landscapes even within this simple and straightforward framework, suggesting that they are of importance as a baseline in the natural setting where more processes play a role in spatial population dynamics. The reference framework following from our results is visualised conceptually in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. The main hypotheses for real plant data generated from our findings are: (1) In static, but patchy habitats, short-distance dispersal (e.g. 
 <italic>μ</italic> &gt; 3) dominates multi-scale dispersal strategies, due to the importance of optimizing habitat encounter. Particularly when patches are small and inter-patch distances are large, there is a strong selection in favour of extremely short-distance dispersal. (2) In contrast, extreme long-distance dispersal (
 <italic>μ</italic> → 1, or even uniform dispersal kernels) is favoured in both stable, continuous habitats as well as in unpredictable and dynamic landscapes. These dispersal strategies are driven by avoidance of kin competition and need to colonize newly formed patches. (3) In patchy and dynamic environments, a complex trade-off between finding habitat, avoiding kin competition and colonizing new patches results in multi-scale dispersal strategies with 
 <italic>μ</italic> correlated to average patch size, inter-patch distance and, most importantly, patch turnover rate. Our results suggest that multi-scale kernels similar to Lévy flights (
 <italic>μ</italic> ~ 2) would be selected for in patchy landscapes with intermediate patch sizes (~ 2 to 100 times the plant size), intermediate inter-patch distances (~ 5 to 100 times the plant size) and relatively high patch turnover rates of around 50% per generation. Some aspects of our findings are in line with well-known patterns observed in plant communities: Plant species in patchy and highly dynamic habitats typically have dispersal strategies dominated by long-distance dispersal and species from patchy but highly static landscapes tend to display predominantly short-distance dispersal that promotes the chance of success in ‘winning the home patch’ [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Yet, such hypotheses are not trivial. For example, in static but patchy landscapes, short-distance dispersal strategies may rapidly evolve. Colonization has been followed by rapid loss of long-distance dispersal in plants on islands and patches in urban environments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Such species are extremely vulnerable to habitat loss and fragmentation, as their dispersal strategy is not adapted to colonizing new areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. With ongoing global change, such dispersal-limited species are under great threat of extinction – an example of such a case is the endemic and highly threatened 
 <italic>Centaurea corymbosa</italic> which is adapted to long term persistent, but isolated rocky outcrops [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. 
</p>
