<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> is a Gram-positive cocci often associated with gastroenteritis acquired from contaminated foods such as milk [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>] and shrimp. The occurrence of multidrug-resistant bacteria in food is a worldwide concern [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>], and 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> drug-resistant to beta-lactams has been isolated from dairy products [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>] and shrimp [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some factors act for selecting drug-resistant bacteria pathogens, such as inappropriate use of antibiotics, and/or the inadequate disposal of antimicrobial drugs in the environment [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. Thus, the inappropriate use of antibiotics in aquaculture [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>] and livestock [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>] has contributed to the selection of resistant microbial species, and, consequently, increased food contamination level of animal origin and derivatives.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As an alternative to mitigate the occurrence of multidrug-resistant bacteria, the study of antimicrobial compounds in phanerogams has been proposed [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. In this context, the plants of genus 
  <span class="italic">Plectranthus</span> - 3000 recognized species, spread along countries in Africa, South America, Asia and Australia – are widely recognized in folk and popular medicine, being employed in digestive treatments as well as in infectious, inflammatory and respiratory problems [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Species of 
  <span class="italic">Plectrantus</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>], including 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>], has been studied due to its pharmacological properties in order to validate its popular use.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioactivity of 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> is related to the occurrence of 76 volatiles and 30 non-volatile compounds belonging to different classes of phytochemicals (monoterpenoids, diterpenoids, triterpenoids, sesquiterpenoids, phenolics, flavonoids, esters, alcohols and aldehydes) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Studies about the pharmacological activities of 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> are conducted from extracts or essential oil, i.e., complex volatile compounds, synthesized naturally in different plant parts during the process of secondary metabolism with great potential in the field of biomedicine [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. In this sense, 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> crude essential oils could be used as a tool for the developing novel and more efficacious antimicrobial agents against 
  <span class="italic">S. epidermidis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span> species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]
  <span class="italic">.</span>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The susceptibility of methicillin-resistant 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> (MRSA) clinical isolates to extracts of 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> has been reported [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>], however, studies about the action of this oil and its major component against planktonic and biofilm of drug-resistant 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> from food are still incipient.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, this study aims to determine the susceptibility of drug-resistant 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> strains isolated from milk and shrimp to 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> essential oil (PAEO) and its major component - carvacrol.
 </p>
</sec>
