<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Most sulfate-reducing bacteria function anaerobically but do have the ability to tolerate O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> as a means for survival (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cypionka et al., 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Marschall et al., 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fauque, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cypionka, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rabus et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ramel et al., 2015</xref>). Molecular oxygen is not toxic to sulfate-reducing bacteria, but the reaction of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> with reduced sulfur compounds releases toxic products, such as thiols, which may explain why O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> appears to be more toxic to metabolizing than resting cells (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cypionka, 2000</xref>). The substrates for aerobic respiration by sulfate-reducing bacteria are the same as the substrates used in sulfate reduction. It has been shown that when exposed to O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, the metabolically versatile sulfate-reducing bacterium 
 <italic class="italic">Desulfobulbus propionicus</italic> can generate native sulfur as an intermediate (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fuseler and Cypionka, 1995</xref>). However, despite (1) their capacity to couple O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> reduction with energy conservation, (2) their chemotaxis toward micro-aerobic zones, and (3) their detoxification mechanisms, proof has yet to be provided for aerobic growth of sulfate-reducing bacteria, i.e., over an infinite number of generations in oxic media (
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rabus et al., 2006</xref>). In environmental samples, including a supralitoral marine microbial mat (
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Visscher et al., 1992</xref>), hypersaline microbial mats (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Canfield and Marais, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jørgensen, 1994</xref>), root zones (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Isaksen and Finster, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Blaabjerg and Finster, 1998</xref>), and biofilms from a sewage plant (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kühl and Jørgensen, 1992</xref>), it has been shown that sulfate reduction can take place under oxic conditions. So far, sulfide production in pure cultures of sulfate-reducing bacteria in the presence of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> has not been documented (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cypionka, 2000</xref>). Recent discoveries indicate that there is the possibility of sulfate-reducing microorganisms growing under oxic conditions. The diversity of microbial groups that may be involved in dissimilatory sulfur cycling is much larger than previously thought (
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rückert, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Anantharaman et al., 2018</xref>). Among these microorganisms are peatland 
 <italic class="italic">Acidobacteria</italic> that possess the genomic toolset to convert sulfite into sulfide with a subgroup that also possesses the toolset to convert sulfate into sulfite (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hausmann et al., 2018</xref>). This is of particular interest because cultivated 
 <italic class="italic">Acidobacteria</italic> related to the peatland 
 <italic class="italic">Acidobacteria</italic> are aerobes or facultative anaerobes (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hausmann et al., 2018</xref> and references therein). However, since O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is energetically a much more attractive electron acceptor than sulfate, it remains uncertain why dissimilatory sulfate reduction would be carried out if O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is persistently available, and why such organisms would not be out-competed by aerobic competitors. Moreover, persistent presence of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> would keep sulfide concentrations low. Sulfide inhibits native sulfur disproportionation (
 <xref rid="B200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thamdrup, 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Finster et al., 1998</xref>). Removing this inhibitor would enable a process that consumes native sulfur, and thus not allow for the formation of a native sulfur deposit.
</p>
