<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Sulfide diffusing toward an oxidizing environment can be oxidized to native sulfur if hydrogen sulfide has a long enough residence time before being oxidized by other processes (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref>). In stratabound or salt diapir settings, such environments could potentially exist at locations with crossflow of oxygenated water adjacent to a dissolving salt, gypsum, or anhydrite (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Warren, 2006</xref>). The locally increased salinity reduces the solubility of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, facilitating the establishment of anoxic microniches. For this model to function, the supply of hydrocarbons or products of hydrocarbon degradation to the sulfate reducers must be maintained (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref>). Anaerobic microorganisms utilizing hydrocarbons always exhibit much slower growth than their aerobic counterparts (
 <xref rid="B221" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Widdel et al., 2010</xref>), and sulfate-reducing bacteria are outcompeted by aerobes, as exemplified by the classical redox sequence in marine sediments (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Canfield and Thamdrup, 2009</xref>). This leads to a conundrum: hydrocarbons must be delivered to the sulfate-reduction zone without exhausting the O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in the oxygenated water since O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is needed for the subsequent oxidation of sulfide to native sulfur, or sulfide oxidation to native sulfur with O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> must be kinetically faster than aerobic oxidation of hydrocarbons (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref>). The former option appears to be unlikely because if excess O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> was present, sulfur oxidation would likely proceed all the way to sulfate. The latter scenario might be possible, as sulfide is a highly effective antioxidant. However, to accumulate a large native sulfur deposit 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic>, supply with oxygenated water needs to be large enough to maintain sulfide oxidation, despite the competition for O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> by aerobic hydrocarbon degradation. Due to the density stratification with gas and oil on top of water, such a massive inflow of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> must come from a lateral source (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1</xref>).
</p>
