<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar to the AFLP results, we found that at the population level, the epigenetic diversity of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> was relatively low. The average values of the Shannon information index (I) and percentage of polymorphic loci (PPL) were 0.038 and 9.21%, respectively (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00291-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). AMOVA results showed that there was significant epigenetic variation among populations (PhiPT = 0.929, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). A total of 87% of the epigenetic variation originated among populations, and 13% of the epigenetic variation originated within population (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00291-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Similar to previous studies of epigenetic variations in natural populations of other species [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], epigenetic variations within populations are higher than genetic variations within populations (MSAP: 13%, AFLP: 5%). A reasonable explanation is that since the spontaneous epigenetic mutation rate is higher than the genetic mutation rate, the epigenetic variation is usually larger [
 <xref rid="B47-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], which may separate the genetic variation from the epigenetic variation. Another common explanation is that populations with limited genetic diversity, especially after genetic drift, can expand their niche through epigenetic variation, which may be sensitive to environmental stimuli [
 <xref rid="B48-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. PCoA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00291-f001">Figure 1</xref>b) and clustering analysis (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-plants-10-00291">Figure S2b</xref>) indicated that there were significant genetic variations in different populations. However, the degree of separation of epigenetic variation among different populations is not as obvious as genetic variation. This means that the effect of geographic distance on epigenetic variation is not obvious.
</p>
