<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antioxidants-09-01089-f003">Figure 3</xref>, 
 <italic>T. polium</italic> extract seems to possess an anticancer effect. In fact, it inhibits the proliferation of both malignant Walker 256/B and MatLyLu cells in a concentration- and time-dependent manner. It has been previously reported that 
 <italic>T. polium</italic> inhibited the proliferation of prostate cancer cells [
 <xref rid="B96-antioxidants-09-01089" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Similarly, several medicinal plant extracts inhibit the invasion, cancer evolution, and metastases. A recent study expected that in the near future, 
 <italic>T. polium</italic> extract may be a novel anticancer agent [
 <xref rid="B97-antioxidants-09-01089" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. This possibility is certainly related to the promising effects of the plant extract and could explain the ethno-pharmacological applications and the traditional use of 
 <italic>T. polium</italic>. In fact, as shown in 
 <xref rid="antioxidants-09-01089-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="antioxidants-09-01089-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the plant methanolic extract exhibits a relevant and promising phytochemical composition following HR-LCMS assay. It includes, but is not limited to, flavonoid and isoflavonoid, isoprenoid, diterpene triepoxide (such as triptonide), and terpene (such as valtratum). All these chemical compounds possess pharmacological activities. Basically, these natural compounds, such as the triptonide, were effective in inhibiting tumorigenicity and tumor growth in a wide variety of cancers, including pancreatic cancer and thyroid induced metastases by activating the tumor-suppressive MAPK (mitogen-activated protein kinase) signaling pathway and via astrocyte elevated gene-1, respectively [
 <xref rid="B98-antioxidants-09-01089" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-antioxidants-09-01089" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. These phytochemical compounds might have better pharmacological properties together rather than separated. In fact, it has been reported that the effect of the whole plant is usually much better than that of its active phytochemical compounds [
 <xref rid="B100-antioxidants-09-01089" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>].
</p>
