<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation methods</div>
 <p id="Par67" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The components in the extract from above methods are complex and contain a variety of natural products that require further separation and purification to obtain the active fraction or pure natural products. The separation depends on the physical or chemical difference of the individual natural product. Chromatography, especially column chromatography, is the main method used to obtain pure natural products from a complex mixture.</p>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation based on adsorption properties</div>
  <p id="Par68" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adsorption column chromatography is widely used for the separation of natural products, especially in the initial separation stage, due to its simplicity, high capacity and low cost of adsorbents such as silica gel and macroporous resins. The separation is based on the differences between the adsorption affinities of the natural products for the surface of the adsorbents. The selection of adsorbents (stationary phase) as well as the mobile phase is crucial to achieve good separation of natural products, maximize the recovery of target compounds and avoid the irreversible adsorption of target compounds onto the adsorbents.</p>
  <p id="Par69" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Silica gel is the most widely used adsorbent in phytochemical investigation. It was estimated that nearly 90% of phytochemical separation (preparative scale) was based on silica gel. Silica gel is a polar absorbent with silanol groups. Molecules are retained by the silica gel through hydrogen bonds and dipole–dipole interactions. Thus, polar natural products are retained longer in silica gel columns than nonpolar ones. Sometimes, certain polar natural products might undergo irreversible chemisorption. The deactivation of silica gel by adding water before use or using a water-containing mobile phase will weaken the adsorption. Severe tailing may occur when separating alkaloids on silica gel, and the addition of a small amount of ammonia or organic amines such as triethylamine may reduce the tailing. Twelve alkaloids belonging to the methyl chanofruticosinate group including six new alkaloids, prunifolines A–F (
   <span class="bold">68</span>–
   <span class="bold">73</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>), were obtained from the leaf of 
   <span class="italic">Kopsia arborea</span> by initial silica gel column chromatography using gradient MeOH–CHCl
   <sub>3</sub> as the mobile phase followed by centrifugal TLC using ammonia saturated Et
   <sub>2</sub>O–hexane or EtOAc/hexane systems as the eluent [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>].
   <div id="Fig11" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 11</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">68</span>–
      <span class="bold">88</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par70" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alumina (aluminum oxide) is a strong polar adsorbent used in the separation of natural products especially in the separation of alkaloids. The strong positive field of Al
   <span class="sup">3+</span> and the basic sites in alumina affecting easily polarized compounds lead to the adsorption on alumina that is different from that on silica gel. The application of alumina in the separation of natural products has decreased significantly in recent years because it can catalyze dehydration, decomposition or isomerization during separation. Zhang and Su reported a chromatographic protocol using basic alumina to separate taxol (
   <span class="bold">74</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>) from the extract of 
   <span class="italic">Taxus cuspidate</span> callus cultures and found the recovery of taxol was more than 160%. They found that the increase of taxol came from the isomerization of 7-
   <span class="italic">epi</span>-taxol (
   <span class="bold">75</span>) catalyzed by alumina. It was also found that a small amount of taxol could be decomposed to baccatin III (
   <span class="bold">76</span>) and 10-deacetylbaccatin III (
   <span class="bold">77</span>) in the alumina column [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Further investigation into the separation of taxol on acidic, neutral and basic alumina indicated that the Lewis souci and the basic activity cores on the surface of alumina induced the isomerization of 7-
   <span class="italic">epi</span>-taxol to taxol [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par71" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The structures of polyamides used in chromatography contain both acryl and amide groups. Hydrophobic and/or hydrogen bond interaction will occur in polyamide column chromatography depending on the composition of the mobile phase. When polar solvents such as aqueous solvents are used as the mobile phase, the polyamides act as the non-polar stationary phase and the chromatography behavior is similar to reversed-phase chromatography. In the contrast, the polyamides act as the polar stationary phase and the chromatography behavior is similar to normal phase chromatography. Polyamide column chromatography is a conventional tool for the separation of natural polyphenols including anthraquinones, phenolic acids and flavonoids, whose mechanisms are ascribed to hydrogen bond formation between polyamide absorbents, mobile phase and target compounds. Gao et al. studied the chromatography behavior of polyphenols including phenolic acids and flavonoids on polyamide column. It was found that the polyamide functioned as a hydrogen bond acceptor, and the numbers of phenolic hydroxyls and their positions in the molecule affected the strength of adsorption [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. In addition to polyphenols, the separation of other types of natural products by polyamide column chromatography were also reported. The total saponins of Kuqingcha can be enriched by polyamide column chromatography, which significantly reduced the systolic pressure of SHR rat [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>]. Using a mixture of dichloromethane and methanol in a gradient as the eluent, the seven major isoquinoline alkaloids in Coptidis Rhizoma including berberine (
   <span class="bold">39</span>), coptisine (
   <span class="bold">40</span>), palmatine (
   <span class="bold">41</span>), jatrorrhizine (
   <span class="bold">42</span>), columbamine (
   <span class="bold">78</span>), groenlandicine (
   <span class="bold">79</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), and magnoflorine (
   <span class="bold">80</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>) were separated in one-step polyamide column chromatography [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par72" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adsorptive macroporous resins are polymer adsorbents with macroporous structures but without ion exchange groups that can selectively adsorb almost any type of natural products. They have been widely used either as a standalone system, or as part of a pretreatment process for removing impurities or enriching target compounds due to their advantages, which include high adsorptive capacity, relatively low cost, easy regeneration and easy scale-up. The adsorptive mechanisms of adsorptive macroporous resins include electrostatic forces, hydrogen bonding, complex formation and size-sieving actions between the resins and the natural products in solution. Surface area, pore diameter and polarity are the key factors affecting the capacity of the resins [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. 20(
   <span class="italic">S</span>)-protopanaxatriol saponins (PTS) (
   <span class="bold">81</span>) and 20(
   <span class="italic">S</span>)-protopanaxadiol saponins (PDS) (
   <span class="bold">82</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>) are known as two major bioactive components in the root of 
   <span class="italic">Panax notoginseng</span>. PTS and PDS were successfully separated with 30 and 80% (v/v) aqueous ethanol solutions from the D101 macroporous resin column, respectively. The chromatography behaviors of PDS and PTS were close to reversed-phase chromatography when comparing the chromatographic profiles of macroporous resin column chromatography to the HPLC chromatogram on a Zorbax SB-C
   <sub>18</sub> column [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. Recently, Meng et al. obtained the total saponins of Panacis Japonici Rhizoma (PJRS) using D101 macroporous resin. The contents of the four major saponins, chikusetsusaponins V (
   <span class="bold">55</span>), IV (
   <span class="bold">56</span>) and IVa 
   <span class="bold">(57</span>), and pseudoginsenoside RT1 (
   <span class="bold">58</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a>), in the obtained PJRS was more than 73%. The PJRS served as the standard reference for quality control of Panacis Japonici Rhizoma [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. Some researchers assumed that the principal adsorptive mechanism between macroporous resins and polyphenols was associated with the hydrogen bonding formation between the oxygen atom of the ether bond of the resin and the hydrogen atom of phenolic hydroxyl group of the phenol. The hydrogen bonding interaction force was significantly affected by the pH value of the solution [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par73" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Silver nitrate is another useful solid support in the separation of natural products. Those natural products containing the π electrons reversibly interact with silver ions to form polar complexes. The greater the number of double bonds or aromaticity of the natural product, the stronger the complexation forms. Silver nitrate is typically impregnated on silica gel (SNIS) or alumina for separation. Several research groups reported the separation of fatty acids on SNIS [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>]. Wang et al. reported the isolation of zingiberene from ginger oleoresin by SNIS column chromatography [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>]. A pair of isomers, brasiliensic acid (
   <span class="bold">83</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>) and isobrasiliensic acid (
   <span class="bold">84</span>), were separated from 
   <span class="italic">Calophyllum brasiliense</span> by Lemos et al. on an SNIS column [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>]. Some research groups also applied silver nitrate in the two-phase system in high-speed counter-current chromatography (HSCCC) to improve the separation. Xanthochymol (
   <span class="bold">85</span>) and guttiferone E (
   <span class="bold">86</span>) are a pair of π bond benzophenone isomers from 
   <span class="italic">Garcinia xanthochymus</span> by AgNO
   <sub>3</sub>-HSCCC. The elution order of the π bond isomers in this AgNO
   <sub>3</sub>-HSCCC separation is internal π bond (earlier) &lt; terminal, which is identical to that observed from SNIS column chromatography [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation based on partition coefficient</div>
  <p id="Par74" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Partition chromatography (PC) follows the liquid–liquid extraction principle based on the relative solubility in two different immiscible liquids. In the early stage, one liquid phase was coated to a solid matrix (silica gel, carbon, cellulose, etc.) as the stationary phase and another liquid phase was employed as the mobile phase. The disadvantage of an easily removed stationary phase and unrepeatable results has led to this kind of PC being rarely used today. The bonded-phase, in which the liquid stationary phase is chemically bound to the inert support, which is used as the stationary phase overcomes those drawbacks. Commercially available alkyl such as C8 and C18, aryl, cyano and amino substituted silanes are often used as bonded phases, which are widely used to separate a variety of natural products, especially in the final purification step.</p>
  <p id="Par75" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three PTS (notoginsenoside R1 (
   <span class="bold">87</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>), ginsenosides Rg1 (
   <span class="bold">55</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a>) and Re (
   <span class="bold">88</span>) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>)) and two PDS [ginsenosides Rb1 (
   <span class="bold">7</span>) and Rd (
   <span class="bold">9</span>)] (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) were well separated in a C18 column using the EtOH–H
   <sub>2</sub>O system as the mobile phase [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>]. A novel polyacrylamide-based silica stationary phase was synthesized by Cai et al. and was successfully applied in the separation of galactooligosaccharides and saponins of 
   <span class="italic">Paris polyphylla</span> with EtOH–H
   <sub>2</sub>O as the mobile phase [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par76" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Counter-current chromatography (CCC) is kind of PC that holds the liquid stationary phase by gravity or centrifugal force. CCC has rarely been used in early stages due to its poor stationary retention, long separation time and labor intensive process. CCC was significantly improved in the 1980s, however, when modern CCC, including HSCCC and centrifugal partition chromatography (CPC), were developed. The hydrodynamic CCC systems such as HSCCC have a planetary rotation movement around two rotating axes with no rotating seals, which offers a low pressure drop process. Hydrostatic CCC, e.g., centrifugal partition chromatography, uses only one rotating axis and has a series of interconnecting chambers to trap the stationary phase which offers a higher retention of the stationary phase and a higher system pressure than that of HSCCC. The high system pressure in CPC prevents the improvement of the resolution by increasing the length of the column. High performance CCC (HPCCC) represents a new generation of hydrodynamic CCC and works in the same way as HSCCC, but with a much higher g-level. The HPCCC instruments generate more than 240 g, while early HSCCC equipment gave g-levels of less than 80 g. HPCCC shortens the separation time to less than an hour compared to several hours in previous HSCCC and can achieve at least ten times the throughput of an HSCCC instrument [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>]. Compared to the conventional column separation method using a solid stationary phase, both hydrostatic and hydrodynamic CCC systems offer some advantages including the elimination of irreversible adsorption and peak tailing, high loading capacity, high sample recovery, minimal risk of sample denaturation and low solvent consumption. The limitation of CCC is that it only separates the compounds in a relatively narrow polarity window. Over the past 20 years, HSCCC, HPCCC and CPC attracted great attention in separation science and have been widely used in the separation of natural products. Tang et al. developed an HSCCC method using a two-phase solvent system comprising ethyl acetate–
   <span class="italic">n</span>-butanol–ethanol–water (4:2:1.5:8.5, v/v/v/v) to separate six flavone 
   <span class="italic">C</span>-glycosides (
   <span class="bold">89</span>–
   <span class="bold">94</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig12">12</a>), including two novel compounds from 
   <span class="italic">Lophatherum gracile</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>]. HSCCC, HPCCC and CPC have also been successfully applied in the separation of volatile oil, which is difficult to separate via conventional column chromatography. Six volatile compounds (curdione (
   <span class="bold">95</span>), curcumol (
   <span class="bold">96</span>), germacrone (
   <span class="bold">97</span>), curzerene (
   <span class="bold">98</span>), 1,8-cineole (
   <span class="bold">99</span>) and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-elemene (
   <span class="bold">100</span>)) were isolated by CPC from the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Curcuma wenyujin</span> using a nonaqueous two-phase solvent system consisting of petroleum ether–acetonitrile–acetone (4:3:1 v/v/v) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>]. Four major sesquiterpenoids (ar-turmerone (
   <span class="bold">101</span>), 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-turmerone (
   <span class="bold">102</span>), 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-turmerone (
   <span class="bold">103</span>), and 
   <span class="italic">E</span>-atlantone (
   <span class="bold">104</span>)) with similar structures were separated from the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Curcuma longa</span> in a single HSCCC run using a two-phase solvent system composed of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-heptane–ethyl acetate–acetonitrile–water (9.5/0.5/9/1, v/v) and each compound achieved over 98% purity [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. Linalool (
   <span class="bold">105</span>), terpinen-4-
   <span class="italic">ol</span> (
   <span class="bold">106</span>), 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol (
   <span class="bold">107</span>), 
   <span class="italic">p</span>-anisaldehyde (
   <span class="bold">108</span>), anethole (
   <span class="bold">109</span>) and foeniculin (
   <span class="bold">110</span>) were successfully isolated from the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Pimpinella anisum</span> by HPCCC using a stepwise gradient elution [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>]. Li et al. developed a CPC method for the separation of patchouli alcohol (
   <span class="bold">111</span>) with a nonaqueous ether–acetonitrile (1:1, v/v) solvent system. More than 2 g of patchouli alcohol with over 98% purity were isolated from 12.5 g of essential oil over a 240 ml column [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>]. The large volume (several liters) column has been adopted in commercial hydrostatic CCC and hydrodynamic CCC equipment for pilot/industrial scale separation. Few reports could be obtained due to commercial confidentiality. It is difficult to judge whether hydrostatic or hydrodynamic CCC is better for industrial applications. Users might select different types of CCC instrument for different purposes. When the stationary phase is poorly retained in hydrodynamic CCC due to high viscosity and small density differences between the mobile and stationary phases, the hydrostatic CCC is more practical than hydrodynamic CCC because the retention of the stationary phase of hydrostatic CCC is less sensitive to the physical properties of liquid systems and will have a higher retention of the stationary phase. When the stationary phase is well retained in hydrodynamic CCC, higher separation efficiency will be obtained from hydrodynamic CCC than from hydrostatic CCC with the same liquid system and similar column volumes because hydrostatic CCC has relatively low partition efficiency due to a limited degree of mixing, and the hydrodynamic system provides efficient mixing to yield a high partition efficiency.
   <div id="Fig12" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 12</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">89</span>–
      <span class="bold">111</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig12_HTML" id="MO12" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation based on the molecular size</div>
  <p id="Par77" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The separation of natural products by membrane filtration (MF) or gel filtration chromatography (GFC) is based on their molecular sizes.</p>
  <sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Membrane filtration (MF)</div>
   <p id="Par78" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In MF, the semipermeable membrane allows smaller molecules to pass through and retains the larger molecules. MF of natural products could be characterized as microfiltration, ultrafiltration, and nanofiltration based on the pore size of the membrane applied.</p>
   <p id="Par79" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Membrane filtration has been a powerful tool for the concentration, clarification and removal of impurities in the lab, as well as in the food and pharmaceutical industries. The contents of total phenols (338%), chlorogenic acid (
    <span class="bold">66</span>) (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig10">10</a>) (483%), theobromine (
    <span class="bold">112</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig13">13</a>) (323%), caffeine (
    <span class="bold">113</span>) (251%), condensed tannins (278%) and saponins (211%) in the aqueous extract of 
    <span class="italic">Ilex paraguariensis</span> were significantly increased by nanofiltration [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>]. Coupling membrane filtration is applied when a single membrane filtration step is not satisfactory. A sequence of microfiltration, ultrafiltration and nanofiltration was applied in the isolation of bioactive components from olive leaf extract. Microfiltration followed by ultrafiltration removed the impurities larger than 5 kDa. Nanofiltration recovered the antioxidative and antibacterial polyphenols and flavonoids, and the content of the major component, oleuropein (
    <span class="bold">114</span>), in the nanofiltration retentate was concentrated approximately ten times [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>].
    <div id="Fig13" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 13</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structures of compounds 
       <span class="bold">112</span>–
       <span class="bold">114</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig13_HTML" id="MO13" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gel filtration chromatography (GFC)</div>
   <p id="Par80" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gel filtration chromatography is also known as gel permeation chromatography or size exclusion chromatography. The small molecules have a longer retention time in GFC than large molecules.</p>
   <p id="Par81" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sephadex is formed by cross-linking dextran, and the G-types of Sephadex were used for the separation of hydrophilic compounds such as peptides [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>], oligosaccharides and polysaccharides [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par82" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sephadex LH20, a hydroxypropylated derivative of Sephadex G25, has both hydrophobic and hydrophilic natures. An adsorption mechanism was also involved in separation using Sephadex LH-20. Sephadex LH-20 can be used for the separation of a wide variety of natural products in either an aqueous or non-aqueous solvent system. The feruloylated arabinoxylan oligosaccharides of perennial cereal grain intermediate wheat were well separated by Sephadex LH-20 using 100% water as the mobile phase [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>]. Three new pyrimidine diterpenes, axistatins 1–3 (
    <span class="bold">115</span>–
    <span class="bold">117</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig14">14</a>) along with three known formamides (
    <span class="bold">118</span>–
    <span class="bold">120</span>) were isolated from the anti-cancer active CH
    <sub>2</sub>Cl
    <sub>2</sub> fraction of 
    <span class="italic">Agelas axifera</span> over Sephadex LH-20 columns with a series of solvent systems [CH
    <sub>3</sub>OH, CH
    <sub>3</sub>OH–CH
    <sub>2</sub>Cl
    <sub>2</sub> (3:2), hexane–CH
    <sub>3</sub>OH–2-propanol (8:1:1), hexane–toluene–CH
    <sub>2</sub>Cl
    <sub>2</sub>–EtOH (17:1:1:1) and exane–EtOAc–CH
    <sub>3</sub>OH (4:5:1)], followed by purification using Prep-HPLC [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>].
    <div id="Fig14" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 14</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structures of compounds 
       <span class="bold">115</span>–
       <span class="bold">120</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig14_HTML" id="MO14" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
   <p id="Par83" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polyacrylamide (bio-gel P) [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>] and cross-linked agarose [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>] were also used in the separation of natural products.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation based on ionic strength</div>
  <p id="Par84" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ion-exchange chromatography (IEC) separates molecules based on the differences in their net surface charge. Some natural products, such as alkaloids and organic acids possessing a functional group capable of ionization, might be separated by IEC. The charged molecules could be caught and released by ion-exchange resin by changing the ionic strength of the mobile phase (e.g., changing pH or salt concentration). Cation ion-exchange resins were used for the separation of alkaloids, while the anion ion-exchange resins were used for the separation of natural organic acids and phenols.</p>
  <p id="Par85" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The positively charged anthocyanins were separated from the neutral polyphenolic compounds in the XAD-7 treated 
   <span class="italic">Actinidia melanandra</span> fruit (kiwifruit) extract using Dowex 50WX8 cation ion-exchange resin [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>]. Feng and Zhao used semi-preparative chromatography to separate (−)epigallocatechin-gallate [
   <span class="bold">121</span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig15">15</a>)] and (−)epicatechin-gallate (
   <span class="bold">122</span>) in tea crude extract with polysaccharide-based weakly acidic gel CM-Sephadex C-25 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>]. A new alkaloid, fumonisin B
   <sub>6</sub> (
   <span class="bold">123</span>), along with a known alkaloid, fumonisin B
   <sub>2</sub> (
   <span class="bold">124</span>), was isolated by IEC over Strata X-C mixed-mode RP-cation-exchange resin followed by reverse-phase chromatography from the fungus 
   <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span> NRRL 326 cultures extract [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>].
   <div id="Fig15" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 15</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Structures of compounds 
      <span class="bold">121</span>–1
      <span class="bold">24</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig15_HTML" id="MO15" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other modern separation techniques</div>
  <sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular distillation (MD)</div>
   <p id="Par86" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular distillation separates the molecular by distillation under vacuum at a temperature far below its boiling point. It is a suitable distillation method for separating thermosensitive and high-molecular-weight compounds. Borgarello et al. obtained a thymol (
    <span class="bold">125</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig16">16</a>) enrichment fraction from oregano essential oil by molecular distillation modeled by artificial neural networks. The obtained fraction had antioxidant properties and could stabilize the sunflower oil [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>]. Three kinds of phthalates were effectively removed from sweet orange oil by molecular distillation under the optimal conditions (evaporation temperature of 50 °C, evaporator pressure of 5 kPa and a feed flow rate of 0.75 ml/min) [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>].
    <div id="Fig16" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 16</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structure of compounds 
       <span class="bold">125</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig16_HTML" id="MO16" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec24" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparative gas chromatography (Prep-GC)</div>
   <p id="Par87" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography (GC) with high separation efficiency and fast separation and analysis makes it potentially the ideal preparative method for the separation of volatile compounds. The injection port, column, split device and trap device of GC equipment must be modified for preparative separation due to a lack of commercial Prep-GC [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par88" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Five volatile compounds, namely, curzerene (
    <span class="bold">98</span>) (6.6 mg), 
    <span class="italic">β</span>-elemene (
    <span class="bold">100</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig12">12</a>) (5.1 mg), curzerenone (
    <span class="bold">126</span>) (41.6 mg), curcumenol (
    <span class="bold">127</span>) (46.2 mg), and curcumenone (
    <span class="bold">128</span>) (21.2 mg) (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig17">17</a>), were separated from the methanol extract of Curcuma Rhizome by Prep-GC over a stainless steel column packed with 10% OV-101 (3 m × 6 mm, i.d.) after 83 single injections (20 μl) [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>]. Prep-GC was also applied for the separation of natural isomers. A total of 178 mg of 
    <span class="italic">cis</span>-asarone (
    <span class="bold">129</span>) and 82 mg of 
    <span class="italic">trans</span>-asarone (
    <span class="bold">130</span>) were obtained from the essential oil of 
    <span class="italic">Acorus tatarinowii</span> after 90 single injections (5 μl) on the same column as above [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>]. Prep-GC has become an important separation method for natural volatile compounds; however, a heavier sample load and the large-diameter preparative column employed decreased the efficiency [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>]. Meanwhile, the disadvantages of Prep-GC, including the lack of commercial Prep-GC equipment, consumption of a large volume of carrier gas, the decomposition of thermolabile compounds under high operation temperature, the difficulties of fraction collection, and low production, still restrict the usage of Prep-GC.
    <div id="Fig17" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 17</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structures of compounds 
       <span class="bold">126</span>–
       <span class="bold">130</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig17_HTML" id="MO17" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec25" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supercritical fluid chromatography (SFC)</div>
   <p id="Par89" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SFC uses supercritical fluid as the mobile phase. SFC integrates the advantages of both GC and liquid chromatography (LC) as the supercritical fluids possess properties of high dissolving capability, high diffusivity and low viscosity, which allows rapid and efficient separation. Thus, SFC can use a longer column and smaller particles of the stationary phase than HPLC, which provides greater numbers of theoretical plates and better separation. SFC can be used for the separation of non-volatile or thermally labile compounds to which GC is not applicable. SFC systems are compatible with a wide range of different detectors including those used in LC and GC systems. The polarity of the widely used mobile phase, S-CO
    <sub>2</sub>, in SFC is close to the polarity of hexane, with the result that SFC was used for the separation of non-polar natural products such as fatty acids, terpenes and essential oils for many years. Eluent modifiers such methanol and acetonitrile enhance the elution strength, which is increasing the interest in separating polar natural products by SFC [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par90" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zhao et al. successfully separated three pairs of 25 
    <span class="italic">R</span>/
    <span class="italic">S</span> diastereomeric spirostanol saponins (
    <span class="bold">131</span>–
    <span class="bold">136</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig18">18</a>) from the TCM Trigonellae Semen (the seed of 
    <span class="italic">Trigonella foenum</span>-
    <span class="italic">graecum</span>) on two CHIRALPAK IC columns coupled in tandem [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>]. Yang et al. applied SFC for the preparative separation of two pairs of 7-epimeric spiro oxindole alkaloids (
    <span class="bold">137</span>–
    <span class="bold">140</span>) from stems with hooks of 
    <span class="italic">Uncaria macrophylla</span> (a herbal source for TCM Uncariae Ramulus Cum Uncis) on a Viridis Prep Silica 2-EP OBD column using acetonitrile containing 0.2% DEA modified S-CO
    <sub>2</sub>. The non-aqueous mobile phase used in SFC prevented the tautomerization of the separated spiro oxindole alkaloids [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>]. SFC is also applied in the separation of natural enantiomers. (
    <span class="italic">R</span>,
    <span class="italic">S</span>)-goitrin (
    <span class="bold">141</span>–
    <span class="bold">142</span>) is the active ingredient of TCM Isatidis Radix. The chiral separation of (
    <span class="italic">R</span>) and (
    <span class="italic">S</span>) goitrins was successfully achieved by prep-SFC on a Chiralpak IC column using acetonitrile as the organic modifier [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>].
    <div id="Fig18" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 18</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structures of compounds 
       <span class="bold">131</span>–
       <span class="bold">142</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig18_HTML" id="MO18" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec26" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular imprinted technology</div>
   <p id="Par91" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular imprinted technology has been an attractive separation method in the last decade due to its unique features, which include high selectivity, low cost and easy preparation. Many complementary cavities with the memory of size, shape, and functional groups of the template molecules are generated when the template molecules are removed from the molecular imprinted polymer (MIP). Thus, the template molecule and its analogs will have the specific recognition and selective adsorption for the MIP. MIPs have been widely used in the separation of natural products or as solid-phase extraction sorbents for sample preparation of herbal materials to enrich the minor compounds.</p>
   <p id="Par92" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ji et al. developed multi-template molecularly imprinted polymers using DL-tyrosine and phenylpyruvic acid as the template molecules to separate dencichine (
    <span class="bold">143</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig19">19</a>) from the water extract of 
    <span class="italic">Panax notoginseng</span>. Both dencichine and the template molecule of DL-tyrosine (
    <span class="bold">144</span>) contain an amino (NH
    <sub>2</sub>) group and a carboxylic acid (COOH) group, and the other template molecule, phenylpyruvic acid (
    <span class="bold">145</span>), has an α-keto acid (COCOOH) group that can also be found in the structure of dencichine [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>]. Ma et al. developed a preparative separation method to separate solanesol (
    <span class="bold">146</span>) from tobacco leaves by flash chromatography based on MIP. The MIP was prepared with methyl methacrylate as the monomer, solanesol as the template molecule and ethylene glycol dimethacrylate as the crosslinker by a suspension polymerization method. A total of 370.8 mg of solanesol with 98.4% purity was separated from the extract of tobacco leaves with a yield of 2.5% of the dry weight of tobacco leaves [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>]. You et al. used the thermo-responsive magnetic MIP to separate the three major curcuminoids, curcumin (
    <span class="bold">147</span>), demethoxycurcumin (
    <span class="bold">148</span>), and bisdemethoxycurcumin (
    <span class="bold">149</span>), from the TCM Curcumae Longae Rhizoma (the rhizome of 
    <span class="italic">Curcuma longa</span>). The designed thermo-responsive magnetic MIP showed good imprinting factor for curcuminoids in a range between 2.4 and 3.1, thermo-responsiveness [lower critical solution temperature at 33.71 °C] and rapid magnetic separation (5 s) [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>].
    <div id="Fig19" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 19</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structures of compounds 
       <span class="bold">143</span>–
       <span class="bold">149</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig19_HTML" id="MO19" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec27" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulated moving bed chromatography</div>
   <p id="Par93" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulated moving bed (SMB) chromatography uses multiple columns with stationary phases (bed). The countercurrent movement of the bed is simulated through rotary valves, which periodically switch the inlet (feed and eluent) and outlet (extract and raffinate). The SMB process is a continuous separation method and a powerful tool for the large-scale separation of natural products with the advantage of lower solvent consumption over a shorter period of time.</p>
   <p id="Par94" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two cyclopeptides, cyclolinopeptides C and E (
    <span class="bold">150–151</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig20" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig20">20</a>), were obtained from flaxseed oil using a three zone SMBC with eight preparative HPLC normal phase spherical silica gel columns and using absolute ethanol as the desorbent [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>]. Kang et al. developed a tandem SMB process consisting of two four-zone SMB units in a series with the same adsorbent particle sizes in Ring I and Ring II to separate paclitaxel (taxol, 
    <span class="bold">74</span>) (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>), 13-dehydroxybaccatin III (
    <span class="bold">152</span>), and 10-deacetylpaclitaxel (
    <span class="bold">153</span>). Paclitaxel was recovered in the first SMB unit while 13-dehydroxybaccatin III and 10-deacetylpaclitaxel were separated in the second SMB unit [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>]. Mun enhanced this SMB chromatography method by using different particle sizes adsorbent in Ring I and Ring II [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>]. Supercritical fluids can also be used as the desorbent in SMB chromatography. Liang et al. successfully applied supercritical carbon dioxide with ethanol as the desorbent for a three-zone SMB to separate resveratrol (
    <span class="bold">60</span>) (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig9">9</a>) and emodin (
    <span class="bold">44</span>) (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) from a crude extract of the TCM Polygoni Cuspidati Rhizoma et Radix [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>].
    <div id="Fig20" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 20</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structures of compounds 
       <span class="bold">150</span>–
       <span class="bold">153</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig20_HTML" id="MO20" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec28" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multi-dimensional chromatographic separation</div>
   <p id="Par95" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The components in the extract subjected to separation were complex, and generally, no pure compound will be separated in one column chromatography. Multi-dimensional separation based on the solid phase extraction and coupling of multiple columns with different stationary phases greatly improves the separation efficiency. With more commercial multiple dimensional separation equipment entering the market, the separation of natural products is becoming more rapid, efficient and automated.</p>
   <p id="Par96" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Usually, the target compound was enriched by first dimensional separation and purified by last dimensional separation. Multi-dimensional separation can be achieved using the same type separation equipment (LC or GC) or different types of equipment (GC and LC). A novel volatile compound, (2
    <span class="italic">E</span>,6
    <span class="italic">E</span>)-2-methyl-6-(4-methylcyclohex-3-enylidene)hept-2-enal (
    <span class="bold">154</span>), was purified by a three-dimensional prep-GC from wampee essential oil [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>]. Five antioxidant compounds, including two alkaloids [glusodichotomine AK (
    <span class="bold">155</span>) and glusodichotomine B (
    <span class="bold">156</span>)] and three flavonoids [tricin (
    <span class="bold">157</span>), homoeriodictyol (
    <span class="bold">158</span>) (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig21" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig21">21</a>), and luteolin (
    <span class="bold">3</span>) (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>)], were separated using a two-dimensional HPLC (RP/HILIC) method from 
    <span class="italic">Arenaria kansuensis</span> on a RP-C18HCE and a NP-XAmide preparative columns [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">104</a>]. Sciarrone et al. exploited the separation of sesquiterpenes in patchouli essential oil by three dimensional Prep-GC. Patchouli alcohol (
    <span class="bold">111</span>, Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig12">12</a>) (496 μg) was separated in the first dimension on a poly(5% diphenyl/95% dimethylsiloxane) column, and 295 μg of 
    <span class="italic">α</span>-bulnesene (
    <span class="bold">159</span>) was from a second column coated with high molecular weight polyethylene glycol as well as 160 μg 
    <span class="italic">α</span>-guaiene (
    <span class="bold">160</span>) from the third dimension on an ionic-liquid based column (SLB-IL60) [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>]. Pantò et al. applied two three-dimensional approaches (GC–GC–GC and LC–GC–GC) to separate the sesquiterpene alcohols [(
    <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
    <span class="italic">α</span>-santalol (
    <span class="bold">161</span>), (
    <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
    <span class="italic">α</span>-
    <span class="italic">trans</span> bergamotol (
    <span class="bold">162</span>), (
    <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
    <span class="italic">β</span>-santalol (
    <span class="bold">163</span>), 
    <span class="italic">epi</span>-(
    <span class="italic">Z</span>)-
    <span class="italic">β</span>-santalol (
    <span class="bold">164</span>), 
    <span class="italic">α</span>-bisabolol (
    <span class="bold">165</span>), (
    <span class="italic">Z</span>)-lanceol (
    <span class="bold">166</span>), and (
    <span class="italic">Z</span>)-nuciferol (
    <span class="bold">167</span>)] from the sandalwood essential oil. They found that the first dimensional separation using LC reduced the sample complexity and increased the productivity of low-concentration components [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>].
    <div id="Fig21" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 21</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>Structures of compounds 
       <span class="bold">154</span>–
       <span class="bold">167</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig21_HTML" id="MO21" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
