<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec26" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular imprinted technology</div>
 <p id="Par91" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular imprinted technology has been an attractive separation method in the last decade due to its unique features, which include high selectivity, low cost and easy preparation. Many complementary cavities with the memory of size, shape, and functional groups of the template molecules are generated when the template molecules are removed from the molecular imprinted polymer (MIP). Thus, the template molecule and its analogs will have the specific recognition and selective adsorption for the MIP. MIPs have been widely used in the separation of natural products or as solid-phase extraction sorbents for sample preparation of herbal materials to enrich the minor compounds.</p>
 <p id="Par92" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ji et al. developed multi-template molecularly imprinted polymers using DL-tyrosine and phenylpyruvic acid as the template molecules to separate dencichine (
  <span class="bold">143</span>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig19">19</a>) from the water extract of 
  <span class="italic">Panax notoginseng</span>. Both dencichine and the template molecule of DL-tyrosine (
  <span class="bold">144</span>) contain an amino (NH
  <sub>2</sub>) group and a carboxylic acid (COOH) group, and the other template molecule, phenylpyruvic acid (
  <span class="bold">145</span>), has an α-keto acid (COCOOH) group that can also be found in the structure of dencichine [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>]. Ma et al. developed a preparative separation method to separate solanesol (
  <span class="bold">146</span>) from tobacco leaves by flash chromatography based on MIP. The MIP was prepared with methyl methacrylate as the monomer, solanesol as the template molecule and ethylene glycol dimethacrylate as the crosslinker by a suspension polymerization method. A total of 370.8 mg of solanesol with 98.4% purity was separated from the extract of tobacco leaves with a yield of 2.5% of the dry weight of tobacco leaves [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>]. You et al. used the thermo-responsive magnetic MIP to separate the three major curcuminoids, curcumin (
  <span class="bold">147</span>), demethoxycurcumin (
  <span class="bold">148</span>), and bisdemethoxycurcumin (
  <span class="bold">149</span>), from the TCM Curcumae Longae Rhizoma (the rhizome of 
  <span class="italic">Curcuma longa</span>). The designed thermo-responsive magnetic MIP showed good imprinting factor for curcuminoids in a range between 2.4 and 3.1, thermo-responsiveness [lower critical solution temperature at 33.71 °C] and rapid magnetic separation (5 s) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>].
  <div id="Fig19" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 19</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structures of compounds 
     <span class="bold">143</span>–
     <span class="bold">149</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig19_HTML" id="MO19" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
