<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation based on partition coefficient</div>
 <p id="Par74" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Partition chromatography (PC) follows the liquid–liquid extraction principle based on the relative solubility in two different immiscible liquids. In the early stage, one liquid phase was coated to a solid matrix (silica gel, carbon, cellulose, etc.) as the stationary phase and another liquid phase was employed as the mobile phase. The disadvantage of an easily removed stationary phase and unrepeatable results has led to this kind of PC being rarely used today. The bonded-phase, in which the liquid stationary phase is chemically bound to the inert support, which is used as the stationary phase overcomes those drawbacks. Commercially available alkyl such as C8 and C18, aryl, cyano and amino substituted silanes are often used as bonded phases, which are widely used to separate a variety of natural products, especially in the final purification step.</p>
 <p id="Par75" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three PTS (notoginsenoside R1 (
  <span class="bold">87</span>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>), ginsenosides Rg1 (
  <span class="bold">55</span>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8</a>) and Re (
  <span class="bold">88</span>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig11">11</a>)) and two PDS [ginsenosides Rb1 (
  <span class="bold">7</span>) and Rd (
  <span class="bold">9</span>)] (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) were well separated in a C18 column using the EtOH–H
  <sub>2</sub>O system as the mobile phase [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>]. A novel polyacrylamide-based silica stationary phase was synthesized by Cai et al. and was successfully applied in the separation of galactooligosaccharides and saponins of 
  <span class="italic">Paris polyphylla</span> with EtOH–H
  <sub>2</sub>O as the mobile phase [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par76" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Counter-current chromatography (CCC) is kind of PC that holds the liquid stationary phase by gravity or centrifugal force. CCC has rarely been used in early stages due to its poor stationary retention, long separation time and labor intensive process. CCC was significantly improved in the 1980s, however, when modern CCC, including HSCCC and centrifugal partition chromatography (CPC), were developed. The hydrodynamic CCC systems such as HSCCC have a planetary rotation movement around two rotating axes with no rotating seals, which offers a low pressure drop process. Hydrostatic CCC, e.g., centrifugal partition chromatography, uses only one rotating axis and has a series of interconnecting chambers to trap the stationary phase which offers a higher retention of the stationary phase and a higher system pressure than that of HSCCC. The high system pressure in CPC prevents the improvement of the resolution by increasing the length of the column. High performance CCC (HPCCC) represents a new generation of hydrodynamic CCC and works in the same way as HSCCC, but with a much higher g-level. The HPCCC instruments generate more than 240 g, while early HSCCC equipment gave g-levels of less than 80 g. HPCCC shortens the separation time to less than an hour compared to several hours in previous HSCCC and can achieve at least ten times the throughput of an HSCCC instrument [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>]. Compared to the conventional column separation method using a solid stationary phase, both hydrostatic and hydrodynamic CCC systems offer some advantages including the elimination of irreversible adsorption and peak tailing, high loading capacity, high sample recovery, minimal risk of sample denaturation and low solvent consumption. The limitation of CCC is that it only separates the compounds in a relatively narrow polarity window. Over the past 20 years, HSCCC, HPCCC and CPC attracted great attention in separation science and have been widely used in the separation of natural products. Tang et al. developed an HSCCC method using a two-phase solvent system comprising ethyl acetate–
  <span class="italic">n</span>-butanol–ethanol–water (4:2:1.5:8.5, v/v/v/v) to separate six flavone 
  <span class="italic">C</span>-glycosides (
  <span class="bold">89</span>–
  <span class="bold">94</span>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig12">12</a>), including two novel compounds from 
  <span class="italic">Lophatherum gracile</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>]. HSCCC, HPCCC and CPC have also been successfully applied in the separation of volatile oil, which is difficult to separate via conventional column chromatography. Six volatile compounds (curdione (
  <span class="bold">95</span>), curcumol (
  <span class="bold">96</span>), germacrone (
  <span class="bold">97</span>), curzerene (
  <span class="bold">98</span>), 1,8-cineole (
  <span class="bold">99</span>) and 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-elemene (
  <span class="bold">100</span>)) were isolated by CPC from the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Curcuma wenyujin</span> using a nonaqueous two-phase solvent system consisting of petroleum ether–acetonitrile–acetone (4:3:1 v/v/v) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>]. Four major sesquiterpenoids (ar-turmerone (
  <span class="bold">101</span>), 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-turmerone (
  <span class="bold">102</span>), 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-turmerone (
  <span class="bold">103</span>), and 
  <span class="italic">E</span>-atlantone (
  <span class="bold">104</span>)) with similar structures were separated from the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Curcuma longa</span> in a single HSCCC run using a two-phase solvent system composed of 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-heptane–ethyl acetate–acetonitrile–water (9.5/0.5/9/1, v/v) and each compound achieved over 98% purity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. Linalool (
  <span class="bold">105</span>), terpinen-4-
  <span class="italic">ol</span> (
  <span class="bold">106</span>), 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol (
  <span class="bold">107</span>), 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-anisaldehyde (
  <span class="bold">108</span>), anethole (
  <span class="bold">109</span>) and foeniculin (
  <span class="bold">110</span>) were successfully isolated from the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Pimpinella anisum</span> by HPCCC using a stepwise gradient elution [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>]. Li et al. developed a CPC method for the separation of patchouli alcohol (
  <span class="bold">111</span>) with a nonaqueous ether–acetonitrile (1:1, v/v) solvent system. More than 2 g of patchouli alcohol with over 98% purity were isolated from 12.5 g of essential oil over a 240 ml column [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>]. The large volume (several liters) column has been adopted in commercial hydrostatic CCC and hydrodynamic CCC equipment for pilot/industrial scale separation. Few reports could be obtained due to commercial confidentiality. It is difficult to judge whether hydrostatic or hydrodynamic CCC is better for industrial applications. Users might select different types of CCC instrument for different purposes. When the stationary phase is poorly retained in hydrodynamic CCC due to high viscosity and small density differences between the mobile and stationary phases, the hydrostatic CCC is more practical than hydrodynamic CCC because the retention of the stationary phase of hydrostatic CCC is less sensitive to the physical properties of liquid systems and will have a higher retention of the stationary phase. When the stationary phase is well retained in hydrodynamic CCC, higher separation efficiency will be obtained from hydrodynamic CCC than from hydrostatic CCC with the same liquid system and similar column volumes because hydrostatic CCC has relatively low partition efficiency due to a limited degree of mixing, and the hydrodynamic system provides efficient mixing to yield a high partition efficiency.
  <div id="Fig12" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 12</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structures of compounds 
     <span class="bold">89</span>–
     <span class="bold">111</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig12_HTML" id="MO12" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
