<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation based on ionic strength</div>
 <p id="Par84" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ion-exchange chromatography (IEC) separates molecules based on the differences in their net surface charge. Some natural products, such as alkaloids and organic acids possessing a functional group capable of ionization, might be separated by IEC. The charged molecules could be caught and released by ion-exchange resin by changing the ionic strength of the mobile phase (e.g., changing pH or salt concentration). Cation ion-exchange resins were used for the separation of alkaloids, while the anion ion-exchange resins were used for the separation of natural organic acids and phenols.</p>
 <p id="Par85" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The positively charged anthocyanins were separated from the neutral polyphenolic compounds in the XAD-7 treated 
  <span class="italic">Actinidia melanandra</span> fruit (kiwifruit) extract using Dowex 50WX8 cation ion-exchange resin [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>]. Feng and Zhao used semi-preparative chromatography to separate (−)epigallocatechin-gallate [
  <span class="bold">121</span>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig15">15</a>)] and (−)epicatechin-gallate (
  <span class="bold">122</span>) in tea crude extract with polysaccharide-based weakly acidic gel CM-Sephadex C-25 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>]. A new alkaloid, fumonisin B
  <sub>6</sub> (
  <span class="bold">123</span>), along with a known alkaloid, fumonisin B
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <span class="bold">124</span>), was isolated by IEC over Strata X-C mixed-mode RP-cation-exchange resin followed by reverse-phase chromatography from the fungus 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span> NRRL 326 cultures extract [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>].
  <div id="Fig15" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 15</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structures of compounds 
     <span class="bold">121</span>–1
     <span class="bold">24</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig15_HTML" id="MO15" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
