<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec29" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary</div>
 <p id="Par97" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Natural products have contributed to drug development over the past few decades and continue to do so. The lab-intensive and time-consuming of extraction and isolation processes, however, have hindered the application of natural products in drug development. As technology continues to develop, more and more new automatic and rapid techniques have been created to extract and separate natural products, which might reach the requirement of high-throughput screening.</p>
 <p id="Par98" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding extraction, reflux extraction is the most commonly employed technique for preparative separation. The modern extraction methods, also regarded as green extraction methods, including UAE, MAE, SFE and PLE, have also been the subject of increased attention in recent years due to their high extraction yields, selectivity, stability of the target extracts and process safety merits. Some of those green methods have become routine sample preparation methods for analytical purposes.</p>
 <p id="Par99" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding isolation, the development of novel packing material could enhance the efficiency of isolation, which should be researched further. The hyphenation of chromatographic and spectroscopic or spectrometric techniques with the aim of elucidating structures without the need for isolation, such as LC-NMR and LC–MS, is a useful dereplication tool for searching for novel natural products. Although the isolation of pure natural products from complex mixtures remains challenging and we are far from one-step isolation procedures, the application of more selective methods from extraction to fractionation and purification will speed up the time from collecting biological material to isolating the final purified compound.</p>
 <p id="Par100" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, there is a clear and increasing interest in the extraction and isolation of natural products and their advantageous applications. These specific applications are also conditioning the employed extraction methods and novel stationary phases and mobile phases to be used by these techniques. It is thus expected that these trends will be maintained in the near future as they are mostly motivated by emerging consumer demands and by safety, environmental and regulatory issues.</p>
</sec>
