<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec25" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supercritical fluid chromatography (SFC)</div>
 <p id="Par89" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SFC uses supercritical fluid as the mobile phase. SFC integrates the advantages of both GC and liquid chromatography (LC) as the supercritical fluids possess properties of high dissolving capability, high diffusivity and low viscosity, which allows rapid and efficient separation. Thus, SFC can use a longer column and smaller particles of the stationary phase than HPLC, which provides greater numbers of theoretical plates and better separation. SFC can be used for the separation of non-volatile or thermally labile compounds to which GC is not applicable. SFC systems are compatible with a wide range of different detectors including those used in LC and GC systems. The polarity of the widely used mobile phase, S-CO
  <sub>2</sub>, in SFC is close to the polarity of hexane, with the result that SFC was used for the separation of non-polar natural products such as fatty acids, terpenes and essential oils for many years. Eluent modifiers such methanol and acetonitrile enhance the elution strength, which is increasing the interest in separating polar natural products by SFC [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par90" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zhao et al. successfully separated three pairs of 25 
  <span class="italic">R</span>/
  <span class="italic">S</span> diastereomeric spirostanol saponins (
  <span class="bold">131</span>–
  <span class="bold">136</span>, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig18">18</a>) from the TCM Trigonellae Semen (the seed of 
  <span class="italic">Trigonella foenum</span>-
  <span class="italic">graecum</span>) on two CHIRALPAK IC columns coupled in tandem [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>]. Yang et al. applied SFC for the preparative separation of two pairs of 7-epimeric spiro oxindole alkaloids (
  <span class="bold">137</span>–
  <span class="bold">140</span>) from stems with hooks of 
  <span class="italic">Uncaria macrophylla</span> (a herbal source for TCM Uncariae Ramulus Cum Uncis) on a Viridis Prep Silica 2-EP OBD column using acetonitrile containing 0.2% DEA modified S-CO
  <sub>2</sub>. The non-aqueous mobile phase used in SFC prevented the tautomerization of the separated spiro oxindole alkaloids [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>]. SFC is also applied in the separation of natural enantiomers. (
  <span class="italic">R</span>,
  <span class="italic">S</span>)-goitrin (
  <span class="bold">141</span>–
  <span class="bold">142</span>) is the active ingredient of TCM Isatidis Radix. The chiral separation of (
  <span class="italic">R</span>) and (
  <span class="italic">S</span>) goitrins was successfully achieved by prep-SFC on a Chiralpak IC column using acetonitrile as the organic modifier [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>].
  <div id="Fig18" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 18</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Structures of compounds 
     <span class="bold">131</span>–
     <span class="bold">142</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13020_2018_177_Fig18_HTML" id="MO18" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
