<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, 
 <italic>Thymus albicans</italic> and 
 <italic>Thymus mastichina</italic>, with 1,8-cineole as the main constituent, also have positive inhibitory effects on bacteria, such as 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>St. aureus</italic> or 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> sp. [
 <xref rid="B75-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Similarly, the terminal alcohol linalool is active against bacteria of the genus 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> [
 <xref rid="B76-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] and other microorganisms such as 
 <italic>Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>, 
 <italic>Citrobacter freundii</italic> or 
 <italic>Clostridium sporogenes</italic> [
 <xref rid="B73-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Alcohols have more bactericidal than bacteriostatic activity, as they denature the proteins of microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B77-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. In summary, essential oils are effective against a wide variety of microorganisms and can be used as food preservatives when added in small amounts; they can delay microbiological contamination and food deterioration without affecting its organoleptic properties [
 <xref rid="B73-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Moreover, baicalein, another flavone identified in the 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> extract, potentiates the antimicrobial effect of tetracycline on 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B78-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Other studies have reported the antibacterial potential of different plant extracts (thyme, fennel, sage, tea and mint) and determined that thyme is the most effective against common pathogenic bacteria and lactic acid bacteria, so these concentrates are considered natural foods or food additives that could have a positive effect on the digestive system of humans and animals [
 <xref rid="B79-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. The aqueous extract obtained from 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> was screened and found to be one of the most effective against bacteria, such as 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> [
 <xref rid="B80-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. The ability of compounds to act against different microorganisms from the extracts of other thyme species, such as 
 <italic>Thymus serpyllum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B81-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] or 
 <italic>Thymus spathulifolius</italic> [
 <xref rid="B82-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], has also been successfully tested. In the latter article, the authors compared the effects of the EO of the plant, containing thymol (36.5%) and carvacrol (29.8%) as the major constituents, with those of the extract. The result showed the strong antimicrobial activity of the EO, both against bacteria and against most of the fungal species tested by these authors, while the extract acted moderately against bacteria and was not effective against fungi. In other work, the antioxidant capacity of these two substances was evaluated, with positive results for both [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-00961" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
