<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="par0005" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The air-filled cavities of sinuses is one of host defense system, which act by classical, pseudostratified and ciliated columnar epithelium. When one or more of paranasal sinuses become inflamed, sinusitis occurs. Classically, there are four types of sinusitis including acute, sub-acute, chronic and recurrent ones. The infection of paranasal sinuses, which occur 10 days and less than 4 weeks is defined as acute sinusitis. The inflammatory diseases of sinuses, much similar to asthma is chronic sinusitis. Viral upper respiratory infection leads to inflammation of sinuses, damaging the mucosa and defective performance of cilia, which prone the environment to bacterial infections
  <a rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0260">
   <span class="sup">1</span>
  </a>. Rhinoviruses, 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus pneumonia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Haemophilus influenza</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Moraxella catarrhalis</span> are the majority pathogens of acute sinusitis 
  <a rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0265">2</a>, 
  <a rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0270">3</a>. In spite of inflammatory nature of acute sinusitis, the involved bacterial pathogens of acute sinusitis, 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, coagulase negative 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococci</span> are found in chronic sinusitis 
  <a rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0275">
   <span class="sup">4</span>
  </a>. Postnasal drip, greenish nasal discharge, nasal congestion, tenderness of the face under the eyes or at the bridge of the nose, frontal headaches, pain in teeth, cough and fever are common symptoms of sinusitis. Antibiotics (amoxicillin, doxycycline, cephalexin and cefadroxil, etc.) are prescribed for 85-98% of patients with acute sinusitis 
  <a rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0280">5</a>, 
  <a rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0285">6</a>, 
  <a rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0290">7</a>. Nasal corticosteroids, and anti-histamines are used in patients with sneezing or rhinitis. Corticosteroids and antibiotics are used in chronic sinusitis 
  <a rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0295">
   <span class="sup">8</span>
  </a>. The appearance of antibiotic resistant pathogens to chemical agents along with the adverse effects of drugs encourage the scientists to search among the medicinal plants. One of popular plants in traditional medicines for management of sinusitis and clinical symptoms is 
  <span class="italic">Nigella sativa</span> seeds.
 </p>
 <p id="par0010" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Nigella sativa</span>, a member of Ranunculaceae family is commonly known as black seed. 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed with a rich historical and religious background is the miracle curative herb for all ailments, except the death. 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seeds are used widely for extraction of fixed oil. 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seeds were used by Dioscorides as diuretic, emmenagogue, galactopoietic. Avicenna in the “Canon of Medicine” used the black seed for stimulating the body's energy and helping recovery from fatigue and dispiritedness. It was a remedy for coryza. Frying the seeds in oil and putting in the lint and putting on forehead, relieves the headache. Soaking the seeds in the vinegar for one night and crushing them and smelling was a remedy for chronic headache 
  <a rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0300">
   <span class="sup">9</span>
  </a>. In Middle East countries, 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed oil is used as antiseptic, local analgesic and for treatment of asthma, bronchitis, rheumatism and other inflammatory diseases 
  <a rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0305">
   <span class="sup">10</span>
  </a>. Algerians take the roasted seeds with butter for cough, and with honey for colic, Arabians use its seed as lactagogue, soaking in rose oil as eye drops for eye infections. Indian people use the seed tincture for anorexia, diarrhea, dyspepsia and fever or seed fixed oil in sesame oil for dermatosis. 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> is anthelmintic, carminative, emmenagogue and stimulant in Ayurvedic. Sniffing the cloth containing the mixture of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed with melted butter is used by Ethiopians for headache. Indonesians combine 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed with astringent medicines for abdominal disorders. The seed extract is used for treatment of liver ailments. The poultice seeds is used by Malayans for treatment of abscesses, headache, nasal ulcers, orchitis and rheumatism. In North Africans, mixture of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed with honey is used as morning aperitif. Unani Medicine consider the plant as abortifacient, diuretic, anthelmintic and emmenagogue and good treatment for cough, fever, jaundice, pulmonosis and sore eyes. In Yemen, the seeds are used for hemorrhoids 
  <a rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0310">
   <span class="sup">11</span>
  </a>.
 </p>
 <p id="par0015" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0005">Fig. 1</a>
  <div id="fig0005" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Nigella sativa</span> fixed oil in management of clinical symptoms of sinusitis.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="gr1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="par0020" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fixed oils is extracted for edible purposes, flavoring foods, preservatives in confectioneries, stabilizing of edible fats and pharmaceutical applications. According to traditional uses of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed for treatment of headache, fever, cough and coryza, 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed fixed oil has a good potency for treatment of sinusitis. In this review article, we evaluate the therapeutic potency of 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> fixed oil in management of sinusitis and its symptoms.
 </p>
</sec>
