<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the current study, we expanded the exposure window from our prior work using a prenatal exposure (GD 11–18) to combine pre-conception, prenatal, and lactational exposure to assess impacts of adult maternal exposure prior to fertilization and to bracket fetal development from GD 1 to PND 21. Exposure during GD 1–11 covers development of the placenta, pancreas, and liver, and maternal high fat diet during this period has been shown to cause adverse metabolic outcomes in offspring (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>). Also, a prolonged exposure through PND 21 includes development of the brain including expression of neurotransmitters and their receptors (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>). The brain is a key modulator of energy balance regulating food intake, energy expenditure, and insulin secretion (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>). UOG chemicals are cleared from the body within hours, so the exposure window for this study did not cover the time of mating to avoid male exposure as it has been shown male sperm can effect the epigenetics of offspring leading to obesity (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>). Exposure started at GD 1, which is 24–36 h after mating depending on exactly when copulation occurred. This exposure paradigm is largely after the major wave of the zygotic activation phase between ~24 and 36 h, when the embryo is becoming transcriptionally active, which will result in some heterogeneity of exposure depending on when copulation occurred (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>). Epigenetic remodeling occurs during this developmental phase and experiments should specifically target this phase for exposure to determine if UOG chemical exposure alters epigenetic reprogramming (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>). Future work is needed to systematically assess the impacts of UOG exposure on the epigenetics of offspring and the unique impacts of different exposure windows.
</p>
