<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The milk composition had an important influence on the growth and development of suckling piglets [
 <xref rid="B4-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. The current findings showed that fat supplementation during gestation increased the colostral protein concentration. Similarly, a previous study showed that the isoenergetic replacement of maize starch with soy oil in sow lactation diets tended to have greater protein concentration in milk [
 <xref rid="B23-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], which may be attributed to the development of the mammary gland [
 <xref rid="B24-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] because fatty acids are required for mammary ductal and alveolar structure development [
 <xref rid="B25-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Data from lambs indicated that dietary polyunsaturated fatty acids stimulate mammary growth through increasing the expression of prolactin receptor in mammary parenchyma and growth hormone receptor in liver [
 <xref rid="B26-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], suggesting a beneficial effect of dietary fat supplementation on improving colostrum composition. In addition, the higher colostral protein concentration in sows fed the HF diet may suggest higher immunoglobulin content in the colostrum, which would provide immediate immune protection to newborn piglets [
 <xref rid="B27-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. However, the inconsistent results showed that the fat concentration in colostrum and milk was not markedly increased by fat supplementation during gestation, which may be related to the dosage and sources of fat [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Furthermore, the limited number of sows used in our experiment cannot be ignored.
</p>
