<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides, the eCBS plays a key role in the process of extinguishing aversive memories, which is mainly mediated by CB1 and could be thus facilitated by CBD administration, as already suggested by animal models, with further confirmation in human studies [
 <xref rid="B34-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Similar mechanisms could also explain the improvement in arousal symptom clusters, that appear to be activated by emotional processing of fear-elicited stimuli and altered responses to trauma-related cues [
 <xref rid="B63-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Interestingly, only one among the included studies considered the administration of CBD at variable doses [
 <xref rid="B47-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], whilst in the remaining studies subjects were treated with different formulations of medicinal cannabis containing THC and CBD at different percentages, or synthetic compounds. Consequently, aversive memories extinction is not expected to be the only mechanism possibly explaining the efficacy of medicinal cannabis in reducing PTSD symptoms. The effect on global PTSD symptomatology might be mediated by the reduction of HPA axis hyperactivation following eCBS signaling enhancement. This could be related to the expression of CB receptors in brain areas that modulate stress, as well as emotional responses to fear and reward, such as the amygdala, pre-frontal cortex, and hippocampus [
 <xref rid="B64-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Particularly, CB1 in the pre-frontal cortex plays a significant role in threat-related responses by modulating the amygdala region [
 <xref rid="B65-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Noteworthy, one of the selected studies showed how the administration of medicinal THC in PTSD subjects could influence cortico-limbic circuitry, also reducing amygdala reactivity in response to potentially threatening stimuli [
 <xref rid="B52-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. This result should hopefully be replicated for CBD and synthetic 
 <italic>Cannabis</italic>-derived compounds, to evaluate whether slightly different actions on eCBS receptors may underpin different effects on brain circuitry. Moreover, future studies should better clarify functional correlates of treatment with medications acting on the eCBS to provide further explanations about their mechanism of action in reducing PTSD symptoms. Furthermore, specific symptom clusters were targeted by treatment with medicinal cannabis in some of the included studies. Particularly, sleep problems such as PTSD-related nightmares were significantly improved by THC oil and nabilone at a maximum dose of 3–6 mg. This result may be of clinical relevance since nightmares are not typically targeted by medications that appear to be efficient in treating other PTSD symptoms [
 <xref rid="B66-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The efficacy of 
 <italic>Cannabis</italic> derivates in ameliorating sleep disorders was already elucidated by animal studies, with specific effects on sleep duration and depth varying based on means and site of administration (e.g., intraperitoneal, amygdala, brain ventriculus, etc.) [
 <xref rid="B67-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Diverse effects of CBD were over time detected depending on medication doses, with higher doses up to 160 mg/day increasing sedative-hypnotic effects [
 <xref rid="B69-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Such effects were hypothesized to be mediated by the monoaminergic system since CBD appeared to increase the expression of c-Fos in the dorsal raphe nuclei [
 <xref rid="B71-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Furthermore, CBD can increase Anandamide (AEA) concentration by blocking the AEA membrane transporter (AMT) or the Fatty Acid Amide Hydrolase (FAAH) enzyme, which catalyzes AEA hydrolysis, increasing time of sleep and of slow-wave phase that is physiologically fostered by this endogenous CB1 ligand [
 <xref rid="B72-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Nevertheless, most preclinical research focused mainly on the administration of CBD, which acts as a negative allosteric modulator of CB1 [
 <xref rid="B73-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], while the included studies considered effects of TCH and its derivates, possibly operating as a partial agonist of the receptor [
 <xref rid="B74-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. In consideration of their different actions on endogenous receptors, further studies on PTSD populations should better clarify different actions of THC and CBD on sleep disorders. This could be of particular interest also due to the frequent association that specific arousal disturbances may present with nightmares and sleep abnormalities, with evidence for nabilone improving such disturbances in non-PTSD populations [
 <xref rid="B75-life-11-00214" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].
</p>
