<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mechanisms described in 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> that contribute to multidrug resistance include (i) alteration of the target at which the drug exerts its activity, (ii) mutations and alterations in cell wall and cellular membrane components that reduce drug access, and (iii) the derepression of chromosomal components that encode multidrug resistance efflux pumps (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Foster, 2017</xref>). Efflux pumps are transmembrane proteins with the capacity to expel or exchange toxic compounds from bacterial cells, thus allowing bacterium survival. They are a self-defense mechanism by which the antibiotic is expulsed from the cell, predisposing the organism to high target-resistance (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jo and Ahn, 2016</xref>). The pumps are classified according to their characteristics into five families, the most studied of which are NorA, TetK, and MrsA (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">dos Santos et al., 2018</xref>). Analyses of the 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> genome have determined that a large number of MDR efflux pumps are encoded by its genes; however, it has been shown that NorA is its predominant efflux pump (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Handzlik et al., 2013</xref>). It has also been reported that the norA gene, which encodes the carrier protein NorA, is overexpressed in 43% of 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Astolfi et al., 2017</xref>). NorA belongs to the major facilitator superfamily (MFS) of efflux pumps, which are composed of approximately 400 amino acids that are putatively arranged into 12 membrane-spanning helices, with a cytoplasmic loop between the helices (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Santos-Costa et al., 2013</xref>). This efflux pump uses the proton motive force to energize the transport of antimicrobial compounds through the membrane via an antiport mechanism. NorA has the capability to efflux diverse drugs, such as hydrophilic fluoroquinolone antibiotics, dyes, such as acridine and ethidium bromide (EtBr); and biocides (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Bambeke et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zimmermann et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
