<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Kryvtsova and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] studied the effect of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> EO on various typical bacterial strains, including (MRSA) methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolated from the oral cavity of patients suffering from periodontitis and pharyngitis. The test of antibiofilm activity showed that the bacteria biofilm was reduced by 53% after exposure to the lowest concentration of thyme EO (0,01% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>). Higher concentration usage (0.05% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) led to a structure reduction of 76%. The lowest activity was demonstrated against 
 <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic> and 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. The main components of volatile oil used in this research were phenolic monoterpenes, including thymol. Also, Tohidpour and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] investigated the effect of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> and 
 <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> Labill. EO on clinically isolated MRSA. It was found that thyme EO, which contained thymol as a main ingredient, showed better growth-inhibiting properties for these microorganisms than eucalyptus EO. Zhongwei and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] also evaluated the effect of thymol on MRSA biofilm and the potential synergy of thymol with vancomycin, which is the antibiotic of choice for this pathogen infection. Thymol has shown the ability to inhibit biofilm formation and eliminate the mature MRSA biofilm by inhibiting the synthesis of important biofilm components of these bacteria, such as polysaccharide intercellular adhesin (PIA) and extracellular DNA (eDNA), which is an important mechanism for 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilm formation. These structures are responsible for, among other functions, supporting cell aggregation and adhesion to neutral solid surfaces, which determines antibiotic resistance [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Neither thymol nor vancomycin applied to MRSA colonies in the biofilm at the concentrations used showed complete bacterial elimination; however, in the combination of these compounds, the percentage of live bacteria was significantly reduced (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-04125-f004">Figure 4</xref>), which suggests that thymol is effective in supporting the therapeutic effect of vancomycin on MRSA biofilms. In 2019, Kerekes and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] studied potential antimicrobial inhibition of biofilm formation and the quorum-sensing mechanism (QS) by Ceylon cinnamon tree (
 <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> Blume), marjoram (
 <italic>Origanum majorana</italic> L.) and thyme (
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic>) EO and three main selected compounds from them—trans-cinnamaldehyde, terpinen-4-ol and thymol. Among them, thymol showed the most potent activity against single-species biofilms of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. In a study on polymicrobic bacterial cultures, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> EO showed a strong biofilm-reducing effect on 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> at a concentration of 0.5–4 mg/mL. On a dual-species (
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> with 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>) biofilm thyme EO caused growth reduction at a concentration of 0.2–1.5 mg/mL and bacterial death at a concentration of 0.2 mg/mL. The destructive effect of thyme EO and thymol on 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> and 
 <italic>P. putita</italic> was also observed in a study using the scanning electron microscope (SEM) [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Research conducted by Qaralleh [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-04125" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] showed a strong biofilm-reducing effect of 
 <italic>T. capitata</italic> L. EO on 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, which was probably also associated with the presence of thymol as a main EO component. Biofilm reduction of 44.8% and 49.8% was achieved at concentration of 0.0046% (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>), while 99.6% and 98.4% reduction (depending on the 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> strain) were observed at a concentration of 0.041% (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>).
</p>
