<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection of Samples</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fruits of blood plum (
   <span class="italic">Haematostaphis barteri</span>) were purchased from a local market in Zing local government area, Taraba State, Nigeria. The fruits were thoroughly sorted to remove the stones, and the bad ones before washing with tap water. The clean fruits were then transported to the laboratory and proper identification was made by a Taxonomist in the Department of Biological Sciences, Federal University Wukari, Taraba State, Nigeria.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation of Samples</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fifty number clean fruits of 
   <span class="italic">H. barteri</span> were dried in an oven at 40°C for 5 days in order to separate the pulp from the seed because the pulp is thin and juicy. The pulp was separated from the seed, and freely ground with Kenwood food blender. The seed was also carefully de-shelled using kitchen knife, and the kernel was dried in an oven at 45°C for 36h and ground into powder. Flours of the two samples were separately kept in the refrigerator at -4°C prior to use.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extraction of Oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each oven dried sample of pulp and seed (5g each) of 
   <span class="italic">H. barteri</span> was extracted for 5h in Soxhlet apparatus with 200 ml of petroleum ether (40-60
   <span class="sup">0</span>C boiling range) of Analar grade (British Drug Houses, London). The extraction flask was removed from the heating mantle when it was almost free of petroleum ether, oven dried at 105
   <span class="sup">0</span>C for 1h, cooled in a desiccator and used for further analysis [
   <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fatty Acid Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oil extracted from each sample was converted to the methyl ester using the method described by Adeyeye and Adesina [
   <a rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" href="#r7">7</a>]. A 50 mg aliquot of the dried oil was saponified for 5 min at 95°C with 3.4 ml of 0.5 M KOH in dry methanol. The mixture was neutralized by 0.7 M HCl and 3 ml of 14% boron trifloride in methanol was added. The mixture was heated for 5 min at 90°C to achieve complete methylation. The fatty acid methyl esters were analyzed using an HP 6890 gas chromatograph powered with HP Chemistation Rev. a 09.01 (1206) software fitted with a flame ionization detector and a computing integrator. Nitrogen was used as the carrier gas. The column initial temperature was 250°C rising at 5°C/min to a final temperature of 310°C, while the injection port and the detector were maintained at 310°C and 350°C, respectively. A polar (HP INNO Wax) capillary column (30 m × 0.53 mm × 0.25 μm) was used to separate the esters. The peaks were identified by comparison with standard fatty acid methyl esters obtained from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis MO, USA) [
   <a rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" href="#r8">8</a>]. However, the quantitative evaluation was carried out on the basis of gas chromatography peak areas of the different methyl esters. The heptadecanoic ester was used to calculate the response factor for fatty acids which was found to be 0.96. Three determinations were made for each sample.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phospholipid Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The phospholipid content of the pulp and seed oils was determined by gas chromatography (GC). 0.01 g of the extracted fats was added to the test tube. To ensure complete dryness of the oil for phospholipids analysis, the solvent was completely removed by passing the stream of the nitrogen gas on the oil. 0.04 mL of chloroform was added to the content of the tube and it was followed by the addition of 0.10 mL of chromogenic solution. The content of the tube was heated at a temperature of 100°C in a water bath for about 1 min. The content was allowed to cool, 5 mL of the hexane was added and the tube with its content shook gently several times. The solvent and the aqueous layers were recovered and allowed to be separated. The hexane layer was recovered and allowed to be concentrated to 1.0 mL for gas chromatography using flame photometric detector. The conditions for phospholipid analysis include: H.P 5890 powered with HP ChemStation REV. A 09.01 (1206) and split injection ratio of 20:1, nitrogen as carrier gas, inlet temperature 250°C, column type HP5, column dimension: 30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 µm, oven program: initial temperature at 50°C, first ramping at 10°C/min for 20 min, maintained for 4 min while second ramping at 15°C/min for 4 min, maintained for 5 min. Detector: PFPD Detector temperature was 300°C, hydrogen pressure being 20 psi, compressor air being 35 psi [
   <a rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" href="#r8">8</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phytosterol Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The phytosterol analysis was done as described by AOAC [
   <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>]. The aliquots of the extracted fat were added to the screw - capped test tubes. The samples were saponified at 90°C for 30min, using 3 ml of 10% KOH in ethanol, to which 0.20 mL of benzene was added to ensure miscibility. Deionized water (3 mL) was added and 2 mL of hexane was added in extracting the non – saponifiable materials. Three different extrations, each with 2 mL of hexane were carried out for 1h, 30min and 30min, respectively. The hexane was concentrated to 1 mL in the vial for gas chromatography analysis and 1 μL was injected into the injection pot of GC. The GC conditions of analyses were similar to the GC conditions for methyl esters analyses [
   <a rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" href="#r8">8</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physico-Chemical Analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The physico-chemical analyses of the 
   <span class="italic">H. barteri</span> pulp and seed oils for kinematic viscosity, specific gravity, unsaponifiable matter, flash point, saponification value, peroxide value, iodine value and acid value were carried out according to the methods of AOAC [
   <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>]. Three determinations were made for each sample.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.8</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The statistical calculations included percentage value, grand mean, standard deviation and relative standard deviation.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
