<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In short, the wound healing property of mushrooms in many studies have been moderately associated to their rich content in polysaccharides. For example, 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> aqueous extract, 
 <italic>Ganoderma tsugae</italic> (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Chien et al., 2008</xref>) and polysaccharides form 
 <italic>Agaricus blazei</italic> and 
 <italic>Phellinus gilvus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Bae et al., 2005b</xref>) have been reported as useful agents in wound healing with several associated mechanisms (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Krupodorova et al., 2015</xref>). The polysaccharides from 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> can bind through specific receptors or serum-specific proteins to leucocyte surfaces and alter their activities of macrophage, T-helper, NK cells, and other effector cells (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Müller et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Mueller et al., 2000</xref>). Moreover, 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> polysaccharides are potent immune-modulating agents (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Gao and Zhou, 2002</xref>). The polysaccharides of 
 <italic>P. gilvus</italic> decreased IL-1 expression in skin of burn wound-treated rats (50 or 100 mg/kg b. w.) (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Sui et al., 2010</xref>). 
 <italic>P. gilvus</italic>-isolated polysaccharides reduced wound contraction and enhanced the re-epithelialization of the 6-mm circular wounds in streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic rat by topical application twice a day for 5 days (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Bae et al., 2005a</xref>). 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> hot aqueous extract was standardized to contain total polysaccharides (25.1%), ganoderic acid A (0.45%), and adenosine (0.069%) (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2013</xref>). A 10% aqueous extract cream of this mushroom was tested on wounds in the posterior neck region of STZ-induced diabetic rats. The mushroom extract accelerated wound closure more than the standard Intrasite gel. Moreover, the antioxidant activity was significantly higher in the serum of treated rats, and oxidative markers, proteins and lipids were lowered. Another study by 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al. (2014)</xref> has shown that the aqueous lyophilized extract of 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> from the Indian Himalayan region promoted the healing efficacy on wound dermal excision in experimental rats. Ling Zhi-8 (LZ-8) is an immunomodulatory protein isolated from 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> mycelia (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2014</xref>). Ten µL of 1 mg/ml LZ-8 protein solution dropped on the wound in rat liver tissues after monopolar electrosurgery significantly increases wound healing and decreased nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB), caspase-3 and apoptosis. The 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> wound healing activity of aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> and 
 <italic>Crinipellis schevczenkovi</italic> (100 mg powder mycelium/1 ml water for injections) were investigated using the excision wound healing model on albino mice line (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Krupodorova et al., 2015</xref>). The topical application of 
 <italic>C. schevczenkovi</italic> mycelium extract induced wound healing on 3
 <sup>th</sup> day, while on the 6
 <sup>th</sup> day, both extracts induced a complete healing (8
 <sup>th</sup> day in control group).
</p>
