<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0100">The development of resistance to commonly used antibiotics amongst human pathogens is partly due to the misuse of these antimicrobial agents, which has led humans to seek new and alternative therapies. In this study, the phytochemical properties and anti-microbial effects of Tris buffer and warm water protein extracts of dry 
 <italic>A. auricula-judea</italic> mushroom were evaluated. The phytochemical analysis of crude extracts revealed the presence of carbohydrate (43.15 %; 38.30 %), proteins (23.75 %; 23.75 %), flavonoids (1.20 %; 0.80 %), alkaloids (0.60 %; 1.00 %), saponin (6.00 %; 2.40 %), tannin (1.65 %; 1.57 %), cyanide (0.24 %; 0.40 %), ash (12.40 %; 10.40 %), moisture (6.00 %;6.00 %), lipids (6.00 %;6.00 %), and fiber (8.70 %; 6.45 %), which was in line with the works of Essien et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], Khan et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], and Deka et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Although the amount of protein extracted by the two solvents did not differ in this study, previous reports have shown that the type of solvent used in the extraction, temperature, pH, duration of extraction, and the presence of interfering materials can affect the extraction process [
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The results of this study revealed variable antimicrobial effects of the protein extracts on the selected organisms confirming the works of Tehrani et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and Kavitha et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] which recorded that Tris buffer and ultrasonic-assisted protein extracts of 
 <italic>Agaricus</italic> mushroom were active against 
 <italic>S. aureus, B. substilli, P. aeruginosa, K. pneumonia,</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>. However, in the work of Zheng et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], the mushroom protein extracts were not active against 
 <italic>Pseudomonas batatae, Erwinia herbicola, E. coli,</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. In another study by Afzal et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], the antimicrobial ability of protein extracts from six medicinal plants (
 <italic>Feniculum vulgare</italic>, 
 <italic>Pegnanum hermala</italic>, 
 <italic>Azadirachata indica</italic>, 
 <italic>Ocimum basilicum, Cichorium intybus,</italic> and 
 <italic>Ricinus communis</italic>) was reported against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> 6736152. Irrespective of the fact that the Tris buffer and warm water protein extracts had no antifungal effects on the 
 <italic>T. mentagrophytes</italic>, 
 <italic>M. gypseum</italic>, and 
 <italic>M. ferugineum,</italic> they showed slight activity against 
 <italic>C. albicans,</italic> and 
 <italic>T. schoenleinii.</italic> These weak antifungal effects were in line with the study by Appiah et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], who reported that methanol extracts of 
 <italic>Trametes elegans</italic>, 
 <italic>Trametes gibbosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Volvariella volvacea,</italic> and 
 <italic>Schizophyllum commune</italic> mushroomsdid not affect 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Aspergillus tamarii</italic>. It appears that the antibacterial properties of mushrooms are stronger than their antifungal properties. The Tris buffer and warm water protein extracts of 
 <italic>A. auricula-judea</italic> indicated activity against all the bacteria isolates, 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, and 
 <italic>T. schoenleinii</italic> with a MIC of 5 μg/mL except for 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, whose, MIC was 2.5 μg/mL. There was no significant difference between the effects of the extracts on Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria, while previous studies reported that mushroom extracts have more antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive bacteria in comparison to Gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. It seems that some fungi have genes that can secrete peptides and proteins with antibiotic-like properties that can eradicate the both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In the current research, the diameter of inhibition zone of studied protein extracts against the tested pathogens was lower than the ciprofloxacin and fluconazole antibiotics, while in a study by Al Akeel et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], the results have revealed a very robust effect of 
 <italic>A. ascolinicum</italic> medicinal plant against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Proteus vulgaris</italic> with an inhibition zone of 17 mm, which was more than the control antibiotic chloramphenicol (25 μg) with a zone of inhibition equal to 8 mm.
</p>
