<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Evidence for the role of these abundant dietary micronutrients in the prevention of degenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s disease or cardiovascular disease is emerging [
 <xref rid="B14-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. For example, various bioactive effects of flavonoids have been investigated, highlighting their anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anti-diabetic, cardioprotective and anti-cancer properties via their action on different enzymes and signaling pathways [
 <xref rid="B18-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Moreover, several studies have shown that dietary polyphenols exert antioxidant activity and display protective effects on erythrocyte oxidative damage and lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-antioxidants-09-00959" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Among the plants selected for this study, some have been described in the literature while others remain poorly documented, in particular because they are rare and endemic. Despite their widespread use in Reunion Island, there is a real lack of information on the chemical composition and biological properties of herbal teas (infusion or decoction) prepared from these medicinal plants. The goal of this study was to explore the polyphenol composition (qualitative and quantitative) of eight different Reunion Island medicinal plants and to assess their antioxidant capacity according to their preparation mode (polyphenol rich extract, infusion or decoction) by different approaches in vitro and in cell culture. 
</p>
