<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Republic of Cuba is an archipelago with more than 1600 islands, islets and cays. Its territorial extension amounts to 109,880 km
 <sup>2</sup> (FAO, 2015). Around 20,800 terrestrial species have been identified, of which 8948 (43%) are endemics [
 <xref rid="B38-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Cuba is recognized as the island with the highest degree of endemism in the West-Indies, including more than half of its plant species [
 <xref rid="B40-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Islands in general contain a higher degree of endemism compared to the mainland, but threats such as land cover loss, human activities and insufficient protection measures should be considered in time [
 <xref rid="B41-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In a recent study, about 67% of native taxa were evaluated and about half of them are now categorized as threatened. Alarmingly, about 65% of these threatened species are considered endemic [
 <xref rid="B42-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The variety of different habitats and especially soils in Cuba might have enhanced speciation processes that occurred in relatively extreme conditions [
 <xref rid="B43-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. For example, speciation on (1) soils derived from serpentinized ultramafic rocks that are rich in magnesium and heavy metals, but poor in calcium and with high pH values [
 <xref rid="B45-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; (2) soils originating from rocks rich in quartz (quartz-alitic) and sand, which are poor in nutrients (in the case of the so-called white sands, markedly oligotrophic), have low water retention capacity and a rather acidic pH [
 <xref rid="B46-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]; and (3) soils where bare karst more or less predominates, which is the case for the more recently emerged arid coasts and elevations with advanced carsification processes, especially mountains with a mogotiform appearance [
 <xref rid="B47-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
