<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7804141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">79896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-79896-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>UV-C mediated accumulation of pharmacologically significant phytochemicals under light regimes in in vitro culture of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> (L.)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>Bilal Haider</given-names></name><address><email>bhabbasi@qau.edu.pk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Taimoor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khurshid</surname><given-names>Razia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nadeem</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Drouet</surname><given-names>Samantha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Hano</surname><given-names>Christophe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412621.2</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2215 1297</institution-id><institution>Department of Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Quaid-i-Azam University, </institution></institution-wrap>Islamabad, 45320 Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.112485.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0217 6921</institution-id><institution>Laboratoire de Biologie des Ligneux et des Grandes Cultures (LBLGC), INRA USC1328, </institution><institution>Universit&#x000e9; &#x0010f; Orl&#x000e9;ans, </institution></institution-wrap>45067 Orl&#x000e9;ans Cedex 2, France </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>679</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><italic>Fagonia indica</italic> (L.) is an important medicinal plant with multitude of therapeutic potentials. Such application has been attributed to the presence of various pharmacological important phytochemicals. However, the inadequate biosynthesis of such metabolites in intact plants has hampered scalable production. Thus, herein, we have established an in vitro based elicitation strategy to enhance such metabolites in callus culture of <italic>F. indica</italic>. Cultures were exposed to various doses of UV radiation (UV-C) and grown in different photoperiod regimes and their impact was evaluated on biomass accumulation, biosynthesis of phytochemicals along antioxidant expression. Cultures grown under photoperiod (16L/8D h) after exposure to UV-C (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) accumulated optimal biomass (438.3&#x000a0;g/L FW; 16.4&#x000a0;g/L DW), phenolics contents (TPC: 11.8 &#x003bc;gGAE/mg) and flavonoids contents (TFC: 4.05 &#x003bc;gQE/mg). Similarly, HPLC quantification revealed that total production (6.967&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) of phytochemicals wherein kaempferol (1.377&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), apigenin (1.057&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), myricetin (1.022&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) and isorhamnetin (1.022&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) were recorded highly accumulated compounds in cultures at UV-C (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) dose than other UV-C radiations and light regimes.. The antioxidants activities examined as DPPH (92.8%), FRAP (182.3&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M TEAC) and ABTS (489.1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M TEAC) were also recorded highly expressed by cultures under photoperiod after treatment with UV-C dose 5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>. Moreover, same cultures also expressed maximum % inhibition towards phospholipase A2 (sPLA2: 35.8%), lipoxygenase (15-LOX: 43.3%) and cyclooxygenases (COX-1: 55.3% and COX-2: 39.9%) with 1.0-, 1.3-, 1.3- and 2.8-fold increased levels as compared with control, respectively. Hence, findings suggest that light and UV can synergistically improve the metabolism of <italic>F. indica</italic> and could be used to produce such valuable metabolites on commercial scale.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biochemistry</kwd><kwd>Biotechnology</kwd><kwd>Plant sciences</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Plants have been conceded as enriched reservoir of pharmaceutically vital products due to wide spectrum of health attributes<bold>.</bold> Employing latest technological approaches, the focus of pharmaceutical industries is diverting towards specific compounds having respective metabolic role<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> (L.) is a remarkable pharmaceutical specie, belongs to the genus &#x0201c;<italic>Fagonia</italic>&#x0201d; and commonly known as &#x0201c;sacchi booti&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. This genus was named after Guy-Crescent Fagon, botanist and first physician to the French King Louis XIV (1638&#x02013;1718). The species included in the genus <italic>Fagonia</italic> other than <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> are <italic>Fagonia cretica, Fagonia olivieri</italic> and <italic>Fagonia Arabica</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> is restricted to warm and arid zones of the world and can be found mostly in arid and semi-arid areas of Pakistan, India and other Asian areas globally<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.
</p><p id="Par3"><italic>Fagonia</italic> species have been reported for having antibacterial and antifungal potential as well<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. <italic>F. indica</italic> is being used traditionally for decades to treat asthma, dysentery, fever, urinary discharge, vomiting, leucoderma, typhoid while plant ash is used to treat anemia in children. The species has been cited as potential plant carrying great capacity to cure breast cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">The pharmacological features of <italic>F. indica</italic> are authorized due to diverse phytochemicals constituents. An estimated range of compounds isolated and classified by employing this plant include phenolics, alkaloids, saponins, flavonoids, terpenoids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The most widely occurring phytochemicals derived by secondary metabolism are phenolics, produced via phenylpropanoid pathway, pentose-phosphate pathway and shikimate pathway in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Flavonoids comprise the biggest class of polyphenols in plants <italic>i.e.</italic> more than 8,000 were reported and the list is continuously expanding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Phenolic compounds play vital aspects of developmental metabolism in plants, protection from harmful and pathogenic agents<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The above mentioned compounds are broadly distributed in plants; exist in specified organs, specific plants or distinct growth stages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. As phytomedicines; these compounds are significant and employed as antidiabetic, anti-inflammatory, anti-allergenic, hepatoprotective, antioxidant, antiatherogenic, anticancer, antimicrobial, vasodilatory agents, cardio-protective and antithrombotic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">However, <italic>its</italic> medicinal preparations are formulated using plants collected from the wild; therefore, unrelated materials can be present in these commercial preparations. Recent innovative approaches based on tissue culture technology are alternatives for efficient production of phytochemicals instead of utilizing whole plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The concentrated production of metabolites has been praised broadly in literature via tissue culture techniques<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Being totipotent, almost each cell in the in vitro culture possesses whole genetic material and has the capacity for production of range of compounds than parental plants. Therefore, emerging trends of biotechnology and genetics mainly has emphasized to adopt in vitro culture techniques broadly in breeding and genetics, as model systems for plant pathology, physiology, biochemistry as well as biosynthesis medicinally vital secondary metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. So, this technology is a substitute to synthesize the phytochemicals that are either sometimes difficult to obtain or expensive in terms of processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. However, the lower contents, large fluctuations and inadequate processes are the key challenges associated with sustainable production from plants when utilizing in vitro culture technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">By employing the defense behavior of plants to stress, the innovative approaches towards the pharmaceutical vital plants production can be possibly established by optimizing conditions.</p><p id="Par7">Elicitation is provoking such behavior of plants by induction of chemical defense as stress response; various types of physiological and molecular factors exist as elicitors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. They are basically classified into two groups as Biotic and Abiotic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Elicitation is one among most widely used and cost effective approach for induction and to maximize the productivity of secondary metabolites by reducing time period as well as high yield in low volume of cultures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. However, the type, dose level and specificity of an elicitor along cultural conditions possess significant role in influencing elicitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">Among different approaches, the application of ultraviolet (UV) light as elicitor got more attention due to its tremendous effects on phytochemicals in several medicinal plant cultures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. The most effective type of UV irradiations proven yet in raising the plant metabolites production is UV-C (190&#x02013;280&#x000a0;nm), employed in different vegetables, medicinal plants and fruits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Mechanistically, the stress raised by UV light activates defense system in plants along producing phytoalexin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. The production of these compounds raise plant factories as more defensive responses including antioxidative enzymes, secondary metabolites and cell wall modifications, that cope the oxidative damage prompted by UV, through scavenging lethal reactive oxygen species (ROS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Other positive impacts include detained chlorophyll degradation, combating pathogens, and effects on nutritional features deeply studied by Shama and Alderson<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and Turtoi<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Alongside, recent developmental approach includes combinatorial use of elicitors for more efficient procedures and raised production of biomass. The application of different light regimes and UV-C has been proved to synergistically enhance production of ligans and neolignas in in vitro culture of <italic>L. usitassium</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, and UV-C melatonin reported with significant effects by Nazir et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. For instance, the impacts of UV-C radiation along melatonin also affirmed on biosynthesis of anti-diabetic phytochemicals and antioxidants in in vitro cultures of <italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> L by Ullah et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par9">Considering the stimulatory aspects of light elicitation and medicinal potential of <italic>F. indica,</italic> its derived in vitro cultures need to be more explored and further optimize its biomass assemblies and phytochemicals production. For this purpose, we have previously established protocol for biomass accumulation and pharmaceutically significant metabolites in callus cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic> applying elicitors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In this sense, although the interest of these approaches is no longer to be demonstrated, our fundamental knowledge regarding production of <italic>F. indica</italic> biomass and phytochemicals under UV-C and different photoperiod regimes is missing. Currently, no previous report exists on elicitation by UV-C radiations for this species. Therefore, the current study aims to figure out the influence of UV-C radiations under various photoperiod regimes over biomass and phytochemicals accumulation in callus cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic>. Further, to assess the antioxidative profile via different in vitro cell free assays (DPPH, FRAP, ABTS) under UV-C stress and evaluate the biosynthesis of these compounds through HPLC. Moreover, to investigate the anti-inflammatory activities including sPLA2, 15-LOX, COX-1 and COX-2 in extracts derived from cultures exposed to UV-C and light regimes. So, this is the first study to show the interactive influence of light regimes and UV-C radiations on the accumulation of pharmacologically significant phytochemicals in in vitro culture of <italic>F. indica</italic> (L.).</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Combined effects of ultraviolet-C radiations and light regimes on biomass accumulation</title><p id="Par10">Light possess significant role in growth and development of plants. The application of different light sources as eliciting phytochemicals in pharmaceutical plants is getting deep attention. UV-C irradiation is one of them that play role in switching control expression of genes associated with growth and secondary metabolism of cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The current study involves the interactive influence of Ultraviolet-C radiation and different light regimes on callus cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic>. The results indicated optimal biomass accumulation (FW: 438.3&#x000a0;g/L; DW: 16.4&#x000a0;g/L) in cultures exposed to UV-C radiation (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 30&#x000a0;min under photoperiod (16L/8D h) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). This was followed by cultures grown under continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) with maximum biomass (FW: 345.9&#x000a0;g/L; DW: 13.9&#x000a0;g/L) at respective dose (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiation for 40&#x000a0;min and biomass accumulation (FW: 227.2&#x000a0;g/L; DW: 9.43&#x000a0;g/L) in dark after 20&#x000a0;min exposure to UV radiation (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) as compared with controls respectively [Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b, c].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Accumulation of Biomass in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> under photoperiod (16L/8D h) after eliciting with various treatments (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiations. (<bold>b</bold>) Accumulation of biomass in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> under contineous light (24&#x000a0;h) after eliciting with various treatments of UV-C radiations. (<bold>c</bold>) Accumulation of biomass in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> under complete dark (24&#x000a0;h) after eliciting with various treatments (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiations. Values represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates. Different (black for FW, red for DW) letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">The UV-C radiations with growth proliferating effects have been reported for in vitro cultures of many medicinal plants previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The findings of current study show highest biomass accumulation among in vitro cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic> elicited previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Usually, a specified span of light is absorbed by photoreceptors in plants that are entailed in certain pathways of developmental processes. For instance, light act significantly in phytochrome diversions into far-red (active prf) and sustain genes expressions, resulting in raised cell division and metabolic activities as photo-response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. The higher biomass accumulation could also be resulted by induction of mutations in plant cells by UV-C light<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> Furthermore; the photoperiod is an influencing factor responsible for growth and developmental processes in plants. Numerous studies revealed the predominant effects of light duration in regulating plant growth and levels of its significant metabolites in many plant species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Carvalho et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>; showed a dramatic increase growth and contents in <italic>I. batatas</italic> leaves by light irradiation for 16&#x000a0;h as compared to light exposure for short time.</p><p id="Par12">Overall, the UV-C treatments for 20&#x02013;40&#x000a0;min (1.2&#x02013;7.2&#x000a0;kJ&#x000a0;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) enhanced the callus proliferation but for extended duration of UV-C doses inhibited the cells growth under different photoperiod regimes.. The reduction in biomass accumulation at higher UV-C treatments could be the result of irreversible toxic effects to cells that might raise cell death in plant cultures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> and inducement of oxidative stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In addition, high light stress for extended hours induces photo-inhibition of photosynthetic system in plants. The resulting outcomes of extreme light exposures have previously mentioned by Kok<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> and Lichtenthaler et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, those include imbalance in photosynthetic O<sub>2</sub> and CO<sub>2</sub> fixation, inhibition of chloroplasts and loosed fluorescence at PS II. Usually, photo inhibition occurs mostly by multifactorial light stress; distracting the QB proteins that is responsible for catalysis of QA (primary quencher) into heavy PQ assembly via electron transfer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the decreased phenolics and flavonoids in cultures in continuous dark could also be due to degradation of chlorophyll contents resulting in reduced photosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par13">Likewise, decreased cell growth and biomass proliferation in <italic>Lepedium satvium</italic> cultures under UV-C exposure for extended periods has been reported by Ullah et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Our findings can be further elaborated and verified by several tissue cultures studies of pharmaceutical plants under UV-C exposure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">Morphologically, all the cultures were found compact while calli under photoperiod (16L/8D h) were observed green, dark green under Cont. Light (24&#x000a0;h) and yellow-white in Dark (24&#x000a0;h) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Naturally, the photosynthetic machinery in plants is adapted with a specific light/dark period. The extended dark phase is undoubtedly a significant stress factor for both the whole plant and photosynthetic system, resulting in reduced photosynthesis. For instance, prolonged dark period if continuously applied decrease the chlorophyll contents. Moreover, the possible reason could also be the senescence induced by both elicitors induced stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Combinatorial effects of UV-C treatments (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) on morphology of callu cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic> grown for 30&#x000a0;days under light regimes; (<bold>a</bold>) P1&#x02013;P2 stands for UV-C treated cultures in photoperiod (16L/8D h), (<bold>b</bold>) C1&#x02013;C7 represents UV-C elicited cultures in cont. light (24&#x000a0;h) and (<bold>c</bold>) D1&#x02013;D2 shows UV-C mediated cultures in complete dark (24&#x000a0;h).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">The effects of UV-C may vary with the variations in dose, plant cells sensitivity and ability to vitiate the UV-C influence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Contrarily, Khan et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> has reported maximum production of biomass in in vitro cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic> and in in vitro culture of <italic>Linum usitatissimum</italic> (L.) by Anjum, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Effects of UV-C radiations and various light regimes on total phenolic and total flavonoids accumulation</title><p id="Par16">Generally, plants receive various kinds of UV radiations that trigger diverse signal transduction pathways. This induces effects on secondary metabolism of plant species and eventually results in accumulation of distinct levels of plants metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. In this study, the UV-C radiation and different photoperiod regimes were found with astonishing effects over biosynthesis of phenolic compounds in callus culture of <italic>F. indica</italic>. The cultures maintained under UV treatment associated with a photoperiod regime showed enhanced levels of total phenolics and total flavonoids contents than respective controls. However, the results indicated that optimum accumulation of phenolics (total phenolics contents (TPC): 11.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g GAE/mg DW, total phenolics production (TPP): 488.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g GAE/mg DW) was found in cultures under photoperiod (16L/8D h) at UV-C dose (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). This was followed by culture grown under continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) with the maximum levels of total phenolic contents (TPC: 10.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g GAE/mg DW; TPP: 378.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g GAE/mg DW) at UV-C dose (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) in comparison to control [Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b]. Likewise, maximum production of total phenolics (TPC: 10.08&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g GAE/mg DW; TPP: 237.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g GAE/mg DW) was found in cultures in dark conditions at UV dose of 3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Determination of Phenolic Contents in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with various treatments (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) UV-C radiations and grown in Photoperiod (16L/8D h). (<bold>b</bold>) Determination of Phenolic Contents in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with various treatments (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiationsand grown in contineous light (24&#x000a0;h). (<bold>c</bold>) Determination of phenolic contents in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with various treatments (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiationsand grown in complete darkness (24&#x000a0;h). Values represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates. Different (black for TPC, red for TPP) letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">Many studies exist about prompting effects of UV-C radiation over plant secondary metabolism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. The enhanced accumulation of flavonoids and phenolics under hermetic UV-C doses has been reported earlier in vegetables, fruits and other plant species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. However, the effect on secondary metabolites production in response to light exposure clearly depends not only on the considered species but also genetic variations among species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par18">Although, earlier investigations reported about the signals transduction under UV irradiations, the exact mechanism of action behind UV-C effects is not properly known<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. In the literature we can find some mechanistic opinions about influence of UV-C radiation over induction and enhancement of secondary metabolism of plants. Some studies indicate that a stimulation of the secondary metabolism under UV-C treatment can be triggered through the activation of key enzymes such as <sc>l</sc>-phenylalanine ammonia-lyase (PAL) and chalcone synthase (CHS). Such enzymes are responsible for catalyzing the main steps during biosynthetic pathways of many phenolics and flavonoids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">Similar patterns were observed for total flavonoids contents and flavonoid production maintained under UV-C treatment associated with photoperiod regimes. The callus cultures maintained in photoperiod (16L/8D h) after UV-C (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) treatment were found with optimum levels of flavonoids (total flavonoids contents (TFC): 4.05&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g quercetin equivalent (QE)/mg DW; total flavonoids production (TFP): 166.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g QE/mg DW), followed by UV-C treatment (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 40&#x000a0;min in continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) with maximum flavonoids accumulation (TFC: 2.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g QE/mg DW; TFP: 65.09&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g QE/mg DW) respectively with comparative controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, b). However, the cultures grown in dark were found with low induction comparatively and maximum flavonoids accumulation (TFC: 0.96&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g QE/mg; TFP: 33.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g QE/mg DW) after exposure to UV dose (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) as compared with control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Determination of flavonoids contents in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with different doses (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiations and photoperiod (16L/8D h). (<bold>b</bold>) Determination of flavonoids contents in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with different doses (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiations and contineous light (24&#x000a0;h). (<bold>c</bold>) Determination of flavonoids contents in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with different doses (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) of UV-C radiations under complete dark (24&#x000a0;h). Values represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates. Different (black for TFC, red for TFP) letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Flavonoids for considerable UV screening potential, the UV-C elicitation deeply enhance the flavonoids accumulation in response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Notably, the flavonoids among all polyphenolics, play dominant role in plants defense against photodamages because of their considerable UV screening and antioxidant features<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. Urban et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> reported that UV-C irradiations almost induce and raise flavonoids biosynthesis among all phenolic compounds. Moreover, Tiecher et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> found about the up regulation of CHS (chalcone synthase) and FLS (flavonol synthase) by UV-C radiation as key factors for flavonoid production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. The reduced levels of phenolics and flavonoids accumulation occurred at higher concentrations and fluctuating light exposures. The underlying mechanistic reasons include high levels of ROS generation, biological membranes disruption, photo inhibition, impairments in lipid metabolism, DNA damages and photosystem II destruction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par21">However, influencing the biosynthesis of plants metabolites via UV-C treatment depends over elicitation levels as well, and increased levels can cause cells death in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>. The same findings reported by Moon et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup> in in vitro cultures of <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.), where UV-C radiations enhance phenolics and flavonoids accumulation. Recently, comparative results on synergistic effects of UV-C and other elicitors have also been reported by Khan et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, Nazir et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> and Ullah et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>HPLC based quantification of phenolics and flavonoids</title><p id="Par22">In this report, based on our previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, a total eleven important phenolic metabolites have been evaluated in UV-C irradiated cultures under different photoperiod regimes via high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). The HPLC evaluation showed that the highest accumulation of compounds (6.067&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03) occurred in cultures grown in photoperiod (16L/8D h) after exposure to UV-C dose of 5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>. The cultures treated with UV-C radiations (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 40&#x000a0;min were found with total production of compounds (4.624&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05) under continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) while least production (4.39&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.015) was found in cultures maintained in dark (24&#x000a0;h) after UV-C treatment (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) as compared with control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Productivity of 11 different phenolic compounds quantified via HPLC, in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> after elicitation with UV-C radiations (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and maintained in different light regimes; cont. light (24&#x000a0;h), dark (24&#x000a0;h) and photoperiod (PHP, 16L/8D h). Values represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates. Different (black for UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;PHP, red for UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;cont light, green for UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;dark) letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">UV-C irradiations have exerting damaging effects over plants including direct destruction of Plastoquinone (PQ) in chloroplast, disturbing activities in Mitochondria, DNA integrity and production of ROS and Peroxyl radicals formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. A broad range of phenolics and flavonoids play role in reducing the photodamage by UV-C radiations due to screening of UV and antioxidative features<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>. Moreover, it is reported previously that the UV induces up regulation of CHS and FLS enzymes, activation of phytoalexins and several genes, decoding enzymes for biosynthesis of phenolics including PAL, CHS, anthocyanidin synthase (ANS) and stilbene synthase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par24">The raised aggregation of compounds was noticed in cultures stressed with Ultraviolet-C treatments and various light regimes as compared with control (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Maximum levels of kaempferol (1.377&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), apigenin (1.057&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), myricetin (1.022&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) and isorhamnetin (1.022&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), followed by ursolic acid (0.235&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), nahagenin (0.226&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), hederagenin (0.207&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) and caffeic acid (0.175&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) were found in cultures prone to UV-C treatment (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) subsequently maintained under photoperiod (16L/8D h) as compared with control. Likewise, the accumulation of gallic acid observed was (0.281&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW), followed by betulinic acid (0.495&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) in cultures mediated with UV-C dose of 7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup> under continuous light. Furthermore, the Catechins biosynthesis was recorded with optimum level (1.032&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mg DW) in cultures at UV-C dose of 3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup> under dark conditions.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>HPLC based quantification of polyphenolic compounds in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with UV-C doses (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) under different photoperiod regimes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Gallic acid</th><th align="left">Caffeic Acid</th><th align="left">Myricetin</th><th align="left">Catechin</th><th align="left">Kaempferol</th><th align="left">Isorhamnetin</th><th align="left">Apigenin</th><th align="left">Nahagenin</th><th align="left">Hederagenin</th><th align="left">Ursolic Acid</th><th align="left">Betulinic Acid</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><bold>UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;photoperiod (16L/8D h)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 f</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002&#x000a0;l</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (9.0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 d</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002&#x000a0;g</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV 3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.92&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 ef</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (1.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003&#x000a0;m</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003&#x000a0;k</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;k</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01gh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003&#x000a0;l</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;k</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 hi</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 j</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><bold>UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;cont. light (24&#x000a0;h)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.88&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;k</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (9.0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 hi</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 i</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 ab</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV 5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.009 def</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 gh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.20&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (1.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;l</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;k</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;l</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 hi</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 ij</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><bold>UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;dark (24&#x000a0;h)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;l</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (9.0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.64&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 gh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 de</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 de</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;k</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 gh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 gh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;fg</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.63&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 fgh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.009 ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 fgh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">1.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03 bc</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.36&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (1.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.61&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03 cdef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 gh</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02 ef</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006&#x000a0;fg</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008&#x000a0;k</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 jk</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02&#x000a0;cd</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.03&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.01 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">0.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.05&#x000a0;cd</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are the mean of three triplicates&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error (SE). Different letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par25">The usual hypothesis regarding UV-C radiations is same as other elicitors, raising the oxidative stress through the production of ROS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>. ROS could have negative effects over cell components, only if not eliminated efficiently and accumulated. Prior to damage, the ROS play signaling role in networking physiological processes based on their redox status. The ROS engaged in induction and regulation of metabolic pathways affiliated secondary compounds biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par26">However, elicitation with UV-C radiation in various species usually occurred in PAL enzyme up-regulation during phenylpropanoid biosynthetic pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Overall, our findings provide best feasible approach for optimum production of polyphenolics in UV-C elicited callus cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic> on both pilot and commercial scales. However, more studies would be needed to completely know biochemical and molecular mechanisms of production of these valuable phytochemicals under UV-C and light regimes treatments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Evaluation of antioxidants activity profile of <italic>F. indica</italic> callus cultures under UV-C radiations and photoperiod regimes</title><p id="Par27">The callus cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic> irradiated by UV-C treatments under various photoperiod regimes were assessed for Antioxidant activity by employing DPPH, FRAP and ABTS assays. The DPPH assay is an extensively adopted technique to evaluate the antioxidant capacity of plant cells-derived products by considerable sensitivity, modest clarity and economic feasibility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>. The results indicated; the optimum DPPH activity (92.8%) was recorded in UV-C (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) mediated cultures maintained in photoperiod (16L/8D h) and DPPH activity (92.4%) in cultures elicited with UV-C (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 40&#x000a0;min and grown in Continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) [Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>]. The least DPPH activity (90.24%) was found in cultures exposed to UV-C dose of 3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup> for 20&#x000a0;min and developed in dark conditions (24&#x000a0;h). Recently, Khan et al. reported the same correlation and phenolics based increase in DPPH activity in cell cultures of <italic>F. indica</italic> under continuous light<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In compliance with our findings, Erkan et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup> and Li et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> have published a phenolic-dependent free radical scavenging activity (FRSA) after exposing the cultures of <italic>Fragaria x ananassava</italic> (Duchesne) to UV-C. The results conclusively show that rise in FRSA activity under UV-C treatments is because of enhanced accumulation of secondary phytochemicals as free radical scavengers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Free radical scavenging activity of UV-C radiations (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) mediated callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> grown in different light regimes [cont. light (24&#x000a0;h), dark (24&#x000a0;h) and photoperiod (PHP, 16L/8D h)]. Values represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates. Different (black for UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;PHP, red for UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;cont light, green for UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;dark) letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">Likewise, the data showed that enhanced levels of FRAP and ABTS antioxidants activities were found in elicited cultures with UV-C radiations than controls (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Among different doses of UV-C radiations, the maximum FRAP antioxidant activity (182.32&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol Trolox-C equivalent antioxidant capacity (TEAC)/ mg DW) was recorded at UV-C dose of 5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup> applied to callus subsequently grown in photoperiod (16L/8D h), while cultures under continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) were found with FRAP activity (174.31&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol TEAC/ mg DW) after exposure to UV-C (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 20 mints. The cultures maintained in dark (24&#x000a0;h) after treating with UV-C doses showed the FRAP activity (194.27&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol TEAC/ mg DW) at UV-C (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/ms<sup>2</sup>) as compared with control.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Antioxidants potential activities of callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with UV-C radiations (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and grown in different photoperiod regimes using FRAP and ABTS cell free in vitro assays. Antioxidant capacity of samples was expressed in terms of TEAC (Trolox C equivalent antioxidant capacity) per mg of DW.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">FRAP</th><th align="left">ABTS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;photoperiod (16L/8D h)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">162.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">390.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1&#x000a0;h</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (9.0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">168.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">474.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">177.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 c</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">478.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">182.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">489.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV 3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">179.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1 b</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">466.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (1.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">152.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">425.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 f.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">168.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">412.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x000a0;g</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;cont. light (24&#x000a0;h)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">158.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">456.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 d</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (9.0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">160.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">472.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 bc</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">168.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 e</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">486.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV 5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">155.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">418.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1 f.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">174.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 d</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">439.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (1.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">135.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 i</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">304.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3&#x000a0;l</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">162.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 f.</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">384.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8 i</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold>UV&#x02009;+&#x02009;Dark (24&#x000a0;h)</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">120.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3&#x000a0;k</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">380.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4 i</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (9.0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">125.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">469.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">194.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 a</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">444.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">126.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 j</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">397.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x000a0;h</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">149.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;g</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">442.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9 e</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UV (1.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">109.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x000a0;l</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">358.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2 j</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">141.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x000a0;h</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">341.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;k</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are the mean of three triplicates&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error (SE). Different letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par29">Similarly, the trend was also noted down in ABTS activity. The data showed that maximum activity (489.11&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol TAEC mg /DW) was recorded in calli mediated with UV-C dose (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and grown in photoperiod (16L/8D h) while cultures grown in continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) after 20 mints of exposure to UV-C radiations (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) were found to enhance the ABTS activity up to (486.05&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol TAEC mg /DW). However, the callus cultures under Dark (24&#x000a0;h) showed maximum activity (468.97&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol TAEC mg /DW) after UV-C dose (9.0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) as compared with control.</p><p id="Par30">A relationship can be established among antioxidants activities with production of biomass and phenolic contents in cultures exposed to UV-C radiations and maintained in various photoperiod regimes. The raised accumulation of phenolics and flavonoids could be the possible cause for raised antioxidant activities of grown calli under photoperiod at UV-C dose (30&#x000a0;min). Here, the highest significant correlation was obtained for myricetin and ABTS assay (Pearson Coefficient Correlation (PCC)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.935, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>) (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Flavanoids were all significantly correlated with this antioxidant assay (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The same correlation between phytochemicals and antioxidants potential has been stated previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Effects of UV-C radiations and Light regimes on Anti-inflammatory activities of <italic>F. indica</italic> callus cultures</title><p id="Par31">Plant metabolites possess efficient enzyme inhibition feature that set off inflammatory activity in the body<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref></sup>. Inflammation happens as defense response against harmed cells, pathogens or any stimuli<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref></sup>. According various mechanisms reported for anti-inflammatory action such as inhibition of lipoxygenase (15-LOX, eicosanoid generating enzymes), cyclooxygenases (COX-1 and COX-2) and phospholipase A2 (sPLA2), dwindle the concentrations of prostanoid and leukotrienes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref></sup>. The underlying phytochemistry behind strong antioxidant profile of <italic>F. indica</italic> explicates its anti-inflammatory features. Therefore, the current study also investigated the anti-inflammatory potential of <italic>F. indica</italic> callus cultures exposed to UV-C radiations and light regimes using in vitro cell free assays.</p><p id="Par32">Optimum % inhibition (sPLA2: 35.8%), 15-LOX: 43.3%), (COX-1:55.3%), and (COX-2: 39.9%) was found in cultures exposed to UV-C dose (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and grown under (16L/8D h) photoperiod as compared with control respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). Whereas, the cultures treated with UV-C radiation (7.2&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and maintained under continuous light (24&#x000a0;h) expressed maximum inhibitory activities towards sPLA2 (28.1%), 15-LOX (36.4%), COX-1 (49.5%) and COX-2 (29.8%) as compared with control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b). For instance, optimum levels of sPLA2 (30.5%), 15-LOX (40.1%), COX-1 (53.4%), and COX-2 (37.5%) activities were recorded in cultures elicited with UV-C dose (3.6&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 20&#x000a0;min and grown in dark conditions (24&#x000a0;h) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c). The highest significant correlation was obtained for kaempferol and isorhamnetin (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Here, with the exception of apigenin and ursolic acid, all analyzed phytochemicals were significantly associated with potential anti-inflammatory action (Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). It is the first report on documenting the anti-inflammatory activities of <italic>F. indica</italic> cultures treated with UV-C radiations and light regimes. Despite, the <italic>F. indica</italic> has previously been exploited for its anti-inflammatory potential and analgesics in mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Anti-inflammatory activities of callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with UV-C radiations (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and grown in photoperiod (16L/8D h) using sPLA2, 15-LOX, COX-1 and COX-2 cell free in vitro assays. The activities of extracts were expressed as % inhibition. (<bold>b</bold>) Anti-inflammatory activities of callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with UV-C radiations (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and grown in cont. light (24&#x000a0;h) using sPLA2, 15-LOX, COX-1 and COX-2 cell free in vitro assays. The activities of extracts were expressed as % inhibition. (<bold>c</bold>) Anti-inflammatory activities of callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> elicited with UV-C radiations (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and grown in complete dark (24&#x000a0;h) using sPLA2, 15-LOX, COX-1 and COX-2 cell free in vitro assays. The activities of extracts were expressed as % inhibition. Employed under the same experimental conditions as sample extracts, reference inhibitors were used as positive controls: Ibuprofen (10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M) was used as positive control for COX-1 and COX-2 activity leading to enzyme inhibition of 31.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8% and 29.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2%, respectively; Thioetheramide-PC (5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M) was used as sPLA2 inhibitor, resulting in an inhibition of 43.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8%; Nordihydroguaiaretic acid (100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M) was used as 15-LOX inhibitor, leading to an inhibition of 30.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7%. The same volume of extraction solvent was used as blank. Values represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three replicates. Different letters represent significant differences between the various experimental conditions (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par33">COXs are cyclooxygenases that are responsible for maintaining homeostasis in the kidney, produced during cancer and other inflammations. They are extensively used to study anti-inflammatory potentials of plant extracts because plants have natural phytochemical inhibition mechanisms that inhibit them<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref></sup>. The compounds detected possess strong anti-inflammatory potentials<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par34">Conclusively, the current study involved the elicitation strategy via UV-C radiations under different photoperiod regimes in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> (L.). The UV-C treatments effectively raised the production of phenolic compounds and biomass proliferation. The cultures exposed to UV-C radiations (5.4&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 30&#x000a0;min and grown under photoperiod (16&#x000a0;h light /8&#x000a0;h dark) were found worthwhile sources of phytochemicals and biomass production. The highest levels of phytochemicals, anti-inflammatory and antioxidants activities were recorded on the same treatment of UV-C under photoperiod. Our data provide evidences showing that elicitation of <italic>F. indica</italic> callus cultures with UV-C radiation is a viable strategy for a safe, sustainable and enhanced production of biomass and phytochemicals. We anticipate that scale up studies at both pilot and commercial scales could confirm these trends. This will definitely assist with decoding the molecular mechanisms behind maximum expression of genes responsible for growth and phytochemicals production.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>In vitro seeds germination</title><p id="Par35">The seeds of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> (L.), were identified by a taxonomist at Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad. Seeds were sterilized and inoculated on MS-0 media according to the protocol of Ahmad, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref></sup>. Briefly, the Incubation Dry Separation Floating technique was applied to determine viable seed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref></sup>. Briefly, autoclaved distilled water was used to rinse seeds, followed by treatment with HgCl2 (0.1%) and ethanol (70%) for a period of 2&#x000a0;min for surface sterilization of seeds. In order to remove impurities, seeds were entirely washed 3 times with autoclaved distilled water, followed by surface drying of seeds with autoclaved filter papers. The growth media (MS0; Murashige and Skoog basal medium; Phytotechnology Labs, USA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref></sup> supplemented with sucrose (30&#x000a0;g/L) as carbon source and 8&#x000a0;g/L of agar (Phytotechnology Labs, USA) as solidifying agents was utilized for inoculation of seeds. The media was autoclaved (Systec VX 100, Germany) at 121&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;min after pH calibration (5.5&#x02013;5.7; Eutech Instruments pH 510, Singapore) using NaOH (0.1&#x000a0;N) and HCL (1.0&#x000a0;N) to produce contamination free plantlets. The flasks having seeds inoculated on media were shifted to growth chamber and kept under fixed growth conditions i.e. temperature 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in photoperiod (16/8&#x000a0;h light/dark) and light intensity of 40&#x02013;50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol&#x000a0;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (Philips TLD 35 Florescent lamps).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Establishment and treatment of callus culture with UV-C and light regimes</title><p id="Par36">The 30&#x000a0;days grown in vitro plantlets were used as source of explant. The stem explant (1&#x000a0;cm) was used for maximum callus biomass production as previously optimized by our research group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Briefly, MS media fortified with sucrose (30&#x000a0;g/L), agar (8&#x000a0;g/L) and Thidiazuron (4.4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M) with PH (5.5&#x02013;5.7) was employed for inoculation of explants. The cultures maintained in conditions of (16L/8D hours) light and temperature 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p><p id="Par37">The experiment of UV-C elicitation was performed using 4&#x000a0;weeks grown calli by following the protocol of Anjum et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The UV-C radiations were applied on cultures at distance of 15&#x000a0;cm from Ultraviolet-C lamp (254&#x000a0;nm, Model ZQJ-254, China with value (intensity) of 3&#x000a0;W/m<sup>2</sup>). The experimental Ultraviolet-C treatments (kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) were calculated as;<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{UV-C dose}} = {\text{Intensity of Radiation }}\left( {{\text{W}}/{\text{m}}^{{2}} } \right) \times {\text{Exposure time of Cultures to UV-C}} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>UV-C dose</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Intensity of Radiation</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Exposure time of Cultures to UV-C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par38">Total 6 Ultraviolet-C doses 0, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, and 60&#x000a0;min equivalent to 0, 1.8, 3.6, 5.4, 7.2, 9.0, and 10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup> were used. First, the Ultraviolet-C lamp was made stabilized by leaving it ON for 15&#x000a0;min prior experiment. Then, fresh callus cultures were equally dispersed in sterile petri plates with sterilized forceps, to fully expose and properly irradiate with Ultraviolet-C doses (1.8&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) for 10&#x02013;60&#x000a0;min total duration. The callus cultures (0.5&#x000a0;g) were inoculated back into Erlenmeyer flask (100&#x000a0;ml) having fresh culture media (40&#x000a0;mL) after UV-C exposure. Subsequently, the cultures were moved to growth room (25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and maintained under their relevant sub-experimental conditions i.e.; complete 24&#x000a0;h-dark, 24&#x000a0;h-continuous light and 16L/8D h photoperiod. The light conditions in different light regimes were as; continuous light (24&#x000a0;h light) continuous dark (complete 24&#x000a0;h dark conditions) and photoperiod (16&#x000a0;h light and 8&#x000a0;h complete dark conditions). The cultures in each light regime without UV-C exposure (UV-C 0&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) were used as respective controls. Three biological replicas were used in each sub-experiment for respective UV-C treatment. Finally, after 30&#x000a0;days of growth period, the callus cultures were harvested, followed by investigation of biomass and stored for further analysis. The different experimental steps of whole study are mentioned in a schematic diagram (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Graphical represenation of synergistic effects of UV-C treatments (0&#x02013;10.8&#x000a0;kJ/m<sup>2</sup>) and light regimes (cont. light (24&#x000a0;h) and complete dark (24&#x000a0;h) on callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Determination of biomass and extract preparation</title><p id="Par39">For Fresh weight investigation, the callus cultures were harvested and placed on filter paper to remove leftover water or media. The callus was subsequently weighed to determine Fresh weight biomass whereas for Dry weight calculation, the cultures were oven dried prior weighing.</p><p id="Par40">For phenolic, antioxidants and anti-inflammatory activities determination, the methanolic extracts of cultures were prepared by using the protocol of Ali and Abbasi<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> with little modifications. Briefly, the 10&#x000a0;mL of methanol (99.9%) was used to thoroughly dissolve 200&#x000a0;mg of each powdered callus (dried at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and placed in rotatory for 24&#x000a0;h at room temperature. The reaction mixtures were then sonicated for 25&#x000a0;min (Toshiba, Japan) followed by vortexing for 5&#x000a0;min. The procedure for phytochemicals extraction was repeated twice and mixtures were then centrifuged at 6000&#x000a0;rpm for 15&#x000a0;min. The supernatants were evaporated to dryness before being subjected to cellulase R10 from <italic>Trichoderma reesei</italic> (Sigma Aldrich) digestion for aglycone release in citrate phosphate buffer (pH4.8) using an enzyme concentration of 2 units/mL during 6&#x000a0;h at 40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under agitation (200&#x000a0;rpm) in a water bath.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Determination of phenolic and flavonoids contents</title><p id="Par41">The determinations of total phenolic content (TPC) was performed via utilizing Folin- Ciocalteu (FC) reagent by the modified protocol of Arias, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref></sup>. Briefly, each sample (20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) extracted was mixed with 90&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of the FC reagent in 96 well plate (10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;diluted with distilled water) followed by 5&#x000a0;min incubation at room temperature (25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C). Then, (6%, w/v) sodium carbonate (90&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l) was added to the wells, incubated for 90&#x000a0;min at room temperature. Gallic acid (1&#x000a0;mg/mL) and methanol (20 &#x003bc;L) were used as positive and negative controls respectively. The absorbance was noted at 725&#x000a0;nm with UV&#x02013;Visible spectrophotometer (Shimadzu-1650; Japan). Gallic acid (0&#x02013;40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) was used as standard for plotting calibration curve (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.967) and the TPC was expressed as gallic acid equivalents (GAE)/g of DW. Total phenolic production (TPP) was calculated by using the following formula and expressed in mg gallic acid equivalent/l.<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Total phenolic production mg/L}} = {\text{DW }}\left( {{\text{g}}/{\text{L}}} \right) \times {\text{TPC }}({\text{mg}}/{\text{g}}) $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Total phenolic production mg/L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>DW</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TPC</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>mg</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par42">For total flavonoid content (TFC) determination, the aluminum chloride (AlCl<sub>3</sub>) colorimetric method was used as reported by Xu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> with minor modifications. Briefly, 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of the extracted sample was mixed with 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of potassium acetate (1&#x000a0;M) and 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of AlCl3 (10%, w/v). This mixture was incubated for 30&#x000a0;min at room temperature (25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) after addition of 160&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of distilled water to adjust the total volume to 200&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l. Absorbance of the reaction mixture was measured at 415&#x000a0;nm by using UV&#x02013;Visible spectrophotometer (Shimadzu-1650; Japan). Quercetin (0&#x02013;40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) was used as standard for plotting calibration curve (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.989) and the TFC was expressed as quercetin equivalents (QE)/g of DW. Total flavonoid production (TFP) was calculated by using the following formula and expressed in mg quercetin equivalent/l.<disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Total flavonoid production mg/L}} = {\text{DW }}\left( {{\text{g}}/{\text{L}}} \right) \times {\text{TFC }}({\text{mg}}/{\text{g}}) $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Total flavonoid production mg/L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>DW</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TFC</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>mg</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Determination of antioxidant activities</title><p id="Par43">The UV-C mediated cultured under various photoperiod regimes were analyzed for their respective level of antioxidants activities via DPPH, FRAP and ABTS assays.<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par44">DPPH scavenging activity</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par45">To determine the antioxidant activity, 2, 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radical scavenging assay (FRSA) was performed using the method narrated by Fazal et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> with slight modifications. Briefly, the sample extracts (20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) and 180 &#x003bc;L of DPPH (3.2&#x000a0;mg/100&#x000a0;mL methanol) were mixed in each well of 96 well plates, and then incubated in dark for 1&#x000a0;h at room temperature (25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C). Absorbance of the reaction mixture was measured at wavelength (517&#x000a0;nm) by using UV&#x02013;Visible spectrophotometer (Shimadzu-1650; Japan). The final concentrations of ascorbic acid (10, 05, 40 and 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) and DMSO (20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l) with DPPH (180&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) were loaded as negative control. The radical scavenging activity was calculated as percentage of DPPH discoloration using the following equation;<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ {\text{Free radical scavenging activity }}\% \, = \, 100 \times (1 - {\text{A}}_{{\text{E}}} /{\text{A}}_{{\text{D}}} ), $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Free radical scavenging activity</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>D</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where A<sub>E</sub> is absorbance of the solution when aculture extract was added at a particular concentration and A<sub>D</sub> is the absorbance of the DPPH solution (standard).<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par47">Ferric Reducing Antioxidant Power (FRAP) Assay</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par48">The FRAP potential of cultures was determined via method of Benzie and Strain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref></sup> with little modifications. Shortly, 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of extracted samples and FRAP solution (190&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) were mixed [composed of acetate buffer (300&#x000a0;mM, pH 3.6); FeCl 3.6H<sub>2</sub>O (20&#x000a0;mM) and TPTZ (10&#x000a0;mM); ratio 10:1:1 (v/v/v)]. Then the reaction mixtures were stored at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min. Absorbance was recorded at wavelength (630&#x000a0;nm) using Microplate Reader (BioTek ELX800, Bio-Tek Instruments). Antioxidant capacity of samples was expressed in terms of TEAC (Trolox C equivalent antioxidant capacity).<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par49">Antioxidant ABTS assay</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par50">To determine the ABTS antioxidant level, the proposed protocol of Tagliazucchi et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref></sup> was used with little modifications. Briefly, ABTS (2,2-azinobis (3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulphonic acid) salt (7&#x000a0;mM) and 2.45&#x000a0;mM of potassium per sulphate were gently mixed in equal proportion to make ABTS solution, followed by incubation for 16&#x000a0;h in dark. The absorbance was measured at wavelength (734&#x000a0;nm), adjusted to 0.7 and solution then mixed with the extracts and incubated at 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in dark for 15&#x000a0;min. The absorbance of was recorded at 734&#x000a0;nm by using Microplate reader (ELX800, BioTek Instruments). Antioxidant capacity of samples was expressed in terms of TEAC.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Quantitative (HPLC) determination of compounds</title><p id="Par51">Detection and quantification were carried out via Varian HPLC system equipped with an online degasser (Metachem Degasit), an autosampler (Prostar 410) and a photodiode array detector (PDA, Prostar 335) using the protocol of Bourgeois, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref></sup> and Wang, et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref></sup> with little modifications. The separation was performed at 35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C on an RP-18 column (250&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4.0&#x000a0;mm id, 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m; Purospher Merck). The mobile phase was composed of acetonitrile (solvent A) and 0.1% (v/v) formic acid acidified ultrapure water (solvent B). The composition of the mobile phase varied during a 1-h run according to a linear gradient ranging from a 5:95 (v/v) to 100:0 (v/v) mixture of solvents A and B, respectively, at a flow rate of 0.6&#x000a0;mL/min. Detection was performed at 260&#x000a0;nm for simple phenolics (gallic acid and caffeic acid), 360&#x000a0;nm for flavonoids (catechin, myricetin, kaempferol, isorhamnetin, and apigenin) and 210&#x000a0;nm for saponins (nahagenin, hederagenin, ursolic acid and betulinic acid). A typical HPLC chromatogram of a <italic>F. indica</italic> callus extract is shown in Supplemental Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. Compounds were identified by comparison with authentic standards purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, and confirmed by standard additions and/or LC&#x02013;ESI&#x02013;MS analysis performed on Water 2695 Alliance coupled with a single quadrupole mass spectrometer ZQ. LC&#x02013;ESI&#x02013;MS data were collected in the positive and negative modes as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Data acquisition and processing were performed with MassLynx 4.0 software. All the compounds were quantified against 5-point calibration curves (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.999) using authentic commercial standards (Sigma-Aldrich). The Quantifications were recorded using calibration curves and retention time of corresponding reference standards and the results were expressed as &#x003bc;g/mg DW of sample. 5-methoxyflavone (0.2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL) was used as internal standard for extraction (with detection set at 360&#x000a0;nm).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Determination of anti-inflammatory activities</title><p id="Par52">The callus cultures were also investigated for anti-inflammatory activities via employing sPLA2, 15-LOX, COX1 and COX2 assays by following the protocol reported by Usman et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref></sup> with slight modification.<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par53">15-LOX Inhibition Assay</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par54">The inhibitory activity in the extracts towards 15-LOX was also performed by the kit method (760700, Cayman Chem. Co., Interchim, Montlu&#x000e7;on, France) according to following the manufacturer&#x02019;s guidelines.</p><p id="Par55">The amount of hydroperoxides accumulated thought the lipo-oxygenation reaction was calculated via the kit using standard filtered soybean 15-lipooxygenase in Tris&#x02013;HCl bu_er (10&#x000a0;mM) at pH 7.4. The microplate reader (BioTek ELX800; BioTek Instruments, Colmar, France) was employed to measure the absorbance at 940&#x000a0;nm. The 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M Thioetheramide-PC was used as sPLA2 inhibitor. The extraction volume in equal amount was applied as blank.<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par56">sPLA2 inhibition assay</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par57">The kit method (10004883, Cayman Chem. Co, Interchim, Montlu&#x000e7;on, France) was followed with manufacturer instructions to measure inhibition of phospholipase A2 (sPLA2) enzyme. The Diheptanoyl thio-PC was used as substrate and thiotheramide-PC was applied as positive control inhibitor. While. Nordihydroguaiaretic acid (100 _M) was used as 15-LOX inhibitor during the assay. The extraction volume in equal amount was applied as blank. The absorbance was recorded via microplate reader (BioTek ELX800; BioTek Instruments, Colmar, France) at 420&#x000a0;nm.</p><p id="Par58">The % inhibition was figured out with the following formula;<disp-formula id="Eque"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \% {\text{ Inhibition }} = \, \left[ {\left( {{\text{IA}} - {\text{Inhibitor}}} \right)/{\text{IA}}} \right] \times {1}00 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/><mml:mtext>Inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.333333em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>IA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Inhibitor</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>IA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_Article_Eque.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where the inhibition is expressed as enzyme activity with adding inhibitor; IA as 100% activity of enzyme in the absence of inhibitor.<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par60">COX-1 and COX-2 inhibition assay</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par61">The COX1 (ovine) and COX2 (human) assay kits were utilized by following the manufacturer guidelines (701050; Cayman Chem; Co, Interchim, Montlu&#x000e7;on; France). The 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M ibuprofen as positive control and Arachidonic acid (1.1&#x000a0;mM) was employed as substrate. In order to estimate the activity, COX peroxidase component kit employed and Synergy II plate (BioTek Instruments, Colmar, France) was used to demonstrate the oxidized tetramethyl-p-phenylenediamine, Wurster&#x02019;s blue (C10H16N2). The microplate reader (BioTek ELX800; BioTek Instruments, Colmar, France) was used to measure the absorbance at 5&#x000a0;nm for 5&#x000a0;min. The extraction volume in equal amount was applied as blank.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par62">All the experiments were performed at least in triplicates. Values represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of at least three replicates. Origin 8.5 software (OriginLab, Northampton, MA, USA) was used to generate graphics with their mean data values and standard errors. The significance at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 means and standard deviation were calculated by using Statistix 8.1 (Statistix, Tallahassee, FL, USA). All statistical analysis was performed with XL-STAT2019 (Addinsoft, Paris, France).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec30"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_79896_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Infomation.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>These authors contributed equally: Bilal Haider Abbasi, Taimoor Khan, Samantha Drouet and Christophe Hano.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-020-79896-6.</p></sec><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>T.K. performed experiments, compiled data and prepared manuscript, M.N. and R.K. assisted him with experimental work, B.H.A. conceived the idea, supervised research and reviewed, S.D., C.H. performed and interpreted HPLC data and biological activities. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par63">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garros</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic effects of melatonin and distinct spectral lights for enhanced production of anti-cancerous compounds in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic></article-title><source>J. Photochem. Photobiol. B</source><year>2019</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2018.10.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30482427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of chitosan and salicylic acid on the production of pharmacologically attractive secondary metabolites in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic></article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2019</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2018.12.048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interplay between light, plant growth regulators and elicitors on growth and secondary metabolism in cell cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic></article-title><source>J. Photochem. Photobiol. B</source><year>2018</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2018.06.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29908408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29908408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farheen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Simjee</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Majeed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triterpenoids and triterpenoid saponins from the aerial parts of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic> Burm</article-title><source>Phytochem. Lett.</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytol.2015.07.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Krohn</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Draeger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive isocoumarins isolated from the endophytic fungus <italic>Microdochium bolleyi</italic></article-title><source>J. Nat. Prod.</source><year>2008</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1078</fpage><lpage>1081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np800095g</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18510362?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18510362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An aqueous extract of <italic>Fagonia cretica</italic> induces DNA damage, cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in breast cancer cells via FOXO3a and p53 expression</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e40152</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040152</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22761954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22761954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinwari</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of thidiazuron on production of anticancer phenolic compounds in callus cultures of <italic>Fagonia indica</italic></article-title><source>Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12010-016-1978-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26758711?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26758711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasundram</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundram</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Samman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic compounds in plants and agri-industrial by-products: antioxidant activity, occurrence, and potential uses</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2006</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2005.07.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheynier</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic compounds: from plants to foods</article-title><source>Phytochem. Rev.</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11101-012-9242-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freeman, B. C. &#x00026; Beattie, G. A. An overview of plant defenses against pathogens and herbivores. <italic>Plant Health Instr.</italic> (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumper</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant phenolics: extraction, analysis and their antioxidant and anticancer properties</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>7313</fpage><lpage>7352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules15107313</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20966876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20966876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zoratti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Karppinen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Luengo Escobar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;ggman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaakola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light-controlled flavonoid biosynthesis in fruits</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>534</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2014.00534</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25346743?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25346743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soto-Vaca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Losso</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of phenolic compounds from color and flavor problems to health benefits</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>6658</fpage><lpage>6677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf300861c</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22568556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22568556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfermann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural product formation by plant cell biotechnology</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult.</source><year>1995</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00052176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ravishankar, G. A. &#x00026; Venkataraman, L. V. Role of plant cell culture in food biotechnology: current trends, limitations and future prospects (1993).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaj</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing somatic embryogenesis induction and plant regeneration with particular reference to <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (L.) Heynh</article-title><source>Plant Growth Regul.</source><year>2004</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:GROW.0000038275.29262.fb</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhong, J.-J. Biochemical engineering of the production of plant-specific secondary metabolites by cell suspension cultures. In <italic>Plant Cells</italic> 1&#x02013;26 (Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg, 2001).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Current approaches toward production of secondary plant metabolites</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Bioallied Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0975-7406.92725</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22368394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22368394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matkowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant in vitro culture for the production of antioxidants&#x02014;a review</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2008.07.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18682287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18682287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gorelick, J. &#x00026; Bernstein, N. Elicitation: an underutilized tool in the development of medicinal plants as a source of therapeutic secondary metabolites. In <italic>Advances in Agronomy</italic> Vol. 124, 201&#x02013;230 (Academic Press, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuler</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-scale plant cell culture</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Biotechnol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0958-1669(97)80094-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9079728?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9079728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulabagal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsay</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant cell cultures-an alternative and efficient source for the production of biologically important secondary metabolites</article-title><source>Int. J. Appl. Sci. Eng.</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasconsuelo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular aspects of the early stages of elicitation of secondary metabolites in plants</article-title><source>Plant Sci.</source><year>2007</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2007.01.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gangopadhyay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UVC-priming mediated modulation of forskolin biosynthesis key genes against Macrophomina root rot of <italic>Coleus forskohlii</italic>&#x02014;a tissue culture based sustainable approach</article-title><source>Phytochem. Lett.</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytol.2016.06.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanh</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Khang</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Elzaawely</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in chemical composition, total phenolics and antioxidant activity of Alpinia (<italic>Alpinia zerumbet</italic>) leaves exposed to UV</article-title><source>Int. Lett. Natl. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of UV-C radiation on bioactive compounds of pineapple (<italic>Ananas comosus</italic> L. Merr.) by-products</article-title><source>J. Sci. Food Agric.</source><year>2015</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.6751</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24852602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24852602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ABA and UV-C effects on quality, antioxidant capacity and anthocyanin contents of strawberry fruit (<italic>Fragaria ananassa</italic> Duch.)</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2013.12.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insights into the mechanisms underlying ultraviolet-C induced resveratrol metabolism in grapevine (V. amurensis Rupr.) cv.&#x0201c;Tonghua-3&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Front. Plant Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>503</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27148326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anjum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Doussot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Favre-R&#x000e9;guillon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of photoperiod regimes and ultraviolet-C radiations on biosynthesis of industrially important lignans and neolignans in cell cultures of <italic>Linum usitatissimum</italic> L. (Flax)</article-title><source>J. Photochem. Photobiol. B Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2017.01.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shama</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alderson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UV hormesis in fruits: a concept ripe for commercialisation</article-title><source>Trends Food Sci. Technol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2004.10.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turtoi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultraviolet light treatment of fresh fruits and vegetables surface: a review</article-title><source>J. Agroaliment. Process. Technol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>337</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nazir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interactive effect of melatonin and UV-C on phenylpropanoid metabolite production and antioxidant potential in callus cultures of purple basil (<italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. var. s purpurascens)</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2020</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25051072</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7179200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7179200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of ultraviolet-C radiation and melatonin stress on biosynthesis of antioxidant and antidiabetic metabolites produced in in vitro callus cultures of <italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> L</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1787</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20071787</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6479895?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6479895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Versari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parpinello</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tornielli</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrarini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Giulivo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stilbene compounds and stilbene synthase expression during ripening, wilting, and UV treatment in grape cv. Corvina</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>2001</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>5531</fpage><lpage>5536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf010672o</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11714355?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11714355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousefzadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of light on gene expression and podophyllotoxin biosynthesis in Linum album cell culture</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2012.04.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22579943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W-D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined elicitation of chitosan and ultraviolet C enhanced stilbene production and expression of chitinase and &#x003b2;-1, 3-glucanase in <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> cell suspension cultures</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult. (PCTOC)</source><year>2016</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-015-0879-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaakola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohtola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of latitude on flavonoid biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ.</source><year>2010</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1239</fpage><lpage>1247</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20374534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20374534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laaksonen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahvonen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of latitude and weather conditions on phenolic compounds in currant (Ribes spp.) cultivars</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>2013</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>3517</fpage><lpage>3532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf4000456</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23480522?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some effects of photoperiod on the biosynthesis of phenylpropane derivatives in Xanthium</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1965</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>273</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.40.2.273</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16656083?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16656083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaco</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Duque</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of photoperiod on flavonoid pathway activity in sweet potato (<italic>Ipomoea batatas</italic> (L.) Lam.) leaves</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2010</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.05.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawkar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UV-induced cell death in plants</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1608</fpage><lpage>1628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms14011608</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23344059?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23344059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katerova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Todorova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasheva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergiev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of ultraviolet radiation on plant secondary metabolite production</article-title><source>Genet. Plant Physiol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>144</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zacchini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Agazio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spread of oxidative damage and antioxidative response through cell layers of tobacco callus after UV-C treatment</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2004.03.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15191749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15191749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the inhibition of photosynthesis by intense light</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1956</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-3002(56)90003-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 13363902?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13363902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lichtenthaler, H. K. <italic>et al.</italic> Effect of high light and high light stress on composition, function and structure of the photosynthetic apparatus. In <italic>Effects of Stress on Photosynthesis</italic> 353&#x02013;370 (Springer, Dordrecht, 1983).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smillie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf chlorophyll fluorescence as an indicator of high light stress (photoinhibition) in <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic> L</article-title><source>Funct. Plant Biol.</source><year>1981</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/PP9810133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the mechanism of photoinhibition in higher plants. II. Inactivation by high light of photosystem II reaction center function in isolated spinach thylakoids and O2 evolving particles</article-title><source>Photobiochem. Photobiophys.</source><year>1985</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1161</fpage><lpage>1165</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00160;iffel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebedev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;est&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in chloroplast absorption and fluorescence spectra during ontogeny of primary bean leaves</article-title><source>Photosynthetica</source><year>1985</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>137</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenthaler</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinderle</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of chlorophyll fluorescence in the detection of stress conditions in plants</article-title><source>CRC Crit. Rev. Anal. Chem.</source><year>1988</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>S29</fpage><lpage>S85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476510.1988.10401466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W-D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of ultraviolet C, methyl jasmonate and salicylic acid, alone or in combination, on stilbene biosynthesis in cell suspension cultures of <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. cv. Cabernet Sauvignon</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult. (PCTOC)</source><year>2015</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-015-0761-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Julkunen-Tiitto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient availability and the effect of increasing UV-B radiation on secondary plant compounds in Scots pine</article-title><source>Environ. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2003</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0098-8472(02)00057-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Matsuura, H. N., de Costa, F., Yendo, A. C. A. &#x00026; Fett-Neto, A. G. in <italic>Biotechnology for Medicinal Plants</italic> 171&#x02013;190 (Springer, Berlin, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light-induced fluctuations in biomass accumulation, secondary metabolites production and antioxidant activity in cell suspension cultures of <italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic> L</article-title><source>J. Photochem. Photobiol. B</source><year>2014</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2014.08.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25169773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25169773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Furusaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shioya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>5-Aminolevulinic acid promotes callus growth and paclitaxel production in light-grown <italic>Taxus cuspidata</italic> suspension cultures</article-title><source>Eng. Life Sci.</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/elsc.201300171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fazal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sucrose induced osmotic stress and photoperiod regimes enhanced the biomass and production of antioxidant secondary metabolites in shake-flask suspension cultures of <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> L</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult. (PCTOC)</source><year>2016</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-015-0915-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Keresztes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of gamma and UV-B/C radiation on plant cells</article-title><source>Micron</source><year>2002</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0968-4328(01)00012-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11567888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11567888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular response of plant cells to UV-B stress</article-title><source>Funct. Plant Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/FP02062</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32689541?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32689541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jenkins, G. I. UV and blue light signal transduction in the regulation of flavonoid biosynthesis gene expression in Arabidopsis. In <italic>Cellular Integration of Signalling Pathways in Plant Development</italic> 71&#x02013;82 (Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg, 1998).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ippolito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lattanzio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Venere</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Salerno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of ultraviolet-C light on postharvest decay of strawberry</article-title><source>J. Plant Pathol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiecher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Paula</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rombaldi</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UV-C effect on ethylene, polyamines and the regulation of tomato fruit ripening</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2013.07.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Miranda</surname><given-names>MRA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aarrouf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the physiological effects of UV-C light and exploiting its agronomic potential before and after harvest</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2016.04.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27064192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27064192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional roles of flavonoids in photoprotection: new evidence, lessons from the past</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Biochem.</source><year>2013</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2013.03.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23583204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23583204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carbonell-Bejerano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Solar ultraviolet radiation is necessary to enhance grapevine fruit ripening transcriptional and phenolic responses</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>183</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-14-183</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25012688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25012688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-dose UV-C irradiation reduces the microbial population and preserves antioxidant levels in peeled garlic (<italic>Allium sativum</italic> L.) during storage</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2014.09.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UV-C light and pulsed light as alternatives to chemical and biological elicitors for stimulating plant natural defenses against fungal diseases</article-title><source>Sci. Hortic.</source><year>2018</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2018.02.057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waszczak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kangasj&#x000e4;rvi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen species in plant signaling</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042817-040322</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29489394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29489394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mittler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ROS are good</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2016.08.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27666517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27666517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UV-C-mediated lipid induction and settling, a step change towards economical microalgal biodiesel production</article-title><source>Green Chem.</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3539</fpage><lpage>3548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4GC00552J</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang, J. W. &#x00026; Wu, J. Y. Effective elicitors and process strategies for enhancement of secondary metabolite production in hairy root cultures. In <italic>Biotechnology of Hairy Root Systems</italic> 55&#x02013;89 (Springer, Berlin, Heidelberg, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A rich source of potential bioactive compounds with anticancer activities by <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> cambium meristematic stem cell cultures</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>217</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2018.02.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29452141?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29452141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivera-Pastrana</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardea</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahia</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-T&#x000e9;llez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Aguilar</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of UV-C irradiation and low temperature storage on bioactive compounds, antioxidant enzymes and radical scavenging activity of papaya fruit</article-title><source>J. Food Sci. Technol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>3821</fpage><lpage>3829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13197-013-0942-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25477649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25477649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of postharvest application of UV-C radiation on the phenolic compounds of conventional and organic grapes (<italic>Vitis labrusca</italic> cv. &#x02018;Concord&#x02019;)</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2016.05.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Windram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis defense against Botrytis cinerea: chronology and regulation deciphered by high-resolution temporal transcriptomic analysis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>3530</fpage><lpage>3557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.102046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23023172?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23023172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>A-N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Low responsiveness of grapevine flowers and berries at fruit set to UV-C irradiation</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1155</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern361</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19174460?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19174460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of commercially important secondary metabolites and antioxidant activity in cell suspension cultures of <italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic> L</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2013</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2013.05.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anjum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biomimetic synthesis of antimicrobial silver nanoparticles using in vitro-propagated plantlets of a medicinally important endangered species: <italic>Phlomis bracteosa</italic></article-title><source>Int. J. Nanomed.</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1663</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erkan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of UV treatment on antioxidant capacity, antioxidant enzyme activity and decay in strawberry fruit</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2007.09.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djeridane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of some Algerian medicinal plants extracts containing phenolic compounds</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>654</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2005.04.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D-O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>H-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of polyphenolics and their antioxidant capacity in fresh plums</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>6509</fpage><lpage>6515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf0343074</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14558771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14558771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H-B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory activity of coptisine free base in mice through inhibition of NF-&#x003ba;B and MAPK signaling pathways</article-title><source>Eur. J. Pharmacol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>811</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejphar.2017.06.027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28648405?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28648405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elansary</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bioactivities of traditional medicinal plants in Alexandria</article-title><source>Evid. Based Complement. Altern. Med.</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>1463579</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/1463579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of action of flavonoids as anti-inflammatory agents: a review</article-title><source>Inflamm. Allergy Drug Targets (Former. Curr. Drug Targets Inflamm. Allergy)</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>235</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu, X., Islam, M. &#x00026; HB, I. in <italic>International Congress and 49th Annual Meeting of the society for Medicinal Plant Research.</italic> 2&#x02013;6 (2001).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tittel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality assessment of herbal preparations as a precondition of pharmacological and clinical studies</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><year>1996</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0944-7113(96)80041-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23194615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23194615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemistry and biological activities of flavonoids: an overview</article-title><source>Sci. World J.</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>162750</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficient regeneration and antioxidant potential in regenerated tissues of <italic>Piper nigrum</italic> L</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult. (PCTOC)</source><year>2010</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-010-9712-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Shoot regeneration and free-radical scavenging activity in <italic>Silybum marianum</italic> L</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult. (PCTOC)</source><year>2010</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-010-9692-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murashige</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoog</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A revised medium for rapid growth and bio assays with tobacco tissue cultures</article-title><source>Physiol. Plant.</source><year>1962</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.1962.tb08052.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of light wavelength on cell growth, content of phenolic compounds and antioxidant activity in cell suspension cultures of <italic>Thevetia peruviana</italic></article-title><source>J. Photochem. Photobiol. B</source><year>2016</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2016.08.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27541569?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27541569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzie</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ferric reducing ability of plasma (FRAP) as a measure of &#x0201c;antioxidant power&#x0201d;: the FRAP assay</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><year>1996</year><volume>239</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abio.1996.0292</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8660627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8660627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tagliazucchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Verzelloni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertolini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro bio-accessibility and antioxidant activity of grape polyphenols</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.10.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nettle (<italic>Urtica dioica</italic> L.) as a source of antioxidant and anti-aging phytochemicals for cosmetic applications</article-title><source>C. R. Chim.</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1090</fpage><lpage>1100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crci.2016.03.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous determination of rutin, luteolin, quercetin, and betulinic acid in the extract of <italic>Disporopsis pernyi</italic> (Hua) Diels by UPLC</article-title><source>J. Anal. Methods Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>2015</volume><fpage>130873</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26798553?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26798553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interactive Effects of wide-spectrum monochromatic lights on phytochemical production, antioxidant and biological activities of <italic>Solanum xanthocarpum</italic> callus cultures</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2020</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2201</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25092201</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7248882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7248882</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>