<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One may think that the interactions involving nanocelluloses in their native or isolated forms are well-understood; however, this is far from true. The same holds for the second component considered here, lignin. Because of the growing interest in using biobased colloids, several aspects need to be addressed with regard to the structures, self-assembly, interactions, and applications of nanocellulosic and lignin particles. As for the former, their building block, the cellulose macromolecule, may be deemed uninteresting given its apparent simplicity as a linear homopolymer comprising C, O, and H atoms. A very different perception arises when it comes to the way it assembles in hierarchical and multiscale structures. In contrast, lignins are heterogeneous and complex macromolecules. Several questions arise relative to the native or isolated forms of nanocellulose and lignin:
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(1)</label>
   <p class="p">How do the structures they form evolve in nature to respond to the multiple demands of living organisms? Can such designs be engineered into new materials after their cleavage from the cell walls of fibers, following suitable deconstruction protocols?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(2)</label>
   <p class="p">What type of structures do cellulose chains make in the native or never-dried forms?
    <sup class="sup">
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1" class="xref">1</xref>
    </sup> Do the structures involve ordered regions alternating with less ordered domains? In addition, in regards to lignin, are the isolated structures branched or not? What type of assemblies do they form?
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(3)</label>
   <p class="p">If we consider both cellulose and lignin, what is the nature of their interactions in the cell wall? And how do such interactions play once they are isolated and/or combined in a given multiphase system? What is the role of hydrophobic interactions that determine the insolubility of cellulosic structures in water?
    <sup class="sup">
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2" class="xref">2</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3" class="xref">3</xref>
    </sup> Likewise, in the case of colloidal lignin, what is the nature of their interactions in liquid media?
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(4)</label>
   <p class="p">Combined in the cell walls of plants, cellulose and lignin form an intricate composite that sustains mechanical, thermal, biological, and environmental stresses (fire, water, pathogens, etc.). Do they lose such features when separated and used as a single component, for example, in a solid material or in an emulsion? Alternatively, once isolated, is it possible to restore some of the properties observed in the original fiber precursors? This last question has been partially addressed in the context of solid composites. However, for liquid/liquid or multiphase systems, this remains an open question.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
