<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">The outbreak of highly transmissible fatal pneumonia in human referred as Coronavirus Disease-2019 (Covid-19) has spread globally (215 countries and territories) with over 16.81 M confirmed cases and over 662,095 deaths worldwide as on 31 July 2020 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus</ext-link>), whereas, in India, 15, 83,792 people with 34,968 deaths (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus</ext-link>). According to the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV), the novel zoonotic pathogenic virus associated with COVID-19 is 
 <italic>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</italic> 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and the virus species is severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus (Gorbalenya et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2020</xref>). The break out of SARS-CoV-2 has been first reported during December 2019 in Wuhan, Hubei Province, China, with a fatality rate of 4 percent (Liu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2020</xref>; Wu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2020</xref>; Zhu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2020</xref>). Sore throat, dry cough, fever, chills, repeated shaking with chills, muscle pain, headache, loss of taste or smell and respiratory distress are major symptoms induced by SARS-CoV-2 (Cheng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>). In most severe cases, the clinical presentation of SARS-CoV-2 infection includes pneumonia that progresses to multi-organ failure and even death (Zaki et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2012</xref>; Machhi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2020</xref>). Covid-19 has become global pandemic and created the wide spread fear of death everywhere in the world resulting lockdown in human society (Mandal 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2020</xref>). The increasing pandemic potential of SARS-CoV-2 is due to its high human-to-human transmissible efficiency which makes it difficult to contain (Wu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2020</xref>; Zhao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2020</xref>).
</p>
