<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interest in natural antioxidants from medicinal plants has increased due to the safety of these antioxidants in comparison with synthetic compounds [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. These natural antioxidants, especially phenolic compounds, have a fundamental role in reducing the harmful effects of free radicals [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. This correlation between phenolic compounds and scavenging activity was clearly reported in several studies [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The antioxidative potency of plants can be evaluated through their ability to scavenge free radicals. The DPPH and ABTS methods are the most widely utilized assays for determining free radical scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In this study, we showed that 
 <italic>S. glaucus</italic> displayed strong antioxidant activity through two screening methods. The results were compared with a recent study which reported that essential oils from 
 <italic>S. glaucus</italic> exerted a concentration-dependent DPPH scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Furthermore, Mohamed (2015) found that root methyl alcohol extract of 
 <italic>S. glaucus</italic> growing in Egypt had an antioxidant activity with IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 79.57 ± 0.74 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/ml using the DPPH method [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. There were no major differences between our results and the results of other previously reported studies, and this may be due to the presence of the same chemical constituents, including GA and VA. Moreover, the presence of GA and VA, which have known antioxidant properties [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], verified the reported antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>S. glaucus</italic>. Furthermore, a hybrid of GA and another phenolic antioxidant strongly enhanced the plant's antioxidant potential [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
