<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antibacterial activity was measured by the disc diffusion method [
 <xref rid="B38-antibiotics-10-00295" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-antibiotics-10-00295" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The microorganisms were grown overnight at 37 °C in 10 mL of Mueller Hinton Broth (Bioxon). The cultures were adjusted with sterile saline solution to obtain turbidity comparable to that of McFarland no. 0.5 standard (10
 <sup>8</sup> CFU/mL). Petri dishes containing Mueller Hinton agar (Bioxon) were inoculated with these microbial suspensions. Discs of filter paper (Whatman no. 5) of 5-mm diameter were impregnated with 4 µL of each compound (α-pinene 3.4 mg, β-pinene 3.4 mg, carvacrol 3.9 mg, eugenol 4.3 mg, limonene 3.4 mg, myrcene 3.2 mg, ocimene 3.3 mg, cineole 3.7 mg, methyl salicylate 4.7 mg, farnesene 3.4 mg) and placed on the agar surface (for thymol, a solution was prepared at a concentration of 0.980 g/mL, discs were impregnated with 4 µL = 3.9 mg). Discs impregnated with chloramphenicol (25 µg) were used as positive controls. The plates were incubated overnight at 37 °C and the resulting inhibition zones were measured with a vernier. Each experiment was performed in triplicate. The estimation of the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) was carried out by the broth dilution method [
 <xref rid="B40-antibiotics-10-00295" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-antibiotics-10-00295" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Ten dilutions of each compound (0.03–4.0 mg/mL) in broth were evaluated. The tubes were inoculated with 10
 <sup>6</sup> CFU/mL microorganism suspensions. MIC values were taken as the lowest essential oil concentration that prevents visible bacterial growth after 24 h of incubation at 37 °C and MBC as the lowest concentration that completely inhibited bacterial growth. Chloramphenicol was used as reference standard and compound-free plates as controls. Each experiment was repeated at least three times. The time-killing curve assay was performed using appropriate concentrations of the compounds (corresponding to ½MIC, MIC, and MBC) in 10 mL of broth. One control tube was prepared without compound. Each tube was inoculated with 0.1 mL of a microbial suspension (10
 <sup>6</sup> CFU/mL) and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. Of each tube, 50 µL aliquots were taken in ranges of 2 h. Aliquots were plated on Muller–Hinton agar and incubated for 24 h at 37 °C. Finally, the number of CFU was determined. Death kinetics was expressed in log10 reduction time kill plots [
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-10-00295" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. 
</p>
