<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The bitter taste can be reduced in a variety of ways. From a food processing standpoint, both high and low temperatures can be used as effective ways of reducing the bitter taste. Storage of olive oil at 5 °C for two to eight weeks leads to a reduction in bitterness [
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. In addition, Garcia et al. showed that heating the olives leads to a decrease in olive oil bitterness and the reduction in bitterness correlated with the time and temperature used for heating [
 <xref rid="B9-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Heating the olives did not cause any changes in the oxidative stability of the olive oil or its acidity, however, Garcia et al. did find decreased levels of phenolic content. Not only heat, but also cold temperatures can be effective in reducing the bitterness of olive oil. Another method used successfully to reduce the bitterness of olive oil is the addition of phospholipids. Koprivnjak et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] showed that the addition of 5–10 g of soy lecithin/kg olive oil leads to a significant reduction in bitterness and an increase in the sweetness of olive oil. The partitioning of polyphenols between oil and water phases can be an effective method used to decrease the total polyphenol content and therefore leads to a reduction in bitterness without affecting the physicochemical parameters of oil [
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Adding spices [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] or flavorings to the oils can also change the taste characteristics in a way to try to make the oil more compatible. Shape Foods, Inc. in Brandon. Manitoba Canada produced a variety of flavored flax oils in dessert flavors (chocolate, caramel, banana, and coconut) and culinary flavors (Italian, Mexican, Indian, Thai, Szechuan and Culinary).
</p>
