<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fish, hempseed, flaxseed, and olive oil can be ingested as an oil by the spoonful, in salad dressings, by pill form or incorporated into food products [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. The oils provide the fatty acids to the body with greater bioavailability than foods that contain the same amount of fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. However, each of these types of oils (i.e., fish versus hemp versus flax) has a different bioavailability to the body [
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Fish oil had its eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA)/docosahexanoeic acid (DHA) content absorbed better than the ALA in flaxseed oil, which was more bioavailable than the LA in hempseed oil [
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. However, although the bioavailability and the biological benefit of each of these fatty acids differ considerably, encouraging the consuming public to actually ingest these oils has been a considerable challenge. The incorporation of these fatty acids into foods commonly consumed disguises their bitter taste characteristics and encourages greater acceptability [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. For example, even though bioavailability may be compromised slightly [
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], the inclusion of milled flaxseed into biscuits, muffins, bagels, bread products, and even pasta can increase consumption [
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In 2011, Aliani and colleagues used a trained sensory panel to test whether adding different flavors will reduce the bitterness of muffins and snack bars containing milled flaxseed [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Flaxseed is rich in the omega-3 fatty acid ALA. Among several flavors used such as apple spice, gingerbread raisin, orange cranberry, and cappuccino chocolate, the gingerbread raisin flavor reduced the bitterness of flax best. Therefore, the authors suggested that the flavorings that naturally contain a small amount of bitterness could be effective in reducing the bitterness caused by flax [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>].
</p>
