<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<glossary>
 <title>Abbreviations</title>
 <p>
  <italic>A. absinthium</italic>: 
  <italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic>; IUPAC: International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry; HIV-1: human immunodeficiency virus; HBV: hepatitis B virus; HDP: heme detoxification protein; 
  <italic>S. aureus</italic>: 
  <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>; 
  <italic>B. subtilis</italic>: 
  <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>; 
  <italic>B. cereus</italic>: 
  <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>; 
  <italic>Sal. typmiruim</italic>: 
  <italic>Salmonella typmiruim</italic>; 
  <italic>E. coli</italic>: 
  <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>; 
  <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>: 
  <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>; 
  <italic>T. brucei</italic>: 
  <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic>; 
  <italic>L. infantum</italic>: 
  <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic>; 
  <italic>A. fumigatus</italic>: 
  <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>; 
  <italic>Pf</italic>TCTP: 
  <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> controlled tumor protein; MIC: minimum inhibitory concentration; LDH: L-lactate dehydrogenase; SAMS: S-adenosyl-methionine synthetase; cGMP: cyclic guanosine-3′:5′-monophosphate; PyrK: pyruvate kinase; SpdSyn: spermidine synthase; OAT: ornithine aminotransferase; DPPH: 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl; IBD: Inflammatory bowel disorders; UC: ulcerative colitis; CD: Crohn’s disease; COX-2: cyclooxygenase-2; NO: nitric oxide; NOS: nitric oxide synthase; TNF-α: tumor necrosis factor-α; NF-
  <italic>κ</italic>B: nuclear factor- kappa B; LPS: lipopolysaccharide; NOEL: no-effect level; GABA: Gamma-aminobutyric acid; AChE: acetylcholinesterase enzymes; AMPK: adenosine monophosphate-activated protein kinase; GLUT4: insulin-stimulated glucose transporter type 4; MAO: monoamine oxidase; SOD: superoxide dismutase; GSH: glutathione; iNOS: inducible NO synthase; PGE(2): prostaglandin E(2); MEK/ERK: mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase/extracellular signal-regulated kinase; Th1: T helper cell 1; GABA
  <sub>A</sub>: Gamma-aminobutyric acid; TBARS: thiobarbituric acid reactive substances; H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>: hydrogen peroxide; DCs: dendritic cells; IgA: immunoglobulin A; LH: luteinizing hormone; MIC: minimal inhibitory concentration; MBC: minimal bactericidal concentration; DNA: deoxyribonucleic acid; 
  <italic>A. absinthium</italic>-Ag NPs: 
  <italic>A. absinthium</italic>-silver nanoparticles; DHA: dihydroartemisinin; CYP2D6: cytochrome P450 2D6; CP: cytochrome P450; WHO: World Health Organization; 
  <italic>Kl. Oxytoca</italic>: 
  <italic>Klebsiella oxytoca</italic>; MRSA: methicillin-resistant 
  <italic>S. aureus</italic>.
 </p>
</glossary>
