<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, the efflux pump activity was evaluated using a fluorometric method that measured the accumulation of the universal efflux pump substrate EtBr. Overexpressing efflux pumps is an important mechanism by which bacteria can evade the effects of antimicrobial agents. The management of efflux pumps is a valuable strategy to restore susceptibility in strains resistant to antibacterial agents. In this context, DCME and the compounds 15-copaenol (6) and 
 <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-cubenol (4) acted as NorA EPIs, as shown by the finding that they produced an higher level of fluorescence over time than was observed for the EtBr curve obtained in untreated 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains. Moreover, 15-copaenol (6) was the only sample that was able to increase the EtBr accumulation in the K1902 (Δ
 <italic class="italic">norA</italic>) strain. Because the 
 <italic class="italic">norA</italic> gene was suppressed in the K1902 (Δ
 <italic class="italic">norA</italic>) strain, K1902 cells cannot express the NorA efflux pump. However, other authors have demonstrated that K1902 cells were able to express other efflux pumps for which EtBr is a substrate, such as MepA, TetK, and MrsA (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jang, 2016</xref>). It should to be noted that, 15-copaenol (6) was able to increase the EtBr accumulation at all the used concentrations in wild type and K2378 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains while it was able to increase the EtBr accumulation in K1902 only at 31.5 μg/mL. These results can be explained using the cytotoxicity experiments. 15-Copaenol (6) at 31.5 μg/mL was toxic for HeLa cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>). Moreover, MIC of 15-copaenol (6) was 62.5 μg/mL in K1902 strain, but, according with cytotoxicity assays (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>), clearly, at 31.5 μg/mL starts to damage membrane of K1902 cells, thus producing an increase in EtBr accumulation. Therefore, it suggests that 15-copaenol (6) at low concentrations likely could inhibit NorA efflux pumps and other efflux pumps, but at high concentrations (≥31.5 μg/mL) 15-copaenol (6) shows a non-specific effect (such as membrane depolarization) thereby resulting toxic for 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains: 8325-4, K2378 and K1902.
</p>
