<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">By following a structure-activity analysis, the EtBr accumulation observed in the K2378 (
 <italic class="italic">norA</italic>++) strain indicated that the hydroxylated compound 15-copaenol (6) exerted a stronger inhibitory effect than was found for the tertiary sesquiterpene alcohols 
 <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-cubenol (4) and cubenol (3) and the sesquiterpene hydrocarbons 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-calamenene (1) and cadalene (2). Among the tertiary alcohols, 
 <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-cubenol (4), which has a C1-α-OH, was more active than the C1-epimer, cubenol (3), which was inactive at all evaluated concentrations. Additionally, when the primary hydroxyl group of 15-copaenol (6) was replaced with an aldehyde or an ester group, resulting in the synthetic derivatives 6OX and 6AC, respectively, the modified derivatives did not act like a NorA EPI, indicating that the primary hydroxyl group is essential to generating the EtBr efflux inhibition of copaene-type sesquiterpenes in 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> K2378 cells. Consistent with these results, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vieira et al. (1991)</xref> observed a decrease in the antibacterial activity of 15-copaenol (6) when it was oxidized at C11 and C8 to aldehyde and ketone groups, respectively. Moreover, the MIC values obtained in this study (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>) are consistent with the results of the structure-antibacterial activity analyses performed in wild type and K2378 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>. However, when we studied growth inhibition in the K2378 strain, we found that the MIC values for cubenol (3) and 
 <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-cubenol (4) were the same. These data indicate that the C1-tertiary hydroxyl configuration was not involved in antibacterial activity. This analysis represents an initial approach to determining the structural characteristics of the cadalene-type sesquiterpenes that act to induce NorA efflux pump inhibition in 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains.
</p>
