<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Transport of the Brazilian flounder for 7 h with the EOs of 
 <italic class="italic">Aloysia gratissima</italic> (90 mg⋅L
 <sup class="sup">–1</sup>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum gratissimum</italic> (10–20 mg⋅L
 <sup class="sup">–1</sup>) increased blood glucose levels compared to control fish subjected to the same procedure. In addition, the EO of 
 <italic class="italic">A. gratissima</italic> induced mortality. Consequently, both EOs are not effective in transport of this species (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Benovit et al., 2012</xref>). Moreover, the EO of 
 <italic class="italic">Nectandra megapotamica</italic> at 15 or 30 μL⋅L
 <sup class="sup">–1</sup> was not able to prevent the stress of transport in fat snook because it did not prevent deterioration in water quality and the post-transport mortality compared to control fish subjected to the same procedure (
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tondolo et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). Studies of the effect of these EOs in freshwater species are still lacking. Simulated transport (6 h) of gilthead seabream with clove oil at 2.5 mg⋅L
 <sup class="sup">–1</sup> increased plasma cortisol levels and expression of head kidney gene-expressions related to cortisol production (
 <italic class="italic">star</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">cyp11b1</italic>) and stimulated amino acids catabolism (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jerez-Cepa et al., 2019</xref>). The gill’s mRNA levels of 
 <italic class="italic">gst3</italic>, a target gene related with the antioxidant response and cell-tissue repair, enhanced after transportation with clove oil, returning to control values after recovery. However, the rest of transcripts assessed (
 <italic class="italic">gpx1</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">cat</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">gr</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">mt</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">hsp70</italic>) related to these responses did not present any alteration (
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Teles et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). Authors proposed that alternative concentrations of this EO should be tested for the transport of gilthead seabream.
</p>
