<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Xanthan is one of the most important industrial biopolymers produced by the gram negative phytopathogenic bacteria 
 <italic>Xanthomonas campestris</italic>. Xanthan is an extracellular polysaccharide composed of repeating units of polymerized pentasaccharide that are assembled together by step-by-step addition of glucose, glucose-1-phosphate, glucuronic acid, and mannose, over a polyprenol carrier of phosphate via a set of enzymatic reactions, in which multiple monosaccharide-specific glycosyltransferases, ketal pyruvate transferase (from nucleotidyl precursor derivatives of GDP and UDP), and acetyltransferases are involved [
 <xref rid="B67-polymers-13-01242" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Xanthan gum is the first industrially used bacterial biopolymer. It is widely used because of its good rheological properties. A high xanthan productivity was obtained by making use of lactose-utilizing 
 <italic>X. campestris</italic>, strain C7 L, growing over a whey media [
 <xref rid="B68-polymers-13-01242" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. A two-step fermentation process by combination of filtered whey (0.18% protein content) and unfiltered whey (0.35% protein content) was carried out, where the first stage utilized the unfiltered whey, showing a xanthan productivity of 12 g/L (0.40 g/L/h) with a yield of 45% followed by the second stage, where the addition of filtered whey increased the total xanthan concentration to 28 g/L (0.58 g/L/h) with a yield of 75%. Final viscosity of the broth was found to be 18,000 cP, and the polymer thus produced in this combined system showed thixotropic and pseudoplastic behavior. A relatively lower yield was achieved by using other strains of 
 <italic>Xanthomonas</italic> such as 
 <italic>X. manihotis</italic> and 
 <italic>X. mangiferaeindicae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B68-polymers-13-01242" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Highest productivity of xanthan was (25 g/L; 0.35 g/L/h) obtained by using these two strains when whey from mozzarella cheese was used as the main carbon source in a shake flask culture for 72 h.
</p>
