<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the works on this subject is an article studying various heterocyclic (–)-borneol derivatives with benzothiazole, benzoxazole, benzimidazole, and other heterocycles moieties (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-07078-f038">Figure 38</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B105-ijms-21-07078" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Those compounds were analyzed due to their biological properties, including their possible use as antiviral, antiulcer, and analgesic agents. The inhibition of the influenza virus replication was evaluated with the A/Puerto Rico/8/34 (H1N1) virus, while rimantadine, amantadine, and deitiforin were tested as reference compounds, due to the structural similarity of their rigid cage fragments relative to heterocyclic (–)-borneol derivatives. Compound bearing two terpene moieties attached to 1
 <italic>H</italic>-benzimidazole-2-thiol core 
 <bold>133b</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-07078-f038">Figure 38</xref>) exhibit considerable antiviral properties. Compounds with 1-methyl-1
 <italic>H</italic>-imidazole-2(3
 <italic>H</italic>)-thione 
 <bold>133c</bold> and 1,2,4-triazole 
 <bold>133d</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-07078-f038">Figure 38</xref>) fragments should be included as heterocyclic (–)-borneol derivatives exhibiting high antiviral activity. Compound 
 <bold>133a</bold> containing benzoxazole-2-thiol fragment shows significant antiulcer activity. The examination of the gastric mucosa of the animals treated with 
 <bold>133a</bold> (–)-borneol derivative prior to the indomethacin administration demonstrated a considerably reduced ulceration rate (PI 0.8) in comparison with the animals of the control group (PI 5.0). The results indicated that the antiulcer activity score of compound 
 <bold>133a</bold> (AA with the value of 6.5) was higher than the same score for the reference compound (AA with a value of 3.8). While considering the analgesic activity of the presented (–)-borneol derivatives only compound 
 <bold>133d</bold> tends to induce hyperalgesia, reducing the time of animal pain response. Some compounds of the large group of (1
 <italic>S</italic>,2
 <italic>R</italic>,4
 <italic>S</italic>)-1,7,7-trimethylbicyclo[2.2.1]-heptan-2-yl 2-chloroacetates and (1
 <italic>S</italic>,2
 <italic>R</italic>,4
 <italic>S</italic>)-1,7,7-trimethylbicyclo[2.2.1]heptan-2-yl 3-chloropropanoates combined with various 
 <italic>N</italic>- and 
 <italic>S</italic>-nucleophiles exhibit promising antiviral and antiulcer activity. Therefore, those heterocyclic (–)-borneol derivatives should be considered as important and highly encouraging compounds for further development of more potent inhibitors of influenza viruses and antiulcer agents.
</p>
