<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The borneol-based polymers are hydrophobic and noncytotoxic, which can significantly improve the cell adhesion ability [
 <xref rid="B121-ijms-21-07078" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-ijms-21-07078" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]; on the other hand, borneol isomers on the material surface contribute to the surface bacterial resistance properties [
 <xref rid="B119-ijms-21-07078" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-ijms-21-07078" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Due to those data, Meng et al. [
 <xref rid="B123-ijms-21-07078" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>] proposed polymerization with borneol based monomer, assuming that the hydrophobicity of zwitterionic polymers might increase, which will promote their cell adhesion ability without compromising their bacterial resistance properties. For this purpose, they synthesized hydrophobized zwitterionic copolymer P-(SBMA-
 <italic>co</italic>-DMA-
 <italic>co</italic>-ISA) (PSDI) (compound 
 <bold>149</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-07078-f043">Figure 43</xref>), containing borneol based segment isobornyl acrylate (ISA) and zwitterionic moiety SBMA was prepared by sulfonation of P(DMA-
 <italic>co</italic>-ISA) (PDI). Together with tannic acid (TA), PSDI colloidal particles (CPs) were deposited onto the Ti alloy surface by electrophoretic deposition to form zwitterionic-based coatings. Due to the synergistic effect between the SBMA and chiral ISA functional units, tested composite coatings can effectively inhibit the adhesion of Gram-negative (
 <italic>E. coli</italic>) and -positive bacteria (
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>). Furthermore, cells can adhere and grow on the surface of CP-TA composite coating as a result of the appropriate hydrophobicity provided by the chiral monoterpene moiety. Meng et al., in their work, presented a new strategy for preparing zwitterionic-based multifunctional coating. The proposed composite coatings have great potential for metal implant surface modification to prevent bacterial infections.
</p>
