<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phytoconstituents of 
 <italic>Nigella</italic> may vary even within the same species and this is related to many factors such as growing and climatic conditions, location, different organs of the plants and the extraction methods used (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Edris, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr">Manju et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">Saxena et al., 2017</xref>) (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Secondary metabolites, compounds which are not directly related to the development, growth and reproduction of plants but they have significant performance in chemical communication, primary defense against biotic and abiotic stress (
 <xref rid="B226" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar and Shetty, 2014</xref>) and also in epigenetic memory. The chemical composition may vary also during development stage and this was confirmed by 
 <xref rid="B224" ref-type="bibr">Zribi et al. (2014)</xref> who demonstrated that the total phenolics, flavonoids, flavonols and flavones, alkaloids and proanthocyanidins contents of Tunisian and Indian 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> aqueous extracts were the highest in the vegetative stage. Moreover, the aerial parts from the two varieties were richer in total phenolics and flavonoids, including flavonols, flavones and proanthocyanidins, than seeds. Salinity is also another factor that greatly influenced the phenolic composition of 
 <italic>Nigella</italic> seeds; e.g. generally the content of certain phenolic compounds decreased, including the major one vanillic acid (45), while the content of 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamic acid (53), quercetin (38), and apigenin (54) increased. This was related with a decrease of the antioxidant activity (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Bourgou et al., 2010a</xref>). Today, this is essential information since water scarcity and salinization of arable lands may occur in a future scenario exposed to drastic changes caused by climate (
 <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr">Selim et al., 2019</xref>), affecting not only crop growth but also its phytochemical content and antioxidant properties.
</p>
