<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because too many environmental variables are not conducive to the prediction of the model, this study combined the knife-cutting method in the MaxEnt software (
 <uri xlink:href="http://biodiversityinformatics.amnh.org/open" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://biodiversityinformatics.amnh.org/open</uri> source/Maxent, version 3.4.1) and the geographic detector software (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.geodetector.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.geodetector.org/</uri>) to eliminate the environmental variables that make little contribution to the prediction results of the MaxEnt model. The specific operation steps of the geographic detector model were as follows: taking the species distribution point as the dependent variable and 21 environmental variables as independent variables, the 21 environmental variables were divided into five categories using the natural breakpoint method. Then, a 10 × 10 km fishing net with a total of 6729 points was used in ArcGIS10.5, and the dependent variable was matched with the independent variable via the fishing net. Factor detection analysis was carried out to obtain the size of the influence of each environmental variable (i.e., the q value, where a higher 
 <italic>q</italic> value indicates greater influence of the factor) and the factor explanatory power value (the higher the 
 <italic>p</italic> value, the smaller the explanatory power of the element). The environmental variables with a 
 <italic>q</italic> value greater than 0.1 were screened out. Compared with the results of the knife cutting method in the MaxEnt software, 10 environment variables were selected for subsequent modelling (
 <xref rid="insects-12-00092-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The temperature and rainfall values of these bioclimatic variables were derived from each month and produced numerous biologically significant variables, which could be broadly divided into three categories: first, annual trends (e.g., annual mean temperature, annual precipitation); second, seasonality (e.g., annual temperature difference and precipitation); and third, extreme or restrictive environmental factors (for example, temperatures in the coldest and hottest months, and precipitation in wet and dry seasons). Because the comprehensive effects of a variety of bioclimatic variables can be considered, they are often used to predict species distribution and related ecological modeling techniques [
 <xref rid="B35-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
