<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A wetland invasive of European origin, 
 <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> L. (Lythraceae) is a tristylous, perennial herb that has undergone a relatively rapid expansion throughout North America, following multiple introductions for horticulture during the 19th and 20th centuries. Flowers are self‐incompatible and are mainly pollinated by bees. Each flowering stem can produce up to ~100,000 seeds (Montague, Barrett, &amp; Eckert, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Although 
 <italic>L. salicaria's</italic> North American lifespan is not well‐documented, genets persist for multiple years even under severe herbivory, and the same plant can regrow from its rootstock after not producing any above‐ground biomass the previous year (Thompson, Stuckey, &amp; Thompson, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>). As such, any differences between populations with different exposure to biocontrol would likely be due largely to genotype sorting, although we note that previous studies have found that 
 <italic>L. salicaria</italic> has rapidly (i.e. within &lt; 50 years) evolved significant local adaptation to climatic variation associated with latitude (Colautti, Agren, &amp; Anderson, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). In the early 1990s, in response to concerns about the impact of 
 <italic>L</italic>. s
 <italic>alicaria</italic> on the integrity of wetland ecosystems (Anderson, 1995), several North American governments, including the Canadian province of Ontario, introduced a pair of specialist leaf‐eating beetles from the species’ European range for the purpose of biocontrol. In our study region, 
 <italic>Neogalerucella</italic> spp. typically complete two generations in a single growing season: mid‐ to late‐spring larval feeding can strongly impact growth, plant architecture and reproduction, while the subsequent, mid‐summer generation also feeds on developing inflorescences (Dech &amp; Nosko, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>), directly impacting fitness. 
 <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> plants exposed to feeding by 
 <italic>Neogalerucella</italic> spp. exhibit a defensive strategy most consistent with tolerance, including compensatory growth and delayed phenology (Quiram, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Thomsen &amp; Sargent, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Follow‐up studies on the success of North American biological control programmes have reported a mixture of outcomes, with some exposed 
 <italic>L. salicaria</italic> populations exhibiting declines in plant size, flowering and abundance, but not others (Denoth &amp; Myers, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Grevstad, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Hovick &amp; Carson, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; St. Louis, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
</p>
