<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">HydroSOStainable</italic> products have been defined as fruits and vegetables cultivated under controlled deficit irrigation treatments, which give them differentiating characteristics that make them unique and environmentally friendly [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">HydroSOStainable</italic> products provide special characteristics to the final commercial commodities, which are richer in some bioactive compounds and have a higher intensity of key sensory attributes, making them attractive for consumers [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Several products from olive trees under RDI are being studied as 
 <italic class="italic">hydroSOStainable</italic>; for instance, “Manzanilla” table olives have been studied [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Arbequina olive oil under water deficit techniques have been previously studied [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], but there is not a clear trend on the effect of irrigation on its quality. At this time, there is not a systematic body of knowledge considering agronomic practices, phenological stage during RDI, climatic constraints, etc. to have a full understanding of the effects of RDI on “Arbequina” oil quality, and further studies looking for the best water saving technique are necessary.
</p>
