<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0205">The present examination is to investigate the presence of antidiarrheal and antimicrobial potentiality of 
 <italic>C. digyna</italic>. Laxity of the guts can be deposited as the consequent defecation of feces at low consistency which might be occurred because of impairment in the vehicle of water and electrolytes in the intestinal tract. Diarrhea results from the quick development of fecal stuff through the large intestine [
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. To introduce diarrhea, castor oil was used in all methods because castor oil induces diarrhea as a result of its active metabolite, ricinoleic acid which is liberated by the action of lipases in the upper part of the small intestine [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. The activity of castor oil is originated by ricinoleic acid, a hydroxylated fatty acid exempt from castor oil by intestinal lipases. Despite the wide-spread application of castor oil in traditional and folk medicine, the molecular mechanism by which ricinoleic acid acts still remain unknown. Prostaglandin E2 receptor 3 (EP3) receptor is specifically activated by ricinoleic acid and that it mediates the pharmacological effects of castor oil. In mice, due to lack of EP3 receptors, the laxative effect and the uterus contraction-induced upon ricinoleic acid are absent. Although a conditional deletion of the EP3 receptor gene in intestinal epithelial cells did not affect castor oil-induced diarrhea, mice lacking EP3 receptors only in smooth-muscle cells were unresponsive to this drug. Thus, the castor oil metabolite ricinoleic acid activates intestinal and uterine smooth-muscle cells via EP3 prostanoid receptors. These findings identify the cellular and molecular mechanism underlying the pharmacological effects of castor oil and indicate the role of the EP3 receptor as a target to induce laxative effects [
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Castor oil-induced diarrhea has been possessed to evaluate the onset of diarrhea, the number of wet feces, and the frequency of feces. In our investigation, MECD significantly delayed the fecal time, retarded the weight of the wet feces, and reduced the frequency of wet feces upon castor oil-induced diarrhea was produced in Swiss albino mice. In the castor oil-induced diarrhea the percent of inhibition rate of feces was mostly found in 200 mg/kg and 400 mg/kg and shows dose-dependant potentiality upon contrast with the control. The effect of MECD 400 mg/kg is likely to the standard drug loperamide (3 mg/kg).As a corollary, the retardation of onset of diarrhea, weight of wet feces and frequency of diarrhea by administering MECD indicates the existence of antidiarrheal potentiality in castor oil induced diarrheal model.
</p>
