<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0215">The charcoal induced intestinal transit in mice implicated that the mean separation gone by the charcoal plug was greatest for the control. During the analysis, the charcoal meal method was chosen to pursue the displacement of the gastrointestinal content due to the fact that the retardation of gastrointestinal motility is one mechanism by which numerous antidiarrheal agents can act [
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Activated charcoal, employed in the gastrointestinal transit model as a marker, has been followed for more than 60 years as a basic tool for assessing the impact of laxatives [
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. This strategy is a pointer of the maximum distance moved by the marker (activated charcoal) through its administration and the appraisal of its way in the small intestinal tract over a period of time [
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. In the current experiment, MECD suppressed the conduction of charcoal marker in a dose-dependent pathway. The peristaltic index and distance travel by the charcoal meal was least in the MECD 200 mg/kg and 400 mg/kg of body weight respectively upon contrasted with the control. This finding proposed that the extracts act on all parts of the intestinal tract. Retardation in the motility of gut muscles enforces the remain of substances in the intestinal tract [
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. This permits better water absorption from the gut. Medications that restrain intestinal transit in pathophysiological states are compelling in relieving diarrhea [
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. It is however presumed that the decrease in the intestinal propulsive development in the gastrointestinal transit model might be because of antispasmodic properties of the test extract [
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Secondary metabolites, for example, flavonoids and tannins are accounted for to have antidiarrheal movement because of their capacity to restrain intestinal motility. Subsequently, the significant anti-motility impact of the extract might be identified with the synergistic inhibitory impact of flavonoids and tannins on charcoal induced gastrointestinal transit test [
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
