<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0220">The disclosure of effective antibiotics, vaccines, and different items or methods have diminished the overwhelming effect of infectious illnesses and improved personal satisfaction. However, the adequacy of numerous antibiotics is being threatened by the rise of microbial resistance from existing chemotherapeutic agents due to their aimless and inappropriate use [
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Even though pharmaceutical companies have introduced several new antibiotics in the last years, resistance to these drugs has elevated at a high rate and has now become a global concern [
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The infliction of some antibiotics is affiliated with adverse effects, including immune suppression, allergy, and hypersensitivity [
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Acceptance of medicines from such plant origins as an elective type of healthcare is expanding due to their promising source of novel antibiotic models. Moreover, these ingredients may have various mechanisms of action than conventional medications and could be of clinical significance to improve healthcare [
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. The plant-determined natural product speaks to an appealing source of antimicrobial agents since they are regular and affordable, particularly for bucolic societies [
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Our study was to assess the antimicrobial effect of MECD and from the investigation, it was noticed that MECD is highly susceptible to 
 <italic>Bacillus azotoformans, Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic> strains, less susceptible to 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> and rest of the gram-positive and negative bacteria are moderately susceptible strains against MECD. As well as, MECD is susceptible to some pathogenic fungi (
 <italic>Candida albicans, Cryptococcus neoformans, Blastomyces dermatitidis, Trichoderma</italic> spp). The Diameter of zone of inhibition (mm) of 
 <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> is most likely to the standard drug which was applied to conduct the antifungal test. Some of the phytochemical compounds e.g., glycoside, saponin, tannin, flavonoids, terpenoid, and alkaloids, have been reported to have antimicrobial activity [
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. From our phytochemical evaluation we have noticed the presence of alkaloid, carbohydrate, flavonoids, saponin, tannin, glycosides, potein, and phenolic compounds. Therefore, several gram positive and gram negative bacteria as well as some fungi showed susceptibility against MECD. So it can be inferred that MECD can be the source of antimicrobial agents.
</p>
