<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The vigorous asexual ramets (abundance) of aquatic invasive plants allow them to rapidly and fully occupy the available niche space, limiting the establishment of other native aquatic plants and, thus, dramatically decreasing aquatic plant diversity (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Stiers and Triest, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2019</xref>). However, in our study, height did not contribute to 
 <italic>E. crassipes</italic> invasiveness, likely because there were several tall hydrophytes in the invaded community (
 <italic>e.g.</italic>, 
 <italic>P. distichum</italic>, 
 <italic>B. syzigachne</italic>, 
 <italic>A. calamus</italic>, 
 <italic>L. hexandra</italic>), which could disrupt the shading effect of 
 <italic>E. crassipes.</italic> The plant C:N ratio may be correlated with defense ability, affecting plant diversity in invaded communities (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Sardans et al., 2017</xref>). An increasing C:N ratio usually leads to higher total phenolic contents and leaf toughness of invasive plants, which would decrease plant nutritional quality and, thus, reduce palatability to herbivores, facilitating invasiveness and increasing the negative impacts on native species (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Cronin et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Petruzzella et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Zerche et al., 2019</xref>). This is consistent with the negative effect of a higher leaf C:N ratio of 
 <italic>E. crassipes</italic> on native plant diversity observed in our study. Similar phenomena have been found in other aquatic invasive plants such as 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> in China and 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> in Europe (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Cronin et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Qiao et al., 2018</xref>). The C:N ratio of 
 <italic>E. crassipes</italic> was weakly affected by the abiotic environment, and this internal stability of ecological stoichiometry might be one of the important mechanisms contributing to aquatic plant invasions (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez et al., 2010</xref>).
</p>
