<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.2.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. Isolation of Compounds</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">(i) Isolation of Volatile Compounds</span>. The essential oil of sample KN2 was received by Clevenger distillation using 15.00 g of sample KN2. The distillate A (35 mL), consisting of essential oil and aromatic water, was collected in a flask, while 2 ml of pure essential oil B was collected separately and analyzed through GC-MS.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the distillate A was added 2 g of NaCl and the solution was cooled in ice water and transferred to a separatory funnel with 50 mL of hexane. The aqueous layer A1 was discarded, and the organic layer A2 was evaporated via rotary evaporation (R-200, Büchi, Flawil, Switzerland) to yield an oily extract C. In the extract C 15 mL hexane and 25 mL of 5% NaOH were added for further liquid-liquid separation. The aqueous layer C1 contained the sodium salt of eugenol, while the eugenol acetate, 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, myristicin, and cinnamic aldehyde remained in the organic layer C2.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Layer C1 was then evaporated and cooled on ice, while 50 mL of 6 M HCl was added to the solution, ensuring that the solution was acidic and it was extracted with 15 mL hexane yielding eugenol, which was identified through NMR, GC-MS, and comparison with literature data [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The organic layer C2 was chromatographed through preparative thin layer chromatography on silica gel plates using cyclohexane/dichloromethane 30/70 v/v as mobile phase, yielding cinnamic aldehyde, myristicin, cinnamyl alcohol, alpha-terpinyl acetate, and 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene. All compounds were identified through NMR and/or GC-MS and literature data [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>, 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">(ii) Isolation of Azo Dyes. </span>The freeze-dried herbal teas of KN1 and KN2 (454 mg), which presented the same chromatographic profile, and the freeze-dried herbal tea of KN3 (450 mg) were separately further purified using a medium pressure liquid chromatography MPLC (Borosilikat 3.3 Code Number 28147, Büchi, Flawil, Switzerland) packed with reversed phase silica gel (RP18) and two Series 1 pumps with flow speed 8 mL/min, eluted with decreasing polarities: H
  <sub>2</sub>O/MeOH (100/0 to 0/100). Azorubine was isolated and identified from the water fraction of KN1-KN2 and amaranth from KN3. The isolated compounds were identified by NMR and literature data [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
