<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bacterial endophytes are present in the flowers, leaves, roots, seeds, and stems of plants (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Compant et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Elmagzob et al., 2019</xref>). Bacterial colonization occurs at particular stages of plant development, and even at the seed stage, there may already be a stable endophytic bacterial community (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Mocali et al., 2003</xref>). These endophytes use the plant’s internal environment (i.e., the endosphere) as a unique niche to protect themselves from drastic altered external environments (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar et al., 2011</xref>). The evolution of these highly specialized symbioses requires tight coordination of physiology, structure, and life cycles between the partner organisms (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Saikkonen et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Reinhold-Hurek and Hurek, 2011</xref>), and the resulting partnership benefits both species (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Aravind et al., 2010</xref>). Such mutualisms serve essential functions in terrestrial ecosystems: host plants house and protect the endophytes, which in turn promote the growth of plants via nitrogen fixation, phosphorus enrichment, and the synthesis of phytohormones (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Borah et al., 2019</xref>). Moreover, pathogenic microorganisms and endophytic bacteria occupy the same niche within plants, and inoculation with endophytic bacteria is a suitable method to biologically control pathogens (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar et al., 2011</xref>). Medicinal plants-isolated bacterial endophytes can produce bioactive metabolites and to significantly induce the secondary metabolite production by their host plants. The host-endophyte relationship can be regarded as a flexible, dynamic interaction, in which endophytic bacteria alter their gene expression or produce different metabolites based on small changes in host plant growth and vice versa (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Ek-Ramos et al., 2019</xref>). Despite their importance to the plant micro-ecosystem, bacterial endophytes’ relationship to their host plants remains poorly understood (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Tiwari et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
