<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Thus, considerable merit exists in identifying a suitable fatty acid blood compartment for assessment of nutritional status or recent intake concentrations in cross-sectional trials. An important consideration in both cross-sectional and prospective studies is to consider the use of circulating fatty acid concentrations as surrogates for fat intakes, but in the context of the limitation of interindividual variations. It has been shown that substantial variations exist not only in circulating fatty acid profiles across individuals, but also in their degree of responsiveness to dietary fat challenges. Some of this variability is random, but some can be ascribed to a range of factors, including baseline dietary patterns (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>). This includes lifestyle behaviors such as smoking, alcohol, and physical activity (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44–46</xref>), but also age (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>), sex (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>), and the increasingly recognized influence of genetics (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>). The role of genetic polymorphisms related to fatty acid interconversion, and ultimately concentrations in circulation, following dietary interventions has been demonstrated and is the focus of ongoing research (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49–51</xref>). For EPA + DHA blood concentrations, fish and fish oil consumption accounts for an estimated 47% of variability, whereas other factors, such as age and smoking, account for ∼10% of variability combined (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>). Analysis of the variation around EPA and DHA fatty acid measurements generally gives a CV of &lt;5% (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>).
</p>
