<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the research effort to identify and explain the success of invasive species in their new range, evolutionary explanations for invasiveness are rarely invoked. Only a small proportion of introduced species succeed in their new range, some attaining greater individual size or fitness or establishing populations of greater numbers or densities, than what might be predicted from their native range (Hinz and Schwarzlaender 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">2004</xref>; but see Thebaud and Simberloff 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b70">2001</xref>). Bossdorf et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">2005</xref>) divided research into invasiveness as seeking either an ecological or an evolutionary explanation and determined that research efforts have been heavily skewed toward identifying ecological explanations. More recently, 26 of the 29 hypotheses of plant invasion identified in a recent review (Catford et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">2009</xref>) explain invasions as the result of static plant traits, suitability of the invaded environment, or ecological interactions between species traits and environments. Studies that link invasions to evolutionary interactions between invasive plants and their new environment represent a small fraction of invasive species research (Lee 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">2002</xref>; Kollmann and Banuelos 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">2004</xref>; Prentis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">2008</xref>; Alexander et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">2009</xref>; Allan and Pannell 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">2009</xref>; Hornoy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">2011</xref>; Haider et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">2012</xref>), despite the importance of local adaptation in determining the distribution and success of some native plant species (Macel et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">2007</xref>; Alvarez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">2009</xref>; Kawakami et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">2011</xref>). The most prominent of the hypotheses of plant invasion which invoke evolution of invasives, the Evolution of Increased Competitive Ability (EICA) hypothesis (Blossey and Nötzold 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">1995</xref>), proposes that evolution of invasive populations occurs as a release from coevolved herbivores, not in response to selective factors in the environment of the new range.
</p>
