<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Chinese scholars of the early seventeenth century knew that the region of Peru in Spanish America was rich in silver ore. In 1602, the world map 
 <italic>Kunyu Wanguo quantu</italic> 坤輿萬國全圖 (Map of the Myriad Countries of the World; 1602; Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>) of the Italian Jesuit missionary, Matteo Ricci (1552–1610), had been printed. Ricci had prepared it for China’s Wanli Emperor (r. 1572–1620). With this map, Ricci introduced Western geographical knowledge, including information about the new Spanish colonies in America to the Chinese. The map had a great impact in China; it was published in five successive editions, attracting the attention of many scholars. Of particular interest is a section on Peru (Bolu 孛露), see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>. Some 20 years later, Giulio Aleni (1582
 <italic>–</italic>1649), following Ricci’s format, drew his own map 
 <italic>Wanguo quantu</italic> 萬國全圖, included in his geographical treatise 
 <italic>Zhifang waiji</italic> 職方外紀 (Record of the Countries Beyond Imperial Administrations; 1623). Aleni also mentions Peru (Bolu 孛露), and speaks of “extremely rich gold and silver” ores (
 <italic>gu jinyin zuiduo</italic> 故金銀最多) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Under the entry “Jinjiaxila 金加西蠟”, referring to “Castilia Del’oro”, that is, the new Spanish colonies in Latin America, silver and gold reserves are mentioned that “rank first under Heaven” (
 <italic>tianxia cheng shou</italic> 天下稱首), and “at the foot of the mountain there is a city, called ‘Silver City’” (Yincheng 銀城) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This is definitely a reference to Potosí, rendered on his map as Boduoxi 波多西 Mountain, but not described in the text, [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b, c. Rumours even had it that a certain Mount Jiyi 機易山 (also 加溢, 交逸 or 佳逸), probably Cavite (?), the Spanish harbour on Luzon, would produce huge amounts of gold and silver [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The military official Yan Yinglong 閻應龍, and a local merchant called Zhang Yi 張嶷, memorialized the emperor that a certain Mount Jiyi “produces gold and silver, and by proceeding there by ship to wash for it, it will be possible to obtain 100,000 
 <italic>liang</italic> of gold and 300,000 
 <italic>liang</italic> of silver every year” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Also 
 <italic>Dongxiyang kao</italic> speaks of gold and silver as local products [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Interestingly, as we will see below, in addition to the references to silver, the just mentioned maps also speak of “balsam”. Why should balsam be mentioned on maps portraying the East Asian maritime world? 
</p>
