<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">MUFA contain a single double bond in the 
 <italic class="italic">cis-</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-configuration. Linseed oil inclusion into diet causes changes in the MUFA profile in MLD, in particular reduces oleic acid (C18:1 
 <italic class="italic">cis-9</italic>), which is the main MUFA. Bessa et al [
 <xref rid="b12-ajas-18-0482" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] also found that linseed oil in diets decreased C18:1 
 <italic class="italic">cis-9</italic> concentration in 
 <italic class="italic">longissimus thoracis</italic> in comparison to un-supplemented diets. Oleic acid reduction in ruminant tissues is often associated with PUFA supplementation in the ration [
 <xref rid="b25-ajas-18-0482" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Such situation can be due to either the absence of C18:0 (stearic acid) desaturated by Δ
 <sup class="sup">9</sup>-desaturase or the inhibition of enzyme activity by high PUFA contents [
 <xref rid="b26-ajas-18-0482" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. In our experiment, the quantity of stearic acid in the ration was low, thus its origin here was primarily derived from endogenous 
 <italic class="italic">de novo</italic> synthesis, and as an end-product of C18 PUFA biohydrogenation in the rumen [
 <xref rid="b12-ajas-18-0482" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. In PUFA-supplemented ruminant diets, 
 <italic class="italic">de novo</italic> FA synthesis is reduced; PUFA biohydrogenation becomes incomplete, and biohydrogenation intermediates start to accumulate, causing lower C18:0 yield, as shown in the current study. Moreover, Mosley et al [
 <xref rid="b27-ajas-18-0482" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] documented in the 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> study a direct octadeceonoate 
 <italic class="italic">cis-trans</italic> isomerization in mixed rumen bacteria, capable of converting oleic acid into 
 <italic class="italic">trans-11</italic> as well as other 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic> isomers. In our study, insignificant increase of C18:1 
 <italic class="italic">trans 11</italic> in MLD and MS was observed when lambs were fed linseed oil in comparison to other diet. However, C18:0 reduction in MLD of lambs fed linseed oil was small. In contrast to our findings, Gallardo et al [
 <xref rid="b22-ajas-18-0482" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] did not find any significant changes in C18:1 
 <italic class="italic">cis-9</italic> concentrations of intramuscular fat of lamb sucking ewes fed diets supplemented with linseed oil.
</p>
