<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_SJBS1794 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEgr7 jpg ?><?FILEgr8 jpg ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?FILEsi2 svg ?><?FILEsi3 svg ?><?FILEsi4 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Biol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi J Biol Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1319-562X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2213-7106</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7499370</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1319-562X(20)30299-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.07.008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Preparative HPLC fraction of <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> essential oil against biofilm forming <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Xinjun</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010"><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>Govindan Nadar</given-names></name><email>rajivgandhimicro@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015"><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>Govindan</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020"><name><surname>Alharbi</surname><given-names>Naiyf S.</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025"><name><surname>Kadaikunnan</surname><given-names>Shine</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030"><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>Jamal M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au035"><name><surname>Almanaa</surname><given-names>Taghreed N.</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au040"><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>Natesan</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au045"><name><surname>viji</surname><given-names>Rajan</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Department of Pediatrics, 3201 Hospital, No. 783, Tianhan Avenue, Hantai District, Hanzhong, Shaanxi 723000, China</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Medical Microbiology and Marine Pharmacology Laboratory, Department of Marine Science, Bharathidasan University, Tiruchirappalli, Tamil Nadu 620024, India</aff><aff id="af015"><label>c</label>Department of Botany and Microbiology, College of Science, King Saud University, Riyadh 11451, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="af020"><label>d</label>Ministry of Education Key Laboratory of Water and Sediment Science, School of Environment, Beijing Normal University, Beijing 100875, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Marine Sciences, Bharathidasan University, Tiruchirappalli, Tamil Nadu, India. <email>rajivgandhimicro@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2853</fpage><lpage>2862</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab005"><p>Recent years <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (<italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>) biofilm formation (BF) is emerging thread worldwide. For tackling this problem, we have chosen Hibiscus rosa-. pneumoniae. The HPLC purified essential oils (EOs sinensis (H. rosa-sinensis) (HRS) to inhibit the BF K) of H. rosa-sinensis was performed against BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> and showed concentration dependent biofilm inhibition. At the MBIC of EOs (90&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/ml), the biofilm inhibition was showed at 92% against selected BF <italic>K. Pneumoniae</italic>. The biofilm metabolic assay, exopolysaccharide quantification and hydrophobicity index variation results exhibited with 88%, 92% and 89% reduction at 90&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL was observed respectively. In addition, the morphological modification of MBIC treated <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> was clearly viewed by scanning electron microscope (SEM). Overall, all the invitro experiments result were confirmed that the MBIC of H. rosa-sinensis EOs was very effective against BF <italic>K. pneumonia.</italic></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kg005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Biofilm bacteria</kwd><kwd>Medicinal plant</kwd><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd>Anti-biofilm activity</kwd><kwd>Exopolysaccharide</kwd><kwd>Scanning electron microscope</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0005">Recent years, biofilm forming (BF) Gram negative bacteria (GNB) has attracted more attention due to their potential risk of antimicrobial resistance and virulence factor production (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Rubini et al., 2018</xref>). Biofilm formation now being considered as a serious problem and it can be developing the resistant against antiseptic agents (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Doulgeraki et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2018a</xref>). In fact, the discovery of novel antimicrobial agents for eradicate the biofilm formation is a worldwide challenge. Recently, plant essential oil has more potential for solving the problem of biofilm producing pathogens (<xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Francesco et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Eman et al., 2018</xref>). EO acts as an excellent antimicrobial agent due to the low viscosity, high capability, excellent surface nature, which allows them to interact with target (<xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Norhaizan et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2018a</xref>).</p><p id="p0010">In this context, we have chosen excellent biomedical properties of HRS for inhibit the BF <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (<italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>). Among the various parts of HRS, the petals, flowers and seeds are frequently produced more therapeutic advances such as antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral, anticancer, larvicidal, antidiabetics, antioxidant properties (<xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Kartinah et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Lingesh et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Maralit Bruan and Tianco, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Elemar Gomes et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Gandhi et al., 2019</xref>). In addition, antihypertensive, anti-inflammatory, antipyretic, antidiarrhoeic and immunomodulator properties of the HRS have been screened from various pharmaceutical industry (<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Begum and Younus, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Abdullah et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Malinowski et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Eman et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Rubini et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">In India, the petals and roots of the <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> (HRS) can be used as food and fiber (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Kaleemullah et al., 2017</xref>). The calyces or flower pots are used as ingredients in various edible items jam, candy, pickles and also used in drinking items including tea, wine (<xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Ruban and Gajalakshmi, 2012</xref>). Among this plant, red flowered HRS is mostly used in our entire world due to the production of some essential chemicals (<xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Pillai and Mini, 2018</xref>). Among these species, 15 species of HRS have more biological activities against drug resistant pathogens were reported with some phytochemical evidences (<xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Vijayakumar et al., 2018</xref>). Recently, the ethanopharmacological survey was reported that the HRS as a important medicinal plant that has the anti-asthmatic, detoxifier, anti-hypertensive and anti-cancer, wound healing properties. In addition, it is a traditional medicine in India for anti-diabetics and anti-oxidant activities (<xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Ansari et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">The seeds of the HRS are mostly used for oil production in many countries, and phytochemical compositions of the oils are applied in various biological process. In the daily meals of West Africa, the HRS leaves and powders are used frequently (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Hui-Min et al., 2017</xref>). In addition, the seeds of the HRS is applied to recover high quantifies in various industries like pharmaceutical and food. The HRS oils are mainly synthesized from plastids (<xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Elemar Gomes et al., 2010</xref>). Also, the HRS oil composed with tremendous chemical compounds including terpenes, fats and flavonoid aglycones (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Gandhi et al., 2019</xref>). In addition, the more polysaccharide composition of the HRS as a format of secretory idioblasts oil or mucilage, which were associated with the parenchyma of HRS. Plant mucilages are complex polysaccharide polymers, it has high molecular weight. All the mucilages are either acidic or neutral polysaccharides (<xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Lingesh et al., 2018</xref>). Hundred years, EOs as a natural medicine for various serious infections including multi drug resistant bacterial infections. Previously the reported <italic>Origanum majorana</italic>, <italic>Thymus zygis</italic>, <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>, <italic>Juniperus communis</italic> and <italic>Zengiber officinale</italic> Eos have excellent inhibitory effect against biofilm formation (<xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Rihab et al., 2019</xref>). Eos has very low toxicity compared with other phytochemical compounds and also, it damaged the bacterial cell wall through hydrophobic channels. Finally, it could enter the inside of the cells and destroy the cell cycle process and cytoplasmic leakages materials (<xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Erika et al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, the current study was initiated an attempt to assess a Chinesh medicinal plant <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> EOs as a potential anti-biofilm agent against CR biofilm forming <italic>K. pneumoniae.</italic></p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Collection of samples</title><p id="p0025">The BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> strain was obtained from Department of Marine Science Bharathidasan University, Tiruchirappalli, Tamil Nadu, and India. All the chemicals, plates and antibiotic discs of this study were purchased from Sigma Aldrich, China.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Purification of EO and hydrosol extraction</title><p id="p0030">The healthy seeds of <italic>HRS</italic> were collected from tropical environment of Bharathidasan University campus, Tamil Nadu, India. The collected plant seeds were stored at 4 &#x000b0;C for further use. To remove the surface contaminants, the seeds were carefully washed with double distilled water (D.DH<sub>2</sub>O) and dried at room temperature with shade for approximately 10&#x0202f;days. After incubation, the seeds were crushed well and maintained in hydro distillation using n-hexane (<xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Jessica et al., 2018</xref>). In this method, 100&#x0202f;g of topped sample was mixed into the 1 L water of conical flask at 3&#x02013;4&#x0202f;h distilled. After time interval, the obtained essential oil solution was maintained in sodium sulfate for drying and filtered for excluding the n-hexane under reduced pressure.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis</title><p id="p0035">GC-MS analysis of <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> EO was followed by the previous report of <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Ruhomally et al. (2015)</xref>. Briefly, 1L of the sample was mixed with 1% dichloromethane which injected with split ratio of 1:20 using EI mode of 70&#x0202f;eV (Agilent technologies) attached with split injector and 220 &#x000b0;C as an injector temperature. Continuously, 5% phenyl followed by 95% dimethylpolysiloxane with 30&#x0202f;m&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;0.25&#x0202f;mm&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;0.25&#x0202f;&#x003bc;m of HP-5MS was used for separate the chemical components. 1&#x0202f;mL/min of helium carrier gas was used for this process and 60 to 240&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C at a rate of 3&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C&#x0202f;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> as a oven temperature. Finally, 1&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of EO was used as a injected volume and diluted with chloroform (1:10).</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Anti-bacterial activity</title><p id="p0040">Anti-bacterial activity of the purified EO was evaluated against selected BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> by agar well diffusion method (<xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Ebani et al., 2018</xref>). Briefly, the 24&#x0202f;h old BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> culture was spread on the muller hinton agar plate (MHA). The wells were cut by using sterile gel borer and different concentration 10, 25, 50&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of EO was added into the well. Whereas, 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of methanol and third generation cephalosporin ceftazidime was served as a positive controls and methanol added well was acted as a negative control at 37&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x0202f;h. After incubation, the zone of inhibition around the wells was noted in diameter and the experiment was conducted in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Purification of essential oil by preparative high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) method</title><p id="p0045">Anti-bacterial effect of the EO was measured by analytical HPLC for detection of active EO fraction (AEOF). The mobile phase of acetonitrile:methanol:ammonium acetate:water (45:10:10:35) was used for purify the EOs. After, all essential oil fractions were purified separately using preparative HPLC. The agar well diffusion method was used to detect the purified EOs fraction at 37&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x0202f;h. Whereas, third generation chaphalosporin chephalosporin piperacillin/tazobactam and methanol was served as a positive and negative control respectively. Finally, active essential oil fraction (AEOF) was separated by preparative HPLC and proved by analytical HPLC followed by lyophilization at 40 &#x000b0;C for study. The instrument of preparatory HPLC was set up with 150&#x0202f;mm&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;4.6&#x0202f;mm of C18 column, linear gradient of 4.6&#x0202f;&#x000b5;m and 1&#x0202f;mL/min flow rate was used. The temperature of 0&#x02013;10&#x0202f;min with 10&#x02013;90% A, 90&#x02013;100% B and 100% C at 10&#x02013;11&#x0202f;min, 11&#x02013;20&#x0202f;min and 15&#x02013;25&#x0202f;min were maintained in gradient elution program. The 20&#x0202f;&#x000b5;L column injected volume at 40 &#x000b0;C temperature was used (<xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2018b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.6</label><title>Minimum biofilm inhibition concentration (MIC)</title><p id="p0050">The biofilm eradication of BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> at different concentration of AEOF was identified by crystal violet staining assay with some modification (<xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Jardak et al., 2017</xref>). Briefly, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 70, 80, 90, 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL of EOs was added into previously filled TSB containing 24-well polystyrene plate and subsequently inoculated 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL of 10<sup>-5</sup> bacterial suspension at 37&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x0202f;h. After incubation, the discarded 24-well plate was rinsed thoroughly with PBS, followed by 0.5% crystal violet solution at 5&#x0202f;min. Next, unstained cells were washed to discard by PBS and solubilized with 2&#x0202f;mL of ethanol and quantified by O.D at 540&#x0202f;nm. Untreated bacterial culture containing well acted as a control.</p><p id="p0055">All the procedure was applied three times and given formula was used to calculate the percentage of biofilm inhibition (PI),<disp-formula id="e0005"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PI</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mn>570</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>nm</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Test</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mn>570</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>nm</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Control</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mn>570</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>nm</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.7</label><title>Biofilm metabolic assay</title><p id="p0060">The viability of bacterial cells in the presence of AEOF at various concentration was detected by 2,3-bis (2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl)-2H-tetrazolium-5- carboxanilide (XTT) reduction method with the modification of <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Anjugam et al., 2018</xref>. Briefly, after removal of non-adherent biofilm cells, 1&#x0202f;mg/mL mixed XTT solution (12.5) was gently added into the 6-well plate. Subsequently, 1&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of fresh standardized menadione acetone solution was added into each well with 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of PBS. Each well were shaken gently and incubated with dark condition at 1&#x0202f;h at 37&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C. Whereas, without addition of AEOF in the pathogen with menadione acetone solution containing well served as control. After incubation, all the wells were calculated by using microtitre plate reader at 570&#x0202f;nm. The test was conducted in triplicate and the result was presented using following Eq,<disp-formula id="e0010"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mtext>D</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mtext>D</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>control</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>2.8</label><title>Exopolysaccharide (EPS) quantification assay</title><p id="p0065">The phenol-sulfuric acid method was adopted in this study to detect the EPS in BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> by <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Maruthupandy et al. (2020)</xref> with some alteration. The BIC of AEOF treated or untreated <italic>K. pneumonia</italic> biofilm culture was collected and centrifuged at 5000&#x0202f;rpm for 10&#x0202f;min. For enzymatic degradation, the pellet was re-suspended in sterile saline solution, followed by 50&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of Pronase E (Hi-Media, India) and vortexed at 30&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x0202f;min. After, 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of trichloroacetic acid was inoculated into precipitate of protein at ice with 1&#x0202f;h. Subsequently, sample was centrifuged at 10,000&#x0202f;rpm for 10&#x0202f;min with cooling temperature. The 10&#x0202f;mL of cold absolute alcohol was added drop wise to precipitate the polysachaaraide quantitatively and kept at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;C for 12&#x0202f;h. After incubation, the sample was centrifuged at 5000&#x0202f;rpm for 20&#x0202f;min for collection of polysaccharides and resuspended in 1&#x0202f;mL of D&#x000b7;H<sub>2</sub>O Further, the sample was digested with 5&#x0202f;mL of H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (98%) into the monosaccharides with continuous vortex. After vortex, 5% phenol (1&#x0202f;mL) was added into recovered material and vortexed for 20&#x0202f;min in water bath. Samples were cooled on ice, and result was read at spectrophotometer (UV-2550, Shimadzu, Japan) at 540&#x0202f;nm wavelength. Dis&#x000b7;H2O served as a blank. In this method, glucose as a standard. The experiment was conducted in triplicate and the result was calculated in inhibition percentage of EPS with following formula<disp-formula id="e0015"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where C<sub>a</sub> is t concentration of the EPS in the sample group, C<sub>b</sub> is the concentration of the EPS in the control group.</p><p id="p0070">Further, the inhibition of EPS was validated through the inoculation of CRA plate result (<xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2018b</xref>). 0.1&#x0202f;mL of 24&#x0202f;h treated culture was directly streaked on the CRA plate at 37&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x0202f;h. After incubation, the CRA plate colonies were calculated based on color variation.</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><label>2.9</label><title>Hydrophobicity index of EO</title><p id="p0075">The effect of AEOF against BF <italic>K. pneumonia</italic> hydrophobicity was evaluated by <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Balasubramanian et al. (2016)</xref>. Briefly, the BIC of AEOF was added in to the test tube with addition of 2&#x0202f;mL old BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> culture<italic>.</italic> Whereas, absence of AEOF was maintained as a control. Then, the sample was measured at 560&#x0202f;nm. Conservatively, 1&#x0202f;mL of misquote sample was mixed 2&#x0202f;min with toluene and vortex vigorously at 37 &#x000b0;C for 10&#x0202f;min to allow the phase separation. After incubation, both the phases were collected separately and aqueous phase was calculated at 560&#x0202f;nm using spectrophotometer and percentage of hydrophobicity was measured using following formula,<disp-formula id="e0020"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>Hydrophobicity</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close="]"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mn>540</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>after</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>vortex</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>OD</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mn>540</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>before</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mtext>vortex</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>2.10</label><title>Morphological damage effect of EO</title><p id="p0080">The shape of the BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> morphology upon AEOF treatment was analyzed by SEM and TEM (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Mehran et al., 2019</xref>). Shortly, the pellet of AEOF treated or untreated biofilm sample was received after centrifugation and washed thrice with 1% PBS. Required amount of suspended culture was taken and inoculated on the sterile cover glass, and the sample was fixed by 4% glutaraldehyde for 4&#x0202f;h. After incubation, the sample was washed two times with sterile PBS. After incubation, the fixed cells were filtered by polycarbonate membrane filters and dehydrated with 30, 40, 50, 60, 70, 80, 90 and 100% ethanol graded series. After dehydration, 1&#x0202f;mL of t-butanol was used and incubated at 1&#x0202f;h for bacterial survival. Next, the t-butanol was altered by fresh t-butanal and incubated in deep freezer with overnight. Further, the cover glass was dried at room temperature and coated with gold&#x02013;palladium metal. Finally, cover glass was viewed under SEM using an accelerating voltage of 20&#x0202f;kV (Shimadzhu, Japan).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>3</label><title>Result and discussion</title><sec id="s0070"><label>3.1</label><title>Purification of essential oil</title><p id="p0085">The hydrosol extraction of EO from <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> more terpenes, oxygenated monoterpenes, monoterpenes hydrocarbon and sesquiterpenes composition by GC-MS (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The highest constituents of the EO were &#x003b1;-terpineol, &#x003b1;-terpinolene, &#x003b1;-pinene, &#x003b2;-pinene, &#x003b1;-terpenyl acetate, spathulenol. Significant amount of other variables were also present in the extract (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table. 1</xref>). Present result was agreed by previous report of <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Norhaizan et al. (2010)</xref>, tropical plant <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> has more oil components were determined by various genetic factors changes. Other promoter and various factors could modify chemical components including soil, fertility, pH, temperature, humidity and other stresses (<xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Kandhare et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Da-Costa-Rocha et al., 2014</xref>). Previously <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Malinowski et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Chou et al., 2019</xref>, reported that the EO production depends on the seasonal variation and various environmental factors. It also increases the common volatile compounds natures due to the stress condition. In our study, the GC-MS report of common volatile and phytochemical compounds were also identified and reported in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Detection of essential oil identification from <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> by GC-MS analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>GC-MS analysis of essential oil form <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> extract.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Peaks</th><th>Essential Oil</th><th>RT</th><th>Molecular Formula</th><th>Total Area</th><th>Area (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>&#x003b1;-Oxide pinene</td><td>5.322</td><td>C10H16O</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>37,933</td><td>0.14</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>N-Nonanol</td><td>5.475</td><td>C9H20O</td><td>138,413</td><td>0.52</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Octanoic acid</td><td>5.512</td><td>C8H16O2</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>121,073</td><td>0.46</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>N-Dodecane</td><td>5.55</td><td>C12H26</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>136,470</td><td>0.51</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Iso-dihydro carveol</td><td>5.672</td><td>C10H18O</td><td>122,056</td><td>0.46</td></tr><tr><td>6.</td><td>Decanoic acid</td><td>7.498</td><td>C10H20O2</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>288,301</td><td>1.09</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>&#x003b2;-biotol</td><td>7.655</td><td>C12H24O11</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>521,376</td><td>1.96</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>&#x003b1;-Atlantone</td><td>7.787</td><td>C15H22O</td><td>393,782</td><td>1.48</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>&#x003b1;-Costol</td><td>7.903</td><td>C15 H24 O</td><td>285,272</td><td>1.07</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>&#x003b1;-Cadalene</td><td>8.045</td><td>C15H18</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>109,955</td><td>0.41</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>&#x003b1;-Pinene</td><td>8.364</td><td>C10H16</td><td>34,370</td><td>0.13</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>&#x003b1;-terpineol</td><td>8.711</td><td>C10H18O</td><td>72,061</td><td>0.27</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Globulol</td><td>9.745</td><td>C15H26O</td><td>552,913</td><td>2.08</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>&#x003b1;-Thujene</td><td>9.965</td><td>C10H16</td><td>33,163</td><td>0.12</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>&#x003b2;-Pinene</td><td>13.725</td><td>C10H16</td><td>47,551</td><td>0.18</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>&#x003b2;-myrcene</td><td>13.791</td><td>C10H16</td><td>53,675</td><td>0.2</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>1,8-Cineole</td><td>14.511</td><td>C10H180</td><td>1,877,333</td><td>7.07</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>Trans-p-menth-en-1-ol-</td><td>14.775</td><td>C10H18O</td><td>52,819</td><td>0.2</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>Cryptone</td><td>15.571</td><td>C9H14O</td><td>390,658</td><td>11.47</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>&#x003b2;-Elemene</td><td>16.413</td><td>C15H24</td><td>465,132</td><td>12.75</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>Aromadendrene</td><td>16.742</td><td>C15H24</td><td>45,940</td><td>0.17</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>Spathulenol</td><td>17.477</td><td>C15H24O</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>177,889</td><td>0.67</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>Aromadendrene</td><td>19.744</td><td>C15H24</td><td>87,813</td><td>0.33</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>Dedecanoic acid</td><td>19.944</td><td>C10H20O2</td><td>184,247</td><td>0.69</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>Oleic acid</td><td>20.190</td><td>C18H34O2</td><td>726,013</td><td>2.74</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>Cyclononasilodane</td><td>20.370</td><td>C10H30O5</td><td>1,765,843</td><td>26.65</td></tr><tr><td>27</td><td>&#x00392;-Asarone</td><td>20.565</td><td>C12H16O3</td><td>2,406,180</td><td>19.07</td></tr><tr><td>28</td><td>Triacetin</td><td>20.625</td><td>C9H14O6</td><td>465,754</td><td>11.75</td></tr><tr><td>29</td><td>Ascaridol</td><td>20.672</td><td>C10H16O2</td><td>977,430</td><td>3.68</td></tr><tr><td>30</td><td>Carvacrol</td><td>20.807</td><td>C10H14O</td><td>4,241,491</td><td>15.98</td></tr><tr><td>31</td><td>Isoascaridole</td><td>20.975</td><td>C10H16O2</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>193,562</td><td>14.5</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>32</td><td>Napthalene</td><td>20.456</td><td>C10H8</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>454,750</td><td>0.14</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>33</td><td>p-Cyamene</td><td>20.670</td><td>C10H14</td><td>7,126,016</td><td>10.50</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0075"><label>3.2</label><title>Anti-bacterial activity</title><p id="p0090">After 24&#x0202f;h incubation, the EO loaded discs exhibited 6, 16, 25&#x0202f;mm zone of inhibition against tested BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> at 10, 25 and 50&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/mL concentration were observed respectively (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>a, b). Whereas, 10&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/mL of third generation chephalosporin antibiotic was exhibited 10&#x0202f;mm zone of inhibition. In addition, the positive control of methanol containing well did not produced any zone in plate. The result suggested that the <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> essential oil has excellent anti-bacterial activity against BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>. The anti-bacterial activity of <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> EO against GPB and GNB have been described in previous studies of <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Da-Costa-Rocha et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Kartinah et al., 2019</xref>, also, excellent anti-bacterial compounds were also present in the purified extract. Some reports identified the MIC of bioactive compound from plant purified compound has high concentration. In the present study, the tested range was minimum 10&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/mL and maximum 50&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/mL with excellent anti-bacterial activity against BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>. Recently, <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Lingesh et al. (2018)</xref>, reported that the <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> essential oil has excellent anti-bacterial activity against MDR of GNB by different environmental factors such as temperature, pH, NaCL and other stresses. Previously, cineole, &#x003b2;-biotol, &#x003b1;-atlantone, &#x003b1;-terpiniol has excellent anti-bacterial activity when compared with bioactive compound (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Gandhi et al., 2019</xref>). Mechanistically, anti-bacterial activity of some petals mediated compounds have more capacity to elevate the permeability to fat soluble compounds, while the bioactive compound constituents were also present highly in inside of the essential oil with low efficiency. They may play active role in inside of the bacterial that leads to cell wall damage, QS inhibition, enzyme alteration and biofilm inhibition activity (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Rubini et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Francesco et al., 2011</xref>).<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Anti-bacterial activity differentiation of crude essential oil (a) and zone of inhibition in MHA plate (b) against CR <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0080"><label>3.3</label><title>Purification of active molecules from essential oil</title><p id="p0095">The preparative HPLC method was used to purify the active anti-bacterial EOs fraction, and the purified fraction was scanned by analytical HPLC. Based on the retention time, percentages of area and percentages of height, 9 different compound peaks (fractions) were identified from the purified essential oil. All the peaks and their retention time, occupation, height and area percentage of analytical HPLC result was inserted in table format (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Among the 9 AEOF, fractions 2 and 4 exhibited 16 and 24&#x0202f;mm zone of inhibition against CRBF <italic>K. pneumonia</italic> at 35&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL was observed (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>b, c). These two fraction peaks occupied the most of the area and height percentages was 5,793,629, 4,955,624 and 15.479, 28.838 observed respectively. These were comparatively very high than other fraction peaks. These two fractions were further purified separately by preparative HPLC using same mobile phase, retention, flow rate, temperature and fraction time. It was confirmed by analytical HPLC. Both the peaks and their retention time, occupation, height and area percentage of analytical HPLC result was inserted in table format (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Finally, both the fractions were mixed together and exhibited 30&#x0202f;mm zone of inhibition at 35&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL was observed (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>d). The differentiation between all the purified fractions was available in <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a. This purification result also suggests, the EO was surrounded with some bioactive compounds constituents that present inside of the essential oil. Therefore, the present result confirmed that the plant <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> could play an effective role against biofilm producing CRBF <italic>K. pneumonia.</italic><fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Analytical HPLC fractions of purified <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> essential oil.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Purified active anti-bacterial fraction of <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> essential oil by preparative HPLC (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Evaluation of purified active fractions of essential oil against biofilm forming <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> at various concentration (a), anti-bacterial activity of preparative HPLC fraction 2 (b), fraction 4 (c) and merged fraction (d) of essential against biofilm forming <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> by agar well diffusion method.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>3.4</label><title>Quantification of biofilm formation</title><p id="p0100">Anti-biofilm ability of AEOF was exhibited with complete biofilm inhibition against selected <italic>K. pneumonia</italic>. The result indicated that the AEOF have neither anti-bacterial nor anti-biofilm activity at very low concentration when compared to control. Among the various concentration, 90&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/ml was exhibited 92 and 89% inhibition against CRBF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> and biofilm positive control <italic>E. coli</italic> BDUMS 3 (KY617770). When compared with previous report, the present result of 90&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/ml concentration was very low against MDR pathogens (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>a). This study suggested that the AEOF was excellent bacteriostatic agent against GNB, and 90&#x0202f;&#x000b5;g/ml was fixed as a biofilm inhibition concentration (BIC). In addition, crystal violet staining assay exhibited that the rigidity of biofilm structure was degraded at the same concentration when compared with untreated control (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>a-Inset figures-1). It revealed that the adherent cells were degraded by BIC and exhibited highest inhibition result after bound with CV. The sparred cells of biofilm arrangement in the treated bacteria indicate that the AEOF has extracellular polysaccharide matrix damage ability through peptidoglycon layer and teichoic acid (<xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Jessica et al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Ebani et al., 2018</xref>). Previously, the <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> essential oil has more inhibition ability against EPS and Hydrophobicity index (<xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Jardak et al., 2017</xref>).<fig id="f0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Minimum biofilm inhibition (a), biofilm metabolic activity (b) of purified active fraction of <italic>H. rosa-sinensis essential oil</italic>. The inset <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a indicates, the presence and absence of biofilm rigidity before (a) and after (b) treatment of essential oil. Inset <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> indicates the decreased viability of <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> cells at increasing essential oil treatment in MHA plates (a, b, c).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0090"><label>3.5</label><title>Biofilm metabolic assay</title><p id="p0105">After treatment with BIC of AEOF, the treated bacterial viability significantly decreased at increasing concentration. Bacterial viability is one of the important mechanistic approaches in biofilm inhibition (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Maruthupandy et al., 2020</xref>). After 24&#x0202f;h incubation, the bacteria loss their antigenic characters like QS, enzyme production, gene stimulation and biofilm formation due to the arrest of formazan production (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Balasubramanian et al., 2016</xref>). This evidence was compared with biofilm quantification result and suggested that the metabolic activity was reduced in the test samples. In our study, the 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL of AEOF was released the bacteriostatic effect and extended to up to 90&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL with 7 and 88% of reduction (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>b). The XTT result proved that the AEOF inhibited the bacterial viability in dose dependent manner.</p><p id="p0110">Further, aliquot the evaluated result of XTT in MHA plates also proved that the AEOF has excellent bacteriostatic effect (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>b-Inset figures). The colonies of MHA plates were shown with distribution at 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL. There was no colony at 90&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL also when compared with control. Both XTT and MHA plate results proved that the AEOF has anti-biofilm activity due to the reduction of metabolic activity. Our result was agreed by <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Eman et al. (2018)</xref> and EO treated GNB increased the reduced viability via XTT assay due to the loss of their antigenicity. Recent report of <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Francesco et al. (2011)</xref>, also reported that the EO disrupted the antigenicity of protein and alters the DNA replication due to the arrest of formazan production. Hence, the indirect and direct method of AEOF results were indicated that the significant reduction on metabolic activity of selected biofilm producing <italic>K. pnumoniae.</italic></p></sec><sec id="s0095"><label>3.6</label><title>EPS quantification assay</title><p id="p0115">EPS is a physical important barrier for bacteria which helps to produce DNA, nucleic acid, extra cellular leakage materials for adhesion, protection and prevention of bacteria from external antibiotics (<xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Nazzaro et al., 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Rajivgandhi et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>). It is an important virulence factor in mode anti-biofilm formation action which gives the structure and shape to bacterial biofilm lead to biofilm matrix (<xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Lodhia et al., 2009</xref>). In our result, AEOF treated samples exhibited 92% at 90&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL concentration, which indicate, adhesion, protection and expand of bacterial antigenicity was lost due to the interfere of AEOF (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>a). It may prevent the fimbriae, flagella, and other slime secreted EPS role in inside of the bacteria (<xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2009</xref>). Recent report of <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Maruthupandy et al. (2020)</xref>, purified plant EO has the EPS ability through capsular polysachharide, which is dangerous for biofilm formation in human. The proposed mechanism was agreed by previous report of <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Vaillancourt et al. (2018)</xref>. Inhibition of EPS was major key factor to eradicate complete biofilm formation, because it lost the production of extracellular polysachharide and damaged binding site modification (<xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Semeniuc et al., 2017</xref>).<fig id="f0035"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Decreased EPS quantification (a) and hydrophobicity inhibition (b) of active fraction of <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> essential oil against CR <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> at different concentration. Inset <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>a indicates, the complete arrest of exopolysaccharide at various concentration of essential oil treated <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> was observed in CRA plates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="p0120">Further, the CRA plate method result was also confirmed that the AEOF has excellent bacteriostatic effect. In result, control plate of untreated BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> exhibited black color colonies, whereas treated plates exhibited loss of black color and no black color colonies (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>a-inset figure). At 90&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL concentration, bacteria lost their complete EPS production was observed when compared with any other concentration. It indicates, the AEOF did not allow developing the bacterial virulence factors in inside of the bacteria. At half inhibition concentration of 60&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL may start their function against DNA replication, nucleic acid synthesis and EPS secretion. In addition, surface charges of antigenicity were more sensitive to external antibiotics (<xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>). However, CRA method was evidently confirmed the invitro EPS inhibition result effectively. Also, the exhibited result consistently agreements with MBIC, XTT, EPS results, that AEOF has excellent inhibition ability against BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s0100"><label>3.7</label><title>Hydrophobicity index (HI) quantification assay</title><p id="p0125">The hydrophobicity is important key factor for biofilm production and involved in the initial adherence process. The rate of fimbriae role, flagella and EPS production was also essential factors for attachment of microbial cell onto the bacterial surface. It comes to enhance the increased biofilm formation in bacteria due to the influence of hydrophobicity. The hydrophobic interaction play a role in increase trends with an elevated non-polar nature of the microbial cell surface and substratum surface. In this study, the HI of AEOF treated BF <italic>K. pnemoniae</italic> exhibited with 89% at 90&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL concentration. Whereas, the control result showed with no any changes on their HI (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>b). The result revealed that the hydrophobicity nature of the BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> was significantly reduced when treated with AEOF. As per regulation of physico-chemical theory for bacteria (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Balasubramanian et al., 2016</xref>), and the higher adhesion rate to hydrophilic surface results in dispersion of bacterial cells from hydrophobic surface.</p></sec><sec id="s0105"><label>3.8</label><title>Surface morphology damage of biofilm</title><p id="p0130">Morphological damage of BIC treated bacteria was clearly depicted in SEM images <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>. The surface integrity of bacteria was modified due to the effect of AEOF (<xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>b). Whereas, tightly packed, attached rod shaped cells were observed in untreated control cells (<xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>a). Cell wall of the bacteria was shown with membrane corrugation damage with belb formation (<xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>c). In addition, arrangement of hank-like exopolysaccharides with organization of EPS was significantly damaged and degraded due to the exposure of AEOF (<xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>d). The result also expressed, a stress responses of the AEOF on bacteria surface was continuously pushed and cleaved the surface, it leads to complete permeation of AEOF inside the cells and shown with irregular shape. It may leads to low electron dense in the inside of the periplasmic space and cytoplasm of the cells creates the fluid discharge (<xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Vaillancourt et al. 2018</xref>).<fig id="f0040"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Morphological analysis of active essential oil fraction untreated (a) treated (b), damage variation (c), belbing formation and shape variation (d) of CR <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> by SEM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0110"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0135">In this research, the purified HPLC fraction of <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> EO shows enhanced anti-biofilm activity against BF <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic>. All the invitro experiments showed that the oil exhibited excellent activity over BF <italic>K. pneumoniae.</italic> Microscopical images of SEM indicated that the EO altered the bacterial replication and internal structure due to the interference of exopolysaccharide layer damage. Also, the structural and shape arrangement was entirely modified at very low concentration. From the identified results, we confirm that the <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> EO could be acted as a promising anti-biofilm agent for BF <italic>K. pneumoniae.</italic></p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0140">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehmood</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahzadi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waseem</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waheed</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chloroplast genome of <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> (Malvaceae): comparative analyses and identification of mutational hotspots</article-title><source>Genomics</source><volume>30062</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>S0888</fpage><lpage>S7543</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anjugam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaseeharan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iswarya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Divya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankaranarayanan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological synthesis of silver nanoparticles using &#x003b2;-1,3 glucan binding protein and their antibacterial, antibiofilm and cytotoxic potential</article-title><source>Microb. Pathog.</source><volume>115</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29208541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>J.M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flatt</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel Wahab</surname><given-names>Y.H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-hyperglycaemic activity of <italic>H. rosa-sinensis</italic> leaves is partly mediated by inhibition of carbohydrate digestion and absorption, and enhancement of insulin secretion</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>253</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">112647</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baskaralingam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganesan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antibiofilm assessment of <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> fruit extract coated silver nanoparticle</article-title><source>Biocatal. Agricul. Biotechnol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>196</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Younus</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis</italic> mediate anxiolytic effect via modulation of ionotropic GABA-A receptors: possible mechanism of action</article-title><source>Metab. Brain Dis.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29372452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-atherosclerotic effect of <italic>Hibiscus</italic> leaf polyphenols against tumor necrosis factor-alpha-induced abnormal vascular smooth muscle cell migration and proliferation</article-title><source>Antioxidants (Basel).</source><volume>8</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Da-Costa-Rocha</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnlaender</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pischel</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Hibiscus sabdariffa L</italic>. &#x02013; a phytochemical and pharmacological review</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>165</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doulgeraki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Ciccio</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ianieri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nychas</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methicillin-resistant food-related <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>: a review of current knowledge and biofilm formation for future studies and applications</article-title><source>Res. Microbiol.</source><volume>168</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27542729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebani</surname><given-names>V.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardoni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertelloni</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancianti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of five essential oils against bacteria and fungi responsible for urinary tract infections</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>23</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0050">Elemar Gomes, M., Rafael da Costa, H., Renato Moreira, R, Joao Antonio, P.H., Ana L&#x000ed;gia Lia de, P.R., Jenifer, S., 2010. Pharmacological evidences for the extracts and secondary metabolites from plants of the genus Hibiscus. Food Chem. 118, 1&#x02013;10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eman</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Attiaa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samar</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokhtar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishrd</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salah</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antimicrobial activities of essential oils of <italic>Ruta graveolens</italic> plants treated with salicylic acid under drought stress conditions</article-title><source>Fut. J. Pharmaceut. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>264</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0060">Erika, Be&#x000e1;ta, K., Anita, V., Mikl&#x000f3;s, T., Tam&#x000e1;s, P., Csaba, V., Gyorgyi, H., Vikt&#x000f3;ria, L. B., Judit, K., 2019. Anti-biofilm effect of selected essential oils and main components on mono- and polymicrobic bacterial cultures. Microorg. 7, 345.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francesco</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariarenat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovann</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanoencapsulation of essential oils to enhance their antimicrobial activity in foods</article-title><source>LWT - Food Sci. Technol.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1908</fpage><lpage>1914</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokhande</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swam</surname><given-names>y.V.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitlange</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational data of phytoconstituents from <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> on various anti-obesity targets</article-title><source>Data Brief</source><volume>24</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103994</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hui-Min</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji-Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi-Lin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen-Feng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bin Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan-Hang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gang-Gang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The N-butyl alcohol extract from <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> L. flowers enhances healing potential on rat excisional wounds</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharm.</source><volume>198</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>301</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jardak</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elloumi-Mseddi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aifa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mnif</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition, anti-biofilm activity and potential cytotoxic effect on cancer cells of <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. essential oil from <italic>Tunisia</italic></article-title><source>Lipids Heal. Dis.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>190</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0085">Jessica, B.S.R., Neyrijane, T.S., Joao, O.A.S., Jana&#x000ed;na, M.S., Myrella, C.L., Regina, C.B. Q.F., E.L. S., Marciane, M., 2018. Efficacy of using oregano essential oil and carvacrol to remove young and mature&#x000a0;Staphylococcus aureus&#x000a0;biofilms on food-contact surfaces of stainless steel. LWT. 93, 293&#x02013;299.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaleemullah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiyauddin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiban</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dhalli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Budiasih</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamal</surname><given-names>O.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddy</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and evaluation of Ketoprofen sustained release matrix tablet using <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> leaves mucilage, Saudi</article-title><source>Pharm. J.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>779</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kandhare</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raygude</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghule</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosavi</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Badole</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodhankar</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of hydroalcoholic extract of <italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis Linn</italic>. leaves in experimental colitis in rats</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Trop. Biomed.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0100">Kartinah, N.T., Fadilah, F., Ibrahim, E.I., Suryati, Y., 2019. The Potential of Hibiscus sabdariffa Linn in Inducing Glucagon-Like Peptide-1 via SGLT-1 and GLPR in DM Rats. Biomed. Res. Int. 8724824.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of quorum sensing regulated bacterial functions by plant essential oils with special reference to clove oil</article-title><source>Lett. Appl. Microbiol.</source><volume>49</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19627477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lingesh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satheeshkumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AMPK activating and anti adipogenic potential of <italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis</italic> flower in 3T3-L1 cells</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>233</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30593890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lodhia</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaker</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of essential oils from palmarosa, evening primrose, lavender and tuberose, Indian</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Sci.</source><volume>71</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>136</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malinowski</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinchak</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanker-Hansen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic similarities in flower characteristics between novel winter-hardy hibiscus hybrids and their tropical relatives</article-title><source>Front. Plant. Sci.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1528</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31824544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maralit Bruan</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tianco</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of 4% <italic>Hibiscus rosa-sinensis</italic> leaf extract ointment as an adjunct treatment to compression stockings on the closure of venous leg ulcers: a pilot study</article-title><source>Wounds</source><volume>31</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31298659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maruthupandy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadaikunnan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veeramanid</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alharbi</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muneeswaran</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alanzi</surname><given-names>K.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-biofilm investigation of graphene/chitosan nanocomposites against biofilm producing <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>K. pneumonia</italic></article-title><source>Carbohyd. Polym.</source><volume>230</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">115646</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naser</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iraj</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>phytosynthesis of zinc oxide nanoparticles and its antibacterial, antiquorum sensing, antimotility, and antioxidant capacities against multidrug resistant bacteria</article-title><source>J. Indust. Engin. Chem.</source><volume>72</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>473</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nazzaro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fratianni</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of essential oils on pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source>Pharmaceuticals (Basel)</source><volume>6</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24287491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norhaizan</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lye</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity in different parts of roselle <italic>(Hibiscus sabdariffa L</italic>.) extracts and potential exploitation of the seeds</article-title><source>Food Chemist.</source><volume>122</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>1055</fpage><lpage>1060</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attenuation of high glucose induced apoptotic and inflammatory signaling pathways in RIN-m5F pancreatic &#x003b2; cell lines by <italic>Hibiscus rosa sinensis</italic> L. petals and its phytoconstituents</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>227</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30120944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayarani</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murugan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and identification of biofilm forming uropathogens from urinary tract infection and its antimicrobial susceptibility pattern</article-title><source>Int. J. Adv. Lif. Sci</source><volume>7</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>363</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthil</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruthupandy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiofilm activity of marine endophytic actinomycetes compound isolated from mangrove plant <italic>Rhizophora mucronata</italic>, Muthupet Mangrove Region, Tamil Nadu, India</article-title><source>J. Terr. Mar. Res.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijayan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruthupandy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaseeharan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiofilm effect of <italic>Nocardiopsis</italic> sp. GRG 1 (KT235640) compound against biofilm forming Gram negative bacteria on UTIs</article-title><source>Microb. Pathog.</source><volume>118</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29524549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0170"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0170">Rihab, L., Fethi Ben, A., Badriah Osama, AL. S., Yassin, Al. S., 2019. Antibacterial and Biofilm Inhibitory Activity of Medicinal Plant Essential Oils Against Escherichia coli Isolated from UTI Patients. Molecules 24, 1161.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruban</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gajalakshmi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antibacterial activity of Hibiscus rosa-sinensis flower extract against human pathogens</article-title><source>Asian Pacif. J. Trop. Biomed.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>403</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubini</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banu</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisha</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murugan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thamotharan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Percino</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nithyanand</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils from unexplored aromatic plants quench biofilm formation and virulence of Methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Microb Pathog.</source><volume>122</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29920307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruhomally</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Somanah</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahorun</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neergheen-Bhujun</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Morinda citrifolia</italic> L. fruit extracts modulates H2O2-induced oxidative stress in human liposarcoma SW872 cells</article-title><source>J. Tradit. Complement. Med.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27419097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semeniuc</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotar</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity and interactions of plant essential oil combinations against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>J. Food Drug. Anal.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28911683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaillancourt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>LeBel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grenier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antibacterial activity of plant essential oils against <italic>Staphylococcus hyicus</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, the causative agents of exudative epidermitis in pigs</article-title><source>Arch. Microbiol.</source><volume>200</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1001</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29623386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0200"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morvin Yabesh</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arulmozhi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Praseetha</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and isolation of antimicrobial compounds from the flower extract of Hibiscus rosa-sinensis L: In silico and in vitro approaches</article-title><source>Microb. Pathog.</source><volume>123</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30086346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0205"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil components inhibit biofilm formation in <italic>Erwinia carotovora</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> via anti-quorum sensing activity</article-title><source>LWT</source><volume>92</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ref-list id="fr005"><title>Further Reading</title><ref id="b0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruthupandy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaseeharan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular identification and structural characterization of marine endophytic actinomycetes <italic>Nocardiopsis</italic> sp. GRG 2 (KT 235641) and its antibacterial efficacy against isolated ESBL producing bacteria</article-title><source>Microb. Pthog.</source><volume>126</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>148</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruthupandy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and identification of antibacterial compound from marine endophytic actinomycetes against multi drug resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Ann. Microbiol. Immunol.</source><volume>1</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1003</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ak005"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The work was supported by University Research Fellowship (Ref. No-05441/URF/K7/2013) <funding-source id="gp005">Bharathidasan University</funding-source>, Tiruchirappalli-24 for entire of this study. The authors extend their appreciation to the Researchers Supporting Project number (RSP-2020/70), <funding-source id="gp010"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100002383</institution-id><institution>King Saud University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d32e642"><p id="np005">Peer review under responsibility of King Saud University.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>