<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The detailed flowchart on the insilico methodologies implemented in this study towards prioritization of phytochemical moieties are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. 
 <italic>Tylophora indica</italic>, a perennial climber indigenous to India, commonly called “Antamool” is an important medicinal plant used in Indian medicine, mainly found in the plains, hills, and the forest borders in eastern and southern India. This plant is ethnically used for treating various types of ailments including cancer, respiratory infections, bronchial asthma, whooping cough, and anaphylaxis. The active ingredients of 
 <italic>T. indica</italic> are mainly available in leaves and roots that exhibit most therapeutic effects mostly due to the pharmacologically active alkaloids tylophorine, tylophorinine, and tylophorinidine (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Some previous studies have shown that Tylophora alkaloids can inhibit viral protease and suppresses viral RNA replication by blocking the JAK2 mediated NF-κB activation (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). While tylophorine derivatives have inhibitory effects on mouse hepatitis virus (MHV), transmissible gastroenteritis virus (TGEV), and SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>–
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). A recent report revealed that Tylophora alkaloids could inhibit the CoV-infected cells of swine (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). However, an earlier pharmacokinetic study demonstrated moderate to good oral bioavailability of tylophorine (65.7%) in rats (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Recent studies also showed that alkaloids from 
 <italic>T. indica</italic> possess anti-replication activity and inhibit the cytopathic effect induced by apoptosis, and apoptosis induced by viral infection (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). While kaempferol derived from 
 <italic>T. indica</italic> could effectively block the 3a channel protein in coronavirus (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>).
</p>
