<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Further research revealed that thyme, lemon, and clove oils influence the cell membranes. Up to a 16-fold increase in MIC value was observed for lemon oil for the 
 <italic class="italic">C. glabrata</italic> strain, even higher than for amphotericin B (8-fold increase for both species), which binds the ergosterol found in lipid bilayer membranes. In the case of 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>, the change was not so noticeable and reached a 2-fold increase. Additionally, we suggest that the 
 <italic class="italic">C. glabrata</italic> cell membrane may be more susceptible to the action of some EOs, as can be seen (apart from the mentioned lemon EO) in the case of geranium and clove oil (8- and at least 4-fold increase, respectively, while for 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> no increase was observed for geranium oil and for clove oil there was at least a 2-fold increase). The 4-fold increase of thyme oil MIC values in both tested strains also indicates its significant role in cell membrane disintegration. On the other hand, cinnamon oil does not seem to affect the cell membrane, as MIC values for this EO in the presence or absence of ergoesterol were unchanged for both species. Results obtained by other researchers also indicate the cell membrane as a potential molecular target of some EOs or their components. This can be, for instance, confirmed by Thakre and co-workers, who suggested that limonene inhibits 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> growth by cell wall/membrane damage [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-23-01116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. A similar statement was made by Xu et al. pertaining to clove oil [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-23-01116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. The influence of thyme oil on the cell membrane was observed by Rajkowska and co-workers, who noticed an up to 32-fold increase of MIC for this oil in ergosterol assay toward 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> ATCC 10231 [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-23-01116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. We also evaluated cell membrane disintegration by the measurement of potassium ion leakage. In the case of clove, the leakage was dose-dependent. The highest efflux was noticed in the case of thyme oil, but it was not proportional to the concentration used (probably the concentration of 1 × MIC was large enough to cause the highest outflow of ions, so a further increase did not result in additional changes). Interestingly, a relatively high efflux of potassium ions was caused by cinnamon oil, compared to a very low one caused by lemon oil, which is not in agreement with the results of the ergosterol assay.
</p>
