<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Lamiaceae</span> family
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rosemary belongs to the 
  <span class="italic">Lamiaceae</span> family, which is one of the largest and most distinguished families of flowering plants, including about 236 genera and 6900–7200 species worldwide [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>]. The original family name is 
  <span class="italic">Labiatae</span> because the flowers typically have petals fused into top and bottom lips, although currently most botanists use the name 
  <span class="italic">Lamiaceae</span> [
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="italic">Lamiaceae</span> is well known for its biologically active essential oils, common to many family members, its ornamental and culinary herbs such as basil, lavender, mint, rosemary, sage and thyme [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>,
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies report the presence of a wide variety of compounds such as terpenes, iridoids, flavonoids and phenolic compounds in plants of the family. The 
  <span class="italic">Lamiaceae</span> family includes species of plants containing large amounts of phenolic acids, such as rosmarinic acid, which have antibacterial, antiviral, antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many species of this family have been the subject of experimental studies confirming the effectiveness of some of its traditional applications. 
  <span class="italic">Thymus</span> spp. (thyme) has antibacterial activity due to the presence of thymol and can be used as a disinfectant; lavender oil, containing terpenic compounds, is used in the treatment of dandruff and hair growth, and also has antimicrobial, antiviral and antifungal properties; the aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">Stachys lavandulifolia</span> Vahl. are effective in the improvement of anxiety disorders due to the presence of apigenin and luteolin in the plant; 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</span> Mill is used for inflammation, cough, as a sedative and in digestive problems; and compounds such as 1,8-cineole are very common in the genus 
  <span class="italic">Nepeta</span>, with expectorant, antiseptic and antihelminthic activities [
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The following sections will further address an important species of the 
  <span class="italic">Lamiaceae</span> family, 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> L. which is very common in Portugal, mainly focusing on its biological compounds and activities.
 </p>
</sec>
