<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Candida infections are becoming more drug resistant; it is necessary to search for alternative medications to treat them. Therefore, the present study estimates the anticandidal activity of 
   <italic>Vitex agnus-castus</italic> (VA-C) leaf extracts.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>We used the agar well diffusion method to assess the anticandidal activity of three different VA-C leaf extracts (ethanol, methanol, and water) against three 
   <italic>Candida</italic> species (
   <italic>Candida tropicalis</italic>, 
   <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, and 
   <italic>Candida ciferrii</italic>). The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was estimated using the two-fold dilution method and the minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC) was determined using the classic pour plate technique. The MFC/MIC ratio was calculated to estimate the microbicidal or microbiostatic activity. A gas chromatography mass spectrometer was used to screen the phytochemicals of the VA-C leaf extracts (ethanol, methanol, and water).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>All VA-C extracts ethanol, methanol, and water were significantly inhibited the growth of the test 
   <italic>Candida</italic> species and the inhibition activity depended on the solvent used and the 
   <italic>Candida</italic> species. The results showed that 
   <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> was the most highly inhibited by all extracts followed by 
   <italic>C. albicans</italic> and 
   <italic>C. ciferrii</italic>. The MIC values were 12.5–25 µg/ml, and MFC values were 25–100 µg/ml. The ratios of MFC/MIC were two-fold to four-fold which was considered candidacidal activity. Ninety-five phytochemical compounds were identified by the GC-MS assay for the VA-C leaf extracts. The total number of compounds per extract differed. Methanol had 43 compounds, ethanol had 47 compounds, and water had 52 compounds. The highest compound concentrations were: 4,5-Dichloro-1,3-dioxolan-2-one in ethanol and methanol, 1H-Indene, 2,3-dihydro-1,1,2,3,3-pentamethyl in ethanol, Isobutyl 4-hydroxybenzoate in methanol, and Benzoic acid and 4-hydroxy- in water. These phytochemical compounds belong to different bioactive chemical group such as polyphenols, fatty acids, terpenes, terpenoids, steroids, aldehydes, alcohols, and esters, and most of which have anticandidal activity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>VA-C leaf extracts may be useful alternatives to anticandidal drugs, based on their effectiveness against all test 
   <italic>Candida</italic> species at low concentrations. However, appropriate toxicology screening should be conducted before use.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
