<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Natural products such as essential oils (EOs), flavonoids, alkaloids, and polysaccharides have attracted numerous researchers’ attention owing to their antimicrobial, antitumor, and anti-inflammatory functions. EOs are complex mixtures of volatile compounds extracted from plants, and the main components of EOs include aromatic and aliphatic constituents which are characterized by low molecular weight [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. They are biosynthesized by all plant organs, such as flowers, leaves, stems, seeds, fruits, roots, wood, bark, and so forth; are usually distributed in secretory cells, cavities, canals, and epidermic cells; and can be obtained by distillation and pressing. Regarding mode of action for cells, because of a vast number of complex compound constituents, EOs appear to have no specific cellular targets [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Owing to the complexity of the inhibitory action of EOs, it is time that the EO compounds (EOCs) should be taken into consideration to clarify the antimicrobial mechanism in detail. As typical lipophilic compounds, some related EOCs could pass through the cell wall and lipid-based cytoplasmic membrane, disturbing the structure of multilayered polysaccharides, fatty acids, and phospholipids, thereby destroying the overall cellular structure. Membrane damage is considered to be a type of cytotoxicity characteristic of EOCs. In eukaryotic cells, cell membranes and mitochondrial membranes control the ingress and egress of different components, such as ionic Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> cycling [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] and other ionic channels. EOCs might affect the membrane expansion and change the membrane fluidity by interfering with the proton pump and the ATP pool to cause the disordering of intracellular macromolecular substances (such as nucleic acids and proteins), intracellular enzyme activities, and energy metabolism. This mode of action of EOCs might be directed to a single target or multiple targets in the cell. Once this interaction mode is triggered, anabolism is promoted or catabolism is inhibited in the cell, resulting in an imbalance between synthesis and catabolism, which in turn leads to the accumulation of energy substances. Moreover, the intracellular respiratory rate, phosphorylation, and oxidative phosphorylation efficiency are also inhibited, leading to cell death by apoptosis and necrosis [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>].
</p>
