<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The use of edible coatings incorporating essential oil components can affect the survival of the two foodborne pathogens during their transition from apples to the host gastrointestinal tract. The impact of edible coatings supplemented with 0.2% Eug or the combination of 0.1% Eug + 0.15% Cit on the survival of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salm.</italic> Typhimurium during the challenge with the simulated gastrointestinal system evidenced that the ability of the two foodborne pathogens to defeat the low pH of the stomach and the intestinal milieu was decreased, in comparison to the control cells. This impact was more pronounced when the bacterial cells were exposed to the gastric fluid at pH 1.5 even leading to no recovery of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> cells from samples containing the edible coatings supplemented with the essential oil components. At this lethal pH 
 <italic class="italic">Salm</italic>. Typhimurium was shown to be more resistant, surviving the gastrointestinal challenge in comparison to 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic>. However, the survival of the 
 <italic class="italic">Salm</italic>. Typhimurium cells from samples contained the edible coatings incorporated with the essential oil components was lower in comparison to control cells. The reports about the ability of either 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">Salm.</italic> Typhimurium to beat the gastrointestinal system using a food matrix are limited [
 <xref rid="B27-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. However, it is evident that these two foodborne pathogens are able to defeat the gastrointestinal barrier of the host [
 <xref rid="B27-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. The present study shows that the use of edible coatings enriched with eugenol and the combination of eugenol and citral causes an increase in the susceptibility of the two pathogens that ultimately impairs their survival during the transition from apples to the gastrointestinal tract. 
</p>
