<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> spp. are extremely common bacteria that occur naturally in 60% of insect species, including some mosquitoes, fruit flies, moths, dragonflies, and butterflies. 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> spp. can invade insect populations using cytoplasmatic incompatibility and provide new strategies for controlling mosquito-borne diseases, such as dengue fever [
 <xref rid="B23-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Cytoplasmic incompatibility causes a significant reduction in brood hatch and promotes the spread of the maternally inherited 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection into the host population. 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected females live longer, produce more eggs, and have higher hatching rates in compatible crosses [
 <xref rid="B24-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The World Mosquito Program released males and females of the 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected mosquito 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> to protect global communities from mosquito-borne diseases [
 <xref rid="B25-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected mosquitoes breed with the wild mosquito population until a higher percentage of mosquitoes carrying 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> has been reached. These infected mosquitoes have a reduced ability to transmit pathogens such as Zika, dengue, Chikungunya, and yellow fever viruses to human populations [
 <xref rid="B25-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-carrying mosquitoes were released across La Paz city, Baja California Sur, México in January 2019 to offer a long-term sustainable alternative to the currently available disease-control strategies [
 <xref rid="B25-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. There are only three reports of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> infected with the bacterium 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in México [
 <xref rid="B26-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Another additional report identified the coinfection of the native 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> populations with both 
 <italic>wAlbA</italic> and 
 <italic>wAlbB</italic> strains of 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B27-insects-12-00143" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
