<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">Mosquito control by chemical utilization specifically, currently plays a role in public health as an essential part of comprehensive and integrated vector management. The most popular chemical methods involve application of insecticides with low toxicity that target mosquito larvae (larvicide) and adults (adulticide). Larval control by source reduction and routine application of chemical larvicides, such as organophosphate compounds and insect growth regulators, is considered as fundamental intervention. However, the adverse environmental impact associated with synthetic pesticides as well as their labor intensiveness and difficulty to sustain remain a major challenge [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. Conventional, aggressive vector management such as adulticide application remains the most efficient means of control during a virus outbreak, due to prompt and massive elimination of infective mosquito vectors as well as a reduction of the lifespan and total reproduction capacity of local vector populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Four classes of chemical insecticides, namely organochlorines (exclusively DDT), organophosphates, carbamates and pyrethroids, are the mainstay of vector control programs, with pyrethroids considered as the most successful class, providing high potency against a wide variety of arthropods and low mammalian toxicity. Synthetic pyrethroids now constitute the majority of commercial insecticides and account for approximately 25% of the global insecticide market [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. Permethrin and deltamethrin are broad-spectrum pyrethroid insecticides that have been used worldwide for decades, controlling a wide range of insect pests of agricultural and medical importance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>]. During the 1950s, DDT was the chemical of choice for national public health mosquito control programs in Thailand. After applying DDT extensively in endemic areas of malaria, its use was phased out gradually in Thailand between 1995 and 2000, and replaced by two pyrethroids: permethrin and deltamethrin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>]. These pyrethroid insecticides were introduced in the early 1990s for controlling malaria and dengue, mainly by treating bednets as well as using thermal fogging and ULV sprays [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>]. However, they lost their effectiveness due to significant mosquito resistance and non-compliance from the community because of concern about public health and the environmental impacts of synthetic chemicals. This caused major problems that threatened the success of vector control programs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>]. Prompt and appropriate counter measures were required to improve the effectiveness of a strategy. Recommended management procedures included substitution by natural substances, rotation of different classes of chemicals, addition of a synergist, and mixing of chemicals or concurrent mosaic application of different classes of chemicals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. Therefore, the search for and development of an environmental and user friendly alternative and synergist with high efficacy are urgently needed, and this study aimed to satisfy this demand.
</p>
