<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Medicinal plants of the 
  <italic class="italic">Plectranthus</italic> genus (Lamiaceae) are known for their ethnopharmacological relevance, mainly against infectious, dermatologic and gastrointestinal pathologies. Three 
  <italic class="italic">Plectranthus</italic> species originated from South Africa, namely 
  <italic class="italic">P. madagascariensis</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">P. neochilus</italic> and the rare 
  <italic class="italic">P. porcatus</italic> were hereby screened for their antimicrobial and cytotoxic activities related with their known and/or potential ethnomedicinal uses. Twenty-six extracts were prepared by the combination of extraction methods (infusion, decoction, microwave-assisted, ultrasound-assisted, maceration and supercritical fluid extraction) with different polarity solvents (water, methanol, acetone and supercritical CO
  <sub class="sub">2</sub>). The comparison study of these extracts was elucidated through the corresponding chemical characterization and cytotoxic activity data. Therefore, the acetone extract from 
  <italic class="italic">P. madagascariensis</italic> prepared by ultrasound extraction method revealed potent antibacterial activity against Gram-positive bacteria (1.95 &lt; minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) &lt; 7.81 μg/mL), including a methicillin-resistant 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) strain. Additionally, acetone extracts from both 
  <italic class="italic">P. madagascariensis</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">P. neochilus</italic> exhibited relevant antibacterial activity against Gram-negative 
  <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pneumonia</italic> (0.48 &lt; MIC &lt; 3.91 μg/mL), validating the traditional uses of such plants as anti-infectious agents. All methanolic extracts showed potent antioxidant effects at 100 μg/mL measured as their radical scavenging activity (60.8–89.0%) in the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) assay. The 
  <italic class="italic">P. madagascariensis</italic> extract obtained by maceration in acetone showed moderate cytotoxic effects in the MDA-MB-231 cell line (triple negative human breast carcinoma). The extract concentration that caused a 50% inhibition in cell viability (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub>) was 64.52 μg/mL. All extracts in this comparative study were profiled by high-performance liquid chromatography-HPLC with a diode-array detector-DAD (HPLC-DAD) and the main known bioactive components were identified in each extract, which included polyphenols (caffeic 
  <bold class="bold">1</bold>, chlorogenic 
  <bold class="bold">2</bold> and rosmarinic 
  <bold class="bold">3</bold> acids), abietane diterpenes (7α-acetoxy-6β-hydroxyroyleanone 
  <bold class="bold">4</bold> and coleon U 
  <bold class="bold">5</bold>) and flavone glycosides (rutin 
  <bold class="bold">6</bold> and naringin 
  <bold class="bold">7</bold>).
 </p>
</abstract>
