<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Published information is often lacking on the effectiveness of interventions in natural resource management, including programs designed to eradicate or control invasive plant species [
 <xref rid="pone.0128482.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Yet it is critical to know the effectiveness of such actions to make well targeted, successful and cost-effective interventions [
 <xref rid="pone.0128482.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0128482.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. This is particularly important in invasive species management because the relative success of control can vary according to many factors such as the stage of invasion that a given species is in, the supply of invasive and native species propagules from the soil seedbank and surrounding populations [
 <xref rid="pone.0128482.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], the extent of non-target impacts on native communities, and the capacity of native flora to colonise and regenerate [
 <xref rid="pone.0128482.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0128482.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. To explore some of these key issues, we took advantage of a major, applied invasive species management program in an iconic National Park in south-eastern Australia to complete a detailed, 7-year experimental case study of Bitou Bush control. Four key findings of our comparative experimental study include: 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Bitou Bush was a driver of environmental change. We reached this conclusion for two reasons. First, we found no evidence that the spray-fire-spray treatment regime increased the susceptibility of treated areas to re-invasion by Bitou Bush or by other exotic plant species within 2–3 years after the last spray. Second, native plant species richness and cover increased over time (
    <xref rid="pone.0128482.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) and approached levels characteristic of control sites where Bitou Bush was absent (
    <xref rid="pone.0128482.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Thus, our findings suggest that removal of Bitou Bush could lead to native plant recovery, indicating ecosystem release from one, apparent (exotic) driver of change. Notably, the recovery of native plant species in our experiment suggests that seed limitation of native species is no greater in areas formerly invaded by Bitou Bush and those where Bitou Bush has been absent. It is possible that Bitou Bush may have responded to other drivers of change in our two target vegetation types (such as altered fire regimes), but we examined for (and found little evidence of) the effects of them using control plots in the experimental design.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The full treatment (spray-fire-spray) protocol significantly reduced Bitou Bush. The number of Bitou Bush plants then remained at, or close to, zero for at least 2–3 years after the final spray event (
    <xref rid="pone.0128482.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). This result, coupled with the limited and relatively short-lived impacts of this treatment sequence on native vegetation cover, suggested that spray-fire-spray was the most cost-effective form of Bitou Bush control.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Outcomes of weed control were often strongly dependent on the treatment sequence deployed. Some incomplete treatment sequences appeared to be relatively ineffective or even increased the abundance of Bitou Bush (
    <xref rid="pone.0128482.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>In the event of an (unplanned) wildfire in an area infested with Bitou Bush, our results suggest it can be useful to follow such natural disturbance with spraying (at the appropriate time of the year) to kill the pulse of seedlings likely to germinate after the fire.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
