<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant and soil samples were collected from the salt marsh of the barrier island of Schiermonnikoog (53°29′ N, 6°10′ E), the Netherlands in July 2017. This island presents a well-documented salt-marsh chronosequence [
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In salt marshes, elevation determines the frequency, amplitude, and duration of sea-water inundation events [
 <xref rid="B24-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. We selected sites with high plant coverage (&gt;90%) where 
 <italic>E. atherica</italic> was dominant. Three sites at high elevation (HE) (&gt;1.6 m Amsterdam Ordnance Data, AOD) and three sites at low elevation (LE) (&lt;1.400 m AOD) (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-08-01619-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Site elevation was measured using a real-time kinetimatic differential GPS (RTK-dGPS, Leica Viva GS12 GNSS receiver and CS15 controller), with a vertical accuracy of less than 2 mm. HE sites were indicated as H1–H3 and LE sites as L1–L3 (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-microorganisms-08-01619">Supplementary Material S1</xref>). Inundation frequency was expressed as the amount of times per year a site was flooded and was calculated using a model, which was based on the seawater-level fluctuation in relation to the natural elevation of each site [
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. At each site, three sampling plots of approximately 5 × 5 m were selected. Salt-marsh age of each sampling site was estimated based on [
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], HE sites were estimated older than LE sites, except L1, which has the same age as H1 (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-08-01619-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Subdominant plant species composition varied at each sampling site (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-08-01619-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). QGis version 3.8 was used to make the map in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-microorganisms-08-01619">Supplementary Material S1</xref>.
</p>
