<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Essential oils are complex volatile compounds, which have potential therapeutic activity that depends mainly on their types, including aldehydes, phenolics, terpenes, and other antimicrobial compounds (
 <xref rid="b29-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>). Essential oil mixed with mint, eucalyptus, spruce and frankincense compounds have exhibited curative effects against acute airway inflammation induced by air PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> air pollutants in mice (
 <xref rid="b30-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>). Phytoncide or wood essential oil has been investigated for health beneficial activities, including enhancing the activity of NK cells by the induction of intracellular perforin, granzyme A, and granulysin in NK-92MI human cells (
 <xref rid="b31-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>). Hinoki cypress (
 <italic class="italic">C. obtusa</italic>) is a coniferous tree and predominant cypress species in Asia, found in Japan and South Korea, which contains volatile or essential oil in its leaves and twigs. The direct inhalation of essential oil or contact with cypress wood has been widely investigated for its physiological and psychological relaxation properties without harmful effects on the body (
 <xref rid="b8-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="b12-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="b13-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="b32-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">In vitro</italic> studies have shown that phytoncides decrease the capacity of LPS-induced inflammatory responses in MAC-T mammary alveolar epithelial cells (
 <xref rid="b33-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>) and in RAW 264.7 macrophage cells (
 <xref rid="b18-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>). Monoterpene β-thujaplicin of 
 <italic class="italic">C. obtusa</italic> have been shown to inhibit inflammatory expression in RAW 264.7 cells and septic shock in mice (
 <xref rid="b34-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>); whereas α-phellandrene mono-terpene in 
 <italic class="italic">Schinus molle</italic> L. essential oil exhibits enhanced NK cell activity in normal BALB/c mice (
 <xref rid="b35-ijmm-43-01-0393" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>). Similarly, in the present study, exposure to terpenes of essential oil at different concentrations led to the inhibition of LPS-induced inflammation in WI38 cells, and inhalation of the essential oil enhanced the capacity of lung alveoli in rats.
</p>
