<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Topical treatment for oral candidiasis is nystatin mouthwash, which its requirement to frequent use and unpleasant taste, often leads to patients’ dissatisfaction and sometimes lack of continuity of treatment. For this reason, offering a proper flavour mouthwash with the ease of use and proper efficacy seems necessary and practical [
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Studies conducted in the last decade clearly show the unpleasant effects of chemical drugs alongside their beneficial effects. Recent studies have paid more attention to the use of medicinal plants due to increased drug resistance to new chemical drugs. This study aimed to evaluate the antifungal effects of cinnamaldehyde extract against 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Candida glabrata</italic>, and compare it with the antifungal effect of nystatin. Most previous studies have been conducted on specific pathogens that affect the skin, respiratory, digestive and urogenital system, and few studies have been done on oral mucosal pathogens [
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], [
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. For many years, 
 <italic class="italic">Candida glabrata</italic> was considered a relatively non-pathogenic saprophytic flora of normal people, unconnected with a serious infection in humans. However, following the large and widespread use of immunosuppressive agents, along with treatment with broad-spectrum antibiotics, the number of systemic and mucosal infections caused by 
 <italic class="italic">Candida glabrata</italic> has increased dramatically [
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In Fani and Kohanteb (2011) [
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], the antifungal effects of cinnamon on 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> are mentioned. Also, Casrto and Lima (2013) pointed to the antifungal effects of essential oil of cinnamon, which the main component of it is eugenol, on 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Candida tropicalis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Candida krusei</italic>. They found the direct effect of cinnamon essential oil on the cell wall synthesis of the yeast [
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Many researchers have indicated that there is a correlation between the chemical composition and the antifungal activity. They also showed that the strong antifungal activity of the oils derived from the skin and the cinnamon leaf was due to the high levels of cinnamaldehyde (44.2%) and eugenol (90.2%) [
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. However, other compounds may also contribute to antifungal activity. The study of Arbabi et al., (2011) aimed at comparing the effect of thyme, cloves and cinnamon extract with nystatin on the inhibition of 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic>. The diameter of the inhibition zone of each plant extract was compared with the diameter of the positive control growth zone with ANOVA. Candida inhibition in the nystatin group was 32.6 ± 0.84, and in cinnamon, extract group was 31.3 ± 0.82. In addition, 
 <italic class="italic">candida</italic> inhibition in clove extract group was 27.4 ± 0.82 and finally in thyme evaluated 13 ± 0.82. As a result, the highest effect was first on nystatin, cinnamon, cloves and ultimately thyme (P &lt; 0.000). The final result was that thyme, cloves, and cinnamon had antifungal effects on the 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. However, in these two studies, the method of measuring the inhibitory effect of cinnamon extract is not the same, but both studies have confirmed that cinnamon has antifungal effects. The aim of the study of Ataei et al., (2007) was an experimental evaluation on the antifungal effects of absinthium Artemisia, eucalyptus, onion, cinnamon, turmeric, sage, mint, and Calendula officinalis on a standard strain of 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> compared to nystatin mouthwash. The results showed that the extract of each of the six herbs had an antifungal effect. Cinnamon has been shown to be more potent and more effective than the onion, mint, Calendula officinalis and sage, with the same effect as turmeric, absinthium Artemisia and eucalyptus. Also, cinnamon, absinthium Artemisia, eucalyptus exhibited significant antifungal effects in comparison with nystatin [
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Carvalhinho et al.,)2012) and Condò et al., (2018) also showed a significant activity of cinnamon against 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Gucwa et al., (2018) exhibited both fungistatic and fungicidal activity of some plant oils toward 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic>
 <italic class="italic">glabrata</italic> isolates and the highest activity was demonstrated for cinnamon oil [
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The results of these studies confirm the result of the present study and the antifungal properties of cinnamon.
</p>
