<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-plants-06-00041" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Cultivation Conditions and Plant Material</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Certified 
  <span class="italic">Ocimum basilicum</span> L. (basil) seeds, belonging to varieties lettuce, cinnamon, minimum, latifolia, and violetto, were purchased from the local market. Basil seeds of the five varieties were sown into sowing boxes filled with universal soil for sowing seeds in an environmentally controlled growth chamber. Environmental conditions were: photoperiod 12/12, air temperature 18/24 °C, and air relative humidity 50/70% (day/night). When the plants formed true leaves were transplanted into small plastic pots. When they reached 12–15 cm height, they were transplanted to their final position either into plastic 20 L pots in the greenhouse or directly to the land in the experimental field. For each variety 20 plants were planted in each cultivation site. For the field conditions, basil transplants were planted into rows with 0.50 m in-row and 1.00 m between row spacing, covering a total area of 15 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>. Plants were irrigated every second day with an irrigation tape providing 5–7 L of water, in both field and greenhouse conditions. During the growing period, no pests or diseases were observed apart from the inability of var. cinnamon to grow in the greenhouse conditions and that var. violetto failed to grow in the field conditions, thus only the results from one cultivation site are given. Harvesting of the plants was performed almost two months after transplantation, prior to flowering stage [
  <a rid="B17-plants-06-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-06-00041">17</a>]. The field cultivation conducted in the experimental field of the Department of Food Technology (Technological Educational Institute of Ionian Islands) in the island of Kefalonia (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="plants-06-00041-f005" href="#plants-06-00041-f005">Figure 5</a>). Plant material was hand harvested by removing the apical portion of the herbage 20 cm above ground and leaving 1–2 internodes in order to promote rejuvenation from the sleeping buds. For each variety and cultivation site, 2–3 harvests were performed depending on the variety and its ability to regenerate stems and flowers. Practically, this includes a period of 30–40 days between each cutting. In every collection, plant material was collected the same time of the day in order to eliminate day variations to the yield of essential oil, transferred to the laboratory and fresh weight was measured, and the essential oil yield to fresh weight was calculated. In total, 23 samples were collected extracted and analysed, namely 10 essential oils obtained from 4 four different varieties cultivated in the greenhouse, and 13 essential oils obtained from four varieties cultivated in the field (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="plants-06-00041-t001" href="#plants-06-00041-t001">Table 1</a>). The plant materials have been deposited in the herbarium of the Department of Food Technology (Technological Educational Institute of Ionian Islands) under the number 737. 
 </p>
</sec>
