<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Humans have used EOs for thousands of years, not only as ingredients of perfumes or as seasonings for the aromatization of food, but also in folk medicine, because of their many different biological properties, including antimicrobial properties [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-02130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The antimicrobial qualities are essential in managing the rapidly growing issue of drug-resistant microorganisms. In 2016, about 6 million people died globally due to infections of the upper respiratory tract, tuberculosis, or diarrheal diseases. At the same time, the number of strains of microorganisms resistant to existing antibiotics is constantly increasing. Patients with infections caused by drug-resistant bacteria are, thus, exposed to an increased risk of worse clinical results and even death. Such patients also consume more healthcare resources than patients infected with non-resistant strains of the same bacteria. According to the WHO report on drug resistance, the most serious problems include the resistance of 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> to third-generation cephalosporins and carbapenem, 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> to third-generation cephalosporins and fluoroquinolone, 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> to methicillin, 
 <italic class="italic">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> to penicillin, and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> sp. to fluoroquinolones. Among the fungal infections, the most common problem is candidiasis caused mainly by 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> and less often by 
 <italic class="italic">C. glabrata</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. parapsilosis</italic>, with more than 20 species of 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> that can cause human infection [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-02130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Other examples of common fungal infections are aspergillosis, histoplasmosis, and skin mycosis (commonly known as ringworm) [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-02130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. 
</p>
