<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The compositions of the fatty acids did not vary in the three different regions (
 <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This implies that there were no variations in the environmental and soil conditions in the three regions. Conceivably, in the evolution of baobab populations into ecotypes with the possibility of genetic drift, the seed oil FA content pattern remained highly conserved. The results for the total fatty acid composition in baobab crude oil obtained in this study were similar to those reported by Idris et al. [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] who obtained 98.76 wt percent for the fatty acid composition. The compositions of palmitic, oleic, and linolenic fatty acids were higher compared to the compositions of other fatty acids. The higher fatty acid compositions of the baobab crude oil in this study were in the ranges of previous studies [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. It has been reported that as healthy fats, linoleic and oleic acids maintain cell membranes which provide energy and offer vitamin E which is a powerful antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Moreover, the oil contains CPFAs mainly sterculic and dehydrosterculic which is the characteristic property of Malvaceae family. Surprisingly, malvalic acid was below the detection limit in the baobab crude oil; hence, it deviates from the results reported in literature by [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The absence of malvalic acid could be attributed to the sample preparation method which involved oil extraction from baobab seeds using a pressing machine, leaving out the seed coat during fatty acid quantification [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The composition of the CPFAs found in the baobab crude oil sterculic (0.97-1.45%) and dehydrosterculic (0.80-1.29%) was higher than the recommended quantity for human consumptions [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
</p>
