<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">We are aware of heterogeneous or inconsistent use of the term “signal” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], that signals of ADRs may be communicated by various stakeholders (see below for definition), that over time signals have been supported by a wide range of types of evidence, and that pharmacovigilance regulation is context-dependent. Defining key concepts thus becomes essential, beginning with the elemental components of a signal: one or more medicinal product (see [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]) and one or more suspected adverse drug reaction (see [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]). Crucially, we understand the concept “signal of ADR”, its subtypes (i.e. indeterminate, verified, refuted), and that of “SDRs” as previously defined [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. These definitions, however, would commit us to determine whether any form of evidence, even single reports of ADRs, would command attention (“whose?”) or regulatory action (“of what type?”); making such judgments for every published and unpublished record would result in an unmanageable amount of work. We further acknowledge the subjectivity that comes into play in assessing some evidence as signal and that our judgments may differ from those of study authors, introducing bias. We therefore decided to consider as signals any findings that are merely described as such (e.g. “these results should be considered as a signal” or “the association between “drug A” and “ADR B” is a signal”) without distinguishing subtypes: following-up signals to ascertain any subsequent verificatory action would entail substantial additional work. We consider SDRs, i.e. results of disproportionality analyses (e.g. proportional reporting ratio (PRR), information component), those that exceed thresholds for statistical significance set by the study authors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].
</p>
