<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several articles in this Special Issue focus on the synthesis of materials or devices designed for pollution remediation. In the feature article by Liao et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], hybrid surface coatings were prepared by modifying TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> films with Au nanoclusters by gas-phase beam deposition. The gold distribution onto the semiconductor support was highly homogeneous and provided efficient plasmonic photocatalytic activity. Tests of stearic acid degradation performed both under UV and green LED light showed a promoting effect due to the metal nanoclusters, especially under green light irradiation. The feature paper by Panzarasa and coauthors [
 <xref rid="B10-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] presents a different approach to pollutant remediation, making use of natural renewable sources. Sepia melanin was used as an active component in hybrid adsorbent materials, owing to its ability to efficiently bind several organic compounds. The resulting hybrid material proved efficient, stable, easily recoverable and showed good reusability. Also in the work by Ren and coauthors [
 <xref rid="B11-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], agro-alimentary waste is valorized as a starting material for hybrid material preparation. Magnetite-carbon nanocomposites were prepared by a hydrothermal procedure adopting pomelo peels as carbon source. The resulting hybrids were used as adsorbents to extract fungicide residues from homogenized fruit samples. One of the main issues in the pollutant remediation of surface waters and wastewaters by adsorption and/or degradation processes is represented by the removal of finely dispersed adsorbents/photocatalysts upon treatment. In the work by Lu and coauthors [
 <xref rid="B12-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], a magnetic separation procedure is proposed to solve this problem: Hybrid magnetic iron oxides were deposited onto MoS
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanosheets in the presence of metallic iron. By combining direct redox and Fenton processes, the hybrid provided simultaneous degradation of both toxic inorganic (Cr(VI)) and organic compounds (4-chlorophenol). Moreover, the nanocomposites could be separated magnetically from the treated effluent, showing good reusability.
</p>
