<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the last decade, hybrids based on carbon nanomaterials, such as carbon nanotubes, have raised a great deal of interest in several fields [
 <xref rid="B13-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. In the work by Das and coauthors [
 <xref rid="B15-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], the in situ formation of either crystalline metals or metal oxides onto multiwalled carbon nanotubes (MWNT) was achieved by modifying the sol-gel conditions of the precipitation reaction, in the absence of any oxidizing or reducing agent, using the electrochemical potential as a control parameter. The reaction occurrence was made possible just by the surface energy and composition of the MWNT activated surfaces, which act as nucleation sites for the growth of the crystals. By the same principles, in the feature paper by Sansotera et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], the successful functionalization of MWNT by perfluoropolyether chains was controlled by the surface features of the carbon nanotubes. The resulting covalent bond produced relevant modifications of the MWNT surface energy imparting superhydrophobic behavior; branched chains, bearing CF
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> groups, produced a higher functionalization degree with respect to linear ones. The functionalization appeared to affect the pore size distribution of MWNT, mainly in the case of branched chains, while the conduction properties were only weakly modified. The control of the porosity and surface features of carbon materials is also the focus of the work by Lu and coauthors [
 <xref rid="B17-nanomaterials-08-00891" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. They proposed a controlled modification of mesoporous carbon by Mg and N in the presence of a non-ionic surfactant, giving rise to a higher microporosity and to two types of basic sites. Thanks to the enhanced morphological and surface features, the resulting materials showed increased CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> adsorption, more than twice with respect to the pristine material.
</p>
