<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Direct stimulation of immune cells by 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> extracts results in the production of NO through the induction of inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) and in the generation of a proinflammatory cytokine/chemokine profile. Depending on the situation, the interaction of 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> extracts with other effectors may result in reduced inflammation. For example, NO inhibition was highly increased in lipopolysaccharide- (LPS-) treated macrophages in the presence of 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> aqueous extracts. Studies also showed that 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> extracts increased RAW 264.7 macrophage proliferation by more than 80% [
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Jeong et al. [
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] confirmed that NO and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> secretion were significantly inhibited when LPS-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells were treated with 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> water extracts (SFWE). Moreover, SFWE inhibited the expression of IL-6 and IL-1
 <italic>β</italic> in a dose-dependent manner. In particular, IL-6 inhibition activity was &gt;50% at a concentration of 1% SFWE. Jaswir et al. [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] showed that 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> ethanol extract (SFEE) inhibited not only the production of NO and proinflammatory cytokines (IL-6, IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>) but also the expression of iNOS and cyclooxygenase 2 in LPS-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells without affecting their viability. SFEE also suppressed the expression of NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B, suggesting that SFEE could affect the expression of inflammation-related cytokines and proteins through the regulation of NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B. Furthermore, the formation of ear edema was 40% lower in mice treated with the highest dose (250 mg/kg) of SFEE than that in the control mice [
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].
</p>
