<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ginger’s distinctive constituents are fragrant and pungent types. The fragrant part is commonly referred to as EOs. EOs are semi-oily yellowish volatile aromatic liquids that are derived from plant materials such as leaves, flowers, fruits, stems, roots, and seeds through steam/hydro distillation (
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Böhme et al., 2014</xref>). They are biosynthesized from plants and plants’ secondary metabolites (
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Fitriady et al., 2017</xref>), which are usually found in unique cells or organized cells (
 <xref rid="ref87" ref-type="bibr">Nirmala and Nagarajan, 2017</xref>). EOs have multiple functions in plants of which they are found to be a part of the plant’s defense mechanisms. In ginger EOs, many chemical compounds were identified and analyzed for their chemical structure using analytical approaches such as high-performance liquid chromatography, GC-MS (
 <xref rid="ref88" ref-type="bibr">Nour et al., 2017</xref>), and headspace (
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Bylaite et al., 2000</xref>). However, there are literature that reported EOs components can be analyzed using gas chromatography but quantifying is done or can be done using spectrophotometer or a combination of these techniques (
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2017</xref>). These techniques are commonly used to determine the volatile compounds in ginger EOs. The mass spectrum of the obscured constituents of ginger are commonly identified by comparing their retention times (RT), similarity index, and mass spectral data (
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Chiang et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref114" ref-type="bibr">Trimanto and Hapsari, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref115" ref-type="bibr">Vairappan et al., 2012</xref>). In general, RT is useful information for characterizing and distinguishing EOs components (
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Bhattarai et al., 2018</xref>), but they are poorly reproducible over the long term or between different systems and should be relied on only when calculating comparison and sample under the same conditions and shortly after one another. In particular, all factors that could impact RT under otherwise constant conditions could also theoretically affect retention indices. All processes that disrupt or reduce or change the column selectivity of the gas chromatographic separation can cause significant deviations in retention indices (
 <xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Koo et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
