<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The constituents of ginger EOs are strongly associated with place of origin or geographical location, and also whether the rhizomes are fresh or dried (
 <xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2017</xref>). Fresh ginger EOs are of higher quality in terms of fragrance/flavor than dried ginger, thus receiving more oils and better anti-microbes activity (
 <xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">Mahboubi, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref89" ref-type="bibr">Onyenekwe and Hashimoto, 1999</xref>). Similarly, 
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref> shows the chemical compounds in domestic and wild ginger by headspace method, they are characterized by monoterpenes such as camphene, geranial, linalool, and neral. The most abundant compounds are sesquiterpene hydrocarbons, mostly 
 <italic>α</italic>-zingiberene, ar-curcumene, 
 <italic>β</italic>-bisabolene, 
 <italic>β</italic>-sesquiphellandrene, 
 <italic>β</italic>-ionone 5,6-epoxide and their % concentrations are camphene (4.6-16.9%), 
 <italic>β</italic>-ionone 5, 6-epoxide (5.6-16.3%), eucalyptol (5.6-14.9%), 
 <italic>β</italic>-phellandrene (4.5-11.6%), 
 <italic>α</italic>-zingiberene (7.1-20%), 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene (2.6-5.4%), geranial (4.1-5.0%), myrcene (4.0-7.7%), neral (2.8-5.8%), 
 <italic>α</italic>-farnesene (2.8-7.9%), heptan-2-ol (1.6-2.0%), 
 <italic>β</italic>-sesquiphellandrene (6.5-11%), and 
 <italic>β</italic>-bisabolene (1.5-5.2%). These compounds could be associated with the distinctive flavor and aroma of EOs as well as their antibacterial and antifungal activities whereas the wild ginger type is made up of 
 <italic>β</italic>-phellandrene (4.2-42.7%), 
 <italic>β</italic>-pinene (17.2-22.0%), 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene (2.1-4.2%), and E-methyl isoeugenol (3.9-37.0%) as the major constituents (
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Awang et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Bhattarai et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">López et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">Mahboubi, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref105" ref-type="bibr">Şener et al., 2017</xref>). However, different analysis of natural products yields different efficiencies (Sharifi-Rad et al., 2017b) because of factors such as time for analysis and rhizomes are not efficiently utilized by headspace. In other words, some of the phytoconstituents are hidden in the rhizomes compared to the extracted EOs. 
 <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> shows selected chemical structures of components in ginger EOs (
 <xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">Mahboubi, 2019</xref>). Furthermore, 
 <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> shows that ginger possess chemical classes and biological activities such as antibacterial, antifungal, antioxidant, and anti-inflammatory activities (
 <xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">Mahboubi, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2019</xref>) because many monoterpene components and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons are known to be the main components of EOs.
</p>
