<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The early days of plasmolysis research were limited to qualitative visualization of changes under a microscope. Some studies aimed to quantify the changes by isolating the cells and weighing them before and after the osmotic stress, which sounds like a challenging task. However, Charles E. Overton would contribute significantly to our understanding of the membrane barrier by applying the osmometric technique with the understanding that the total osmotic pressure is equal to the sum of partial pressures in solution (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kleinzeller, 1999</xref>). With this improved resolution in hand, he could apply a quantitative and extensive approach to plasmolysis studies. Over a short period of time, from 1890 to 1900, he studied nearly 500 different compounds for setting the osmotic gradient, including salts, sugars, and nonpolar molecules (
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Overton, 1895</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kleinzeller, 1997</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>). One of the surprising findings was that aliphatic alcohols did not lead to changes in the protoplasm’s volume. Using his large body of quantitative data, he built a physical model of the cell membrane to explain his observations, modeled after gas laws that were being developed at the same time. He proposed that the lack of the change in the cell volume was caused by the free equilibration of nonpolar or lipoid-like molecules across the cell membrane. With this, he postulated that the cell membrane itself must be composed of similar nonpolar molecules to support the free partitioning of these substances and at the same time provide a barrier to salts and sugars. Therefore, the cell membrane was lipid impregnated and a distinctly different chemical environment from that of the cell’s protoplasm or the external solution in which the cell bathed. Most surprisingly, he even proposed that cholesterol and phospholipids could be candidates for the nonpolar chemicals composing the membrane. Finally, he investigated a series of nonpolar molecules that were well known for their activity in humans: general anesthetics. In parallel research with Hans Horst Meyer, they both found that the propensity for an anesthetic to partition into olive oil strongly correlated with its efficacy in the clinical setting (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meyer, 1899</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Overton, 1901</xref>), supporting the idea of a lipid-filled nonpolar barrier to cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" class="xref">Fig. 3</xref>). The work of Overton and Meyer is a fine example of biophysics-based translational research at the turn of the 19th century. Although debates about the actual composition of the cell membrane persisted over the years, Overton’s findings would end up standing the test of time. In 1976, Alan Finkelstein clarified these findings by carrying out a series of experiments studying the partitioning and diffusion of different solutes into nonpolar solvents. By studying solutes of different structures and sizes, he demonstrated that membrane permeability follows a coupled solubility–diffusion mechanism (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Finkelstein, 1976</xref>).
</p>
