<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nolkemper et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr121-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>
 </sup> examined the antiviral effects of aqueous extracts from different species in the Lamiaceae plant family, including extracts from M. officinalis, Mentha piperita, Prunella vulgaris, Rosmarinus officinalis, Salvia officinalis, and Thymus vulgaris. All extracts showed inhibitory effects when virions were treated with the extracts pre-infection, but effects were more potent against HSV-1 (strain KOS) compared to HSV-2 (strain HG). From strongest to weakest antiherpetic activity, the extracts were M. piperita (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.041 μg/ml and SI = 2610 for HSV-1; IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.227 μg/ml and SI = 471 for HSV-2), M. officinalis (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.025 μg/ml and SI = 2200 for HSV-1; IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.027 μg/ml and SI = 2037 for HSV-2), T. vulgaris (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.065 μg/ml and SI = 954 for HSV-1; IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.077 μg/ml and SI = 805 for HSV-2), P. vulgaris (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.229 μg/ml and SI = 546 for HSV-1; IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 2.114 μg/ml and SI = 59 for HSV-2), S. officinalis (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.777 μg/ml and SI = 113 for HSV-1; IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.359 μg/ml and SI = 65 for HSV-2), and R. officinalis (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.646 μg/ml and SI = 98 for HSV-1; IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.055 μg/ml and SI = 60 for HSV-2). Time-of-addition experiments revealed all extracts elicited their strongest antiviral effects when virions were pretreated, and none of the extracts demonstrated an ability to inhibit viral replication if treated post-infection. After treatment of an acyclovir-resistant strain of HSV-1 with maximum non-cytotoxic concentrations of each extract, it was observed that M. piperita and S. officinalis were able to decrease viral infectivity by 85% and 97%, respectively. The authors proposed that aqueous extracts of various species in the Lamiaceae family are able to inhibit HSV adsorption, including strains known to be resistant to pharmaceutical antiviral treatment. As such, these plants may be beneficial as a topical therapeutic treatment to prevent recurrent HSV infections.
</p>
