<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Subsequently, Reichling et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr126-2515690X20978394" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>
 </sup> prepared ethanolic extracts of 4 common medicinal plants from the Lamiaceae family and investigated their antiviral activities against HSV-1. The plants tested were Prunella vulgaris, Mentha piperita, Rosmarinus officinalis, and Thymus vulgaris. Two extracts of each plant were prepared using 20% ethanol and 80% ethanol as solvents and tested against acyclovir-sensitive HSV-1 (strain KOS) and acyclovir-resistant HSV-1 (strains Angelotti and 1246/99). A series of dilutions of all extracts were done and tested for viral infectivity. All dilution extracts were effective, even low concentrations of 0.01% almost completely reduced viral infectivity. M. piperita extracts were the most effective against wild-type HSV-1, demonstrating IC
 <sub>50</sub> and SI values, respectively, of 0.06 μg/ml and 7040 for the 20% ethanolic extract and 0.05 μg/ml and 5632 for the 80% ethanolic extract. The other extracts demonstrated IC
 <sub>50</sub> values ranging 0.08-0.82 μg/ml and SI values ranging 90-4530. Moreover, when the extracts were tested against acyclovir-resistant HSV-1, all 80% ethanolic extracts demonstrated complete plaque reduction of both strains. Time-of-addition experiments revealed when host cells were pretreated with the extracts, the 80% ethanolic extracts of P. vulgaris and M. piperita were the only extracts that significantly reduced viral infectivity. When the virus was pretreated, the 20% ethanolic extract of M. piperita and 80% ethanolic extracts of P. vulgaris, M. piperita, and T. vulgaris were effective at entirely reducing viral infectivity. The other extracts were effective at reducing plaques by more than 75%. When the extracts were added during viral adsorption, the 80% ethanolic extracts of P. vulgaris and M. piperita fully suppressed viral infectivity while all other extracts, except the 80% ethanolic extract of R. officinalis, reduced plaque formation by more than 50%. The authors conclude that the 80% ethanolic extracts of M. piperita and P. vulgaris show a dual antiherpetic mechanism of action, and hence are promising candidates for treatment of HSV infections.
</p>
