<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This is the first study that characterizes the airborne fungal communities of invasive plants and evaluates their potential to cause plant disease. Similar to previous reports, we found that Cladosporiaceae was the most frequent fungus in the air, mainly represented by the genus 
 <italic>Cladosporium</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0230822.g002">Fig 2</xref>). Other fungi included common genera, such as 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic>, 
 <italic>Alternaria</italic> and 
 <italic>Epicoccum</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Previously, there have been verified the occurrence of more fungal spores in the air in the low part of the canopy, which is close to plant leaves (i.e., the important release source of fungal spores), compared with the number of spores in the air of the high part of the canopy [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Several reports from crop systems have also verified this trend [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. We did not found a higher fungal diversity and abundance in low part than high part of the canopy (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0230822.g001">Fig 1</xref>). This is possible due to the small distance of two heights (~1.5m, see methods). Many reports have indicated that the determining factors for airborne pathogen spores are very complex, related to the environment, season and time [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], and in particular meteorological factors [
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230822.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In this study, therefore, it is impossible to conclude the difference in fungal diversity across air column due to the small size of air samples (only two heights from two regions). However, partially supporting our expectation, we found that the air in the low part of the canopy (LC) had more fungal co-occurrences than the air in the high part of the canopy (HC) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0230822.g003">Fig 3</xref>). In particular, we found that the dominant pathogens on 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>adenophora</italic> enhanced the links among themselves (e.g., Didymellaceae fungi OTU90) and reduced their links with other fungi in the canopy air (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0230822.g003">3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0230822.g004">4A</xref>).
</p>
