<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some thioxanthonic derivatives were tested for P-gp activation and/or induction, and its ability to protect Caco-2 cells from the herbicide paraquat induced toxicity was assessed. All tested thioxanthones (
 <bold>83</bold>–
 <bold>87</bold>) at 20 μM caused a significant increase in both P-gp expression (inducer) and activity (activator) as evaluated by flow cytometry using the UIC2 antibody and rhodamine 123, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f020">Figure 20</xref>). They also increased P-gp ATPase activity in MDR1-Sf9 membrane vesicles, indicating that all compounds were P-gp substrates. Paraquat cytotoxicity was significantly reduced in the presence of four thioxanthone derivatives (
 <bold>83</bold>–
 <bold>86</bold>), and this protective effect was reversed upon incubation with a specific P-gp inhibitor. In silico studies suggested a potential co-transport mechanism of thioxanthones and paraquat [
 <xref rid="B184-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>]. The most potent P-gp inducer and activator, 
 <bold>85</bold>, can be considered a new and promising antidotal model against P-gp substrates cytotoxicity (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f020">Figure 20</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B184-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>]. Therefore, it was important to find a simple, rapid and economical method for the analysis and quantification of this thioxanthone. A reverse-phase high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) using a C18 column and a mobile phase composed of methanol-water (90/10, 
 <italic>v/v</italic>) with 1% (
 <italic>v/v</italic>) TEA, at a flow rate of 1 mL/min, was used for chromatographic separation. The method was validated according to ICH and it was selective, as there were no interferences of endogenous compounds with the same retention time. Also, the developed method was linear for 
 <bold>85</bold> concentrations between 0.5 and 150 μM. Therefore, this HPLC method could be used to detect trace amounts of these thioxanthone in biological samples [
 <xref rid="B185-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>].
</p>
