<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0170">For instance, 
 <italic>I. indigotica</italic> root extract showed significant 
 <italic>anti</italic>-SARS-CoV activity via inhibitory effects on 3C-like proteases (3CLpro) in the virus (
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2005</xref>). Similarly, in another study, aqueous extract of 
 <italic>H. chordata</italic> showed inhibition of RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) and 3CLpro activity in SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Lau et al., 2008</xref>). It was also revealed through flow cytometry-based analysis that extracts of 
 <italic>H. chordata</italic> boosted immune response against SARS-CoV through increasing the proportion of cluster of differentiation (CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup>) T cells. Similarly, root extract of 
 <italic>P. sidoides</italic> has been shown to interfere with replication of human coronaviruses (
 <xref rid="bib140" ref-type="bibr">Whitehead et al., 2019</xref>). Currently, there are numerous studies available on plant-based compounds from limited number of plants against coronaviruses. Plants used in the form of extracts or any other form against different respiratory viruses could be employed to work against COVID-19. One area that bears enormous potential exploring these and many other such plants which are used against viruses having similar structural features as that of COVID-19, exhibiting the same pattern of infection, similar pathophysiology, and similar symptoms. This can be demonstrated by a detailed analysis of replication cycle of the COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). For example, those plant products used against viruses belonging to the same origin as COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Cyprus_Mail, 2020</xref>), or those having genome of similar orientation (i.e. positive stranded RNA viruses (
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Ogbole et al., 2018</xref>) could be employed for fighting against COVID-19.
</p>
