<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiments presented here have been carried out with RC, which has been used traditionally for the symptomatic treatment of mild, spasmodic and other gastrointestinal complaints, however, the presumed smooth muscle-relaxant effect has not been confirmed experimentally. The aim of our study was to investigate the effect of a traditionally used extract of the plant, its fractions and the essential oil of the plant, as well as of four of its flavonoid components.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The phytochemical analysis of the extract revealed the presence of flavonoids in the plant, four of which (apigenin, luteolin, eupafolin, and hispidulin) were isolated and identified. The hydroethanolic extract was fractionated on polyamide to gain fractions with different flavonoid content in order to examine the role of these compounds in the effect on smooth muscles. The flavonoid content of the extract and fractions was analyzed by HPLC. The flavonoid content of the extract was fractionated successfully, fractions F80, F100 (and to some extent F60) containing higher amounts of flavonoids than the crude extracts. The flavonoid pattern of fractions also differed. The essential oil analyzed by us belongs to the chemotype characterized by the predominance of methallyl angelate.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pharmacological experiments were carried out with the hydroethanolic extract, its fractions (F20, F40, F60, F80, and F100), four flavonoids (apigenin, eupafolin, hispidulin, and luteolin) and the essential oil of the plant on different smooth muscles 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span>. The hydroethanolic extract of RC has both stimulatory and relaxant effects on guinea pig ileum. The moderate, transient stimulatory activity results from the activation of cholinergic neurons, as confirmed by its inhibition by tetrodotoxin (an inhibitor of neuronal voltage-sensitive Na
  <span class="sup">+</span> channels) and atropine (antagonist on muscarinic receptors for acetylcholine). Although capsaicin, a stimulant of a certain class of sensory receptors (through which it evokes a “local efferent” response) shows a similar cholinergic, neurogenic effect in guinea pig small intestine preparations (see 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Barthó et al., 2004</a> for review), a functional blockade of capsaicin-sensitive nerve endings by capsaicin pretreatment failed to inhibit the contractile action of RC extract. The contractile action of RC extract was moderately, yet significantly reduced by the cyclooxygenase inhibitor indomethacin, which may indicate a modulatory role of endogenous prostanoids. Other pharmacological inhibitors tested had no contraction-reducing effect, therefore it is proposed that neither endogenous serotonin, nor PPADS-sensitive purinergic mechanisms play a role in the excitatory action of RC extract. It should be noted that both serotonin and ATP or the P
  <sub>2X</sub> receptor agonist α,β-methylene ATP are able to evoke cholinergic contractions in guinea pig ileum (
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">Benko et al., 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Barthó et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">Sandor et al., 2016</a> for recent data).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following the transient and mild-to-moderate stimulant effect, the RC crude extract exhibited a sustained relaxant effect on the guinea pig ileum in the presence of tetrodotoxin and atropine, and preliminary experiments indicated a similar relaxant effect also in the absence of atropine and tetrodotoxin. Yet, atropine and tetrodotoxin were included into these experiments for creating a methodologically clear situation, where an initial, neuronally mediated excitatory action would hardly interfere with the relaxant one. The concentrations of the extract causing relaxation were roughly the same as those causing contraction. Based on these data we propose that the site of action for the relaxant effect of RC is on the smooth muscle itself. Neither the adrenergic β-receptor antagonist propranolol nor the NO synthase inhibitor N
  <span class="sup">G</span>-nitro-
  <span class="sc">L</span>-arginine significantly reduced the relaxant effect of the RC extract, hence, no evidence was found for these mechanisms to be involved in the relaxant response. In fact, a direct relaxant effect of the extract was demonstrated on all gastrointestinal preparations tested, including human and rat gastrointestinal preparations, as well as in guinea pig bladder. In preparations with high intrinsic tone (rat ileum and rat colon), relaxant activity was practically the only response to be seen.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Different RC extract fractions evoked both contraction and relaxation on guinea pig ileum. While there was a clear-cut tendency correlation between the flavonoid content and the relaxant effect, in case of contractile action such correlation was not observed (on the contrary, fractions with lower flavonoid content exerted slightly higher contractile activities). Fractions with high flavonoid content (F60, F80, and F100) had remarkable relaxant effects, whereas fractions with no (F20) or low (F40) flavonoid content exerted no such activity. The pure flavonoids of the extract showed dual effects in the guinea pig ileum, much similarly to the crude extract. Moreover, there was no substantial difference between the potencies of the flavonoids. This means that any of these flavonoids may contribute to the sustained relaxant and the transient contractile effect of the extract. The essential oil of RC caused no contraction on the test preparations; nevertheless, a consistent relaxant effect was detected. This seems to indicate that (i) chemical components responsible for the stimulant effect may be absent in the essential oil; (ii) it may be that several types of compounds present in the extract are responsible for the smooth muscle-relaxant action. This point needs to be clarified in subsequent experiments.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contraction of guinea pig bladder in response to the RC extract proved to be special, in that it was reduced by half following 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> capsaicin pretreatment. This indicates that capsaicin-sensitive sensory nerves of the bladder wall are in some way involved in the excitatory effect of the RC extract (see 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Barthó et al., 2004</a>). Nevertheless, the RC extract and oil also induced bladder relaxation in pre-contracted preparations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Roman chamomile extract was effective in human jejunal preparations as well. Both an excitatory and a tetrodotoxin- and atropine-resistant relaxing effect were demonstrated, again, the smooth muscle relaxant one being more sustained than the excitatory one. Preliminary experiments have shown that this early contraction is reduced by atropine. Due to limited access to human tissue, no further analysis of these responses could be performed.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of possible medical uses it may be noted that a combination of nerve-mediated, mild-to moderate excitatory effect and a smooth muscle-relaxant action may even be advantageous for some gastrointestinal problems, e.g., diminished peristaltic activity, while for spasms in the stomach or large intestine it is obviously the smooth muscle relaxing activity that offers benefits.</p>
</sec>
