<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mints were also employed to manufacture perfumes and to mask distasteful substances in medicines. For hygienic purposes, Paulus Aegineta (625–690), a Byzantine Greek physician and compiler of Greek–Roman medicine, best known for his encyclopedia 
 <italic>Medical Compendium</italic>, mentioned the use of ground pennyroyal in a mint decoction, among several ingredients, to mask the displeasing taste of medicinal draughts [
 <xref rid="B31-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Peppermint essential oil is featured in several formulations containing either laudanum (i.e., an opium tincture) or morphine (i.e., the main component of opium). Albert Ethelbert Ebert (1840–1906), a prominent pharmacist of the late 19th century, featured peppermint essence in 
 <italic>The Standard Formulary</italic> as an ingredient of a complex formulation in which morphine was included [
 <xref rid="B32-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Similar uses were later carried out to mask the odor of fish oil [
 <xref rid="B33-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], cod liver oil [
 <xref rid="B34-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and laudanum. An example of the last case was the inclusion in the infamous nostrum 
 <italic>Shiloh’s consumption cure</italic> to be used for colds, coughs, bronchitis, asthma, and irritation of the throat [
 <xref rid="B36-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Unquestionably, the most explored mint compound for scenting and perfuming is menthol. This is easily explained by its capacity to induce the perception of coolness, which can strongly affect cognition, emotion and behavior [
 <xref rid="B37-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. It is legitimate to interpret that, given the inflammatory component of many diseases, manifested topically with redness and warmth, a “cooling” or “fresh” sensation would be logically sought for to calm the effect. Furthermore, the known local menthol anesthetic seems to have been also an important reason to include these herbs in medical recipes.
</p>
