<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">El-Subbagh et al. prepared and evaluated some new ethyl 2-substituted-aminothiazole- 4-carboxylate derivatives for their antitumor activity against 60 human tumor cell lines. Compound 
 <bold>13</bold> indicated significant activity toward RPMI-8226 leukemia cell line (GI
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.08 µM), and showed a wide spectrum activity against a set of 60 different human cells with GI
 <sub>50</sub> (MG-MID) value of 38.3 µM. According to a comparison between the known antineoplastic agent melphalan and derivative 
 <bold>13</bold>, melphalan showed more activity than analogue 
 <bold>13</bold> in all tested cell lines except the higher activity of compound 
 <bold>13</bold> against colon cancer cell lines and leukemia RPMI-8226 cell line. Based on the SAR studied, in the 2-aminoacetamide series, only derivatives with morpholino group or N-phenylpiperazino exhibited activity against MOLT-4 leukemia cell line. Compound with N-phenylpiperazino was more active than morpholino derivative and this derivative affect on another cell lines of SNB-19 CNS cancer and IGORV1 ovarian cancer. In the 3-aminopropanamido series, compound 
 <bold>13</bold> with diethylamino was the most active member with particular sensitivity toward six different cell lines and exchange of pyrrolidino, piperidino, morpholino, and N-methylpiperazino with the diethylamino moiety in 
 <bold>13</bold>, decreased a nearly 2-3 fold the antitumor activity. In the 2-aminopropanamido series, only derivatives 
 <bold>14a</bold> with pyrrolidino and 
 <bold>14b</bold> with piperidino displayed significant activity against the leukemia cell lines RPMI-8226 and SR. Among these three series, the 3-aminopropanamido series were more potent than the others. The results exhibited that compound 
 <bold>13</bold> is a promising lead for further development to characterize the scope and limitation of its activity (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].
</p>
