<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Developing viruses such as Ebola virus (EBOV), Lassa virus (LASV), avian influenza virus H5N1 (AIV) and the more recent SARS-COV-2 virus are seen as global health concerns. Despite many advancements in science, no effective vaccine or specific therapy has been approved for humans against these viruses, and so there is an urgent need to develop therapeutic treatments against these threats [
 <xref rid="B68-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Traditional Chinese medicine holds an exclusive position among the variety of traditional medicines because of its thousand-year history. The extracts described in this review have been proven to possess great antiviral activities, with a general consensus of low toxicity. In addition, compared to commercial pharmaceuticals, such medicinal herbs are readily available and much cheaper. With the current pandemic, many scientists have rushed to the development of a potential vaccine and therapeutic agent that is effective against COVID-19; however, herbal agents should not be overlooked. The data presented in this review show the promising effects many herbs and mushrooms have against a variety of viral infections. This review has highlighted the therapeutic potential of 
 <italic>Inonotus obliquus</italic> as a natural antiviral treatment against SARS-COV-2. Earlier studies into this mushroom have laid the groundwork into the antiviral capabilities of 
 <italic>Inonotus obliquus</italic>, however further research into characterising the bioactive ingredients, understanding the underlying mechanisms as well as assessing the efficacy and potential application in vivo should be encouraged in order to develop an effective antiviral treatment against COVID-19. Until the present time, there has not been much research regarding the potential of natural agents against COVID-19, thus opening the research into this field may unlock the potential such extracts may have against SARS-CoV-2. 
</p>
