<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Temperature played the most important role in reducing seed longevity in 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic>. Increasing temperatures are described to reduce the accelerated aging time, with seeds reaching the 0% viability in a shorter time [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Substantial decrease in the activity of antioxidants in response to increased accumulation of reactive oxygen species is associated with accelerated aging [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. If not counterbalanced, reactive oxygen species lead to the accumulation of damaged molecules such as lipid hydroperoxides and protein carbonylation that increase strongly in deteriorating seeds and may ultimately lead to seed death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Seeds may respond to high temperatures with seed death (non-tolerant seeds), non-altered viability (tolerant seeds) or trigger increased germination (i.e. pyrophile plants) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Seed survival curves may vary depending on specific temperature and exposure time [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In the case of 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic>, 5 °C increase from 45 to 50 °C were enough to reduce 4 times the L
 <sub>50</sub>, suggesting a strong sensitivity to temperature. Moreover, 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> seeds did not tolerate 3 h exposure at 95 °C as other Aizoaceaceae may do according to the study developed by Daws et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], where at least 20% seed survival was observed in 26 Aizoaceae species at 103 °C for 17 h. Seeds of 
 <italic>Welwitschia mirabilis</italic> from the Namib Desert have been reported to tolerate 80 °C for 48 h [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. However, those studies were orientated to evaluate seeds thermo-tolerance and low RH was used. High RH (up to 75–80%) is recommended for testing seed longevity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Differences in RH generate differential seed survival curves in 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> seeds under sensitive temperatures, with higher RH (87%) promoting a faster seed aging in comparison with lower RH (73%). This result coincides with those obtained in 
 <italic>Jatropha curcas</italic> L. seeds, which showed a faster deterioration in AA tests over water in contrast with using a saturated salt solution [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Similar results were obtained with 
 <italic>Hirschfeldia incana</italic> when comparing humid (75%) and dry (33% RH) storage at 35 °C, where humid storage decreased almost 100 times seed longevity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In fact, resultant products of non-enzymatic modifications of protein structures through glycation found in accelerated aged soybean seeds were formed most rapidly in seeds at high humidity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. The inactivation of proteins would depress the metabolic capacity and reduce the ability of biological systems to repair cellular damage occurring during storage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].
</p>
