<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Examples for which there are indications for the genesis of native sulfur in the absence of a classical oxidant include sulfur transformations by AOM and sulfur-carbon cycling in the highly sulfidic, hypersaline Urania deep-sea basin. Moreover, our thermodynamic calculations imply that genesis of native sulfur may be coupled to methanogenic pathways that couple oxidation of sulfide to the reduction of carbon dioxide or acetate (Eqs. 4, 10). From this follows that methane cycling may play a critical role in the genesis of ENSDs. However, this does not imply that the here proposed mechanisms are only applicable to systems that are fueled by methane (natural gas), but not to native sulfur deposits that are fueled by crude oil. Methanogenesis is a key process in the formation of heavy oil and can take place in the presence of sulfate (for a review, see 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gray et al., 2010</xref>). However, in a sulfate-rich environment, it is likely that the produced methane is immediately consumed by AOM coupled to sulfate reduction. Thus, genesis of ENSDs in an oil-dominated system can take place, even if the process is tied to methane transformations that remain hidden. Such cryptic carbon cycling via methane has been identified at the sulfate-methane transition in marine sediments (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beulig et al., 2018b</xref>), notably the very same environment for which cryptic sulfur cycling has been inferred (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Holmkvist et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brunner et al., 2016</xref>). If the genesis of native sulfur and methane is coupled (Eqs. 4, 10), the coincidence of cryptic carbon and sulfur cycles at the sulfate-methane transition would be a logical consequence: disproportionation of native sulfur to sulfide and sulfate provides the oxidant for subsequent methane oxidation by AOM. In ENSDs, sulfur disproportionation would not take place because the reaction is unfavorable at high sulfide concentrations, allowing for the accumulation of native sulfur.
</p>
