<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The preservation mechanism including gas modification and induction defense properties of ECF with NPs were demonstrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01695-f006" class="xref">Figure 6</xref>. As indicated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01695-f006" class="xref">Figure 6</xref>, the solution of ECF with NPs can form a thin coating film on the surfaces of fresh products after being treated and dried. Then, the matrix carriers such as CS-based coatings with semipermeable properties could retard the respiration rate of fruits by modifying the concentrations of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, and ethylene in the packages. This gas modification might inhibit the loss of water and nutrients in the products [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>]. On the other hand, the NPs in coating materials on the produce surface might exhibit excellent antimicrobial activities, especially induced by UV light, against pathogens in the packages and grown on the surface of fresh products. These antimicrobial activities could provide the significant contributions for controlling the decay and quality loss of produce. Moreover, some coating materials such as CS also might provide the antimicrobial activities against bacteria and fungi during the storage of fruits and vegetables [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. More importantly, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01695-f006" class="xref">Figure 6</xref>, the ECF such as CS with NPs could possibly reduce the free radicals and activate the defense-related enzymes in the fruits cells, and then induce the defense activity of fruits and vegetable during the storage period [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. This combined effectiveness would keep the firmness, bioactive and inside color and then maintain a good quality and a suitable shelf life of treated fresh products (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01695-f006" class="xref">Figure 6</xref>).
</p>
