<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-antioxidants-07-00006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Environmental Effects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tocopherol levels increase in response to a variety of abiotic stresses, considered as evidence of its protective role [
  <a rid="B49-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-antioxidants-07-00006">49</a>]. Tocopherol concentration in almond oil depends on the genotype and the climatic conditions of the year [
  <a rid="B36-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-antioxidants-07-00006">36</a>,
  <a rid="B38-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-antioxidants-07-00006">38</a>,
  <a rid="B39-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-antioxidants-07-00006">39</a>,
  <a rid="B40-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-antioxidants-07-00006">40</a>,
  <a rid="B42-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-antioxidants-07-00006">42</a>], as well as on the environmental conditions of the growing region [
  <a rid="B36-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-antioxidants-07-00006">36</a>,
  <a rid="B38-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-antioxidants-07-00006">38</a>]. Drought and heat have been the most important stresses studied until now on the expression of the chemical compounds in fruit trees, including almond. The climatic conditions of the year, mainly temperature, affect the concentration of the different tocopherol homologues in several nut crops [
  <a rid="B50-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-antioxidants-07-00006">50</a>], indicating that these components depend on the temperature and the occurrence of drought during fruit or nut growth.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of drought stress on the oil percentage in almond kernels and on its composition is not clear since the results of different studies undertaken in this field are ambiguous. However, studies in other species reported that water stress appears to promote tocopherol synthesis [
  <a rid="B51-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-antioxidants-07-00006">51</a>,
  <a rid="B52-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-antioxidants-07-00006">52</a>,
  <a rid="B53-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-antioxidants-07-00006">53</a>]. In almond there was no obvious relationship between almond tocopherol content and the degree of water deficiency [
  <a rid="B54-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-antioxidants-07-00006">54</a>], since little variation in kernel oil tocopherols was observed under moderate water stress, except for the more severe deficit of 70% SDI (sustained deficit irrigation) which for all components, except γ-tocopherol, had higher values than the control. In this study, the minor tocopherol homologues appeared to be slightly more responsive to deficit irrigation than the main homologue, α-tocopherol, but their small proportion had little impact on the amount of the total tocopherol content [
  <a rid="B54-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-antioxidants-07-00006">54</a>]. In the “Nonpareil” almond cultivar, the highest accumulation rate of α-tocopherol takes place during the period from 74 to 94 days after anthesis [
  <a rid="B44-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-antioxidants-07-00006">44</a>], indicating that the critical period to add nutrient and water to ensure normal accumulation of these chemical compounds is during this period. Tocopherol concentration has been reported to be affected by drought stress in olive oil [
  <a rid="B55-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-antioxidants-07-00006">55</a>], but not in 
  <span class="italic">Brassica napus</span> [
  <a rid="B56-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-antioxidants-07-00006">56</a>], by temperature in soybean [
  <a rid="B57-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-antioxidants-07-00006">57</a>], and by a combination of both in shea butter (
  <span class="italic">Vitellaria paradoxa</span> C.F. Gaertn.) [
  <a rid="B50-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-antioxidants-07-00006">50</a>]. In olive oil, the total tocopherols and α-tocopherol were highly influenced by the crop-year rainfalls, with the highest concentration from olives harvested during the driest year [
  <a rid="B58-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-antioxidants-07-00006">58</a>]. The increase in tocopherol content might contribute to the prevention of plant oxidative damage in drought conditions [
  <a rid="B59-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-antioxidants-07-00006">59</a>,
  <a rid="B60-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-antioxidants-07-00006">60</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Higher tocopherol concentrations were found in almond kernels harvested in years with higher temperatures suggesting that this environmental factor could affect tocopherol synthesis during kernel development [
  <a rid="B34-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-antioxidants-07-00006">34</a>]. A study on the effect of two contrasting environments, with drought and heat conditions in Morocco, and irrigated and cold conditions in Spain, concluded that the tocopherol content, mainly of α-tocopherol, increased under the warmer climate conditions of Morocco [
  <a rid="B37-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-antioxidants-07-00006">37</a>]. More recently, higher α-tocopherol concentrations (~646 µg/g in average) were found when the almond kernel development mostly coincided with spring and summer months with warmer mean temperature in a study in arid Northwestern Argentina [
  <a rid="B40-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-antioxidants-07-00006">40</a>]. Similar results were reported for α-tocopherol in some almond genotypes grown under hot and dry conditions in Afghanistan [
  <a rid="B61-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-antioxidants-07-00006">61</a>]. Temperature during seed development in sunflower has shown to affect oil yield and tocopherol concentration since high temperatures may have a negative effect in oil synthesis, but not in tocopherol concentration [
  <a rid="B62-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-antioxidants-07-00006">62</a>,
  <a rid="B63-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-antioxidants-07-00006">63</a>]. In soybean seed, it has been reported that the increasing temperature from 23 °C to 28 °C can significantly increase tocopherol levels [
  <a rid="B64-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64-antioxidants-07-00006">64</a>]. Thus, the temperature could be considered an important parameter playing a great role in tocopherol accumulation in different species, including almond.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the effect of solar radiation, in “Nonpareil” almond kernels the concentration of α-tocopherol was increased after a mild solar UV radiation supplement using the white weed mat, which may have altered metabolic pathways and stimulated α-tocopherol accumulation in almond lipids [
  <a rid="B44-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-antioxidants-07-00006">44</a>]. In sunflower, it has been reported that an increase in intercepted solar radiation per plant increased the amount of tocopherol per grain [
  <a rid="B65-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65-antioxidants-07-00006">65</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
