<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Multiple molecular mechanisms mediate the pathogenic events of LPS-induced ALI [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Interaction between oxidative stress and inflammation plays a major role in mediating LPS-induced ALI [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. During the inflammatory response, neutrophils undergo a respiratory burst and produce superoxide. ROS overproduction is extremely toxic to host tissues, and their interactions with various cellular macromolecules result in severe pathophysiological consequences. Excessive LPS-induced ROS release is accompanied by production of lipid peroxides, inactivation of proteins, and DNA mutation [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Moreover, LPS-induced oxidative stress is associated with depressed antioxidant activity of the lung, which may aggravate LPS toxicity. Catalase is one of the most important antioxidant enzymes that antagonizes oxidative stress by destroying cellular hydrogen peroxide to produce water and oxygen. GSH acts as a major cellular antioxidant defense system by scavenging free radicals and other ROS. SOD is the only antioxidant enzyme that can scavenge superoxide. Catalase, GSH, and SOD are greatly depressed by LPS [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Our results are consistent with previous studies, as LPS caused marked lipid peroxidation. LPS increased MDA and 4-HNE, which are stable end-products of lipid peroxidation and are frequently used as biomarkers of oxidative stress. Moreover, LPS repressed the activities of the antioxidants (catalase, SOD, GSH, TAC) in lung tissue. Significantly, EC reversed LPS-induced oxidative changes as EC enhanced antioxidant activities and subsequently depressed lipid peroxidation, clearly demonstrating the potent antioxidant activity of EC.
</p>
