<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The decoctions were also screened for toxicity against human primary dermal fibroblasts (HDF). The HDF cells were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC PCS-201-012) and were cultured and maintained in Dulbecco's modified eagle medium (DMEM; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Australia), supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (Invitrogen), 50 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich, Australia), and 50 IU/mL penicillin (Sigma-Aldrich, Australia) by standard methods [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Briefly, the cells were maintained as monolayers in 7 mL flasks at 37°C, 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> in a humidified atmosphere, until approximately 80% confluent. Once confluency was achieved, 1 mL of trypsin (Sigma-Aldrich, Australia) was added to the culture flasks and incubated at 37°C, 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>, for 15 min to dislodge the HDF cells. The cell suspensions were then transferred to a 10 mL centrifuge tube and sedimented by centrifugation. The supernatant was discarded, and the cells were resuspended in 9 mL of fresh media. Aliquots of the resuspended cells (70 
 <italic>μ</italic>L containing approximately 5000 cells) were added to individual wells of a 96-well plate. A volume of 30 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of the test extracts or cell media (for the negative control) was added to individual wells, and the plates were incubated at 37°C, 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> for 24 h in a humidified atmosphere. All extracts were screened at 200 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL. The cells were then washed in PBS (pH 7.2) to remove interference due to sample colour. A volume of 20 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of CellTiter 96 AQueous One Solution (Promega) was subsequently added to each well, and the plates were incubated for further 3 h. Absorbances were recorded at a test wavelength of 540 nm and a blank wavelength of 690 nm using a Molecular Devices, SpectraMax M3 plate reader. All tests were performed in at least triplicate, and triplicate controls were included on each plate. The % cellular viability of each test was calculated using the following formula:
 <disp-formula id="EEq1">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="M1">
   <mtable>
    <mtr>
     <mtd>
      <mtext>% cellular viability</mtext>
      <mo>=</mo>
      <mfrac>
       <mrow>
        <mtext>Abs test sample</mtext>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|">
         <mrow>
          <mtext>mean Abs control</mtext>
          <mo>−</mo>
          <mtext>mean Abs blank</mtext>
         </mrow>
        </mfenced>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|">
         <mrow>
          <mtext>mean Abs control</mtext>
          <mo>−</mo>
          <mtext>mean Abs blank</mtext>
         </mrow>
        </mfenced>
       </mrow>
      </mfrac>
      <mo>.</mo>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
   </mtable>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
