<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The 
 <italic class="italic">Lippia</italic> species, which are morphologically similar to the 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana</italic> genus, contain limonene, citral, carvacrol, β-myrcene, camphor, and thymol as the main chemical components [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Some examples are 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> EO composed of carvone and limonene (group I), citral and β-caryophyllene, found in 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">L. citriodora</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">L. dulcis</italic> EOs (group II), and carvacrol, thymol, and 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene present in 
 <italic class="italic">L. origanoides</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">L. micromera</italic> species (group III). The group IV is characterized by a greater presence of 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene and a small amount of carvacrol and thymol, as in 
 <italic class="italic">L. origanoides</italic> EO [
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. The chemical composition of 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> EO is an example of the variations in EOs’ components, which determines the existence of a large number of chemotypes. In different regions of Colombia, the citral, carvone, and limonene chemotypes were found while, in Uruguay, the linalool chemotype was identified [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> species in Argentina present the linalool chemotype (up to 91%), citral chemotype (up to 76% with two subtypes, i.e., myrcene or limonene), piperitone chemotype (up to 37%), lippione chemotype (up to 50%), and dihydrocarvone chemotype [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Another example of the variable chemical composition of Verbenaceae EOs is 
 <italic class="italic">Lippia javanica</italic>, which presents five chemotypes, namely, the myrcenone rich-type (36–62%), carvone rich-type (61–73%), piperitenone rich-type (32–48%), ipsenone rich-type (42–61%), and linalool rich-type (&gt;65%) [
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. The EO of 
 <italic class="italic">L. graveolens</italic> consists mainly of thymol (31.6%) and sesquiterpenes such as caryophyllene (4.6%) and caryophyllene oxide (4.8%) [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. The EO from 
 <italic class="italic">L. origanoides</italic> also shows diversity in its chemical composition. Several authors revealed the different chemotypes found in various South American countries. Vega-Vela et al. [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>] described different chemotypes in several Colombian regions: chemotype B (rich in carvacrol), chemotypes C and D (rich in thymol), chemotype E (eucalyptol and α-phellandrene), chemotype F (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, eucalyptol or β-phellandrene trace, and thymol methyl ether), and chemotype G (thymol methyl ether, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, thymol, and γ-terpinene). On the other hand, Stashenko et al. [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>] classified 
 <italic class="italic">L. origanoides</italic> EO into three chemotypes according to their major components; they were: chemotype A (α and β-phellandrene, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, and limonene), chemotype B (carvacrol), and chemotype C (thymol). The comparison of these results allowed concluding that the chemical composition of the EOs obtained from different regions shows significant variation based on its main constituents [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. This chemical diversity is related to monoterpene and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons. The principal compounds are aromatic monoterpenes such as thymol and carvacrol, and monoterpene hydrocarbons and their oxygenated compounds type thujene, pinene, and carene, which are present in a lower proportion. The sesquiterpenes and their oxygenated derivates (β-caryophyllene, humulene and germacrene) constitute about 15% of EOs [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-23-00544" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>].
</p>
