<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par56">The anti-inflammatory activity of NLE extract was measured using carrageenan-induced rat paw oedema assay, skin prick test and erythrocyte sedimentation rate assay. Carrageenan-induced rat paw oedema model is an appropriate test commonly used in screening of anti-inflammatory agents. The biphasic acute inflammation induced by carrageenan is characterized by the release of pro-inflammatory mediators such as kinins, histamine and serotonin, in the first phase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], followed by the release of prostaglandins-like substances, the main mediators causing the acute inflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. This later phase is responsive to clinically useful anti-inflammatory agents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. The extract significantly decreased paw oedema sizes in a dose-dependent manner, thus, might be containing some anti-inflammatory compounds causing the inhibition of prostaglandin-induced inflammatory pathway. Subcutaneous injection of histamine (or other allergens) causes mast cells to degranulate and release histamine and other mediators, following the cross-linkage of specific IgE bound to their surface receptors. This leads to a triple response characterized by a capillary dilatation (causing a red spot), an arteriolar dilatation mediated by axon reflex leading to a flare (causing the redness in the surrounding area) and an exudation of fluid from venules and capillaries (causing the formation of a wheal), which wheal can be quantitated by measuring its diameter [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Thus, the skin prick test was used to measure the anti-inflammatory effect of NLE on the immunoglobulin E (IgE) response to ovalbumin (OVA) and on the vasodilatory activity of a preformed mediator, histamine, in sensitized rats. The extract significantly decreased wheal diameters in a dose-dependent manner, thus, might be containing anti-inflammatory compounds that could also block mast cells degranulation and the release histamine (or other mediators). Erythrocyte sedimentation rate assay measures the distance that erythrocytes have sedimented (under the influence of gravity) after 1 h in a vertical column of anticoagulated blood. The main factor influencing and directly correlating with the sedimentation rate is the amount of fibrinogen in the blood. The extract significantly decreased the ESR in a dose-dependent manner, thus, might be containing anti-inflammatory compounds that could block the synthesis of fibrinogen. Altogether, these results showed a consistent anti-inflammatory activity of NLE extract. These findings are consistent with the traditional use of 
 <italic>N. lotus</italic> as anti-inflammatory medicine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>] to treat arthritis and rheumatic pains [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>].
</p>
