<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par57">Invasive ductal carcinoma is the commonest histological type of breast cancer in Africa and acute T-cell leukemia exhibits a very aggressive course of progression with poor prognosis associated with shorter overall survival. Therefore, there is a need to discover new effective agents against these two types of cancer. MCF-7 is a human adenocarcinoma breast cancer cell line with estrogen, progesterone and glucocorticoid receptors, while Jurkat cell line was derived from human acute T-cell leukaemia. These two cell lines are excellent models for screening anticancer (cytotoxic) agents. The cytotoxic activity of NLE extract was determined using an MTT assay. Both NLE and curcumin (positive control) exhibited cytotoxic activities on MCF-7 and Jurkat cell lines, however, NLE was not as potent as curcumin. This difference could be explained by the fact that curcumin is a pure isolated compound and NLE is a crude extract containing several active compounds which could have antagonistic effects on each other. The cytotoxic activity of NLE revealed some cell-specificity for Jurkat cell line, as shown by the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of NLE for Jurkat and MCF-7. Interestingly, NLE showed less cytotoxic activity on Chang liver cells (normal cell line) when compared to the cancer cell lines (Jurkat and MCF-7). In the opposite, curcumin rather showed a potent cytotoxic activity on Chang liver cell line. These results corroborate similar antiproliferative studies on the cytotoxic activities of 
 <italic>Nymphea lotus</italic> (whole plant), 
 <italic>Nymphea alba</italic> and 
 <italic>Nymphaea mexicana</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>] and could be attributed to the phytochemical and elemental contents of 
 <italic>N. lotus</italic> leaves and therefore, could justify its traditional use as cancer treatment. Further bioactivity-guided fractionation studies would be necessary to isolate the active compounds responsible for the aforementioned activities.
</p>
