<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">We found that our lab experiments on herbivory results were species specific; 
 <italic>M. sexta</italic> (chewing herbivore; feeds on most Solanaceae members) gained less mass on mowed plants inflicting less damage to these plants than unmowed plants (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). However, 
 <italic>L. texana</italic> (chewing herbivore, co-evolved and feeds exclusively on SLN
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>
 </sup> mass gain was similar in both mowed and unmowed plants (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C). On the other hand, 
 <italic>A. craccivora</italic> (sucking herbivore, generalist aphid) population fared significantly better on mowed plants (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). In general, aphids induce SA pathway (salicylic acid phytohormonal signaling that provides resistance to plants against sucking insect pests and pathogens; 90) while chewing herbivores induce JA (Jasmonic acid) pathway in plants. Results from herbivory experiments are consistent with the JA and SA pathway negative crosstalk. Plenty of studies have reported negative crosstalk of JA suppressing SA action
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>
 </sup>. Traw et al. also found suppression of SA due to JA in Wassilewskija wild type of 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>which increased their susceptibility to 
 <italic>Pseudomonas syringae </italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>
 </sup>. We speculate that increased constitutive defenses under the JA pathway enhanced defenses against herbivores in general (as observed in field), and more specifically against 
 <italic>M. sexta</italic> in lab and field damage on the seedlings. Consequently, JA mediated SA suppression possibly led to mowed SLN being susceptible to sucking herbivore A. craccivora. However, the most important herbivore that damages SLN- 
 <italic>L. texana</italic>, a potential biocontrol agent
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>
 </sup> was unaffected by mowing, clearly suggesting that regardless of any enhanced defenses due to mowing, the co-evolved specialist herbivore was able to continuously feed and develop, as documented in other systems
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>
 </sup>. For example, Yang et al., looked at 
 <italic>Triadica sebifera</italic> in its native (Asia) and invasive habitat (USA). Using two generalist and one specialist herbivores, they found that even though the chemical composition of flavonoids and tannins changed in their respective habitat, the specialist fed more and consequently had better growth when compared to the generalist herbivores
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, Blair and Wolfe, have shown that plants introduced to new environmental conditions found to have faster germination, growth and enhanced reproduction but invest less in defense traits due to reduced herbivory pressure and enemy free space
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>
 </sup>. Our results are opposite (lower height and reduced number of leaves in mowed plants) is possibly due to the need of increased investment in defense traits due to higher herbivory and continuous mowing.
</p>
