<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p class="p">Due to their chemical constituents and biological properties, plants have long been used to control life-threatening diseases. The flora of Lebanon includes many plants that have already been demonstrated to have medicinal value, and other species, such as 
   <italic class="italic">Pentapera sicula libanotica,</italic> that are yet to be characterized. The present study characterized the chemical composition, anti-oxidant, anti-inflammatory, and anti-proliferative potential of aqueous, ethanol, and methanol extracts derived from the leaves of the Lebanese 
   <italic class="italic">Pentapera</italic> plant.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Material/Methods</title>
  <p class="p">High-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) was used to determine the chemical composition. Gas chromatography (GC) coupled with mass spectrometry (MS) was applied to determine the content of essential oil. DPPH radical scavenging assay was performed to evaluate the anti-oxidant potential. The anti-inflammatory potential was assessed using quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) by measuring TNF-α, IL-6, and CCL4 mRNA levels, and we assessed Cox-2 and iNOS proteins levels using Western blot (WB) analysis. MTT assay was carried out to determine the anti-proliferative potential.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">We identified, mainly in the alcoholic (methanol and ethanol) extracts, distinct bioactive compounds with pharmacological relevance. In parallel, with their phytochemical content, these 2 extracts showed significant anti-oxidant, anti-inflammatory and anti-proliferative capacities.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">Pentapera sicula libanotica</italic> appears to be a promising pharmacological tool.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
