<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="s2001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Malaria is among the most devastating and widespread tropical parasitic diseases which is more prevalent in developing countries. 
   <italic>Acanthus polystachyus</italic> (Acanthaceae) leaves are traditionally used for the treatment of malaria in Ethiopia. This study aimed to investigate the in vivo antimalarial and in vitro antioxidant activity of the leaves extract of 
   <italic>Acanthus polystachyus.</italic>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2002">
  <title>Materials and Methods</title>
  <p>The leaves part of 
   <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> were extracted using 80% methanol. The antioxidant effect of 
   <italic>Acanthus polystachyus</italic> extract was evaluated by using (DPPH) diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl assay model. To evaluate the antimalarial effect of the 
   <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> extract, 
   <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic> ANKA strain (chloroquine sensitive) was used to infect the mice in three different experimental protocol: suppressive, curative, and prophylactic test models.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The leaves extract of 
   <italic>Acanthus polystachyus</italic> significantly (
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05–0.0001) suppressed the parasitemia in all experimental protocol. The extract exhibited a chemosupression of 27.64%, 33.67% and 49.25% in 4-day suppressive test; 33.76%, 39.24% and 53.59% in curative test, and 25%, 32.84% and 50% in prophylactic tests at dose of 100, 200, and 400mg/kg, respectively. The extract also extended the mean survival time, prevented the bodyweight loss and body temperature drop, and packed cell volume significantly (
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) as compared to the negative control. Dose-dependent antioxidant activity was shown by the leaf extract of 
   <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> with an IC
   <sub>50</sub> value of 9.37µg/mL.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2004">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>The current finding showed that the leaves extract of 
   <italic>Acanthus polystachyus</italic> has revealed promising antimalarial effects. Thus, this finding supports the traditional use of 
   <italic>A. polystachyus</italic> for the treatment of malaria.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
