<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">X-ray diffraction (XRD) pattern analysis in the investigation by Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>], indicated that the bio-NC contained TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs in an anatase crystalline form with increasing intensity of the TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> region, and corresponded to the added TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. However, Zolfi et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] established that the integration of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs did not exert any influence on the crystal type in kefiran-WPI. As reported by Xu et al. [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], with the addition of CS, the characteristic absorption peak of GO in the UV-vis spectra disappeared. However, with the addition of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs, the absorption peak appeared to be higher. Achachlouei et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] found that the increase of crystallinity was prompted by the limited accumulation of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs due to the systematic arrangement of the clay nanolayers forming an intercalated structure in the NC. Moreover, the XRD test of Oleyaei et al. [
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>] further confirmed the completely exfoliated structure that originated in the potato starch-sodium montmorillonite (PS-MMT) NC containing 3% and 5% MMT. Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] indicated that the crystallinity of the biopolymer-based matrix decreased with the addition of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>
 <sub class="sub">.</sub> While Salarbashi et al. [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] established that the crystalline structure of the TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs remained intact in the SSPS matrix. Xu et al. [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] also indicated that in the fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectrum, the typical C-O stretching band of the amide group shifted to a lower wave number. During the investigations of Oleyaei et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], Achachlouei et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>], and Alizadeh-Sani et al. [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>], FTIR confirmed that the same bands found between CMC and TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs, also occurred between hydroxyl groups of starch and TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanofillers.
</p>
