<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Examining XRD patterns, Carvalho et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] discovered that several major peaks of ZnO were evident in the ZnO(Ag)-1 and ZnO(Ag)-2 samples, which denoted low crystalline preferential growth. From the XRD patterns and the FTIR spectra conducted by Singh et al. [
 <xref rid="B142-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">142</xref>], it was found that the amide bands shifted to a lower wavelength. These findings in conjunction with the change in the intensity of Infrared (IR) transmission at the CH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, amine, and carbonyl bands were compared with those of CS and found to be suggestive of contact between CS, β-Ca
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>(PO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>)
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and silver ions. Hasheminya et al. [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] indicated that hydrogen bond formation in the polymer matrix with CuO NPs and the crystalline structure in the CuO NPs polymer were revealed by FTIR spectroscopy and XRD analysis, respectively. Shankar et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] utilized FTIR analysis to reference the intensity increase in the amide-A region, which suggested that hydrogen bonding was employed to initiate contact between N-H groups of gelatin protein chains and ZnO NPs. According to Lungu et al. [
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>], a red shift with 1 nm was evident with reference to the Ag-ZnO NPs (mechanical deposition, MD) specimen, while a blue shift of 10 nm appeared to signify the Ag-ZnO NPs (CD) sample. These shifts were closely related to the Ag-ZnO NPs size, as well as contact with the electron-hole exchange on the NPs surface. AgNPs loading onto ZnO NPs surface substantially elevated the absorption levels within the visible light spectrum. The presence of (COO-), (-OH) and (-CH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) groups confirmed CMC capping of the synthesized Ag-ZnO NPs samples.
</p>
