<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Danish Environmental Protection Agency has specified regulations on the PW with respect to dispersed oil discharged into the ocean [
 <xref rid="B21-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. All Danish platforms in the North Sea are by law required to discharge less than 222 ton of oil per year in total [
 <xref rid="B21-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The regulations are stated by The Danish Environmental Protection Agency based on requirements from OSPAR Commission, which protects the marine environment and biodiversity in the North-East Atlantic Ocean [
 <xref rid="B25-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The amount of dispersed oil in PW can carefully be monitored and hereby reduced by the implementation of e.g., MPFMs, as they can optimize the separation process and chemical injection. In the permissions provided by The Danish Environmental Protection Agency given from 2019 to 2023 it can be seen from 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02184-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref> that the amount of PW and discharged dispersed oil is increasing with exception of some years due to shut down of big platforms (reconstruction of Tyra field in 2019–2022 [
 <xref rid="B26-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]). The increase of PW is a result of maturing fields with increasing water cut. This is supporting the importance of accurate measurements of the multi-phase flow and, hereby, the necessity of MPFMs. The increase in PW can also be a huge problem, if the legal requirements are not adjusted to this change, as it will be difficult to respect the given law. The data from 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02184-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref> are based on reports from The Danish Environmental Protection Agency regarding discharge permissions of dispersed oil in PW for the Danish North Sea fields operated by Total E&amp;P Danmark A/S, Hess Danmark ApS and INEOS Oil &amp; Gas [
 <xref rid="B21-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>].
</p>
