<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The size of the functional food market was approximately 161.49 billion in 2018, and its compound annual growth rate has been 7.9% since 2014. Thai foods are rich in medicinal ingredients [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Traditional Thai curry paste has been used for centuries as part of many famous foods in Thai restaurants. Tom yum and massaman are renowned among these lists. Over the centuries, Thai curry paste recipes were developed, and these vary by region. The composition is comprised of local Thai herbs, which include lemongrass, garlic, turmeric, fragrant basils, kapi (shrimp paste), lime juice, sugar, and chilies. Sugar is more often added in the central region of Thailand. Turmeric is also added in the southern region [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. There are several studies that suggest biological properties of these ingredients. Lemongrass fragrance showed antioxidant properties using a 2,2-diphenyl-1-picryl-hydrazyl-hydrate scavenging test [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Antimicrobial and anti-inflammatory properties have been tested. The effects of lemongrass essential oil related to the nervous system functions were investigated. Oil injections reduced nociceptive face-rubbing behavior in an animal study [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The anxiolytic-like and antidepressant activities in animal study were also reported for lemongrass essential oil treatment [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Garlic also shows antioxidant, antimicrobial, and anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Garlic oil and its components showed antidepressant-like effects via the increase of serotonin and the dopamine level [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> essential oil showed antioxidant activity and anti-inflammatory activity in a macrophage and animal model, respectively. For the nervous system, turmeric essential oil showed antinociceptive activity in acetic acid-induced writhing movements in mice [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The anxiolytic-like effect of curcumin was also investigated in an animal study [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Lime juice is an important source of antioxidants, such as flavonoids and vitamin C. This juice also confers favorable physicochemical characteristics of refreshing and a pleasing flavor to products [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02939" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
