<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies reported that oxidative stress increased Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx from extracellular fluid into neurons (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> driven by the endoplasmic reticulum might raise Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> concentration as well. The increased Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> concentration raises amount of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> in nuclei and mitochondria and finally leads to disrupting normal metabolism and neurodegeneration. T-type calcium channels (TTCCs) play important roles in neuroprotection, neuronal excitability, sleep, and sensory processes. They are also involved in pain and epilepsy. Diversity in the functional properties of T-type calcium channels is further supported by molecular investigations that have explained three genes encoding these channels: CaV3.1, CaV3.2, and CaV3.3 subunits (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). In a research done by El Alaoui, 2017, essential oil and methanolic extract of rosemary, as well as rosmarinic acid, inhibit the Cav3.2 current in a concentration-dependent manner in HEK-293T cells. Furthermore, they induce a negative shift of the steady-state inactivation of CaV3.2 current with no change in the activation properties. These results suggest that the inhibition of TTCCs might contribute to the neuroprotective and anxiolytic effects of rosemary (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Taken together, these findings support a pharmacological modulation of TTCCs by rosemary and suggest that TTCC inhibition might contribute to the anticonvulsant and neuroprotective properties of this medicinal plant. TTCCs might therefore, represent a novel molecular target for rosmarinic acid; although further studies are needed to investigate the efficacy of rosmarinic acid to possibly regulate other ion channels. Some performed studies on addiction are summarized in 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.
</p>
