<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_TOXREP559 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEgr7 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 pdf ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Toxicology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2214-7500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5978008</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2214-7500(18)30192-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2018.03.014</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Essential oil from <italic>Cymbopogon flexuosus</italic> as the potential inhibitor for HSP90</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gaonkar</surname><given-names>Roopa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shiralgi</surname><given-names>Yallappa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lakkappa</surname><given-names>Dhananjaya B.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>Gurumurthy</given-names></name><email>hegde@bmsce.ac.in</email><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Department of Biotechnology, B.M.S College of Engineering, Bangalore, 560019, Karnataka, India</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Centre for Nano-materials &#x00026; Displays, B.M.S. College of Engineering, Bangalore, 560019, Karnataka, India</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Toxinology/Toxicology and Drug Discovery Unit, Center for Emerging Technologies, Jain Global Campus, Jain University, Kanakapura Taluk, Ramanagara, 562112, Karnataka, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>hegde@bmsce.ac.in</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>05</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 Published by Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0005"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="fig0040" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="lis0005"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0005">The essential oil of Cymbopogon flexuosus or lemongrass oil (LO) is reported.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0010">Essential oil of C. flexuosus significantly suppresses the HSP90 gene expression.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0015">Increased expression of HSP90 gene by citral and geraniol in HEK-293 cells.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0020">Inhibition of HSP90-ATPase acitivity by the essential oil of C. flexuosus.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0015"><p>The essential oil of <italic>Cymbopogon flexuosus</italic> or lemongrass oil (LO) is reported to have antibacterial, antifungal and anticancerous effects. HSP90 is one of the major chaperones responsible for the proper folding of cancer proteins. In this paper we show that the essential oil of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> significantly suppresses the HSP90 gene expression. The cytotoxicity of the compounds was tested by MTT assay and the gene expression studies were carried out using HEK-293 and MCF-7 cells. Also we tested the efficacy of the major component of this essential oil viz. citral and geraniol in inhibiting the HSP90 expression. The oil was found to be more cytotoxic to MCF-7 cells with different IC<sub>50</sub> values for the oil (69.33&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL), citral (140.7&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) and geraniol (117&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL). The fold change of expression was calculated by RT-qPCR using &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct (2<sup>^&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup>) method and it was 0.1 and 0.03 in MCF-7 cells at 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL of LO. Western blot results showed suppression of HSP90 protein expression and HSP90 &#x02013; ATPase activity inhibition was also observed using LO. This study shows the anticancer mechanism exhibited by the essential oil of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> is by the inhibition of the important chaperone protein HSP90.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Abbreviations</title><kwd>DEPC, diethyl pyrocarbonate</kwd><kwd>DMEM, Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium</kwd><kwd>DMSO, dimethyl sulfoxide</kwd><kwd>ER, estrogen receptor</kwd><kwd>FBS, fetal bovine serum</kwd><kwd>GAPDH, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase</kwd><kwd>GC&#x02013;MS, gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry</kwd><kwd>HER 2, human epidermal growth receptor 2</kwd><kwd>HPLC, high performance liquid chromatography</kwd><kwd>HSP90, heat shock protein 90</kwd><kwd>LO, lemongrass oil</kwd><kwd>MTT, 3-(4,5-dimethythiazol-. 2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl tetrazolium bromide</kwd><kwd>PR, progesterone receptor</kwd><kwd>RT-qPCR, reverse transcriptase quantitative polymerase chain reaction</kwd><kwd>SERMS, selective estrogen receptor modulators</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="kwd0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Cymbopogon flexuosus</italic></kwd><kwd>Cytotoxicity</kwd><kwd>Gene expression</kwd><kwd>HSP90</kwd><kwd>RT-qPCR</kwd><kwd>Western blot</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="par0025">Breast cancer was found to be the second highest cause of death in women in USA and as of March 2017 statistics, more than 3.1 million women with a history of breast cancer [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Breast cancer is classified into subtypes based on the receptors expressed on the tumour cells viz. estrogen receptor (ER), progesterone receptor (PR) and human epidermal growth receptor (HER 2) [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The triple negative subtype had the minimum survival. MCF-7 cells are extensively used human breast adenocarcinoma cells with the useful characteristics similar to mammary epithelium, having the capability to process estrogen (ER positive) [<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The estrogen induces the proliferation of MCF-7 and the therapy for breast cancer targets mainly the blocking of estrogen action [<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The anti-estrogens are used as therapeutics against the ER+ve tumours have the inhibitory effects on MCF-7 [<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Estrogen binds to the DNA and modulates the gene expression of ER [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Selective estrogen receptor modulators (SERMS) i.e. tamoxifen compete with estrogen for ER binding and thus the antiestrogen therapy is one of the major therapies in ER positive breast cancer [<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p id="par0030">The treatment with anti-estrogen drugs like tamoxifen is the most preferred choice for the ER positive breast cancers. The resistance developed against the antiestrogen therapy is becoming a major problem in treating the estrogen dependent breast cancers. The de novo resistance is the complete absence of the estrogen receptor function or it may be the acquired resistance by the unresponsiveness of the hormone receptors to the anti-estrogens [<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Different compositions consisting of the admixture of different essential oils and pharmaceutically acceptable carrier has been reported to be useful in the treatment of breast cancer [<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The anti-proliferative and anti-estrogenic properties of the essential oils could be useful as alternative therapy in treating estrogen dependent cancers. Though there are monoterpenoids like linalool, d-limonene and &#x003b1;-terpineol have been studied for potential treatment for breast cancer, there are no reports about their anti-estrogenic mechanism.</p><p id="par0035">The essential oil of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> is reported to inhibit the proliferation of various cancer cells [<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. A component of LO i.e. citral, an important monoterpene and a flavouring agent is reported to inhibit the proliferation of human and murine cancer cell lines A2780, ECC-1, OVCAR-3, SKOV-3, ID8 and MOVCAR [<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Citral is reported to induce benign and atypical prostate hyperplasia [<xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and also the hormone sensitive tissue responsiveness was reported by its anti-estrogenic actions [<xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. One of the precursors of citral i.e. geraniol was also found to induce gynacomastia in man following its use [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In another study both citral and geraniol, did not show estrogenic or antiestrogenic actions at lower concentrations. Also these compounds did not show any estrogenic response in overiectemized mice. However at higher concentrations both citral and geraniol showed anti-estrogenic activity in estrogen responsive human cell line Ishikawa var &#x02013; I [<xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Citral is also reported to inhibit the proliferation and also inducing apoptosis in estrogen receptor positive MCF-7 cells [<xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p id="par0040">There are other compounds isolated from the natural sources and used in folk remedy reported to induce apoptosis in MCF-7 cells. Farnesiferol-C which was isolated from <italic>Ferula asafoetida</italic> (a type of coumarins) is induces cell cycle arrest and apoptosis in MCF-7 cells [<xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Also the naturally occurring secondary metabolites viz. depsidones isolated from marine fungus also have shown to inhibit tumour cell proliferation in T47D breast tumour cells [<xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. These studies show the anticancer potential of the compounds used in folk medicines.</p><p id="par0045">Though the anticancer properties are reported for the lemongrass essential oil, we report the anticancer mechanism by the inhibition of the important chaperone involved in oncogenic pathways viz. HSP90 gene and protein. The present study gives an understanding of the effect of lemongrass oil and its constituents viz. citral and geraniol on gene and protein expression of HSP90 in MCF-7 cells in comparison with normal HEK-293 cells. Also here we study the functional inhibition of HSP90-ATPase activity using pure HSP90 protein. To separate the components of LO and evaluate the mechanism of binding of those components into the N-terminal or C-terminal domains of HSP90 to study the interactions would be the future perspective for this study</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and method</title><p id="par0050">MCF-7 (HTB22) and HEK-293 (CRL1573) were obtained from ATCC. The essential oil of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> (LO) was obtained from Perfect Herbals and Oils, Madhya Pradesh, India. Citral (95%) and geraniol (98%) were obtained from Sigma, India. The essential oil, citral and geraniol were analysed using the newly developed HPLC method in our laboratory and also by GC&#x02013;MS [<xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The DMEM medium, FBS, penicillin G, streptomycin were obtained from Invitrogen, India. MTT powder was obtained from Sigma, India. The solution is filtered through a 0.2 &#x003bc; m filter and stored at 2&#x02013;8&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for frequent use or frozen for extended periods. DMSO and DEPC water, trizol and isopropanol were obtained from Sigma, India. Tecan Plate reader was from Tecan, Switzerland. The chloroform and ethanol were obtained from Ranchem. PBS required for cell culture was obtained from Himedialabs, India. 1.5 and 2&#x0202f;mL vials were obtained from Eppendorf and 15&#x0202f;mL falcon tubes were obtained from Tarsons Ltd. The vials and tubes were washed with DEPC treated water, autoclaved and oven dried. Human HSP90 protein was obtained from Stressmarq Biosciences, Canada. ATP&#x02013; Sodium salt was obtained from Sigma, India. Other reagents used in the HSP90 &#x02013; ATPase inhibition experiement were of analytical grade.</p><p id="par0055">The rabbit polyclonal antibody against HSP90 (sc-7947) was obtained from Santa-Cruz, Biotechnology, USA. The secondary anti-rabbit antibodies were from Invitrogen. The beta actin primary antibody (MA5-15739) and the anti-mouse secondary antibodies were also procured from Invitrogen. The SDS-PAGE and western blot analysis were done using the buffers from Invitrogen and ECL kit from Thermo Scientific-Pierce.</p><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Cytotoxicity study</title><p id="par0060">Cytotoxicity of LO and citral was tested on breast cancer cell lines MCF-7 using MTT assay. Cells were collected when they reach about 70&#x02013;80% confluency. Cells were checked for viability using Trypan blue staining and centrifuged. The wells were seeded at 50,000 cells / well of MCF-7 in a 96 well plate and incubated for 24&#x0202f;h at 37&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. The essential oil, citral and geraniol were added from 5 to 320&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL concentration in DMEM without FBS and incubated for 24&#x0202f;h. After incubation with test samples, filtered MTT (5&#x0202f;mg/10&#x0202f;mL of MTT in 1X PBS) was added to the respective wells (50&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g /well) and incubated for 3&#x02013;4&#x0202f;h. After incubation with MTT reagent, the MTT reagent was discarded by pipetting without disturbing cells and 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of DMSO was added to rapidly solubilize the formazan. The absorbance was measured at 590&#x0202f;nm.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Gene selection and primer design</title><p id="par0065">The GAPDH was used as housekeeping gene for HEK&#x002d7;293 and MCF-7 cell lines. HEK&#x002d7;293 was used as control cell line for the comparison of gene expression. Primers were designed for GAPDH gene (NG_007073) and HSP90 gene (NM_001017963.2) using Primer&#x02013; 3 and synthesized for GAPDH and HSP90 at Eurofins Genomics, India. The details of the primers were as tabulated in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap id="tbl0005" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primers used for the RTPCR reaction.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0185">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Gene</th><th align="left">Primer pair</th><th align="left">Sequence (5'&#x0202f;&#x02192;&#x0202f;3')</th><th align="left">Tm</th><th align="left">GC %</th><th align="left">Expected product size (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><bold>HSP90</bold></td><td align="left">FP</td><td align="left">TGGACAGCAAACATGGAGAG</td><td align="left">57.3</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">204</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RP</td><td align="left">AGACAGGAGCGCAGTTTCAT</td><td align="left">57.3</td><td align="left">50</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><bold>GAPDH</bold></td><td align="left">FP</td><td align="left">CGACCACTTTGTCAAGCTCA</td><td align="left">58.4</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">238</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RP</td><td align="left">CCCCTCTTCAAGGGGTCTAC</td><td align="left">58.8</td><td align="left">60</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>2.3</label><title>RNA isolation</title><p id="par0070">Both MCF-7 and HEK-293 cultured in DMEM medium and subjected to different treatments were washed twice with PBS and to the adherent cells 2&#x0202f;mL of Trizol (per T25 flask) was added and transferred to a falcon tube and vortexed. Samples were allowed to stand for 5&#x0202f;min at room temperature. To this 0.2&#x0202f;mL of chloroform per 1&#x0202f;mL of Trizol was used. The tube was shaken vigorously for 15&#x0202f;s. The tube was allowed to stand at room temperature for 5&#x0202f;min. The resulting mixture was centrifuged at 10,000<italic>g</italic> for 15&#x0202f;min at 4&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C. The colourless upper aqueous phase was transferred to a new clean tube. To this 0.5&#x0202f;mL of isopropanol was added per 1&#x0202f;mL of Trizol used. The mixture was mixed gently and incubated at room temperature for 5&#x0202f;min and centrifuged at 10,000&#x0202f;rpm for 10&#x0202f;min at 4&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C. The supernatant was discarded and the RNA pellet was washed by adding 1&#x0202f;m&#x0202f;L of 70% ethanol and mixed properly. The suspension was centrifuged for 5&#x0202f;min at 14,000&#x0202f;rpm at 4&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C and the supernatant was discarded. The pellet was dried by incubating in a dry bath for 5&#x0202f;min at 55&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C. The pellet was then resuspended in 25&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of DEPC treated water (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl0010" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>IC<sub>50</sub> values of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> oil with different cancer cells.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0190">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Tissue</th><th align="left">Cell lines</th><th align="left">IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4"><bold>Colon</bold></td><td align="left">HT-29</td><td align="left">42.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HCT-15</td><td align="left">60.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SW-620</td><td align="left">28.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">502713</td><td align="left">4.2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"><bold>Lung</bold></td><td align="left">H-226</td><td align="left">61.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">A-549</td><td align="left">49.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hop-62</td><td align="left">79</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5"><bold>Liver</bold></td><td align="left">Hep-2</td><td align="left">4.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SiHa</td><td align="left">6.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DU-145</td><td align="left">41.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KB</td><td align="left">50.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IMR-32</td><td align="left">4.7</td></tr></tbody></table><attrib>Adapted from Sharma et al. [<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</attrib></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>2.4</label><title>cDNA synthesis and semiquantitative RT-PCR</title><p id="par0075">A semi quantitative reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) was carried out using Techne Prime system to determine the levels of HSP90 and GAPDHmRNA expressions. The cDNA was synthesized from 2&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g of RNA using the Verso cDNA synthesis kit (Thermo Fischer Scientific) with oligo dT primer according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The reaction volume was set to 20&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L and cDNA synthesis was performed at 42&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 60&#x0202f;min, followed by RT inactivation at 85&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x0202f;min. The PCR mixture (final volume of 20&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L) contained 1&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of cDNA, 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of Red Taq Master Mix 2x (Amplicon) and 1&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M of each complementary primer specific for HSP90 and GAPDH (internal control) sequence (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The samples were denatured at 94&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x0202f;min, and amplified using 30 cycles of 94&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x0202f;s, 52&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x0202f;s, and 72&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x0202f;min for HSP90 and for GAPDH the renaturation was set to 52&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x0202f;s followed by a final elongation at 72&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x0202f;min. The optimal numbers of cycles have been selected for amplification of these two genes experimentally so that amplifications were in the exponential range and have not reached a plateau. 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of the final amplification product were run on a 2% ethidium&#x02013; stained agarose gel. Quantification of the gene expression was measured by the optical density of the bands, using the imaging program Image J.</p></sec><sec id="sec0035"><label>2.5</label><title>RT-qPCR and gene expression study</title><p id="par0080">A quantitative reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) was carried out using SYBR green in Stratagene Mx3005P real time PCR to determine the levels of HSP90 and GAPDH mRNA expressions. The cDNA was synthesized from 2&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g of RNA using the Verso cDNA synthesis kit (Thermo Fischer Scientific) with oligo dT primer according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The reaction volume was set to 20&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L and cDNA synthesis was performed at 42&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 60&#x0202f;min, followed by RT inactivation at 85&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x0202f;min. RT- PCR was done in 20&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L volume containing cDNA (1&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L), forward and reverse primer (1&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L), Sybr green MM (10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L), DEPC treated water (7&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L). 2step RT PCR reaction temperature profile was 95&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x0202f;min followed by 40 cycles of 95&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x0202f;s, 52&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 0.3&#x0202f;min, 72&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x0202f;min and a final extension step at 72&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x0202f;min. Relative expression of target HSP90 gene in relation to housekeeping gene (GAPDH) and untreated control cells were determined by the comparative Ct method (&#x00394;&#x00394; Ct method) described by Schmittgen et al. [<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The average of Ct values of triplicate data from different groups for HSP90 (target) and GAPDH (reference) genes were used for &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct [<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The fold change was calculated by using the formula fold change&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;2<sup>&#x02212; &#x00394;&#x00394; Ct</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><label>2.6</label><title>Western blotting</title><p id="par0085">The cell lysates were prepared using 20&#x0202f;mM Tris-HCl buffer (pH 8.0) containing 150&#x0202f;mM NaCl, 1% SDS and 1&#x0202f;mM EDTA. The protease inhibitor solution was added at 2&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL concentration. Lysates were sonicated for 10&#x0202f;s, centrifuged for 15&#x0202f;min at 10,000<italic>g</italic> and stored at &#x02212;80&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C. The protein concentration was measured before loading on the gel, using the BCA protein assay kit from Thermo Fisher (Compat-Able&#x02122;). 40&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g of protein lysate was mixed with 4X loading buffer. The proteins were separated on 10% SDS-PAGE gel. The gel was electrophoretically transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane. Nitrocellulose blot was blocked with 5% non-fat dry milk in TBST buffer (20&#x0202f;mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.4), 150&#x0202f;mM NaCl, and 0.1% Tween-20) for 1&#x0202f;h and incubated for 4&#x0202f;h with primary antibodies diluted in TBST/5% non-fat dry milk as per the supplier's recommendations (1/1000). Membranes were then washed with TBST for 20&#x0202f;min, 3 times and incubated for 1&#x0202f;h with HRP (horseradish peroxidase) labelled secondary antibodies in TBST. After an additional four washes with TBST, bound antibody was visualized by chemiluminescence.</p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>2.7</label><title>Inhibition of HSP90 &#x002d7; ATPase activity</title><p id="par0090">The terpenoids, alkaloids and glycosides are the biomolecules mainly obtained from plant sources naturally. These constitute the major components of folk medicine. The standard compounds like Withaferin a, asiatic acid, lemongrass oil were used at 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL for screening the HSP90-ATPase activity inhibition. The HSP90 &#x02013; ATPase activity inhibition was tested according to the protocol described by Martin et al. using malachite green reagent for colorimetric detection of phosphomolybdate complex [<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The malachite green reagent was prepared freshly and allowed to stand at room temperature for 2&#x0202f;h before use.</p><p id="par0095">The compounds viz. LO, citral and geraniol were diluted in 100% DMSO and further dilute to get 0.1%DMSO and also to get 400&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL concentrations of the components. 5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of the diluted sample was used in the assay (final concentration of 100&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL). The HSP90 (Stressmarq, SPR&#x002d7;102A) was diluted to 0.2&#x0202f;mg/mL using 100&#x0202f;mM Tris buffer (100&#x0202f;mM Tris &#x02013; HCl, 20&#x0202f;mM KCl, 6&#x0202f;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, pH 7.4). This protein solution (10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L) was used as HSP90 &#x02013; ATPase protein in the assay. The colorimetric assay was carried out using 5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of diluted components were added in the test reactions. The control reaction was carried out using 5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of 0.1% DMSO. 6&#x0202f;mM ATP prepared in Tris &#x002d7; HCl buffer was used as substrate in the revsactions. The reactions were carried out in 96 &#x002d7; well plates in triplicates. The standard graph was prepared from 0 to 8.3&#x0202f;&#x003bc;M of inorganic phosphate using KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4.</sub> After incubating plate for 3&#x0202f;h at 37&#x0202f;&#x000b0;C (with intermittent shaking) the reaction was stopped using 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L malachite green reagent and 10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;L of sodium citrate. The plate was read using microplate reader (Biorad) at 620&#x0202f;nm.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0050"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec0055"><label>3.1</label><title>Cytotoxicity study</title><p id="par0100">The GC&#x02013;MS analysis was carried out before using it in the cytotoxicity study and the GC&#x02013;MS graph was as shown in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. The cytotoxicity of the LO, citral and geraniol was tested with MCF-7 cells grown in DMEM medium for 24&#x0202f;h without FBS. The compounds were tested from10&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL to 320&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL. When tested using MTT (3 &#x02013; (4, 5 &#x02013; dimethythiazol &#x02013; 2 &#x02013; yl) &#x02013; 2, 5&#x02013; diphenyl tetrazolium bromide) assays, all 3 compounds inhibited the proliferation of MCF-7 cell lines with LO showing the highest inhibition (IC<sub>50</sub> &#x0202f;=&#x0202f;69.33&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL). Citral (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;140.7&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) and geraniol (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;117&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) also inhibited the cell proliferation with less efficiency as shown in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>b whereas with HEK&#x002d7;293 cells (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>a), the values were LO (80.19) citral (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;174.5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) and geraniol (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;138.9&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL). Apparently MCF-7 cells were more susceptible to the lemongrass oil, citral and geraniol treatments. The results were as shown in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(a &#x00026; b).<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>GC&#x02013;MS analysis of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> essential oil.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0150">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Cytotoxicity of citral, lemongrass oil (LO) and geraniol with a.HEK-293 cells, and b. MCF-7 cells.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0155">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="par0105">The results of cytotoxic studies showed that lemongrass oil had the highest inhibition of both HEK-293 and MCF-7. The IC<sub>50</sub> values were 80.19, 138.9 and 174.5&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL for lemongrass oil, geraniol and citral with HEK-293 cells. It was 69.33, 117 and 140.7&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL for lemongrass oil, geraniol and citral with MCF-7 cells. The lemongrass oil was the most effective among the 3 components considered for the study with respect to toxicity to both the cells, 80.19&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL with HEK-293 and 69.33&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL with MCF-7. The citral and geraniol inhibited the proliferation at comparatively high concentrations compared to lemongrass oil as shown in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(a &#x00026; b).</p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><label>3.2</label><title>cDNA synthesis and semiquantitative RT-PCR</title><p id="par0110">The HEK-293 and MCF-7 cells were treated with the selected low and high concentrations i.e. 80 and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL of the lemongrass oil, citral and geraniol. The gene selection and primer design was done as explained in the Section <xref rid="sec0020" ref-type="sec">2.2</xref>. The semiquantitative PCR was carried out as described in the Section <xref rid="sec0030" ref-type="sec">2.4</xref>. The gel doc images of cDNA were as shown in <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>(a&#x02013;c). The intensity of the bands was analysed using Image J software. The results of the analysis were as shown in <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>(a&#x02013;c). The fold change of gene expression from the semiquantitative RT-PCR results were calculated normalizing the value of HSP90 gene expression to the GAPDH expression. The results indicate the lemongrass oil is inhibiting the HSP90 gene expression in HEK-293 and MCF-7 with comparatively higher inhibition in MCF-7 cells. HSP90 gene expression was significantly affected at 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL (0.55 fold) and at 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL was five times lesser (0.22 fold) compared to control as shown in <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a. Further to confirm these observations a quantitative RT-PCR was carried out.<fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Effects of LO, citral and geraniol on the expression of HSP90 GAPDH in HEK-293 and MCF-7 cells. a) LO (80 and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) on HEK-293 and MCF-7, b) citral (80 and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) and geraniol (80 and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) on MCF-7, c) citral (80 and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) and geraniol (80 and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) on HEK-293.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0160">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0065"><label>3.3</label><title>HSP90 gene expression quantification by RT-qPCR</title><p id="par0115">The quantitative RT-PCR reaction was carried out as described in Section <xref rid="sec0035" ref-type="sec">2.5</xref> and the fold change of gene expression was calculated using 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394; Ct</sup> method. The experiments were done three times and the results were as shown in <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. The error bars represent the standard deviation of the triplicate data. The fold change of HSP90 gene expression was calculated by keeping GAPDH as internal control. The results showed that lemongrass oil at 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL reduced the expression of the HSP90 gene significantly in MCF-7 compared to HEK-293 cells as shown in <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>.<fig id="fig0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>HSP90 mRNA expression levels relative to GAPDH mRNA levels under treatment stress of selected lemongrass oil concentrations analyzed by real-time quantitative RT-PCR.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0165">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0070"><label>3.4</label><title>Western blotting</title><p id="par0120">The expression of HSP90 protein in the different treatments were analysed using western blotting as described in Section <xref rid="sec0040" ref-type="sec">2.6</xref>. The &#x003b2;-actin was used as internal control. The bands observed as shown in <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a.<fig id="fig0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Western blot analysis fold expression of HSP90 calculated using the &#x003b2;-actin as an internal standard. a) HEK-293 cells treated with C &#x02013; Control (0&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL), 40,80,160 and 320&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL lemongrass oil b) MCF-7 cells treated with C &#x02013; Control (0&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL), 40, 80, 160 and 320&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL lemongrass oil.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0170">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="par0125">The intensity of the bands was assessed by Image J software. The results were as shown in <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>(b &#x00026; c). There was comparatively reduced in different treatments of lemongrass oil. The experiments were carried out using fresh samples of cells which were treated with different compounds and dosages. The cell extract kept in storage for 1 week time showed complete absence of HSP90 bands in the treatment samples. So fresh samples were used for the study. The intensity analysis of the bands showed HSP90 protein was found to be present at 75% in 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL treatment and 53% in 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL in MCF-7 compared to control. In HEK-293 cells it was 89% in 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL and 77% present in 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL compared to control. This confirms LO is inhibiting the HSP90 expression at protein level also with a higher inhibition observed in cancer cells compared to normal cells (<xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>).<fig id="fig0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>HSP90 gene expression by RT-qPCR at different treatment concentrations of LO.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0175">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0075"><label>3.5</label><title>Inhibition of HSP90&#x02013;ATPase activity</title><p id="par0130">The gene expression and protein expression studies showed that the essential oil inhibits the HSP90 in HEK-293 and MCF-7 cells. To study the in vitro functional roles of the essential oil and its components citral and geraniol in inhibiting the HSP90-ATPase activity we performed HSP90-ATPase activity inhibition assessment by following the high throughput colorimetric screening protocol reported by Rowlands et al. [<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] as discussed in the Section <xref rid="sec0045" ref-type="sec">2.7</xref>. The HSP90&#x002d7;ATPase activity using pure human HSP90 (SPR102A, Stress Marque Biosciences, Canada). The order of HSP90 &#x002d7; ATPase activity inhibition was: Withaferin A&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;lemongrass oil&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;citral&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;geraniol&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;asiatic acid. The results were as shown in <xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>a.<fig id="fig0035"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>HSP90-ATPase activity inhibitory activity a) screening of plant based compounds, b) inhibition by LO at different concentration.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0180">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="par0135">Further the LO was tested at 4 concentrations 20&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL, 40&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL, 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL, 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL in duplicates. The results were as shown in <xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>b. The inhibition of the HSP90-ATPase activity was observed from 40&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL of LO. The inhibition was enhanced in 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL and 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0080"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="par0140">The present study reports the cytotoxicity, the inhibition of HSP90 at both gene and protein level by lemongrass oil significantly in the cancer cells. The cytotoxicity studies showed the lemongrass oil was highly cytotoxic (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;69.33&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL). The IC<sub>50</sub> values were reported with the essential oil of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> with different cancer cell lines by Sharma et al. [<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The same essential oil was found to be inhibitory to the HSP90-ATPase activity also in our study.</p><p id="par0145">The gene expression studies showed that the essential oil of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> (LO) showed inhibition of HSP90 in both HEK-293 and MCF-7 cells. Citral showed 20% inhibition in 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL and 10% inhibition in 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL in MCF-7 cells. However it showed increase in the mRNA expression of HSP90 in HEK-293 cells. Geraniol showed no inhibition in either HEK-293 or MCF-7; however the HSP90 expression was significantly increased in MCF-7 cells. Considering these outcomes, further studies of quantification of gene expression by RT-qPCR and quantification of protein expression was carried out using LO. The RT-qPCR studies confirmed the indications of semiquantitatice RT-PCR that LO inhibited the HSP90 gene expression to a great extent (90% with 80&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL and 97% in 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL) with LO treatment as calculated by &#x00394;&#x00394; Ct method.</p><p id="par0150"><italic>Withania somnifera</italic> contains Withaferin A which is reported to inhibit the Hsp90/Cdc37 chaperone/co-chaperone complex [<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Also Withaferin A was reported to be very promising anticancer compound in pancreatic cancer and B-cell lymphomas by HSP90-ATPase activity [<xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Another pentacyclic triterpene asiatic acid is reported to protect human bronchial 16HBE and BEAS-2B cells against hydrogen peroxide induced oxidative and inflammatory injury [<xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Asiatic acid is reported to show antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and protection against glutamate or &#x003b2;-amyloid induced toxicity [<xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In our study we included Withaferin A and asiatic acid for studying the HSP90 inhibition alongwith the essential oil from <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> and its components citral and geraniol. The results showed the HSP90-ATPase activity was inhibited significantly with both LO and Withaferin A as shown in <xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>a. But asiatic acid showed increased HSP90-ATPase activity. The inhibition observed with citral and geraniol were not significant compared to LO or Withaferin A. The study with different concentrations of LO showed the ATPase activity was inhibited by LO from 40&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL to 160&#x0202f;&#x003bc;g/mL (<xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>b). However, it is unclear which component of the LO is responsible for the HSP90-ATPase activity inhibition. Because the major components of the lemongrass oil viz. citral and geraniol did not show HSP90-ATPase activity in vitro. Also, it could be possible that the synergy of the different components is responsible for the HSP90-ATPase activity inhibition. To separate the components of LO and evaluate the mechanism of binding of those components into the N-terminal or C-terminal domains of HSP90 to study the interactions would be the future perspective for this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec0085"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="par0155">The essential oil of <italic>C. flexuosus</italic> showed higher cytotoxicity to the MCF-7 cells and HEK-293 cells with the higher cytotoxicity for MCF-7 cells. The components citral and geraniol failed to inhibit the HSP90 gene expression. However the essential oil LO was also shown to inhibit the gene and protein expression. Also the LO showed inhibition of HSP90-ATPase activity.</p></sec><sec id="sec0090"><title>Transparency document</title><p id="par0170"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="upi0005"><caption><title>Transparency Document</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>American cancer society</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Cancer Facts and Figures</chapter-title><year>2017</year><comment>. (Accessed 29 April 17)</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures" id="intr0010">https://www.cancer.org/content/dam/cancer-org/research/cancer-facts-and-statistics/annual-cancer-facts-and-figures</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onitilo</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenlee</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukesh</surname><given-names>B.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer subtypes based on ER/PR and HER-2 expression: comparison of clinicopathologic features and survival</article-title><source>J. Clin. Med. Res.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="oref0015">MCF-7 cells infromation, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mcf7.com" id="intr0015">www.mcf7.com</ext-link>. (Accessed 29 April 17).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamelers</surname><given-names>I.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Schaik</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sussenbach</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenbergh</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>17&#x003b2;-Estradiol responsiveness of MCF-7 laboratory strains is dependent on an autocrine signal activating the IGF type I receptor</article-title><source>Cancer Cell Int.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12633505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De los Santos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Iglesias</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aranda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-estrogenic actions of histone deacetylase inhibitors in MCF-7 breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Endocr. Relat. Cancer</source><volume>14</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18045953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keenen</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor suppressor ING4 inhibits estrogen receptor activity in breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Breast Cancer - Targets Therapy</source><volume>8</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>221</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Early Breast Cancer Trialists&#x02019; Collaborative Group (EBCTCG)</surname></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relevance of breast cancer hormone receptors and other factors to the efficacy of adjuvant tamoxifen: patient-level meta-analysis of randomised trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>378</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21802721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouker</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaar</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilakivi-Clarke</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiestrogen resistance in breast cancer and the role of estrogen receptor signaling</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><volume>22</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>7316</fpage><lpage>7339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="oref0045">S. Bessette, E. Enan, Cancer treatment composition and method using natural plant essential oils with signal transduction modulators, Pat. No. US 20040156922 A1, 12-Aug-2004.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondhe</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthiah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahi</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>G.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anticancer activity of an essential oil from <italic>Cymbopogon flexuosus</italic></article-title><source>Chem. Biol. Interact.</source><volume>179</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Felder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Justanjyot</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavya</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manish</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The monoterpene, citral, increases intracellular oxygen radicals and inhibits cancer cell proliferation by inducing apoptosis and endoplasmic reticulum stress</article-title><source>AACR: Clin. Cancer Res.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scolnik</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Servadio</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramovici</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of experimentally induced benign and atypical hyperplasia in the ventral prostate of different rat strains</article-title><source>J. Androl.</source><volume>15</volume><year>1994</year><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7527017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geldof</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estrogenic action of commonly used fragrant agent citral induces prostatic hyperplasia</article-title><source>Urol. Res.</source><volume>20</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1372772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abramovici</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandbank</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mortician&#x02019;s mystery solved?</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><volume>319</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>1157</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pocock</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of estrogenic activity in some common essential oil constituents</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Pharmacol.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>1521</fpage><lpage>1528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12495555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaouki</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>D.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liagre</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beneytout</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hmamouchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Citral inhibits cell proliferation and induces apoptosis and cell cycle arrest in MCF-7 cells</article-title><source>Fundam. Clin. Pharmacol.</source><volume>23</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19656204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasanzadeh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahdavi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dehghan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charoudeh</surname><given-names>H.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Farnesiferol C induces cell cycle arrest and apoptosis mediated by oxidative stress in MCF-7 cell line</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28959668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chottanapund</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Duursen</surname><given-names>M.B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwartsen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Timtavorn</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navasumrit</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kittakoop</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sureram</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruchirawat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Berg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depsidones inhibit aromatase activity and tumor cell proliferation in a co-culture of human primary breast adipose fibroblasts and T47D breast tumor cells</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28959637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaonkar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yallappa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhananjaya</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of reverse phase high performance liquid chromatography for citral analysis from essential oils</article-title><source>J. Chromatogr. B</source><volume>1036</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyzing real-time PCR data by the comparative CT method</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18546601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowlands</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yvette</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prodromou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearl</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Workman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wynne</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput screening assay for inhibitors of heat-shock protein 90 ATPase activity</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>327</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15051534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamza</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu1</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunatilaka</surname><given-names>A.A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitesell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Withaferin A targets heat shock protein 90 in pancreatic cancer cells</article-title><source>Biochem. Pharmacol.</source><volume>79</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19769945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gachuki</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alhakeem</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oben</surname><given-names>K.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangnekar</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondada</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-cancer activity of withaferin A in B-cell lymphoma</article-title><source>Cancer Biol. Ther.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1088</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26020511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidative and anti-inflammatory activities of asiatic acid, glycyrrhizic acid, and oleanolic acid in human bronchial epithelial cells</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>63</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>3196</fpage><lpage>3204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25779760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Senut</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zemke</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frenkel</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudreau</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassab</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Panickar</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asiatic acid, a pentacyclic triterpene from <italic>Centella asiatica</italic>, is neuroprotective in a mouse model of focal cerebral ischemia</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Res.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>2541</fpage><lpage>2550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19382233</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Roopa G, gratefully acknowledges the <funding-source id="gs0005">Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR), New Delhi</funding-source> for awarding CSIR&#x002d7;SRF [Ref. No. 08/408(0001)/2013&#x002d7;EMR&#x002d7;I] and for the financial assistance provided. We thank <funding-source id="gs0010">TEQIP&#x002d7;II</funding-source> for the financial support in procuring the antibodies and HSP90 protein. We thank Dr.Yogisha (Skanda lifesciences, Bangalore) for providing the cell lines and facility to carry out the cell culture and gene expression studies. We thank Dr. Savitri Bhat, Sahana Rao and Krithika HL of Dept of Biotechnology, BMS College of Engineering for providing the Asiatic acid and Withaferin A standards.</p></ack></back></article>