<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Essential oils and chemical constituents of several 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia</italic> species have been investigated in the laboratory to protect against oxidative damage by inhibiting or quenching free radicals and reactive oxygen species. They have been proved as alternative antioxidants of synthetics. The antioxidant properties of the oils were assessed by several methods such as β-carotene bleaching (BCB) test, the 2,20-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical scavenging method, thiobarbituric acid reactive species (TBARS), Trolox equivalent antioxidant capacity assay (TEAC I-III assay), Total radical-trapping antioxidant parameter assay (TRAP assay), N,N-dimethyl-p-phenylendiamine assay (DMPD assay), 2,2′-Azinobis 3-Ethyl-benzothiazoline-6-Sulphonate (ABTS), 2,2-diphenyl-
 <span class="sc" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">l</span>-picrylhydrazyl assay (DPPH assay), Photochemiluminescence assay (PCL assay) and Ferric reducing ability of plasma assay (FRAP assay) [
 <xref rid="B105-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. We assessed the antioxidant activity of 
 <italic class="italic">A. nilagirica</italic> essential oil in our laboratory and found that the oil significantly inhibited radical cation formation, with 15.729 μL IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> (Inhibitory concentration) and 13.539 μL IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> preventing the bleaching of β-carotene [
 <xref rid="B106-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. While this oil exhibited higher antioxidant activity in the experiment of Sandip et al. [
 <xref rid="B33-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] in the DPPH (IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> 6.72 μg/mL) test, they reported the 
 <italic class="italic">A. chamaemelifolia</italic> essential oil as weak antioxidant. Oil of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">scoparia</italic> induced secondary metabolites production in root cells viz., scavenging enzymes—superoxide dismutase, catalase, ascorbate and guaiacol peroxide and was phytotoxic to root growth causing its inhibition [
 <xref rid="B107-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> essential oil (IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> 27.07 mg/mL) was able to reduce the stable violet DPPH radical to the yellow DPPH-H, reaching 50% of reduction. However, IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> reported in ABTS method was 5.97 mg/mL lower than that of DPPH method. This oil was also 50% able to reduce the ferric ions to ferrous ions (Fe
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>) at 127.17 mg/mL [
 <xref rid="B11-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. This oil showed 18% antioxidant activity of the reference compound (tocopherol) [
 <xref rid="B108-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. Phenolic compounds present in the 
 <italic class="italic">A. campestris</italic> essential oil contributed its major antioxidant activity, where 47.66 μg/mL EC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> was reported in radical scavenging activity, 5.36 μg/mL in FRAP, 0.175 μg/mL in superoxide scavenging activity and 0.034 μg/mL in OH scavenging activity [
 <xref rid="B109-medicines-04-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>]. Thus, this oil can be used as an antioxidant in the pharmaceutical industry.
</p>
