<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Curcuma</italic> is a plant genus comprising more than 70 rhizome-producing species worldwide. In China, there are approximately 20 
 <italic>Curcuma</italic> species, a small number of which have been used in Chinese herbal medicines and food products for more than a thousand years. Rhizoma Curcuma is the dried rhizome of 
 <italic>Curcuma kwangsiensis</italic> S.G. Lee &amp; C.F. Liang, 
 <italic>Curcuma phaeocaulis</italic> Valeton, and 
 <italic>Curcuma wenyujin</italic> Y.H. Chen &amp; C. Ling [
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The essential oils of 
 <italic>Curcuma</italic> are considered the active ingredients of these plants and have been demonstrated to have antiviral and antitumor properties [
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The main constituents of the essential oils in Curcumae rhizomes are curcumol, germacrone, and curdione, which account for most of the known pharmacological effects, and are typically used as quality control markers for the essential oils [
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>wenyujin</italic> (“
 <italic>wen e zhu</italic>” in Chinese) from Wenzhou, Zhejiang Province, China, is widely considered to be the best source of Rhizoma Curcumae (“
 <italic>e zhu</italic>” [
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]), on account of its distinctive regional characteristics and high medicinal value, and is mainly produced in Ruian, Wenzhou. The main active constituents of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>wenyujin</italic> are volatile oil and curcumin [
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], the former of which is composed of terpenoids and sesquiterpene derivatives, which have been reported to have anti-inflammatory, antitumor, lipid-regulating, antioxidant, antiviral, antibacterial, and other therapeutic effects [
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242776.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
