<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="ack0001">
 <sec id="sec0002">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p id="para0025">LSPM acknowledges support from the National Institute of Health Research (NIHR) Imperial Biomedical Research Centre (BRC) and the National Institute for Health Research Health Protection Research Unit (HPRU) in Healthcare Associated Infection and Antimicrobial Resistance at Imperial College London in partnership with Public Health England. The views expressed in this publication are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the National Institute for Health Research, The Wellcome Trust or the UK Department of Health. DAJ is funded by the DHSC Centre for Antimicrobial Optimisation, at Imperial College, London. The views expressed in this publication are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the Department of Health and Social Care, NHS, or the National Institute for Health Research. DAJ is also funded by a Cystic Fibrosis Trust Strategic Research Centre (SRC015) and a Wellcome Trust Collaborative Award (219551/Z/19/Z).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec0003">
  <title>Ethics</title>
  <p id="para0026">Ethical approval was not required for this service evaluation and audit of practice.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec0004">
  <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
  <p id="para0027">SD, AR and NM designed the study methodology. SD, TE and XG collated the data. SD drafted the initial manuscript with all authors contributing significantly to revising this for submission. All authors agreed on the final version for submission to the journal.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec0005">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p id="para0028">This research did not receive any grant from funding agencies in the public or commercial sectors.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec0006">
  <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p id="para0029">The data analysed during the current study and further details on the assays are available from the corresponding author (SD; sarahdenny1@nhs.net) on reasonable request, as long as this meets local ethical and research governance criteria.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
