<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prenylated flavonoids are a subclass of flavonoids, combining a flavonoid skeleton with a lipophilic prenyl side chain. They are compounds of low abundance in nature. Prenylation provides these compounds with improved biological activity. Increases the lipophilicity of flavonoids, providing a greater affinity for biological membranes and a better interaction with target proteins [
 <xref rid="B127-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. It was found that pterocarpan erycristagallin decreased the edema induced by phospholipase A2 by 51% in the first 30 min, however, the effect disappeared 60 min after application. This suggests that the effect may be an indirect inhibition of the enzyme. In rat peritoneal leukocytes, the application of erycristagallin inhibited the production of leukotriene B4 (metabolite 5-lipoxygenase). This compound showed purifying properties, inhibiting the stable free radical DPPH by 96% at a concentration of 50 AM, while the reference drug quercetin produced inhibition of 92% at the same dose. Previous studies have suggested that different antioxidant agents and free radical scavengers can reduce 5-lipoxygenase activity through a mechanism that interferes with divalent ions involved in catabolism of arachidonic acid [
 <xref rid="B129-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Besides, some prenylated flavonoids have been shown to have the ability to inhibit COX or LOX activity, depending on substitution patterns. Sigmoidins A and B, prenylated flavanones from 
 <italic>E. sigmoidea</italic>, contain a catechol group in ring B and a 2′5-diphenyl group (Sigmoidin A) or a 2′-prenyl group (sigmoidin B). At a concentration of 100 nm, sigmoidin A clearly inhibited leukotriene B4 production in rat polymorphonuclear leukocytes by 100%, while the same dose of sigmoidin B only reduced production by 44%. In PLA
 <sub>2</sub>-induced paw edema, sigmoidin B showed a clear inhibitory effect against the induction of edema (59% at 60 min) while sigmoidin A had only a mild effect at 30 min. Since sigmoidin B did not affect arachidonate metabolism, it was suggested that it affected histamine release [
 <xref rid="B49-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Another prenylated flavonoid, the prenylisoflavone warangalone isolated from the bark of 
 <italic>E. addisoniae</italic>, is a potent inhibitor of protein kinase A and showed marked anti-inflammatory efficacy on phospholipase A2-induced paw edema and 12-induced ear edema. O-tetradecanoylphorbol 13-acetate in mice [
 <xref rid="B46-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Prenylated flavonoids have been reported to act as anti-inflammatory, through five mechanisms that include antioxidant and radical scavenging activities; regulation of the activities of cells related to inflammation; modulation of the activities of the enzymes of arachidonic acid metabolism (phospholipase A
 <sub>2</sub>, cyclooxygenase, lipoxygenase) and nitric oxide synthase; modulation of the production of other pro-inflammatory molecules and the modulation of the expression of pro-inflammatory genes [
 <xref rid="B128-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B131-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>].
</p>
