<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Erythrina</italic> alkaloids have been of interest for their structural characteristics and their variety of biological activities [
 <xref rid="B93-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. The dihydro-β-erythroidine alkaloid was used to characterize the nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) [
 <xref rid="B94-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>], a preferential antagonist of the α4β2 nicotinic receptor subunit that acts as a competitive inhibitor like erisothrin, erisopine, erisodine [
 <xref rid="B59-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. nAChRs are involved in several central nervous system (CNS) disease states, including depression, schizophrenia, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s diseases, substance abuse, and pain [
 <xref rid="B95-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. On the other hand, it has been suggested that nAChRs may represent viable targets for new analgesics [
 <xref rid="B96-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. These receptors are widely distributed throughout the CNS, expressing themselves in neurons and non-neuronal cells [
 <xref rid="B98-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. In recent years, α7 nAChRs in macrophages has been shown to regulate inflammation, activating the “cholinergic anti-inflammatory pathway” [
 <xref rid="B98-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. There is accumulating evidence suggesting that α7 nAChR agonists and modulators are promising targets for the treatment of chronic inflammatory pain [
 <xref rid="B101-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>] The treatment with 
 <italic>E. mulungu</italic> extract significantly reduced the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines, as well as the infiltration of inflammatory cells in lung tissue. The main compounds identified in the extract were erisothrin, erisothrin-N-oxide and hypaphorine (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00248-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The cholinergic anti-inflammatory pathway allows the suppression of inflammation, it was characterized by its effects on the release of cytokines by macrophages. This pathway allows the suppression of inflammation by vagal efferents depending on α7 nAChRs [
 <xref rid="B99-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Hypaphorine, an anti-inflammatory compound [
 <xref rid="B102-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>] has been isolated from many 
 <italic>Erythrina</italic> species and other plant species [
 <xref rid="B98-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. A study carried out by Aswad 2017 determined that hypaphorine is one of the molecules that is considered as a potential candidate for an anti-inflammatory drug. Hypophorine present in 
 <italic>Vaccaria segetalis</italic> demonstrated downregulation of cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) and inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS). Furthermore, it delayed LPS-induced phosphorylation of ERK, and immunofluorescence staining revealed that 
 <italic>Vaccaria</italic> hypophorine eliminated nuclear translocation of NFκB in LPS-treated RAW 264.7 cells [
 <xref rid="B102-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. During inflammation, the action of α7 nAChR is associated with the entry of calcium and the interruption of the stimulation of nuclear factor κB (NF κB) [
 <xref rid="B105-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. It is possible that 
 <italic>Eryhrina</italic> hypaphorine regulates the inflammatory process through α7 nAChRs, activating a cholinergic anti-inflammatory pathway.
</p>
