<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The fatty acid profile was determined by gas chromatography (GC). About 5 g of wholemeal flour (in duplicate) was introduced in a Corning tube and suspended in 10 mL of chloroform–methanol 2:1 acidulated with 6 N HCl. A magnetic bar was added, and the tube was left to extract overnight at room temperature on a magnetic stirrer. The mixture was filtered through Whatman Grade 1 (1–11 μm) filter paper into an oven dried flask, then the solvent was evaporated by nitrogen flux followed by oven drying at 30 °C. The contents of the flask were re-dissolved in chloroform–methanol 2:1 to a volume of exactly 10 mL, then an aliquot was derivatized according to Zweig and Sherma [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-08-00223" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] as follows: 100 μL of this solution was introduced into a Corning tube containing 3 mL of methanol and a few boiling stones, then 0.5 mL of BF
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>–methanol (10% 
 <italic class="italic">w/w</italic>) was added and the tube caps were loosely screwed. The tubes were put onto a heating plate in a water bath and left to gently reflux at 72 °C for 30 min. Following this, the reaction was quenched with 2 mL of water, then the mixture was cooled to room temperature and extracted three times with 3 mL of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane. The hexane extracts were reunited into a vial and finally the hexane was evaporated by nitrogen flux. The vial was stored under nitrogen at −18 °C for a few days. Immediately prior to GC analysis, the contents of the vial were re-dissolved in 300 μL of hexane and 2 μL were injected. The GC instrument was an HP 5890 equipped with a Supelco (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) SPB
 <sup class="sup">®</sup>-PUFA (poly unsaturated fatty acids) column of 30 m length and a flame ionization detector (F.I.D.). The instrumental analysis was run according to Finotti et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-foods-08-00223" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]: 50 °C for 1 min, ramp of 10 °C/min until 160 °C, stay at 160 °C for 1 min, ramp of 2 °C/min until 240 °C. The detected peaks were individuated by comparison with chromatograms of standards (C16:0, C16:1, C18:0, C18:1, C18:2, C18:3) and quantified by using C17:0 as an internal standard.
</p>
