<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An interesting case is Andosan
 <sup>TM</sup> (ACE Co. Ltd. produced for Immunopharma, Gifu-ken, Japan), a product made from the mycelium of 
 <italic>Agaricus blazei</italic>, as well as smaller amounts of 
 <italic>Grifola frondosa</italic> (3%) and 
 <italic>Hericium erinaceus</italic> (15%), three mushrooms traditionally used for therapeutic purposes in Asia. This product has been tested in various clinical trials, demonstrating antitumor, anti-inflammatory, and antiallergic action, presumably mainly due to β-glucans and isoflavonoids [
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Although to date it remains unknown what the main constituent of this product is, as only small amounts of β-glucans have been detected in it, it seems that the results obtained in humans are due to the β-glucan stimulation of Peyer’s patches in the gut-associated lymphoid tissue (GALT), together with other less defined absorbable low-molecular-weight (LMW) substances, such as flavonoids [
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. In 2015, Tangen et al. [
 <xref rid="B71-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] reported the results of a clinical trial in which Andosan
 <sup>TM</sup> extract was orally given (60 mL/d) for seven weeks to patients with multiple myeloma undergoing high-dose chemotherapy with autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT). In patients receiving Andosan
 <sup>TM</sup>, increased percentages of Treg cells (CD4+, CD127d+, and CD25+) and plasmacytoid dendritic cells (CD303+) were observed, as well as a significant increase in serum levels of interleukins IL-1ra (receptor antagonist), IL-5, and IL-7. Furthermore, gene expression studies were also carried out, showing increased expression of immunoglobulin genes, killer immunoglobulin receptor (KIR) genes, and Human Leukocyte Antigens (HLA) genes in the bone marrow in the 
 <italic>Agaricus</italic> group; in more detail, an upregulation of endosomatic HLA genes and the plasma membrane CD86 gene was observed, and a downregulation of IL-7 and the proinflammatory chemokine CCL2 (MCP-1) genes, whereas the expression of the IL-5 gene was unaltered. In addition, the overall survival increased notably.
</p>
