<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Arbuscular mycorrhizal (AM) fungi are functional microorganisms that can form mutually beneficial symbiotic relationships with more than 80% of land plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. An arbuscular mycorrhizal network is formed by AM fungal mycelia, which are widely distributed in soil ecosystems and link two or more plant root systems [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Mycorrhizal networks can promote plant absorption of mineral nutrients in the soil and can change competition relationships among plant species [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. AM fungi have a positive feedback effect on the growth of 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>adenophorum</italic> and can enhance the competitive effect of 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>adenophorum</italic> on native plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Awaydul et al. (2019) [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] discovered that a mycorrhizal network preferentially transfers soil N and P to the invasive plant when invasive 
 <italic>Solidago canadensis</italic> and native 
 <italic>Kummerowa striata</italic> are interconnected with an arbuscular mycorrhizal network. When resources are scarce, there will be competition for aboveground light and competition for belowground water and mineral nutrients among plant species [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, at present, the research on invasion and AM fungi mainly focus on the effects of invasive plants on the diversity of AM fungi in invaded habitats and the effect of its feedback on aboveground competition between invasive and native plants. There is less research on the competition between belowground roots of invasive and native plant species. In the early stage of community succession, due to sufficient light resources, plants need to absorb more nutrients from the soil to promote growth, and thus the root systems of adjacent species have a fierce competition for soil water and fertilizer resources [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The nutrient absorption for competitiveness is proportional to the size of the plant itself in belowground competition [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Meanwhile, the neighboring competition under limited resources is more reliable [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Thus the belowground competition of plants plays a crucial role in plant growth and productivity [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].
</p>
