<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Roots can enhance a plant’s competitive advantage by adjusting its morphology when two adjacent plants compete for limited soil resources [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Additionally, through changes in root morphology, roots can improve the plant’s ability to absorb and utilize nutrients in the soil, which can be particularly beneficial in nutrient-deficient karst areas such as Southwest China [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Research has shown that plant roots in karst habitats have many branches and grow horizontally, thereby ensuring strong competitiveness for water and nutrients [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Xu et al. (2019) [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] believed that Chinese fir seedlings could enhance its specific root length to improve their P acquisition, when in competition with adjacent plants for a limited supply of phosphorus. Besides, root morphology and nutrients were significantly affected by soil microorganisms such as AM fungi [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Researches have shown that AM fungi can promote growth and change the traits of plant roots, thereby helping plants absorb more mineral elements from the soil [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. For instance, AM fungi can significantly enhance the total root length and volume of tea plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], and can markedly improve the P acquisition of the leguminous herb roots and invasive species [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Yang et al. (2014) [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] believed that AM fungi directly affect the utilization efficiency of nutrients of competing for the root system, and cause different plants to have asymmetric competition trends. Also, the mycorrhizal networks can change the nutritional and phenotypic traits of plants by amplifying the nutritional competition among plant species [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Therefore, AM fungi can affect species competition by changing plant root morphology and nutrients. However, it is unclear how do invasive plants compete with native plants in changing root traits by nutrient uptakes through mycorrhizal networks in karst habitats. We present and test the following hypotheses: (1) AM fungi can promote roots growth and nutrient uptakes of invasive and native species in karst soil; (2) the mycorrhizal networks can enhance the competitive advantage of invasive species over native species in nutrient acquisition fostering root morphological developments in karst soil.
</p>
