<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fluorescence spectroscopy has proved itself as an excellent nondestructive analytical technique with high specificity and sensitivity for the characterization of edible oils, thermal effects on olive oil during heating and storage, thermal processing of milk fats and dry milk storage effects[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. A number of research papers have been published for the investigation of temperature effects on edible oils using Fluorescence spectroscopy[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] but no study has been made so far reporting such effects on the molecular composition of desi ghee. Cheikhousman et al. employed Fluorescence spectroscopy to investigate the thermal deterioration of olive oil by heating the samples at 170°C and reported possible deterioration of different ingredients including vitamin E[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Microwave and conventional heating effects have been studied by applying fluorescence spectroscopy on mixtures of olive oil samples[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. It has also been used on heated samples of olive oil mixed with sunflower oil for their discrimination[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. F.G. Vila reported detailed molecular composition of olive oil and the effects of temperature using fluorescence spectroscopy[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Similarly, evolution of fluorescence compounds has been studied by fluorescence spectroscopy during the thermal deterioration of olive oil[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Temperature effects on extra virgin olive oil (EVOO) have been suggested a temperature range from 140 to 190°C where minimum variations in its molecular composition have been observed[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Literature review indicates that only a few article appear regarding desi ghee attributes[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], where gas chromatography has been employed to investigate the effects of storage on chemical properties of desi ghee[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. In another study explained molecular composition of desi ghee along with margarines and different edible oils[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Recently, Saleem et al. defined a safe cooking temperature range for EVOO where it almost retains its nutritional values[
 <xref rid="pone.0197340.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>].
</p>
