<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">However, our data also point towards a negative influence of the habitat change (Cimadom et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>). On Santa Cruz Island, the 
 <italic>Scalesia</italic> forest had been reduced to only 1% of its original distribution by previous agricultural activity (Mauchamp and Atkinson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2009</xref>), and more recently has been invaded by different introduced plant species (Renteria et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2012</xref>). Of these, 
 <italic>Rubus niveus</italic> (blackberry) has had the strongest negative effect on the original plant species composition. After its introduction on Santa Cruz Island in 1986, it spread rapidly and became very abundant in the last remnants of the 
 <italic>Scalesia</italic> forest at ‘Los Gemelos’ approximately 10 years ago (Rentería and Buddenhagen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2006</xref>; Renteria et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2012</xref>). Uninvaded 
 <italic>Scalesia</italic> forest with natural understory has disappeared entirely (personal observation Cimadom and Tebbich). In some areas of the 
 <italic>Scalesia</italic> zone, the Galápagos National Park Directorate (GNPD) manually controls 
 <italic>R. niveus</italic> with machetes and subsequently applies herbicides onto the regrowth to assist in the natural regeneration of the forest. The manual control caused a temporary removal of the understory, and we found that the breeding success of Warbler Finches was significantly lower in areas in which 
 <italic>R. niveus</italic> had been recently controlled (Cimadom et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>). Since arthropods use plants for refuge and/or for food, the removal of the understory may reduce their abundance (Boada 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>). Studies conducted in British and Canadian agricultural systems showed that the use of herbicides can cause declines in plant diversity that lead to a reduction in arthropods (Moreby and Southway 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1999</xref>; Morris et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2005</xref>; Boutin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2012</xref>). Like most small passerines, Darwin’s Finches depend on insects for chick rearing (Betts 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1955</xref>; Stutchbury and Morton 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2001</xref>). Therefore a lower insect abundance or availability might contribute to the lowered breeding success of the Warbler Finch in blackberry control areas (Cimadom et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2014</xref>). We hypothesized that habitat changes, due to both invasion by 
 <italic>R. niveus</italic> and the control measures used, reduce the availability of arthropods and change their micro-spatial distribution (e.g. across forest strata) and thus influence the foraging behaviour of the two study species.
</p>
