<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Conventional therapies for the management of cancer have several side effects due to their lack of specificity and are limited in rural settings [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Further, the sturdy resistance of cancerous cells to cytotoxic and antineoplastic drugs has presented a fresh challenge, giving unsatisfactory ministration outcomes and capricious resistance to antineoplastic agents [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Coupled with the prohibitive costs, unavailability of allopathic drugs, and chronic poverty in Uganda, there is a need to fold back on home grown solutions, exploring flora and fauna [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Uganda, the pearl of Africa, is part of the East African botanical block and is blessed with over 6,000 plant species [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Plants are regaining shape and emerging as an integral part of the ethnomedical approach for the management of diseases in Uganda [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The most cathartically notable anticancer botanical species in Uganda are 
 <italic>Prunus africana</italic> (Hook.f.) Kalkman and the periwinkle plant (
 <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.) G. Don) from which antitumor drugs vinblastine and vincristine have been developed [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Over 5,000 phytochemicals such as phenolics, carotenoids, glucosinolates, terpenoids, and alkaloids from over 3,000 plant species have been reported to be key actors in cancer therapy [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In Uganda, anecdotal reports reveal that there exists a pool of plants utilized locally for the management of cancer [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Indeed, information on indigenous medicinal plants used for various maladies has been reported by preceding authors, but none of them scrutinized anticancer plants. This review seeks to obtain a list of medicinal plants reported by ethnobotanical surveys in Uganda as anticancer plants and identify the active phytochemicals in the claimed plants and the anticancer studies done on them as per global studies. Potential candidates from this review which are scantily studied will be investigated in penultimate studies.
</p>
