<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As discussed earlier in this review, a number of publications have asserted that bacterial infections have been the source of elevated serum BDG [
 <xref rid="B106-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. While elevated BDG titers have been associated with bacterial infections in a number of studies, the demonstration of a contribution of BDG derived directly from the bacterium has not, in the main, been systematically demonstrated. Mennink-Kersten and colleagues described elevated BDG titers in a case series of bacteremic patients, particularly in infections with multiple 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. and a 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B107-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Among the 
 <italic>Streptococci</italic>, 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> Type 37 has been described as producing a BDG with a (1→3)-β-backbone with each glucose moiety having a (1→2)-β-glucose side chain [
 <xref rid="B108-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Held et al. 2013 described a mean serum BDG titer of 135 pg/mL in patients with enterococcemia while patients with other causes of bacteremia displayed a mean level of 15 pg/mL [
 <xref rid="B84-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Enterococcal species, which produce exopolysaccharides of mixed monosaccharide and glycosidic linkage composition, are not known to produce BDG. As the etiology of enterococcal bacteremia includes overgrowth in the intestinal lumen followed by invasion through the intestinal barrier [
 <xref rid="B109-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>], the possibility of BDG translocation through a damaged intestinal barrier represents a plausible mechanism of its elevation in the circulation. Recently, the Enterococcal exopolysaccharide poly-
 <italic>N</italic>-acetyl glucosamine has been determined to be a virulence factor due to its role in breaching the intestinal permeability barrier [
 <xref rid="B109-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. In contrast to bacterial species not observed to directly produce BDG, circulating BDG derived from invasive 
 <italic>Nocardia</italic> infections has been definitively demonstrated in a series of independent case reports. Elevated BDG titers were reported in infections caused by multiple species of 
 <italic>Nocardia</italic> including 
 <italic>N.abscessus</italic>, 
 <italic>N. elegans</italic>, 
 <italic>N. farcinica</italic>, and 
 <italic>N. nova</italic> [
 <xref rid="B110-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Additional evaluation to verify the presence of BDG involving the culturing of clinical isolates of 
 <italic>N. asteroides</italic>, 
 <italic>N. neocalidoniensis</italic>, and 
 <italic>N. cyriacgeorgica</italic>, as well as the control species 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, and the semi-purification of the post-growth culture broth supernatants was conducted. The un-inoculated medium and the controls were negative for BDG while the 
 <italic>Nocardia</italic> species’ supernatants were all over-range in the assay, confirming the source of the BDG as the 
 <italic>Nocardia</italic> infections [
 <xref rid="B112-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Thus, while a number of bacterial genera are known to produce BDG, very few are human pathogens. Of those pathogenic genera that do make beta-linked polyglucans, the genus 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> makes small, 2-12-mer, periplasmic osmoregulatory cyclic (1→2)-β-linked glucan sequences [
 <xref rid="B113-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>] which are broadly similar to the short (5-12-mer) branched (1→2)-β-linked glucans produced by 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B114-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Accordingly, while some bacteria are capable of producing (1→3)-β-linked beta-glucans, such as 
 <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B115-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>], of those genera that are human pathogens it is rare that they make the (1→3)-β-linked glucan structures that are the only forms known to be capable of the activation of 
 <italic>Limulus</italic>-based detection reagents.
</p>
