<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objective</title>
  <p class="p">A study was conducted to develop non-dairy creamer analogs/mimics using egg white, egg yolk, soy protein and their combinations, and their nutrient content, shelf-life and flavor acceptability were compared.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p class="p">Spray dried egg white, egg yolk, and soy protein isolate were purchased from manufacturers and used for the formulae.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">The protein contents of the non-dairy creamer analogs/mimics were about 8.5% as calculated. The amounts of oleic and linoleic acid content increased as the amount of yolk increased in the formula, but the increases of polyunsaturated fatty acids were &lt;0.5% of total fat. Addition of egg yolk to the formula increased choline and lutein content in the products, but the amounts were &lt;0.4 mg/g for choline and 4 μg/g for lutein. The lutein in the products continued to decrease over the storage time, and only about 15% to 20% of the 0-month amounts were left after 3 months of storage. Although the thiobarbituric acid reactive substances values of the spray-dried non-dairy creamer analogs/mimics increased as storage time increased, the values were still low. Yellowness, darkness, and egg flavor/odor of the non-dairy creamer analogs/mimics increased as the amount of egg yolk in the formula increased. The overall acceptability of the non-dairy creamer analogs/mimics was closely related to the intensity of egg flavor/odor, but storage improved their overall acceptance because most of the off-odor volatiles disappeared during the storage. Water temperature was the most important parameter in dissolving spray-dried non-dairy creamer analogs/mimics, and 55°C to 75°C was the optimal water temperature conditions to dissolve them.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p class="p">Higher amounts of yolk and soy protein combinations in place of egg white reduced the cost of the products significantly and those products contained better and balanced nutrients than the commercial coffee creamers. However, off-flavor and solubility were two important issues in the products.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
