<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Alginate gel formation is rather a complex process. The proportion and length of the guluronic acid block (G-blocks) in the polymeric chain, the capacity to bind the number of divalent ions, the type of gelling ions and gelling conditions affect strongly the hydrogel properties of alginate [
 <xref rid="B39-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. The introduction of divalent cations (usually Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> ions) to the system induces conformational changes in alginate such as alignment of the G-blocks and the formation of the egg-box model [
 <xref rid="B54-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] due to bounding of calcium ions between two chains and forming divalent salt bridges (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-07-00170-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>b) [
 <xref rid="B39-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. A higher amount of G-Blocks will create rigid and dense gels, while a higher amount of M-Blocks will build flexible, porous gels [
 <xref rid="B54-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Therefore, the diffusional resistance of gels containing predominantly high polyguluronic alginate content against high-molecular-weight-compounds is high [
 <xref rid="B56-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Besides, the study by Olivas and Barbosa-Cánovas [
 <xref rid="B58-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>] revealed that films containing higher proportions of G-Block (in other words, lower M/G ratio) showed better moisture barrier characteristics. 
</p>
