<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Datura metel</italic> belongs to family Solanaceae which grows throughout the year and is normally known as devil's trumpet [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> is nourished in the humid and hot climate. It is found in India, Pakistan, Africa, and South America [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Its flower is long and possessing a white color and has a purple color that scented up to 6 inches [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], while the leaves are green in color and bread in shape. 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> plant length ranges from 10 to 20 cm and broad from 5 to 18 cm. Its fruits are 4-10 cm thick and like a spiny capsule. 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> is a rich source of manufacturing numerous secondary metabolites such as saponins, flavonoids, triterpenoids, alkaloids, steroids, and tannins [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The biological potency of 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> is correlated due to the presence of secondary metabolites. An alkaloid known as scopolamine is a major compound isolated from 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> has been reported for the treatment of different diseases such as bronchitis and asthma [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> is also used for the cure of epilepsy, heart disease, fever, diabetes, insanity, diarrhea, and a skin disease [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. It is also a key source of producing anolides, which is also used for the treatment of pain and also have hallucinogenic strength [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Its seeds are used for the treatment of dental pain. It has extensive application in ayurvedic medication such as many classes of compounds isolated from the title plant that is used to treat hair fall and many skin-related infection disease [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The plant extracts of 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> has been reported for anti-inflammatory and antimicrobial effects [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Phytochemical 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> is discovered very slightly; atropine reported from 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>metel</italic> is used to dilate the pupil and it helps in the surgery of eyes [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The 
 <italic>α</italic>-glycosidase catalyzed the hydrolysis of glycosidic bonds in glycoconjugates as well as polysaccharides and act an acute role in different biological processes, such as lysosomal catabolism of glycoconjugates, posttranslational changes of cellular glycoproteins, and digestion of carbohydrate [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Particularly, human 
 <italic>α</italic>-glycosidase enzymes in the mucosal brush edge of the small intestine catalyzed the finale step of digestion of disaccharides and starch present in human food. 
 <italic>α</italic>-Glycosidase in the small intestine is selectively involved in the hydrolysis of terminal (1→4) connected 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucose residues (disaccharides/starch) to release a single 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucose molecule [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Potent 
 <italic>α</italic>-glycosidase inhibitor delay is involved in the reeducation of the postprandial blood glucose excursion and decomposition of carbohydrates in the small intestine; therefore, the inhibitor of 
 <italic>α</italic>-glycosidase has an important effect on metabolism polysaccharide, cellular interaction, glycoprotein processing, and wide chances for the development of new and novel therapeutic agents against various diseases including cancer, viral infection, and metastatic diabetes [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. 
 <italic>β</italic>-Secretase is an aspartic proteinase that is involved in numerous functions such as physiological processes in humans, including immunoregulation, death of the cell, and cell differentiation [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. There are several pieces of evidence that a change in 
 <italic>β</italic>-secretase action is involved in various diseases including schizophrenia, epileptic behavior, and Alzheimer's diseases [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. 
 <italic>β</italic>-Secretase enzyme is mainly involved in the breakdown of 
 <italic>β</italic>-amyloid precursor protein at one of the two decompositions required to produce 
 <italic>β</italic>-amyloid peptides. 
 <italic>β</italic>-amyloid peptides are the main compound of amyloid plaques in Alzheimer's disease brain and act as a key role in the pathogenesis of divesting neurodegenerative disorder [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The finding deals with the 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase and 
 <italic>β</italic>-secretase inhibitory screening of extract/fractions and isolated daturaolone (
 <bold>1</bold>), namely, 3-oxo-6-
 <italic>β</italic>-hydroxy-
 <italic>β</italic>-amyrin from chloroform fraction of 
 <italic>Datura metel</italic> L.
</p>
