<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From different taxonomic levels, the results of LEfSe analysis show significant differences in the relative abundances of bacterial and fungal communities in mangrove community (MC), 
 <italic>Kandelia obovataSpartina alterniflora</italic> transition zone (TC) and the 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> community (SC). Our research show that the relative abundance of some bacterial taxa is not significantly different between the MC and SC communities, but different changes have occurred during the invasion process (i.e., TC community). For example, the phylum Acidobacteria and Gemmatimonadetes, the class Alphaproteobacteria decreased sharply, whereas the phylum Proteobacteria and the class Epsilonproteobacteria increased rapidly during the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>. Previous studies have demonstrated that the relative abundance of Alphaproteobacteria in rhizospheric soil of the mangrove–
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> transition zone exhibited sharply decreasing trend after invasion by 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>, and that the phylum Acidobacteria has a significant positive correlation with soil pH [
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], which were consistent with our research. Janssen found that highly nutritious soils lead to greater relative abundance of Alphaproteobacteria [
 <xref rid="B51-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. However, Gao indicated that the indicator class of bacteria Alphaproteobacteria was strongly associated with the presence of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> [
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], which may explain that the relative abundance of Alphaproteobacteria returned to a higher level after the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>. Among them, the Epsilonproteobacteria and its members (i.e., the order Campylobacterales, the family Helicobacteraceae, and the genus 
 <italic>Sulfurovum</italic>), which increased significantly during the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>, belong to the relationship in which the former includes the latter in the order of the level in taxonomy. We infer that the genus 
 <italic>Sulfurovum</italic> plays an important role in the changes of higher classification levels, as it is the dominant group of the class Epsilonproteobacteria. Moreover, some taxa, such as the phylum Nitrospirae, the class Gammaproteobacteria and Nitrospira showed an increasing trend in the later stages of invasion. The order Xanthomonadales, which is the dominant order of the Gammaproteobacteria, contains a single family (Xanthomonadaceae) but many Gram-negative rod-shaped bacteria. The members of this group range from plant and human pathogens to non-pathogenic environmental bacteria, which can survive in harsh conditions such as contaminated soil and hot springs [
 <xref rid="B52-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
