<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Anthraquinones (9,10-dioxoanthracenes) are an important class of natural/synthetic compounds with a great range of applications [
 <xref rid="B279-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">279</xref>]. The most studied compounds as related to anti-viral activity are chrysophanol, emodin, and aloe-emodin [
 <xref rid="B280-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">280</xref>]. Anthraquinone based compounds includes chrysophanic acid, or chrysophanol, which is chemically 1,8-dihydroxy-3-methylanthraquinone and is extracted and isolated from Australian-based medicinal plant 
 <italic>Dianella longifolia</italic>. Chrysophanol showed antiviral activity against poliovirus through in vitro assays, mainly inhibiting the replication of poliovirus types 2 and 3 in vitro. Compared to other anthraquinone compounds, chrysophanol showed the highest antiviral activity against type 3 poliovirus [
 <xref rid="B281-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">281</xref>]. Emodin is anthraquinone used for the treatment of SARS-associated coronavirus which is obtained from genus polygonum and acts by inhibiting and blocking interactions of the coronavirus with ACE receptors [
 <xref rid="B282-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">282</xref>]. Recently, anthraquinones have been proposed as agents capable of counteracting SARS CoV-2 as, as reported in a molecular docking study, they are potentially capable of inhibiting the main protease of this virus. However, this property would be present in several anthraquinones since they are able to establish non-covalent bonds in the area adjacent to the active site with catalytic dyad HIS41 and CYS145. However, the inhibitory potential of these compounds was lower when compared to the FDA approved drug remdesivir. The data obtained from this research on the antiviral role of anthraquinones, highlighted that the alterporriol Q could be considered among the anthraquinone compounds the most promising inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 Mpro. Gingerol is product derived from ginger and mainly employed for the treatment of sore throats and common cold. It is used as a major constituent in ayurvedic formulations [
 <xref rid="B283-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">283</xref>].
</p>
