<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">HPTLC analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydroalcoholic and dichloromethane extracts were analyzed by HPTLC using a CAMAG (Muttenz, Switzerland) system constituted by a semiautomatic TLC Sampler Linomat 5 as application device, an Automatic Development Chamber ADC 2, a TLC Plate Heater III device, a Chromatogram Immersion Device III, Reprostar 3 (Digistore) as chromatogram documentation device, and the software WinCATS 1.4.6.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Test solutions were the hydroethanolic and dichlorometane extracts. Aliquots of 4 μL of test and reference solutions were applied on the plates as bands of 8 mm in length (distance from the left edge 15 mm and from the lower edge 8 mm). Plates were developed in ascending mode over a distance of 6 cm from the application position using a twin-through chamber fitted with filter paper previously saturated for 20 min with the mobile phase. Analyses were carried out at constant humidity (33%) at room temperature (23 ± 2°C). Two mobile phases were used depending on the test solutions analyzed: ethyl acetate, acetic acid, formic acid, water (100:10:10:25) for hydroethanolic extracts, and toluene, ethyl acetate, formic acid (70:30:1) for dichloromethane extracts.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Derivatization of the plates was carried out by dipping with either the Natural Products Reagent (NPR) and the PEG-400 solution (hydroethanolic extracts), or the anisaldehyde solution (dichloromethane extracts). In the case of hydroethanolic extracts, after elution, the plates were dried in cold air for 5 min, heated at 100°C for 3 min and dipped in the NPR solution (1 g of diphenylboric acid aminoethyl ester in 200 mL of ethyl acetate) while still hot. Once the plates were dried, they were subsequently dipped in the PEG-400 solution (10 g of PEG 400 in 200 mL of dichloromethane) and dried. Evaluation was performed under UV light at 366 nm. In the case of dichloromethane extracts, plates were immersed in anisaldehyde solution, prepared according to the European Pharmacopoeia (EDQM, 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">2016</a>), and heated at 100°C for 5 min. They were examined immediately in daylight and eventually under UV light at 366 nm.
 </p>
</sec>
