<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Laurus nobilis</italic>, known as laurel, is a perennial shrub which is widespread in temperate and warm regions, especially in the Mediterranean area where is cultivated as an ornamental plant reaching considerable size [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]; it grows spontaneously in the environment and is a diagnostic taxon of many habitats such as Lauro nobilis–Sambucion nigrae, Lauro nobilis-Tilion platyphylli, and Lauro nobilis–Ulmion minoris [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Laurel belongs to the Lauraceae family, which comprises approximately 2500 species, and was well-known in antiquity for being a symbol of peace and victory in Greece and ancient Rome, both in the military and in sport competitions, with its intertwined branches to create crowns. The use of laurel in foods is nowadays diffused and its particularly odorous leaves and berries are added to various dish preparations. In previous studies, the chemical composition of liquid phase 
 <italic>L. nobilis</italic> EO was investigated and 1,8-cineole, α-terpinyl acetate, α-pinene and α-terpineol resulted among the main components [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. During time laurel gained a considerable importance in traditional medicine [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and its leaf extracts or EO were used as gastroprotective and antidiarrheal [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], analgesic and anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], as antidiabetic and to decrease the risk factors of cardiovascular diseases [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The cytotoxic, antibacterial and antioxidant activities were also investigated, and different authors reported anticancer, antioxidant, insecticidal and molluscidal, antidiabetic, antimicrobial and antifungal activities by 
 <italic>L. nobilis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-00707" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
