<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="sec008" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fresh leaves of 
   <span class="italic">Cymbopogon citratus</span> (DC) Strapf and 
   <span class="italic">Pelargonium graveolens</span> L’Hér were harvested in July 2014 and June 2015 in Reunion Island. Roots of 
   <span class="italic">Vetiveria zizanioides</span> (L.) Nash were harvested in December 2015. All plant samples were kindly provided by the CAHEB (Coopérative Agricole des Huiles Essentielles de Bourbon), Le Tampon, Reunion Island.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec009" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil isolation and analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils were extracted in triplicate from 2.5 kg of aerial part (PG and CC) or roots (ZV) by hydrodistillation during 3 h using a Clevenger-type apparatus. Essential oils were decanted from aqueous phase, dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate and filtered using Minisart filters (0.2 μm). Samples were then stored at 4°C in darkness. The chemical composition of the essential oils was quantified by gas chromatography-flame ionization detector (GC-FID) on 
   <span class="italic">Clarus 500</span> gas chromatograph and identified by gas chromatography-time-of-flight-mass spectrometry on a GC×GC-TOF MS LECO Pegasus 4D system [
   <a rid="pone.0196757.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref027">27</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell culture</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human embryonic kidney cell line HEK293T (ATCC) and the kidney epithelial cell line Vero (ATCC) were grown in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle’s medium (DMEM, Dutscher, Issy-les-Moulineaux, France) or modified Eagle’s medium (MEM, Dutscher) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum heat inactivated (FBS, Dutscher) and completed with 2 mmol.L
   <span class="sup">-1</span>
   <span class="sc">l</span>-glutamine (Dutscher), 100 U.mL
   <span class="sup">-1</span>–0.1 mg.mL
   <span class="sup">-1</span> penicillin-streptomycin (Dutscher), 1 mmol.L
   <span class="sup">-1</span> sodium pyruvate (Dutscher) and 250 μg.mL
   <span class="sup">-1</span> amphotericin (Dutscher). Cells were maintained in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub> at 37°C in Petri dishes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec011" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cytotoxicity assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell viability was measured using the tetrazolium salt MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide) assay [
   <a rid="pone.0196757.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref028">28</a>]. Vero or HEK293T cells were seeded in 96-well plates (2×10
   <span class="sup">5</span> cells/well) and allowed to adhere overnight at 37°C. Cells were then treated 21 h at 37°C with each essential oil within a wide range of concentrations (0.14–1130 μg.mL
   <span class="sup">-1</span>). The essential oils were solubilized in 0.4% DMSO (Sigma). Following the treatment, 20 μL of 5 mg.mL
   <span class="sup">-1</span> MTT solution (Sigma, Saint-Quentin Fallavier France) were added on the 96-well plates and cells were stored at 37°C in the darkness. After 3 h of treatment, supernatant was removed and replaced by 100 μL of DMSO. Plates were then read at 570 nm on a microplate reader Tecan Sunrise™. The cytotoxic concentrations are defined as the concentration of the essential oil that causes death to 50% (CC
   <sub>50</sub>) or 10% (CC
   <sub>10</sub>) of viable cells with respect to controls without the essential oil (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0196757.t001" href="#pone.0196757.t001">Table 1</a>). Experiments were performed in hexaplicate from five independent experiments (see 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196757.s001" href="#pone.0196757.s001">S1 Fig</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0196757.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0196757.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Main characteristics of the essential oils.</div>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0196757.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0196757.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Essential oil</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major components %</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC
        <sub>50</sub> (μg.mL
        <span class="sup">-1)</span>
        <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001" href="#t001fn001">
         <span class="sup">a</span>
        </a>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC
        <sub>10</sub> (μg.mL
        <span class="sup">-1</span>)
        <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn002" href="#t001fn002">
         <span class="sup">b</span>
        </a>
       </th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">Cymbopogon Citratus</span> (CC)
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranial (45.11 ± 2.46%)
        <span class="break"/>Neral (32.16 ± 0.69%)
        <span class="break"/>Myrcene (7.85 ± 1.46%)
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.5 ± 20.5</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6 ± 8.2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">Pelargonium Graveolens</span> (PG)
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citronellol (23.43± 0.14%)
        <span class="break"/>Geraniol (16.85 ± 0.05%)
        <span class="break"/>Citronellyl formate (12.29 ± 0.05%)
        <span class="break"/>Linalool (10.79 ± 0.05%)
        <span class="break"/>Isomenthone (7.06 ± 0.02%)
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 1000</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">533 ± 199</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">Vetiveria Zizanoides</span> (VZ)
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khusimol (23.78 ± 0.13%)
        <span class="break"/>(
        <span class="italic">E</span>)-Isovalencenol (6.79 ± 0.12%)
        <span class="break"/>α-Vetivone (3.84 ± 0.04%)
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.9 ± 72.2</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4 ± 13.5</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="t001fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="sup">a</span> Cytotoxic concentration CC
      <sub>50</sub> that cause death to 50%
     </p>
    </fn>
    <fn id="t001fn002" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="sup">b</span> Cytotoxic concentration CC
      <sub>10</sub> that causes death to 10%. Results are expressed as mean ± SD from triplicate determination.
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec012" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Virus strains</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ross River virus derived from an infectious clone of strain T48 (RRV-T48), GenBank GQ433359 was generously provided by Professor Richard J. Khun, Purdue University [
   <a rid="pone.0196757.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref029">29</a>]. The recombinant RRV-T48 expressing 
   <span class="italic">Renilla reniformis</span> luciferase, as an integral part of the non-structural polyprotein precursor, was obtained according to the procedure previously described for Chikungunya virus [
   <a rid="pone.0196757.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref030">30</a>]. Briefly, the resulting plasmids pRRV-
   <span class="italic">ren</span>Luc was linearized and the corresponding RNA was transcribed 
   <span class="italic">in vitro</span> using the kit mMESSAGE mMACHINEs Kit (Ambion) before transfection into Vero cells to provide live RRV-
   <span class="italic">ren</span>Luc viruses [
   <a rid="pone.0196757.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref031">31</a>]. Supernatants were collected after 48 h (first passage) and used to infect Vero cells in order to grow final virus stocks for experiments (second passage).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec013" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plaque reduction assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Virus titers were determined by plaque assays in Vero cells growing in 48-well plates as previously described [
   <a rid="pone.0196757.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref032">32</a>]. Briefly, cells at confluence were incubated (0.1 mL/well) in triplicate with a serial of ten-fold dilutions of RRV-
   <span class="italic">ren</span>Luc containing samples for 2 h at 37°C. Then, 0.1 mL of 0.8% carboxymethylcellulose (CMC, Sigma) was added. After 48 h incubation at 37°C, CMC was removed and the monolayers were fixed with 3.7% v/v of paraformaldehyde (10 min at room temperature). Cells were then stained with 0.5% w/w crystal violet solution (10 min) and the virus titer in each well was estimated by counting the number of plaques observed. The results are expressed as plaque-formation unit per milliliter (PFU.mL
   <span class="sup">-1</span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec014" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cytoprotective effect of the essential oils against RRV-T48</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The capacity of the tested essential oils on RRV-T48 inducing cytopathic effect was assessed on HEK293T cells using MTT assay as described above. HEK293T were seeded in 96-well plates (2×10
   <span class="sup">5</span> cells/well) and allowed to adhere overnight at 37°C. Cells were infected by RRV-T48 alone at MOI 2 or by RRV-T48 at MOI 2 and addition of the essential oil at the highest non-toxic concentration (1×CC
   <sub>10</sub>) during 2 h at 37°C. After virus adsorption, supernatants were removed and cell culture medium or 1×CC
   <sub>10</sub> of the essential oil was added again. Cell viability was measured at different time points from incubation at 37°C (6;12;18;24;30;36;42;48 or 24;32;48 h post-infection). Controls consist in RRV-infected-HEK293T cells untreated with the essential oils. Chloroquine at non-toxic concentration was used as positive control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec015" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Virucidal activity of the essential oils against RRV-T48 and entry assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the virucidal activity, each essential oil at concentrations 0.1×CC
   <sub>10</sub> or 1×CC
   <sub>10</sub> was mixed with the RRV-T48 strain (1×10
   <span class="sup">5</span> PFU) during 1 h at 37°C. The residual infectivity was titrated by plaque assay on Vero cells with a serial of ten-fold dilutions. For the entry assay, Vero cells monolayers were pre-treated 3 h at 37°C with the essential oils. The residual infectivity of RRV-T48 strain was then titrated by plaque assay with a serial of ten-fold dilutions on the pre-treated Vero cells. All the experiments were performed in triplicate from five independent experiments and controls consist in RRV-T48-infected Vero cells without treatment with the essential oils.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec016" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RRV-renLuc reporter assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After infection with RRV-renLuc, the luciferase reporter is released in the cytoplasm during the polyprotein processing. HEK293T cells were seeded in 96well plates (2×10
   <span class="sup">5</span> cells/well) and allowed to adhere overnight at 37°C. Cells were infected with RRV-
   <span class="italic">ren</span>Luc at MOI 2 for 48 h. At different time points (6;12;18;24;30;36;42;48 h post-infection), supernatants were removed and cells were lysed using 20 μL of lysis buffer (0.4% CHAPS, 10% glycerol, 1 mmol.L
   <span class="sup">-1</span> EGTA, Tris-HCl, Sigma). 100 μL of the substrate coelenterazine (Euromedex, Souffelweyersheim, France) were then added and plates were immediately read by a luminescent plate-reader FLUOstar® Omega (BMG Labtech, Offenburg, Germany). Experiments were performed in hexaplicate from five independent experiments.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec017" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time-of-addition assay</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the effect of the essential oils on the replication of RRV, HEK293T cells were seeded in 96-well plates (2×10
   <span class="sup">5</span> cells/well) and allowed to adhere overnight at 37°C. Cells were infected with RRV-
   <span class="italic">ren</span>Luc at MOI 2 in presence of the essential oil. The essential oils were added at the highest non-toxic concentration (1×CC
   <sub>10</sub>): (i) 3 h before virus incubation (pre-treatment) and after virus incubation; (ii) during virus incubation (co-treatment) and after virus incubation; (iii) 2 h, 4 h or 6 h after virus incubation (post-treatment). In all cases, the luciferase activity was measured in hexaplicate from five independent experiments by the RRV-
   <span class="italic">ren</span>Luc assay. Virus titers were determined from five independent experiments from harvested supernatants. The end point of these two analyses was 24 h post-infection. Controls consist in RRV-infected-HEK293T cells untreated with the essential oils. Chloroquine at non-toxic concentration was used as positive control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec018" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where applicable, a one way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukeys or Dunn’s post-test when relevant, using the GraphPad Prism software, version 7.01 (GraphPad Software Inc.). A 
   <span class="italic">p</span> value lower than 0.05 was considered significant. Values are reported as the means standard errors (SEM) of n = 5 determinations unless otherwise stated. For the cytotoxicity assay, values were derived from dose-response curves and were calculated using GraphPad Prism.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
