<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The luminol-photochemiluminiscence (PLC) assay corroborated afterwards the high antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> essential oil [
 <xref rid="B217-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>]. It results in an easy, fast and sensitive method to know the scavenging activity of antioxidants against the radical anion superoxide, especially for hydrophobic-like essential oils [
 <xref rid="B217-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>]. This property may be due to the total phenolic content of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> essential oil that also highlights over more than 15 essential oils from different plant species [
 <xref rid="B235-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">235</xref>]. However, the phenolic compounds of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> essential oil and, consequently, the antioxidant activity can vary depending on the cultivation conditions. Especially, the substrate type, together with the presence of fungi, have significantly influenced the composition and activity of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> leaf essential oil [
 <xref rid="B169-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>,
 <xref rid="B170-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. The antioxidant activity can also change according to many other factors, such as the degree of dryness of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> rhizome. Specifically, the essential oil from the fresh rhizomes (24.4% ar-turmerone, 20.5% α-turmerone and 11.1% β-turmerone) exhibited higher DPPH radical scavenging, as well as Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>-chelating abilities, than the dry ones (21.4% ar-turmerone, 7.2% α-santalene and 6.6% ar-curcumene). The antioxidant activity of both essential oils was significantly higher than the commercial antioxidants BHA and butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) [
 <xref rid="B164-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>] (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00044-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Nevertheless, other authors reported a different trend. Gounder et al. demonstrated throughout several tests that dried and cured rhizomes had higher antioxidant activity than the fresh ones (ar-turmerone (21.0–30.3%), α-turmerone (26.5–33.5%) and β-turmerone (18.9–21.1%)). Specifically, ABTS radical cation scavenging [Trolox equivalent antioxidant capacity (TEAC) 68.0, 66.9 and 38.9 µM at 1 mg/mL]; ferric-reducing antioxidant potential (TEAC 276.8, 264.1 and 178.4 µM at 1 mg/mL); total antioxidant capacity by phosphomolybdenum assay (686, 638 and 358 ascorbic acid equivalents per 1 mg of oil) and reducing power were stronger in dried and cured rhizome than in fresh ones, respectively [
 <xref rid="B165-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>]. These differences are mainly due to the different compositions reported by the authors [
 <xref rid="B164-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>] in the fresh and dry rhizome essential oils used in the test.
</p>
