<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par49">In recent years, the importance of SPX domain-containing proteins in plant Pi homeostasis including sensing, signalling, and transport of Pi have been illustrated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. SPX proteins refer to proteins exclusively harbouring the conservative SPX (SYG1/PHO81/XPR1) domain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Previous studies have demonstrated that the activities of PHR1 are negatively regulated by SPX1 in Arabidopsis or SPX1, SPX2 and SPX4 in rice in a Pi-dependent manner [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. In the presence of Pi, SPX protein binds to PHR1 at high affinity and restricted its binding to P1BS 
 <italic>cis</italic>-element. Conversely, the binding affinity of the SPX-PHR1/2 complex declined in the absence of Pi and PHR1 is released to activate the transcription of downstream Pi-starvation induced genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In oil palm seedling roots, two SPX-domain containing genes (105,058,610 and 105,047,822) were low Pi inducible. This scenario was in agreement with those observed in Pi deficiency transcriptome analysis of other plant species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Moreover, a SPX-MFS domain-containing gene (105054157) was also significantly up-regulated at 28d. Protein harbouring SPX-MFS domain was designated as a member of PHOSPHATE TRANSPORTER 5 family (PHT5) and involved in vacuolar Pi sequestration to maintain cytoplasmic Pi equilibrium in the cell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. In plant cells, vacuoles seem to play a dual role as source and sink of Pi and changing of Pi concentration in cytosol or vacuole could acts as signal to activate PSR pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Thus, this SPX-MFS domain-containing gene is probably involved in modulation of Pi homeostasis in oil palm seedling roots after experiencing prolonged Pi scarcity stress.
</p>
