<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par52">Pi scarcity has profound impacts on diverse metabolic pathways as well as on transcription control. Such transcription reprogramming is expected to assist plants in accommodating to Pi deficiency and altering metabolism to ensure durability. After 28d growth in Pi-depleted media, several sulfate transporter genes were found to be down-regulated in oil palm seedling roots. SULTR1;3, a phloem-specific sulfate transporter is responsible for source-sink redistribution of sulfate while SULTR3;5 performs in synergy with SULTR2;1 in root-to-shoot transfer of sulfate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Conjointly with that, five DEGs (two ATP sulfurylase genes, two APS reductase genes and one cytochrome C gene) involved in sulfur metabolism were also being repressed. ATP-sulfurylase catalysed the first step in sulfate metabolism through adenylylation reaction to forms 5′-adenylylsulfate (APS) which subsequently undergo reduction assimilation carried out by the enzyme APS reductase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. Hence, it is conceivable that sulfate subcellular and inter-organ translocation and assimilation process was attenuated by prolonged Pi deficiency stress in oil palm seedling roots. Besides, Pi deprivation also exhibits repression effects on the expression of Fe-deficiency-induced Fe acquisition genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Even though no Fe acquisition related gene being listed as DEG in this study, there was a bHLH transcription factor, FIT being detected. Colangelo and Guerinot [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>] had demonstrated the importance of FIT in the regulation of two major players in iron uptake system, FRO2 and IRT1 at the transcriptional level and protein accumulation level respectively. In oil palm, the abundance of FIT transcripts was tremendously down-regulated at 28d which is consistent with the same down-regulated expression profile reported for Pi deficient Arabidopsis roots [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. This could likely be one of the rebalancing responses in plants to impede iron uptake in order to avoid the frequently observed iron overload in plants under low Pi stress [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>].
</p>
