<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Conservation of the 
 <italic>Anatrachyntis</italic> pollinators may pose the greatest dilemma for decision-makers. A biological control program for 
 <italic>A. yasumatsui</italic> may use aggressive exploratory and permitting methods because there are no native armored scale species in the Mariana Islands that may suffer collateral damage. In contrast, a biological control program for the non-native 
 <italic>Erechthias</italic> leaf miner carries great risk to the native 
 <italic>Anatrachyntis</italic> pollinator population, as these two genera are closely related. Parasitoids may use cues from leaf-mining activity that are more challenging to find from mining activity [
 <xref rid="B73-insects-11-00888" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], so a particular biological control organism that focuses on the leaf-mining stage may be available. Pursuing this would require the input of an expert in this form of biological control. The pollinator relies on frequent 
 <italic>C. micronesica</italic> microstrobili production within an area of occupancy to provide brood sites to enable regeneration [
 <xref rid="B74-insects-11-00888" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Less frequent production of smaller microstrobili has been occurring in recent years due to the severely damaged tree population. These plant behaviors carry the potential to reduce localized 
 <italic>Anatrachyntis</italic> populations, which can reduce future pollination services. If the pollinator population crashes in some or all of the Guam and Rota areas of occupancy, 
 <italic>C. micronesica</italic> populations’ potential to passively recover would be minimal. Some of the justification for the in situ conservation management plan in northern Guam [
 <xref rid="B60-insects-11-00888" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] was to ensure the pollinator population had access to healthy 
 <italic>C. micronesica</italic> trees within the management plots to sustain regeneration and ensure the pollinator remained viable for future 
 <italic>C. micronesica</italic> species recovery.
</p>
