<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cactus family consists of about 1,500 species belonging to the genus 
 <italic>Opuntia</italic>, distributed in Africa, the Mediterranean countries, Northern Mexico, the Southwestern United States, and other regions [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. 
 <italic>O. dillenii</italic> is a species of cactus, and it is found in the northeast and west Morocco. Its fruit is consumed exclusively in the form of fresh fruit. The fruit of 
 <italic>O. dillenii</italic> is used by the population in traditional medicine to treat diabetes, inflammation, analgesic, and gastric ulcers [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Much information about the cladode, juice, and pear of 
 <italic>O. dillenii</italic> is available but little about the nutritional value and biological activities of its seed oil. Ghazi et al. investigated the 
 <italic>O. dillenii</italic> seed oil composition and its chemical characteristics. They showed that this product belongs to the kind of oils that have increased degrees of unsaturated fatty acids, in which linoleic acid is the highest fatty acid, and 
 <italic>ß</italic>-sitosterol is the majority sterol. At the same time, 
 <italic>γ</italic>-tocopherol is the only vitamin 
 <italic>E</italic> present in this oil [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Besides, it is characterized by the presence of other components such as phenols [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. All of which may contribute to human health [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These antioxidant components have pharmacological properties that can prevent and reduce oxidative stress-related diseases [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. As a result, interest has recently increased in the use of new natural antioxidants, mainly of plant origin. Several studies that have been performed on the fruit seeds oil of this plant have shown that this oil has significant antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], the hepatoprotective effect [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and the curative antidiabetic effect [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Currently, no study has been carried out on the preventive effect of this oil against the onset of diabetes or its antihyperlipidemic effect in high-fat diet-fed mice. For that, the objective of this study is to evaluate the antidiabetogenic effect of ODSO from Morocco against alloxan-induced diabetic mice and searching for the mechanism of this effect by or through the analysis of their total phenolic content and antioxidant activity. Also, the antihyperlipidemic effect in high-fat diet-fed mice was evaluated.
</p>
