<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par71" class="p">The phylum 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacteres</italic> is present -albeit at low levels of relative abundance- in both the Oslo fjord cod [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>] and our control and low-level individuals. Nonetheless, here we find that it is the sole order that significantly increased in relative abundance with increasing oil exposure levels. 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacterales</italic> has a wide environmental distribution and members have been found in hydrothermal vent communities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>], the gut microbiota of the hydrothermal shrimp 
 <italic class="italic">Rimicaris exoculate</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>] and in rodents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>]. Yet interestingly this order has also been found in high abundance in subsea petroleum reservoirs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>]. Moreover, it also occurs in relatively high abundance (19.2%) in biodegraded crude oil samples while it is absent in non-biodegraded samples from the same site [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>]. This implies that 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacteres</italic> species thrive under oil exposed conditions. A recent metagenomic study of succession in a petroleum reservoir detected gene clusters encoding the pathway for anaerobic degradation of monoaromatic compounds in bins assigned to the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Flexistipes</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacterales</italic>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>]. This could suggest that other genera in the 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacterales</italic> might be capable of breaking down aromatic hydrocarbons as well. However, since none of the described species within the 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacteres</italic> are implicated in the active breakdown of complex recalcitrant hydrocarbons [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>], it is of interest to see the results of such experiments. Until then, we have to be cautious to interpret that our findings are due to catabolism of aromatic compounds by 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacterales</italic> species found in the Atlantic cod gut microbiome. Nonetheless, the 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacterales</italic> metabolize small molecules that are also abundant in the gut, such as monosaccharides, amino acids, short chain fatty acids in the presence of a suitable electron donor such as iron and nitrate. Therefore, when PAH exposure triggers higher iron concentrations in the cod gut, these bacteria could metabolize more of the small molecules and outcompete others. Our results provide another line of evidence suggesting that specific members of this order thrive in an environment exposed to oil, regardless of the presence of extant, complex microbial communities.
</p>
