<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the modern era, the emergence and control of novel microbes poses a significant challenge to the scientific community. Various fatal diseases caused by opportunistic pathogens of different fungal strains have been reported all over the world [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Literature related to various mycological studies indicates that there has been a significant increase in the cases of candidemia in the past decade [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Additionally, fungal infections have affected over one billion people globally, causing more than 1.5 million deaths every year, comparable to tuberculosis deaths and more than 3 times the deaths from malaria [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Apart from causing mild fungal infections in healthy volunteers, a single fungal spore can start a deadly process in immune-compromised patients. Furthermore, patients suffering from chronic diseases such as diabetes, cystic fibrosis, AIDS and recurrent infection as well as patients on chemotherapy or receiving bone marrow or any other organ transplantation are at higher risk [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, 
 <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic>, and 
 <italic>Scedosporium</italic> spp. are some of the important infection-causing fungal strains in both crops and animals. Among the two factors responsible for the increases in the number of fungal infections, one is the incessant use of broad-spectrum antibiotics, which reduces the population of non-pathogenic bacteria that usually compete with the fungi. Another worrying factor has been a rise in number of persons with lessened immune response caused by the use of chemotherapeutic drugs, immunosuppressant treatments, or by acquired immunodeficiency syndrome [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In the past, the various synthetic analogues of imidazoles and azole nucleus were developed to treat fungal infections. However, with passage of time, their effectiveness has diminished; additionally, there is the chance that the infection will relapse after their use [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Moreover, the currently established antifungal candidates suffer from a number of limitations that render their use problematic, such as amphotericin B-linked dose-limiting nephrotoxicity, quick resistance development associated with flucytosine, interactions among drugs, and resistance development against azoles. Keeping in view the above facts, we can say that there is an urgent need to search for new and effective antifungals [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
