<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The binding at the active site plays a vital role in increasing the binding affinities between ligand-receptor. Phlorizin was found to form nine hydrogen bonds with DPP (IV) among the seven compounds, and its binding energy was the highest among the seven compounds. We observe that the binding of phlorizin forming two H- bonds with active site residues of DPP (IV), Arg125 contribute to the lowest binding energy formed due to the molecular shape and size of a compound that makes it easier to penetrate the binding pockets. Meanwhile, compounds such as monobenzone, mundulone, berberine and dimethylcaffeic acid were also observed with a quite high binding energy is probably due to the formation of H-bonds at the active site, residue like Ser630. We also notified that the majority of the compounds such as berberine, dimethylcaffeic acid, phlorizin, monobenzone, sandenin found to be exclusively involved in the π-staking interaction with one of DPP (IV) active site, Tyr547 as similar with sitagliptin. These factors claimed as one of reason on these compounds have the ability to mimic the binding interaction and found to follow the same interaction pattern as compared with sitagliptin. Theoretically, π-staking was analysed as the three top most binding interaction in protein-ligand binding including H-bonds, hydrophobic bonds and others that also enhance binding affinity
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref>. It is believed that π-staking is considered as one of the natural keys in non-covalent interaction and the presence of these bonds is significant in many biological systems as solitary effects but also their interplay omnipresent
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref>. Moreover, the docking with the insulin receptor (1IR3) was also included in these studies. Residues of amino acids, namely Ser1006, Lys1030, Asp1083, Met1079, Ala1080, and Glu1077, were the major residues of amino acids involved in internal ligand interaction and most of the active components in 1IR3. According to the molecular docking results, pomiferin and scandenin were the only compounds that were notified to interact with one of the active sites of 1IR3, which are Asp1083 and Ala1080 respectively through hydrogen bonding interaction. By interacting with the active site of IR, these compounds have the potential to act as IR activators therefore, adjust blood glucose to promote the utilisation of glucose. Besides, results also showed that for ligands with high-affinity scores were also influenced by the increase in the number of H-bond formed. The presence of H-bonds is definitely attributed to form a major interaction and regarded to be the main driving force of conformational change of the receptor upon ligand binding. To the best of our knowledge, our present studies were found to be as the first studies that revealed the molecular docking with the compounds that present in 
 <italic>C. latifolia</italic> extracts and this works is based on continuation from our previous studies that involving with antioxidant activity and screening of compounds by LC-MS analysis
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>. Thus, these studies have been pointed out the potential of phlorizin by inhibiting the activity of α-glucosidase and DPP (IV) enzyme as the new alternative for antidiabetic drugs that potentially being used in the treatment for type 2 diabetes.
</p>
