<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The formation of heartwood is often accompanied by physiological processes such as xylem dehydration (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Nakada, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Kuroda et al., 2009</xref>), programmed cell death (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Spicer, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Nakaba et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Nakaba et al., 2012</xref>), depletion of storage compounds (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Magel et al., 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Piispanen and Saranpää, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Nakaba et al., 2013</xref>), deposition of heartwood substances (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Magel et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Nakada and Fukatsu, 2012</xref>), and changes in cell wall structure (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Nakada and Fukatsu, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2014</xref>). The deposition of heartwood substances is the most important manifestation of heartwood formation due to its importance in natural durability; it is also important as heartwood extractives may be important pharmaceuticals. Heartwood substances are the products of secondary metabolism of trees, whose metabolized substrates are mainly non-structural carbohydrates (NSCs). NSCs in trees are the main photosynthetic storage compounds and transported inwards through ray parenchyma cells in the formation of secondary components in heartwood (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Hillis, 1987</xref>). NSCs mainly include starch and soluble sugars (
 <italic>e.g.</italic> sucrose, fructose, glucose, arabinose, galactose, stachyose). The arabinose and galactose contents were reported to be related to the synthesis and hydrolysis of hemicellulose in the cell wall during the formation of heartwood (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Saranpää and Höll, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Fischer and Höll, 1992</xref>). In addition, the content of lipid in xylem has also proved to be involved in heartwood formation (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Bergström, 2003</xref>).
</p>
