<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the tropical countries insects are the major destroyers of stored food commodities especially of cereals and pulses. The important storage insect pests such as pulse beetles (
 <italic class="italic">Callosobruchus</italic> species), maize weevil (
 <italic class="italic">Sitophilus zeamais</italic>), rice weevil (
 <italic class="italic">S. oryzae</italic>), and red flour beetle (
 <italic class="italic">Tribolium</italic> species) are reported to cause about 60% loss in cereals and pulses (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh et al., 2012</xref>). These problems arise due to agroclimatic conditions as well as improper storage facilities. In recent years, there are several chemical and non-chemical methods were used for the control of these insect pests. Use of commercial fumigants against these stored insect pests is either effective, but due to climate change insects have started develop resistant against these fumigants (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chaudhry, 1997</xref>) or also these insecticides have several side effect on human beings. Use of essential oils is one of the non-chemical options for the management of these insect pests which have been proved as effective method for the management of stored product insects and also have fewer chances of resistance problems against these insect pests. Earlier, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kumar et al. (2010)</xref> reviewed the insecticidal properties of extract and essential oils from different 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> species against storage as well as field insects’ pests. In continuation of these reports, here we are updating the report on 2000 onwards, dealing only on the efficacy of essential oils against stored insect pests. Attempts have been made to determine the insecticidal efficacy of essential oils and their constituents from different 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> species against stored product insects. 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha haplocalyx</italic> (31.5 μg/cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) essential oil at 72 h of exposure showed 83% repellent activity against 
 <italic class="italic">T. castaneum</italic> when assessed by area preference method (
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wagan et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">M. haplocalyx</italic> essential oil and its main constituent’s menthol, menthyl acetate, limonene, and menthone had LD
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values of 16.5, 7.91, 5.96, and 13.7 g/adult, respectively, against 
 <italic class="italic">Lasioderma serricorne</italic> adults in contact toxicity bioassay and among all menthol showed higher repellent activity (
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al., 2015</xref>). In fumigant toxicity test, 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> showed 27.52 μl/l of air LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values against 
 <italic class="italic">Rhyzopertha dominica</italic> adults affecting stored maize (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nubia et al., 2016</xref>). However, in their study this oil was reported as poor fumigant than that of 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum basilicum</italic> oil. However, 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> essential oil exhibited 100% mortality to 
 <italic class="italic">C. chinensis</italic> during a fumigation test with an LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 0.003 μl/ml air after 24 h of treatment and 100% repellency at 0.025 μl/ml air concentration. Oil showed 98.46% oviposition deterrence, 100% ovicidal activity, 88.84% larvicidal activity, 72.91% pupaecidal activity, and 100% antifeedant activity against 
 <italic class="italic">C. chinensis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kedia et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> oil showed a more than 80% mortality of 
 <italic class="italic">Ephestia kuehniella</italic> (Zeller) and 
 <italic class="italic">Plodia interpunctella</italic> (Hubner) at 2.5 ml/l dose and 2 h of exposure times (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Eliopoulos et al., 2015</xref>). They found that oil caused 50–60% of egg mortality, and 18 and 28% of larval and pupal mortality, respectively, at same dose and 24 h of exposure. In 
 <italic class="italic">T. castaneum, M. arvensis</italic> oil was found to reduce 67.50 and 61.25% acetylcholinesterase activity over control (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mishra et al., 2014</xref>) after 24 h of fumigation. 
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saroukolai et al. (2014)</xref> reported that 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> essential oil showed 259.73 and 75.31 ppm LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value against fourth star larvae of potato beetle 
 <italic class="italic">Leptinotarsa decemlineata</italic> (Say) by fumigant bioassay and oil also exhibited 39.26% feeding deterrent index against the adults at 16 ppm. 
 <italic class="italic">M. pulegium</italic> essential oil and its major component, pulegone, showed potent insecticidal activity against mushroom scatopsid flies, 
 <italic class="italic">Scatopse</italic> spp. (after 0.5 h, LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 0.17 and 0.13 μl/L air, respectively) in fumigant bioassay and 100% mortality of adults were observed at 4 h of exposure period (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gurkan and Fedai, 2013</xref>). In another study, adults of 
 <italic class="italic">T. castaneum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. maculatus</italic> were killed by 
 <italic class="italic">M. longifolia</italic> essential oils at 13.05 μl/l air LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value by fumigant bioassay (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abbas and Javad, 2012</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Halit et al. (2012)</xref> studied the fumigant effect of three essential oils of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> such as 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata, M. villoso-nervata</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> against 
 <italic class="italic">S. granarius</italic>. Among these 
 <italic class="italic">M. villoso-nervata</italic> exhibited 90% mortality of adults by fumigant bioassay, while its main constituent carvone exhibited 100% mortality at 24 h of exposure with 0.024 μl/ml LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value. Thus, 
 <italic class="italic">M. villoso-nervata</italic> and carvone can be commercialized as potent insecticidal agent against 
 <italic class="italic">S. granarius</italic>. Leaf essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> species possessed 55% mortality after 48 h of exposure with LD
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values 0.044 μl/ml by topical application and 3.51 μl/cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> by fumigant application against the 
 <italic class="italic">T. castaneum</italic> adults (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Franz et al., 2011</xref>). Author reported that this oil is poor insecticidal agent than that of 
 <italic class="italic">Cymbopogon citratus</italic>. It was found that 1.75 μl of essential oil per 0.5 ml acetone dose of 
 <italic class="italic">M. viridis</italic> strongly repelled (63 81%) 
 <italic class="italic">S. granarius</italic> adults, thus this oil can be used in organic food production as a repellent and insecticidal agent (
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Somaye, 2010</xref>). Also 100% mortality of 
 <italic class="italic">S. granarius</italic> was achieved by 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> subsp. 
 <italic class="italic">tomentosa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">M. spicata</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">formasa</italic> essential oils at 1 μl/l air and the exposure periods of 36 and 48 h and potent mortality of adults at 0.5 μl/l air and an exposure period of 48 h (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Irfan et al., 2009</xref>). In the study of 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mohamed and Abdelgaleil (2008)</xref>
 <italic class="italic">M. microphylla</italic> exhibited potent fumigant activity against 
 <italic class="italic">T. castaneum</italic> (LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 4.51 μl/l) and 
 <italic class="italic">S. oryzae</italic> (LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 0.21 μl/l). Thus, this oil can be used as protectant against this insect. 
 <italic class="italic">M. longifolia</italic> essential oil exhibited 100% mortality of 
 <italic class="italic">S. zeamais</italic> deteriorating maize at 0.50 μl/g dose in contact toxicity bioassay with 100% repellency at the same dose (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Odeyemi et al., 2008</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">M. viridis</italic> essential oil showed more that 50% mortality of 
 <italic class="italic">C. maculatus</italic> at 235 ppm dose of essential oil and also reduced 67.4% egg hatching and 72% of progeny emergence at 300 ppm dose (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Derbalah and Ahmed, 2011</xref>). Inhibition of oviposition in insects by essential oils is also an important criterion to manage the stored product insects. There are several essential oil including 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> are reported as effective ovipositional inhibitor against eggs of stored product insects. 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kumar et al. (2009)</xref> reported that essential oil from 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> species is very effective and completely inhibited oviposition of 
 <italic class="italic">C. chinensis</italic> at 200 μl/l and protected seed (94.05%) from biodeterioration of 
 <italic class="italic">C. chinensis</italic>. Against adults of 
 <italic class="italic">C. maculatus, Mentha</italic> oil showed 4.43 μl/l air LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values and at 1.01 μl/l air dose possessed anti acetylcholinesterase activity (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Al-Sarar et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
