<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We have described here that insecticides based on essential oil are the good options for the management of insect pests hazardous and resistance problems of the commercial insecticides. To combat with increasing resistance rate in commercial insecticides, identification of novel effective insecticidal compounds is essential. Researchers reported that essential oil based botanical insecticides have wide range of target action on insect pests. When insects are exposed to the essential oils, breakdown of the nervous system of insects occurs (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kostyukovsky et al., 2002</xref>). The main target sites of essential is octopaminergic system (
 <bold class="bold">Figure 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </bold>) which plays a key role as a neurotransmitter, neurohormone, and neuromodulator in invertebrate systems, with a physiological role analogous to norepinephrine in vertebrates (
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shaaya and Kostyukovsky, 2006</xref>). During the insecticidal activity of the essential oils, the mechanism behind the insect mortality is that the volatiles penetrates in the insect body via respiratory system and results in abnormal breathing which leads to asphyxiation and final death of insects (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pare and Tumlinson, 1999</xref>). Some investigators also reported that acetylcholinesterase enzyme activity in insect is also inhibited by the essential oil and constituents (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Picollo et al., 2008</xref>) which lead to the blockage of nerve impulse, later paralysis and then death of the insects occurs. 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Miyazawa et al. (1998)</xref> reported that three 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> oils viz., 
 <italic class="italic">M. aquatica, M. gentilis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">M. arvensis</italic> essential oils significantly inhibited acetylcholinesterase (AChE) activity and their IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values were in the range of 28-32 μg/ml. 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> essential oils also showed oviposional activity against the stored insects. This may be due to either death of the insects before their egg laying, failure of live females to lay eggs when they come in contact with essential oils (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pandey et al., 2011</xref>). Since 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> essential oils are made up of terpenic and phenolic chemical constituents, which affect the octopamine receptor and inhibit the acetyl cholinesterase of the larvae and pupae, thereby killing them and protect the food commodities (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Khanikor et al., 2013</xref>). Additionally, multiplication of larvae and pupae do not occur inside the grains due to low penetration of essential oil vapors inside the grains, which further protect the grains from infestation of larvae and pupae (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rahman and Schmidt, 1999</xref>). Changes in physiology and behavior of insects are also affected by the essential oils which further affect the nervous system. These essential oils also cause reduction in egg laying capacity when it comes in contact with adults as described in the above section. Due to these properties essential oils are also addressed as semiochemicals and have been implemented in IPM (integrated pest management) program in place of those which cause lethality to insects (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rajendran and Sriranjini, 2008</xref>). Investigators also reported that in few studies eggs were laid by insects but progeny emergence failed due to the potent components of the oils which penetrate into the eggs via chorion and inhibit the embryonic development (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abdullahi et al., 2011</xref>). Failure of egg hatching is also occur when essential oils interferes the physical process of eggs, causing alteration in oxygen and surface tension within the eggs (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abdullahi et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, at beginning of the lifecycle, the population of insects can be reduced by inhibiting their ovipositional behavior. In this paper we reviewed that 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> oil from different species also caused inhibition of egg laying and progeny emergence of several stored product insects. Therefore, these 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> oil based ovipositional inhibitors would be useful against insects developing resistance treated with those responsible for lethal toxicity. Such properties of 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> oil strengthen their recommendation in storage system due to infestation caused by insects. 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> oils also have ovicidal activity. The mechanism behind ovicidal property is that, through the posterior pole the vapors of essential oil circulate into the eggs and disrupt embryonic development of eggs causing death of the embryo (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Credland, 1992</xref>). Additionally, essential oils exhibited ovicidal action, may act as neurotoxins when development of nervous system starts (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Papachristos and Stamopolos, 2002</xref>). It is also reported in this paper that researchers were screened essential oils of 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> species at different life stage of the insects. Hence, during the insecticide formulation the 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> oil exhibited potent toxicity at all stages should be considered.
</p>
