<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Arguably, from a biogeochemical perspective, ENSDs are the most intriguing native sulfur deposits. Since the recognition that anaerobic bacteria may have generated the native sulfur deposits in Sicily by 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hunt (1915)</xref>, a problem vexes scientists to this day: presumably, sulfide is the only product of dissimilatory sulfate reduction and a subsequent oxidative step is required to generate native sulfur (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">2</xref>). The seemingly easy way out of this problem, the circumstance that sulfide is readily oxidized to zero-valent sulfur in the presence of molecular oxygen (O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>), comes with two caveats: (1) there is no geochemical proof for the involvement of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in the genesis of the ENSDs; and (2) for some, if not most, ENSDs it is difficult to conceive how O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> could be supplied in the required quantities without inhibiting dissimilatory sulfate reduction. For example, to generate the largest native sulfur caprock deposit with 89 million tons of native sulfur (Boling dome; 
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Long, 1992a</xref>), approximately 44 million tons or 1.4 ⋅ 10
 <sup class="sup">12</sup> moles of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> would be required, not including O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> lost to hydrocarbon oxidation. If such a supply is provided by oxygenated water to the subsurface and assuming a solubility of 250 μmol O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> per liter freshwater, this corresponds to approximately 5,100 km
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> of oxygenated water, or for ease of comparison, to 9 months of draining of the Amazon River. Despite these concerns (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lindgren, 1913</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feely and Kulp, 1957</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Parafiniuk, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kirkland, 2014</xref>), it has become widely accepted that oxidation of sulfide with O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is required for the formation of bioepigenetic native sulfur deposits (
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ruckmick et al., 1979</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kyle and Posey, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Machel, 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Klimchouk, 1997</xref>). This notion has been eloquently summarized by 
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Machel (1992)</xref>: “Economically viable deposits of native sulfur usually are formed by only one process: inorganic oxidation of H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>S by molecular oxygen.” The disparity between the paradigm that O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is required and the absence of direct evidence that O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is available in the needed quantities to drive the process resulted in a conundrum that has now persisted for over 100 years.
</p>
