<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par76">Highly active formulations include potato and tomato glycoalkaloids, black tea extracts, and several essential oils and plant and marine extracts. There is also progress in the therapy to expose the protozoa to photosensitized light. It would be of interest to compare the therapeutic efficacy of treatment by light with some of the anti-trichomonad formulations derived from natural sources. This is, however, still a challenging problem because only a few studies have reported on medicinal plants that have a similar efficacy against 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> in infected women to that observed with metronidazole. One of the plants, 
 <italic>Zataria multiflora,</italic> had a dual benefit: it inhibited both 
 <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> and inactivated pathogenic bacteria in the vagina that cause vaginosis, which often accompanies trichomoniasis. There is, therefore, an urgent need to evaluate some of the other anti-trichomonad formulations based on effective natural and safe compounds and extracts in human trials for their efficacy against both trichomoniasis and vaginosis, as well as their efficacy in infected cows, bulls, pigs, cats, and dogs. Some of these compounds could be used in conjunction with probiotics to restore or modify the natural microbiota of the urogenital environment. We hope and anticipate that this review will stimulate interest in such studies, in view of the fact that several of described anti-trichomonad compounds have been reported to have additional health-promoting properties, including anti-oxidative, anti-inflammatory, anti-acrylamide, anti-obesity, anti-carcinogenic, anti-microbial, anti-viral, anti-malarial, and anti-aging effects. As noted above, the use of the described extracts and isolated pure compounds in the prevention and treatment of trichomoniasis and other diseases should be guided by the ratio of preventive/therapeutic to toxic dose. A combination of low doses of metronidazole with the active extracts and isolated compounds might act synergistically with reduced side effects to benefit human health.
</p>
