<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bisnorterpenes, purified from the roots of 
 <italic>Salacia madagascariensis</italic> Lam. DC. of the family Celastraceae, a shrub found in East Africa whose roots are used in the treatment of malaria fever and menorrhagia specifically in Tanzania for its potent antiprotozoal activity (
 <xref rid="B190" ref-type="bibr">Murata et al., 2008</xref>). Recent 
 <italic>in silico</italic> studies supports the anti-SARS CoV-2 activity [
 <bold>Level IV</bold>] of bisnorterpenes such as 22-Hydroxyhopan-3-one and 6-Oxoisoiguesterin which have been isolated from endemic African plants with impressive binding affinities for the 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> of coronaviruses of −8.6 and 9.1 kcal mol
 <sup>−1</sup> respectively (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Gyebi et al., 2020</xref>). 
 <italic>Aframomum exscapum</italic> (Sims) Hepper (Zingiberaceae) synthesizes acyclic triterpenes compounds such as S-nerolidol 
 <bold>(157)</bold> isolated from the seeds and represents an important constituent of essential oils used in the treatment of malaria. This compound is also found in 
 <italic>Artemisia herba alba</italic> Asso and in 
 <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (DC.) Stapf. (Poaceae), and is able to arrest development of the intraerythrocytic stages of malaria (
 <xref rid="B261" ref-type="bibr">Titanji et al., 2008</xref>) and as such may be considered in future search for anti-viral agents including SARS-CoV-2. 
 <italic>Hyptis suaveolens</italic> (L.) Poit. from Nigeria has also yielded abietane-type diterpenoid endoperoxide, a molecule with high anti-plasmodial activity (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Chukwujekwu et al., 2005</xref>). Sesquiterpenes and sesquiterpene lactones 
 <bold>(51)</bold> derived from 
 <italic>Vernonia</italic> spp. are known to have interesting anti-plasmodial activities. Vernodalin 
 <bold>(132)</bold> is the most active compound in bitter leaf. The plant has many uses in Traditional African Medicine, the leaves of 
 <italic>V. amygdalina</italic> Del. are used in the treatment of various diseases including malaria and viral infections. Recent 
 <italic>in silico</italic> anti-SARS-CoV-2 investigation reported promising activity of terpenes, iridoids and lignans which are able to effectively interact with the host enzyme transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS2) [
 <bold>Level IV</bold>]. This enzyme facilitates viral particle entry into host cells, and its inhibition blocks virus fusion with angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). The structural complexity of these plant metabolites and the presence of hydroxyl moieties and aromatic rings significantly improves the inhibition of their molecular target (
 <xref rid="B224" ref-type="bibr">Rahman et al., 2020</xref>). Traditional African Medicine knowledge could be very useful in drug discovery efforts from African medicinal plants, but the quality and reproducibility of such investigation is key. Chinedu and colleagues in a review of plants used in malarial treatment, reported over one hundred indigenous plants which have been employed traditionally in the management of malaria infection in six African Countries namely Nigeria, Ghana, Ethopia, Benin, Cameroon and Togo (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Chinedu et al., 2014</xref>). Komlaga and colleagues have also evaluated some of the plants employed in the traditional management of malaria in Ghana, namely 
 <italic>Persea americana</italic> Mill (Lauraceae), 
 <italic>Theobroma cacao</italic> L. (Malvaceae) and 
 <italic>Tridax procumbens</italic> (L.) L. (Compositae) and found that they have good antiplasmodial activities to justify their employment in such treatment (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">Komlaga et al., 2015</xref>). African Medicinal plants used in treating malaria may therefore represent promising areas to investigate for their potential in treating viral infections including the novel coronavirus (COVID-19) and HIV. However, since their findings are only preliminary, there is still a long path to clinical application as these remedies must be well standardized, authorized for use and administered by qualified medical personnel to African populations.
</p>
