<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mineral and elemental composition of 
 <italic class="italic">D. dewevrei</italic> shown on Table 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref> reveal the presence of selenium, chromium, copper, manganese, iron, sodium, calcium, magnesium, potassium, and zinc in the leaves and fruits at appreciable levels. Copper, calcium, magnesium, and potassium which have been recommended as therapeutically useful are more inherent in leaves than in the fruits of 
 <italic class="italic">D. dewevrei</italic>. Copper plays a role in the oxidative defense system but chronic copper toxicity can cause severe poisoning (Uriu‐Adams &amp; Keen, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). In this study, the copper concentration in the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">D. dewevrei</italic> was more than in the fruits (Table 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). However, both concentrations of copper were less than the WHO recommended the level of copper in the acceptable range of 20µg/mg body weight per day (FDA, 1993; Watson, 1993). However, copper could be poisonous depending on the dose and duration of exposure (Obi, Akunyili, Ekpo, &amp; Orisakwe, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Copper has been reported to potentiate anti‐inflammatory activities (Rajeshwari &amp; Andallu, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Copper is an essential part of several enzymes and it is necessary to the synthesis of hemoglobin, and its deficiency can lead to anemia and hypoproteinemia (Ahmed, Rehman, Qadiruddin, &amp; Badar, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>; Idu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2015). Calcium, potassium, magnesium, and sodium being macronutrients are important for the proper functioning of vital organs in the body. They also play vital roles as structural and functional components of metalloproteins and enzymes in living cells (Ansari, Ahmad, &amp; Aafaqi, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Zaidi, Asrar, Mansoor, &amp; Farooqui, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Magnesium is a component of chlorophyll and an important mineral element with reference to the prevention of heart diseases and calcium metabolism in bones (Idu, Erhabor, Timothy, &amp; Ovuakporie‐Uvo, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Ishida et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). It orchestrates the electric current that sparks through the body nerves (Idu &amp; Igeleke, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Magnesium is an anti‐inflammatory and antidiabetic agent (Rajeshwari &amp; Andallu, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Magnesium is a central mineral for retention of vitamin D and calcium into the bones for maintaining bone structure and helps in prevention of osteoporosis and cardiovascular diseases (Chakraborti et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). According to Hooker (
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>), magnesium plays an important role in the metabolism of cholesterol and heart diseases. Sodium present in salt regulates the amount of fluid that the body contains, eliminates fluid waste through urine, and maintains fluid balance (Akpanyung, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Iron is an important constituent of hemoglobin. The leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">D. dewevrei</italic> have an appreciable amount of calcium which is good for growth and maintenance of bones, teeth, and muscles (Mohd, Idris, &amp; Abdulrasheed, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Zinc is involved in the normal function of immune system and is a component of over 50 enzymes in the body (Okaka, Akobundu, &amp; Okaka, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">D. dewevrei</italic> from literature can supplement the daily requirements of calcium, sodium, magnesium, and zinc.
</p>
