<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Vitamins A, B
 <sub class="sub">1</sub>, B
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, B
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, B
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>, B
 <sub class="sub">6</sub>, B
 <sub class="sub">9</sub>, B
 <sub class="sub">12</sub>, C, D, E, and K were found present in 
 <italic class="italic">D. dewevrei</italic> leaves and fruits (Table 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-tbl-0003" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>, Figures 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref> and 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-fig-0008" ref-type="fig" class="xref">8</xref>). However, vitamins B
 <sub class="sub">1</sub> (6.742 g/100 g),B
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> (5.360 g/100 g), C (53.430 g/100 g), and K (4.234 g/100 g) were the most prominently appreciable vitamins present in 
 <italic class="italic">D. dewerei</italic> leaves which were far more than the quantity of each of the vitamins in the fruits of the plant (Table 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-tbl-0003" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>). Vitamins B
 <sub class="sub">1</sub> and B
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> otherwise known as thiamine and niacin distinctively are water‐soluble vitamins which function as coenzymes needed for energy metabolism. They are also important for keeping the nervous system, digestive system, and skin healthy (Anonymous, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Vitamin C, also referred to as ascorbic acid, also functions as an antioxidant and a coenzyme needed for protein metabolism. Vitamin C is important for healthy functioning of the immune system and healing of cuts, wounds, and gums. It also aids in iron absorption, prevention of cell damage, reduces the risk of certain cancers, heart, and other diseases (Anonymous, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). High intake of vitamin C helps protect low‐density lipoproteins ex vivo against oxidation keeping the immune system in fine fettle. Vitamin C increases the amount of iron absorbed from some foods by the body (Hillstorm, Yacapin‐Ammons, &amp; Lynch, 
 <xref rid="fsn31019-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>).
</p>
