<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Treatment of flax fibers with different silanes was carried out to increase interfacial adhesion between the polymeric matrix and the hydrophilic fiber, thus leading to an improvement of mechanical performances of the resulting fiber/polymer composites. Initially, silanes are hydrolyzed resulting in silanols, which are adsorbed onto the fiber surface, acting as a chemical bridge in the interface after drying which allows chemical bonding of silanol groups with hydroxyl groups in cellulose [
 <xref rid="B39-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Silane treatments were carried out as follows: first a solution of 1 wt.% silane in acetone was prepared and stirred until homogenization. The use of different solvents was broadly studied [
 <xref rid="B38-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>], however acetone is widely used to promote hydrolysis [
 <xref rid="B31-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Pickering et al. reported that acetone improves the surface roughness of fibers, increasing their specific area [
 <xref rid="B48-polymers-11-00301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Previous to immersion of flax fabrics into the corresponding silane solution (with amino- or glycidylsilane), pH was adjusted to 3.5 with acetic acid and stirred for 10 min. Then, flax fabrics were immersed in this solution during 1 h and after this, soaked fabrics were dried in an air oven at 65 °C for 12 h. After this, silanized flax fabrics were washed several times with distilled water (until pH = 7 was obtained) and dried in an air oven at 40 °C during 24 h in order to remove residual acetone solution by evaporation.
</p>
