<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">A random pore network pattern was created in AutoCAD (Version 2017, Autodesk Inc.). The morphology of the pores can be depicted in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig" class="xref">11</xref>. The pattern was then transferred into a chrome mask for silicon mould microfabrication using standard lithography techniques, as previously described
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">71</xref>
 </sup>. The silicon mould was etched using deep reactive ion etching (DRIE) to define the channel features on the wafer to achieve an etch depth of 100 µm. The process of creating the silicon mould was outsourced to the South Australian node of the Australian National Fabrication Facility. This mould was then silanized, coated with de-gassed PDMS (Sylgard 184, Dow Corning Corporation) at ambient conditions and then cured for 4 hours at 65 °C in-house using a well-known process termed “soft lithography”
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>
 </sup>. The resulting PDMS slice containing the porous media was then peeled off the silicon mould and treated with oxygen plasma (Harrick Plasma Cleaner, NY, USA) for 4 minutes and 15 seconds, and 1 ml of the desired mineral solution was immediately placed on top of the PDMS slice. The PDMS slice was then air-dried and cleaned with ethanol and inspected using a stereo microscope (PSB X2-4, Saxon) to ensure no particles are present in the top of PDMS pillars. Lastly, a blank PDMS cover was bonded to the PDMS slice containing the porous medium with the deposited mineral via a second plasma treatment. The reason why the PDMS cover is left blank because the silanol groups on the PDMS are required for permanent bonding between the cover and the pillars of the PDMS with minerals. Examining the PDMS prior to the second plasma treatment was crucial for strong bonding of the porous media containing the minerals and the PDMS cover. If some particles were present on the top surface of the PDMS pillars, this would result in weak bonding. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> summarises the fabrication workflow. The total time needed to fabricate the geo-material PDMS microfluidic chip was 4.5 hours.
</p>
