<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Vitiligo is an acquired, progressive, multifactorial, and depigmentation disorder characterized by the appearance of circumscribed white macules in the skin caused by chronic, progressive loss of functional melanocytes in the epidermis [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. The etiology of vitiligo is poorly understood. Also, the numerous factors have been implicated in the development of vitiligo, including trauma, stress, exposure to sunlight for long time, skin infections, neural stress, cancer, melatonin receptors dysfunction, some drugs, and endocrine diseases and toxic compounds. These causal factors may act independently or in concert [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. The pigmentation of the skin provides many valuable function; perhaps foremost among these is the photo protection of underlying tissues from ultraviolet (UV) radiation. Melanocytes respond to a wide variety of intrinsic and extrinsic factors produced by the environment or by neighboring cells in the skin, including UV, stimulating hormone (MSH), agouti signal protein (ASP), endothelin 1 (ET1), dickkopf 1 (DKK1), a wide variety of growth factors, and cytokines [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Melanin biosynthesis is catalyzed by three melanocyte-specific enzymes: TYR, tyrosinase-related protein 1 (TRP-1), and TRP-2 [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. The tyrosinase playing an essential role in melanocyte melanin biosynthesis has been known for many decades. Therefore, tyrosinase is an important index for the treatment and diagnosis of vitiligo. In our result the AVO increased the melanin synthesis and slightly impacted tyrosinase activity but did not make a significant difference with untreated group, so, we considered that AVO can promote melanin biosynthesis may relate with other enzyme (TRP-1, TRP-2). It provided potential research value.
</p>
