<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As volatiles, AVO was characterized by a strong odor. It is synthesized by plants as secondary metabolites and has been widely used owing to its bactericidal, virucidal, fungicidal, antiparasitic, insecticidal, anticancer, antioxidant, antidiabetic and cardiovascular effects [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. The AVO was mainly composed of terpenoids occupying 73.53% of total chemical content, such as caryophyllene, sabinene, and limonene. Being natural compounds, the terpenoids were shown to have wide range of biological and pharmacological activities, including central effects, antimicrobial, and antitumor actions [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. In our results, high concentrations of AVO showed little cytotoxic properties in melanocytes. Therefore, we observed the protective effect of AVO on H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-induced B16 cells injury. Result showed that pretreatment of AVO reduced H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-induced cell injury in a dose-dependent manner (supplementary 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplementary-material-1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). From our result, we tentatively conclude that AVO could protect melanocytes from harmful factors in vitiligo like oxidative stress. This result is similar to the antitumor and antioxidant effect of terpenoids. So, we considered that the terpenoids were major biologically active compounds in AVO. Since AVO had possessed terpenoids such as caryophyllene, sabinen, 4-epi-
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-acoradiene, 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-thujene, and limonene, it is hypothesized that the unsaturated double bond in active ingredients of AVO may be responsible for its antioxidant properties (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>). Caryophyllene as a main content in AVO provided extensive pharmacological effects. Dahham et al. [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] reported that compounds have anticancer, antioxidant, and antimicrobial activities. They observed the antiproliferative effect of caryophyllene on the cancer cell lines. Among the tested cancer cells, the compound demonstrated selective antiproliferative effect against three cancer cell lines, namely, HCT 116, PANC-1, and HT29 cells, whereas it exhibited either moderate or poor cytotoxic effects against ME-180, PC3, K562, and MCF-7. Noteworthily, the compound displayed low toxicity against the normal cell lines such as 3T3-L1 and RGC-5. The study concluded that caryophyllene has strong selective cytotoxic properties against human colorectal cancer cells. Based on this report and our result of AVO cell viability assay, we considered that caryophyllene may be responsible for AVO's biological effect. In addition, we employed the TCMSP database to check the ADME properties and targets for the main compounds of AVO (http://lsp.nwu.edu.cn/molecule.php?qn=193). Data showed that caryophyllene and limonene related some autoimmune diseases, genetic diseases, and corresponding targets (supplementary 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplementary-material-1" class="xref">Table 1</xref>), such as cardiovascular disease, arthritis, cancer, autoimmune cardiomyopathy, and Parkinson's disease. From the database, we could not correlate the exact relation between AVO active components and vitiligo or melanin loss disease. But according to the database information, we inferred that caryophyllene and limonene has immunomodulatory, antioxidant, and anticancer effects. Hence, we hypothesized that AVO increased melanin biosynthesis may be related to immunomodulatory and antioxidant effect from caryophyllene and limonene.
</p>
