<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">As in other valleys in the Western Alps [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], the traditional economy of the communities in the Sangone Valley relied on a multifunctional agricultural model based on small family farms, which combined the cultivation of cereals (mainly barley, rye, and maize) with that of vegetables (such as cabbages, carrots, onions, potatoes, onions, turnips) and fruits (apples, pears). In addition, and more importantly, it also included cattle, sheep and goat pastoralism, which supported local dairy production, while hunting and gathering practices (which included the collection of chestnuts, mushrooms and herbs used for both food and medicine) were mainly carried out in forests and higher pastures. This model was still followed in the early decades of the twentieth century [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Despite the importance of agriculture, the manufacturing industry has played a key role in the valley since the late nineteenth century. The Sangone Valley is located on one of the main transit routes between Italy and France [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], and its municipalities are easily accessible from Turin, one of the most important industrial cities in Italy. This allowed rapid development of the manufacturing industry in the valley beginning in the nineteenth century [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] and fostered the emergence of a mixed household economy that linked wage-earning to multifunctional farming activities. Moreover, at the beginning of the twentieth century, the valley became one of the first destinations for Alpine tourism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], primary associated with trekking and cross-country skiing, which further complexified the local economy. As in the rest of the Alpine region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], the post-WWII period marked the decline of agriculture as an economic sector of the valley, with the reduction of cultivated land in the valley [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], as well as specialization of agricultural production (e.g. apples, pears). While in the 1960s and 1970s, the valley experienced fast industrial development, in the following decades, like the rest of the region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], the economy of the Sangone Valley opened to the service sector, accelerating the agricultural decline. In this transformation, tourism has played a vital role, expanding its reach and encompassing initiatives linked to the promotion of local cultural and gastronomic heritage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>].
</p>
