<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To respond to pathogen stimulation and invasion, plants have evolved an advanced and complex immune system that is sensitive to stimuli from the outside environment [
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Recognition of pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) by pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) leads to PAMP-triggered immunity (PTI) [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Furthermore, when PTI is no longer protective of plants, resistance (R) proteins recognize pathogen-derived effectors and initiate effector-triggered immunity (ETI) [
 <xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The two immune processes share common defense responses, including an outburst of reactive oxygen species (ROS), secretion of antimicrobial compounds, and reinforcement of plant cell walls [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In addition to the plant’s immune response, there is also evidence that pathogens interfere with plant immunity. Two bio-structures are formed where pathogens secrete effectors in response to plant immunity. Host-derived extrainvasive hyphal membranes (EIHM) are formed to enfold biotrophic IH [
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and host membrane-rich structures called biotrophic interfacial complexes (BIC) are formed focally at the periphery of invasive hyphae during biotrophic invasion [
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Additionally, apoplastic and cytoplasmic effectors, two distinct effector secretion systems, have been identified in 
 <italic>M. oryzae</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Apoplastic effectors are associated with host plants before cytoplasmic effectors and partly decide the outcome of the interaction between pathogens and plants [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The apoplastic effector Bas4 and Slp1 are dispersed in the extracellular compartment formed by EIHM and the IH membrane to indirectly act on host plant cells through signal transduction [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The apoplastic effectors are secreted via the conserved ER (endoplasmic reticulum)-to-Golgi secretion pathway. Conventional protein secretion is the transport route of secretory proteins from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) to the Golgi apparatus (GA) and subsequently through secretory vesicles or secretory particles into the plasma membrane (PM) [
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Conversely, the function of cytoplasmic effectors is to impair the normal physiological metabolism inside plant cells [
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Pwl2 is a classical cytoplasmic effector that preferentially accumulates in BIC after being secreted from IH and subsequently enters the plant host cell [
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The delivery of cytoplasmic effectors is mediated by the exocyst complex, which is essential for establishing epithelial polarity, morphogenesis, and homeostasis [
 <xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
