<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45">Indigo naturalis, as traditional Chinese medicine, has been widely used in autoimmune diseases and inflammatory diseases, such as psoriasis and allergic contact dermatitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. A study has shown that indigo naturalis can inhibit oxazolidone induced allergic dermatitis by reducing eosinophil recruitment and production of Th2 related cytokines. But at the same time, indigo naturalis can change the structure of intestinal flora and aggravate colitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Indirubin can decrease serum IgE and cytokines production, and normalize the expression of NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B, I
 <italic>κ</italic>B-
 <italic>α</italic> and MAP kinase expression in a dose dependence by regulating the co-expression of Th1 and Th2-mediated immune response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Indirubin can also improve the proliferation of keratinocytes, inhibit the activation of JAK3/STAT3 pathway, reduce the osmosis of CD3 + T cells, 
 <italic>γδ</italic>T cells and CD11b + neutrophils, and decrease the level of 
 <italic>γδ</italic>T cells in spleen and lymph nodes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. What’s more, indirubin can selectively increase the number of CD4 + CD25 + Treg cells, which is important in the induction and maintenance of peripheral self-tolerance, leading to the induction of immune tolerance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Man et al [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. detected the effect of indirubin on ATP-induced macrophage immune response: neutral red dye uptake was used to measure cell death, and the ROS level was tested by dihydroethidium fluorescence probe. The results showed that indirubin could reverse the ATP-induced decrease in phagocytosis and cell death, and inhibit ATP-induced ROS production, indicating that indirubin blocked ATP-induced macrophage immune response.
</p>
