<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies suggest the MCD and SPD cause growth retardation in rats (
 <xref rid="b8-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="b28-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>). Furthermore, that liver-specific 
 <italic class="italic">Phb1</italic> knockout mice have retarded growth (
 <xref rid="b24-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>). However, in the experimental period of the present study, weight loss was not observed, and any differences in final body weight between groups were not significant (
 <xref rid="t2-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). These results may be explained by the nutritional content of the diets. Complete methionine deficiency triggers loss of body weight; however, the methionine content of soy protein is less than 50% of casein protein used in the normal diet and CDD (
 <xref rid="t1-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Soy protein showed no significant effect on the body weight of mice when they were fed the SPD for 16 weeks, which indicates supplementation of methionine at approximately 50% of normal levels does not influence growth retardation. Furthermore, mouse body weight did not correlate with genotype; the liver-specific 
 <italic class="italic">Phb1</italic> knockout mice used in this experiment were heterozygotes, suggesting that presence of at least one 
 <italic class="italic">Phb1</italic> allele does not affect growth. However, a previous study showed liver weight loss in mice fed the SPD (
 <xref rid="b28-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>). Relative liver weight was significantly lowered in mice fed the CDD and SPD compared with the normal diet (
 <xref rid="t2-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). This increase in relative liver weight reflects the hepatomegaly caused by hepatitis, hepatotoxins, and liver tumors (
 <xref rid="b29-pnfs-24-032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>). However, the results of this study indicate that mice fed the CDD and SPD are not affected by severe liver disease.
</p>
