<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diarrhea is one of the most infectious diseases, caused due to drinking of unsafe water, a situation of poor sanitation and hygiene, uncooked meat, and food intolerances, which leads to 3.2% of mortalities globally [
 <xref rid="B79-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. The key organisms responsible for this disease include microbial communities like 
 <italic>Escherichia coli, Candida albicans, Vibrio cholerae, Shigella flexneri, Staphylococcus aureus,</italic> and 
 <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic>. Diarrhea accounts for about 1.6 million deaths as per reports of WHO generally observed in developing countries, causing 28% mortality in infants residing in Africa and Southeast Asia due to serious gastroenteritis [
 <xref rid="B81-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Therefore, researchers throughout the globe are paying attention to the search for new plant-based therapeutic agents that can overcome this global problem [
 <xref rid="B83-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Recently available medicines are having various side effects with some toxicity. The occurrence of diarrhea in developing nations is facing scarcity of traditional antidiarrheal medicines and healthcare facilities. Hence, conventional drugs from medicinal plants are the only solution control to diarrhea in such countries [
 <xref rid="B84-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. De et al. [
 <xref rid="B85-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] reported effects of aqueous young leaves extract of mango on Gram-negative microorganisms causing gastrointestinal disorders. The authors reported that phytochemicals present in the crude extract play a vital role as antidiarrheal agent. Aqueous extract of MLs was screened against various pathogens like 
 <italic>E. coli, S. typhi, Vibrio cholera,</italic> and 
 <italic>S. sonnei</italic> at a dose level of 300, 200, 100, and 50 mg/mL. It was observed that the antidiarrheal activity increased with an increase in dose level. Hence, it was concluded that the aqueous young leaves extract of mango plant can treat the situation of diarrhea.
</p>
