<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For a closer examination of changes in nutritional dynamics, we also specifically sampled a representative orb‐weaving spider common to eastern deciduous forests (Tetragnathidae: 
 <italic>Leucauge venusta</italic> Walckenaer 1841) prior to vacuum sampling for the remaining invertebrate community. We sampled 
 <italic>L. venusta</italic> as this species was commonly found throughout the study area and has a wide geographic distribution across much of eastern North America. This species spins a relatively horizontal orb web with attachment points in low‐growing vegetation in wooded areas. 
 <italic>L. venusta</italic> and other relatively small orb‐weaving spiders prey mostly on flies (Diptera), leafhoppers (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae), and other small, alate true bugs, and beetles (Coleoptera). We collected mature female spiders by hand from plots in early July 2017. Samples were immediately frozen and individually dried for 24 hr at 60°C. We then weighed the dry spider samples to obtain body mass. Spiders were then individually ground, homogenized, and encapsulated. We analyzed individual spiders for δ
 <sup>15</sup>N and δ
 <sup>13</sup>C using a continuous flow isotope ratio mass spectrometer (DELTA V Plus; Thermo Fisher Scientific) and elemental analyzer (NC 2,500, Carlo Erba; 95% CI ±0.5‰). Isotopic nitrogen ratios can provide information on a predator's diet, while isotopic carbon can reveal photosynthetic pathways in sampled organisms: 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic>, a C
 <sub>4</sub> species, maintains δ
 <sup>13</sup>C levels between −13‰ and −15‰, while C
 <sub>3</sub> plants generally have δ
 <sup>13</sup>C values near −27‰ (Bradford et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Hyodo, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Analyses were conducted at the Central Appalachians Stable Isotope Facility at the University of Maryland Center for Environmental Science's Appalachian Laboratory. Isotopic carbon results were expressed in parts per mille relative to Vienna PeeDee Belemnite, with isotopic nitrogen reported in parts per mille relative to atmospheric nitrogen.
</p>
