<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous work has quantified responses of root fungal communities to garlic mustard and provides context for interpreting our results. At our study site, root fungal communities within some species’ roots changed in response to our garlic mustard treatments (Burke 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), particularly in the presence of deer (Burke et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Ongoing work shows that species in the ambient garlic mustard treatments have reduced hyphal colonization in their roots, and higher evenness in the soil AM fungal community (Bialic‐Murphy, L. et al. 
 <italic>unpublished manuscript</italic>). In other locations, studies have documented no recovery of mycorrhizal fungi after three years (Anthony et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>) or only partial recovery after six years (Lankau et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Since we did not observe a response in the aboveground community until 4–6 yr of garlic mustard weeding, it is possible that the aboveground response is mirroring the recovery of the belowground mycorrhizal fungal community, or that the mycorrhizal fungal community has not yet responded to garlic mustard removal. In addition, it is possible that changes in the abiotic soil conditions that are associated with garlic mustard invasion attribute to the observed response of mycorrhizal plant species (Rodgers et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>, Anthony et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). However, no differences in abiotic soil conditions between ambient and weeded garlic mustard treatments after 14 yr were found by Bialic‐Murphy, L. et al. (
 <italic>unpublished manuscript</italic>). Thus, findings from our experiment provide a link between mechanistic evidence of mutualism disruption from careful fine‐scale experiments (e.g., Stinson et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>, Hale et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>, Brouwer et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy3201-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) to observed shifts in mycorrhizal plant communities.
</p>
