<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The eDNA extraction steps described below were performed on the 110 membranes and the negative control. To extract the eDNA, we used the Dougherty et al. (
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) protocol with some minor modifications. Each filter paper was allowed to thaw and then cut into quarters using new razor blades. Each quarter was placed into individual 2‐ml microcentrifuge tubes containing ~250 mg of 1‐mm‐diameter glass beads, and 500 μl of CTAB buffer prewarmed to 65°C in a heat block. The filter paper quarters were pulped using the TissueLyser II (Qiagen) at a frequency of 30 Hz for one minute and then incubated at 65°C for one hour in a heat block. Following incubation, each tube received 500 μl of 24:1 chloroform–isoamyl alcohol and was briefly vortexed. The aqueous phase containing the eDNA was separated from the chloroform phase by centrifuging the tubes at 13,000 
 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min to enable phase separation. After two passes with 24:1 chloroform–isoamyl alcohol, the aqueous phase (approximately 500 μl) was transferred to new 2.0‐ml Eppendorf tubes and mixed with 500 μl of isopropanol, and 200 μl of a 5 M NaCl solution. Tubes were briefly vortex and stored at −20°C overnight to facilitate precipitation of eDNA. Tubes were then centrifugated at 13,000 
 <italic>g</italic> for another 15 min to pellet the eDNA. The supernatant was removed by pipetting, and 200 μl of 70% ethanol was added to wash the pellet. After centrifugation at 13,000 
 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min, the ethanol was removed by pipetting and replaced anew. The contents were again briefly vortexed and centrifuged at 13,000 
 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min. The ethanol was removed for a final time, and the tubes were then placed in a fume hood to allow any remaining ethanol to evaporate at room temperature (~1 hr). Once the eDNA pellet was dry, it was then resuspended in 25 μl 1X TE buffer (prewarmed at 70°C) to favor DNA dilution. eDNA extracts from each quarter belonging to the same trap were pooled. A 5 μl subsample was used to visually assess the presence and quality of eDNA on a 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. The concentration of eDNA (ng/μl) was determined by fluorometry (Qubit). All eDNA extracts with concentrations over 5 ng/μl were diluted to 5 ng/μl with 10 mM Tris pH = 8.5 This was done to normalize the amount of starting material per sample and to reduce the effect of potential PCR inhibitors in the samples. Eight samples exhibited signals of inhibition by showing no amplification during the first PCR of library preparation (see below). These samples were treated to remove inhibitors using a 1x NGS magnetic beads (Macherey‐Nagel) ratio, following manufacturer's protocols. Following quality control steps, the remaining volume of solution containing eDNA extract was placed in 1.5‐ml LoBind Eppendorf tubes and stored at −20°C.
</p>
