<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is well known that NO and PGE2 are two key mediators of inflammatory responses.
 <xref rid="b38-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref> Excessive NO production, especially by macrophages, can lead to cytotoxicity, inflammation, and autoimmune disorders.
 <xref rid="b39-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="b40-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref> PGE2 is a metabolite of arachidonic acid that elicits a wide range of physiological and pathological processes, such as gastrointestinal protection, inflammation, and cancer.
 <xref rid="b41-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref> PGE2 mediates the onset of the symptoms of classic signs of inflammation, including redness, swelling, and pain.
 <xref rid="b42-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref> Hence, measuring the production of LPS-induced NO and PGE2 can evaluate the progression of inflammation, and inhibition of their production might have potential therapeutic value for controlling inflammatory reactions and diseases. In the present study, we examined the effects of DCEO on the production of NO and PGE2. We observed that DCEO remarkably suppressed LPS-induced release of NO and PGE2 in RAW264.7 cells, suggesting that DCEO has potential anti-inflammatory activity. Since iNOS and COX-2 catalyze the production of NO and PGE2, respectively, in activated macrophages,
 <xref rid="b43-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="b44-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref> we determined the expression of iNOS and COX-2 in LPS-stimulated RAW264.7 cells. It was found that upon stimulation, the mRNA and protein levels of iNOS and COX-2 were markedly increased and DCEO lowered mRNA and protein levels of iNOS and COX-2 in a concentration-dependent manner. These results suggest that DCEO suppresses NO and PGE2 production through inhibiting the expression of iNOS and COX-2, respectively. Further studies will be conducted to investigate the effect of DCEO on the activities of these two enzymes. In addition to PGE2 and COX-2, leukotriene and 5-lipoxygenase also play an important role in the arachidonic acid metabolic pathway and are linked to asthma pathogenesis.
 <xref rid="b45-dddt-12-2731" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref> In the future, we will investigate the impact of DCEO on leukotriene formation and 5-lipoxygenase activity.
</p>
