<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Extracellular plaque deposits of the Aβ-peptide and flame-shaped neurofibrillary tangles of the microtubule-binding protein tau are the two hallmark pathologies required for AD patients. Familial early-onset forms of AD are associated with mutations either in the precursor protein for Aβ (APP) or in presenilin-1 (PS1) or presenilin-2 (PS2). Peptide generation pathways synthesise γ-secretase with either PS1 or PS2 as the catalytic subunit. APP is sequentially cleaved, where β-secretase first cleaves APP to release a large, secreted derivative, sAPPβ, followed by γ-secretase that cleaves a fragment of 99 amino acids (CTFβ) to generate Aβ. The process of γ-secretase cleaving can be inaccurate, leading to C-terminal heterogeneity of the resulting peptide population that generates numerous Aβ species, with Aβ1–-40 of the highest abundance followed by Aβ42. The slightly longer forms of Aβ, particularly Aβ1–42, are the principal species deposited in the brain that are more hydrophobic and fibrillogenic [
 <xref rid="B193-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]. In view of their vital role in Aβ synthesis, both β- and γ-secretase are considered as key components in anti-AD pharmaceuticals developments [
 <xref rid="B193-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>,
 <xref rid="B194-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. Normal pathology tests refer to the density in the affected brain regions of neuritic amyloid plaques and neurofibrillary tangles of tau protein. AD diagnosis involves the presence of large neuritic plaque portions, consisting of highly insoluble Aβ in the brain parenchyma. There are also deposits of tau protein, although they occur among less common neurodegenerative disorders, especially in the absence of neuritic plaques. There are some distinctive morphological features of the neurofibrillary tangles in the various diseases, and may exhibit a distinct composition of tau isoforms that vary from AD [
 <xref rid="B195-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>].
</p>
