<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7373747</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.00344</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>Melaleuca armillaris</italic> Essential Oil in Combination With Rifaximin Against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> Isolated of Dairy Cows</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buldain</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/502943/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gortari Castillo</surname><given-names>Lihuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1012579/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buchamer</surname><given-names>Andrea Ver&#x000f3;nica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1012606/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aliverti</surname><given-names>Florencia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1012585/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bandoni</surname><given-names>Arnaldo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/552712/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/262471/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mestorino</surname><given-names>Nora</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/262099/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laboratorio de Estudios Farmacol&#x000f3;gicos y Toxicol&#x000f3;gicos (LEFyT), Facultad de Ciencias Veterinarias, Universidad Nacional de La Plata</institution>, <addr-line>La Plata</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas y T&#x000e9;cnicas (CONICET)</institution>, <addr-line>La Plata</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Facultad de Farmacia y Bioqu&#x000ed;mica, C&#x000e1;tedra de Farmacognosia, Universidad de Buenos Aires</institution>, <addr-line>Buenos Aires</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Instituto de Qu&#x000ed;mica y Metabolismo del F&#x000e1;rmaco (IQUIMEFA), CONICET-Universidad de Buenos Aires</institution>, <addr-line>Buenos Aires</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Alessandro Di Cerbo, University of Camerino, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Kok Van Kessel, University Medical Center Utrecht, Netherlands; Roberto Christ, Federal University of Santa Maria, Brazil</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Daniel Buldain <email>dbuldain@fcv.unlp.edu.ar</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>344</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Buldain, Gortari Castillo, Buchamer, Aliverti, Bandoni, Marchetti and Mestorino.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Buldain, Gortari Castillo, Buchamer, Aliverti, Bandoni, Marchetti and Mestorino</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is the major subclinical mastitis-causing pathogen in dairy cows. In some European and Latin American countries, rifaximin (RIF) is a commonly used therapy at drying off. Phytotherapeutics are alternatives for the treatment of infectious diseases. <italic>Melaleuca armillaris</italic> essential oil (EO) has been reported as a good antimicrobial against <italic>S. aureus</italic>. The aim of this work was to investigate, <italic>in vitro</italic>, the combined effect of EO and RIF to identify a synergic interaction against <italic>S. aureus</italic> in order to obtain enough information for subsequent pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic studies. The minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) for RIF, EO, and combinations of these against <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains were determined at pH 7.4, 6.5, and 5.0, representing intracellular conditions where <italic>S. aureus</italic> is usually located. The fractional inhibitory concentration index (FIC) and the index of antibacterial activity (<italic>E</italic>) were evaluated. The MIC of EO at pH 7.4 was 25&#x02013;12.5 &#x003bc;L/mL and decreased with the acidity of the medium. RIF presented a high antimicrobial activity (0.032 &#x003bc;g/mL) against <italic>S. aureus</italic> regardless of the pH conditions. Combining RIF with EO, we found a synergic effect. A mix of 0.004 &#x003bc;g/mL of RIF and 12.5 &#x003bc;L/mL of EO led to a virtual eradication effect against wild-type strains at pH 7.4. Media acidification improves the EO/RIF activity, so EO would be a good adjuvant for RIF to treat staphylococcal infections and decrease antimicrobial resistance.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></kwd><kwd>dairy cows</kwd><kwd><italic>Melaleuca armillaris</italic></kwd><kwd>essential oil</kwd><kwd>rifaximin</kwd><kwd>checkerboard</kwd><kwd>synergism</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="59"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="7421"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The growing threat of antimicrobial resistance to antibiotics has dramatically increased therapeutic failure and encourages exploring new therapeutic alternatives (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is one of the major contagious pathogens responsible for subclinical bovine mastitis. It is believed that the intracellular survival of this microorganism contributes to its recurrence (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). This microorganism is important for public health because of its virulence and the potential risk of genetic antimicrobial resistance determinants transference among animals, humans, and the environment (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Plant essential oils (EOs), complex mixtures of secondary metabolites, together with conventional antibacterials (ABs) may have synergistic effects (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The different compounds present at the same time in plant extracts make it more difficult for the bacteria to develop simultaneous resistance mechanisms against each of them (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p><italic>Melaleuca armillaris</italic> (Sol. ex Gaertn.) Sm. is one of the most widely cultivated <italic>Melaleuca</italic> plants. Gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry research of <italic>M. armillaris</italic> EO revealed the presence of 1,8-cineol as the main component (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Inhibitory activity, <italic>in vitro</italic>, was found against several bacterial species, including <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>Difficulties in finding new AB molecules led to exploiting different strategies in those already in existence (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Combined therapy, which associates conventional ABs with natural compounds such as EOs, represents a promising strategy to facing resistance to ABs (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Synergistic combinations have greater efficacy and lower toxicity than their isolated components. There are some studies accounting for the synergistic activity between EOs and ABs (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) which suggest that the oil has potential to be used as an adjuvant in antimicrobial therapy.</p><p>Rifaximin (RIF) is an AB belonging to the ansamycin group, developed from rifamycin (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). It acts as an inhibitor of the RNA synthesis processes (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>RIF has been traditionally applied in human medicine to treat travelers' diarrhea (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and hepatic encephalopathy (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Valentin et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) found rifampicin resistance in <italic>Staphylococci</italic>. Rifaximin and rifampicin are analogous. Consequently, RIF resistance in a microorganism can be compared to rifampicin resistance (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Rifampicin resistance is mainly produced by chromosomal alteration of DNA-dependent RNA polymerase, which is the AB target (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). There are reports evidencing a quick <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> resistance development to rifamycins when these are used as mono-drugs (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Therefore, it is usually combined with other compounds (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>Rifaximin usage in veterinary medicine is indicated for reproductive disorder treatments for cows and horses (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Moreover, this antimicrobial is used as a good alternative to metronidazole to treat chronic enteropathy in dogs (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) as well as for localized treatment in bovine mastitis (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). RIF usage in cows with mastitis has been approved by the European Agency for the Evaluation of Medicinal Products in Europe and is widely used in countries such as Italy, France, Poland, Austria, Estonia, and Israel. On the other hand, this antibiotic is also being widely used with the same purpose in South America, mainly in Argentina, Chile, and Uruguay. However, information about its pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetic behavior is non-existent. There are only a few publications on its efficacy in milk cattle (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>There are no reports about RIF combined with essential oils. We previously found a synergic activity between <italic>M. armillaris</italic> essential oil and cloxacillin (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>Thus, the aim of this study was to establish the <italic>in vitro</italic> antimicrobial activity of RIF combined with <italic>M. armillaris</italic> EO at different pH values (emulating intracellular conditions). This condition allows us to assess whether this EO is a good adjuvant for ansamycins in <italic>S. aureus</italic> treatment within the intracellular environment where it is usually located.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title><italic>M. armillaris</italic> Essential Oil Extraction and Characterization</title><p>Leaf and herbaceous branch collection was carried out in Coronel Brandsen, Buenos Aires, Argentina (latitude 35&#x000b0;06&#x02032;18.9&#x02033; S and longitude 58&#x000b0;10&#x02032;57.0&#x02033; W). In July 2015, we obtained 44.85 kg of plant material. A sample portion was reserved for the identification and further storage at the LPAG herbarium at the Faculty of Agrarian and Forestry Sciences, UNLP (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). EO was obtained by steam distillation of the whole collected fresh biomass, yielding 550 ml of oil. Subsequently, the EO was dried with sodium sulfate anhydrous at room temperature, filtered using a cotton funnel, and stored in a glass amber bottle until use at 4&#x000b0;C.</p><p>The EO composition was analyzed before starting the antimicrobial assays with gas chromatography&#x02013;flame ionization detection&#x02013;mass spectrometry (GC-FID-MS), as we previously described (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), in order to avoid any variation in the EO composition during the storage until use.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>S. aureus</italic> Strains and Susceptibility Against RIF</title><p>Three wild-type (<italic>n</italic> = 3) <italic>S. aureus</italic>, isolated according to the National Mastitis Council procedure (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), from subclinical mastitis Holstein cows were used. The protocol was carried out following the Guide for the Care and Use of Agricultural Animals in Agricultural Research and Teaching (Federation of Animal Science Societies, FASS) and was approved by the Institutional Committee (CICUAL) of the Faculty of Veterinary Sciences, National University of La Plata (47.3.15J). For quality control, <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 was used. <italic>S. aureus</italic> susceptibility was checked with the disk diffusion test using rifampicin disk (5 &#x003bc;g) as a marker for the RIF susceptibility of <italic>S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Minimum Inhibitory and Bactericidal Concentrations of RIF and EO</title><p>The minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of RIF and EO were determined by the broth microdilution method in 96-well polystyrene microplates. Mueller Hinton Broth (MHB) culture medium was used with the addition of 0.5% of Tween 80 to improve the EO dissolution. The MICs and minimum bactericidal concentrations (MBCs) were evaluated at three pH values (7.4, 6.5, and 5.0) in order to analyze what would happen at the intracellular level (inside cytosol or phagolysosome) where <italic>S. aureus</italic> is internalized. Hydrochloric acid 0.1 N for the broth pH adjustment was applied.</p><p>The antibiotic stock solution was prepared by using high-potency RIF (&#x0003e;99%, <italic>w</italic>/<italic>w</italic>; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, CA, USA). Methanol (Baker-Mallinckrodt, Phillipsburg, USA) was applied as the solvent and MHB as the diluent. The range of dilutions assessed was from 256 to 0.007 &#x003bc;g/mL using 2-fold serial dilution (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In the case of the EO, a range of 50&#x02013;0.1 &#x003bc;l/mL was tested. We applied the same procedure described by CLSI 2009 (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), with the addition of 0.5% Tween 80 for EO solubilization.</p><p>Each plate was inoculated with a final bacterial concentration of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> UFC/ml and incubated at 35&#x000b0;C for 18&#x02013;24 h. MIC was established as the lowest concentration inhibiting bacterial growth. Positive and negative controls with MHB containing 0.5% Tween 80 were performed. Every determination for each strain was evaluated at the three different pH conditions by triplicate.</p><p>Once MIC was established, 25 &#x003bc;L was taken from each well-showing no evident bacterial growth. Then, these were inoculated individually in nutritive agar plates for colony counting after incubation at 35&#x000b0;C for 18&#x02013;24 h. Thus, MBC was the first antimicrobial concentration in which the initial inoculum falls at 99.9%.</p></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial Activity of Combinations of RIF/EO</title><p>Once MIC determinations were established, a checkerboard technique (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) was carried out for the combinations of RIF and EO at pH of 7.4, 6.5, and 5.0. This led to establishing the presence or absence of a synergistic interaction between them against <italic>S. aureus</italic>. The microplate design comprised a 2-fold serial dilution column of RIF with a 2-fold serial dilution row of EO (both MIC controls). The additional wells contained RIF and EO in different proportions. The final volume was 200 &#x003bc;L, so it was added 100 &#x003bc;L of broth, 50 &#x003bc;L of the correspondent antibiotic concentration, and the same for the EO. The inocula were dispensed considering a final concentration of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/ml per well, as for the MIC determination explained above. Microplates were incubated at 35&#x000b0;C for 18&#x02013;24 h, and every determination was carried out in triplicate. The results were interpreted by considering the fractional inhibitory concentration indexes (FICs), where this index is defined as the sum of the quotients between the MIC of the single and the combined antimicrobials. In this way, synergism exists if FIC &#x02264; 0.5, partial or low synergism (PS) if 0.5 &#x0003c; FIC &#x0003c; 1, indifference or addition (I) if 1 &#x02264; FIC &#x0003c; 2, and antagonism (A) if FIC &#x02265; 2 (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Antibacterial Activity Index of Rifaximin Alone and Combined With EO</title><p>Once the MICs of EO, RIF, and their combinations were identified, the data were used to perform time-kill assays so as to evaluate the antibacterial activity index (<italic>E</italic>). Each <italic>S. aureus</italic> strain was exposed to different concentrations (0.5, 1, 2, 4, and 8 MICs) of RIF and EO/RIF combinations. In the last case, the mixture which had the lowest FIC value was established as the MIC and the proportions of both components were retained. For quality control, <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 was used.</p><p>Considering the positive (without antimicrobials) and negative (without antimicrobials and inocula) controls, seven tubes were prepared. Each one contained a final volume of 1 ml including MHB with 0.5% Tween 80 (pH 7.4, 6.5, and 5.0), antimicrobials, and a final inoculum of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> colony forming units (CFU)/ml, depending on the case. Incubations were carried out at 35&#x000b0;C. Time-kill curves by bacterial plate count at the initial time, 2, 4, 8, 12, and 24 h incubating at 35&#x000b0;C by 24 h were performed. This assay was carried out in triplicate for each strain.</p><p>Thereafter, the results were applied into a CFU/ml <italic>vs</italic>. time graph design to evaluate the antibacterial activity index (<italic>E</italic>). Once <italic>E</italic> is assessed, an index <italic>vs</italic>. antibiotic concentration (Log<sub>10</sub>) graph is generated to compare any effect with the presence of EO. The wild strains were grouped by obtaining an <italic>n</italic> = 3 (using the mean of triplicates for each strain). Graphics were plotted using the GraphPad Prism 6 program.</p><p>The <italic>E</italic> was quantified as the difference between the Log<sub>10</sub> values of the number of viable bacteria (in colony forming units per milliliter) at the initial time (nt-0) and at the end of the test (nt-24). This is represented in the following equation: <italic>E</italic> = nt-24 &#x02013; nt-0. Three theoretical breakpoints were applied to assess <italic>E</italic>: a) bacteriostatic effect, <italic>E</italic> = 0 (there are no changes in the value of nt-0); b) bactericidal effect, <italic>E</italic> = &#x02212;3 (there is a reduction of &#x02265;3 Log10 of nt-0; and c) effect of virtual eradication of bacteria, <italic>E</italic> = &#x02212;4 (there is a reduction of &#x02265;4 Log10 (99.99%) with respect to the Log of nt-0 (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>After EO extraction, we obtained 550 ml of this, which resulted in a yield of 1.22%, <italic>v</italic>/<italic>w</italic> (volume/100 g of fresh material). <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the compounds found by chromatographic analysis of the EO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> shows the gas chromatogram).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Relative percentage composition of <italic>Melaleuca armillaris</italic> essential oil (EO).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Compounds</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Area (%)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Compounds</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Area (%)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,8-Cineole</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Caryophyllene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limonene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Terpinene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Pinene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;-Ocimene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myrcene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Pinene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Phellandrene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Thujene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinolene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Cymene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;-Terpineol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinen-4-ol</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aromandendrene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Terpineol</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranyl isobutyrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sabinene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cis</italic>-Calamenene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Terpinene</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxi-Caryophyllene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Gas chromatographic profile of the <italic>Melaleuca armillaris</italic> essential oil used (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fvets-07-00344-g0001"/></fig><p>Three wild-type strains (<italic>n</italic> = 3) and a reference strain (ATCC 29213) of <italic>S. aureus</italic> were tested against RIF, EO, and their combinations at pH 7.4, 6.5, and 5.0. The MICs obtained and the FICs in each pH condition are listed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The MBC obtained for each strain and the pH condition tested for EO and RIF are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, including the relation MBC/MIC.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Fractional inhibitory concentration indexes obtained for the EO/RIF combination under different pH conditions <italic>vs</italic>. individual MICs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Strains</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>pH 7.4</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>pH 6.5</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>pH 5.0</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO/RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)/(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FIC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO/RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)/(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FIC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO/RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)/(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FIC</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC 29213</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5/0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25/0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1/0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA 13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25/0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1/0.008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6/0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA 96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25/0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1/0.008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6/0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA 139</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25/0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1/0.008</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6/0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>MIC, minimum inhibitory concentration; EO, essential oil; RIF, rifaximin; FIC, fractional inhibitory concentration</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Minimum bactericidal concentrations (MBC) of EO and RIF at pH 7.4, 6.5, and 5.0 and the relation MBC/MIC in the three conditions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Strains</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>pH 7.4</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>pH 6.5</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>pH 5.0</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC/MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC/MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC/MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC/MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;L/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC/MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>EO</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold><break/>
<bold>(&#x003bc;g/mL)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>MBC/MIC</bold><break/>
<bold>RIF</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCC 29213</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA 13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA 96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA 139</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>MIC, minimum inhibitory concentration; EO, essential oil; RIF, rifaximin; MBC, minimum bactericidal concentrations</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The MICs of EO and RIF, shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, were used to perform time-kill assays at pH 7.4, 6.5, and 5.0. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, it is possible to observe the effect of the different RIF concentrations against the <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains (reference and wild type, respectively). The acidity seems to influence the bactericidal activity. At pH 5.0, concentrations of 4 and 8 MIC of RIF had a stronger antimicrobial effect after 24 h with respect to the situation at pH 7.4. The addition of EO improves the antimicrobial activity of RIF, requiring less concentration of it for the same effect against the reference (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>) and wild-type strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Time-kill curve for rifaximin on <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 at pH 7.4 <bold>(A)</bold>, 6.5 <bold>(B)</bold>, and 5.0 <bold>(C)</bold> [minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) = 0.032 &#x003bc;g/mL].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fvets-07-00344-g0002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Time-kill curve for combinations of essential oil/rifaximin on <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 at pH 7.4 <bold>(A)</bold>, 6.5 <bold>(B)</bold>, and 5.0 <bold>(C)</bold> [minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) = 0.032 &#x003bc;g/mL].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fvets-07-00344-g0003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Time-kill curve for rifaximin on <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> wild types (<italic>n</italic> = 3, using the mean of triplicates for each strain) at pH 7.4 <bold>(A)</bold>, 6.5 <bold>(B)</bold>, and 5.0 <bold>(C)</bold> [minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) = 0.032 &#x003bc;g/mL].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fvets-07-00344-g0004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Time-kill curve for combinations of essential oil/rifaximin on <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> wild types (<italic>n</italic> = 3, using the mean of triplicates for each strain) at pH 7.4 <bold>(A)</bold>, 6.5 <bold>(B)</bold>, and 5.0 <bold>(C)</bold> [minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) = 0.032 &#x003bc;g/mL].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fvets-07-00344-g0005"/></fig><p>Data obtained from the time-kill assays were used to establish the antibacterial activity index (<italic>E</italic>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> show the E <italic>vs</italic>. Log<sub>10</sub> (RIF concentration) and highlight again the synergic antibacterial effect obtained by the addition of EO to the culture with RIF against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (reference and wild-type strains, respectively). In this way, it is possible to observe that the amount of RIF necessary to decrease the bacterial inoculum in 24 h is lower in the presence of EO.</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Graphic representation of the antibacterial effect (<italic>E</italic>: &#x00394;Log CFU/ml 24&#x02013;0 h) of rifaximin against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 at pH 7.4 <bold>(A)</bold>, 6.5 <bold>(B)</bold>, and 5.0 <bold>(C)</bold> in the presence and absence of EO.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fvets-07-00344-g0006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Graphic representation of the antibacterial effect (<italic>E</italic>: &#x00394;Log CFU/ml 24&#x02013;0 h) of rifaximin against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> wild type (<italic>n</italic> = 3, using the mean of triplicates for each strain) at pH 7.4 <bold>(A)</bold>, 6.5 <bold>(B)</bold>, and 5.0 <bold>(C)</bold> in the presence and absence of EO.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fvets-07-00344-g0007"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>EO Extraction and Characterization</title><p>Chromatographic analysis of the EO revealed the presence of 1,8-cineol as the main component (72.3%) and, in lesser magnitude, limonene (7.8%) and &#x003b1;-pinene (6.0%). These chemical compounds are commonly present in EOs with high antimicrobial activity, particularly 1,8-cineol. This compound is a cyclic monoterpene and is, in general, the main component in the essential oil of <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> species (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). In several studies, 1,8-cineol has also been reported as the main component of the EO of <italic>M. armillaris</italic>: 33.9% in Egypt, 85.8% in Tunisia, and 80.2% in Brazil (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). However, these results do not agree with other authors such as Amri et al. (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and Siddique et al. (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), who determined markedly low concentrations of 1,8-cineol: 3.6% and 0.29%, respectively. Two other major compounds present in the EO with high antimicrobial activity are limonene and &#x003b1;-pinene (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). These differences are common in aromatic plants and can be attributed both to genetic varieties and/or exogenous variables. For these reasons, it is essential that the chemical composition of the EO we used in this study is shown.</p><p>Standardization of the EO composition is very important for pharmaceutical use. Obtaining clones with their own specific characteristics would be a probable solution to this issue. This would facilitate the EO to be used for the establishment of commercial crops. In this way, the problem of heterogeneity would be obviated, resulting in the production of homogeneous EO quality required by market standards. Siani et al. (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) carried out a vegetative propagation of one chemotype of <italic>Lippia alba</italic> cultivated in six different locations in Brazil under several different environmental conditions. After EO extraction, only slight variations of the content and qualitative profiles of the compounds were observed.</p><p>On the other hand, it would be possible to obtain some of the compounds available in the market in case it is necessary to enrich the obtained EO. This will allow assessing the quality and efficacy. However, it is necessary to understand which variation on the composition has an effect on the biological activity to establish a range of variations without difference.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibitory and Bactericidal Activity of EO</title><p>The MIC of <italic>M. armillaris</italic> EO against <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 was 25 &#x003bc;L/mL at pH 7.4 and 6.5, while at pH 5.0 it decreased by half. This same pattern of antimicrobial activity was observed in all the wild-type strains tested (SA13, SA96, and SA139); the MIC was 12.5 &#x003bc;L/mL at pH 7.4 and 6.5, decreasing to 6.25 &#x003bc;L/mL when the pH of the medium was acidified. Something similar occurred when evaluating the MBC. This parameter decreased between two and four times at pH 5.0 with respect to pH 7.4 (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>In addition, the high content of 1,8-cineol may be one of the factors contributing to the antibacterial activity of the EO. This compound has been attributed with the permeabilization of the membranes of microorganisms (such as <italic>S. aureus</italic>) as an antimicrobial action due to its high hydrophobicity (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Ya&#x000f1;ez Rueda and Cuadro Mogoll&#x000f3;n (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) found an important antibacterial activity of the <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> essential oil against <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213. The MIC was 12.4 &#x003bc;g/mL. It is noteworthy that the composition of the <italic>E. globulus</italic> EO was similar to that of the <italic>M. armillaris</italic> evaluated in this study: with 1,8-cineol (82.3%), followed by limonene (3.7%), &#x003b1;-pinene (3.2%), terpinen-4-ol (1.4%), &#x003b1;-terpineol (1.2%), &#x003b2;-myrcene (1.12%), and &#x003b1;-terpinene (1.1%), among others. Thus, it is likely that a synergism between these components is particularly effective against <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains.</p><p>The mechanism of the antimicrobial action of the <italic>M. armillaris</italic> EO against <italic>S. aureus</italic> has not yet been investigated. Hayouni et al. (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) studied the antimicrobial activity of this plant's oil against different species of <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>. As 1,8-cineol was the main component found in a concentration of 68.9%, these authors suggested as a hypothesis that this compound could have destabilized the bacterial cytoplasmic membrane, as was demonstrated by Li et al. (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). However, the postulated mode of action of <italic>M. armillaris</italic> by Hayouni et al. (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) also involves a minority of the components found (&#x003b1;-pinene, terpinen-4-ol, sabinene, &#x003b2;-myrcene, and &#x003b1;-terpinene, among others). According to these authors, these molecules interact with the cell membrane, where they are dissolved in the phospholipid bilayer and aligned between the chains of fatty acids. The distortion of the physical structure would cause the expansion and destabilization of the membrane, increasing its fluidity, which would increase the passive permeability.</p><p>A compound is bacteriostatic if the MBC/MIC ratio is &#x0003e;4 (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). The capacity of an EO to act as a bactericidal or bacteriostatic will depend on the chemical composition of this extract. When analyzing the MIC and MBC of the EO of <italic>M. armillaris</italic> against strains SA13, SA96, and SA139, we found that these parameters were very close, with a ratio of MBC/MIC ranging between 2 and 4 (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Therefore, considering the above-mentioned definition, the EO would act as a bactericidal antimicrobial maintained with different pH values.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibitory and Bactericidal Activity of RIF</title><p>The rifaximin MIC values for quality control to establish the susceptibility of <italic>S. aureus</italic> are not included in the CLSI documents, so we compared our results with the information published for rifampicin in the CLSI document VET01-S2 (CLSI 2013), which establishes a range of 0.004&#x02013;0.016 &#x003bc;g/mL (it is the only ansamycin that appears in the document).</p><p>A MIC of 0.032 &#x003bc;g/mL was obtained for all the studied strains (reference and wild-type strains). This value is higher than the value established for rifampicin (0.004&#x02013;0.016 &#x003bc;g/mL) by CLSI 2013 (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Broth acidification did not produce a variation in the inhibitory activity of RIF; the MIC was the same at the three pH values evaluated.</p><p>In this study, we observed that RIF had high antimicrobial activity against the <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains ATCC 29213, SA13, SA96, and SA139. The obtained MIC values were similar for all strains analyzed (0.032 &#x003bc;g/mL). This indicates an important antibiotic potency against <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Moreover, Hoover et al. (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) found values ranging between &#x02264;0.015 and 0.03 &#x003bc;g/mL for strains of these types of species, coinciding with our results. In another study carried out by Pistiki et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), the reported MIC values of RIF were &#x02264;0.25 &#x003bc;g/mL. No changes were observed in the MIC values at different pH levels. However, MBC showed differences when the antimicrobial activity was analyzed at the most acidic pH level. The MBC was 0.512 &#x003bc;g/mL for all strains at pH 7.4 and 6.5, whereas at pH 5.0 it decreased to 0.064 &#x003bc;g/mL for strain ATCC 29213 and to 0.128 &#x003bc;g/mL for the three wild-type strains. The MBC/MIC for all the analyzed strains was 16 at pH 7.4 and 6.5, working as a bacteriostatic antimicrobial. But at pH 5.0, the ratio ranged between 2 and 4 (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), meaning that the antimicrobial activity is bactericidal at a lower pH level.</p><p>When we evaluated with the time-kill assay how the presence of RIF affects the growth of the reference strain of <italic>S. aureus</italic>, it was observed that it grew at a concentration of 0.5 MIC (0.016 &#x003bc;g/mL) at the three pH conditions, which was always lower than the control growth curve (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Concentrations of 2, 4, and 8 MIC showed curves with similar profiles, independently of the broth pH. The concentrations evaluated (0.016&#x02013;0.256 &#x003bc;g/mL) allowed us to obtain a decrease of at least 3 Log<sub>10</sub> of the initial inoculum at pH 7.4 and 6.5. In contrast, at pH 5.0, the bactericidal effect was achieved for 2, 4, and 8 MIC; this coincides with the results observed in the determination of MBC since the values obtained for this parameter were 0.512 &#x003bc;g/mL (pH 7.4 and 6.5) and 0.064 &#x003bc;g/mL (pH 5.0).</p><p>Something similar was observed for the wild-type strains SA13, SA96, and 139 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>) because bactericidal effects were not seen with the concentrations evaluated at pH 7.4 and 6.5. At pH 5.0, the initial inoculum decreased more than 3 Log<sub>10</sub> with concentrations of 4 and 8 MIC, corresponding to concentrations of 0.128 and 0.256 &#x003bc;g/mL, respectively. These values were also consistent with those obtained in the determination of MBC since, for these strains and at this pH, this value was 0.128 &#x003bc;g/mL.</p><p>It is possible to observe a reduction in the bacterial count of <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains against RIF as early as 2 h after starting the time-kill assay. For this antibiotic, it is not yet well-established whether it is an antimicrobial time- or a concentration-dependent one. However, some studies report that rifampin (belonging to the ansamycin family) acts as a concentration-dependent antimicrobial bactericide (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). On the other hand, this antibiotic should be combined with other antimicrobials, such as penicillins resistant to penicillinase, vancomycin, or trimethoprim, due to it quickly selecting resistant strains when used as a mono-drug. Resistance to rifampin takes place by chromosomal mutation and develops easily in most bacteria. Such mutants show stable changes in the RNA polymerase (the target site of the antimicrobial action), preventing fixation. These result from mutations in the <italic>rpoB</italic> gene, which codes for the sub-subunit of the bacterial RNA polymers, where these antibiotics bind (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial Activity of EO/RIF Combinations</title><p>In the literature, there are no reports on the combinations of ansamycins with essential oils against <italic>S. aureus</italic>. There are only a few reports of natural extracts with this type of drugs. For example, Liu et al. (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) found a strong synergistic activity between rifampicin and manuka honey against strains of <italic>S. aureus</italic>-producing biofilm.</p><p>Combining RIF with the EO of <italic>M. armillaris</italic>, a synergistic effect was found, and the antibiotic activity was enhanced, particularly at pH 6.5 and 5.0, in all the strains assayed. At pH 7.4, there were combinations obtained that presented partial synergism, with FIC = 0.56, very close to the FIC value considered for synergism (0.5). In this case, it was possible to decrease, for the four strains studied, 16 times the MIC of RIF with a decrease to half of the MIC of the EO with respect to each compound applied alone. At pH 6.5, the decrease in the inhibitory concentration of the antibiotic was lower (four times for the wild-type strains and eight times for the reference strain). However, the drop in the amount of EO necessary to enhance the antibiotic antimicrobial activity was more evident here since, for all the strains, the decrease was four times the MIC of the plant extract. Finally, at pH 5.0, the MIC of RIF decreased eight times for all strains. In the last case, the decrease in the inhibitory concentration of the EO is much more evident since it decreased by a factor of 4 again. Therefore, as a result of the significant reduction in the inhibitory concentrations at pH 5.0, both essential oil and antibiotic, the FIC values obtained were of 0.38, which show an important synergy between them.</p><p>Thus, RIF has a potentiated effect by the sum of two factors: combination with the essential oil and the acidification of the culture medium.</p><p>In the time-kill assay, we could observe a slow decrease in the bacterial count for RIF alone that occurs mainly between 12 and 24 h after starting the experiment. On the other hand, when it was combined with the EO of <italic>M. armillaris</italic>, a strong drop in the bacterial count was observed at 4 h, with a maximum decrease at 8 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Moreover, it is evident that the drop of the slopes of the curves is more important in the presence of the mixture compared with the EO alone since this produces the greatest decrease in the viable cell counts at 12 h. Xiao et al. (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>) combined <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> essential oil with rifampin, managing to eliminate <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> strains in a stationary phase in 24 h. This effect is different when both compounds act alone, thus could not kill all the inocula at the same time. Therefore, combining some essential oils with ansamycins seems to be useful in treating staphylococcal infections.</p><p>In another respect, by analyzing bacteria inoculum decrease with <italic>E</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>), it is possible to graphically observe how <italic>S. aureu</italic>s is inhibited in a higher magnitude with lower RIF concentrations when <italic>M. armillaris</italic> EO is present. This means that the EO allows a reduction of the amount of necessary antibiotic for microorganism inhibition. At pH 7.4 and 6.5, RIF was not able to produce any bactericidal effect on its own at the tested concentrations, unlike as occurred at pH 5.0, while when combined with the EO of <italic>M. armillaris</italic> allowed achieving, with lower concentrations, bactericidal effects even close to virtual eradication. For example, a mixture of 0.004 &#x003bc;g/mL RIF and 12.5 &#x003bc;L/mL EO allowed achieving a virtual eradication effect against the wild-type strains at pH 7.4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). Something similar happened with the reference strain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). The acidification of the media improves the activity of the essential oil/rifaximin combination. These outcomes are similar to those previously obtained by combining cloxacillin with EO (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In both cases, the acidic conditions increased the synergic effect and the bactericidal activity, which is interesting if we are dealing with intracellular infections.</p><p>There are a few studies <italic>in vivo</italic> with EO; however, Byung-Wook et al. (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) treated cow's clinical mastitis with essential oil of <italic>O. vulgare</italic>. A decrease in infection by <italic>S. aureus</italic> without causing swelling, redness, pain, and heat to the udder has been observed. There are some essential oil-based products for intramammary application in the market, such as Phyto-Mast. This is recommended for intramammary use in lactation and dry-off. Thymus EO is the antimicrobial active component (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>), and its residues (main component) were only detected 12-h post-treatment in milk using goats and cows as animal models. The activity did not present any irritating and inflammatory effects (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). These findings allow us to consider the feasibility of administering the essential oil of <italic>M. armillaris</italic> intramammary in the future.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We observed a reduction of the necessary antibiotic concentration needed to inhibit <italic>S. aureus</italic> by combining <italic>M. armillaris</italic> essential oil with rifaximin even at different pH conditions. The <italic>in vitro</italic> bactericidal activity of the mixture was very important since, with the RIF/EO mixture, an effect close to a virtual eradication was obtained.</p><p>As was previously mentioned, rifaximin is highly used in humans and animals and contributes to antimicrobial resistance. It is known that when rifamycins are used alone, they select quickly antimicrobial resistance <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic>, so it is required to use them in combination with other compounds to avoid that effect.</p><p>Consequently, we conclude that the essential oil of <italic>M. armillaris</italic> could be considered as an effective adjuvant for therapies with RIF. Nonetheless, it is essential to assess security by using cell and animal models.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p><italic>S. aureus</italic> isolations used in this work belong to the microorganism's collection of our laboratory obtained in previously projects. The protocol of bacterial isolation was carried out following the Guide for the Care and Use of Agricultural Animals in Agricultural Research and Teaching (Federation of Animal Science Societies &#x02013; FASS) and was approved by the CICUAL of the Faculty of Veterinary Sciences, National University of La Plata (47.3.15J).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>NM conceived and designed the experiments. DB: performed all the experimental assay, statistical analysis, and wrote the manuscript. LC, AVB, FA, and LM contributed to the experimental assays. AB performed the EO quality assay. All authors contributed to the redaction and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work is partially financed by the Laboratory of Pharmacological and Toxicological Studies (LEFyT) and the National Agency for Scientific and Technical Promotion (ANPCyT) (PICT 15-831). The authors thank the National Scientific and Technical Research Council (CONICET) for their collaboration in granting the 2016&#x02013;2021 PhD Scholarship.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group>
<source>Antimicrobial resistance.</source> (<year>2018</year>). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs194/en/">http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs194/en/</ext-link> (accessed March 19, 2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Penad&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Staphylococcus aureus in Animals</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <fpage>7</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.GPP3-0060-2019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yiap</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SHE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Essential oils, a new horizon in combating bacterial antibiotic resistance</article-title>. <source>Open Microbiol J.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874285801408010006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24627729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24627729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sthapylococcus aureus virulence factors identified by using a high throughput caenorhabditis elegans-killing model</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.73.2.872-877.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15664928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15664928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sifri</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Barech-Bernal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderwood</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>von Eiff</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Virulence of staphylococcus aureus small colony variants in the caenorhabditis elegans infection model</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>1091</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.74.2.1091-1096.2006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16428756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16428756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chabir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Romdhane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moukarzel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzoug</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brahim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical study and antimalarial, antioxidant, and anticancer activities of melaleuca armillaris (Sol ex gateau) sm essential oil</article-title>. <source>J Med Food.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jmf.2010.0168</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21476932?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21476932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buldain</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchamer</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliverti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mestorino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Combination of cloxacillin and essential oil of melaleuca armillaris as an alternative against staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2018.00177</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30116728?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30116728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Martino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marandino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical composition and biological activities of the essential oils from three melaleuca species grown in tunisia</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>16580</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms131216580</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23443119?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23443119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikaido</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevention of drug access to bacterial targets: permeability barriers and active efflux</article-title>. <source>Science.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>264</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.8153625</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8153625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8153625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elshafie</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Martino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattia</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>De Feo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antifungal activity of some constituents of Origanum vulgare L. essential oil against postharvest disease of peach fruit</article-title>. <source>J Med Food.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jmf.2014.0167</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25599273?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25599273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitali</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>De Laurentis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Armenise</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Milillo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibacterial effect of some essential oils administered alone or in combination with norfloxacin</article-title>. <source>Phytomedicine.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2007.01.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17303397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17303397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Synergy effects of the antibiotics gentamicin and the essential oil of croton zehntneri</article-title>. <source>Phytomedicine.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1052</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2009.04.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19524417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19524417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brufani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Segre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The synthesis of 4-deoxypyrido[1),2)-1,2]imidazo[5,4-c]rifamycin SV derivatives</article-title>. <source>J Antibiot.</source> (<year>1984</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7164/antibiotics.37.1611</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6526730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6526730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rivkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rifaximin: new therapeutic indication and future directions</article-title>. <source>Clin Ther.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>812</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2011.06.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21741091?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21741091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>DuPont</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rifaximin a novel antimicrobial for enteric infections</article-title>. <source>J Infect.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2004.05.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15667909?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15667909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>DuPont</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rifaximin: a unique gastrointestinal-selective antibiotic for enteric diseases</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Gastroenterol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOG.0b013e328333dc8d</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19881343?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19881343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanyal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Poordad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Neff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Leevy</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rifaximin treatment in hepatic encephalopathy</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>362</volume>:<fpage>1071</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0907893</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20335583?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Leitner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zollner-Schwetz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoenigl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzer</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rifaximin intake leads to emergence of rifampin-resistant staphylococci</article-title>. <source>J Infect.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2010.11.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21073894?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21073894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pistiki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Galani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyleris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbatzas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giamarellos-Bourboulis</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In vitro activity of rifaximin against isolates from patients with small intestinal bacterial overgrowth</article-title>. <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>236</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2013.12.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24461710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24461710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Orainey</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drug resistance in tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>J Chemother.</source> (<year>1990</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1120009X.1990.11739007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2116504?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2116504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprat</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Resistance to antibiotics mediated by target alterations</article-title>. <source>Science.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>264</volume>:<fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.8153626</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8153626?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8153626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapusnik</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Parenti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sande</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The use of rifampicin in staphylococcal infections&#x02013;A review</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother.</source> (<year>1984</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/13.suppl_C.61</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6381463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6381463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evolution of drug resistance in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>: clinical and molecular perspective</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.46.2.267-274.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11796329?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11796329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frieden</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sterling</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsiff</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>362</volume>:<fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)14333-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 13678977?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13678977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parmigiani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Truszkowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Terapia dell'endometrite nella bovina e nella cavalla (In italian)</article-title>. <source>Summa.</source> (<year>1990</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menozzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dall'Aglio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintavalla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dallavalle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meucci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rifaximin is an effective alternative to metronidazole for the treatment of chronic enteropathy in dogs: a randomised trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-016-0851-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27716258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27716258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>EMEA</collab></person-group>
<source>The European Agency for the Evaluation of Medicinal Products. Rifaximin (Extension to topical use), EMEA/MRL/443/98-FINAL</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Veterinary Medicine Evaluation Unit, Document EMEA/MRL/443/98-FINAL</publisher-name> (<year>1998</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;ngeles Manjarrez</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c1;vila</surname><given-names>T&#x000e9;llez S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosiles</surname><given-names>Mart&#x000ed;nez R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>Hern&#x000e1;ndez VO</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Determination of rifaximin in milk of dairy cows using high pressure liquid chromatography (HPLC)</article-title>. <source>Rev Cient&#x000ed;fica FCV LUZ.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/959/95921788003.pdf">https://www.redalyc.org/pdf/959/95921788003.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertocchi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Varisco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Farina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rifaximin and cephacetrile in a control program for <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> infections in dairy herds</article-title>. <source>Page 145 In XXI Worl Buiatric Congress Proceeding</source>. <publisher-loc>Punta del Este</publisher-loc> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Courrier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rifaximin-cefacetril treatments of clinical mastitis: efficacy of one-day treatment compared to two-day treatment</article-title>. <source>57th Annual Meeting of National Mastitis Council.</source>
<publisher-loc>Tucson, AZ</publisher-loc> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Index Herbariorum. The Herbaria of the World Part I</source>, <edition>8th ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>New York Botanical Gardens</publisher-name> (<year>1990</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NMC, National Mastitis Council</collab></person-group>
<source>Laboratory Handbook on Bovine Mastitis.</source>
<publisher-loc>Madison, WI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Mastitis Council Inc</publisher-name> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CLSI Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab></person-group>
<source>Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Disk and Dilution Susceptibility Tests for Bacteria Isolated From Animals.</source> Second Informational Supplement, CLSI document VET01-S2, <publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CLSI Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute</collab></person-group>
<source>Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Disk and Dilution Susceptibility Tests for Bacteria Isolated from Animals</source>. CLSI Document M31-A3. <publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eliopoulos</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Moellering</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antimicrobial combinations</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lorian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> Editor. <source>Antibiotics in Laboratory Medicine</source>, <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Williams &#x00026;Wilkins Co</publisher-name> (<year>1996</year>). p. <fpage>330</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Landoni</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliabadi</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PK-PD integration and modeling of marbofloxacin in sheep</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2009.05.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19523661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19523661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Men&#x000e9;ndez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biotransformation of 1,8-cineole, the main product of eucalyptus oils</article-title>. <source>Electron J Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2225/vol9-issue3-fulltext-28</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farag</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalaby</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Baroty</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical and biological evaluation of the essential oils of different melaleuca species</article-title>. <source>Phytother Res.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.1348</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14750197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14750197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maltha</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative study of the essential oils of seven melaleuca (myrtaceae) species grown in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Flavour Fragr J.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>474</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ffj.1823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Rigal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative <italic>in vivo</italic> antioxidant levels in schistosoma mansoni infected mice treated with praziquantel or essential oil of melaleuca armillaris leaves</article-title>. <source>Pak J Biol Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>971</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/pjbs.2012.971.978</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24199475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24199475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parveenb</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bareen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawaz Chaudhary</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The essential oil of Melaleuca armillaris (Sol. ex Gaertn.) Sm. leaves from Pakistan: a potential source of eugenol methyl ether</article-title>. <source>Ind Crops Prod.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>912</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2017.09.048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical composition, antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of essential oil from wedelia prostrate</article-title>. <source>EXCLI J.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 26648809?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26648809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siani</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tappin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzei</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>De Aquino Neto</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Linalool from lippia alba: study of the reproducibility of the essential oil profile and the enantiomeric purity</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>3518</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf011592n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12033821?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12033821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Melaleuca alternifolia (tea tree) oil: a review of antimicrobial and other medicinal properties</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.19.1.50-62.2006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16418522?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>KAR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>JAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>RCBQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maganni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Siqueira</surname><given-names>JP</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Synergistic inhibition of bacteria associated with minimally processed vegetables in mixed culture by carvacrol and 1,8-cineole</article-title>. <source>Food Control.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2014.07.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Y&#x000e1;&#x000f1;ez Rueda</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuadro Mogoll&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Composici&#x000f3;n qu&#x000ed;mica y actividad antibacteriana del aceite esencial de las especies eucalyptus globulus y E. camaldulensis de tres zonas de Pamplona (Colombia)</article-title>. <source>Bistua: Rev Facult Ciencias B&#x000e1;sic.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. Available online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://biblat.unam.mx/hevila/BistuaPamplona/2012/vol10/no1/5.pdf">https://biblat.unam.mx/hevila/BistuaPamplona/2012/vol10/no1/5.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayouni</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouix</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abedrabba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leveau</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamdi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanism of action of Melaleuca armillaris (Sol. ex Gaertu) Sm. essential oil on six LAB strains as assessed by multiparametric flow cytometry and automated microtiter-based assay</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.04.044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antibacterial activity of leaf essential oil and its constituents from cinnamomum longepaniculatum</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Exp Med.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1721</fpage>&#x02212;<lpage>7</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 25126170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25126170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pankey</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabath</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical relevance of bacteriostatic versus bactericidal mechanisms of action in the treatment of gram-positive bacterial infections</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/381972</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14999632?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14999632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoover</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlach</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoban</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliopoulos</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaller</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity and spectrum of rifaximin, a new topical rifamycin derivative</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis.</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0732-8893(93)90004-Q</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8385592?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8385592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jayaram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaonkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahesh</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayashree</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics-pharmacodynamics of rifampin in an aerosol infection model of tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>2118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.7.2118-2124.2003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12821456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12821456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gumbo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deziel</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Salfinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Concentration-dependent mycobacterium tuberculosis killing and prevention of resistance by rifampin</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>3781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01533-06</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17724157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17724157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Resistance to rifampicin: a review</article-title>. <source>J Antibiot</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ja.2014.107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25118103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25118103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cokcetin</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rifampicin-manuka honey combinations are superior to other antibiotic-manuka honey combinations in eradicating staphylococcus aureus biofilms</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>2653</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.02653</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29375518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29375518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of essential oils with activity against stationary phase staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/727883</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32209108?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32209108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byung-Wook</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun-Nam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Soo-Mi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mee-Jeong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju-Yeon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang-Yeol</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Therapeutic effect of oregano essential oil on subclinical bovine mastitis caused by staphylococcus aureus and escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>KSVS.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14405/kjvr.2015.55.4.253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Washburn</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An in-vitro assessment of the antibacterial activity of plant derived oils</article-title>. <source>Int J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>5587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2013-7806</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25022682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25022682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McPhee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeatts</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baynes</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Milk and plasma disposition of thymol following intramammary administration of a phytoceutical mastitis treatment</article-title>. <source>Int J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>1738</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2010-3988</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21426962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21426962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armorini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeatts</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>KAE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehmeti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a HS-SPME-GC-MS/MS method for the quantitation of thymol and carvacrol in bovine matrices and to determine residue depletion in milk and tissues</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>7856</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7865</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.6b02899</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27723978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27723978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>