<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant cell cultures compared with wild plants and other types of cultures have the advantage of being (1) less prone to various environmental variations, (2) stable production platforms of homogeneous and uniform yield, (3) rapid growth, (4) reproducible, and (5) able to synthesize novel products that do not normally exist in the native plants (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Khan M. A. et al., 2020</xref>). In addition to medicinal products, cell suspensions have been employed to produce compounds used as fragrances, food flavors, and additives, dyes, and coloring agents (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">Saeed et al., 2017</xref>). A lot of important medicinal plants have been exploited for the production of useful antiviral medicinal metabolites through callus and cell cultures (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2018a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). For example, as listed in 
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, considerable levels of diosgenin (an anti-SARS-CoV metabolite) were detected in the callus cultures of 
 <italic>Helicteres isora</italic> L (
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">Shaikh et al., 2020</xref>). Callus and cell cultures in 
 <italic>Gymnema sylvestre</italic> have shown an optimal production of gymnemic acid (GA) which possesses the potential to work against SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr">Veerashree et al., 2012</xref>). In some studies, the cell cultures were found to only accumulate the precursors of volatile medicinal compounds; while, cultures of other plants such as mentha have been recommended to produce high-valued medicinal monoterpenes compared to those found in the intact mentha plants. Likewise, callus cultures of 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> have been reported for the accumulation of monoterpenes in special secretory organs (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2019a</xref>). Similarly, results from another study have shown that callus cultures of 
 <italic>Carum copticum</italic> also accumulated higher levels of thymol and p-cymene than their wild-grown respective plants (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Razavizadeh et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
