<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Light intensity or quality during 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures can influence the plant cell’s physiological and hormonal status through the initiation of distinct metabolic pathways that ultimately influence and regulate the biosynthesis of important essential oils (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Giri and Zaheer, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2018b</xref>). In cell cultures of 
 <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic>, constant light illumination produced higher total essential oil yield including the potent volatile linalool than the cell cultures grown under complete darkness. The process of elicitation by application of chemical elicitors, e.g., phenylacetic acid and methyl jasmonate and under the effects of physical elicitors such as the absence of light illuminance in the cultures have positively influenced the production of medicinally potent metabolites in an 
 <italic>A. bracteosa</italic> cell culture (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2018b</xref>). In another study, important monoterpenes such as limonene and terpinolene (potential anti-SARS-CoV-2 metabolites) were elicited by methyl jasmonate under dark in higher amounts in 
 <italic>Rosa damascene</italic> cell cultures (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Olgunsoy et al., 2017</xref>). The process of elicitation is directly linked with the biosynthesis of essential oils in the plant cell. Several factors are responsible for the regulation of volatile compound biosynthesis. These factors include the genetic makeup of the explant used in cell cultures, the type of culture media, and the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> developmental phase of plant cells (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Holopainen, 2011</xref>). There are, however, many limitations to cell suspension culture technology including slow growth and scale-up hurdles, the instability of cell lines, and subsequent lower yield of some important metabolites (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abbasi et al., 2016</xref>). Nevertheless, optimization of cell cultures could result in the generation of very viable factories to produce medicinal compounds that could work against SARS-CoV-2 and other human viruses.
</p>
