<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chitosan is a family of polysaccharides present in the exoskeleton of crustaceans and insects as well as in the cell wall of fungi. The members of this family are classified according to their molecular weight [
 <xref rid="B132-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. A 0.7% 
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic> solution of chitosan applied for three hours could decrease the infectivity of MS2 by up to 2.80 log
 <sub>10</sub> (when using a molecule with a molecular mass of 53 kDa) and 5.16 log
 <sub>10</sub> (when using 222 kDa). By increasing the concentration to 1%, only the 222 kDa form could completely inhibit MS2 [
 <xref rid="B98-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Higher concentrations of both forms (1.5% 
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) were needed to achieve the inactivation of φX174, albeit the magnitude was much smaller than that of MS2 (0.94 log
 <sub>10</sub>). Chitosan was also active against 
 <italic>Bacillus thuringiensis</italic> phage 1–97 A [
 <xref rid="B99-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] and 
 <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> phage c2 in vitro [
 <xref rid="B100-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Furthermore, in vivo experiments with mice showed that chitosan was able to reduce Stx expression and the diffusion of induced 933 W progeny into the tissues, and to improve the lifespan of mice infected with enterohemorrhagic 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B101-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. The mechanism of action was hypothesized to be a structural modification of the capsid [
 <xref rid="B134-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. Moreover, mutagenic effects of a sucrose-rich diet were reported by Dragsted et al. when investigating the colon of Big Blue rats, a specific strain of Fischer rats that carries 40 copies of the lambda phage on chromosome 4. In this study, a sucrose-rich diet resulted in an increase of mutational frequency in the DNA of these colons [
 <xref rid="B137-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Lysozyme, which is widely distributed among prokaryotes and eukaryotes, is expressed by the R gene of phage lambda. Accordingly, the latter is called bacteriophage lambda lysozyme (LaL), and it has been shown to have bacteriolytic capabilities [
 <xref rid="B138-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. In contrast to other lysozymes, however, LaL differs regarding the cleavage of the glycosidic bond between N-acetylmuramic acid and N-acetylglucosamine of bacterial peptidoglycan. Duewel and colleagues showed that high concentrations of β(1→4) N-acetyl-D-glucosamine oligomers inhibit LaL but are not cleaved by the enzyme [
 <xref rid="B138-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. A similar observation of degrading peptidoglycans into fragments has also been reported for lysates of phage Vi II [
 <xref rid="B139-cancers-13-02036" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>].
</p>
