<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Corroborating the results obtained regarding the phenolic profile with those obtained in the case of antioxidant activity, we can affirm that there is a strong relationship between the concentrations of phenolic compounds in hydro-alcoholic extracts and their free radical scavenging activity. The presence of a higher content of phenolic compounds in hydro-alcoholic extracts leads to the improvement of their antioxidant potential. An improved antioxidant potential shows that 
 <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. hydro-alcoholic extracts may be subservient to pharmaceuticals industry, with the purpose of formulating a drug/nutritional supplement, which may help in the prevention or treatment of various problems that could arise through the formation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) [
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-25-05442" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In order to increase the effective inhibition of ROS, the production of phytocompounds must be increased. To accelerate the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites, the plant cells could be expose to ultraviolet radiation which act as an abiotic component, thus allowing the plant’s defense mechanism to produce and stimulate the essential phytochemicals [
 <xref rid="B42-molecules-25-05442" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-25-05442" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In a study conducted by Nazir et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-25-05442" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], the in vitro cell-free antioxidant potential of 
 <italic>O. basilicum</italic> extract was evaluated using yeast cells. In order to established a protocol of in vitro callus cultures of 
 <italic>O. basilicum</italic>, the author’s culture the basil leaf on Murashige and Skoog medium augmented with different concentrations of plant growth regulators. When the basil leaf was treated with 2.5 mg/mL of α-naphthalene acetic acid regulator, the antioxidant activity evaluated by DPPH assay was 93%. Another recent study also led by Nazir et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-05442" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] describes the treatment of callus culture of 
 <italic>O. basilicum</italic> with various concentrations of melatonin and UV-C radiations. Following the evaluation of in vitro antioxidant activity with DPPH test, the maximum value (90.6%) was observed when the callus culture of basil leaf was treated with UV-C for 50 min.
</p>
