<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">The soil contamination with petroleum-derived substances (PDSs), chiefly associated with the development of petroleum industry, is one of the most important issues in the natural environment (Jørgensen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2000</xref>; Ziółkowska and Wyszkowski 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">2010</xref>). PDSs have adverse effects on all the components of the environment, and many of these have carcinogenic and mutagenic effects (Iturbe et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2007</xref>; Jain et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">2011</xref>). PDSs modify the physical, chemical, and biological properties of soils and, by so doing, can negatively affect the growth and development of cultivated plants (Shirdam et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2008</xref>; Gbadebo and Adenuga 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2012</xref>). Penetrating into plants, they move in the intercellular spaces as well as in the vascular system. The particles of carbohydrates cause damage in cell walls, which leads to the leakage of the content of plant tissues, plasmolysis, the deformation of cells, disturbances in the function of conductive tissue, and the dehydration of tissues. In conditions of soil contamination with PDSs, the growth of plant roots is inhibited as well as that of root hairs (Omosun et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">2008</xref>). In cereals, the deposition of PDSs is observed around cell walls and parenchyma impeding water transport. The aboveground parts of plants growing in the conditions of soil contamination with petroleum are characterised by tiny leaves with small assimilation surfaces, visible symptoms of chloroses and necroses, and by thin, short, and poorly branched stems (Wyszkowski and Wyszkowska 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">2005</xref>).
</p>
