<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Human gingival fibroblasts (HGFs) were isolated from biopsies of gingiva from human adult patients, all informed and consenting (ethical approval by ethics committee review boards for human studies in Sassari, ref. number 2034/2014). The samples were disinfected in poly(vinylpyrrolidone)–iodine solution (PVP-I, Sigma Aldrich Chemie GmbH, Munich, Germany) for 3 min and washed twice in Hank’s balanced salt solution (HBSS; Sigma Aldrich Chemie GmbH, Munich, Germany). Dissociation was then performed by mechanical fragmentation and enzymatic digestion in 0.1% type I collagenase (Gibco Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, USA) for 120 min at 37 °C in Hanks balanced salt solution (HBSS; Sigma Aldrich Chemie GmbH, Munich, Germany). The cell suspension was filtered through a 70 μm cell strainer (Euroclone, Milano, Italy) and centrifuged at 1800 rpm for 10 min. Then, the cells were transferred in culturing medium containing DMEM medium (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), 200 U/mL penicillin, and 0.1 mg/mL streptomycin. The cells seeded in culture flasks were placed at 37 °C in a humidified atmosphere containing 5% CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. The MTT assay was used to analyze the cytotoxic effect of the two extracts on fibroblasts, according to recently published papers [
 <xref rid="B27-pharmaceutics-11-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-pharmaceutics-11-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. In total, 1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">4</sup> cells were suspended in 96-well plates diluted in 200 μL of medium. After attachment, the cells were incubated for 48 h with 200 μL of medium containing the different compounds to be tested at different concentrations (1, 10, 100 μg/mL). After 48 h, the medium was removed and 100 μL of 0.65 mg/mL MTT were added in each well and incubated for 3 h. The MTT (yellow tetrazolium salt) was enzymatically converted into purple formazan precipitate by viable cells. The concentration of formazan represents an indicator of viable cells. After removing the medium, 100 μL of DMSO was added to dissolve the formazan participates. Finally, absorbance was detected at the 570 nm wavelength by an ELISA plate reader (Gemini EM Microplate Reader; Molecular devices, San Jose, CA, USA). Control untreated cells were incubated for 48 h with the medium alone (100% viability).
</p>
