<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An Australian project called ‘Engaging in Biosecurity’ developed guidelines for engaging communities in biosecurity for agriculture [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The project aimed to develop an engagement framework that identified what enables and hinders effective community engagement about biosecurity issues. This was done by profiling six existing biosecurity engagement programmes and conducting four biosecurity engagement trials. A number of principles that address the enablers and barriers identified through their work are also included in 
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531TB2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. These principles include the fact that sources providing information and advice need to be trusted by those receiving the information, thus information needs to be channelled through the most appropriate person or organisation that has the respect and trust of the stakeholder group. This might require intermediaries to be involved so these need to be identified. Research with hikers in the Loch Lomond National Park in Scotland revealed key trusted organisations and communication media that were relied upon and commonly utilised. Specifically, people said they get information online about the environment, plants and trees, and conservation organisations were mentioned as trusted sources they use to find out about trees and plants [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Nevertheless, it is important to recognise that providing additional information, even through trusted sources, and well-used channels, does not automatically translate into additional knowledge and awareness, and changed behaviours [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Communication should also be a two-way process of mutual learning, such that communicators understand the recreationists’ perspectives on risks, their observations, concerns and experiences [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Some further lessons described by authors include the need to adopt a multifaceted approach to engagement at various scales, thus effective public engagement will likely involve multiple methods and will require collaboration and coordination across multiple partners [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
