<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Thailand is botanically very rich [
 <xref rid="B12-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and at the same time a culturally diverse country with more than 70 ethnic minorities in addition to the Thai speaking majority [
 <xref rid="B14-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There are many studies of medicinal plants from many of these ethnic minorities [
 <xref rid="B15-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], but only a few of them focus on infectious diseases [
 <xref rid="B16-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The Karen is an ethnic minority group—the largest of the hill-tribes in Thailand [
 <xref rid="B14-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. They migrated from Myanmar because of wars in the 1800s [
 <xref rid="B17-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and now live in 16 provinces in northern and western Thailand [
 <xref rid="B18-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Thai Karen are farmers and their villages are located close to forests and streams [
 <xref rid="B19-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], where most of them practice their original animism even if some have converted to Buddhism and Christianity [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In their remote settlements, plants are a primary source of medicines for their health care and the Karen possess tremendous amounts of traditional ethnomedicinal plant knowledge [
 <xref rid="B21-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The ethnomedicinal knowledge of Karen is the most extensively studied among ethnic minorities in Thailand [
 <xref rid="B23-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The ethnobotany of Thai Karen was first published in 1993 [
 <xref rid="B24-antibiotics-09-00298" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and since then several studies have been conducted in many Karen villages, especially in Chiang Mai province. However, none of these studies were focused on medicinal plants used to treat infectious diseases. Using the Cultural Importance index (CI), which measures how commonly a particular use is mentioned among villagers, and doing a meta-analysis of 25 villages of the Karen traditional knowledge, we aim to find medicinal plants used for treatments of infection diseases. Specifically, we ask: (1) which plant species and families were most commonly used by the Karen in Thailand for treatments of infectious diseases? and (2) which plant species have the potential to be developed into a new medicine?
</p>
