<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">The plant, 
 <italic>N. lotus,</italic> was collected, following the local legislation, in August 2015 from the wild in Koumassi (Latitude: 5° 16′ 60.00“ N; Longitude: -3° 58’ 59.99” W), a suburb of Abidjan (Cote d΄Ivoire). No permission was required to collect these plants. The plant was identified by Mr. Digbeu Luc Gouda (a herbalist) and authenticated by Dr. Cindy Kitcher at the Department of Pharmacognosy and Herbal Medicine (School of Pharmacy, University of Ghana), where a voucher specimen was placed (voucher number PH/2015/001). Plant extraction was performed as previously described [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], with slight modification. Briefly, the fresh leaves of 
 <italic>N. lotus</italic> were separated from the other parts of the plant, dried at room temperature for 2 weeks and then ground into a powder. The powder was then dried again in an incubator at 45 °C for 36 h. A mass of 157.5 g of the powdered plant was weighed and dissolved in 20:80 
 <inline-formula id="IEq1">
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ \raisebox{1ex}{$\mathrm{v}$}\!\left/ \!\raisebox{-1ex}{$\mathrm{v}$}\right. $$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M2" display="inline">
    <mspace width="0.25em"/>
    <mfrac bevelled="true">
     <mi mathvariant="normal">v</mi>
     <mi mathvariant="normal">v</mi>
    </mfrac>
   </math>
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3195_Article_IEq1.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> of water and ethanol. Dissolution was in the ratio 1:10 (1 part of powder to 10 parts of solvent). The mixture was macerated with intermittent stirring for 24 h and filtered. Filtrates were pulled together and concentrated using a rotary evaporator (Rotavapor, Switzerland) at 40 °C. The resulting concentrate was freeze-dried. The powder obtained (referred to as NLE) was kept in an air-tight container and stored at room temperature.
</p>
