<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">
 <italic>M. domestica</italic> management in human settlements, animal and poultry sheds mainly involves the application of insecticides or raising the birds on feed premixed with growth regulators (Macovei et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2008</xref>; Ghosh and Zurek 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2015</xref>). The excessive dependence on chemical insecticides leads to the development of insecticide resistance in flies to pyrethroids, organophosphates, spinosad, indoxacarb and spiromesifen (Khan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>; Alam et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2020</xref>) and also build-up of xenobiotics that are toxic to humans and nontarget animals. Alternatively, botanical-based insecticides pose minimal safety risks and can be used in tandem with biocontrol agents (Kaufman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2010</xref>; Khan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>; Scott 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2017</xref>; Saeed et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2018</xref>; Senthil-Nathan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2020</xref>; Shi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2020</xref>). This necessitates the development of “green” insecticides and repellents with diverse modes of action (Pavela and Benelli 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2016</xref>; Benelli and Pavela 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2018</xref>; Pavela et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2019</xref>; Isman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2020</xref>) that can mitigate the problems posed by synthetic insecticides to humans and the environment (Isman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2017</xref>; Pandiyan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2019</xref>; Ikbal and Pavela 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2019</xref>). The essential oils (EO) are an alternative to synthetic insecticides as they possess potential biological effect on insect pests with low mammalian toxicity (Koul et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2008</xref>; Chellappandian et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2018</xref>; Vasantha-Srinivasan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2018</xref>). Several studies have exhibited the larvicidal, ovicidal, adulticidal, repellence, and ovipositional deterrence of essential oils on 
 <italic>M. domestica</italic> which can be exploited for its management (Pavela and Benelli 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2016</xref>; Khater and Geden 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>).
</p>
