<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Common microcapsule shell materials include gum arabic, gelatin, cyclodextrins, sodium caseinate, cellulose derivatives, sodium alginate, chitosans, etc. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Cyclodextrins, amphiphilic hollow polysaccharides, have been used as effective carriers for food and drug delivery in the food, pharmaceutical and biomedical fields [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. β-Cyclodextrin is one of the most common microcapsule shell materials with advantages such as photostability and thermostability [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Many plant essential oils contain 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, a monoterpenoid with highly volatile properties, possessing analgesic and anti-inflammation activities. Because the half-lifetime of 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene is short; it brings the problem for the storage and utilization. Quintans et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] microencapsulated 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene by β-cyclodextrin to improve its stability and pharmacological activity. 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-Cinnamaldehyde, a major compound in cinnamon leaf oil, is classified as a phenylpropanoid and cinammic acid derivative in the classification of natural products. Microencapsulated bioactive plant essential oils with more functional properties can be applied in the food and pharmaceutical industries. Jiang et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-23-01107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] investigated the combination of β-cyclodextrin and its derivatives with 
 <italic class="italic">C. loureirii</italic> bark oil, which was rich in 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde (69.6%). Among the three materials studied, which included β-cyclodextrin (β-CD), 2,6-di-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-methyl-β-CD (DM-β-CD), and 2-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-(2-hydroxypropyl)-β-CD (HP-β-CD), the inclusion ability of β-cyclodextrin was better than that of the other two derivatives, so in this study, β-cyclodextrin was selected as the microcapsule shell material.
</p>
