<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Numerous studies have shown that exercise can have a beneficial effect on postprandial lipemia (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>–
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). Postprandial lipemia can be reduced by a single exercise (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>). Exercise intensity and duration and other factors affect the improvement of postprandial lipemia (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>). Exercise intensity is important for the protection of vascular function in adolescent boys between 12 and 15 years of age (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>). Studies have demonstrated that adolescent boys between 12.5 and 14.1 years of age who repeatedly sprint for a short time have lower postprandial TG and FMD levels than those who do not exercise (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>). Acute high-intensity interval running also reduced postprandial TG in adolescent boys age 11.3–12.9 years (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>). Adults who regularly exercise had lower postprandial TG and lower oxidative stress levels such as TBARS than inactive adults, which reduces the negative postprandial changes affecting vascular health (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Long-term exercise may alleviate postprandial lipid or oxidative stress in older adults with chronic diseases or those with elevated fasting label values (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>). In addition, moderate- to high-intensity brief exercise can reduce postprandial TG, while high-intensity interval exercise reduces postprandial free fatty acid, thiobarbituric acid reactive substances, and protein carbonyl oxidative stress markers (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>–
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>). Furthermore, high-intensity training may be more effective than moderate continuous training in reducing vascular injury (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>).
</p>
