<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0014">Person-to-person transmission is primarily reported in families, communities, and hospitals (
 <xref rid="bib0072" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2020</xref>). Droplet transmission is considered as the main route of person-to-person transmission (
 <xref rid="bib0076" ref-type="bibr">Han et al., 2020</xref>). The infection also spreads through direct contact and via fomite exposure i.e., direct contact to eyes, nose, and mouth after touching surfaces and objects contaminated by an infected individual (
 <xref rid="bib0179" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0158" ref-type="bibr">Morawskaa and Cao, 2020</xref>). In general, human-CoVs can remain infectious on some material surfaces for even 9 days (
 <xref rid="bib0098" ref-type="bibr">Kampf et al., 2020</xref>). Besides, SARS-CoV-2 also spreads through contact with asymptomatic carriers (
 <xref rid="bib0179" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2020</xref>). Since SARS-CoV-2 infection is spreading at an unprecedented pace, airborne transmission too warrants meticulous determination (
 <xref rid="bib0158" ref-type="bibr">Morawskaa and Cao, 2020</xref>). In addition, SARS-CoV-2 was found in a stool sample, gastrointestinal tissue even urine and saliva of an infected person, suggests the possibility of intestinal and fecal-oral transmission (
 <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2020</xref>). Although no case of mother to child transmission has been reported yet, infection in two newborns of Wuhan, China raises the question for vertical transmission (
 <xref rid="bib0076" ref-type="bibr">Han et al., 2020</xref>). Apart from this, there are recent studies that reveal that there is a possibility of sexual transmission of COVID-19 infection. There are an array of evidences for this transmission such as through faecal-oral route 
 <italic>via</italic> gastrointestinal infection (
 <xref rid="bib0179" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2020</xref>). This is most probably due to ACE2 that enable virus entry and ACE2 mRNA is overexpressed in gastro-intestinal system as revealed through immunofluorescent analysis of rectal epithelial cells (
 <xref rid="bib0081" ref-type="bibr">Hindson, 2020</xref>). Moreover, RNA analysis of SARS-CoV-2 also revealed that the viral particles can infect these cells therefore, it is quite predictable that sexual intercourse could be the possible way of contagion. There have been cases when person shows negative results on nasopharyngeal swabs, while, positive on rectal swabs, depicting that sexual transmission might be the possibility (
 <xref rid="bib0252" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2020</xref>). Henceforth, the physicians as well as doctors in particular recommend a strong message to discourage sexual practices if in any case of COVID-19 infection. Hence, comprehensive possible means of SARS-CoV-2 transmission warrants further study.
</p>
