<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Subsequently, IPA (2.5 g) was suspended in MeOH-H
 <sub>2</sub>O (75:25, 350 mL) and extracted with CH
 <sub>2</sub>Cl
 <sub>2</sub> (3 × 350 mL) to afford, upon evaporation, a dichloromethane soluble powder (1.9 g) (IPAD). Then, 500 mg of this residue was separated on a hand-packed reversed phase column (LiChroprep RP18, 25–40 μm, 120 g, MerckMillipore, Darmstadt, Germany) using a medium pressure liquid chromatographic (MPLC) instrument (Isolera ONE, Biotage, Uppsala, Sweden). Solvents A and B of the mobile phase were H
 <sub>2</sub>O and MeOH, respectively. A linear gradient was applied from a 70:30 A/B mixture to 100% solvent B (MeOH), over 30 min at room temperature, at a flow rate of 30 mL/min; the detection UV wavelength was set at UV 254–366 nm. Finally, the column was washed with 100% MeOH for 3 min to elute strongly adsorbed compounds. Forty-five fractions (20 mL each) were collected; the solvent in the tubes was evaporated using a centrifuge under vacuum and a liquid nitrogen trap, and the residues were weighed. The overall recovery of the chromatographed mixture was 95%. Then, the content of each fraction was analyzed by TLC on analytical silica gel 60 (GF
 <sub>254</sub>, Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) plates, eluted with EtOAc/
 <italic>n</italic>-BuOH/HCO
 <sub>2</sub>H/H
 <sub>2</sub>O (5:3:1:1), and on RP-18 (Sigma-Aldrich) plates, eluted with MeOH/H
 <sub>2</sub>O (1:1). Spots were detected under UV light at 254 and 366 nm and by spraying the plates with 0.5% vanillin in sulfuric acid/EtOH (4:1), followed by heating at 105 °C for about 1 min. Repeated MPLC separation of main fractions on reversed-phase columns afforded L-tryptophan (29 mg), androsin (
 <bold>66</bold>, 13 mg), apigenin 6-
 <italic>C</italic>-glucoside (isovitexin) (
 <bold>109</bold>, 45 mg), swertisin (
 <bold>111</bold>, 17 mg), 2″-
 <italic>O</italic>-rhamnosyl swertisin (
 <bold>112</bold>, 12 mg). A portion of IPR (5 g) was suspended in 500 mL of water and partitioned with 500 mL of 
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol to yield, after evaporation, 2.2 g of residue IPRB. Then, 1 g of this mixture was loaded onto a preparative RP-MPLC column installed in the MPLC instrument that was eluted with a gradient of 20–100% MeOH in H
 <sub>2</sub>O for 2 h at a flow rate of 10 mL/min. Repeated MPLC chromatographic separations of the main collected fractions on reversed-phase columns afforded 
 <italic>trans</italic>-ε-viniferin (
 <bold>113</bold>, 9 mg), 
 <italic>trans</italic>-resveratrol 3,4′-
 <italic>O</italic>-diglucoside (
 <bold>114</bold>, 7 mg), and isotectorigenin (
 <bold>115</bold>, 21 mg).
</p>
