<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Differences between lignocellulosic fiber and lignin-reinforced bioplastics are identified as follows. Firstly, lignocellulosic fibers and lignin play different roles when introduced into other biopolymers. Lignin can function as reinforcement, plasticizer, stabilizer, coating or bio-compatibilizer, which widens its application. By contrast, lignocellulosic fibers primarily act as reinforcement or replacement for the biopolymers in the bioplastics, which is ascribed to the more complex compositions and recalcitrant structures of lignocellulosic fibers compared to lignin [
 <xref rid="B74-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. Secondly, chemical modifications of lignin such as functionalization of hydroxyl group are more widely studied than those of lignocellulosic fibers, which is also related to their composition and structures. The interaction between lignin and biopolymers is hydrogen bond, which can be promoted by compatibilizers, crosslinkers or chemical modification. However, the interaction of lignocellulosic fibers and biopolymers is not addressed clearly. Compatibilizers and crosslinkers are used to improve the interaction of lignocellulosic fibers and biopolymers. Physical treatments such as thermal and ultrasonic treatment also reduce the degree of association of lignocellulosic fibers. In the end, the hydrophilic nature of lignocellulosic fibers is also a great challenge needed to overcome in the bioplastics. Conversely, the lignin is hydrophobic [
 <xref rid="B60-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. As a consequence, lignin presents more advantages than lignocellulosic fibers in the bioplastics. It seems to be unwise to remove lignin when the researchers fabricate the bioplastics with lignocellulosic fibers. One way is to separate lignin by destroying the degree of association of lignin and other components and mix lignin with the residuals to produce the bioplastics. Another way is to apply the lignocellulosic fibers directly or with simple modification in the bioplastics.
</p>
