<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">In the MIC test, five concentrations of the fluid extracts (ethanolic, aqueous and essential oil) of 
 <italic>Ocimum micranthum</italic> Willd leaves were analyzed. These concentrations were chosen through the evaluation of the results of osmolality and pH assays that were performed to avoid interferences in the tests with mammalian cells. The dilutions of the extracts were prepared with 5% dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) solution (D8418-500 mL ® Sigma Aldrich). This concentration of reagent was selected based on the results of a preliminary test where different concentrations of DMSO were evaluated to measure its toxicity on the microorganisms utilized in the present study and to eliminate the possibility of interference by the concentration of DMSO. Positive controls such as amikacin (4 mg/L) and nystatin (2 mg/mL), control of culture medium, color control of each extract concentration and positive control of growth of each microorganism were used. In the test, 100 μL of each microorganism suspension at a concentration of 1.5 × 10
 <sup>8</sup> CFU/mL (0.5 of the McFarland scale) was inoculated in the 96 well microplates, and then 100 μL of each extract solution were added. The microplates were incubated at 35 °C for 20–21 h in the case of 
 <italic>S. aureus, B. subtilis</italic>, and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>; in the case of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, the incubation time was 40–42 h. Once the incubation period had lapsed, 20 μL of a solution of iodonitrotetrazolium chloride 0.25 mg/mL (58030-1 g-F ®Sigma Aldrich) was added to the 96 well microplates, which were incubated at 35 °C for 1 h [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Subsequently, the MIC was determined visually, and of the wells that did not present a color change, an aliquot of 50 μL was taken to inoculate a Petri dish with a media corresponding to the evaluated microorganism. On the Petri dish, an extension technique using a digralsky spreader was carried out, after the Petri dishes were incubated at 35 °C for 24 h (
 <italic>S. aureus, B. subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>and P. aeruginosa</italic>) and 48 h (
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>). Finally, the microplates were read in a microplate reader (model Stat Fax 4200 (® Awareness Technology) at a wavelength of 492 nm.
</p>
