<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Involvement of the 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic> allelopathy in the competition was demonstrated by Reigosa et al. [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>], who proved that soil extracts from the 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic> sites during its flowering inhibit germination and growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Trifolium repens</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Lolium perenne</italic>. It was later shown that soil percolates from the 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic> plantation inhibited the germination and growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactuca sativa</italic> stronger than throughfall and stemflow, and an increase in phytotoxicity coincided with the acacia flowering period and the germination of undergrowth species, which increased the allelopathic effect [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. Lorenzo et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>] evaluated the role of allelopathy in the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic> in Southern Europe using throughfall, litter leachate, and aqueous soil extracts collected in the main phenological and stress phases of the tree, i.e., formation of pods, in a period of severe drought, during formation of inflorescences, and in the flowering period. The effects of the 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic> extracts on the germination and growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactuca sativa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Zea mays</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Dactylis glomerata</italic> were species-specific and more often stimulating rather than inhibiting. Such a reaction can have long-term negative effects on native plant populations, since advanced growth during periods of scarce resources can be harmful [
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. The decomposition of the 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic> plant materials showed high phytotoxic activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Lactuca sativa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Trifolium repens</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Lolium perenne</italic>, with toxicity being maintained for up to 16 weeks [
 <xref rid="B70-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. In order to investigate the mechanism of germination and growth inhibition, evaluation of the physiological parameters of the native understory species in Northwest Spain was carried out [
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. Net photosynthetic and respiration rates of 
 <italic class="italic">Hedera hibernica</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Dicranum</italic> sp., 
 <italic class="italic">Dactylis glomerata</italic> L., and 
 <italic class="italic">Leucobryum </italic>sp. were significantly affected by canopy leachate and apical branche macerate of 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic>, with the strongest effect during the flowering period. These results showed that 
 <italic class="italic">A. dealbata</italic> could limit distribution of understory species [
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>].
</p>
