<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have revealed that these fertilizer treatments improve this trait compared to the control, and the integrated treatments were more effective than the simple treatments, which can be attributed to the positive effect of these fertilizers on the physical and chemical features of the soil. The addition of nano Fe-chelate to integrated fertilization regimes increased phenol synthesis in 
 <italic>L. iberica</italic> plants by inhibiting the conversion of hydrogen peroxide to free radicals [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Research also shows that there is a direct relationship between the content of phenol compounds and antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The higher content of phenol compounds as a free radical scavenger is the main reason for the higher antioxidant activity of the plant extracts. It has been documented that growth and nutritional conditions bring about various phytochemical changes in plants. For example, the application of K and N fertilizer increased phenol compounds in basil and tea leaves or the foliar application of Fe, Zn and Cu enhanced borage herb total phenols. Fertilizers can be applied as a soil enhancer, so that nutrients are absorbed by the plant roots, or applied as a foliar application, in which they are absorbed through the leaves, or in a combined method. Research has shown that foliar application had more beneficial effects than soil application. Because nanoparticles have high surface/volume ratios, they subsequently cause higher leaf absorption properties (than soil application) that increase biochemical activities and reactivity [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-00252" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
