<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effects of dietary insect meal inclusion on the carcass characteristics and meat quality parameters of poultry products (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00170-t008" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 8</xref>) have been investigated by testing different inclusion levels of HI, TM and MD meals.The carcass traits of broiler chickens and quails were unaffected by dietary HI, MD, and TM larva meal inclusion [
 <xref rid="B24-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>]. However, Schiavone et al. [
 <xref rid="B91-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>] showed that an inclusion of up to 10% of HI larva meal, in partial substitution of SBM, improved the live and carcass weights of broiler chickens. Loponte et al. [
 <xref rid="B52-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>] reported greater carcass weights in Barbary partridges (
 <italic class="italic">Alectoris barbara</italic>) fed HI and TM-based diets as a partial replacement (25 % or 50%) of SBM than in the control group. Ballitoc and Sun [
 <xref rid="B65-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>] also found improved slaughter yields, dressed carcass and eviscerated weights in broiler chickens fed TM diets at a 2% inclusion level. Similarly, Biasato et al. [
 <xref rid="B61-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>] evaluated the effects of a partial replacement of SBM, corn gluten meal and soybean oil with TM larva meal on the carcass characteristics of female broiler chickens and found an increase in the carcass weight, abdominal fat weight and abdominal fat percentage with increasing levels of TM meal utilization (from 5 to 15%). Pieterse et al. [
 <xref rid="B92-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>] similarly demonstrated that broilers that received 10% MD larva meal had higher live and carcass weights, as well as higher breast and thigh yields than those of the control diet. Téguia et al. [
 <xref rid="B67-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>] did not observe any significant difference for different dietary inclusion levels of MD and the control group for the hot carcass yield and proportion of different parts of the carcass, but instead observed higher proportions of liver and gizzard.
</p>
