<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0230">Prepare an input parameter file, in which all the parameters for AILDE calculation are contained.
 <list list-type="simple" id="olist0025">
  <list-item id="o0040">
   <label>4.</label>
   <p id="p0235">Create a parameter file which contains all the necessary parameters for AILDE protocol (
    <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). Mandatory parameters are “step,” “complex,” “ligand_name,” “ligand_charge,” “parallel,” “MDstart,” “MDend,” “mm_pbsa,” “md_request,” and “entropy.” Each parameter has a default value.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0045">
   <label>5.</label>
   <p id="p0240">An example parameter file is provided in the AILDE source code (
    <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). A standard format must be followed to define the parameters. Among those parameters, the following three parameters should be adjusted according to actual situation:
    <list list-type="simple" id="olist0030">
     <list-item id="o0050">
      <label>a.</label>
      <p id="p0245">complex: define the structure file name of the protein complex with hit ligand.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="o0055">
      <label>b.</label>
      <p id="p0250">ligand_name: define the name of the hit ligand in the complex structure file.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="o0060">
      <label>c.</label>
      <p id="p0255">md_request: define whether structural relaxation is performed on the newly obtained hit analogs-protein complex by molecular dynamics (MD) simulation.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0065">
   <label>6.</label>
   <p id="p0260">Other parameters can be maintained as default value and the detail descriptions about these parameters are recorded in the template parameter file (
    <xref rid="sec6.1" ref-type="sec">Troubleshooting 1</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <disp-quote>
  <p>
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx3.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <bold>CRITICAL:</bold> The parameters should be accordant with the actual situations and abide by the format in the example parameter file.
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
</p>
