<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">
 <italic>Artemisia argyi</italic> is a region-specific plant from northern temperate zones, especially in Asia. Both in vitro and in vivo studies have revealed that 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>argyi</italic> phytochemicals afford various health-promoting potentials, including antioxidant, anti-cancer, anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory, neuroprotective, anticoagulant, and anti-osteoporotic activities, as well as antimicrobial and insecticidal properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The whole plant is used as an insecticide; branches of the herb are used as battens in livestock houses to repel parasites in survey area. The fresh leaves are taken and crushed, and after that, are combined with fresh ginger and 
 <italic>Blumea balsamifera</italic> and rubbed on cattle’s external tongue for oral disease and as anthelmintic by the Buyi villagers. 
 <italic>Curcuma aromatica</italic> contains curcumene, sesquidentenol, camphor, and camphene. It functions to clear up congestion and fever and detoxifies and relieves pain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Jeon et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] investigated the effects of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>aromatica</italic> water extracts (CAW) in the stomachs of rats with ethanol-induced gastritis. CAW increased the production of prostaglandin Esub2/sub. These findings suggest that CAW protects against ethanol-induced gastric mucosa injury by increasing the antioxidant status. Fresh roots are crushed and given to livestock for fracture in Buyi villages. 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> has been widely used in traditional medicines since ancient times, and is also utilized as a dietary supplement. Extracts of 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> including zingiberol, zingiberene, gingerol, and shogaol have a variety of health functions, such as warming the stomach and accelerating blood circulation. The pharmacological actions of ginger include antioxidant, anti-tumor, anti-apoptosis, anti-inflammation, anti-hyperglycemia, anti-cough, and anti-colds effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. It has been found that extracts obtained in alcohol and water from 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> had significant inhibitory effects on 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and also antihypercholesterolemic activities as well as diuretic potential [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Local veterinarians use ginger in a variety of ways. Ginger is a common veterinary medicine used by local veterinarians to treat diseases such as oral diseases, digestive diseases, and colds in livestock. Tubers are crushed and mixed with fodder and orally given to livestock for promotion stomach digestion and against digestive disorders, for flatulence and as appetizer. 
 <italic>Taraxacum mongolicum</italic> has been used in traditional Chinese medicine and dietary applications throughout the history of China. It has been reported that alcoholic and aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>Taraxacum mongolicum</italic> have antibacterial activities and certain bactericidal effects on pneumococci, meningococcus, diphtheria bacillus, pseudomonas aeruginosa, dysentery bacillus, and typhoid bacillus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Decoction is made from its roots, and orally given to livestock for treating respiratory troubles used by local Buyi people. 
 <italic>Sophora flavescens</italic>, also known as Kushen in Chinese, has been an important species in Chinese medicine since the Qin and Han dynasties. The root of 
 <italic>Sophora flavescens</italic> has a long history in the traditional medicines of many countries, including China, Japan, Korea, India, and some European countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. In China, 
 <italic>Sophora flavescens</italic> has been used extensively, mainly in combination with other medicinal plants, to treat fever, dysentery, hematochezia, jaundice, oliguria, vulvar swelling, asthma, eczema, inflammatory disorders, ulcers, and diseases associated with skin burns [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Its main medicinal components are matrine and oxymatrine in alkaloids, which have function to inhibit tumor cells and improve immunity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. 
 <italic>Sophora flavescens</italic> is a very important herb for local veterinaries. Decoction is made from its roots and orally given to livestock for treating diarrhea along with 
 <italic>Ardisia crispa</italic>, and treating respiratory disorders along with 
 <italic>Taraxacum mongolicum</italic> and 
 <italic>Lonicera japonica</italic>.
</p>
