<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_TOXREP1032 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEga1 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Toxicology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2214-7500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7787995</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2214-7500(20)30472-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2020.12.027</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>A vision for the future of pesticide toxicology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Acute and repeated-dose toxicity of <italic>Echinops kebericho</italic> Mesfin essential oil</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0005"><name><surname>Deyno</surname><given-names>Serawit</given-names></name><email>dserawit@std.must.ac.ug</email><email>dserawit@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0010"><name><surname>Tola</surname><given-names>Mesfin Asefa</given-names></name><email>mesfin.asefa@sphmmc.edu.et</email><xref rid="aff0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0015"><name><surname>Bazira</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><email>jbazira@must.ac.ug</email><xref rid="aff0025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0020"><name><surname>Makonnen</surname><given-names>Eyasu</given-names></name><email>eyasumakonnen@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff0030" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="aff0035" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0025"><name><surname>Alele</surname><given-names>Paul E.</given-names></name><email>paulalele@must.ac.ug</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Department of Pharmacology, Mbarara University of Science and Technology, Mbarara, Uganda</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Department of Pharmacology, School of Pharmacy, College of Medicine and Health Sciences, Hawassa University, Hawassa, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Pharmbiotechnology and Traditional Medicine Center of Excellence (PHARMBIOTRAC), Mbarara University of Science and Technology, P.O. Box 1410, Mbarara, Uganda</aff><aff id="aff0020"><label>d</label>Department of Pathology, St. Paul&#x02019;s Hospital Millennium Medical College, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff0025"><label>e</label>Department of Microbiology, Mbarara University of Science and Technology, Mbarara, Uganda</aff><aff id="aff0030"><label>f</label>Center for Innovative Drug Development and Therapeutic Trials for Africa, College of Health Sciences, Addis Ababa University, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</aff><aff id="aff0035"><label>g</label>Department of Pharmacology and Clinical Pharmacy, College of Health Sciences, Addis Ababa University, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Pharmacology, Mbarara University of Science and Technology, Mbarara, Uganda. <email>dserawit@std.must.ac.ug</email><email>dserawit@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0005"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="fig0025" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="ga1"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="lis0005"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0005">No mortality was observed up to 2000 mg/kg dose in acute toxicity study of <italic>Echinops kebericho</italic> essential oil.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0010">On repeated-dose toxicity study, essential oil treated groups and controls did not show significant variations.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0015">No significant variation was observed in food consumption, body and organ weight, and histopathology between treated and control groups.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0020">Urea, albumin, aspartate aminotransferase, andorgan weight of kidney significantly varied between some treated groups compared to control.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0025">Significant variations were observed between male and female in many parameters.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0015"><p><italic>Echinops kebericho</italic> Mesfin is used for the management of various diseases and fumigation during child birth. This study investigated acute and repeated-dose toxicity of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> M. essential oils (EOs). The study was conducted in Swiss albino mice. Organ weight, histopathology and clinical chemistry were analyzed. The dose and duration of treatment were defined in accordance with Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) guideline.</p><p>No mortality was observed in acute oral dose toxicity study up to 2000 mg/kg per body weight. Compared to control group, treated groups did not show significant abnormalities in body weight and most parameters of clinical chemistry parameters and relative organ weight in repeated-dose toxicity study. However, urea, albumin, aspartate aminotransferase, and relative organ weight of right kidney showed variations in treated groups compared to control group. All treated groups and control group showed normal histology except lymphocytic infiltrates observed on the kidney with 200 mg/kg treated female group. The current study revealed that EO of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> M. could be considered well tolerated in acute and repeated-dose exposure. Further, teratogenic, mutagenic, carcinogenic, and sub-chronic and chronic toxicity studies are warranted.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Abbreviations</title><kwd>EO, essential oil</kwd><kwd><italic>E. kebericho</italic>, <italic>Echinops kebericho</italic></kwd><kwd>AST, aspartate transaminase</kwd><kwd>ALT, alanine transaminase</kwd><kwd>ALP, alkaline phosphate</kwd><kwd>TG, triglycerides</kwd><kwd>Cr, creatinine</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="kwd0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Safety</kwd><kwd>Herbal medicine</kwd><kwd>Clinical chemistry</kwd><kwd>Histopathology</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><p id="misc0005">Edited by DR. A.M. Tsatsaka</p></notes></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Background</title><p id="par0030">Medicinal plants contributed to the treatment of many common diseases and are sources of new modern medicines. Their use is increasing owing to perceived low cost, alignment with sociocultural, religious and spiritual values, emergence of resistance, and dissatisfaction with conventional healthcare [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Secondary metabolites within the plants exert biological activities with potential therapeutic effects [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and adverse effects. Essential Oils (EOs) are among the many secondary metabolites produced by plants, and are commonly employed in the arena of health and health-related care for many years. Essential oils possess significant commercial, environmental, agricultural, dietary, medical, perfumery and aromatherapy applications [<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Essential oils are complex natural mixtures containing about 20&#x02013;60 components of different concentrations and are characterized by one or two major components at high concentrations (20&#x02013;70 %) compared to the other components present in trace amounts [<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Essential oils&#x02019; major use is in fragrances where approximately about 300 EOs are in use from 3000 known EOs sources [<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Essential Oils&#x02019; includes flavoring in foods, fragrances in perfumes and cosmetics and food preservatives due to their antimicrobial activity. Their direct addition to food stuff exerts antimicrobial, antioxidant and radical scavenging effect [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. A recent systematic review and meta-analysis revealed that EOs could be viable alternatives for the decolonization of methicillin resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA), acne treatment, and topical antifungal infections [<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p id="par0035">Essential oils are traditionally used commonly in food processing or as medicines in Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Fresh or dried leaves of thymus species are used as condiments and ingredients in the preparation of &#x0201c;<italic>berbere&#x0201d;</italic> and <italic>&#x0201c;shirro&#x0201d;</italic> (pepper and bean/pea flour) as well as Metata ayb (traditionally fermented cottage cheese) in Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. <italic>Echinops kebericho</italic> Mesfin (family, Asteraceae) is among the commonly used EO-producing endemic medicinal plants in Ethiopia [<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Ethno-pharmacological survey showed <italic>E. kebericho</italic>&#x02019;s tremendous use in the treatment of infectious disease, stomachache, headache, heart disease, migraine, mental illness, kidney disease, where the smoke is inhaled in most cases [<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>]. The tuber is also smoked to repel snakes from the vicinity and for fumigation during child birth [<xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The traditional use of inhalation could imply volatile component&#x02019;s therapeutic effect. It has been confirmed that the major constituent of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EO is dehydrocostus lactone [<xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] which was proved to exert anticancer activity [<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>] and antimicrobial activities [<xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. <italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> studies revealed various pharmacological activities of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EOs such as antibacterial and antifungal activities [<xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], anti-mycobacterial activity (against <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic>) with significant resistance modulatory effects [<xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], stronger activity against leishmania [<xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], insect repellent activity [<xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and mosquito larvicidal activity [<xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p id="par0040">Previous toxicity studies established relative safety of the EOs <italic>in vitro</italic> model [<xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and decoction in rats [<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Extrapolation of <italic>in vitro</italic> toxicity to human is less reliable and there is a need for animal model toxicity study. Given the numerous studies confirming the medicinal use and wide traditional use of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> as inhalation, characterization of its EO toxicity profile is required in order to protect and promote public health. Hence, this is the continuation of our previous study [<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] to establish the acute and repeated-dose toxicities of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EOs. The study predicted the safety of the EO in human use, ensure the public safety, and promote further development.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="par0045">The experimental procedures were conducted in accordance with Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) guidelines [<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], complied to the ethical standards of EU Directive 2010/63/EU for animal experiments, and was conducted with proper animal handling under well-founded conditions in accordance with the recommendations of guide for the care and use of animals [<xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The protocol was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of Mbarara University of Science and Technology and registered with Uganda National Council for Science and Technology (UNCST).</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Extraction and formulation of the essential oil</title><p id="par0050"><italic>Echinops kebericho</italic> M. was collected from Andracha woreda, Sheka zone, Southwest, Ethiopia. The identification of the plant material was previous described [<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The collected fresh tuber was first washed by tap water and then by distilled water to remove dirt and debris. Pounded material of the plant was added to 5 L of distilled water in 1/5 (w/v) ratio in a round bottom glass flask and subjected to hydro-distillation for 3 h using Clevenger type apparatus at Pharmacognosy Department, School of Pharmacy, Addis Ababa University. After extraction, the EO was collected; its volume and weight were measured. The EO was dissolved in 4% Tween 80 solutions for administration. The volume of solution administered was 1 ml/100 g and the concentration was adjusted to volume needed for administration.</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Study design, sample size and allocation</title><p id="par0055">This was a laboratory-based experimental study in Swiss albino mice and the results of the study were reported in accordance with ARRIVE guidelines [<xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The sample size was determined in accordance with OECD guideline. The dose level for repeated-dose toxicity study were determined based on the acute toxicity and ethno-pharmacological claims [<xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Graded doses, 100 mg/kg, 200 mg/kg and 400 mg/kg, of the EOs and the vehicle were administered by oral gavage once daily for 28 consecutive days every morning. The control groups received the same volume of vehicle, 4% tween 80, as the test group. In acute toxicity study, female mice were used as per OECD-423 guideline [<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In repeated-dose toxicity study, ten mice of five from female and male were included. Total number of groups in acute toxicity study was three while in repeated-dose toxicity study it was four as outlined in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Number of animals used and dose level in acute and repeated-dose toxicity study.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="par0060">The mice were allocated into experimental groups by simple randomization technique using lottery method and were marked using permanent marker for identification purpose. The animals were treated in rotation every other day from control to highest dose and vice versa.</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Experimental animals and husbandry</title><p id="par0065">Swiss albino mice weighing 18&#x02013;26 g were obtained from Ethiopian Public Health Institute. The mice were kept in plastic cages in environmental conditions (22&#x02013;24 &#x000b0;C, 12 h: 12 h dark/light cycle), fed a rodent pellet diet and allowed to drink water <italic>ad libitum</italic>. All mice were housed in standard cages in groups and acclimatized for two weeks before experiment. In acute toxicity study three female mice of the same group were housed together. In repeated-dose toxicity study five per group were housed together.</p></sec><sec id="sec0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Experimental procedures in acute toxicity study</title><p id="par0070">Acute toxicity study was conducted and results were interpreted before the commencement of repeated-dose toxicity study. In acute toxicity study, nine mice grouped in three groups were employed as recommended in OECD guideline [<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The first group received 4% Tween 80, the second group 300 mg/kg EO and the third group 2000 mg/kg EO after 24 h. The mice were fasted overnight and provided with water only, and then EO was administered via oral gavages. Observations were made closely for the first 4 h, 24 h and up to 14 days. The number of death within the study period was recorded. At the end of the experiment, the mice were sacrificed for gross anatomy investigation and organ weight measured. The LD<sub>50</sub> values of the EOs were determined based on the Globally Harmonized System of Classification and Labeling of Chemicals (GHS) [<xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><label>2.6</label><title>Experimental procedures in repeated-dose toxicity study</title><p id="par0075">Ten mice, five male and five female, were employed in accordance with the repeated-dose 28-day oral toxicity study OECD guideline in rodents [<xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Parameters measured include: food consumption, body weight, relative organ weight, clinical chemistry (aspartate transaminase (AST), alanine transaminase (ALT), alkaline phosphate (ALP), total protein (TP), total cholesterol (TC), blood urea nitrogen (BUN), creatinine (Cr), total bilirubin (T-Bili), direct bilirubin (Bili-dir), albumin (Alb), triglycerides (TG), and glucose (Glu)) and histopathology as described previously [<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The relative organ weight, defined as the organ weight per 100 g of body weight at sacrifice was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>2.7</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="par0080">Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism version 5 software. Data were presented as mean &#x000b1; (Standard deviation, SD). ANOVA assumptions were checked using Bartlett's test for equality of variance and D'Agostino &#x00026; Pearson omnibus normality test. ANOVA was performed; if assumptions were met otherwise Kruskal-Wallis analyses. For significant values post-hoc analysis was performed using Tukey for ANOVA or Dunn's Multiple Comparison Test for Kruskal-Wallis analysis. The p &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0050"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="par0085">The yield of the essential oil was 0.18 % per dry weight of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> M. All mice were na&#x000ef;ve to the treatment gievn. All mice completed treatment in good health condition and were included in the analyses.</p><sec id="sec0055"><label>3.1</label><title>Acute toxicity of EO of <italic>Echinops kebericho</italic></title><p id="par0090">Single oral dose of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> M. EO up to 2000 mg/kg did not show treatment-related morbidity in mice. Treated mice did not show significant treatment related morbidity: yet short term disturbances including piloerection, muscle spasm and apathy were observed immediately after administration of 2000 mg/kg and ended in 12 h&#x02019; time. The changes in body weights were not statistically significant (slope of linear regression, P = 0.5231). Better increase in body weight was observed in control group compared to 300 mg/kg and also 300 mg/kg compared to 2000 mg/kg treated (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Mean body weight showed non-significant variation between 300 mg/kg treated group versus 2000 mg/kg, p = 0.2950.<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EO on body weight as function of time (in days) after single dose exposure in 300 mg/kg and 2000 mg/kg treated groups compared to controls.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><label>3.2</label><title>Sub-acute toxicity of essential oil of <italic>Echinops kebericho</italic></title><sec id="sec0065"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Body weight, food consumption and relative organ weight</title><p id="par0095">Body weight and food consumption remained constant for combined groups but significant variations when male and female groups were analyzed separately. Control and 100 mg/kg EO treated female groups showed constant weight, while 200 mg/kg and 400 mg/kg EO treated female groups showed significant loss in weight. All male groups showed significant weight gain, increased food consumption pattern in controls and those treated with 100 mg/kg EO, but constant consumption pattern in medium and high dose treated male groups. However, combined groups showed constant weight and food consumption pattern throughout the treatment period (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>)<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Linear regression of weight gain in different groups of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EO treated and control group.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2">Group</th><th colspan="4" align="left">Weight gain<hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="left">Food consumption<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Slop (95 %CI)</th><th align="left">p-value</th><th align="left">R<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left">Interpretation</th><th align="left">Slop (95 %CI)</th><th align="left">p-value</th><th align="left">R<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left">Interpretation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="9" align="left">Males and females treated separately</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control-Female</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.1040 &#x000b1; 0.04773</td><td align="left">0.0721</td><td align="left">0.4419</td><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">0.07349 &#x000b1; 0.1533</td><td align="left">0.6420</td><td align="left">0.02246</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">100 mg/kg-Female</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.05847 &#x000b1; 0.02829</td><td align="left">0.0842</td><td align="left">0.4160</td><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">0.06484 &#x000b1; 0.1358</td><td align="left">0.6432</td><td align="left">0.02230</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">200 mg/kg-Female</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.1610 &#x000b1; 0.03272</td><td align="left">0.0027</td><td align="left">0.8014</td><td align="left">Loss</td><td align="left">0.1427 &#x000b1; 0.1730</td><td align="left">0.4290</td><td align="left">0.06363</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">400 mg/kg-Female</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.1098 &#x000b1; 0.04439</td><td align="left">0.0482</td><td align="left">0.5048</td><td align="left">Loss</td><td align="left">0.1547 &#x000b1; 0.1077</td><td align="left">0.1816</td><td align="left">0.1709</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control-Male</td><td align="left">0.4130 &#x000b1; 0.01038</td><td align="left">&#x0003c; 0.0001</td><td align="left">0.9962</td><td align="left">Gain</td><td align="left">0.3833 &#x000b1; 0.1336</td><td align="left">0.0167</td><td align="left">0.4516</td><td align="left">Increased</td></tr><tr><td align="left">100 mg/kg-Male</td><td align="left">0.4623 &#x000b1; 0.03946</td><td align="left">&#x0003c; 0.0001</td><td align="left">0.9581</td><td align="left">Gain</td><td align="left">0.4025 &#x000b1; 0.1490</td><td align="left">0.0222</td><td align="left">0.4220</td><td align="left">Increased</td></tr><tr><td align="left">200 mg/kg-Male</td><td align="left">0.4249 &#x000b1; 0.03962</td><td align="left">&#x0003c; 0.0001</td><td align="left">0.9504</td><td align="left">Gain</td><td align="left">0.4433 &#x000b1; 0.2160</td><td align="left">0.0672</td><td align="left">0.2964</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">400 mg/kg-Male</td><td align="left">0.3757 &#x000b1; 0.02571</td><td align="left">&#x0003c; 0.0001</td><td align="left">0.9727</td><td align="left">Gain</td><td align="left">0.07637 &#x000b1; 0.1991</td><td align="left">0.7094</td><td align="left">0.01449</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="left">When male and females combined</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td align="left">0.1545 &#x000b1; 0.1030</td><td align="left">0.1559</td><td align="left">0.1384</td><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">0.2248 &#x000b1; 0.1302</td><td align="left">0.0984</td><td align="left">0.1193</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">100 mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.2019 &#x000b1; 0.1126</td><td align="left">0.0945</td><td align="left">0.1868</td><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">0.2157 &#x000b1; 0.1143</td><td align="left">0.0723</td><td align="left">0.1394</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">200 mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.1320 &#x000b1; 0.1104</td><td align="left">0.2520</td><td align="left">0.09255</td><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">0.2394 &#x000b1; 0.1668</td><td align="left">0.1653</td><td align="left">0.08560</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr><tr><td align="left">400 mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.1330 &#x000b1; 0.1274</td><td align="left">0.3142</td><td align="left">0.07221</td><td align="left">No change</td><td align="left">0.1152 &#x000b1; 0.1175</td><td align="left">0.3375</td><td align="left">0.04187</td><td align="left">No change</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="par0100">No statistical significant variations in food consumption and weight were observed between treated groups and the control group (p = 0.3518 and p = 0.6942, respectively). However, significant variations in food consumption were observed between females and males (p = 0.0001). <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows a trend of similar food consumption and weight among high dose treated groups compared to other groups as a function of time (in days) though the difference is non-significant (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Food consumption pattern among different groups of male, female and male and female merged together. Body weight pattern among different groups of male, female and male and female merged together.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="par0105">No significant difference in relative organ weight (left kidney, lung, heart, spleen) was observed in treated groups compared to controls. However, there was a significant difference in mean relative organ weight of right kidney treated with highest dose of EO (400 mg/kg) compared to control group (mean difference 0.1896, 95 % CI: 0.04638, 0.3329, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0093). Significant variations in relative organ weight of spleen, left and right kidney was also observed between male and female groups (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of oral administration of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> essential oil on organ weight.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0030">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2">Organs</th><th colspan="4" align="left">Male<hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="left">Female<hr/></th><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2">P-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">control</th><th align="left">100 mg/kg</th><th align="left">200 mg/kg</th><th align="left">400 mg/kg</th><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left">100 mg/kg</th><th align="left">200 mg/kg</th><th align="left">400 mg/kg</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="10" align="left">Relative weight = Organ weight in gram/body weight of the mice (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">5.94 &#x000b1; 0.63</td><td align="left">6.12 &#x000b1; 0.76</td><td align="left">6.57 &#x000b1; 0.43</td><td align="left">6.54 &#x000b1; 0.68</td><td align="left">5.85 &#x000b1; 0.84</td><td align="left">4.66 &#x000b1; 0.60</td><td align="left">5.08 &#x000b1; 0.74</td><td align="left">4.98 &#x000b1; 0.41</td><td align="left">0.0014/0.6172</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Right kidney</td><td align="left">0.82 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td align="left">0.87 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">0.82 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td align="left">0.76 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td align="left">0.91 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td align="left">0.74 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td align="left">0.72 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.59 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td align="left">0.0121/0.0093</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Left kidney</td><td align="left">0.81 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td align="left">0.86 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.83 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="left">0.80 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.63 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.58 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">&#x0003c; 0.0001/0.7258</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spleen</td><td align="left">0.40 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="left">0.37 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="left">0.55 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td align="left">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.33</td><td align="left">0.85 &#x000b1; 0.63</td><td align="left">0.43 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="left">0.42 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.0304/0.0677</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lung</td><td align="left">0.90 &#x000b1; 0.27</td><td align="left">0.84 &#x000b1; 0.19</td><td align="left">0.94 &#x000b1; 0.30</td><td align="left">0.95 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td align="left">0.91 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td align="left">0.88 &#x000b1; 0.24</td><td align="left">1.00 &#x000b1; 0.35</td><td align="left">0.88 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td align="left">0.9129/0.7411</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Heart</td><td align="left">0.66 &#x000b1; 0.30</td><td align="left">0.60 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">0.55 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">0.58 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td align="left">0.53 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">0.57 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="left">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.6719/0.8303</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10" align="left">Absolute weight (in grams)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Liver</td><td align="left">2.14 &#x000b1; 0.40 g</td><td align="left">2.05 &#x000b1; 0.42</td><td align="left">2.31 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td align="left">2.11 &#x000b1; 0.20</td><td align="left">2.09 &#x000b1; 0.38</td><td align="left">1.64 &#x000b1; 0.37</td><td align="left">1.60 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td align="left">1.72 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Right kidney</td><td align="left">0.29 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.29 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left">0.29 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="left">0.25 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td align="left">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.23 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left">0.21 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Left kidney</td><td align="left">0.29 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td align="left">0.29 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.29 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.23 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.21 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Spleen</td><td align="left">0.14 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.19 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.21 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">0.31 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td align="left">0.15 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left">0.15 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left">0.14 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Lung</td><td align="left">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="left">0.28 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">0.31 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td align="left">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td align="left">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="left">0.30 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Heart</td><td align="left">0.23 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td align="left">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td align="left">0.19 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.18 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.18 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.18 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.17 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>Note</italic>: The first serious of the p-value column shows ANOVA/ Kruskal-Wallis analysis result when male and female groups are grouped separately while the second when both are grouped together.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0070"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Clinical chemistry</title><p id="par0110">Except for albumin and AST, no significant variations in biochemical values were observed between male and female groups. However, significant variations in urea, albumin and AST levels were observed between males and females (<xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Clinical chemistry parameters in repeated dose oral toxicity study of E. kebericho essential oil treated mice.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0035">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th colspan="4" align="left">Male<hr/></th><th colspan="4" align="left">Female<hr/></th><th align="left">P-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left">100 mg/kg</th><th align="left">200 mg/kg</th><th align="left">400 mg/kg</th><th align="left">Control</th><th align="left">100 mg/kg</th><th align="left">200 mg/kg</th><th align="left">400 mg/kg</th><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">AST (U/L)</td><td align="left">406.4 &#x000b1; 297.7</td><td align="left">237.0 &#x000b1; 111.1</td><td align="left">229.6 &#x000b1; 60.54</td><td align="left">711.3 &#x000b1; 184.0</td><td align="left">209.6 &#x000b1; 92.13</td><td align="left">379.0 &#x000b1; 215.4</td><td align="left">669.8 &#x000b1; 324.9</td><td align="left">553.4 &#x000b1; 365.9</td><td align="left">0.0086*/0.0394*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ALT (U/L)</td><td align="left">163.4 &#x000b1; 188.0</td><td align="left">77.00 &#x000b1; 50.20</td><td align="left">51.80 &#x000b1; 22.31</td><td align="left">104.8 &#x000b1; 44.89</td><td align="left">55.00 &#x000b1; 24.05</td><td align="left">71.40 &#x000b1; 35.08</td><td align="left">151.2 &#x000b1; 93.45</td><td align="left">104.8 &#x000b1; 44.89</td><td align="left">0.1195/0.3339</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ALP (U/L)</td><td align="left">128.6 &#x000b1; 16.92</td><td align="left">188.0 &#x000b1; 138.1</td><td align="left">186.8 &#x000b1; 108.4</td><td align="left">109.4 &#x000b1; 62.68</td><td align="left">245.2 &#x000b1; 179.2</td><td align="left">69.40 &#x000b1; 21.82</td><td align="left">50.40 &#x000b1; 44.65</td><td align="left">165.8 &#x000b1; 90.73</td><td align="left">0.0588/0.5238</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Creatinine (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.19</td><td align="left">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="left">0.28 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">0.22 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">0.20 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td align="left">0.26 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td align="left">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.39</td><td align="left">0.45 &#x000b1; 0.31</td><td align="left">0.6380/0.7947</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Urea (mg/dL)</td><td align="left">57.04 &#x000b1; 10.24</td><td align="left">48.86 &#x000b1; 19.47</td><td align="left">64.80 &#x000b1; 27.33</td><td align="left">56.40 &#x000b1; 6.98</td><td align="left">51.23 &#x000b1; 8.97</td><td align="left">77.20 &#x000b1; 32.23</td><td align="left">102.6 &#x000b1; 25.71</td><td align="left">74.83 &#x000b1; 25.67</td><td align="left">0.0104*/0.0817</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Protein-T (g/dl)</td><td align="left">6.38 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td align="left">6.66 &#x000b1; 2.07</td><td align="left">5.98 &#x000b1; 2.89</td><td align="left">5.74 &#x000b1; 0.39</td><td align="left">5.90 &#x000b1; 1.06</td><td align="left">5.88 &#x000b1; 0.24</td><td align="left">14.04 &#x000b1; 4.79</td><td align="left">5.90 &#x000b1; 0.97</td><td align="left">0.9880/0.9312</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Albumin (g/dl)</td><td align="left">2.72 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td align="left">2.86 &#x000b1; 0.19</td><td align="left">2.18 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td align="left">2.72 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td align="left">2.82 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td align="left">2.84 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td align="left">2.42 &#x000b1; 0.50</td><td align="left">2.92 &#x000b1; 0.38</td><td align="left">0.0006*/&#x0003c; 0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Glucose (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">235.6 &#x000b1; 111.0</td><td align="left">290.4 &#x000b1; 136.6</td><td align="left">188.0 &#x000b1; 40.79</td><td align="left">175.8 &#x000b1; 24.67</td><td align="left">162.6 &#x000b1; 33.25</td><td align="left">151.2 &#x000b1; 18.20</td><td align="left">163.2 &#x000b1; 66.84</td><td align="left">186.6 &#x000b1; 26.54</td><td align="left">0.0630/0.5758</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bil-total (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">0.45 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td align="left">1.62 &#x000b1; 2.08</td><td align="left">0.68 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td align="left">1.10 &#x000b1; 0.54</td><td align="left">0.34 &#x000b1; 0.23</td><td align="left">0.94 &#x000b1; 0.55</td><td align="left">2.90 &#x000b1; 3.83</td><td align="left">1.08 &#x000b1; 0.65</td><td align="left">0.2987/0.3310</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bil-dams (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">0.60 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td align="left">1.34 &#x000b1; 1.69</td><td align="left">0.32 &#x000b1; 0.28</td><td align="left">1.06 &#x000b1; 0.38</td><td align="left">0.16 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td align="left">0.72 &#x000b1; 0.40</td><td align="left">2.08 &#x000b1; 2.23</td><td align="left">1.00 &#x000b1; 0.74</td><td align="left">0.1472/0.3799</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TG (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">120.4 &#x000b1; 18.72</td><td align="left">130.4 &#x000b1; 49.15</td><td align="left">106.8 &#x000b1; 28.92</td><td align="left">116.8 &#x000b1; 10.35</td><td align="left">106.9 &#x000b1; 37.42</td><td align="left">110.0 &#x000b1; 26.69</td><td align="left">128.2 &#x000b1; 45.10</td><td align="left">87.00 &#x000b1; 23.01</td><td align="left">0.5148/0.6195</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cholesterol (mg/dl)</td><td align="left">149.2 &#x000b1; 20.43</td><td align="left">158.6 &#x000b1; 23.66</td><td align="left">142.8 &#x000b1; 34.11</td><td align="left">149.6 &#x000b1; 28.36</td><td align="left">127.2 &#x000b1; 30.06</td><td align="left">115.4 &#x000b1; 17.21</td><td align="left">131.6 &#x000b1; 55.39</td><td align="left">121.0 &#x000b1; 17.00</td><td align="left">0.3004/0.9978</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>Note</italic>: The first serious of the p-value column shows ANOVA/ Kruskal-Wallis analysis result when male and female groups are grouped separately while the second when both are grouped together.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0075"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Post-hoc analysis</title><p id="par0115">Relative right kidney weight, AST and albumin values showed significant variations between treated and control groups. Groups treated with highest dose of the EO showed elevated level of AST value compared to control (mean difference of controls versus 400 mg/kg = -315.6, 95 % CI: &#x02212;610.3 to &#x02212;20.83). Significant difference in mean albumin level was observed among different treated groups. Albumin concentration in those treated with 200 mg/kg EO was significantly lower compared to all other treatment groups (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Post-hoc test for the sub-acute toxicity study.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0040">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Parameters</th><th align="left">Mean Diff.</th><th align="left">95 % CI of diff</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Relative right kidney weight</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Control vs 400 mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.1896</td><td align="left">0.04638, 0.3329</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">AST</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Control vs 400 mg/kg</td><td align="left">&#x02212;315.6</td><td align="left">&#x02212;610.3, &#x02212;20.83</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left">Albumin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Control vs 200 mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.4778</td><td align="left">0.1628, 0.7927</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;100 mg/kg vs 200 mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.5500</td><td align="left">0.2434, 0.8566</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;200 mg/kg vs 400 mg/kg</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.5200</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.8266, &#x02212;0.2134</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0080"><label>3.2.4</label><title>Sex variations</title><p id="par0120">Food consumption, clinical chemistry, liver weight, relative left kidney weight, relative right kidney weight, and urea as well as albumin levels were significantly higher in males compared to females (Supplementary file 1).</p></sec><sec id="sec0085"><label>3.2.5</label><title>Effect on histopathology</title><p id="par0125">Gross anatomical examination of the vital organs (liver, kidney, heart, lung and spleen) did not show gross pathological lesions in both acute and repeated-dose oral toxicity studies. Histopathological examinations revealed mild alterations in the kidney lymphocytic infiltrates at medium dose of EO. Photomicrographs of the liver and spleen showed normal morphological architecture in all different treatment groups (<xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).<fig id="fig0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Photomicrograph of liver, kidney and spleen in repeated-dose <italic>E. Kebericho</italic> EO oral toxicity study. All liver including female (from control to highest dose, 1&#x02013;4) and male (from control to highest dose 5-8) &#x02018;showed normal morphology architecture. &#x02018;All kidneys (9-16) showed normal morphology except medium dose treated female (200 mg/kg). &#x02018;Spleen of all groups (17&#x02013;24) showed normal morphology, H&#x00026;E, magnification 10&#x000d7;.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec0090"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="par0130">The present study revealed the relative safety of EO of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> in a mouse model. Acute toxicity and repeated-dose 28-day toxicity studies did not show significant physiological alterations. No death was observed up to the 2000 mg/kg dose, and hence <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EO could be considered Category 4 according to GHS classification [<xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Changes observed in body weight, relative organ weight, food consumption, clinical chemistry parameters and histopathology were not significant in 28-day repeated-dose toxicity studies. However relative right kidney weight, AST and albumin levels in treated groups showed significant variations compared to controls. Food consumption, relative liver weight, relative left kidney weight, relative right kidney weight, and urea as well as albumin concentrations were observed to be higher in males compared to females.</p><p id="par0135">Single oral dose of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EO up to 2000 mg/kg did not show significant treatment-related morbidity in female mice, though piloerection, muscle spasm and apathy were observed immediately after administration. Body weight increment was observed in those treated with 300 mg/kg EO compared to those which received 2000 mg/kg. The LD<sub>50</sub> of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EO could be considered greater than 2000 mg/kg as no death was noted up to this dose. This LD<sub>50</sub> is lower compared to <italic>Ocimum gratissimum</italic> EO (1410 mg/kg [<xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] but higher to that of <italic>Eucalyptus citriodora</italic> EO (2337.9&#x02013;2967.5 mg/kg) [<xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. On the other hand, <italic>Litsea cubeba</italic> EO (used as ingredient of food, cosmetics, and cigarettes) showed oral LD<sub>50</sub> of approximately 4000 mg/kg [<xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. No histopathological changes, or biochemical alterations or skin irritation were not observed Cymbopogon citratus EO up to dose of 2000 mg/kg [<xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Similarly, black caraway essential oil did not affect the immune, blood system, body enzymes and vital organs of the body [<xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. On the other hand, Citrus aurantifolia EO showed mild hematotoxicity, nephrotoxicity and hepatotoxicity among the 100 mg/kg and 500 mg/kg dose groups [<xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p><p id="par0140">Constant body weight and food consumption pattern was observed for combined groups with significant variations in gender groups which is in line to previous findings [<xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Constant weight pattern was observed in control and 100 mg/kg EO treated female groups. Significant weight loss was seen in 200 mg/kg and 400 mg/kg EO treated female groups indicating reduced tolerability to increased dose. Significant weight gain in all male groups, increased food consumption pattern in controls and those treated with 100 mg/kg, and constant consumption pattern in medium and high dose treated male groups could explain less sensitivity of males to toxicants compared to females [<xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The present finding is in agreement with international guidelines and results of most studies which revealed that males tolerate better compared to females [<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Relative body weight in most of the tested organs did not show significant variations except mean relative organ weight of right kidney where highest dose treated groups varied significantly compared to controls in concentration dependent toxicity fashion.</p><p id="par0145">Most clinical chemistry values did not show significant variations among different treatment groups, except albumin concentration and AST values. Elevated AST level was observed in high-dose treated group compared to control group. AST and ALT levels are widely used as sensitive markers to evaluate toxic manifestations of liver [<xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Increased serum ALT level could be attributed to hypertrophy and other disorders of the liver yet with possible extra hepatic sources [<xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], while an increased AST level could indicate hepatic cell damage. Elevated AST level in this study was observed without histological abnormalities. ALT is a cytoplasmic enzyme present in the liver, and it significantly increased during hepatocellular damage [<xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], while AST is present extra-cellularly in various tissues including heart, skeletal muscles, liver, kidneys, pancreas, and erythrocytes [<xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. AST is released from multiples of cells in response to cellular damage or change in membrane permeability. Hence, as ALT is a more sensitive biomarker of hepatic damage compared to AST, an elevated AST without change in ALT level could not necessarily indicate an insult in the liver.</p><p id="par0150">Lower albumin concentration observed among medium dose treated groups may be associated with the observed lymphocytic infiltrates which could confer some level of renal toxicity in medium-dose treated group. Renal inflammatory responses could increase renal excretion of albumin [<xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] consequently decreasing serum albumin level. Renal toxicity dose-response curve in this study appears to be concentration-dependent peaking in the middle, while toxicity observed with middle-dose compared to a higher or a lower dose requires confirmation from a large sample size.</p><p id="par0155">Sex variations on food consumption, relative liver weight, relative left kidney weight, relative right kidney weight and urea and albumin concentrations could not be explained based on this study. Most parameters showed higher values in males compared to females. Similarly, higher TG, ALP, ALT, and glucose levels were reported in male Sprague-Dawley rats compared to females [<xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Male mice had also been reported to have higher TG, cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein cholesterol, glucose, and amylase values [<xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p><p id="par0160">Compounds with similar chemistry can trigger common mechanisms of toxicity and toxicity profile at the level of organism, organ, tissue, and cell [<xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In the current study, the EO largely displayed similar toxicity profile to most EOs from other plant EOs. Turmeric EO oral administration up to the dose of 5 g/kg body weight is safe to rats [<xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Thymus vulgaris L EO was well tolerated up to the dose of 2000 mg/kg in acute exposure, and the 28-day sub-acute toxicity study revealed that the no-observed-adverse effect level (NOAEL) was greater than 250 mg/kg/day [<xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. <italic>Citrus aurantifolia</italic> posed mild hematotoxic, nephrotoxic and hepatotoxic effects in doses of 100 mg/kg and 500 mg/kg in 60-day repeated dose study [<xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Mild toxicity observed in the latter case could be attributed to longer treatment; 28 days versus 60 days. Long term exposure to moderate concentrations of mixtures of terpenes could cause possible adverse health effect [<xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Ursolic acid a pentacyclic triterpenoid which can be isolated from different plant EO did not cause significant toxicity [<xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The biological effects (either therapeutic or toxic) of EOs could be because of the pro-oxidant effect in cells [<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and display more or less similar effect because of their structural similarity [<xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p><p id="par0165">Plant medicines are blindly considered safe without any scientific evidence but could cause significant damage to public health. Equating &#x0201c;natural to safe&#x0201d; does not work where dozens or more poisons are coming from natural compounds [<xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In most developing countries, people use plants from their courtyards as well as street markets without any valid knowledge of their safety. Despite significant numbers of people using herbal medicine for their primary health care, there is paucity of studies on safety of herbal medicine. Clinical studies can be commenced in humans, after assessment of quality, efficacy and safety of herbal medicines in animal models [<xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. With growing use of natural derived substances from plants all over the world, it is now wise not to rely only on the traditional beliefs; explanatory and reasonable preclinical and clinical studies, similar to the current one, are required and should be considered mandatory in gaining trustworthy findings.</p></sec><sec id="sec0095"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="par0170">This study provided comprehensive evidence on the safety of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> EO and confirmed the relative safety in acute and repeated-dose conditions. No significant morbidity or mortality was observed up to 2000 mg/kg. The repeated-dose toxicity study demonstrated no observable behavioral adverse effect or damages on gross anatomy. Histological changes did not occur in the liver and spleen. The indifferent finding of AST and histopathology at highest dose and the observation of some level of renal adverse effect at low dose but not higher or lower dose warrants further investigation in larger sample sizes. In general, EO of <italic>E. kebericho</italic> M. could be considered well tolerated in acute and repeated-dose exposure. Further, teratogenic, mutagenic, carcinogenic, and sub-chronic and chronic toxicity studies are warranted.</p></sec><sec id="sec0100"><title>Authors&#x02019; statement</title><p id="par0175">Serawit Deyno conceived the research idea and drafted the manuscript. Mesfin Asefa Tola read and interpreted the histopathological findings. Joel Bazira, Eyasu Makonnen, Paul E. Alele supervised and mentored the research work. All authors revised, edited and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec0105"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="par0180">The experimental protocol was approved by the Research Ethics Committee (REC) of Mbarara University of Science and Technology, Uganda. The protocol was approved and registered with Uganda National Council for Science and Technology (UNCST) with reference number HS398ES.</p></sec><sec id="sec0110"><title>Funding</title><p id="par0185">This study was funded by <funding-source id="gs0005">Pharm-Biotechnology and Traditional Medicine Centre (PHARMBIOTRAC)</funding-source>, <funding-source id="gs0010">African Center of Excellence II (ACE-II) Project</funding-source>. The funder contributed research money and stipends (SD) but was not involved in planning and implementation of the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec0115"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p id="par0190">SD conceived the research idea. MAT read and interpreted the histopathological findings. JB, EM and PEA supervised and mentored the research work. SD drafted the manuscript. All authors revised, edited and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec0120"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="par0195">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec0125"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="par0200">The data supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="par0205">The authors report no declarations of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wardle</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional, complementary and alternative medicine use in Sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic review</article-title><source>BMJ Glob. Heal.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e000895</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome inference and systems approaches to polypharmacology and drug discovery in herbal medicine</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2016.10.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhifi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellili</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jazi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahloul</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mnif</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils&#x02019; chemical characterization and investigation of some biological activities: a critical review</article-title><source>Medicines</source><volume>3</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>25</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakkali</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Idaomar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological effects of essential oils&#x02013;a review</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van de Braak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leijten</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Essential Oils and Oleoresins: a Survey in the Netherlands and Other Major Markets in the European Union</chapter-title><year>1999</year><publisher-name>CBI, Cent. Promot. Imports from Dev. Countries</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rotterdam</publisher-loc><fpage>116</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils: their antibacterial properties and potential applications in foods&#x02014;A review</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</source><volume>94</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15246235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deyno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mtewa</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hymete</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makonnen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazira</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alele</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils as topical anti-infective agents: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Complement. Ther. Med.</source><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102224</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gedif</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>H.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of medicinal plants in self-care in rural central Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12860301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damtie</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thymus species in Ethiopia: distribution, medicinal value, economic benefit, current status and threatening factors</article-title><source>Ethiop. J. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demissew</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A description of some essential oil bearing plants in Ethiopia and their indigenous uses</article-title><source>J. Essent. Oil Res.</source><volume>5</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>479</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abera</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants used in traditional medicine in Jimma zone, Southwest Ethiopia</article-title><source>Ethiop. J. Health Sci.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2003</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demissew</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Aromatic Plants of Ethiopia</chapter-title><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Shama Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kloos</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menberu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadele</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debebe</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zealiyas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadele</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debella</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional medicines sold by vendors in Merkato, Addis Ababa: aspects of their utilization, trade, and changes between 1973 and 2014</article-title><source>Ethiop. J. Heal. Dev.</source><volume>28</volume><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teklehaymanot</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used by people in Zegie Peninsula, Northwestern Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Ethnobiol. Ethnomed.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-3-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17355645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wondimu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asfaw</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelbessa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants around &#x02018;Dheeraa&#x02019;town, Arsi Zone, Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>112</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17418987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wubetu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abula</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dejenu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnopharmacologic survey of medicinal plants used to treat human diseases by traditional medical practitioners in Dega Damot district, Amhara, Northwestern Ethiopia</article-title><source>BMC Res. Notes</source><volume>10</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28420410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yigezu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haile</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayen</surname><given-names>W.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnoveterinary medicines in four districts of Jimma zone, Ethiopia: cross sectional survey for plant species and mode of use</article-title><source>BMC Vet. Res.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>76</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-6148-10-76</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24679045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teklehaymanot</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medhin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge and use of medicinal plants by people around Debre Libanos monastery in Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.11.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tariku</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hymete</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohloff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro evaluation of antileishmanial activity and toxicity of essential oils of Artemisia absinthium and Echinops kebericho</article-title><source>Chem. Biodivers.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21480507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioassay-guided isolation of dehydrocostus lactone from Saussurea lappa: a new targeted cytosolic thioredoxin reductase anticancer agent</article-title><source>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</source><volume>607</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27545438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dehydrocostus lactone, a natural sesquiterpene lactone, suppresses the biological characteristics of glioma, through inhibition of the NF-&#x003ba;B/COX-2 signaling pathway by targeting IKK&#x003b2;</article-title><source>Am. J. Cancer Res.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1270</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28670490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dehydrocostus lactone suppresses proliferation of human chronic myeloid leukemia cells through Bcr/Abl&#x02010;JAK/STAT signaling pathways</article-title><source>J. Cell. Biochem.</source><volume>118</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>3381</fpage><lpage>3390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28300289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential anti-cancer activities and mechanisms of costunolide and dehydrocostuslactone</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>10888</fpage><lpage>10906</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25984608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duraipandiyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Harbi</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignacimuthu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthukumar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of sesquiterpene lactones isolated from traditional medicinal plant, Costus speciosus (Koen ex. Retz.) Sm</article-title><source>BMC Complement. Altern. Med.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22397713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belay</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tariku</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hymete</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yalemtsehay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Antibacterial Activity of Five Oil Bearing Ethiopian Medicinal Plants against Eleven Pathogenic Bacterial Strains</chapter-title><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5958/j.0975-4261.3.4.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivana</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Phytochemische und antimikrobielle Untersuchung an Echinops kebericho Mesfin</chapter-title><comment>M.Sc Thesis</comment><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jemberie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadie</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enyew</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debebe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repellent activity of plant essential oil extracts against malaria vector Anopheles arabiensis Patton (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>ENTOMON</source><volume>41</volume><year>2016</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://entomon.in/index.php/Entomon/article/view/166" id="intr0010">http://entomon.in/index.php/Entomon/article/view/166</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debella</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taye</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melaku</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taye</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of some Ethiopian medicinal plants for mosquito larvicidal effects and phytochemical constituents</article-title><source>Pharmacol Online</source><volume>3</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>243</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deyno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tola</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hymete</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazira</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makonnen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alele</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and sub-acute toxicity of Echinops kebericho decoction in rats</article-title><source>BMC Complement. Med. Ther.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32020865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>OECD_423</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Test No. 423: Acute Oral Toxicity - Acute Toxic Class Method</chapter-title><year>2002</year><publisher-name>OECD</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1787/9789264071001-en</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>OECD_407</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Test No. 407: Repeated Dose 28-day Oral Toxicity Study in Rodents</chapter-title><year>2008</year><publisher-name>OECD</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1787/9789264070684-en</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0160"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonder</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 1996 guide for the care and use of laboratory animals</article-title><source>ILAR J.</source><volume>38</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11528046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilkenny</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuthill</surname><given-names>I.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The ARRIVE Guidelines Checklist Animal Research: Reporting in Vivo Experiments</chapter-title><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0170"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bitew</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hymete</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genus echinops: phytochemistry and biological activities: a review</article-title><source>Front. Pharmacol.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0175"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>UN</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Globally Harmonized System of Classification and Labelling of Chemicals (GHS)</chapter-title><year>2005</year><publisher-name>United Nations Publications, United Nations Publications</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0180"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orafidiya</surname><given-names>L.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agbani</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwalewa</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelusola</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyedapo</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the acute and sub-chronic toxicity of the essential oil of Ocimum gratissimum L. leaf</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><volume>11</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14971724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0185"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>W.L.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camur&#x000e7;a-Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>A.L.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>I.T.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J.M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>H.C.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo Filho</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevilaqua</surname><given-names>C.M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of free and nanoencapsulated Eucalyptus citriodora essential oils on sheep gastrointestinal nematodes and toxicity for mice</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol.</source><volume>204</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24929446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0190"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>G.-L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and genetic toxicity of essential oil extracted from Litsea cubeba (Lour.) Pers</article-title><source>J. Food Prot.</source><volume>68</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15771186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0195"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lulekal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesfaye</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebrechristos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dires</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenebe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zegeye</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feleke</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassahun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiferaw</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical analysis and evaluation of skin irritation, acute and sub-acute toxicity of Cymbopogon citratus essential oil in mice and rabbits</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2019.11.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0200"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabarraei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parvizi</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golshahi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>keshavarz-Tarikhi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the acute and sub-acute toxicity of the black caraway seed essential oil in Wistar rats</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2019.08.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0205"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adokoh</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asante</surname><given-names>D.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acheampong</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotsuchibashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Armah</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirikyi</surname><given-names>I.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gmakame</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul-Rauf</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical profile and in vivo toxicity evaluation of unripe Citrus aurantifolia essential oil</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2019.06.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31372347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0210"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>OECD_425</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Test No. 425: Acute Oral Toxicity: Up-and-Down Procedure</chapter-title><year>2008</year><publisher-name>OECD</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1787/9789264071049-en</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0215"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mennecozzi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landesmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palosaari</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in liver toxicity&#x02014;Do female and male human primary hepatocytes react differently to toxicants in vitro?</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0122786</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0220"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zopf</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabe</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neubert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gassmann</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rascher</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brune</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dormann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Women encounter ADRs more often than do men</article-title><source>Eur. J. Clin. Pharmacol.</source><volume>64</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>999</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0225"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schomaker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The current state of serum biomarkers of hepatotoxicity</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><volume>245</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tox.2007.11.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18291570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0230"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Center</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpretation of liver enzymes</article-title><source>Vet. Clin. North Am. Small Anim. Pract.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17336677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0235"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanisms relating to increases in plasma enzymes and isoenzymes in diseases of animals</article-title><source>Vet. Clin. Pathol.</source><volume>12</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0240"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishola</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>van der Giezen</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahnel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldschmeding</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koomans</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joles</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In mice, proteinuria and renal inflammatory responses to albumin overload are strain-dependent</article-title><source>Nephrol. Dial. Transplant.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfi303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16326737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0245"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petterino</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Argentino-Storino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical chemistry and haematology historical data in control Sprague-Dawley rats from pre-clinical toxicity studies</article-title><source>Exp. Toxicol. Pathol.</source><volume>57</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16343876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0250"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lillie</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Temple</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Florence</surname><given-names>L.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reference values for young normal Sprague-Dawley rats: weight gain, hematology and clinical chemistry</article-title><source>Hum. Exp. Toxicol.</source><volume>15</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8863053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0255"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of sex and age on serum biochemical reference ranges in C57BL/6J mice</article-title><source>Comp. Med.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/aalas/cm/2004/00000054/00000002/art00006" id="intr0015">https://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/aalas/cm/2004/00000054/00000002/art00006</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15134363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0260"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerberick</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The practice of structure activity relationships (SAR) in toxicology</article-title><source>Toxicol. Sci.</source><volume>56</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0265"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liju</surname><given-names>V.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeena</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuttan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and subchronic toxicity as well as mutagenic evaluation of essential oil from turmeric (Curcuma longa L)</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><volume>53</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23201370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0270"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas-Armas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo-Acevedo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomino-Pacheco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro-Luna</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Cevallos</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Justil-Guerrero</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilario-Vargas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera-Calder&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute and repeated 28-day oral dose toxicity studies of Thymus vulgaris L. essential oil in rats</article-title><source>Toxicol. Res.</source><volume>35</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>225</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31341551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0275"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tisserand</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balacs</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Essential Oil Safety</chapter-title><year>1996</year><publisher-name>New York Churchill Livingst</publisher-name><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>157</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0280"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geerlofs</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Z.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repeated dose (90 days) oral toxicity study of ursolic acid in Han-Wistar rats</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2020.04.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0285"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R.S.H.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Toxicology of Chemical Mixtures: Case Studies, Mechanisms, and Novel Approaches</chapter-title><year>2016</year><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0290"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aschwanden</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbs for health, but how safe are they?</article-title><source>Bull. World Health Organ.</source><volume>79</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>692</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0295"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety evaluation of commonly used Chinese herbal medicines during pregnancy in mice</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2448</fpage><lpage>2456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22647451</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0135" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="par0220"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="upi0005"><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="par0210">This study was supported by PhD study grant under Pharm-biotechnology and Traditional Medicine Center of Excellence, World Bank project. We would like to acknowledge PHARMBIOTRAC World Bank African center of excellence II (ACE-II) project for making this work possible.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="sec0130" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="par0215">Supplementary material related to this article can be found, in the online version, at doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxrep.2020.12.027" id="intr0005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxrep.2020.12.027</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>