<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to other storage proteins, dioscorin also exhibits enzymatic activities, such as carbonic anhydrase, trypsin inhibitor, dehydroascorbate reductase, monodehydroascorbate reductase and lectin activities [
 <xref rid="B152-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B159-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. The antioxidant potential of dioscorin purified from yam tuber has also been reported [
 <xref rid="B160-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B161-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>] examined the antioxidant activities of dioscorin in the tubers of two 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species (
 <italic>D. alata L</italic>. and 
 <italic>D. batatas</italic> [presently known as 
 <italic>D. polystachya</italic>]) using (2,2-diphenyl-1-picryl-hydrazyl-hydrate) and hydroxyl radicals scavenging activity assay, reducing power test and anti-lipid peroxidation test. Their findings revealed that dioscorins from the two yam species exhibited different scavenging activities against DPPH (1, 1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl) and hydroxyl radicals, with 
 <italic>D. alata</italic> dioscorin showing higher antioxidant and scavenging activities as compared to that of 
 <italic>D. polystachya</italic>. This variation is ascribed to the variation in amino acid composition and protein conformations [
 <xref rid="B161-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Dioscorin has been reported to inhibit the activities of angiotensin converting enzymes, thus suggesting its potential for control of hypertension [
 <xref rid="B162-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. In addition, Fu et al. [
 <xref rid="B163-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>] demonstrated the potential of dioscorin isolated from 
 <italic>D. alata</italic> as a Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4) activator as well as an inducer of the cytokine expression in macrophage through TLR4-signalling pathways, thus, resulting in the activation of innate and adaptive immune system. 
</p>
