<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Carotenoids are relatively complex molecules included in the group of orange, yellow and red lipo-soluble pigments synthesised by plants, algae, bacteria and fungi. More than 750 different structures have been described, some of which (α and β-carotenes, β-cryptoxanthin) are considered provitamin A as they can be transformed into retinol in the intestine or liver (vitamin A). To act as provitamin A, a carotenoid must contain a β-ionone structure. Carotenoids are included in the most prominent lipophilic antioxidants group. They protect organisms from photosensitised formation and 
 <sup>1</sup>O
 <sub>2</sub> accumulation through the absorption of excitation energy and its dissipation as heat. For this reason, they play an important role in ultraviolet- and light-stress damage. Their efficiency as antioxidant and scavengers of ROS, especially single molecular oxygen and peroxyl radicals, means they play a key role in the prevention and treatment of diseases related to oxidative stress and ageing, including AMD (Khoo et al., 2019; Sandmann, 2019). Humans cannot synthesise carotenoids, which must be obtained from diet or using supplements. Although they are widespread in nature, only 40 are present in the human diet and only half can be found in tissues and biological fluids. The major carotenoids present in human blood and tissues are α- and β-carotene, lycopene, lutein, zeaxanthin and β-cryptoxanthin,, of which, lutein, zeaxanthin and their stereoisomer meso-zeaxanthin selectively accumulate in the retina of the eye to enrich the macular pigment of the central macula area. In the central fovea of the human retina, lutein and zeaxanthin reach concentrations between 0.1 and 1 mM, which is about 1000-fold higher than in other tissues. The inner plexiform layer, Henle’s fiber layer and Muller cells are the places where maximal accumulation occurs (Jia et al., 2017; Buscemi et al., 2018). The double bound position in one of the end rings creates differences in their activities and functions, which are correlated with their retinal spatial distribution. In the inner macula, the concentration of zeaxanthin, which is a much more effective antioxidant, is about twice that of lutein. Conversely, lutein is the dominant component in the peripheral retina (Jia et al., 2017). Meso-zeaxanthin, a substance that is much better capable of quenching oxygen radicals, is considered a metabolite of lutein and its presence in ocular tissues indicates its conversion at the eye level (Bungau et al., 2019). Lutein has a greater filtering efficiency and zeaxanthin is better at preventing UV-induced light lipid peroxidation (Jia et al., 2017). Macular carotenoids are considered the most potent antioxidants to protect against the development of AMD and also other eye disorders. These substances are believed to protect the retina in several ways: filtering high energy and short wave-length blue light; protecting the underlying photoreceptor cell layer from light-induced damage; neutralizing oxidation reactions in photoreceptor cells (Berstein, 2016). It has been reported that lutein, zeaxanthin and astaxanthin can also modulate other signaling cellular pathways in retinal pigment epithelium cells. In ARPE-19 cells, these substances can activate the nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 pathway, thereby protecting the cells against oxidative damage by upregulation of the antioxidant system. The nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 pathway regulates the transcription of genes (NQO1, GCLm, and HO-1) with antioxidant effects and related to antioxidant active enzymes expression such as superoxide dismutase, NQO1, HO-1 and catalase, or to glutathione or thioredoxin metabolism. Some evidence exists that lutein can reduce inflammation in these cells by protecting the proteosoma against photo-oxidative damage and the modulation of the expression of inflammation-related genes like IL-8 (Frede, 2017). Moreover, carotenoids can preserve optimal visual performance by reducing age-related lipofuscin formation in the retinal pigment epithelium. Lipofuscin is a protein-lipid mixture integrated by metabolites from vitamin A and products from lipid peroxidation. This compound induces mitochondria damage and apoptosis in retinal pigment epithelium cell cultures. It has been found that lutein and zeaxanthin diminish the amount of lipofuscin formed 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and in culture cells (Berstein, 2016). These substances can also abolish the elevated expression of matrix metalloproteinase-2 (MMP-2) and tissue inhibitor metalloproteinase-2 (TIMP-2), observed in H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> treated ARPE-19 cells, and are able to contribute beneficially to matrix homeostasis altered in AMD involved in oxidative stress (Jia et al., 2017). While most research works seem to have confirmed a relation between xanthophylls intake and an increase in their serum and macular concentrations, not all of them have observed a benefit in preventing and treating AMD. Human nutritional studies indicate that lutein and zeaxanthin administration may improve visual performance by enhancing contrast sensitivity, and by reducing glare disability and photo stress recovery (Khoo et al., 2019). Although several studies have shown the protective effects of these carotenoids in AMD, in others the results have been negative because these substances did not delayed the progression of AMD (Evans and Lawrenson, 2017; Khoo et al. 2019, Bungau et al., 2019). Age-Related Eye Disease Study 2 (AREDS 2) is a multicentre, randomized placebo-controlled study designed to demonstrate whether supplementation with lutein and zeaxanthin can slow the AMD progression rate. This study shows that lutein (10 mg/d) and zeaxathin (2 mg/d) supplementation intake are inversely associated with the prevalence of neovascular AMD, geographical atrophy, and large or extensive intermediate drusen. However, a comparison with placebo demonstrates no statistically significant reduction in progression to advanced AMD (AREDS, 2014). The significant dose range of lutein intervention to improve visual function in the AMD population is 2.5 to 20 mg/d, with 2.5 mg/d being the lowest effective dose. The recommended dietary intake of lutein supplements does not exceed 6 mg/d in discontinuous treatment (Jia et al., 2017). It is noteworthy that although AREDS formulation initially contained β-carotene as an antioxidant substance, it had to be replaced with lutein and zeaxanthin because of a potentially increased incidence of lung cancers, mostly in participants who previously smoked. For this reason, lutein and zeaxanthin should be considered a better option than β-carotene in preventing the development of AMD (AREDS, 2014). Another study concludes that lutein-rich and zeaxanthin-rich diets may protect against intermediate AMD in female patients under the age of 75 years. The Blue Mountain Eye study reports that higher dietary lutein and zeaxanthin intake reduce the risk of incident early or neovascular AMD over 5 and 10 years (Sin, 2013). A systematic Cochrane review, published in 2017 and included six studies, indicates that lutein intake (with or without zeaxanthin) induces only a slight effect in reducing progression to late AMD, neovascular AMD and geographic atrophy compared to a placebo (Evans and Lawrenson, 2017). It is also worth mentioning the possible benefit of the synergic association of these carotenoids, mainly lutein, with other antioxidants such as polyphenols and ω-3 LCPUFAs (Yanai et al., 2018). In a cross-sectional case-controlled study, the authors find that lower circulatory levels of carotenoids and omega-3 PUFAs, and higher levels of omega-6 PUFAs, oleic acid and saturated fatty acids, increase the odds ratio of developing neovascular AMD (Ng, 2017). No adverse reactions to short-term or long-term lutein/zeaxanthin dietary and/or supplement normal intake are reported. However, researchers note that smokers who take high lutein supplement doses (&gt;10 mg/d) are at increased risk of lung cancer. Yellow spots may also appear on skin during the long-term intake of higher doses (≥ 15 mg/d) of this substance (Jia et al., 2017). No 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> mutagenic and cytotoxic activities are observed (Ravikrishnan, 2011). The approved Acceptable Daily Intake (ADI) values for lutein are 1 mg/kg per day (EFSA- European Food Safety Authority) and 2 mg/kg per day (JECFA- Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives) (Jia et al., 2017). Vitamin A plays also an important role in retinal health because some carotenoids can be cleaved 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> into vitamin A active compounds through beta-carotene oxygenase 1 (BCO1) pathway. Vitamin A is a fat-soluble substance found in three different oxidative states: alcohol (retinol), acid (retinoic) and aldehyde (retinal). It normally exists in the body as retinol (Barlett and Eperjesi, 2004). Epidemiological and interventional studies, but not all, show that a significant increase in the intake of fruit and vegetables rich in vitamin A lowers the risk for any AMD stage (Khoo et al., 2019). Excessive vitamin A intake is potentially toxic to the liver and other tissues, and is also associated with intracranial hypertension (Barlett and Eperjesi, 2004).
</p>
