<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) are important and ubiquitous soil microorganisms that form symbioses with many plant species in terrestrial ecosystems 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Rillig1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Interestingly, AMF also influence invasive plants’ competition 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Richardson1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Pringle1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. For example, invasive Asian knapweed (
 <italic>Centaurea maculosa</italic>) in North America is able to tap into and benefit from the mycorrhizal network linking native plant roots 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Marler1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Carey1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Invasive 
 <italic>Solidago canadensis</italic> in China can alter the AMF composition in the introduced range in ways that promote its competition against native plants 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. In some cases, the secondary compounds released by invasive plants disrupt the symbioses between the AMF and native plants. For example, secondary chemicals released by the invasive plant 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic>, which cannot form symbioses with the AMF, disrupted the symbioses between native canopy tree seedlings and AMF 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Stinson1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. A specific flavonoid fraction released by 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> has a far stronger inhibitory effect on AMF in the invaded soil than in its original soils 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Callaway1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Additionally, the secondary compounds from 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> not only inhibited AMF hyphal growth and spore germination 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Cantor1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> but also altered the AMF community associated with native sugar maple seedlings 
 <xref rid="pone.0097163-Barto1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.
</p>
