<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Under prolonged cold conditions, the brown fat size and activity increases, a term called BAT “recruitment.” BAT recruitment is associated with increased proliferation and differentiation of BAT precursor cells. Exposure to cold also increases BAT volume and activity in humans (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Blondin et al., 2014</xref>) and also in individuals with obesity and type 2 diabetes (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hanssen et al., 2016</xref>). Increased sympathetic nervous system (SNS) activity, including on cold exposure, is a primary mechanism of BAT activation. Activated SNS releases norepinephrine which acts on the beta-adrenergic receptors on the BAT. In addition to epinephrine and norepinephrine, dopamine stimulation of brown adipocytes was also associated with increased oxygen consumption, UCP1 protein and mitochondrial mass (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kohlie et al., 2017</xref>). Prolonged exposure of mice to cold not only leads to brown fat recruitment but also to appearance of white adipocytes containing multilocular fat droplets and UCP1-expressing mitochondria – a process called “browning” of the white adipose tissue (WAT) depots. Brown-like adipocytes in WAT can arise from several origins – through the development of distinct subpopulations or through the trans-differentiation of differentiated white adipocytes (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Okamatsu-Ogura et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, the “brite” cells may also develop through the bi-directional interconversion of some cells between brite and white adipocyte phenotypes (
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rosenwald et al., 2013</xref>). In spite of many molecular similarities between the BAT and brite cells, there is a differential expression of certain genes between BAT and brite cell. These include metabolic proteins (e.g., Slc27a1), inflammatory proteins (e.g., CD40 and CD137) and transcription factors (Tbx15 and Zic1) (
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Waldén et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wu et al., 2012</xref>). The gene expression profile of BAT in human infants resembles that of the classical BAT (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lidell et al., 2013</xref>), though they also express typical brite marker proteins TBX1 and CD137 (
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sharp et al., 2012</xref>). The BAT in the neck of adult humans contains a mixture of classical brown and brite cells (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jespersen et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lidell et al., 2013</xref>). While the expression of browning genes in mice is greater in subcutaneous WAT (scWAT) compared to visceral WAT (vWAT), an opposite pattern of browning gene expression with vWAT having higher expression than scWAT was observed in humans (
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zuriaga et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
