<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Agilent Technology 7820A (AGILENT Scientific, Santa Clara, CA, USA), coupled with mass spectrometer MSD 5975 and equipped with a capillary column DB WAX (30 m × 250 μm × 0.25 μm) was used. The carrier gas was helium with a mass flow of 1 mL/min. In order to separate the compounds, the following GC oven program was used: 40 °C for 1 min, 5 °C min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> to 210 °C for 5 min. The injector and ion source temperatures were 250 and 150 °C, respectively. The injection volume was 1 μL of each pure oil or mixture, without solvent with a split ratio 1:20. One run for each sample was performed. The NIST spectra library has been used to identify the volatile compounds. Identification was made by comparison of their mass spectra with those stored in NIST 02, Wiley 275 libraries. The percentages of individual components were calculated based on GC peak areas without using correction factors. The linear retention indices (LRI) were determined in relation to a homologous series of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkanes (C8–C24) under the same operating conditions and calculated according to Van den Dool and Kratz [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-23-00185" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>] Formula (1):
 <disp-formula id="FD1-molecules-23-00185" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">LRI</mi>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mn class="mn">100</mn>
     <mo class="mo">×</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">n</mi>
     <mo class="mo">+</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mn class="mn">100</mn>
       <mo class="mo">×</mo>
       <mo class="mo">(</mo>
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</mi>
        <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">x</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</mi>
        <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">x</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo class="mo">)</mo>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</mi>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">n</mi>
         <mo class="mo">+</mo>
         <mo class="mo">1</mo>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</mi>
        <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">n</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where t
 <sub class="sub">n</sub> and t
 <sub class="sub">n+1</sub> are the retention times of the reference 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkane hydrocarbons eluting immediately before and after chemical compound “X” and t
 <sub class="sub">x</sub> is the retention time of compound “X”.
</p>
