<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>M. alba</italic>, with its biologically beneficial polyphenolic compounds, is a suitable functional food ingredient. Unfortunately, the poor stability and heat and light sensitivity of phenolic compounds are a widely known weakness [
 <xref rid="B144-foods-10-00689" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. There is evidence that the stability of 
 <italic>M. alba</italic> polyphenols can be destroyed by environmental factors, including pH, temperature, and oxygen [
 <xref rid="B145-foods-10-00689" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. These downsides have limited their commercial applications, especially for hot-processed foods, as reported in Cheng et al. [
 <xref rid="B146-foods-10-00689" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>] and their previous studies. Many studies have investigated methods to stabilize and protect polyphenols from degradation. Microencapsulation is an effective technique to ameliorate the unstable physiochemical properties of a substance or compound, including their solubility and dispensability [
 <xref rid="B147-foods-10-00689" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. Xu et al. [
 <xref rid="B145-foods-10-00689" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>] stated that 
 <italic>M. alba</italic> polyphenol (MP) stability in dried minced pork slices was significantly enhanced after gum Arabic microencapsulation with a core/wall ratio of 1:90. After 20 days of storage, the microencapsulated polyphenol (MMP) pork slices showed lower loss of total phenolic, flavonoid, and anthocyanin contents (15.10%, 16.87%, and 19.88%, respectively), with higher recovery (by 1.35-fold, 1.26-fold, and 1.16-fold, respectively). Moreover, both MP and MMP exhibited a synergistic inhibitory effect on protein and lipid oxidation, with MMP showing better oxidation and color stability. In addition, Cheng et al. [
 <xref rid="B146-foods-10-00689" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>] found 1% β-cyclodextrin MMP significantly improved the dried minced pork slices’ recovery of total phenolic, flavonoid, and anthocyanin contents as compared to the nonencapsulated product by 5.6%, 5.8%, and 18.6%, respectively. Furthermore, as compared to the control, the MP-added pork slices showed 1.03-fold higher FRAP and 1.18-fold higher ABTS▪+ scavenging ability, whereas the β-cyclodextrin MMP showed 1.2-fold and 3.58-fold increases, respectively. These positive effects were attributed to β-cyclodextrin’s protective ability on phenolic compounds. However, the degradation of certain compounds such as quercetin, cryptochlorogenic acid, and caffeic acid, were not effectively avoided, presumably due to the difference in structures, thermochemical stabilities, and reaction modes between the compounds and β-cyclodextrin.
</p>
