<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many volatile compounds commonly found in essential oils have been assessed for antibacterial activity, but their effectiveness varies depending on the bacterium. For example, (-)-limonene (which is found in similar amounts in both resins used in this study), inhibits the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, but does not inhibit the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] (two bacteria commonly found in fruit fly gut microbiotas [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]). This significantly reduces the amount of data we have to determine the antibacterial activity of the two resins: only six of the 23 compounds of interest—carvacrol, carvacrol methyl ether, and 3-carene, (-)-terpin-4-ol, sabinene, and α-pinene—have been studied, and their antibacterial effectiveness has only been assessed against 1 (
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum)</italic> of the many bacteria (at least 44 genera) found in our fruit fly gut microbiotas (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s012" class="xref">S6 Table</xref>). In our analysis, we only identified the gut microbiota bacteria to the genus level; however the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> was found in our samples and 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic> is a very common species in a fruit fly gut [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus sylvestris</italic> resin is enriched relative to 
 <italic class="italic">W</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nobilis</italic> resin in carvacrol, carvacrol methyl ether, and 3-carene: carvacrol and carvacrol methyl ether inhibit 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic>; and 3-carene does not inhibit 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">Wollemia nobilis</italic> resin is enriched relative to 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">sylvestris</italic> resin in (-)-terpin-4-ol, sabinene, and α-pinene: (-)-terpin-4-ol inhibits 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic>; sabinene and α-pinene do not inhibit 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic>. These results only illustrate a tiny fraction of the complex chemical interactions between the resin and gut microbiota activity, and they are therefore inconclusive. Based on this we once again cannot determine which resin should have a stronger influence on decay due to the interaction of volatile compounds and gut microbiota activity.
</p>
