<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mixtures of volatile compounds may also inhibit bacterial activity, and so we compared the resin composition to the composition of essential oils that do or do not inhibit the activity of 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic>. As with investigating the compounds individually, this only reflects a small proportion of the complexity: only 10 compounds were included to describe the chemical composition of each sample; and the samples were tested against only one component of the fruit fly gut microbiota (
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum)</italic>. Multiple correspondence analysis (MCA) does completely separate the essential oil samples into those that do and do not inhibit 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic> activity (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s006" class="xref">S6 Fig</xref>). However, the two resin samples do not fall into either of these groups. Moreover, it is not clear which group the samples resemble more closely; depending on whether inhibiting activity increases along coordinate 1 or at a slight angle to coordinate 1 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0195482.s006" class="xref">S6 Fig</xref>), either 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">sylvestris</italic> resin or 
 <italic class="italic">W</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nobilis</italic> resin is more closely allied with the essential oils that inhibit 
 <italic class="italic">L</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plantarum</italic> activity. So once again, the results are inconclusive as to which resin should more effectively inhibit decay. In summary, only a small subset of the resin chemical compounds, and a small subset of the fruit fly gut microbiota, have been previously investigated, and therefore the published literature does not capture the full complexity of the interactions between resin chemistry and gut microbiota activity. Moreover, even at this oversimplified level, the results of our experiments are inconclusive as to which chemical compounds and which gut bacteria have the strongest influence on decay.
</p>
