<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While research on biodiversity and disease relationships has largely focused on parasites transmitted through vectors or direct contact, less is known about the effects of biodiversity on parasites that are transmitted through the environment, i.e., in soil and water. One important pathogenic bacterium of global importance that is environmentally transmitted is 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic>, which causes the diseases leptospirosis. Across the tropics, leptospirosis is among the most important neglected diseases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], estimated to result in over 1 million human cases and almost 60,000 deaths per year [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Rats (genus 
 <italic>Rattus</italic>, family Muridae) are known to be important reservoirs for 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> because they are asymptomatic and retain the bacteria in their renal tissue, shedding living microbes into the environment through urine [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> is predominantly water-borne, but viable 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> can persist in soil for months [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and contact by people with contaminated soil and water sources can lead to infection. Infection is often characterized by mild flu-like symptoms but it can also lead to the life-threatening Weil’s disease, which is characterized by jaundice, pulmonary hemorrhagic fever and multi-organ failure [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. To date, there have been few investigations of how variation in human land use affects the prevalence of 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> across host species. In southeast Asia, two 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> species differed in the infection and prevalence in rodents according to habitat, with one (
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>borgpetersenii</italic>) found in forest, flooded and dry habitats while the other (
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>interrogans</italic>) was restricted to forest and flooded environments [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008946.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, it is likely that habitat type affects the dynamics of 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> transmission.
</p>
