<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> is regarded as an Asian species of the genus 
 <italic>Dactylorhiza</italic> [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. It is distributed across India, China, Pakistan, Iran, Afghanistan, Tibet, Bhutan, Europe, North Africa, Temperate Asia, Mongolia, and Nepal [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In India, the plant is found in Jammu and Kashmir, including Ladakh, Uttarakhand, Himachal Pradesh, Arunachal Pradesh, and Sikkim [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Over the years, the market value of crude drugs obtained from the plant has shown an increasing trend which has led to the expansion of its market across different Indian states [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The huge demand in the pharmaceutical sector has driven a flourishing trade of around USD 71,583 [
 <xref rid="B50-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Kala [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] reported that the annual demand for 
 <italic>D. hatagirea</italic> is approximately 5000 tons, due its use in both traditional as well as modern medicine. Around ~7.38 tons of salep (processed tubers) obtained from 
 <italic>D. hatageria</italic> are consumed annually to cure different ailments [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-09-01644" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Overexploitation of the plant has drastically reduced its populations and has brought it under threat. Based on the number of existing populations and the area under its cover, Conservation Assessment and Management Plan (CAMP), Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of wild flora and fauna (CITES), and International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) have placed this plant under different categories of threat (
 <xref rid="plants-09-01644-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
