<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Hammes and Ganzle (
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>) reported that “Sourdough is a leavening agent traditionally obtained through a backslopping procedure, without the addition of starter microorganisms, whose use in bread making has a long history.” Likewise, according to Hammes et al. (
 <xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>) “The concerted hydrolytic activities of the grain and microorganisms (LAB and yeasts) are the origin of all cereal fermentations and are best represented by the traditional sourdough fermentation.” The application of selected autochthonous LAB to ferment sourdough constitutes an adequate biotechnology to exploit the potential of cereals, non- wheat cereals and pseudocereals in breadmaking (
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">141</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">142</xref>). This criterion is of great importance when considering the different biochemical, technological, nutritional, and functional characteristics of different flours. The activity of LAB during cereal fermentation is well-documented. A wide variety of metabolites and compounds, such as organic acids, exopolysaccharides (EPS), antimicrobial compounds, and useful enzymes, among others, are produced by LAB (
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">143</xref>–
 <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">151</xref>). There are several different ways how the nutritional and functional quality of cereals and pseudocereals could be improved by their fermentation such as: production of bioactive peptides that may stimulate immune system (
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">152</xref>); elimination of cereal gluten (
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">153</xref>–
 <xref rid="B158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">158</xref>); production of gamma-aminobutyric acid (
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">141</xref>); increasing total phenolic content and antioxidant capacity (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>–
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">162</xref>); improving antiproliferative activity (
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">162</xref>); decreasing of antinutritional factors, such as phytic acid, tannins and enzyme inhibitors (
 <xref rid="B163" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>–
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>).
</p>
