<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As demonstrated by previous studies conducted by Załuski, 
 <italic>E. senticosus</italic> is successfully cultivated in the botanical garden in Rogów (Central Polish Lowlands), and some methods required for determination of phenolic metabolites in the plant material and the biological activity of extracts have been developed [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The observations have also been confirmed by Bączek, who studied the impact of growth conditions on accumulation of biologically active compounds in organs of two-, three-, and four-year-old plants [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Nevertheless, the species cultivated in Bydgoszcz (North Polish Lowlands) has not yet been studied in detail (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-01969-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Preliminary information on chemical compounds in the 
 <italic>E. senticosus</italic> fruits intractum have been previously reported by Graczyk et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, no data are available on the localization of eleutherosides and phenolic acids in anatomical structures or on pharmacognostic features that can be used as markers in quality assessment. It is well known that phytochemicals can be accumulated in different fruit parts, e.g., 
 <italic>Citrus limon</italic> Burm. contains the highest amount of chlorogenic or caffeic acids or hesperidin in the peel [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In addition, there is no information about the oil in the fruits, which may be of interest e.g., for the food industry [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. 
</p>
