<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Consumption of wild edible plants carries the connotation of belonging to a lower strata in society and is considered an insult, because of lack of knowledge [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Similarly, in Kayissa Kebele, South Omo Zone, 10 WEPs are not consumed by the majority of the population except when there is a serious shortage of food affecting all strata of the population from the poorest to the richest [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Different studies in Ethiopia show that the local taboos seem to dread being fully depressed to the point of consuming WEPs [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Although WEPs play an important role in food security, their utilization was constrained by different factors like cultural ignorance, difficulty of collection, and being choice foods [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In a similar study, Addis et al. [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>] indicated that despite the fact there was a common understanding and belief that WEPs are important to bridge gaps of food deficiency and serve as food supplements, some individuals in communities consider the use of WEPs as a sign of underdevelopment and poverty. This is a serious threat to conservation and consumption of wild edible plants. On the other hand, Addis et al. [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] stated that wild plants in Ethiopia are used as a source of food both at times of plenty and at times of food shortages. Households have indicated the desire to continue to gathering and hunting for wild foods, but the amount they obtained was very low due because the availability of wild foods have been currently reduced due to substitution with staple crops, wild foods are not culturally acceptable, and the hunting and gathering of wild foods have been legally banned [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The literature indicates that the perception of wild edible plants as food varies from location to location, and it also varies with economic status, gender, and age of the consumer.
</p>
