<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the most commonly investigated EOs for its antifungal and antimycotoxigenic activity was obtained from 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> species. Although different sensitivities against different fungal cultures were exhibited, EOs from different 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> species have a wide spectrum of antifungal activity (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-04711-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Many studies about EOs from 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> species indicated that these activities were superior to its thymol and carvacrol contents. The corresponding EO pronounced antifungal activity against 
 <italic>Aspergillus carbonarius</italic> [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], and 
 <italic>Aspergillus parasiticus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. In addition to 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> spp., the other most studied molds were 
 <italic>Penicillium</italic> spp. [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Lastly, 
 <italic>Fusarium solani</italic> [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] and 
 <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> [
 <xref rid="B73-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] have also been subjected to studies on 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> species. In these studies, differences in the results were observed for the obtained minimum inhibition concentration (MIC) values. These differences in the antifungal and antimycotoxigenic activities of EOs may originate from differences in geographical location, harvesting season, or part of the plant that was used during EO preparation. The composition of the EO is also assumed as a key factor, which can vary even within the same species. Variations in the profile and content of components resulted in an extensive difference in databases. This situation was demonstrated with a study that was carried out by Mohammadi et al. [
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], who have reported different antifungal activities of EOs from different species of the same plant. The remarkable finding according to this group was that while thymol was the major component in the EO from 
 <italic>Thymus kotschyanus</italic>, it was carvacrol in 
 <italic>Thymus daenensis</italic> EO [
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Studies on the antimycotoxigenic effects of 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> EO were generally focused on aflatoxins. The inhibition of aflatoxin B
 <sub>1</sub> [
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], aflatoxin B
 <sub>2</sub> [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], and aflatoxin G
 <sub>1</sub> [
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] by using EOs has been demonstrated in different studies. It is interesting to notice that in the presence of 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> EO, the production of fumonisin increased, while aflatoxin production decreased by 4% [
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
