<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Proximate compositions of the feeds and fish samples were analyzed following AOAC methods (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>). Moisture content was determined by oven (Heating and Drying Oven, XMTD-8222, Jinghong, Shanghai, China) drying at 105°C to constant weight (Method 934.01, AOAO 2003). Ash content was determined via combustion in a muffle furnace (Muffle furnace, Yingshan, Hubei, China) at 550°C to a constant weight [Method 942.05, (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>)]. Crude protein content (N × 6.25) was determined after acid digestion with the Kjeldahl method [Method 990.03, (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>)], using a 4,800 Kjeltec Analyzer Unit (FOSS Tecator, Haganas, Sweden). Crude lipid content was determined using ether extraction in a Soxtec system (Soxtec System HT6, Tecator, Haganas, Sweden), with diethyl ether as the extraction liquid [Method 920.39, (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>)]. The starch content of the diet was measured using the commercial starch content kit (A148-1-1, Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China). The liver and muscle were freeze-dried in a freeze dryer (Christ ALPHA 1-4 LD plus, Germany), and the crude lipid contents of the freeze-dried organs were determined using ether extraction in a Soxtec system (Soxtec System HT6, Tecator, Haganas, Sweden), with diethyl ether as the extraction liquid. For the measurement of fatty acid compositions, lipids of the experimental diets were extracted with a chloroform:methanol (2:1 v/v) mixture as described by Folch et al. (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>). Fatty acid methyl esters were obtained by transmethylation as described by Christie (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>). The fatty acid composition of diets was determined using the gas chromatography (7890A-5975C, Agilents Technologies Inc., Santa Clara, CA, USA). An HP-88 capillary column (60 m × 250 μm × 0.2μm, Agilent 112-8867) was used to provide the fatty acid separation. The column was set at a constant flow rate of 1 mL/min using helium as carrier gas, and the septum purge flow was 3 mL/min. The injection volume was 1.0 μL in splitless mode with the split ratio at 10:1. The temperature of injector, ion source, and transfer line was set at 280 °C, 230 °C and 230 °C, respectively. The total runtime was 46 min and the oven temperature was programed as follows: the initial temperature was 100 °C for 5 min, then increased to 230°C (for 15 min) at 5°C/min. Fatty acids in the diet samples were calculated by the standard curves and fatty acid composition was expressed as percentage of total fatty acids.
</p>
