<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A far more influential compound is 1-o-cis-cinnamoyl-b-d-glucopyranose-6-o- (4-hydroxy-2-methylenebutyroyl)-1-o-cis-cinnamoyl-b-d-glucopyranose, isolated from 
 <italic>Spiraea thunbergii</italic>, which has a very high specific activity, as well as a high total activity (1000) [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-00684" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The seeds of lettuce (
 <italic>Lactuca sativa</italic> L.) were used as the receptor plant for the bioassay for initial screening. Other weeds and crop species including red clover (
 <italic>Trifolium pratense</italic> L.), white clover (
 <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> L.), alfalfa (
 <italic>Medicago sativa</italic> L.), and bird’s-foot trefoil (
 <italic>Lotus corniculatus</italic> L.) seeds were also used for the bioassay. The working solutions of star anise with 90% methanol extract were at concentrations of 20, 50, 100, 200, 500, and 1000 ppm. The synthetic shikimic acid was also tested for potential inhibitory effect on the receptor species. Ten milligrams of pure shikimic acid was dissolved in 10 mL of 90% methanol and further diluted to obtain the solutions at concentrations of 20, 50, 100, 200, 500, and 1000 ppm. One milliliter of the different concentrations of plant extract or pure shikimic acid was added to 27 mm filter papers in same size glass Petri dishes and dried completely in vacuo. The control treatments were set up with only 90% methanol without plant extract or pure shikimic acid. After adding distilled water (0.7 mL), five pre-germinated (20 h at 22 °C in the dark) lettuce seeds were placed in each of the dishes with three replications and incubated at 22 °C in darkness for 52 h. The other pre-germinated seeds of white clover, red clover, alfalfa, and bird’s-foot trefoil were also used for the bioassay. Finally, the inhibition of radicle elongation was determined by comparing the radicle lengths of treated plants with that of the control (same as 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot2-plants-09-00684">Section 2.2</xref>). The effective concentrations required to induce half-maximal inhibition of growth (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) were calculated according to the linear relationship between concentration and per cent inhibition of plant growth.
</p>
