<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have demonstrated the antimicrobial (antibacterial, antifungal, and antiviral) properties of extracts and isolated compounds obtained from Indian gamboge (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-05690-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Narasimha Rao et al. [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] examined the antibacterial and antifungal properties of morellins and found that 
 <italic>Micrococcus pyogenes</italic> var. 
 <italic>aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Mycobacterium phlei</italic>, and 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis hominis</italic> were susceptible to the methyl ether of morellin. Similarly, morellin, morellin-T, morellin-M, morellin-L, and isomorellin, which were isolated from 
 <italic>G. morella</italic>, demonstrated antibacterial activity against Gram-positive and -negative bacteria, fungi, yeast, and actinomycetes [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The antibacterial activity of leaf methanolic extracts of nine 
 <italic>Garcinia</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], including 
 <italic>G. morella</italic>, against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (MTCC 441), 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (MTCC 430), 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MTCC7433), 
 <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> ser. 
 <italic>typhi</italic> (MTCC733), and 
 <italic>Vibrio cholera</italic> (MTCC 3906), was evaluated and it was found that 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> methanolic extract exhibited remarkable antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>B. cereus</italic> (MTCC 430) and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MTCC7433) at 200 and 500 µg/mL concentrations. Similarly, Sarma et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] demonstrated the antifungal activities of fruit extracts of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> against skin pathogenic fungi, namely 
 <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic>, 
 <italic>Microsporum gypseum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Microsporum fulvum</italic> (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-05690-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Zuo et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] investigated the in vitro antimicrobial activities of 80% ethanol extracts of 30 Chinese medicinal plants, including 
 <italic>G. morella</italic>, against conventional clinical pathogens such as 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 25923, methicillin-sensitive 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MSSA)), 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922), 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC 27853), and 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (ATCC Y0109) by agar diffusion method and calculated the inhibition zone diameters (IZDs). The screening of the in vitro antimicrobial activity of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> extracts revealed the anti-MSSA (IZD 17 mm) and anti-MRSA (methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>) (IZD 15.7 mm) effects at various levels of potency, and the authors reported that the anti-MRSA activity of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> was due to morellin and other caged xanthones. Numerous in vitro and in vivo studies have demonstrated that mangostin (
 <bold>10</bold>) exhibited antibacterial, antifungal, and antimalarial properties [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Another study reported that α-mangostin exhibited inhibitory effects against MRSA and vancomycin-resistant 
 <italic>Enterococci</italic> (VRE [
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]), wherein the authors showed that α-mangostin is involved in the disruption of the bacterial cytoplasmic membrane at minimum inhibitory concentrations of 0.78–1.56 µg/mL. Similarly, previous studies [
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] reported the inhibitory effects of α-mangostin against 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>, 
 <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic>, 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, 
 <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Plasmodium berghei</italic>. Garcinol (
 <bold>11</bold>) also demonstrated significant activity against disease-causing microbes, namely influenza A [
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], 
 <italic>Bacillus anthracis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], and 
 <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Garcinol was reported to inhibit both the viral nucleoprotein and regulation of the viral polymerase of influenza A.
</p>
