<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Partially or highly defatted protein meal, however, is only one of the products that can be obtained from the HI larvae. In fact, the industrial processing of this insect species to produce the protein meal, generates another co-product which is quantitatively (30%–40% of the dry matter (DM)) and nutritionally relevant: the fat fraction. The fat derived from HI larvae was studied as a possible source for biodiesel production and provided interesting results [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], but it could also possibly be exploited in the formulation of poultry diets as a substitution for the commonly used lipid sources such as rendered fat and vegetable oils, in particular that obtained from soybean. This is because HI larvae fat is rich in medium chain fatty acids (MCFA) that can have positive effects on gut health, thus improving growth performance [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Moreover, MCFA was shown to be preferentially utilized as an energy source, improving energy availability without increasing the deposition of lipids [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Despite its potential, there is still a limited number of research papers dealing with the dietary application of HI larvae fat in meat-producing birds. HI larvae fat has been included as a partial (50%) or total (100%) replacement of soybean oil in the diet for broiler chickens from one day of age up to slaughter (35 days) [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Independently of the replacement percentage, it was observed that chickens fed with HI larvae fat had satisfactory productive performance, carcass traits and overall meat quality. The only possible drawback was the fatty acid (FA) profile of the meat which was negatively influenced by the new ingredient: the total saturated fatty acids (SFA) increased to the detriment of the polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) fraction. Based on these initial results, it was decided to test the same fat source on the same bird species, but limiting the supplementation period solely to the finisher phase, when dietary SFA are used to improve the firmness of the carcass fat depots. The first part of this work considered growth performance, carcass traits, blood parameters, intestinal morphology and histological features [
 <xref rid="B14-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] and no adverse effects were observed for the studied traits. Therefore, the present research was aimed at evaluating the effects of a partial (50%) or total (100%) replacement of soybean oil with HI larvae fat in finisher broiler chickens’ diets on the t physical traits, proximate composition, cholesterol content, oxidative status, fatty acid profile and sensory traits of the meat.
</p>
