<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
 <p>MP performed the preliminary investigations, adapted the fluorescence-microscopy technique, designed the experiment and analyzed the data. AB performed the fluorescence-microscopic works, including sample preparation, staining and image processing, and was a major contributor in writing the manuscript. AN and AK assisted the work and the interpretation of the Fourier-transform infrared (FTIR) imaging and co-wrote the sections, which included the FTIR. HS and HH enabled the investigation in their working groups. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 <sec id="FPar2">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p id="Par76">Special thanks to Dr. Elisabeth Seigner, Dr. Martin Müller and Stefanie Gellan of the Research Groups IPZ5c, IPZ1a and IPZ4a at the Bavarian State Research Center for Agriculture (LfL) for supply, guidance and assistance in the fluorescence-microscopy, to Dr. Dieter Treutter† and Ina Tittel of the Technical University of Munich, TUM School of Life Sciences Weihenstephan, department of fruit science for supply, guidance and assistance in the histological techniques and light-microscopy.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3">
  <title>Competing interests</title>
  <p id="Par77">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="d29e1728">
  <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4">
  <title>Consent for publication</title>
  <p id="Par78">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5">
  <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p id="Par79">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p id="Par80">The valerian breeding project is part of the Demonstration Project Medicinal Plants (KAMEL) and is being supported by Fachagentur Nachwachsende Rohstoffe e.V. (FNR) on behalf of the German Federal Ministry of Food and Agriculture based on a decision of the German Bundestag.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7">
  <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
  <p id="Par81">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
