<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Extractives are a heterogeneous group of substances which can be extracted from plants. The oregano herb material contains mainly phenolic compounds as well as tannins, resins, flavonoids, bitter substances, sterols, and other compounds [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The dietary importance of medicinal plants is due to their phenolic phytochemicals which are a rich source of antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. These phenolic substances have advantageous outcomes on human health, in particular by preventing mutagenesis along with carcinogenesis [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Flavonoids and phenolic acids are the main types of phenolic compounds present in oregano. Flavonoid molecules are characterized by having at least one aromatic ring with one or more hydroxyl group attached [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Flavonoids are accumulated in plant tissues (such as leaves, flowers, stems, and roots) as a response to biotic and abiotic stress such as pathogen and insect attacks, UV radiation, and damage to the plant [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Moreover, phenolic compounds help plants survive and adapt to environmental disturbances through various physiological functions [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00750" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The total extractive substance refers to the percentage of material remaining after the removal of water. This indicator is more important for food materials, but for the content and composition of the essential oils of herbs, it is one of the most important characteristics.
</p>
