<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4583994</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26407176</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139234</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-10800</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Specialist Insect Herbivore and Light Availability Do Not Interact in the Evolution of an Invasive Plant</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Specialist Herbivore and Shading on Evolution of Invasive Plant</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zhijie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Xiaoyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Ziyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001">
<sup>&#x02021;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Kate S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001">
<sup>&#x02021;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="econtrib001">
<sup>&#x02021;</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Ministry of Education Key Laboratory for Biodiversity Science &#x00026; Ecological Engineering, Institute of Biodiversity Science, Fudan University, Shanghai, People&#x02019;s Republic of China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, Murray State University, Murray, Kentucky, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;dler</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research (UFZ), GERMANY</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: ZJZ XP. Performed the experiments: ZJZ ZYZ. Analyzed the data: ZJZ XP. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XP BL. Wrote the paper: ZJZ XP. Provided editorial advice: KH BL.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="econtrib001"><p>&#x02021; These authors also contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>xypan@fudan.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e0139234</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 Zhang et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0139234.pdf"/><abstract><p>Release from specialist insect herbivores may allow invasive plants to evolve traits associated with decreased resistance and increased competitive ability. Given that there may be genetic trade-off between resistance and tolerance, invasive plants could also become more tolerant to herbivores. Although it is widely acknowledged that light availability affects tolerance to herbivores, little information is available for whether the effect of light availability on tolerance differ between the introduced and native populations. We conducted a common garden experiment in the introduced range of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> using ten invasive US and ten native Argentinean populations at two levels of light availability and in the presence or absence of a specialist stem-boring insect <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>. Plant biomass (total and storage root biomass), two allocation traits (root/shoot ratio and branch intensity, branches biomass/main stem biomass) and two functional traits (specific stem length and specific leaf area), which are potentially associated with herbivore resistance and light capture, were measured. Overall, we found that <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> from introduced ranges had comparable biomass and tolerance to specialist herbivores, lower branch intensity, lower specific stem length and specific leaf area. Moreover, introduced populations displayed higher shade tolerance of storage root biomass and lower plastic response to shading in specific stem length. Finally, light availability had no significant effect on evolution of tolerance to specialist herbivores of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>. Our results suggest that post-introduction evolution might have occurred in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>. While light availability did not influence the evolution of tolerance to specialist herbivores, increased shade tolerance and release from specialist insects might have contributed to the successful invasion of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was financially supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant Nos. 31070369, 31370433). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are available via Dryad (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.7j2d4">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.7j2d4</ext-link>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are available via Dryad (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.7j2d4">http://dx.doi.org/10.5061/dryad.7j2d4</ext-link>).</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Rapid adaptation to the novel environments in introduced ranges is one of the mechanisms by which invasive species could spread and become extremely successful invaders after a lag time [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. A relevant hypothesis is the evolution of increased competitive ability (EICA) hypothesis [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] which posits that release from specialist enemies may have caused evolution in exotic plants, specifically lowered resistance to herbivores and increased growth and competitive ability.</p><p>In addition, attempts to explain rapid evolution in invasive species have led to several other hypotheses. A potentially essential but still understudied mechanism is phenotypic plasticity, the property of a genotype to express different phenotypes in different biotic or abiotic environments [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Two types of plasticity that are generally considered to be important for the success of invasive plants are (1) the capacity of plants to alter biomass allocation and functional traits in response to different levels of resource availability, and (2) herbivory tolerance, the capacity of plants to reduce the negative effects of damage on fitness [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>Empirical tests have been strongly biased toward examining the evolution of herbivory resistance rather than tolerance in invasive plants [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A trade-off between resistance and tolerance has come to light recently [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Therefore, introduced populations of exotic plants are expected to have higher tolerance to specialist herbivores [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, comparisons of herbivory tolerance between native and introduced populations of invasive plants have shown conflicting results, some invasive plants have evolved increased tolerance to specialist insects [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; others have showed no differences in tolerance between native and introduced populations [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. While these studies have been focused on the novel biotic condition: release from specialist enemies, invasive species can also experience novel resource availability (e.g. light, water and nutrients) [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], which may lead to evolution in functional traits, and influence plant responses to herbivory [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>Several hypotheses have been proposed to explain the effects of resource availability on tolerance. The compensatory continuum hypothesis (CCH) predicts that herbivory tolerance should be greater in high-resource and low-competition conditions [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The growth rate model (GRM), makes the opposite prediction: herbivory tolerance should be greater in more stressful conditions [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Most recently, the limiting resource model (LRM) has been proposed. LRM is more flexible than either the CCH or GRM, because it specifically considers which factors are limiting plant fitness and which resources are affected by particular herbivore [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Several studies in invasion research have proposed that release from natural enemies and resource availability may interact [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and then could affect the evolution of anti-herbivore defense [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Therefore, we suppose resource availability may also influence the evolution of tolerance in alien invasive plants.</p><p>Light is the most important resource for plant performance [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and previous studies have demonstrated that many exotic plants are likely to invade deeply shaded environment and establish denser stands [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, it is suggested that invasive plants may have evolved to be more shade tolerant [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Nonetheless, little information is available for whether introduced populations have higher shade tolerance than the natives [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In addition, plant responses to herbivores and shading may be in opposition for particular traits [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Previous tests have also found light availability affects tolerance to herbivores [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Therefore, light availability may affect the evolution of tolerance to specialist herbivores in invasive species.</p><p>In this study, we manipulated <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> (alligator weed) to detect the effect of light availability on tolerance of plants from two geographical origins (native and invasive ranges). As one of the most rapidly spreading plant invaders, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> grows abundantly in habitats ranging from open waterways to shaded sites under dense vegetation in the introduced ranges [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and is reported to be shade tolerant. We have been studying defense against the specialist enemy <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> and competitive ability in invasive <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>. We have found that one aspect of resistance to stem-boring <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> is the specific stem length (SSL), calculated as the main stem length divided by the main stem dry weight. We found different genotypes of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> vary widely in SSL, and genotypes with lower SSL experience much more herbivory (e.g. higher rate of feeding, oviposition and pupation from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic>) [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>Here, we addressed the possible evolution of defense traits and tolerance to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic>, and the impact of shade on possible evolution of herbivory tolerance in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>. We conducted a common garden experiment in the introduced range of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> using ten invasive (USA) and ten native (Argentina) populations at two levels of light availability and in the presence or absence of a specialist insect <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic>. Plant biomass (total biomass and storage biomass), two allocation traits (root/shoot ratio and branch intensity, branches biomass/main stem biomass) and two functional traits (specific stem length and specific leaf area) were measured. These traits are all potentially plastic in response to herbivory and shade.</p><p>We focused on testing the following effects of each trait: 1) significant effects of plant origin could indicate differences between native and introduced ranges; 2) significant effects of origin by shading interaction on biomass would show differences in shade tolerance between plant origins; 3) significant effects of origin by shading interaction on allocation and functional traits would show differences in plasticity to shading between plant origins; 4) significant effects of origin by herbivore interaction on biomass can indicate differences in herbivory tolerance due to plant origin; 5) significant interactions of origin, shading, and herbivory can indicate the difference in effect of light availability on tolerance between native and introduced populations.</p><p>Specifically, we tested the following hypotheses: 1) introduced populations will have lower levels of resistance traits (lower SSL and higher SLA) and enhanced tolerance to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic>; 2) introduced populations will be more shade tolerant; 3) the interactive effect of light and herbivory on traits may be different between introduced and native populations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Study species</title><p>Alligator weed (<italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>) is a perennial herbaceous plant native to South America from Buenos Aires Province, Argentina (39&#x000b0;S) to southern Brazil (18&#x000b0;S). It typically emerges from belowground buds on storage roots in spring and then spreads vegetatively throughout a growing season to form dense monospecific stands. It overwinters with storage roots and rhizomes [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Although plants may produce viable seeds, sexual reproduction contributes little to population regeneration because of both extremely low seed outputs and low germination rates [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Vegetative propagation with storage roots and stem fragments is the primary regenerative mode in the field [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Biomass allocation to storage roots plays important roles in the life history of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]: the large root reserves act as the primary energy sources for shoot emergence in early spring and also enable rapid shoot regrowth after herbivory or other physical damage. Root fragments also act as propagules for long-distance dispersal by flooding or human activities (e.g. soil transportation and dredging). Therefore, the biomass of storage roots is in some sense equivalent to the reproductive output for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>In the United States, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> was first introduced in Alabama in 1897 probably through ballast water [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Since 1930s, its populations have spread rapidly into northeastern wetlands and also expanded into California [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In South America, as many as 40 insect species were recorded on <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>, five of which are considered to be specialists [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. There are few native insects feeding on introduced <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> in the USA [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], suggesting that release from specialist insect attack could play an important role in explaining its successful invasion. Although three insect species, <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> Selman &#x00026;Vogt (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae), <italic>Amynothrips andersoni</italic> O&#x02019;Neill (Thysanaptera: Phlaeothripidae), and <italic>Arcola malloi</italic> (Pastrana) (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae, Phycitinae), have been introduced into the United States as biological control agents since 1964&#x02013;1971 [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], these insects are still restricted to certain areas of the ranges of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroide</italic>s. Consequently enemy release may continue to act on the host in the US range, but vary regionally in its strength [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In turn, this could lead to high inter-population variation or high phenotypic plasticity in defense against specialist herbivores in introduced populations.</p><p>Alligator weed flea beetle (<italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>) is a specialist phytophagous insect of alligator weed that has been used as one of the most important biological control agents of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> in USA since 1964. The life stages of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> consist of the egg, 3 larval instars, the pupa, and the adult [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0139234.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). Both adults and larvae feed on the leaves and other aerial portions of alligator weed. Mature larvae bore into the hollow stems where they pupate as adults, and exacerbate the acquisition of nitrogen by phloem, which causes damage to the fitness of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. It has been suggested that the completion of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic>&#x02019;s life cycle requires hollow stems for pupation, which may contribute, in part, to its specific adaptation to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0139234.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139234.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Four life stages of <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> and damage to on <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> by <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>.</title><p>(a) egg stage, 4.1&#x000b1;0.77 days, (b) larva stage, 7.8&#x000b1;0.78 days, (c) pupa stage,8.6&#x000b1;0.57 days, and (d) adult stage, 50.3&#x000b1; 2.42 days [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. (e) leaf feeding by larvae and adults, (f) stem boring after pupation. Average means &#x000b1;1 standard error.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139234.g001"/></fig><p>In the present study, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> was initially introduced from Florida, USA in 1986. We collected insects from the field station of Institute of Plant Protection (Fujian Academy of Agricultural Sciences), Fuzhou, China.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Seed collection and experimental set-up</title><p>In 2006, clones (stem fragments) of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> weed were collected from ten native populations in Argentina that covered a broad range distribution (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For each population, we created a mixture of clones from 20&#x02013;30 maternal families. In 2005, similar collections were made in ten American populations. The sampled stem fragments were transplanted in a greenhouse and vegetatively propagated three times before experiments to remove maternal effects.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0139234.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139234.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Sampling locations of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0139234.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0139234.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collection site</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latitude</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitude</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitat</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">abundance of <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Argentina (Native)</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Formosa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.46'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.34'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wetland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tucuman</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.54'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.18'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">roadside</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">high</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">San ignacio</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.11'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.53'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rocks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chaco</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.12'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.29'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">shrub vegetation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Misiones</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.15'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.31'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">roadside</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corrientes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.59'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.20'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">roadside</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Santa Fe</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.16'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.49'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">river bank</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">low</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buenos Aires</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.36'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.37'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pond side</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buenos Aires</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.00'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.44'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">roadside</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buenos Aires</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.11'S</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.03'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">roadside</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>USA (Introduced)</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North Carolina</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.42'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.42'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wetland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kentucky</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.11'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.22'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lake bank</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arkansas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.42'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.18'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">river bank</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Georgia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.12'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.06'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wetland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mississippi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.31'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.28'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">river bank</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mississippi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.16'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.47'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">river bank</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Texas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.54'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.57'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wetland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Louisiana</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.06'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.08'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wetland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Florida</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.35'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.30'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">river bank</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Texas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.12'N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.38'W</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">wetland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>We performed a common garden experiment on the campus of Fudan University, Shanghai, China. The climate is humid subtropical, with rainfall averaging 1895 mm year<sup>&#x02013;1</sup>, and temperatures averaging 4.2&#x000b0;C in January and 27.9&#x000b0;C in July. The native ranges of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>, such as Buenos Aires, is humid subtropical, with rainfall averaging 1214 mm year<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and averages 7.4&#x000b0;C in July and 30.4&#x000b0;C in January. The introduced ranges of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>, for example, the gulf of Mexico, is humid subtropical or humid tropical, with rainfall averaging 1418 mm year<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> and averages 10.4&#x000b0;C in January and 28.9&#x000b0;C in July (data from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://worldweather.wmo.int/en/home.html">http://worldweather.wmo.int/en/home.html</ext-link>). Therefore, the climates of different origins are similar.</p><p>On 18 June 2013, we propagated over 30 stem fragments (with one node, 2cm in length) from one genotype of each population, and 16 randomly selected ramets with similar height and leaf numbers (four leaves) from each population were transferred individually to 700ml plastic pots. Each plant was watered 100ml every two days and received a total of 2 g slow-release 16:9:12 N:P:K fertilizer (Osmocote). A three-factor, randomized block design was then used for executing this experiment. The layout consisted of four blocks. In each block, treatments were randomly assigned to each pot and included two levels of light and two levels of herbivory. Thus, a total of 320 plants were tested in the experiment (2 origins: native and introduced ranges x 2 light x 2 herbivory x 10 populations x 4 blocks).</p><p>The two light treatments were control light and shading. Plants in the control light treatment were covered with nylon nettings to exclude herbivores. Plants in the shading treatment were first covered with the nylon nettings and then covered with black fiberglass shading cloth in order to decrease light quantity without changing light quality. The control treatment received approximately 80% light compared to ambient sun measured by an illuminometer (Li-1400, Li-Cor Inc., Lincoln, NB, USA). The shading treatment received approximately 25% light compared to the control light treatment.</p><p>Before the herbivory treatment, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> were fed on Fujian populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> and raised for three generations to reduce maternal effects. Four weeks after transplantation, plants in the control treatment received no herbivory. Plants in herbivory treatment were first uncovered from the nettings and shade cloth, then two randomly chosen second-instar larvae were carefully placed on a fully expanded leaf (second or third position from the tip) with a paintbrush, finally the nettings and shade cloth were replaced. The larvae fed on the plants for five days and consumed an average of 4.6% of leaf area in control light conditions and 15.6% of leaf area in shade conditions. Larvae were then allowed to bore into the stem till the end of experiment.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Data collection</title><p>All plants were harvested on 18 August 2013 (six weeks after transplantation). We separated each plant into leaf, main stem, lateral branch, storage root, and fine root. We also measured the length of the main stem, and determined leaf areas with a leaf-area meter (Li-3100, Li-Cor Inc., Lincoln, NB, USA). All plant materials were dried at 70&#x000b0;C to a constant weight (for 72 hours) and weighed to determine leaf dry weight, stem dry weight, branch dry weight, storage root dry weight, and fine root dry weight.</p><p>The following allocation parameters were further derived from the above measurements: (1) biomass traits including total biomass as total dry weight, storage root biomass as storage root dry weight; (2) biomass allocation parameters including root/shoot ratio (RSR, [root dry weight]/[shoot dry weight], branch index (BI, [branch dry weight]/[stem dry weight]), (3) functional traits related to light capture and resistance including specific stem length (SSL, [length of stem, cm]/[stem dry weight, g]), and specific leaf area (SLA, [leaf area, cm2]/[leaf dry weight, g]).</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>We used mixed model ANOVAS (SPSS Proc GLM; v 19.0, SPSS institute Inc, 2010) to test effects of origin (native versus invasive), shading, herbivory, and their interactions on biomass, allocation parameters, and functional traits. We treated population nested within origin as a random effect. We used K-S test and Levene&#x02019;s test to analyze normality and homoscedasticity respectively. To achieve normality and homoscedasticity, total biomass, BI and SSL were square-root transformed; SLA was log-transformed. In the cases where transformations were done, the results are presented as back-transformed means and standard errors. We used type-III sum of squares for the calculation of F statistics. Tukey&#x02019;s <italic>post hoc</italic> tests were used to contrast specific means.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec007"><title>Results</title><p>Both of the experimental treatments employed in this study strongly affected the biomass, biomass allocation and functional traits of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), but their interactions were not significant.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0139234.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139234.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>ANOVA showing effects of origin,shading, herbivore, and their interactions on <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> according to F ratio.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0139234.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0139234.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Biomass</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Allocation parameters</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Functional traits</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d.f.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Storage root</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSR</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BI</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSL</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">origin</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,18</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.95<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shading</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,282</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1943<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">907<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">826<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">502<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381<xref rid="t002fn004" ref-type="table-fn">***</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">herbivory</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,282</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.59<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S x H</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,282</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.175</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O x S</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,282</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.582<xref rid="t002fn002" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.85<xref rid="t002fn003" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O x H</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,282</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O x S x H</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,282</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>The allocation parameters are: LWR, leaf weight ratio; SWR, stem weight ratio; BWR, branch weight ratio; SRWR, storage-root weight ratio; and FRWR, fine-root weight ratio. The functional traits are: RSR, root/shoot ratio; BI, branch intensity; SSL, specific stem length; and SLA, specific leaf area. Statistical significance is indicated as:</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>*p&#x0003c;0.05,</p></fn><fn id="t002fn003"><p>**p&#x0003c;0.01,</p></fn><fn id="t002fn004"><p>***p&#x0003c;0.001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="sec008"><title>Differentiation between native and introduced populations</title><p>On average, and across treatments, introduced <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> populations had similar biomass to that of the natives (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The introduced populations also had lower branch intensity (BI, -23.2%), specific stem length (SSL, -15.3%) and specific leaf area (SLA, -6.2%) than the natives (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, Figs <xref rid="pone.0139234.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0139234.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0139234.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139234.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>The effects of shading and a specialist herbivore (<italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>) on biomass of native (Argentina, dashed lines) and invasive (USA, solid lines) populations of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>.</title><p>The biomass parameters are: total biomass and storage root biomass. Estimated marginal means &#x000b1;1 standard error. Statistical significance in origin &#x000d7; treatment is indicated as: *p&#x0003c;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139234.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone.0139234.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139234.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>The effects of shading and a specialist herbivore (<italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>) on biomass allocation of native (Argentina, dashed lines) and invasive (USA, solid lines) populations of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>.</title><p>The allocation parameters are: root/shoot ratio,RSR; branch intensity, BI. Estimated marginal means &#x000b1;1 standard error. There is no statistical significance in origin &#x000d7; treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139234.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone.0139234.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0139234.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>The effects of shading and a specialist herbivore (<italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic>) on functional traits of native (Argentina, dashed lines) and invasive (USA, solid lines) populations of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>.</title><p>The functional traits are: specific stem length, SSL; and specific leaf area, SLA. Estimated marginal means &#x000b1;1 standard error. Statistical significance in origin &#x000d7; treatment is indicated as: *p&#x0003c;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0139234.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Responses to shading</title><p>Shaded plants had significantly lower average total biomass (-77.8%) and storage root biomass (-93.2%) (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>), also differed substantially from control plants in biomass allocations and functional traits, with a strong induction of the shading-avoidance response (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, Figs <xref rid="pone.0139234.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0139234.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Shaded plants had lower root/shoot ratio (-65.4%) and branch intensity (-56.8%) (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>), but had increased specific stem length (SSL, +235.7%) and specific leaf area (+ 56.3%) (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p><p>Responses of storage root biomass and SSL to shading differed significantly between native and introduced populations. Storage root biomass was reduced by 70.1% and 75.4% to shading in introduced and native populations, respectively (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Shading increased SSL by 221.6% and 246.4% in introduced and native populations respectively (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Responses to herbivory and its interaction with light</title><p>Plants damaged by specialist <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> showed significantly lower total biomass (-6.8%) (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Herbivory also significantly decreased branch intensity (-18.6%) and specific leaf area (-3.5%) (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, Figs <xref rid="pone.0139234.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0139234.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). There was no significant effect of herbivory by shading interaction on all traits measured (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, Figs <xref rid="pone.0139234.g002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0139234.g004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><p>There were no significant origin by herbivory interactions or origin by shading by herbivory interactions for any measured traits (<xref rid="pone.0139234.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The results were virtually identical when we used the percentage of foliar damage as a covariate.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec012"><title>Differences in biomass allocation and functional traits between native and invasive ranges</title><p>Specific stem length (SSL) is a putative structural defense trait of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> against its stem-boring enemy <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> because low SSL stems experience much more herbivory from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The lower SSL is indicative of reduced resistance to specific herbivory in introduced <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>. Meanwhile, introduced populations had similar biomass to the natives in the presence or absence of a specialist insect herbivore. These results partially support the EICA hypothesis which predicts that, in the absence of specialist herbivores, introduced plants should reduce allocation to resistance traits but increase biomass production or competitive ability. On the other hand, lower SSL is predicted to reduce plants&#x02019; ability to capture light [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Thus the significant decrease in SSL may also be indicative of reduced intraspecific competition for light in introduced populations (unpubl. data, X.Y. Pan).</p><p>Introduced populations allocated biomass differently than did native populations and showed decreased branch intensity (BI). Plant architectural traits (such as BI) that affect light capture are believed to be vital in determining the degree of self-shading [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and competitive ability for light [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Hence, the decreased BI in the introduced populations is likely to reduce both self-shading and light competition within populations (unpubl. data, X.Y. Pan). These findings could partly explain why invasive plants were often found to form dense and monospecific stands [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p>Specific leaf area (SLA) is a morphological trait which is associated with light capture and resistance to herbivory [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Although we found that introduced populations had lower SLA, the fact that they had similar biomass to native populations suggested that light capture may be similar between native and introduced populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>. This is also supported by our previous study which found introduced populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> exhibited similar photosynthetic energy use efficiency and photosynthetic nitrogen use efficiency to the natives [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Thus, the lower SLA may be indicative of increased sclerophylly and suggests that the introduced populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> which are not released from generalist herbivores [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] may have higher resistance.</p><p>The differences among native and introduced populations in several traits examined in this study suggest that evolution might have occurred in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> in the introduced ranges. However, we also recognize that this study does not provide direct evidence of such evolutionary. Further studies from population genetic within and between native and introduced populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> are still needed.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Shade tolerance and plastic responses to shading</title><p>
<italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> responded significantly to shading and displayed shading-avoidance syndrome. Shaded plants showed increased allocation to aboveground tissue, elongation of main stem, high SLA leaves, and decreased allocation to branches, which are similar to the shading responses of many other species [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and may help <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> to survive in low light environments.</p><p>We found no significant origin by shading interaction for total biomass, indicating that native and introduced populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> did not differ in the shade tolerance of total biomass. But we found a significant effect of origin by shading on storage root biomass, and introduced populations showed a flatter slope of the response of storage root biomass to shade, indicating that introduced populations had higher shade tolerance of storage root biomass. Since storage root serves as the primary resource pool from which clonal plants can support population regeneration [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], higher shade tolerance of storage root can enhance the potential for faster future plant regrowth [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. There is little available literature on comparisons of shade tolerance between native and introduced populations. Matlaga et al.[<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] have found that invasive <italic>Miscanthus sinensis</italic> seedlings have similar shade tolerance to natives.</p><p>Our result also showed that except for SSL there are no significant differences between native and invasive ranges in plasticity to shading. This is contrary to the hypothesis proposed by Richards et al [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]which predicted increased plasticity in introduced populations, but in accord with other observations. For example, invasive populations of <italic>Microstegium vimineum</italic> showed similar plasticity of SLA to shading [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and invasive populations of <italic>Clidemia hirta</italic> had similar plasticity to shading for eleven growth and biomass allocation traits [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Only one study [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] found leaf area and biomass of <italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic>, showed greater plasticity to light in introduced populations. Given that plasticity is correlated with risks that compromise long-term survival [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and is not always adaptive [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], the evolution of increased plasticity does not appear to be a universal phenomenon among invasive alien plants. Because plants often increase SSL in response to shading or crowding [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], lower plasticity of SSL to shading in introduced plants may reduce intraspecific competition [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], and hence help to form dense stands in fields.</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Tolerance to herbivory and effect of light</title><p>
<italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> that was damaged by specialist herbivores had a significantly lower total biomass and indicated under-compensating tolerance in our study. We found that damaged plants showed decreased branch intensity (BI). The responses of BI to herbivory are in contrast to several other studies. Bergman found that <italic>Salix caprea</italic> increased branches after foliar damage [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]; Bossdorf et al found that <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> increased branches after stem removal [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The mechanisms underlying different forms of herbivore tolerance vary widely [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], thus plants may vary in response to different types of damage. Damaged plants showed decreased SLA while shaded plants had increased SLA, indicating plant responses to herbivory and shading may vary among the traits of different functions [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p><p>Contrary to our predictions, we found no significant herbivory by shading interaction for total biomass or storage root biomass, indicating that light availability did not affect tolerance to specialist herbivores. This finding is inconsistent with the compensatory continuum hypothesis (CCH) or growth rate model (GRM), but seems to be consistent with the prediction of the limiting resource model (LRM) [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Studies to date have mixed results. Rogers and Siemann found that <italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic> exhibited equal tolerance at different levels of light availability but <italic>Celtic laevigata</italic> had higher tolerance in high light availability [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. We also found no significant herbivory by light interaction on resistance-related traits like SSL or SLA, indicating the light availability did not affect the induced resistance in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>.</p><p>In this study, we found no significant difference in tolerance to specialist insects between native and invasive populations, as indicated by the lack of significant herbivory by origin interaction for biomass. This is consistent with previous studies of <italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic> and <italic>Solidago gigantean</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0139234.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. But some alien species have evolved increased tolerance to specialist insects [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] in the introduced ranges. Since invaders have no history of local adaptation and co-evolution with the community of enemies in the introduced ranges, their resistance traits may be less effective [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Therefore, tolerance is likely to be a more reliable mechanism for reducing the negative effects of damage and should be maintained or increased in the introduced ranges.</p><p>To our knowledge, no one has ever tested the effect of light availability on the evolution of herbivore tolerance in invasive plants. Here we have made a first attempt to address this question. We found no significant origin by shading by herbivory interactions for total biomass or storage root biomass, indicating that light availability did not affect the evolution of tolerance to specialist herbivory in invasive populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic>. But other resources such as nitrogen and water may drive evolution of tolerance in invasive plants. Future studies need to be done for testing this possibility.</p><p>Tolerance in our study may be underestimated given that introduced populations can be less resistant to specialist herbivory [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, as the percentage of foliar damage was not significantly different between native and introduced populations (<xref rid="pone.0139234.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>, stem damage was not available to be measured), tolerance of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> was likely the result of different biomass allocation patterns.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Implications for biological control</title><p>These results have practical implications for biological control of invasive plants. Although invasive populations of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> had significantly reduced their resistance to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0139234.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], maintained tolerance to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic> will probably decreased the impact of biological control on introduced populations. Our study may also explain why shading does not accelerate the biological control of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>philoxeroides</italic> using <italic>A</italic>. <italic>hygrophila</italic>. It is important to detect which resources influence plant tolerance of herbivory and to consider these in biocontrol programs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec016"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0139234.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Average of percentage leaf area eaten by <italic>Agasicles hygrophila</italic> on native (Argentina, white) and introduced (USA, black) <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>.</title><p>Estimated marginal means &#x000b1;1 standard error. P = 0.141. For each seedling we selected all leaves to estimate the magnitude of herbivory. Each of the five leaves was assigned to one of the following categories of damage, based on visual inspection of leaf area removed: 0, no damage; 1, less than 25% damage; 2, from 25% to 50% damage; 3, from 50% to 75% damage; and 4, damage above 75%. The score of all leaves was used to calculate an individual index of herbivory, IH = &#x003a3; nC<sub>0&#x02013;4</sub>N<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; where C is the category of damage, n is the number of leaves in the Cth category, and N is the number of total leaves of each plant.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0139234.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dana Blumenthal (USDA-ARS Rangeland Resources Research Unit, Fort Collins, CO) for the critical reading of the manuscript and the valuable comments, and the reviewers who contributed valuable comments to the final version of the manuscript. We also thank Alejandro Sosa (The Foundation for the Study of Invasive Species, Spanish acronym: FuEDEI) for providing clones of the Argentina plant populations. We are also grateful to Jiahui Zhou for her assistance in conducting the greenhouse experiment. This research was financially supported by National Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 31070369, 31300467)</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0139234.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simberloff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lonsdale</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clout</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bazzaz</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biotic invasions: Causes, epidemiology, global consequences, and control</article-title>. <source>Ecological Applications</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>710</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>N&#x000f6;tzold</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of increased competitive ability in invasive nonindigenous plants&#x02014;a hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ecology</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Pigliucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <source>Phenotypic plasticity: beyond nature and nurture</source>.: <publisher-name>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD</publisher-loc>; <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The ecology and evolution of plant tolerance to herbivory</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10322530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fornoni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecological and evolutionary implications of plant tolerance to herbivory</article-title>. <source>Functional Ecology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bossdorf</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schroder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Auge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Palatability and tolerance to simulated herbivory in native and introduced populations of <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> (Brassicaceae)</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Botany</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>856</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.91.6.856</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21653441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Orians</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of Plant Defenses in Nonindigenous Environments</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Entomology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>55</volume> p. <fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-ento-112408-085333</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19737084?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19737084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stowe</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hochwender</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>. <article-title>The evolutionary ecology of tolerance to consumer damage</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stastny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Do vigour of introduced populations and escape from specialist herbivores contribute to invasiveness?</article-title>
<source>Journal of Ecology</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Resource allocation to defence and growth are driven by different responses to generalist and specialist herbivory in an invasive plant</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ecology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeWalt</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Decreased resistance and increased tolerance to native herbivores of the invasive plant Sapium sebiferum</article-title>. <source>Ecography</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrillo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Invader partitions ecological and evolutionary responses to above- and belowground herbivory</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 23236906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23236906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hull-Sanders</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Altered patterns of growth, physiology and reproduction in invasive genotypes of Solidago gigantea (Asteraceae)</article-title>. <source>Biological Invasions</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grime</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fluctuating resources in plant communities: a general theory of invasibility</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ecology</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>528</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Atwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyerson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Beyond EICA: understanding post-establishment evolution requires a broader evaluation of potential selection pressures</article-title>. <source>NeoBiota</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of herbivory on plants in different resource conditions: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Alward</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plasticity and overcompensation in grass responses to herbivory</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>358</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28314011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abrahamson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Beyond the compensatory continuum: environmental resource levels and plant tolerance of herbivory</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>109</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Blumenthal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecology&#x02014;Interrelated causes of plant invasion</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>310</volume>(<issue>5746</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16224008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Interactive effects of habitat productivity and herbivore pressure on the evolution of anti-herbivore defense in invasive plant populations</article-title>. <source>Journal of theoretical biology</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>242</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>935</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16824547?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16824547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niinemets</surname><given-names>&#x000dc;</given-names></name>. <article-title>Shade tolerance, a key plant feature of complex nature and consequences</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Canham</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Why forests appear resistant to exotic plant invasions: intentional introductions, stand dynamics, and the role of shade tolerance</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Ecology and the Environment</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>142</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Size-symmetric competition in a shade-tolerant invasive plant</article-title>. <source>Journal of Systematics and Evolution</source>. <year>2013b</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>318</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schooler</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Klinken</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of clonal integration and light availability on the growth and physiology of two invasive herbs</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ecology</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>98</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Matlaga</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Light response of native and introduced <italic>Miscanthus sinensis</italic> seedlings</article-title>. <source>Invasive Plant Science and Management</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Salgado-Luarte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gianoli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Herbivory on temperate rainforest seedlings in sun and shade: resistance, tolerance and habitat distribution</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e11460</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0011460</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20628638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20628638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of simulated herbivory and resource availability on native and invasive exotic tree seedlings</article-title>. <source>Basic and Applied Ecology</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Longstreth</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The effect of light on growth and dry matter allocation patterns of Alternanthera philoxeroides (Mart.) Griseb</article-title>. <source>Botanical Gazette</source>. <year>1984</year>;<volume>145</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>For or against: the importance of variation in growth rate for testing the EICA hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Biological Invasions</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Allometric growth, disturbance regime, and dilemmas of controlling invasive plants: a model analysis</article-title>. <source>Biological Invasions</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>743</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Julien</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>New research on <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> (alligator weed) in its South American native range</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Briese</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kriticos</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (eds) <source>Proceedings of the XI international symposium on biological control of weeds</source>. <name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Briese</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kriticos</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lonsdale</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, editors. <publisher-name>CSIRO Entomology</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc><year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Invasive <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>: Biology, ecology and management</article-title>. <source>Acta Phytotaxonomica Sinica</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>884</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>900</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Selected weeds of the United States</chapter-title>
<source>U.S. Department of Agriculture Handbook</source>
<fpage>366</fpage>: <publisher-name>Government Printing Office</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C</publisher-loc>; <year>1970</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Maddox</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hennesse</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blackbur</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Insects to control alligatorweed&#x02014;invader of aquatic ecosystems in United States</article-title>. <source>Bioscience</source>. <year>1971</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>985</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>&#x00026;</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biological control of alligator weed, Alternanthera philoxeroides, the world's first aquatic weed success story</article-title>. <source>Castanea</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>. <source>Probable evolution and morphological variation in South American Disonychine flea beatles (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) and their Amaranthaceous hosts</source>. <publisher-name>Agricultural Research service, US Department of Agriculture</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><year>1979</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrington</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frampton</surname><given-names>CMA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Influence of temperature on adult longevity, oviposition and fertility of Agasicles hygrophila Selman &#x00026; Vogt (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae)</article-title>. <source>New Zealand Journal of Zoology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Ecologieal adatation of the introduced biocontrol agent,Agasicles hygrophila, for Alternathera philoxeroides in China</article-title>. <source>Chinese Acadamy of Agricultural Sciences</source>. <year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Geographical diversification of growth-defense strategies in an invasive plant</article-title>. <source>Journal of Systematics and Evolution</source>. <year>2013a</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Poorter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niklas</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oleksyn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mommer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biomass allocation to leaves, stems and roots: meta-analyses of interspecific variation and environmental control</article-title>. <source>The New phytologist</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>193</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2011.03952.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22085245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22085245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pearcy</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muraoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Crown architecture in sun and shade environments: assessing function and trade-offs with a three-dimensional simulation model</article-title>. <source>The New phytologist</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>800</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15869642?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15869642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Photoreceptor signaling networks in plant responses to shade</article-title>. <source>Annual review of plant biology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-050312-120221</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23373700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23373700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>DeWalt</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Denslow</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamrick</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biomass allocation, growth, and photosynthesis of genotypes from native and introduced ranges of the tropical shrub <italic>Clidemia hirta</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>138</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 14689299?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14689299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Can&#x000f5;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Escarre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blanco-Moreno</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sans</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name>. <article-title>Increased fitness and plasticity of an invasive species in its introduced range: a study using Senecio <italic>pterophorus</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ecology</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>468</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Do higher resource capture ability and utilization efficiency facilitate the successful invasion of exotic plant? A case study of <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic>
</article-title>. <source>American Journal of Plant Sciences</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller-Sch&#x000e4;rer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution in invasive plants: implications for biological control</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Flory</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Invasive Microstegium populations consistently outperform native range populations across diverse environments</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 22352164?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22352164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bossdorf</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muth</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gurevitch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pigliucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Jack of all trades, master of some? On the role of phenotypic plasticity in plant invasions</article-title>. <source>Ecology Letters</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>981</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16913942?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16913942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plasticity of <italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic> seedling growth to light and water resources: Inter- and intraspecific comparisons</article-title>. <source>Basic and Applied Ecology</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pigliucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Manipulative approaches to testing adaptive plasticity: Phytochrome-mediated shade-avoidance responses in plants</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>S43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>van Kleunen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Constraints on the evolution of adaptive phenotypic plasticity in plants</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>166</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15760350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15760350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Aphalo</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ballare</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scopel</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Plant-plant signalling, the shade-avoidance response and competition</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>340</issue>):<fpage>1629</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bossdorf</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prati</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Auge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Reduced competitive ability in an invasive plant</article-title>. <source>Ecology Letters</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>346</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Can saliva from moose, Alces alces, affect growth responses in the sallow, Salix caprea?</article-title>
<source>Oikos</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>96</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0139234.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abrahamson</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of resource availability on tolerance of herbivory: A review and assessment of three opposing models</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17253430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17253430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>