<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">UOG activities, including drilling, hydraulic fracturing, and wastewater removal and storage, can contaminate surface and ground water with endocrine-disrupting chemicals (EDCs), defined as exogenous chemicals that can interfere with normal hormone action [(
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>) and reviewed in (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>)]. We have previously observed an association between endocrine-disrupting activity in surface water and UOG activities. For example, we measured greater antagonistic activities for the estrogen, androgen, progesterone, thyroid, and glucocorticoid receptors immediately downstream of a UOG wastewater disposal facility relative to upstream (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>). Our laboratory has reported that prenatal exposure to a laboratory-created mixture of 23 UOG chemicals was associated with altered organ weights, reproductive endpoints, and body weight in adult offspring of gestationally-exposed C57BL/6 mice, suggestive of developmental programming (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). Previous studies on hydraulic fracturing flowback and produced water also support the hypothesis that UOG chemical mixtures can alter fetal development, as developmentally-exposed zebrafish exhibited reduced reproduction, developmental malformations, and developmental toxicity (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>). Additionally, a systematic review by Elliot et al. found that 40% of 240 UOG chemicals with publicly-available reproductive and/or developmental toxicity information had been shown to exhibit developmental toxicity (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>).
</p>
