<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Few studies on biochemical properties of 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia</italic> varieties are reported [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Thus, leaf essential oils from three herbaceous members of the Asteraceae family, 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia fulgida</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia hirta</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Symphyotrichum novae-angliae</italic>, were obtained by hydrodistillation and analysed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. The main components in the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia fulgida</italic> were found to be the sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (germacrene D (30.1%) and δ-cadinene (17.8%)); similar composition was reported in the case of leaf oil of 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia hirta</italic>, with 23.6% germacrene D and 16.2% δ-cadinene. The leaf oils of these extracts were found to be inactive for antimicrobial activity [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Another study reports the chemical composition, minerals, and antioxidative effect of 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia laciniata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. General component of 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia laciniata</italic> is crude protein. The highest content of minerals is potassium, followed by calcium and magnesium, suggesting that 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia laciniata</italic> was alkaline material. The content of total phenolic and flavonoid compounds and DPPH· radical scavenging activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia laciniata</italic> were also reported. The chemical profile of 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia hirta</italic> was established by thin-layer chromatography (TLC) technique and by means of the total content of polyphenols [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. As about the therapeutic actions of the species of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia</italic>, they are relatively varied. The active compounds or extracts of these plants exhibit anti-inflammatory effects (
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia hirta</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], antimycobacterial (
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia subtomentosa</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], antileukemic (
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia mollis</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], antitussive (
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia fulgida</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], antioxidant, antibacterial, antiviral, antifungal, and cytotoxic activities (
 <italic class="italic">Rudbeckia laciniata</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>].
</p>
