<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the patents, Earle et al. designed an alginate-based coating formulation commercially known as Flavor-Tex
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> [
 <xref rid="B203-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">203</xref>,
 <xref rid="B204-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">204</xref>]. Meat, seafood, and poultry products were immersed into an aqueous dispersion of water-soluble algin and carbohydrate comprising mono and/or disaccharide sugar and gelatinized with a CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-CMC solution (the addition of CMC to the calcium crosslinking bath reduced the gelling time and required concentration of the CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) [
 <xref rid="B203-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">203</xref>,
 <xref rid="B204-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">204</xref>]. Lazarus, West, Oblinger, and Palmer [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]; West, Lazarus, Oblinger, and Palmer [
 <xref rid="B24-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]; and Williams, Oblinger, and West [
 <xref rid="B114-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>] evaluated the effects of Flavor-Tex
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> on lamb carcasses and beef pieces/steaks. Although calcium alginate coating acted as a sacrificing agent rather than a moisture barrier, maintaining a lower water activity (a
 <sub class="sub">w</sub>) on the surface together with the toxic effect of CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> lead to lower microbial counts [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. Nevertheless, the coating helped to stabilize the meat color, reduced shrinkage and obtained the same sensory scores compared to the uncoated meat samples [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. Flavor-Text was also used to coat pork patties for solving the flavor and texture problems of precooked meat products [
 <xref rid="B205-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>]. Coating decreased the oxidative rancidity, cooking losses, and increased meat tenderness. To the contrary of the findings presented previously [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], calcium alginate coated row and precooked products received the highest sensory scores, which indicated that the higher structural integrity given by the coating was favored by consumers [
 <xref rid="B205-foods-07-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>].
</p>
