<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preclinical studies: The ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>C. pluricaulis</italic> and its ethyl acetate and aqueous fraction at the dose of 100 and 200 mg/kg, p.o showed memory enhancing properties in Cook and Weidley’s Pole Climbing Apparatus, passive avoidance paradigms and active avoidance tests [
 <xref rid="B237-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>]. Convolvine, a chemical constituent of 
 <italic>C. pluricaulis</italic> potentiated the effect of arecoline (memory enhancer) and improved cognitive dysfunction in AD [
 <xref rid="B238-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>,
 <xref rid="B239-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">239</xref>]. Sharma et al. [
 <xref rid="B240-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>] also reported that the ethanolic extract at 100 and 200 mg/kg oral dose significantly improved memory in young and aged mice but the retention was better in young mice. 
 <italic>C. pluricaulis</italic> also possesses antioxidant and hypolipidemic effects, which may be partially responsible for improvement in cognitive function [
 <xref rid="B190-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>,
 <xref rid="B241-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. pluricaulis</italic> administration for 3 months at the dose of 150 mg/kg prevented aluminum chloride induced neurotoxicity by decreasing AChE activity, reducing oxidative stress and preserving the activity of ChAT and Nerve Growth Factor-Tyrosine kinase A receptor (NGF-TrkA) [
 <xref rid="B242-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">242</xref>]. Alcoholic extract of 
 <italic>C. pluricaulis</italic> Choisy (leaves) showed Aβ production inhibition in-vitro [
 <xref rid="B243-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">243</xref>]. Additionally, isolated bioactive coumarins from 
 <italic>C. pluricaulis</italic> ameliorated scopolamine induced amnesia in mice [
 <xref rid="B244-brainsci-10-00964" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>]. Despite detailed experimental studies, the herb has not been evaluated clinically.
</p>
