<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The central composite design (CCD) component of the RSM (free trial of Design Expert 10.0.6.0; Stat-Ease, Godward St NE, Minneapolis, MN, USA) was used to develop the experimental matrix of the batch adsorption study. The adsorption test was conducted at a temperature (27 °C) while the pH (6 to 7), sorbent dosage (2 to 6 g) and contact time (10 to 100 min) where varied accordingly. The adsorption experiments were conducted in a set of plastic Erlenmeyer flasks (250 mL) containing an equal volume of POME sample, 100 mL, following the experimental matrix. The treated samples were placed in the isothermal incubator shaker set at agitation speed and temperature of 150 rpm and 27 °C, respectively. All the treated samples were filtered before the final concentration analysis using 0.47 μm filter paper. After that, the filtrates were used for the final ADMI colour concentration analysis using the DR/4000-U spectrophotometer at 700 nm wavelengths. Each of the experiments was replicated three times to improve the accuracy of the results by taken the average. The summary of the experimental design for the colour adsorption study is shown in 
 <xref rid="ijerph-15-02200-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. Subsequently, the percentages of colour removal were determined using Equation (1):
 <disp-formula id="FD1-ijerph-15-02200" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">Removal</mi>
     <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
     <mi class="mi">Percentage</mi>
     <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mo class="mo">(</mo>
      <mo class="mo">%</mo>
      <mo class="mo">)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">C</mi>
        <mi class="mi">i</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">C</mi>
        <mi class="mi">f</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">C</mi>
        <mi class="mi">i</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo class="mo">×</mo>
     <mn class="mn">100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm2" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
      <mi class="mi">i</mi>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is the initial ADMI colour concentration and 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm3" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">C</mi>
      <mi class="mi">f</mi>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is the final ADMI colour concentration.
</p>
