<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="fsn31015-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">To study the nutritional composition of Indian 
  <italic class="italic">Moringa oleifera</italic> seed and the antioxidant activity of 
  <italic class="italic">M. oleifera</italic> seed polypeptide, Indian 
  <italic class="italic">M. oleifera</italic> seed was used as raw material for composition analysis and content determination. After extraction of the seed protein, enzymatic hydrolysis with flavourzyme, dispase, papain, pepsin, and alcalase was conducted for different time, and the optimal enzymatic hydrolysis conditions was determined with DPPH scavenging capacity as an indicator. The seed polypeptides obtained by enzymatic hydrolysis were ultrafiltered, and the active peptide fragments were tracked with DPPH, HO (•OH), ABTS and superoxide anion (O
  <sub class="sub">2</sub>•
  <sup class="sup">−</sup>) free radical scavenging ability and lipid oxidation inhibition rate as indicators. The results showed that the protein content in Indian 
  <italic class="italic">M. oleifera</italic> seed was high to 40.34%, containing seven essential amino acids. The content of macroelements such as potassium, sodium, and magnesium is high, with the potassium content as high as 2,357.71 mg/kg, among the microelements, the iron content as high as 36.2 mg/kg. The optimum enzymatic hydrolysis conditions were as follows: enzymatic hydrolysis with flavourzyme (50°C, pH 6.7) for 300 min, and DPPH scavenging capacity was 84.76%. Activity tracing found that the polypeptide fragment with molecular weight &lt;3.5 kDa had the strongest antioxidant capacity, and the EC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> values of DPPH, •OH, ABTS, and O
  <sub class="sub">2</sub>•
  <sup class="sup">−</sup> free radical scavenging rates were 4.0, 4.2, 5.3, and 4.3 mg/ml, respectively. The above results show that Indian 
  <italic class="italic">M. oleifera</italic> seed not only has high nutritional value, but its protease enzymatic hydrolyzate also has significant antioxidant activity, which can be further developed into nutrition products, healthcare products, functional foods, beauty and skin care products, liver protection drugs, etc.
 </p>
</abstract>
