<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To a similar extent, De Simone et al. have recently proposed a series of HDAC/GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic> inhibitors here represented by compound 
 <bold>52</bold> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17">Figure 17</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. As already mentioned, GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic> plays a central role in the pathogenic mechanisms of AD through the phosphorylation of pTAU, and the close connection between the latter and HDACs has already emerged. For instance, the neurotoxicity induced by HDAC1 has already been linked to GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic> activity [
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>], while the enhanced phosphorylation of HDAC6 by GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic> has been connected with an increase in the activity of this HDAC and pTAU phosphorylation [
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Compound 
 <bold>52</bold> is a combination of pharmacophoric elements where the HDAC-interacting part is once again represented by hydroxamic acid while the phthalimide-like scaffold served as the binder for the ATP-site of GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic>. This analogue is able to inhibit HDAC1, HDAC6, and GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic> in the low micromolar range of concentration (12.78, 3.19, and 2.69 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, respectively). SH-SY5Y cells were used to determine the effect of this compound 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, by analyzing the level of acetylation of tubulin and histone H3 at lysins 9 and 14, and the phosphorylation of pTAU. Treated cells showed hyperacetylated 
 <italic>α</italic>-tubulin, while no effect was observed on AcH3K9 or K14, highlighting a preferential action through HDAC6; pTAU hyperphosphorylation induced by copper was counteracted by 10 
 <italic>μ</italic>M concentrations of 
 <bold>52</bold>. Despite the fact that HDAC inhibitors are used as anticancer agents, the molecule was safe in this cell line up to 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, and it was also able to efficiently contrast H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative stress, with an effect also on the levels of p53 expression. Moreover, compound 
 <bold>52</bold> was able to promote neurogenesis, as confirmed by the induced expression of recognized markers of neurogenesis such as GAP43, N-myc, and MAP-2, and it had an immunomodulatory activity on microglia, producing a shift from neurotoxic to neuroprotective phenotype. Starting from 50 
 <italic>μ</italic>M, a clear effect on zebrafish development was also observed and correlated to the inhibition of GSK-3
 <italic>β</italic>. Although additional studies have to be assessed, the profile of compound 
 <bold>52</bold>, coupled with its low MW and high solubility, make it a promising hit compound for the development of innovative AD-modifying agents.
</p>
