<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A nice example of PDE inhibitors coupled with a multifaceted activity against A
 <italic>β</italic>-induced toxicity and metal-chelating/antioxidant properties came from the work of Hu et al. (
 <bold>55</bold> and 
 <bold>56</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig17">Figure 17</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. They proposed hybrid compounds merging the metal ion chelating framework of chloroquine and the key binding site fragments of the known PDE4 inhibitors Rolipram and Roflumilast, already tested in preclinical models of AD [
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>] (see also 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01433666" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT01433666</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT02051335" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT02051335</ext-link>). The result was a series of novel (halo)hydroxyquinolines linked via an amidic bond to di-alkoxy-substituted aryls, which resulted to be a 
 <italic>μ</italic>M inhibitor of PDE4D. Differently from the reference compounds, these analogues exerted a good antioxidant activity in the ORAC assay (comparable to Clioquinol) and showed the ability to chelate metals, including Cu
 <sup>2+</sup>, Zn
 <sup>2+</sup>, and Fe
 <sup>2+/3+</sup>, with a stoichiometry of 2 : 1 ligand : metal in the case of Cu
 <sup>2+</sup>. The PAMPA test assessed the potential of these analogues to be brain penetrant and cross the BBB, thus prompting the author to perform further analysis. In the Cu
 <sup>2+</sup>-ascorbate system, no significant production of ROS was observed after coincubation with the compounds, preventing Cu redox by metal chelation. A similar effect was observed in SH-SY5Y cells where besides the lack of a cytotoxic effect, there was a concentration-dependent protective effect against BuOOH-induced intracellular oxidative stress. The effects on metal-induced A
 <italic>β</italic> aggregation were evaluated, and both the ThT and TEM analysis confirmed that title compounds influenced Cu-induced aggregation. Being safe up to 2000 mg/kg dose and relatively stable in liver microsomes, some compounds were also tested 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> in the Morris water maze test, performed with mice affected by A
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>25-35</sub>-induced cognitive dysfunction. Compared to the reference PDE inhibitors, the results indicated an enhancement in cognitive spatial memory and behavioral performances, in addition to a protecting effect on hippocampal neurons. Clearly, these structures represent promising candidates for the development of a novel class of anti-AD agents.
</p>
