<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The egg white is a gel-like structure that lacks lipids and is composed mainly of water (about 88%) [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-00684-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>), fibrous structural proteins (ovomucins), glycoproteins (ovalbumin, protease inhibitors), antibacterial proteins (lysozyme), and peptides (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1-nutrients-11-00684" class="xref">Section 3.1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. The average volume of egg white is estimated to be 30 mL (for an egg weighting 60 g, eggshell included) and protein concentration is about 110 mg/mL of egg white. In total, 150 distinct proteins have been identified in egg white [
 <xref rid="B35-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], knowing that the very abundant ovalbumin accounts for 50% of the total egg-white proteins. The physiological function of this protein in egg remains unknown but ovalbumin is assumed to provide essential amino-acids for the chicken embryo growth. Egg-white ovalbumin thus represents a valuable source of amino-acids for human nutrition. Besides ovalbumin, egg white is concentrated in antibacterial lysozyme that is currently used as an anti-infectious agent in many pharmaceuticals and as food preservative (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1-nutrients-11-00684" class="xref">Section 3.1</xref>). The viscous aspect of egg white is essentially due to ovomucin [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Remarkably, egg white is also characterized by the presence of four highly abundant protease inhibitors [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] that may delay digestion of egg components, especially when egg white is used as a raw ingredient in some food preparations.
</p>
