<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some of the reports describe investigations on 
 <italic>Kalanchoe</italic> species, which are more and more popular as house ornamental plants. These plants have antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, and cytotoxic properties. However, only 
 <italic>K. brasiliensis</italic> Camb. has been described as a remedy in human prostate cancer treatment (Johnson 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). Studies on cytotoxic activities of 
 <italic>Kalanchoe</italic> plants containing bufadienolides are focussed on main isolated metabolites. For example, bryophyllin B (from 
 <italic>K. pinnata</italic> (Lam.) Pers.) has strong cytotoxic activity on the KB cell line (Yamagishi et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>). Kalanchosides A–C (from 
 <italic>K. gracilis</italic> Hance) revealed toxic activity on lung (A549), prostate (PC-3), epidermoid (A431), and ovarian (1A9) cancer cell lines (Wu et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Bufadienolides isolated from the leaves of 
 <italic>K. pinnata</italic> and 
 <italic>K. daigremontiana</italic> × 
 <italic>tubiflora</italic> (Harv.) Raym.-Hamet &amp; H. Perrier showed antitumor-promoting activity on Burkitt’s lymphoma Raji cells (Supratman et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Kalantuboside A and B, bryotoxin C, bersaldegenin-1-acetate, and bersaldegenin-1,3,5-orthoacetate from 
 <italic>K. tubiflora</italic> showed significant effects against oral adenosquamous carcinoma (Cal-27), lung adenocarcinoma (A549), promyelocytic leukaemia (HL-60), and melanoma (A2058) cell lines (Huang et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). In our previous study on 
 <italic>K. daigremontiana</italic>, bersaldegenin-1,3,5-orthoacetate (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>) demonstrated strong cytotoxic activity on cervical (HeLa), ovarian (SKOV-3), melanoma (A375), and breast (MCF-7) cell lines (Stefanowicz-Hajduk et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Some of the above mentioned bufadienolides have determined the molecular mode of cell death. However, the pathway of bersaldegenin compounds has not yet been described.
</p>
