<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECAM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Evidence-based Complementary and Alternative Medicine : eCAM</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1741-427X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1741-4288</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7671816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/3862642</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of the Antibacterial and Antioxidant Activity of <italic>Mimosa rubicaulis</italic> and <italic>Reinwardtia indica</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2701-7227</contrib-id><name><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>Roshani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8501-0256</contrib-id><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>Sundar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5968-4051</contrib-id><name><surname>Parajuli</surname><given-names>Kalpana</given-names></name><email>kalpanaprjl@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, School of Health and Allied Sciences, Pokhara University, Pokhara-30, Kaski 33700, Nepal</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editor: Man Hee Rhee</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2020</volume><elocation-id>3862642</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Roshani Gurung et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Many plants have the property of wound healing, but most of the people are using costly allopathic medicine for the wound. This might be due to lack of awareness about the traditional uses and lack of scientific study of ethnomedicinal plants. So, this study aimed to carry out the antibacterial and antioxidant activity of two medicinal plants which are used traditionally for wound healing activity, i.e.,<italic>Mimosa rubicaulis</italic> and <italic>Reinwardtia indica.</italic> Different parts of <italic>Mimosa rubicaulis</italic> (root, stem, and leaves) and <italic>Reinwardtia indica</italic> (flower and leaves) were used for the study. Extractions were done by maceration using ethanol as solvent. Antibacterial activity was carried out by the well diffusion method, and antioxidant activities were screened by DPPH radical scavenging and NO scavenging assays. Extract of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> has shown a weak zone of inhibition towards <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> whereas <italic>R. indica</italic> has shown no zone of inhibition towards selected bacterial strains. Leaf, root, and stem extracts of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> have shown potent antioxidant activity, i.e., IC<sub>50</sub> value of 9.8&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, 10.19&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, and, 13.64&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, respectively. Similarly, leaf extract of <italic>R. indica</italic> exhibited antioxidant activity with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 19.73&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml. The percentage inhibition of NO radicals of root and stem of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> and leaves of <italic>R. indica</italic> was 31%, 21%, and 22%, respectively. Out of these two plant species, <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> had shown antibacterial activity towards selected microorganism, but antioxidant activity was shown by both plant species. These properties on above mentioned two plant species might help for the development of a marketed formulation for antibacterial and wound-healing agent since wound healing is promoted by antibacterial and antioxidant activities.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Pokhara University</funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>In developing countries, infectious diseases due to bacteria are the main causes of morbidity and mortality among the general population [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In the present context, various antibiotics have been discovered for the treatment of infectious diseases. It was assumed that infectious diseases will no longer exist after the discovery of antibiotics [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, the increased use of antibiotics has led to the drug-resistant strain of bacteria which in turn has resulted in the emergence of new infectious diseases. So, it is a necessity and challenge to develop new antibiotics with novel mechanisms of action to overcome the problem of antibiotic resistance [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Today's another issue is that many people in this fast-growing world are suffering from diseases such as heart disease, cancer, Alzheimer's disease, neurological disorders, hypertension, diabetes mellitus, renal failure, liver diseases, and early aging [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] due to exposure on various exogenous sources such as radiations, various toxic chemicals, and pollution [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. That might be due to the generation of free radicals [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] which are capable of attacking the healthy cells of the body, causing them to lose their structure and function [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>An antioxidant is a molecule that inhibits the oxidation of other molecules and terminates the chain reactions of free radicals by donating an electron or hydrogen atom to free radical causing the stable chemicals [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Free radicals can be scavenged by the in vivo production of antioxidant compounds, but the endogenous antioxidants are insufficient to remove them completely and maintain a balance. As a result, dietary antioxidants are required to counteract excess free radicals [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Different phytochemicals are present in plants such as terpenoids, aromatic and aliphatic compounds, carbohydrates, lactams, peptides, and quinines where these chemicals are responsible for antimicrobial activity of some plants [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Some plants have natural antioxidant activity as they may contain vitamin C, vitamin E, carotenes, flavonoids, isoflavones, anthocyanin, catechin, and isocatechin [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Due to the presence of such phytochemicals, plants are widely used as medicine ethnomedicinally. The primary benefits of using plant-derived medicines are relatively safer with fewer side effects than synthetic alternatives, offering profound therapeutic benefits and more affordable treatments [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Although plants have traditional uses as medicine, which are safer for use, most of the people use allopathic medicine for their primary healthcare. Also, traditionally used plants have not been extensively studied scientifically yet. So, the main aim of this study was to determine the antibacterial and antioxidant activity of <italic>Mimosa rubicaulis</italic> and <italic>Reinwardtia indica</italic> which are used for wound-healing activity traditionally.</p><p>
<italic>Mimosa rubicaulis</italic> belongs to the Leguminosae family. It is a straggling shrub. Traditionally, it is used in peptic ulcer, dislocated bone, sprains, backache, hemorrhoids, wound, and fever [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. <italic>Reinwardtia indica</italic> belongs to the Linaceae family. It is an erect perennial herb about 1&#x02009;m high. Traditionally, plant is applied to boils, headaches, scabies, wounds, bee stings, insect's bites, and thorn stabs [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>2.1. Plant Material</title><p>Different parts of plant samples, i.e., root, stem, and leaves of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic>, and flower and leaves of <italic>R. indica</italic> were collected from Pokhara Valley, Nepal. Proper identification of plants was done under the supervision of local traditional healers. The collected samples of crude drugs were properly identified by the botanist Prof. Dr. Radhe Shyam Kayastha and preserved in the Pharmacognosy Laboratory of School of Health and Allied Sciences, Pokhara University, Nepal.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>2.2. Chemicals</title><p>Ascorbic acid (Loba Chemie), dimethyl sulphoxide (Alpha Chemika), 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) (Wako Pure Chemical), methanol (Fischer Scientific), Muller Hilton Agar (Himedia Laboratories), N-(1-naphthyl)ethylenediamine (NEDD) (Loba Chemie), sodium nitroprusside (Fischer Scientific), and all the other required chemicals were obtained from various chemical suppliers as well from the Laboratory of School of Health and Allied Sciences, Pokhara University, Pokhara-30, Kaski, Nepal.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>2.3. Extraction</title><p>Shade-dried samples were extracted by a double maceration process using ethanol as solvent. For this, 25&#x02009;g of each sample was weighed and macerated in 175&#x02009;ml ethanol (ethanol: crude drug&#x02009;=&#x02009;7&#x02009;:&#x02009;1) for 24&#x02009;hr. After 24&#x02009;hr, filtration was done by using filter paper and the obtained residue was again macerated with 175&#x02009;ml, i.e., the same volume of ethanol for 24&#x02009;hr. Then, obtained filtrates were mixed and solvent evaporation was done by using a rotatory vacuum evaporator and collected in the Petri dish. Again, the samples were kept in a vacuum desiccator for the complete removal of the solvent present in the extract. The obtained dried extracts were collected in a sample vial. They were labeled with symbols using alphabetical letters and preserved in the refrigerator.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Antibacterial Activity</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>3.1. Bacterial Strain and Its Growth Condition</title><p>The bacterial strains, i.e., one Gram-positive bacterium, <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and two Gram-negative bacteria, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Proteus vulgaris</italic>, were obtained from the National Public Health Laboratory (NPHL), Kathmandu, and growth conditions were maintained according to the method described previously [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] with some modifications.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>3.2. Well Diffusion Method</title><p>The well diffusion method was done to determine the antibacterial activity of plant extract according to the method described previously [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] with some modifications. Wells (8&#x02009;mm diameter and about 2&#x02009;cm apart) were made in each of the plates using a sterile cork borer. A stock solution of each plant extract was prepared at a concentration of 1&#x02009;mg/ml and 2&#x02009;mg/ml in 10% dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) solution. A volume of 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l of stock solution of plant extract was added by sterile syringe into the wells and allowed to diffuse at room temperature for 2&#x02009;hr. Ofloxacin and cefpodoxime were taken as positive control where 10% DMSO solution was taken as a negative control. Then, medium plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;hr in an incubator. After 24&#x02009;hr, zones of inhibition were measured.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>3.3. Antioxidant Activity Assay</title><p>The antioxidant activity of the plant extract was determined using DPPH radical scavenging assay and nitric oxide (NO) radical scavenging assay methods.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>3.4. DPPH Radical Scavenging Assay</title><p>DPPH is a free radical-generating compound which is used to determine the radical scavenging activity of extracts. It is a rapid, simple, and inexpensive method to measure antioxidant capacity. The odd electron in the DPPH free radical gives a strong absorption maximum at 517&#x02009;nm and has a deep purple color [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>DPPH free radical assay was performed according to the method described previously [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] with some modifications. In brief, 2&#x02009;ml of different extract solution was mixed with 2&#x02009;ml of DPPH solution (60&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>M) and allowed to stand for 30 min. Then, absorbance of each plant samples was measured at 517&#x02009;nm by using a UV spectrophotometer. Radical scavenging activity of each sample was calculated by using the following formula:<disp-formula id="EEq1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>radical&#x02009;scavenging&#x02009;activity&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext/><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext/></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>0</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;absorbance of control and <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>S</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;absorbance of a sample. Control is the test solution without a sample. A similar process was done with an ascorbic acid solution of concentrations (100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml, 10&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml, and 1&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml). Ascorbic acid was taken as a positive control.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>3.5. NO Radical Scavenging Assay</title><sec id="sec3.5.1"><title>3.5.1. Preparation of Griess Reagent</title><p>A total amount of 0.25&#x02009;g of NEDD was mixed in sufficient deionized water to produce 250&#x02009;ml of 0.10% of the NEDD solution. Then, 1% sulfanilamide solution was prepared by dissolving 2.50&#x02009;g of sulfanilamide in 5% phosphoric acid to produce 250&#x02009;ml. Finally, 500&#x02009;ml of Griess reagent was prepared by mixing NEDD solution and sulfanilamide solution which was then stored in a refrigerator and used before 8&#x02009;hr.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5.2"><title>3.5.2. Determination of NO Radical Scavenging Assay</title><p>In NO scavenging assay, incubation of solutions of sodium nitroprusside in phosphate buffer saline at 250&#x000b0;C for 2.5&#x02009;hr resulted in a linear time-dependent nitrite production [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The quantities of NO produced is determined using Griess reagent by the development of purple to pink color during the diazotization of nitrite with sulfanilamide and its subsequent coupling with NEDD. The absorbance is observed at 548&#x02009;nm on UV spectrophotometer [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>NO radical scavenging activity was measured by the method described previously [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] with slight modifications. In brief, 1&#x02009;ml of test samples of different concentrations were taken in a test tube and mixed with 1&#x02009;ml of sodium nitroprusside (5&#x02009;mM) solution and test tubes were incubated for 2.5&#x02009;hr at 29&#x000b0;C. After 2.5&#x02009;hr, 2&#x02009;ml Griess reagent was added to each test tubes and absorbance was measured at 548&#x02009;nm in a UV spectrophotometer after 30&#x02009;min incubation at room temperature. The radical scavenging effects of test samples were calculated by the following formula:<disp-formula id="EEq2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>radical&#x02009;scavening&#x02009;activity</mml:mtext><mml:mtext/><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>o</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;absorbance of control and <italic>A</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;absorbance of sample.</p><p>Control is the test solution without the test sample. A similar process was done for curcumin solution used as positive control, i.e., standard solution.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>4. Results</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>4.1. Extraction Yield Value</title><p>The extract yield % was calculated using equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq3">3</xref>). The extract yield % of the plant sample is shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The extract yield percentage was relatively higher in root and leaves of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic>, and flower of <italic>R. indica</italic> while relatively lower in the stem of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> and leaves of <italic>R. indica</italic>.<disp-formula id="EEq3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext/><mml:mtext>yield</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>weight&#x02009;of&#x02009;extract&#x02009;yield</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>weight&#x02009;of&#x02009;crude&#x02009;sample&#x02009;taken</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>4.2. Antibacterial Activity</title><p>Each of different parts of plant extract, i.e., root, stem, and leaves of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic>, and flower and leaves of <italic>R. indica</italic> were used to measure and compare the zone of inhibitions with the standard antibiotics ofloxacin and cefpodoxime at a concentration of 1&#x02009;mg/ml and 2&#x02009;mg/ml in 10% DMSO in test microorganisms, i.e., two Gram-negative bacteria, which are <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>P. vulgaris</italic>, and one Gram-positive bacteria, which are <italic>S. aureus</italic>. The standard drug, ofloxacin had shown zone of inhibition towards <italic>E. coli</italic> (45&#x02009;mm), <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> (48&#x02009;mm), and S. <italic>aureus</italic> (34&#x02009;mm), respectively. Similarly, cefpodoxime had shown zone of inhibition towards <italic>E. coli</italic> (36&#x02009;mm), <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> (34&#x02009;mm), and S. <italic>aureus</italic> (24&#x02009;mm), respectively. The root extract of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> was found to have a weak zone of inhibition towards <italic>S. aureus</italic>, i.e., 12&#x02009;mm, and leaves and stem extracts were found to have a weak zone of inhibition towards <italic>P. vulgaris</italic>, i.e., 11&#x02009;mm and 11&#x02009;mm, respectively. However, the flower and leaves extract of <italic>R. indica</italic> were found to have no zone of inhibition towards the selected bacteria even in 2&#x02009;mg/ml of concentration. At a concentration of 1&#x02009;mg/ml, none of the extracts had shown a zone of inhibition towards the selected organism.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>4.3. Antioxidant Activity</title><sec id="sec4.3.1"><title>4.3.1. DPPH Radical Scavenging Activity</title><p>The result of the DPPH radical scavenging assay is shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>. Among the studied plant extracts, root, leaves, and stem extracts of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> exhibited high antioxidant activity in DPPH free radical scavenging assay as 89%, 88%, and, 81%, respectively, in 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml. The half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) value of leaves extract was 9.80&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml. Similarly, the IC<sub>50</sub> value of root extract and stem extract was found to be 10.19&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml and 13.64&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, respectively, which was very close to that of standard (ascorbic acid) as 9.99&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml. The leaves extract of <italic>R. indica</italic> exhibited DPPH radical scavenging assay as 34% with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 19.73&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, but flower extract of <italic>R. indica</italic> exhibited low antioxidant activity, i.e., 4% with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 165.36&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml. IC<sub>50</sub> is defined as the amount of antioxidant required to inhibit 50% of DPPH free radicals under the experimental conditions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>4.4. NO Scavenging Activity</title><p>The NO scavenging activity of different plant extracts was determined by using Griess reagent. Sodium nitroprusside was used as nitric oxide-producing agent. The root and stem of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> and leaves of <italic>R. indica</italic> had shown NO scavenging activity at higher concentrations (100&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml), i.e., 31% and 21% and 22%, respectively. The root, stem, and leaves extracts of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> had shown IC<sub>50</sub> value as slightly higher than that of standard drug curcumin as 0.23&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, 0.32&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, and 0.58&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, respectively. Similarly, the extract of <italic>R. indica</italic> had also exhibited higher IC<sub>50</sub> value to that of standard, which is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><p>The result of the IC<sub>50</sub> value of samples from DPPH scavenging assay against the DPPH free radical and NO scavenging assay against the nitric oxide free radical is in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Ascorbic acid had shown a good IC<sub>50</sub> value of 9.99&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml against DPPH free radical, but curcumin had exhibited an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.12&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml towards nitric oxide free radical. However, both the extracts of plant samples had shown IC<sub>50</sub> value nearly similar to that of standard as ascorbic acid and curcumin which is shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>5. Discussion</title><p>Antibacterial activities were assayed to determine the zone of inhibition towards <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>P. vulgaris</italic>, and <italic>S. aureus</italic> at a concentration of 1&#x02009;mg/ml and 2&#x02009;mg/ml. The root, stem, and leaves extract of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> were found to have a negligible zone of inhibition, but flower and leaves of <italic>R. indica</italic> were found to have no zone of inhibition as compared to the reference drug ofloxacin and cefpodoxime even at a concentration of 2&#x02009;mg/ml, but no zone of inhibition was shown by any selected plants extract at 1&#x02009;mg/ml which is shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. This activity was comparatively lower than that observed in methanolic leaves extract of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> by the agar diffusion method against Gram-negative (<italic>E. coli</italic>), at a concentration of 15&#x02009;mg/ml [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and methanolic root extract of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> at a concentration of 1000 mcg/ml (<italic>E. coli</italic>) by the cup plate method [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. No zones of inhibition were seen for both ethanolic leaves and root extracts of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> at 2&#x02009;mg/ml by using a well diffusion method towards <italic>E. coli.</italic> It may be due to the solvent effect as well as concentration effect.</p><p>The antioxidant activities were assayed by DPPH free radical scavenging and NO scavenging assays. The DPPH free radical is a simple and acceptable method to evaluate the antioxidant activity of plant extracts. The DPPH forms a stable molecule on accepting an electron or a hydrogen atom and thus has applications in the determination of radical scavenging activity of natural products as well as synthetic compounds [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The leaves, root, and stem extracts of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> exhibited high antioxidant activity by DPPH free radical scavenging assay with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 9.80&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, 10.19&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, and 13.64&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml, respectively, which was very close to that of standard (ascorbic acid) shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>. It may suggest that the extract might contain an electron donor molecule that reacts with free radicals to convert them to more stable products and terminate radical chain [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>NO is an important chemical mediator involved in the regulation of various physiological processes. NO or RNS (reactive nitrogen species) formed during their reaction with oxygen or with superoxides, such as NO<sub>2</sub>, N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>, and N<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> which are very reactive and are responsible for altering the structural and functional behavior of many cellular components [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Scavengers of nitric oxide compete with oxygen leading to reduced production of nitrite ions [<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Among the plant extract under study, the root extract of <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> showed the NO scavenging activity by 31% at 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml and other extracts showed less activity. The IC<sub>50</sub> value of both the plant samples had shown similar value to that of the standard drug, curcumin, which is shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The ability of the extract to generate the nitrite in decreased amount may be due to the capacity to decompose the sodium nitroprusside in vitro due to the presence of different phytoconstituents mainly phenolic compounds such as flavonoids responsible to scavenge the free radical by competing with the oxygen molecule of NO free radical, thus leading to antioxidant activity [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This activity was comparatively lower than that observed in water and carbinol extract of leaves of <italic>R. indica</italic> in previous studies [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] whereas ethanolic leaves extract of <italic>R. indica</italic> showed less activity in this study. This may be due to the solvent effect.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>6. Conclusion</title><p>Out of two plant species, <italic>M. rubicaulis</italic> had shown antibacterial activity towards <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> and <italic>S. aureus</italic>, but antioxidant activity was shown by both plant species. Antibacterial and antioxidant activities found in plant species might help in formulation development which could be marketed as antibacterial and wound-healing agents in future days.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to express their sincere thanks to Lecturer Suresh Jaiswal, Pokhara University, for helping them during the test of antibacterial activity. The authors would like to express their sincere thanks to Prof. Dr. Radheshyam Kayastha, Prithivi Narayan Campus, Tribhuvan University, for helping in the identification of plant samples. This is a part of the thesis work of Master of Pharmaceutical Sciences, and all the materials needed for research were fully supported by the Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Pokhara University.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The data will be available upon request to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors involved in this research declare that there are no conflicts of interest regarding the publication of this paper.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swati</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary phytochemical screening, antibacterial and nitric oxide radical scavenging activities of <italic>Reinwardtia indica</italic> leaves extract</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Pharm Tech Research</italic></source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1670</fpage><lpage>1678</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wajid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants as potential source of antimicrobial agents</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Pharmacy and Alternative Medicine</italic></source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valgas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>S. M. d.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sm&#x000e2;nia</surname><given-names>E. F. A.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Smania</surname><given-names>A.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Screening methods to determine antibacterial activity of natural products</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Brazilian Journal of Microbiology</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/s1517-83822007000200034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-34447128809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and free radical scavenging activities of <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic></article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Biological &#x00026; Pharmaceutical Bulletin</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>1335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.26.1331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-2142808700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12951481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antolovich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prenzler</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patsalides</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robards</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for testing antioxidant activity</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">The Analyst</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>127</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b009171p</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0036141823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudhe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity of ethanolic extract of <italic>Parthenium hysterophorus</italic> Linn</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Asian Journal of Pharmaceutical and Clinical Research</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide radical scavenging assay of bioactive compounds present in methanol extract of <italic>Centella asiatica</italic></article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Science Research</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5963/lsmr0201002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigelholf</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eugene</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Analytical Progress</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-oxidant activity and total phenolic content of some Asian vegetables</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Food Science and Technology</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2621.2002.00552.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0036106525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ijaz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Review on methods used to determine antioxidant activity</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Multidisciplinary Research and Development</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selvamohan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadas</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishore</surname><given-names>S. S. S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of selected medicinal plants against some selected human pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Advances in Applied Science Research</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>3374</fpage><lpage>3381</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manandhar</surname><given-names>N. P.</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic toggle="yes">Plants and People of Nepal</italic></source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Portland, OR, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Timber Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antimicrobial activity of different solvent extracts of medicinal plant: <italic>Melia azedarach</italic> L</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Current Pharmaceutical Research</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E.-J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of aqueous extract of Perilla frutescens on tert-butyl hydroperoxide-induced oxidative hepatotoxicity in rats</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Food and Chemical Toxicology</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1738</fpage><lpage>1744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2007.03.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-34547125977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17467864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glogowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skipper</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wishnok</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of nitrate, nitrite, and [15N]nitrate in biological fluids</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Analytical Biochemistry</italic></source><year>1982</year><volume>126</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(82)90118-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0020448709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7181105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karthik</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro nitric oxide scavenging activity of ethanol extract of <italic>Canthium coramandelium</italic></article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Pharma and Bio Sciences</italic></source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>P695</fpage><lpage>P700</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shakoor</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A. U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaib</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biological screening of <italic>Albizia lebbek</italic> L. and <italic>Mimosa himalayana</italic> gamble (mimosaceae)</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Medicinal Plant Research</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>735</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganji</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yedla</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial investigation on different root extracts of <italic>Mimosa rubicaulis</italic> Lam</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Pharmacognosy and Phytochemical Research</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhuiyan</surname><given-names>M. A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoque</surname><given-names>M. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free radical scavenging activities of methanol extracts of three Bangladeshi medicinal plants</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">The Pharma Innovation Journal</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petricevich</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity, total phenolic and flavonoid contents, and cytotoxicity evaluation of <italic>Bougainvillea xbuttiana</italic></article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">International Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical Sciences</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>502</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parul</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro nitric oxide scavenging activity of Portuguese shrubs: <italic>Pterospartum tridentatum, Cytisus scoparius</italic> and <italic>Erica</italic> spp.</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of Medicinal Plants Research</italic></source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>886</fpage><lpage>893</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehandzhiyski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batovska</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evstatieva</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Danova</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide scavenging activity of in vitro cultured Balkan medicinal and aromatic plants</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Bulgarian Journal of Agricultural Science</italic></source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Graphical representation of percentage scavenging of DPPH free radicals by extract and ascorbic acid (AA) at 517&#x02009;nm. The error bar represents the standard deviation of three independent determinations performed in triplicate of sample size (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2020-3862642.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Graphical representation of percentage scavenging of NO free radicals by extract and curcumin at 548&#x02009;nm. The error bar represents the standard deviation of three independent determinations performed in triplicate of sample size (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ECAM2020-3862642.002"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Extraction yield value and symbol code used for plant samples.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific name</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parts used</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample code</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage yield value (ethanol)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic>Mimosa rubicaulis</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stem</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<hr/>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>Reinwardtia indica</italic>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flower</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.95</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaves</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Result of IC<sub>50</sub> value of samples and standard drugs from DPPH scavenging activity and NO scavenging activity.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Samples</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPPH scavenging activity IC<sub>50</sub> (<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO scavenging activity IC<sub>50</sub> (<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>g/ml)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.64</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.73</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Curcumin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>