<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0020">For years Gawé Dorjé has been interested in differentiating specimens according to modern botanical taxonomic identification so as to elucidate the nuance in the Tibetan medical classification system that had previously incurred confusion in conversations with Western researchers when various distinctly identified specimens in the Tibetan taxonomical system fell under a single species or Latin nomenclature in the Western taxonomical system (see, for instance, a single 
 <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> Retz botanical identification for multiple types of 
 <italic>arura</italic> (
 <italic>a ru ra</italic>) from the Sowa Rigpa system). Dorjé was also interested in establishing clarifications on debates within the Tibetan medical field of specific materia medica identifications and elucidating distinctions for colleagues recognizing similar species and sub-species in traditional Chinese medicine and Ayurveda. His-text even includes the accepted Chinese name for each specimen since his main non-Tibetan interlocutors are Chinese medical physicians and researchers. This has the potential to create equivalences with TCM materia medica which may not be identical in terms of sourcing, processing, traditional classification and description. However, the attempt, again, is at creating bridges of discourse in both clinical and research settings. The dataset provided herein does not include nor reanalyze the Chinese identifications since the aim of this dataset is to provide the accepted Latin botanical names for the Tibetan identifications to an English-speaking research and clinical community. Due to his focus on providing a resource that facilitated rigorous engagement with the research community as well as a comprehensive materia medica compilation for practioners, Gawé Dorjé analyzed the materia medica literature thoroughly and substantiated his definitive identifications with related source texts and scholars, as well as his own analysis and consultation with relevant botanical, biological and geological experts.
</p>
