<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Aromatic plants are rich in essential oils with considerable antimicrobial properties. The aim of this study was to investigate chemical composition, antimicrobial activity and antioxidant properties of 
  <italic class="italic">Melissa officinalis</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Deracocephalum moldavica </italic>essential oils (EOs). The identification of chemical constituents of the EOs was carried out using gas chromato-graphy-mass spectrometry analysis and antimicrobial activity of the EOs was evaluated by disc diffusion assay as well as determination of minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimal bactericidal concentration against four important food-borne bacteria: 
  <italic class="italic">Salmonella typhimorium, Escherichia coli, Listeria monocytogenes </italic>and
  <italic class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. Antioxidant activity of the EOs was also determined by 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl, 2,2-azinobis 3-ethylbenzo thiazoline-6-sulfonic acid and β-carotene bleaching tests. The major compounds of 
  <italic class="italic">D. moldavica </italic>were geranial (28.52%), neral (21.21%), geraniol (19.60%), geranyl acetate (16.72%) and the major compounds of 
  <italic class="italic">M. officinalis</italic> EO were citronellal (37.33%), thymol (11.96%), citral (10.10%) and β-caryophyllene (7.27%). The underlying results indicated strong antimicrobial effects of the oils against tested bacteria. 
  <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> with the lowest MIC value (0.12 mg mL
  <sup class="sup">-1</sup>) for both EOs was the most sensitive bacterium, although, antibacterial effect of 
  <italic class="italic">M. officinalis</italic> EO was stronger than 
  <italic class="italic">D. moldavica</italic>. In addition, the results of the antioxidant activity showed that both EOs had notable antioxidant properties. In conclusion, both EOs are appropriate alternatives as potential sources of natural preservative agents with the aim of being applied in food industries.
 </p>
</abstract>
