<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Leishmaniasis is a vector-borne complex parasitic disease caused by obligate intramacrophagic protozoan parasite 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic>. Leishmaniasis is a major global health problem threatening almost 350 million people worldwide with about 1.2–2 million new cases reported annually.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>
 </sup> Leishmaniasis is manifested in three clinical forms: visceral, mucocutaneous, and cutaneous; the visceral form is the severest with approximately 500 000 new cases reported annually.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> Visceral leishmaniasis (VL) or kala azar, is a lethal, chronic neglected tropical disease caused by intracellular protozoan parasites 
 <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic> and 
 <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic>. VL is endemic in more than 80 countries; however, about 80% of new VL cases worldwide are reported from the Indian subcontinent (India, Nepal, and Bangladesh).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>
 </sup> If left untreated, VL becomes fatal. There is no vaccine available for human leishmaniasis. Currently, VL is treated using leishmanicidal drugs such as paromomycin, amphotericin B, liposomal amphotericin (AmBisome), and only available oral drug miltefosine (MIL).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>
 </sup> Initially, these drugs had shown promising efficacy, but current studies have reported relapse rates between 6.8 and 10.8% after 6 months post-chemotherapeutics in immunocompetent patients in India.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>
 </sup> The higher pathogenicity of 
 <italic>L. donovani</italic> was connected with both SSG treatment failure and relapse after MIL treatment.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>
 </sup> Drug resistance is another complication associated with the available chemotherapeutics. In addition, the available drugs have limitations like high cost, least availability, toxicity, and painful route of administration. Therefore, there is a need for new therapeutic options. Plants and their constituents had been in use for primary health care since ancient times. 
 <italic>Cassia fistula</italic> Linn belongs to the family Caesalpiniaceae usually known as Amulthus and has been broadly used for the treatment and prevention of diseases in different types of traditional medicines. It is also known as the golden shower and Indian laburnum.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>C. fistula</italic> is a very common plant known for its various medicinal properties and is native to South Asia and grown in other parts of the world. Animal model-based studies have shown that 
 <italic>C. fistula</italic> and their constituents play a role in disease management via modulation of biological activities.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>C. fistula</italic> has been reported to have antifertility,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>
 </sup> antipyretic, analgesic, anti-inflammatory, hypoglycemic effects, and antimicrobial activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
