<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The proportion of individuals choosing the EOs-treated chamber, in the behavioral assays were compared by likelihood chi-square test, with a null hypothesis of a 50:50 chance of insects choosing the control versus the EOs-treated chamber (SPSS 22.0, IBM SPSS Statistics, Armonk, North Castle, NY, USA). The median repellent concentration (RC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>) of the EOs against 
 <italic class="italic">S. zeamais</italic> adults was calculated by log-probit regressions. Significant differences between the RC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values of the two EOs were determined by relative median potency (RMP). Differences between the RC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values were considered statistically significant when RMP 95% confidence interval was ≠ 1.0 (SPSS 22.0, IBM SPSS Statistics, Armonk, North Castle, NY, USA). Differences in the latency time and the permanence time were analyzed by generalized linear models (GLM, Poisson loglinear model) by assessing the main effect of EO and concentration as predictors and calculating the estimated marginal means (EMMeans) (SPSS 22.0, IBM SPSS Statistics, Armonk, North Castle, NY, USA). EAG absolute responses (mv) of the two gender and to 
 <italic class="italic">C. nubigeum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. tomentosum</italic> essential oils, octanal and paraffin oil as control were compared by two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) considering the gender and the odor compound as main factors. F tests were used to assess the significance of the effects and their interactions. For significant factors, the Dunnett test was used to compare the response to each compound to those of the control (paraffin oil) [
 <xref rid="B36-insects-10-00171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Data obtained in the dose-response experiments and reported as relative responses to octanal (%) were analyzed separately for 
 <italic class="italic">C. nubigeum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. tomentosum</italic>, by two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) considering the gender and the concentrations as main factors. and by the unequal N Tukey honestly significant difference HSD test for multiple comparisons between the means [
 <xref rid="B36-insects-10-00171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. For significant factors, the Dunnett test was used to compare the response to each concentration to those of the control (paraffin oil) [
 <xref rid="B36-insects-10-00171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Before the analysis, Box–Cox transformations were used to reduce data heteroscedasticity [
 <xref rid="B37-insects-10-00171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Analysis were performed by the SPSS 22.0 software (IBM SPSS Statistics, Armonk, North Castle, NY, USA).
</p>
