<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In African countries, the baobab tree (
 <italic class="italic">Adansonia digitata</italic> L.) has been extensively used for centuries as a source of food, medicine, and fodder (Sidibe &amp; Williams, 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). In Sudan, the dry pulp of the fruit is consumed fresh or is dissolved in water as a fermenting agent in local brewing or as a sauce in food (Abdalla, Mohammed, &amp; Mudawi, 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). The fruit pulp is regarded as a good source of vitamin C, pectin, polyphenols (epicatechin and procyanidin), carotenoids, fatty acids (linoleic and oleic), and major minerals including calcium, magnesium, and phosphorus, good quality protein (Kabore et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). In addition, it has antioxidant, antimicrobial, antiviral, and anti‐inflammatory potentials and has been used extensively in African and Asian traditional medicine to cure several diseases such as diarrhea, microbial infections, malaria, and fever (De Caluwé, Halamová, &amp; Van Damme, 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Domestic processing conditions of baobab fruits to produce juice or fermented products have been previously investigated (Parkouda, Ba/Hama, Ouattara/Songre, Tano‐Debrah, &amp; Diawara, 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Parkouda et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Tembo, Holmes, &amp; Marshall, 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Uncontrolled heat treatments and storage conditions have great influences on the bioactive compounds of baobab fruit juice (Tembo et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). In the natural fermentation of Maari, a fermented baobab seed product largely prepared and consumed in western Africa, several aerobic mesophilic and lactic acid bacteria (LAB) were involved (Parkouda et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), and the process resulted in several biochemical changes in amino acids and fatty acids of Maari (Parkouda et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3913-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). However, there is insufficient information on the utilization of fermented baobab fruit pulp as starter culture for fermentation of cereal‐based products.
</p>
