<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">With the exception of the animal by-product diet, diets containing ≥5% fish meal and ≥5% fish oil gave the same final weight, and length gain, probably because the minimum level of essential fatty acids was provided [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. However, as with the ω3LC0 diet, the animal by-product diet resulted in significantly lower growth despite containing 5% fish meal and 5% fish oil, which may relate to lipid oxidation. While muscle in fish fed the animal by-product diet was expected to be less exposed to lipid oxidation due to the lower content of PUFAs (
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.t007" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 7</xref>), the TBARS results revealed that these fish muscle samples were oxidized significantly more than the ones fed ω3LC1.41. This may reflect the types of materials used for animal by-products and how they were handled. Nonetheless, the oxidation results suggested that lipid rancidity was not high in any of the three diet treatments studied, as the TBARS values were significantly lower than the results of other studies on salmon (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]). A TBARS value of about 16.5 mg MDA kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> was obtained in [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] after 6 days, while the TBARS values in this study did not exceed 3.13 mg MDA kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> (mean of 1.52 mg MDA kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>). Also, lower levels of animal by-products may be well tolerated. It was shown in [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] that 7% inclusion of porcine blood meal had no negative effects on salmon performance compared with fish meal based control diets. The animal by-product diet also resulted in the lowest concentrations of muscle triacylglycerols which is consistent with the down-regulation of fatty acid synthesis in the livers of these fish [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>].
</p>
