<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While five of the treatments gave no significant difference in muscle DHA and EPA concentrations the two with the lowest and highest levels of fish oil did give significant differences, as expected ([
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]). This resulted in significant regressions between 20:5ω3 and 22:6ω3 in diets and muscle tissues. The slope of the regression line for dietary content of 20:5ω3 and 22:6ω3 against their contents in muscle tissue indicates the extent of this dependency. The higher slope for 22:6ω3 (0.30 mg g
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> wet weight) compared to 20:5ω3 (0.08 mg g
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> wet weight) showed that 22:6ω3 was deposited four times more than 20:5ω3 in muscle tissue. A similar result was observed when fish oil was replaced with crude palm oil in Atlantic salmon diets [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], where 22:6ω3 (slope = 0.81) was more deposited than 20:5ω3 (slope = 0.58) in muscle tissues when proportions (% total fatty acids) were compared. Similar to other studies (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]), the concentration of long chain MUFAs (20:1ω9 and 22:1ω11(13)) in the muscle tissues were highest for fish fed marine based diets (2.81 mg g wet weight
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> total). However, unlike the previous studies in which the replacement of marine based ingredients generally resulted in lower proportions of long chain MUFAs, the use of other diets led to statistically the same concentrations of 20:1ω9 and 22:1ω11(13) in muscle as when marine based diets were fed, with a couple of exceptions (
 <xref rid="pone.0198538.t007" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 7</xref>). The difference in the results here to those previously probably relates to the determination of concentrations 
 <italic class="italic">versus</italic> proportions.
</p>
