<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At present, the discovery of new compounds was urgent but very difficult from common environments (e.g., soils) [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Researchers have focused on the selection of antimicrobial substances from microorganisms in other ecosystems, particularly those in special habitats, such as marine microorganisms and endophytes [
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In our research, ethyl acetate extracts of 13 endophytic fungi (10% of total screened strains) showed inhibitory activity against pathogenic microorganisms. Most of the 13 isolates represent fungal genera, including 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, 
 <italic>Diaporthe</italic>, and 
 <italic>Trichoderma</italic>, previously reported to produce antimicrobial compounds [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, new bioactive compounds are constantly being discovered from plant endophytes. For instance, a new cadinene-sesquiterpenes and seven of its analogues were isolated from an endophytic fungus, 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic>, which was isolated from a toxic medicinal plant, 
 <italic>Tylophora ovate</italic> [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Guo et al. isolated a new antibacterial secondary metabolite (Diaporone A) from the plant endophytic fungus 
 <italic>Diaporthe</italic> sp. [
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Seven previously unreported cyclonerane derivatives were isolated from the culture of 
 <italic>Trichoderma asperellum</italic> A-YMD-9-2, an endophytic fungus obtained from the marine red alga 
 <italic>Gracilaria verrucosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-21-05958" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In addition, it is noteworthy that the strain F8157 (
 <italic>Thanatephorus cucumeris</italic>, an opportunistic pathogen) showed antibacterial and antifungal activity, which is reported firstly in this study, and has the potential research value.
</p>
