<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to the Biopharmaceutical Classification System (BCS), the bioavailability of pharmaceuticals delivered orally is influenced by their solubility and intestinal permeability. The BCSII includes low-solubility groups that cause drug absorption via the gastrointestinal tract to be the limiting factor in terms of bioavailability, which can be useful in achieving suitable blood levels [
 <xref rid="B8-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Emulsion formulations have the potential to enhance the solubilization of BCSII drugs. The solubility and bioavailability of BCSII drugs can be improved with certain kinds of delivery systems, such as those involving microencapsulation, nanoemulsion, solid lipid nanoparticles, and self-emulsifying drug-delivery systems (SEDDS). Self-emulsifying drug-delivery systems are composed of a given drug, oils, surfactants, and sometimes co-solvents. Self-emulsifying drug-delivery systems consist of emulsion concentrates, but they are not themselves emulsions [
 <xref rid="B8-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. However, when they are subjected to mild agitation in the aqueous environment of the stomach, they easily form stable emulsions. Self-emulsifying drug-delivery systems have been marketed in the form of liquid or semisolid products, but these forms have a few shortcomings, especially in terms of the manufacturing process. These shortcomings have led to the development of SEDDS in solid-dosage forms, which besides offering improved solubility, also offer further advantages over liquid forms, such as minimizing gastrointestinal tract irritation without lowering drug bioavailability [
 <xref rid="B8-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. In the market, SEDDS formulations of Tretinoin, Cyclosporin A, and Saquinavir have already been introduced as commercial products [
 <xref rid="B9-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Emulsification combined with gelation has been suggested as an alternative means of encapsulating several compounds, including sensitive or hydrophobic biologicals. Together, emulsification and gelation provide an inert environment, which allows the embedded drugs to maintain greater biological activity and to have strong stability for the duration of their shelf life [
 <xref rid="B9-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-marinedrugs-17-00156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
