<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="fsn3535-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</div>
 <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0012" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Efficiency of oil extraction process after pretreatments with PEF and microwave</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison of data means, using Duncan's test indicated that use of PEF and microwave pretreatments in this research led to an increase in the efficiency of oil extraction process (Figure 
   <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0001">1</a>). Also, it was specified that those samples pretreated by microwave had a higher oil extraction efficiency in comparison with other samples. This could be attributed to the increased fracture of cell walls which contain oil during treatment with microwave (Uquiche, Jeréz, &amp; Ort, 
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0042">2008</a>). Also, Mohamed and Awatif (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0031">1998</a>) reported that the higher efficiency of oil extraction through heating with microwave may be resulted from destruction of protein components. Our findings conformed to the results of Momeny et al. (2012), and Nde, Boldor, and Astete (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0032">2015</a>). On the other hand, Schroeder, Buckow, and Knoerzer (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0036">2009</a>) expressed that applying PEF leads to an improvement in extraction efficiency because of electrical decomposition of cells and their higher permeability. Our results were in agreement with the results of Guderjan, Topfl, Angersbach, and Knorr (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0014">2005</a>).The morphological analysis by Scanning Electron Microscopy (Figure 
   <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0002">2</a>) confirmed that application of PEF and microwave pretreatments will lead to disintegration of cells and consequently better extraction of oil from them.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The influence of various pretreatments on the efficiency of oil extraction process from black cumin seed</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SEM</span> micrographs of the control sample (a), the treated sample with pulsed electric fields (b) and the treated sample with 
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">MW</span> (c)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0013" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Influence of PEF and microwave pretreatments on physical properties of black cumin seed oil</div>
  <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0014" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Refractive index</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The refractive index is usually used as a criterion for oil purity. This parameter will increase with higher chain length (however the relation is not a linear one) and the nonsaturation level. Different oils and fats have their own and particular refractive indices, so this feature is used to identify and determine the purity of oils and fats (Bakhshabadi et al., 
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0007">2017</a>). The refractive index is useful in controlling the progress of reactions such as hydrogenation and catalytic isomerization of oils. Also, it is used to recognize the oil oxidation too, and the temperature and saturation are some factors that influence the refractive index (Malek, 
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0026">2001</a>).As shown in Figure 
    <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0003">3</a>, applying various pretreatments didn't have any significant influence on the refractive index of black cumin oil (
    <span class="italic">p</span>&gt;.05) and for all samples about 1.469. Haroon et al. (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0500" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0500">2014</a>) stated that based on the variety, the refractive index of black cumin oil is ranged from 1.4697 to 1.4730, which conformed with our results. Bakhshabadi et al. (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0007">2017</a>) attributed no changes in refractive index of oils obtained from microwave process to the similarity of fatty acid compositions in the nontreated and treated samples. Also, Gorji et al. (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0012">2016</a>) through studying the physicochemical properties of orange seed oil extracted by various methods, indicated that modern extraction technologies in comparison with common and usual methods, do not change physical properties of oils such as refractive index.
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The influence of various pretreatments on the refractive index of black cumin seed oil</p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0015" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.2</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oil density</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It was found that different pretreatments in oil extraction from black cumin led to an increase in oil density (Figure 
    <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0004">4</a>). When the microwave and PEF were used, the oil density was increased 1.51% and 0.96%, respectively in comparison with samples that didn't have any pretreatments. Likely, this increase can be attributed to the more decomposition of seed cell walls and increase in resulted particles within the oil. Anjum, Anwar, Jamil, and Iqbal (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0003">2006</a>) reported that microwave leads to a higher oil density that was inconsistent with the findings of Uquiche et al. (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0042">2008</a>) and Kittiphoom et al. (2015). Theoretically, density is not an important property but economically it is very important. Although the oil shipments are sold on the basis of their weight but they are measured on the basis of their volume and also their relationship is defined by density. This parameter is not similar for all the oils and it is dependent on the composition of fatty acids, the trace and low compounds that exist in oil, and also the temperature (Hamm, Hamilton, &amp; Calliauw, 
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0015">2013</a>).
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The influence of various pretreatments on the oil density of black cumin seed</p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0016" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.3</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The color index of extracted oils</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analysis of variance indicated that the influence of pretreatment type on the color index of oils extracted from black cumin seeds was completely significant (
    <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;.01). Comparing the means of data obtained from samples (Figure 
    <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0005">5</a>) revealed that the color index ranged between 82.1–155.34. As it is clear, the use of PEF and microwave pretreatments caused an increase in the color index of black cumin oil and the maximum color index was obtained for microwave pretreatment. The increase in color index can be attributed to the fracture of plant tissues during treatment and therefore more extraction of the pigments. In this regard, Lee, Oh, Chang, and Kim (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0023">2004</a>) studied the influence of different temperatures of parching the safflower seeds on its oil color. They stated that formation of color in oil was under the influence of parching temperatures in such a manner that when the temperature is increased, the oil color would change from light yellow to dark brown. Also, Kim et al. (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0020">2002</a>) reported a distinct color increase in the rice bran oil at higher parching temperatures. Megahad (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0029">2001</a>) attributed the increase in color in peanut oil as the result of treating the seeds with microwave to the nonenzymatic browning reactions and destruction of phospholipids during the parching process; so an increase in the brown components can be occurred together with elevation of other components as a result of decomposition of phospholipids. Guderjan, Elez‐Martínez, and Knorr (
    <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0013">2007</a>) observed similar results at the time of using PEF.
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The influence of different pretreatments on the color index of black cumin seed oil</p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0017" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Influence of PEF and microwave pretreatments on the oxidative stability of produced oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oxidative stability is the time required to reach a point in which one oxidation index such as peroxide value or carbonyl number increases suddenly and it causes an undesirable taste and aroma in the oil. There are several methods to evaluate the chemicals resulted from heating processes which have so many influences on the quality and nutritional properties of oils, and the oxidative stability index is the most important one (Holser, 
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0016">2003</a>). Measurement of oxidative stability index alone during the heating processes of oils is not sufficient to evaluate the quality of oils, but it gives some information about the initial situation of oil sample (Matthaus, 
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0028">2006</a>). As can be seen in Figure 
   <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0006">6</a>, our results indicated that PEF and microwave pretreatments increased the oxidative stability of black cumin seed oils; the highest oxidative stability obtained with PEF treatment and then, with the microwave pretreatment. This can be explained by the increase in tocopherols and other antioxidant components in extracted oils as a result of these pretreatments. More details will be provided later in section 3.5. Spielmeyer, Wagner, and Jahreis (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0038">2009</a>) and Guderjan et al. (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0013">2007</a>)found similar results and claimed that use of different pretreatments leads to an increase in oxidative stability of extracted oils.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The influence of different pretreatments on the oxidative stability of black cumin seed oil</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0018" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The meal protein of black cumin seeds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The optimum use of required protein for body is dependent to the digestibility and pattern of essential amino acids in the foods(Taghizadeh, Asemi, Shaker Hoseini, Aminpour, &amp; Valaiee, 
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0040">2007</a>). On the other hand, pricing the meals in the oil extraction companies is performed on the basis of their protein and moisture level (Rostami, Farzaneh, Boujmehrani, Mohammadi, &amp; Bakhshabadi, 
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0034">2014</a>).We found that the influence of PEF and microwave pretreatment on the amount of protein in meals was completely significant (
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;.01). Comparing the means of data (Figure 
   <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0007">7</a>) indicated that the maximum and minimum protein levels were related to the samples treated by microwave and the control, respectively. In other words, use of PEF and microwave treatments in oil extraction caused an increase in the protein of meal compared with the sample which didn't have any pretreatments. The reason of this phenomenon can be attributed to the extraction of more oil from the seeds and consequently, increase in the percentage of remaining proteins in the meals. Choi, Choi, Chun, and Moon (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0008">2006</a>) and Sarkis et al. (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0035">2015</a>) reported an increase in the amount of extracted protein by the microwave and PEF methods, respectively.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The influence of different pretreatments on the amount of protein in the meals of black cumin seed</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-15" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3535-sec-0019" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of different pretreatments on the chemical compositions of oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results revealed that the influence of PEF and microwave pretreatments on the amount of chemical components of oil samples were quite significant (
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;.01). As it is clear in Table 
   <a rid="fsn3535-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#fsn3535-tbl-0001">1</a>, in all samples, the amount of thymoquinone was higher than other components and this is the dominant phenolic component in the black cumin oil. Thymoquinone has probably some antioxidant, anti‐inflammatory, and anti‐cancer properties and can inhibit and control the oxidative stresses (Khan &amp; Sharma, 
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0019">2003</a>). According to Table 
   <a rid="fsn3535-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#fsn3535-tbl-0001">1</a>, it can be stated that when PEF was used as a pretreatment, much more components were extracted into the oil. After thymoquinone, cymene was the main component and it was completely conformed to the results of El Dakhakhny, Barakat, Abd El Halim, and Aly (
   <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0010">2000</a>). Some of these components were not observed in the control samples without any treatments; probably these components remain in the seed but when the microwave or PEF pretreatments were used, these components found their way into the oil.
  </p>
  <div id="fsn3535-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The influence of different pretreatments on the chemical composition of black cumin seed oil</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <thead valign="top">
     <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
      <th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Compound</th>
      <th align="left" colspan="3" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Treatment</th>
     </tr>
     <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MW</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEF</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cymeme</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymoquinone</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclopropanemethanol, α., 2‐di methyl‐2‐(4‐methyl‐3‐pentenyl)</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2‐Amino‐4,6‐dihydroxypyrimidine,N,O,O′‐tris(trifluoroacetyl)</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclohexanol</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorine compounds</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">β‐Pinene</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D‐Limonene</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longifolene</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">γ‐Terpinene</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="fsn3535-note-0001" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Numbers with different letters in each row imply significant differences in the 5% level of probability.</p>
    </fn>
    <fn id="fsn3535-note-0002" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PEF, pulsed electric fields.</p>
    </fn>
   </div>
   <div class="permissions">
    <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
