<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="fsn3535-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oils and fats are important nutrients in the case of health and also in business. Due to these reasons, much research and investment are allocated to study them. Oils and fats are responsible to supply a significant part of required energy for body, necessary fatty acids, and fat‐soluble vitamins (Kebriti, HoseiniMazhari, Gerami, Ghiassi, &amp; Esfandyari, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0018">2011</a>). Recently, with the growth and increase in general knowledge, the demand for health‐promoting oils in addition to energy supply increased. On the other hand, utilization of available sources and cultivation of underexplored oilseeds is a step toward providing more functional oils in the food industry. Oils and fats are prepared from various plant and animal sources of which have different metabolic, physical and chemical properties (Zomorrodi, Shokrani, Shahedi, &amp; Dokhani, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0045">2003</a>). Black cumin (
  <span class="italic">Nigella sativa L</span>.) variety is an annual herbaceous with a short‐life term, that is, particular to the semiarid areas. Thymoquinone is detected as one of the main phenolic components of black cumin with antioxidant properties (Al‐Othman, Ahmad, Al‐Orf, Al‐Murshed, &amp; Arif, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0002">2006</a>; Yar, El‐Hariri, El‐Bahai, &amp; Bamosa, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0043">2008</a>). The antioxidant compounds have shown their activities via different mechanisms (Farzaneh &amp; Carvalho, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0011">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are various conventional methods to extract oil from oilseeds such as extraction with solvents through various extractors or extraction by mechanical approach such as pressing. Generally, oil extraction with pressing is a simple, safe and economical technology; therefore the advantages of this method makes it more efficient compared to solvent application approach. The mechanical method is used for oilseeds with high oil content. Applying this method solely is not sufficient and high amounts of oil remain in the meal which should be extracted by solvents. Oil extraction by pressing is done in hot or cold conditions. The yield of oil extracted in hot pressing is higher than cold pressing but because of elevated temperatures during hot pressing, the quality of the obtained oil is low while the oil obtained through cold pressing maintains its natural properties with limited chemical reactions. For this reason, the demand for oils obtained from cold pressing increased (Singer, Nogala‐Kalucka, &amp; Lampart‐Szczap, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0037">2008</a>). In oil extraction with cold pressing, several factors such as pressing pressure, seed moisture and process temperature, should be considered in the efficiency of extracted oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In modern technologies, it is tried to perform the extraction process more easily and effectively in such a manner of solvent usage, extraction time and temperature could be reduced while the extraction efficiency can be improved economically (Li, Pordesimo, &amp; Weiss, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0024">2004</a>). In the oil extraction process, appropriate pretreatments of seeds before oil extraction is one of the most important and necessary steps to produce a high‐ quality oil with a high efficiency (Azadmard‐Damirchi, Habibi, Hesari, Nemati, &amp; Fathi, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0006">2010</a>). Therefore, recently some techniques such as extraction with supercritical solvents (Meireles &amp; Angela, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0030">2003</a>), ultrasound (Dolatabadi et al., 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0009">2016</a>; Jalili, Jafari, Emam‐Djomeh, Malekjani, &amp; Farzaneh, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0017">2017</a>; Lou, Wang, Zhang, &amp; Wang, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0025">2010</a>), microwave pretreatments (Bakhshabadi et al., 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0007">2017</a>), and pulsed electric fields (Zeng, Han, &amp; Zi, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0044">2010</a>) have been investigated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The microwave, nonionized electromagnetic waves with 300 MHz to 300 GHz frequency are placed between radio and infrared waves in the electromagnetic spectrum. These waves are made of two oscillating vertical fields, which are electrical and magnetic fields. In this procedure, heating is occurred in a determined and chosen procedure without temperature waste and dissipation in the environment, it means that it is similar to heating in a closed system. This heating mechanism leads to a lower extraction time in comparison with common and usual oil extraction methods. The influence of this procedure is through two phenomena of ionic transfer and dipolar rotation and mostly, both of them are occurred simultaneously (Mandal, Mohan, &amp; Hemalatha, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0027">2007</a>). The energy of microwave penetrates into the food and generates internal temperatures, leading to a more heating rate and shorter procedure time. The oilseeds have high moisture content as a dipolar material, although in this case some other materials, including salts and proteins can also act as the dielectric components (Sultana, Anwar, &amp; Przybylski, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0039">2007</a>). The procedure of pulsed electric fields (PEF) has more advantages toward, using the common heating procedures for foods, because its application leads to maintain the original color, aroma and taste, texture and nutritional value of foods. Furthermore, PEF might increase the speed and efficiency of the extraction. PEF has been used in deactivation of microorganisms in milk, dairy products, egg, water, and other food materials (Qin, Chang, Barbosa‐Cfinovas, &amp; Swanson, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0033">1995</a>). Sarkis et al. (
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0035">2015</a>) used the PEF and high voltage electrical discharge as the pretreatment in oil extraction from sesame seeds with the purpose of destructing the cell wall and increasing the oil extraction efficiency. Their results indicated that when the output energy of high voltage process increases, the destruction index might increase and also these two procedures lead to an increase in oil extraction efficiency. Tale Masouleh, Asadollahi, and Eshaghi (
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0041">2015</a>) used the PEF as the pretreatment for oil extraction from sesame seeds. Their findings revealed that PEF assists the procedure of oil extraction from sesame seeds with the use of cold pressing and an electric field with intensity of 1 kV/cm and pulse power equals to 50 might led to the maximum efficiency. La et al. (
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0022">2016</a>) used the PEF to produce fat from microalgae. They used the PEF with a low energy in their research and expressed that this procedure can be an appropriate replacement for common and usual methods of fat extraction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To the best of the authors’ knowledge, there are no studies on the application of PEF and microwave as pretreatments in oil extraction from black cumin seeds. Therefore, the objective of the current research was to study the influence of applying novel technologies as the pretreatments in the oil extraction of black cumin seeds and their influence on the physicochemical properties and chemical composition of the final extracted oil.</p>
</sec>
