<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="fsn3535-sec-0018" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The meal protein of black cumin seeds</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The optimum use of required protein for body is dependent to the digestibility and pattern of essential amino acids in the foods(Taghizadeh, Asemi, Shaker Hoseini, Aminpour, &amp; Valaiee, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0040">2007</a>). On the other hand, pricing the meals in the oil extraction companies is performed on the basis of their protein and moisture level (Rostami, Farzaneh, Boujmehrani, Mohammadi, &amp; Bakhshabadi, 
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0034">2014</a>).We found that the influence of PEF and microwave pretreatment on the amount of protein in meals was completely significant (
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;.01). Comparing the means of data (Figure 
  <a rid="fsn3535-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#fsn3535-fig-0007">7</a>) indicated that the maximum and minimum protein levels were related to the samples treated by microwave and the control, respectively. In other words, use of PEF and microwave treatments in oil extraction caused an increase in the protein of meal compared with the sample which didn't have any pretreatments. The reason of this phenomenon can be attributed to the extraction of more oil from the seeds and consequently, increase in the percentage of remaining proteins in the meals. Choi, Choi, Chun, and Moon (
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0008">2006</a>) and Sarkis et al. (
  <a rid="fsn3535-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3535-bib-0035">2015</a>) reported an increase in the amount of extracted protein by the microwave and PEF methods, respectively.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="fsn3535-fig-0007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The influence of different pretreatments on the amount of protein in the meals of black cumin seed</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-15" xlink:href="FSN3-6-111-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
