<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Lyme disease (LD) is a multisystem disorder caused by certain species of spirochetes from the 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">sensu lato</italic>) complex. Since all 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> species are host-propagated bacteria that move between a vertebrate host and tick vector, the spirochetes have developed strategies to sense and survive in these diverse environments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>]. Survival is achieved by altering the level of gene expression in response to changes in temperature, pH, salts, nutrient content, multiple host and vector dependent factors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Nutrients, especially carbon sources, and/or their metabolic by-products seem to provide regulatory and chemotactic signals that guide the spirochete as it moves between hosts and vectors. The spirochetes that are exposed to antibiotic treatment are able to survive by regulation of the differential expression of genes involved in spirochete pathogenicity and the mechanism of persister formation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. However, the change in gene expression level is not the only route to spirochete survival. Signals that 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> receives from hostile environments evoke morphological alterations that keep the pathogen alive and induce the production of atypical forms or persisters that are refractory to elimination. The formation of persisters 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> is a reversible process that establishes the basis for disease recurrence when the hostile pressure drops [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>].
</p>
