<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An alternative hypothesis for how SI plants overcome mate limitation during colonization is that biparental inbreeding may increase mate availability, relative to incompatibility among all related individuals, enough to overcome Allee effects. Biparental inbreeding is mating among related individuals. Self-incompatibility is controlled by a group of tightly linked genes, the 
 <italic>S</italic>-locus, and fertilization is prevented by an SI response that is activated when individuals with shared alleles interact. There are two major types of SI, gametophytic (GSI), and sporophytic (SSI) (Busch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">2012</xref>). In GSI, alleles are codominant, whereas alleles can be dominant, codominant, or recessive in the SSI system. Male gametophytes from SSI plants express the parental diploid phenotype and often exhibit dominance that allows some mating among individuals with a single shared allele (Brennan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">2010</xref>) which may increase mate availability relative to an SI system without dominance (Brennan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">2003</xref>). Matings permitted among relatives due to dominance among 
 <italic>S</italic>-alleles may represent an intermediate option between self-incompatibility and self-compatibility. This is fundamentally different from a mixed mating strategy in which both self-fertilization and outcrossing occur regularly (Winn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">2011</xref>). Dominance interactions that allow biparental inbreeding may be a viable strategy to increase mate availability in the short term to allow successful colonization of sites after long-distance dispersal events such as invasions (Brennan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">2003</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">2010</xref>; Lafuma and Maurice 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">2007</xref>) without forfeiting the long-term fitness benefits of maintaining a SI mating system.
</p>
