<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">In 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> cv. Sis 6001, although some nematodes penetrated and established in the roots, there was actual reproduction in only one replicate of the first bioassay. The reduced number of nematodes found in the roots may be related to the existence of exudates or compounds produced by the roots of this cultivar that prevent J
 <sub>2</sub> penetration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. This type of resistance occurs before the nematode penetrates the root (i.e. pre-infection) and is called passive
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. From analysis of the results of other authors, 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> presents great variability, both between and within cultivars. In some cases, resistant and susceptible plants may co-exist within the same cultivar
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. In Ali et al. (1992), for 
 <italic>M. incognita</italic>, although 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> was invaded by nematodes which formed some (4–5) swellings (not real galls), the nematodes did not develop beyond J
 <sub>2</sub> and there was no egg mass production
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Similar results were also reported by Fassuliotis &amp; Bhatt (1982), possibly due to a tracheid discontinuity, due in turn to the formation of a small, thin-walled giant cell. However, for 
 <italic>M. javanica</italic>, using regenerated plants rather than seeds, 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> demonstrated low resistance
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Some reports do not mention the 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> cultivar and 
 <italic>Meloidogyne</italic> species used and 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> may react differently to different species of 
 <italic>Meloidogyne</italic>. As reported by Daunay &amp; Dalmasso (1985), 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> was a poor host for 
 <italic>M. arenaria</italic> and 
 <italic>M. incognita</italic> but it was a better host for 
 <italic>M. javanica</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, caution should be taken when choosing the 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> cultivar to control RKN because the results can change with the cultivar and/or the nematode species considered. The effects of some 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> cultivars, or their plant extracts, on hatching, infectivity and/or reproduction of PCN, RLN and RKN has also been demonstrated by other authors with positive results
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
