<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">In this study, it was demonstrated that 
 <italic>S. linnaeanum</italic> can reduce RKN densities in the soil. Its roots attract 
 <italic>M. chitwoodi</italic> juveniles, removing them from the soil but at the same time reducing the reproduction of the nematodes. The fact that the nematodes developed into males, without females, avoids the risk of reproduction or leaving a dangerous, viable population of nematodes in the soil. Since the number of J
 <sub>2</sub> that hatch and penetrate the roots is high, the population density of nematodes in the soil decreases and even those that hatch but do not enter the roots will die. In that way, the use of 
 <italic>S. linnaeanum</italic> as a trap crop, in a crop rotation system, or even as rootstocks, may be an appropriate component of Integrated Pest Management, keeping RKN populations at levels low enough not to cause economic losses, thereby increasing production and crop quality and avoiding or limiting the use of synthetic nematicides. Using a trap crop does not disturb the ecological balance in the soil and the extensive and deep root systems of 
 <italic>S. linnaeanum</italic> grow deeper into the soil than nematicides can penetrate. 
 <italic>Solanum linnaeanum</italic> could be a good alternative to other PPN control measures but more studies are required, including field studies. The crop should be completely removed before flowering or incorporated into the soil as green manure before seeds are produced, preventing it from becoming invasive in areas where it does not yet exist. Also, different conditions should be tested to investigate whether the resistance of the plants is stable at different temperatures. There are no known uses for this plant in Portugal. In this way, it may be possible to find a use for a plant that, despite having existed in Portugal for many years, was only ever considered a weed. In this study, resistance to 
 <italic>M. chitwoodi</italic> in another cultivar of 
 <italic>S. sisymbriifolium</italic> (cv. Sis 6001) was also confirmed.
</p>
