<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia</italic> essential oil was purchased from Huile &amp; Sens (Crestet, France). Terpinen-4-ol was purchased from Sigma (Sigma-Aldrich S.r.l. Milan, Italy). The essential oil was analyzed by gas chromatography–flame ionization detector (GC–FID) and gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC–MS). GC–FID analyses were performed using a Perkin Elmer Sigma-115 gas chromatograph with a data handling system and an FID. Analyses were carried out using an HP5 fused silica column (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d.; 0.25 µm film thickness). The operating conditions were as follows: injector and detector temperatures, 250 °C and 280 °C, respectively; oven temperature program, 5 min isothermal at 40 °C, then at 2 °C min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> up to 250 °C and finally held isothermally for 20 min. Aliquots of 1 µL were injected manually at 250 °C and in the splitless mode. Analysis was also run by using a fused silica HP Innowax polyethylene glycol capillary column (50 m × 0.20 mm i.d.; 0.20 µm film thickness). In both cases, helium was used as the carrier gas (1 mL min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). A diluted sample (1/100 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>, in 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane) of 1 µL was injected manually at 250 °C and in the splitless mode. GC–MS analyses were carried out using a Hewlett-Packard 5890 A gas chromatograph connected on line to an HP mass selective detector (MSD 5970HP), equipped with an HP-1 fused-silica column (25 m × 0.25 mm i.d.; 0.33 µm film thickness); GC and GC–MS conditions: ionization voltage 70; electron multiplier energy 2000 V. Gas-chromatographic conditions were as reported above; transfer line was kept at 295 °C. Most constituents were identified by GC by comparison of their Kovats retention indices (Ri) (determined relative to the tR of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkanes (C
 <sub class="sub">10</sub>–C
 <sub class="sub">35</sub>)), with either those of the literature [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-23-02672" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-23-02672" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-23-02672" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-23-02672" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] and mass spectra on both columns with those of authentic compounds available in our laboratories by means NIST 02 and Wiley 275 libraries [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-23-02672" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. The component relative concentrations were obtained by peak area normalization. No response factors were calculated.
</p>
