<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27" class="p">We have consistently shown that ethanol extract of hemp leaves of Nigeria origin causes gonadotoxicity in male rats by eliciting hyperprolactinemia, down-regulation of HPT axis, oxidative stress, and endocrine disruption [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. The improvement in semen parameters by BHE in this study is contrary to our previous reports and expectation, and thus of great surprise and interest to us. Because environmental variables of the soil at different location have been known to affect plant species composition and richness [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>], we speculate that the discrepancy in our previous and current findings could result from different origins of the hemp samples used in both studies. We queried this speculation further by determining the GC-MS composition of acetone and n-hexane fractions of the ethanol extract of Nigerian hemp used for our previous studies. We confirmed the presence of α-linolenic acid in the acetone fraction only, but linoleic acid in both fractions. Furthermore, both fractions have cannabinoids including cannabichromene, THC, and cannabinol. It is interestingly worthy of note that these cannabinoids accounts for about 58% of the total composition of the acetone fraction but 75% of the n-hexane fraction of the Nigerian hemp. However, the BHE contains only cannabinol at very negligible quantity (1.2%) but no cannabichromene and tetrahydrocannabinol. Because both hemp samples from these two different locations gave varying GC-MS composition despite the same extraction method (using Soxhlet apparatus), it could be opined that the discrepancy in the composition is not related to the methods of extraction but related to the climatic difference of the origin of both hemp samples.
</p>
