<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY5382 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?FILEsi2 svg ?><?FILEsi3 svg ?><?FILEsi4 svg ?><?FILEsi5 svg ?><?FILEsi6 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7610326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(20)32225-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e05382</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e05382</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of phytochemicals, minerals and <italic>in vitro</italic> medicinal activities of bael (<italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> L.) pulp and differently dried edible leathers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>Sudipta Kumar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>Tanmay</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Salauddin</surname><given-names>Molla</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>Hassan I.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Pati</surname><given-names>Siddhartha</given-names></name><email>patisiddhartha@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>Runu</given-names></name><email>crunu@hotmail.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Food Technology and Biochemical Engineering, Faculty of Engineering and Technology, Jadavpur University, Jadavpur, Kolkata 700032, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Malda Polytechnic, West Bengal State Council of Technical Education, Govt. of West Bengal, West Bengal 732102, India</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Faculty of Fisheries and Food Science, University MalaysiaTerengganu, 21030, Kuala Nerus, Terengganu, Malaysia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Research Divisions, Association for Biodiversity Conservation and Research (ABC), Balasore, 756001 Odisha, India</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Institute of Tropical Biodiversity and Sustainable Development, University Malaysia Terengganu, 21030 Kuala Nerus, Terengganu, Malaysia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>crunu@hotmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x02217;&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>patisiddhartha@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Both the authors have equal contribution.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e05382</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p><italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) is a seasonal fruit that contains significant amounts of bioactives like, phenolic acids (gallic acids, 2,3-dihydroxy benzoic acid, chlorogenic acid, <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid, vanillic acid), flavonoid (rutin), organic acids (oxalic acid, tartaric acid, malic acid, lactic acid, acetic acid, citric acid, propionic acid, succinic acid, fumaric acid), vitamin C, vitamin B group (thiamine, niacin, pyridoxine, pantothenic acid, biotin, cobalamins, riboflavin), tocopherols (&#x003b1;<bold>-</bold>tocopherol, &#x003b2;<bold>-</bold>tocopherol, &#x003b3;<bold>-</bold>tocopherol, &#x003b4;<bold>-</bold>tocopherol), carotenes (&#x003b1;<bold>-</bold>carotene, &#x003b2;<bold>-</bold>carotene, &#x003b3;<bold>-</bold>carotene, &#x003b4;<bold>-</bold>carotene) and also rich in essential minerals (potassium, calcium, phosphorus, sodium, iron, copper, manganese). This study provides a comprehensive composition analysis (determined using RP-HPLC and Energy Dispersive X-Ray Fluorescence (EDXRF) Spectroscopy). <italic>In vitro</italic> medicinal activities (antioxidant activity, anti-inflammatory activity, anti-diabetic activity) are quantified for different bael samples. The study also investigates the changes of these bioactive components with freeze, sun, hot air, and microwave drying. The study gives a proper vision to preserve the nutraceutically rich pulp by converting it into fruit leather.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Food science; Natural product chemistry; Microwave drying; Freeze drying; Hot air drying; Sun drying; Polyphenols; Vitamins; Organic acids; In vitro nutraceutical Activities; Multivariate analysis; EDXRF analysis</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Food science</kwd><kwd>Natural product chemistry</kwd><kwd>Microwave drying</kwd><kwd>Freeze drying</kwd><kwd>Hot air drying</kwd><kwd>Sun drying</kwd><kwd>Polyphenols</kwd><kwd>Vitamins</kwd><kwd>Organic acids</kwd><kwd>In vitro nutraceutical Activities</kwd><kwd>Multivariate analysis</kwd><kwd>EDXRF analysis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Bael (<italic>Aegle marmelo</italic>s L.) is the only species within the monotypitonus <italic>Aegle</italic> of <italic>Ructaceae</italic> family, native to the dry (tropical and subtropical regions) forests of hilly and plain areas of South Asian countries like Thailand, Pakistan, Bangladesh, Srilanka, India, and Malaysia (<xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Sharma and Dubey, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Neeraj and Johar, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020a</xref>, <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020c</xref>). This fruit is rich in health-promoting bioactive compounds such as polyphenols, flavonoids, carotenes, vitamins, and organic acids. It also contains essential minerals like potassium, calcium, phosphorus, sodium, iron, copper, and manganese in significant amounts (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Manandhar et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref><xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Ranganna, 1986</xref>). In this study, the proper quantitative amounts of most of the above-mentioned components were unveiled using reverse-phase high performance liquid chromatography (RP-HPLC). Energy dispersive X-ray fluorescence (EDXRF) analysis was also performed for the identification and quantification of the minerals.</p><p id="p0015">The bioactive compounds (marmelosin, luvangetin, aurapten, psoralen, marmelide, tannin, riboflavin, aegeline, &#x003b2;-carotene, lupeol, eugenol) of <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> fruit show multiple biological activities like, antihelminthic, antibacterial, antiulcer, antispasmodic, artemicide, anti-diarrhea, astringent, antiproliferative, anticancer, anti-diabetic, anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activities (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Lim, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et al., 2020d</xref>). Reactive oxygen species (ROS) is a harmful group of components which get generated during the aerobic metabolic processes in human body cells and these radicals lead towards many types of health-related diseases like stroke, cardiovascular disease, arthritis, asthma, retinal damage, neuro degeneration, diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and dermatitis (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">La Vecchia et&#x000a0;al., 1998</xref>). Bioactive compounds (mainly polyphenols) show protective effects against cell oxidation by scavenging these ROS (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Kaur and Kapoor, 2008</xref>). In inflammatory disorder proteinases lead the protein denaturation, here we tried to evaluate the ability of fruit extract to inhibit both the proteinases and protein denaturation. While for inducing diabetic disorder, &#x003b1;-amylase plays a major role by raising the sugar level in the body, here we studied the inhibitory activities of the extracts to prevent &#x003b1;-amylase to form simple sugars from starch. Previously many authors reported the <italic>in-vivo</italic> activities of <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) against these diseases (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Manandhar et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">In spite of being rich in these beneficiary components and activities, it is still underutilized because of its unavailability throughout the year. The ripe fruits are available only from March to June (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Hazra et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Baliga et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). After harvesting, the shelf life of bael fruit is normally two weeks at room temperature (27&#x02013;32 &#x000b0;C). The shelf life can be enhanced to twelve weeks by preserving it at 9 &#x000b0;C (85&#x02013;90% relative humidity), but it is highly sensitive to spoilage (chilling injury) below 9 &#x000b0;C (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Pal et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Roy et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>). The possible solution we found is to convert it into fruit leather which is one of the prominent methods, mainly used to preserve fully ripe unconsumed or excess fruit pulp for a long period of time without adding any preservative, and can be consumed as snacks or, dessert for a long. Bael leather can be utilized in the fruit bar industry, fruit cake industry, and importantly as ayurvedic medicine. The traditional way of making leather is to dry the pulp in the sun, which is one of the easiest and cheapest methods. However, the main problems associated with this are uncertain climatic conditions, microorganisms, dust, dirt and insect infections that produce an inferior quality product in terms of hygiene (<xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Uribe et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, it is better to focus on other possible alternatives, mainly industrial methods like, microwave drying, hot air drying, and freeze drying which gives better yields in terms of production rate and quality of the leather. In this study, the quality of fresh and differently dried <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) fruit leathers in terms of nutraceutical components, compositional changes, and medicinal activities was evaluated.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="p0025">Ripe <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) fruits were purchased from the Kole market of Kolkata, West Bengal, India. Sound fresh ripe bael fruits of uniform size were randomly chosen depending on their visual appearance. Generally, the shelf life of bael fruit is 3&#x02013;4 days if not broken, although pulping was done immediately after brought to the laboratory.</p><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Chemical used</title><p id="p0030">The solvents (ethanol; methanol; acetonitrile; water) and standards (chlorogenic; <italic>p</italic>-coumaric; ferulic; sinapic; 2,3-dihydroxybenzoic; gallic; vanillic acids; quercetin; apigenin; myricetin; rutin; kaempferol; oxalic acid; tartaric acid; malic acid; lactic acid; acetic acid; citric acid; propionic acid; succinic acid; fumaric acid; L-ascorbic acid; thiamine; riboflavin; niacin; pantothenic acid; pyridoxine; biotin; cobalamins; &#x003b1;-tocopherol; &#x003b2;-tocopherol; &#x003b3;-tocopherol; &#x003b4;-tocopherol; &#x003b1;-carotene; &#x003b2;-carotene; &#x003b3;-carotene and &#x003b4;-carotene) used were of chromatography grade. Other reagents (Folin-Ciocalteus's phenol reagent; sodium carbonate; sodium nitrite; aluminium chloride; sodium hydroxide; di sodium phosphate; mono sodium phosphate; trifluoroacetic acid; potassium ferricyanide; ferric chloride; potassium persulphate; trolox; tris hydrochloride; pyrogallol; ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid; bovine serum albumin; corn starch; 3,5-dinitrosalicylic acid; 2,4,6-tris(2-pyridyl)-s-triazine, 2,2-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl; &#x003b1;-amylase; 2,2&#x02032;-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonicacid); phosphoric acid), phosphate-buffered saline and hydrogen peroxide solution were of analytical grade. All the chemicals were purchased Merck and Sigma-Aldrich, India. C<sub>18</sub> columns were bought from the Waters (India) Private Limited.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Sample preparation</title><p id="p0035">After breaking the fruit rind, only the pulp of the fruit pulp was extracted using a muslin cloth. Bael flesh was poured onto glass Petri dishes which were previously oiled with glycerol and a uniform puree load of 0.5 g/cm<sup>2</sup> was maintained for all the samples (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Diamante et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). A total of twelve Petri dishes were prepared by counting three samples for each drying technique. The drying operation was conducted following our previous work (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020a</xref>, <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Drying</title><sec id="sec2.3.1"><label>2.3.1</label><title>Freeze drying</title><p id="p0040">Samples were frozen at -50 &#x000b0;C for 12 h to solidify, in a deep freezer (New Brunswick Scientific, England; Model no: C340-86) and further dried in a laboratory-scale freeze dryer (FDU1200, EYELA, Japan) by maintaining -40 &#x000b0;C and 0.1 mBar.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3.2"><label>2.3.2</label><title>Sun drying</title><p id="p0045">Samples were kept in sunlight under open-air conditions. The pulp was sun dried for two days, six hours each (9 a.m.&#x02013;3 p.m.). The overall temperature throughout the time period was 33 &#x000b1; 2 &#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3.3"><label>2.3.3</label><title>Hot-air drying</title><p id="p0050">Samples were dried in a laboratory hot air dryer (Concepts International, Kolkata, India) by maintaining a temperature of 60 &#x000b0;C and an air flow rate of 1 m/s for consecutive six hours to get a final moisture content of 14&#x02013;17%.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3.4"><label>2.3.4</label><title>Microwave drying</title><p id="p0055">Microwave oven (Samsung, Combi CE1031LAT, Mumbai, India) drying was carried out at 100 W for successive 20 min to get the expected moisture content.</p><p id="p0060">All the drying processes were performed until the leathers reached a moisture content between 14-17% (fresh weight basis). Pulp, microwave, sun, hot, and freeze dried leathers were coded as BP, BM, BS, BH, and BF, respectively. All the analyses were completed immediately after sample preparation to avoid any deterioration.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Extraction preparation</title><sec id="sec2.4.1"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Ultrasonic-assisted extraction</title><p id="p0065">1.00 g of each sample (BP, BM, BS, BH, and BF) were extracted with 30.00 ml of the ethanol-water mixture (1:1) using ultra-sonication (Trans-O-Sonic, Mumbai) for an hour and filtered with 0.45 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m Millipore filter. The final volume of the filtrate was 25.00 ml, so the dose becomes 1.00 gm/25.00 ml or, 40 mg/ml. This filtrate was used for the overall quantification of polyphenols, flavonoids, determination of medicinal values (antioxidant activity, anti-inflammatory activity, anti-diabetic activity), also in HPLC analysis of phenolic acids, flavonoids, and organic acids.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Total polyphenols</title><p id="p0070">TPC test was performed using the protocol mentioned by <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ainsworth and Gillespie (2007)</xref>, while the <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Baba and Malik (2015)</xref> method was followed to determine TFC content. The results were reported on a dry basis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>HPLC analysis</title><sec id="sec2.6.1"><label>2.6.1</label><title>Phenolic acids and flavonoid</title><p id="p0075">The ethanolic extract was injected into an RP-HPLC system (Alliance 2695 HPLC system, Waters Corporation, Massachusetts, USA) for quantification of phenolic acids and flavonoids. The separation was achieved with a C<sub>18</sub> column of 4.6 mm (internal diameter) and 5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m pore size. Two solvents, solvent A (0.5% aqueous H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> solution) and solvent B (9:1 methanol-water solution) were used as eluents at a flow rate of 1 ml/min in the following order: 100% A for the first 8 min, 7:3 A-B in the interval of 8&#x02013;15 min, 1:1 A-B for 15&#x02013;20 min, 2:3 A-B for 20&#x02013;25 min, 3:7 A-B for 25&#x02013;35 min and 100 % B for the last 5 min by maintaining 38 &#x000b0;C temperature. Quantification was carried out with a dual lambda (&#x003bb;) absorbance UV detector 2487 at 280 nm and for data processing, Empower 2 software (Waters Corporation) was used (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020a</xref>, <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et&#x000a0;al., 2020c</xref>). Phenolic acids (chlorogenic, <italic>p</italic>-coumaric, ferulic, sinapic, 2,3-dihydroxybenzoic, gallic, vanillic acids) and flavonoids (quercetin, apigenin, myricetin, rutin, kaempferol) were used as standards.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.2"><label>2.6.2</label><title>Organic acids and vitamin C (ascorbic acid)</title><p id="p0080">The quantification of the organic acids and vitamin C was carried out using an RP-HPLC system (Alliance 2695 HPLC system, Waters Corporation, Massachusetts, USA). We followed <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Sami et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref>, to extract vitamin C using metaphosphoric acid (0.3 M) and acetic acid (1.4 M). For quantification, extracts were injected in the system and eluted with 10 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> solution (pH 2.5). The separation was done using a C<sub>18</sub> column of 4.6 mm internal diameter (3.5 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m pore size) at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/min and chromatogram was observed at 214 nm (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Hu et&#x000a0;al., 2020</xref>). In total nine organic acids were quantified namely, oxalic acid, tartaric acid, malic acid, lactic acid, acetic acid, citric acid, propionic acid, succinic acid, fumaric acid, and L-ascorbic acid.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.3"><label>2.6.3</label><title>Vitamin B group</title><p id="p0085">For sample preparation, 2.00 g sample was taken in 25 ml of 0.1 NH<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> solution and incubated at 121 &#x000b0;C for 30 min. The mixture was then cooled and the pH was fixed to 4.5 using 2.5 M sodium acetate solution and 50 mg &#x003b1;-amylase enzyme was mixed. The mixture was incubated overnight at 35 &#x000b0;C. Then, the preparation was filtered with a Whatman No. 4 filter and the filtrate was diluted up to 50.00 ml of distilled water and filtered again with a 0.45 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m Millipore filter (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">AOAC International, 1990</xref>). 10 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l filtrate was infused into the RP-HPLC system (Alliance 2695 HPLC system, Waters Corporation, Massachusetts, USA). The separation was achieved by a C<sub>18</sub> column (internal diameter: 4.6 mm; pore size: 3.5<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m) using a mobile phase of 0.5% aqueous H<sub>3</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>/30% aqueous acetonitrile solution at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/min (gradient elution) by maintaining a temperature of 35 &#x000b0;C and quantification was at 254 nm <xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">Sarkar et al., 2020e</xref>. In total 7 standards were used, thiamine (vitamin B<sub>1</sub>), riboflavin (vitamin B<sub>2</sub>), niacin (vitamin B<sub>3</sub>), pantothenic acid (vitamin B<sub>5</sub>), pyridoxine (vitamin B<sub>6</sub>), biotin (vitamin B<sub>7</sub>), and cobalamins (vitamin B<sub>12</sub>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6.4"><label>2.6.4</label><title>Tocopherols and carotenes</title><p id="p0090">To determine tocopherols and carotene content, 0.10 g of pyrogallic acid, 1.00 g sample, 3 ml (50%) KOH, and 7 ml ethanol were added, agitated, and heated up using a water bath at 50 &#x000b0;C for 40 min. To neutralize the preparation double-distilled water was used, further anhydrous sodium sulfate (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) was used to dehydrate it. The preparation was concentrated to 5 ml (approx.) with a water bath maintaining 50 &#x000b0;C, followed by dilution to 10.00 ml by using methanol and filtered with 0.45 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>m Millipore filter (<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Sami et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). The filtrate was injected into the RP-HPLC system. The preparation was eluted using 100% methanol through a C<sub>18</sub> column of 4.6 mm internal diameter at a flow rate of 0.5 ml/min by maintaining 35 &#x000b0;C and absorbance was recorded at 292 nm and 450 nm respectively for tocopherols and carotenes. In total 8 standards were used &#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3;, and &#x003b4; forms for both tocopherols and carotenes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Energy Dispersive X-Ray fluorescence (EDXRF) analysis</title><p id="p0095">For elemental analysis using an energy-dissipative X-ray system (Quantax, Bruker Nano GmbH, Germany) differently dried samples (BM, BS, BH, and BF) were powdered, and pellets were formed of 50 mm &#x000d7; 50 mm x 20 mm. All spectra were processed to quantify potassium (K), calcium (Ca), phosphorus (P), sodium (Na), iron (Fe), copper (Cu), manganese (Mn). The machine was operated at a voltage of 10 kV and an X-flash 5010 detector (silicon drift detector) was used for secondary electrons at a high vacuum.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Antioxidant activity</title><p id="p0100">DPPH and ABTS assays were performed as mentioned in <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Kasote et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref>, while to measure hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) and super-oxide radical (O<sub>2</sub><sup>-</sup>) scavenging activity we followed <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Prathapan et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref>. To assess FRAP, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Benzie and Strain (1996)</xref> method was followed. All medicinal activities were reported in percentage (using <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (1)</xref>) by recording the absorbance of the test solution with respect to a null control, using only the pure solvent replaced by the extract (<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Rajan et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib115" ref-type="bibr">Pati et al., 2020</xref>),<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg" alttext="Equation 1."><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">x</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0105">For, all the assessment ethanolic extracts were used.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Anti-inflammatory activity</title><sec id="sec2.9.1"><label>2.9.1</label><title>Protein denaturation using bovine-serum albumin (BSA) and egg-albumin (EA)</title><p id="p0110">To prepare 5.00 ml of the reaction mixture, 0.20 ml of egg-albumin was diluted with 2.80 ml phosphate buffer saline of pH 6.4 and at the end, 2.00 ml ethanolic extract of 40 mg/ml concentration was added in the preparation. The preparations were taken in screw-capped test tubes and incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 15 min, followed by heating at70 &#x000b0;C for 5 min in a water bath. The absorbance of the cooled preparation was evaluated in a UV-Vis spectrophotometer at 660 nm against ethanol as blank (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Chandra et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). The same test was repeated by taking BSA instead of egg albumin and the percentage of inhibition of protein denaturation was calculated using <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (2)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg" alttext="Equation 2."><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2.9.2"><label>2.9.2</label><title>Anti-proteinase activity</title><p id="p0115">The test was executed as mentioned by <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Sakat et&#x000a0;al., (2010)</xref>, with some customization (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Gunathilake et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). To prepare the test solution, 0.12 mg trypsin, 2 ml of 0.02 MTris-HCl buffer (pH7.4),0.04 ml ethanolic extract, and 1.96 ml methanol were poured into a screw-capped test tube. The mixture was incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for 5 min and further 2.00 ml of 0.8% (w/v) casein solution was mixed. The preparation was incubated again for another 20 min. To stop the reaction 4 ml of perchloric acid solution (70%) was poured into the preparation. The centrifugation was performed to obtain a clear supernatant out of the cloudy suspension and the absorbance was evaluated at 210 nm against a blank of ethanol. Here also buffer was taken instead of the extract for control. <xref rid="fd3" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (3)</xref> was used for calculating the anti-proteinase activity for all the samples.<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg" alttext="Equation 3."><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">u</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Anti-diabetic activity</title><p id="p0120">A procedure according to <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abirami et&#x000a0;al. (2014)</xref> was performed to determine the anti-diabetic activity with some modifications. To prepare the test solution, 1.00 ml sample extract (40 mg/ml), 1 ml of 0.02 M sodium phosphate buffer, and 1 mg/ml &#x003b1;-amylase solution were poured into a screw-capped test tube and incubated at 30 &#x000b0;C. Further, it was mixed with 1 ml 1% aqueous starch and kept at 37 &#x000b0;C for 60 min. The reaction was paused with 1 ml of 3,5-dinitro salicylic acid. The mixture was then boiled in a water bath for 5 min at 90 &#x000b0;C and immediately cooled to 30 &#x000b0;C (room temperature) using an ice bath. Later, the preparation was diluted to 8.00 ml using water (distilled) and absorbance was evaluated using a UV-vis spectrophotometer at 540 nm against ethanol as blank. The control was prepared by replacing the sample extract with the same volume of buffer. The results were calculated using <xref rid="fd4" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (4)</xref> and expressed in percentage.<disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg" alttext="Equation 4."><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">b</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">a</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">o</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><label>2.11</label><title>Calculation to convert data in dry weight basis</title><p id="p0125">The moisture content of all samples was recorded following the AOAC method (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">AOAC International 2000</xref>). For the actual comparison between raw pulp and dried leather samples, all the values were calculated and reported based on dry weight using the following <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. 5</xref> and <xref rid="fd6" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. 6</xref>,<disp-formula id="fd5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg" alttext="Equation 5."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>The</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>content</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>w/w</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>on</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>dry</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>weight</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>basis</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>the</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>amount</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ml</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>final</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>volume</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>after&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>extraction</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ml</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>moisture</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>content</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd6"><label>[6]</label><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg" alttext="Equation 6."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>The</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>activity</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>w/v</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>on</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>dry</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>weight</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>basis</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>percentage</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>activity</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>moisture</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>content</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><label>2.12</label><title>Statistical and multivariate analysis</title><p id="p0130">All evaluations were carried out in triplicates and presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation. Total values were calculated using &#x0201c;&#x02211;mean &#x000b1; sqrt&#x02211;(s.d.<sup>2</sup>)&#x0201d;. The Shapiro-Wilk test was performed for normal distribution testing. One-way ANOVA was conducted at 95% confidence interval using SPSS 14.0 while PCA (principal component analysis) and correlation analysis were carried out with R Studio software version 3.4.4 (2018-03-15) software. The cluster analysis (hierarchical clustering heat map) was performed using MATLAB 2018a.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Total polyphenols (TPC and TFC)</title><p id="p0135">The phenolic compounds that exist in fruits have low potency, which is responsible for various beneficial activities like antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities. These phenolic functional groups share their electron pair or hydrogen with the ROS (reactive oxygen species) to scavenge them (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Baba and Malik, 2015</xref>). These phytochemicals mainly exist in polymeric forms bound to the cell wall, during different drying operations the heat flux generated, which may incur the breakdown of the polymeric linkage and leading to the development of the antioxidant of lower molecular weight (<xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0140">The TPC content in <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) pulp varies from 1.02 g GAE/100 ml to 8.73 g GAE/100 g as reported by <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Charoensiddhi and Anprung (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Panda et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</xref>. We also found a similar value of 2.3 &#x000b1; 0.03 g GAE/100 g for BP. Due to drying processes, the TPC value varied significantly, with a maximum in BM and minimum for the BS (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). The amount increased only by 9.11% for BM while for BS, BH, and BF the retentions were 75.91%, 70.44%, 98.3%, respectively. However, the differences in the case of BP, BM, and BF were insignificant (p = 0.09). While an insignificant change was observed for the BS and BH also (p = 0.48).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Polyphenol content of all the samples (BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>BP</th><th>BM</th><th>BS</th><th>BH</th><th>BF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6">Total Polyphenols<hr/></td></tr><tr><td>TPC (GAE mg/g)</td><td>23.04 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>25.14 &#x000b1; 1.15<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>17.49 &#x000b1; 1.15<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>16.23 &#x000b1; 1.16<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>22.65 &#x000b1; 0.17<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>TFC (CE mg/g)</td><td>11.63 &#x000b1; 0.44<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>16.27 &#x000b1; 0.66<sup><bold>ab</bold></sup></td><td>14.51 &#x000b1; 0.30<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>9.74 &#x000b1; 0.35<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>18.17 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><bold>Phenolic acids (mg/100g)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Gallic acid (GA)</td><td>617.17 &#x000b1; 2.58<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>605.55 &#x000b1; 3.45<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>592.15 &#x000b1; 3.33<sup><bold>cd</bold></sup></td><td>580.27 &#x000b1; 4.13<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>595.57 &#x000b1; 1.29<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>2,3-dihydroxy benzoic acid (DHBA)</td><td>nd</td><td>22.45 &#x000b1; 0.19<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>20.17 &#x000b1; 0.42<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>35.94 &#x000b1; 0.18<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>10.35 &#x000b1; 0.24<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Chlorogenic acid (CGA)</td><td>0.38 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>e</sup></td><td>56.31 &#x000b1; 0.26<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>46.57 &#x000b1; 0.53<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>49.65 &#x000b1; 0.43<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>30.97 &#x000b1; 0.55<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td><italic>p</italic>-Coumaric acid (p-CA)</td><td>233.54 &#x000b1; 1.32<sup>e</sup></td><td>337.77 &#x000b1; 2.01<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>361.42 &#x000b1; 1.49<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>305.95 &#x000b1; 1.13<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>243.07 &#x000b1; 1.02<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Vanillic acid (VA)</td><td>69.98 &#x000b1; 0.2<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>71.45 &#x000b1; 0.87<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>102.40 &#x000b1; 0.93<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>97.50 &#x000b1; 0.84<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>52.80 &#x000b1; 0.76<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><bold>Flavonoid (mg/100g)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Rutin</td><td>32.25 &#x000b1; 0.17<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>59.90 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>56.25 &#x000b1; 0.19<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>43.40 &#x000b1; 0.11<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>40.50 &#x000b1; 0.02<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are reported <bold>on</bold> dry basis. The amounts are provided in the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (s.d.) form, after performing at least triplicate experiments. The superscript letters a, b, c, d and e shown in the table represent the significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for the same parameters of the different samples. GAE mg/gm = Gallic Acid Equivalent mg/gm; CE mg/gm = Catechin Equivalent mg/gm; nd = not detected.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0145">During the microwave drying the polar molecules present in the cellular matrix vibrate spontaneously by the microwave radiation, this causes rapid temperature rise with the generation of vigorous compressive forces which consecutively distort the cell wall and allows more polyphenols to be accessible. The hastier heating phenomenon in the microwave drying causes the deactivation of polyphenol oxidases more quickly than other drying processes, so the degradation of enzymatic polyphenol was reduced. And even for the freeze-drying, the enzyme gets inactivated at low temperature, so the maximum retention was observed. <xref rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr">Valadez-Carmona et al. (2017)</xref>, found a similar trend, highest in microwave dried cacao pod husks followed by freeze dried and hot air dried sample. Previously, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Hazra et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> also observed an insignificant change after freeze drying of bael (<italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> L.).</p><p id="p0150">In our study, 1.16 &#x000b1; 0.04 g CE/100 g TFC value was observed for the BP, which is similar to the value reported by <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Charoensiddhi and Anprung (2008)</xref> studied for Thai <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) fruit. We observed an increase in TFC values by 39.89%, 24.76%, and 56.23% for BM, BS, and BF, respectively. While depletion in the amount was observed for the BH by 16.25%; an insignificant change was observed for BM, BS (p = 0.06), while for BM, BF (p = 0.08). <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Saifullah et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref>, reported the highest TFC in freeze dried lemon myrtle leaves compared to other drying (hot air, microwave, and sun). Whereas <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen and Le (2018)</xref> found, microwave drying yield higher TFC value than hot air drying for carrot peel.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>HPLC analysis</title><sec id="sec3.2.1"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Phenolic acids and flavonoid</title><p id="p0155">Phenolic acids are nearly 1/3 of the dietary phenols (depending upon type, variety, and nature of foodstuffs), exist in both free and bound forms in various parts of plants and having antibacterial, antiviral, anti-inflammatory, anti-carcinogenic and vasodilator actions (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Robbins, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Duthie et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Shahidi and Naczk, 1995</xref>). In plants, bound-phenolics mainly exist by forming ester or acetyl bonds (<xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">Zadernowski et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>). Phenolic acids mainly comprise of two subgroups, hydroxycinnamic acids and hydroxybenzoic acids (<xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Saifullah et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref>).</p><p id="p0160">In total five phenolic acids, two from the hydroxycinnamate subclass (chlorogenic and <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acids) and three from the hydroxybenzoic (gallic, 2,3-dihydroxybenzoic and vanillic acid) were detected in BS, BM, BH, BF; while only 2,3-dihydroxybenzoic acid was not detected in BP. Gallic acid (GA) is the predominant phenolic acid for all the samples (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Gallic acid was observed maximum in BP (617.17 &#x000b1; 2.58 mg/100 g), while the same was decreased by 1.86%, 4.02%, 5.99%, and 3.40% for BM, BS, BH, and BF, respectively. All the drying treatments significantly (p = 3.34 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>) affected the GA content, though the GA content varied insignificantly for BS, BH (p = 0.11) and BS, BF (p = 0.07). <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Saifullah et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> found a similar trend of lowering GA in the case of freeze, sun, and hot air drying of <italic>Backhousia citriodora</italic> leaves. <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Gasecka et&#x000a0;al., (2020)</xref> observed a higher GA content for fresh <italic>Hericium erinaceus</italic>, than the oven dried sample. Despite being absent in pulp, the 2,3-dihydroxybenzoic acid came into existence after undergoing the drying processes and detected maximum in BH (35.94 &#x000b1; 0.18 mg/100 g). This was may be due to the conversion of chorismic acid into DHBA with a rise in temperature (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Gibson, 1964</xref>). Chlorogenic acid (CGA) was present in the second-lowest amount in the pulp among the detected phenolic acids, it also increased significantly with all the drying procedures (p = 4.40 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;22</sup>) and measured highest in BM (56.31 &#x000b1; 0.26 mg/100 g). <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Slatnar et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</xref> also reported the enhancement in CGA content due to sun and oven-drying. The existence of CGA in bound/esterified form in the fresh pulp may be the reason behind its low detection, while the drying conditions may allow the better release (<xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">Wildermuth et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). Both for <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid (p-CA) and vanillic acid (VA) the amount was significantly lower in BP than the differently dried products. p-CA content increased by 44.63%, 54.76%, 31.01%, 4.08% for BM, BS, BH, and BF, respectively. In the case of VA also, the values increased by 2.1%, 46.33%, 39.33% for BM, BS, and BH, respectively. But, for BF it was decreased by 24.55%.</p><p id="p0165">Rutin is the glycoside composed of quercetin and disaccharide rutinose. It is also known as vitamin P and is widely distributed in vegetables, fruits, and medicinal herbs (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Hosseinzadeh and Nassiri-Asl, 2014</xref>). <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Manandhar et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> reported that rutin is the major flavonoid present in <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.). During HPLC analysis, only rutin was detected among the other given flavonoids. It was found maximum for BM (59.90 &#x000b1; 0.05 mg/100 g) and a minimum for BP (32.25 &#x000b1; 0.17 mg/100 g). The rutin content was significantly increased by 87.18%, 75.78%, 35.62%, and 26.56% after microwave, sun, hot air, and freeze-drying, respectively. Previously some studies also reported that in the case of freeze and sun drying the amount of rutin content increased for black grape and figs respectively (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">&#x000c7;oklar and Akbulut, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Kamiloglu and Capanoglu, 2015</xref>). <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Kamiloglu and Capanoglu. (2015)</xref> suggested the higher detection in sun dried sample is mainly due to the cell wall breakdown and/or release from sequestration.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.2"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Organic acids</title><p id="p0170">Quantification of the organic acids found in fruits is considered to be a crucial parameter for the assessment of their quality since these acids not only contribute to the flavor but also provide stability and nutrition (<xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">Walker and Famiani, 2018</xref>). In total nine organic acids were quantified namely, oxalic acid (OA), tartaric acid (TA), malic acid (MA), lactic acid (LA), acetic acid (AA), citric acid (CA), propionic acid (PA), succinic acid (SA) and fumaric acid (FA) in all the bael samples. Previously, <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">Yadav et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</xref> quantified only three organic acids (tartaric, malic acid, and oxalic acid) for the bael pulp, in the range of 40&#x02013;210 mg/100 g (0.04&#x02013;0.21%), whereas in our study, the amount ranged within 38.66&#x02013;265.33 mg/100 g DB, for the same (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Organic acid profile and ascorbic acid content of all the samples (BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><italic>Organic Acids (mg/100 g)</italic></th><th>BP</th><th>BM</th><th>BS</th><th>BH</th><th>BF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Oxalic Acid (OA)</td><td>38.66 &#x000b1; 0.06<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>80.34 &#x000b1; 0.88<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>48.07 &#x000b1; 0.57<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>29.47 &#x000b1; 0.37<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>29.47 &#x000b1; 0.32<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Tartaric Acid (TA)</td><td>265.33 &#x000b1; 2.08<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>201.86 &#x000b1; 0.58<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>93.51 &#x000b1; 1.20<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>138.10 &#x000b1; 0.58<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>91.46 &#x000b1; 0.57<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Malic Acid(MA)</td><td>108.11 &#x000b1; 0.69<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>186.81 &#x000b1; 0.46<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>88.89 &#x000b1; 0.52<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>60.01 &#x000b1; 0.12<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>63.10 &#x000b1; 0.49<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Lactic Acid(LA)</td><td>765.48 &#x000b1; 2.66<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>794.14 &#x000b1; 2.03<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>721.12 &#x000b1; 1.22<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>372.32 &#x000b1; 0.65<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>76.88 &#x000b1; 1.20<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Acetic Acid(AA)</td><td>728.99 &#x000b1; 0.29<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>261.01 &#x000b1; 0.52<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td><bold>5</bold>84.50 &#x000b1; 2.73<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>215.75 &#x000b1; 0.30<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>41.63 &#x000b1; 0.22<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Citric Acid (CA)</td><td>542.45 &#x000b1; 1.45<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>395.36 &#x000b1; 0.88<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>17.59 &#x000b1; 0.15<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>271.62 &#x000b1; 0.82<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>50.63 &#x000b1; 0.11<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Propionic acid (PA)</td><td>104.21 &#x000b1; 0.58<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>103.82 &#x000b1; 0.31<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>37.62 &#x000b1; 0.37<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>53.79 &#x000b1; 0.29<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>54.80 &#x000b1; 0.47<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Succinic Acid(SA)</td><td>8.69 &#x000b1; 0.11<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>1.19 &#x000b1; 0.08<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>0.57 &#x000b1; 0.02<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>2.65 &#x000b1; 0.12<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>8.55 &#x000b1; 0.17<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Fumaric Acid(FA)</td><td>394.89 &#x000b1; 1.76<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>517.28 &#x000b1; 0.83<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>19.55 &#x000b1; 0.23<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>57.08 &#x000b1; 0.17<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>38.48 &#x000b1; 0.38<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Ascorbic Acid (Asc-A)</td><td>8.40 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>4.81 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>3.74 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>4.27 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>6.00 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are reported on dry basis. The amounts are provided in the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (s.d.) form, after performing at least triplicate experiments. The superscript letters a, b, c, d and e shown in the table represent the significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for the same parameters of the different samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0175">It was observed that lactic acid (765.48 &#x000b1; 2.66 mg/100 g) was the predominant one followed by acetic acid (728.99 &#x000b1; 0.29 mg/100 g), citric acid (542.45 &#x000b1; 1.45 mg/100 g), and fumaric acid (394.89 &#x000b1; 1.76 mg/100 g) for BP. While oxalic acid (38.66 &#x000b1; 0.06 mg/100 g) and succinic acid (8.69 &#x000b1; 0.11 mg/100 g) contributed in a lesser amount in the profile. For lactic acid, the trend followed BM &#x0003e; BP &#x0003e; BS &#x0003e; BH &#x0003e; BF, and for acetic acid, it was BP &#x0003e; BM &#x0003e; BS &#x0003e; BH &#x0003e; BF. Gaseckaet. al. (2019) also observed a similar trend for lactic acid and acetic acid in the case of fresh, natural convective and oven-dried <italic>Hericiumerinaceus</italic> (Bull.). <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref> also found higher acetic acid content in microwave dried <italic>Pleurotuseryngii</italic> than the hot air-dried sample. In most of the cases, the drying procedures significantly affected the organic acid content. Both for oxalic acid (p = 0.99) and propionic acid (p = 0.13), an insignificant change was noticed between hot air and freeze dried samples.</p><p id="p0180">Most of the previous studies reported the effect of drying on the amount of citric, malic, and succinic acids for edible mushrooms (<italic>Pleurotus eryngii; Stropharia rugosoannulata; Leccinum scabrum</italic> (Bull.) Gray; <italic>Hericium erinaceus</italic> (Bull.) Pears), Figs (<italic>Ficus carica</italic> L.), Jujubes (<italic>Ziziphus jujuba</italic> Mill.), lemon slices (<xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Slatnar et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Hu et&#x000a0;al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Gasecka et&#x000a0;al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Ding et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). For citric acid, it was found that after drying there was a retention of 72.93%, 3.24%, 50.07%, and 7.67% for BM, BS, BH, and BF, respectively. <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> observed a similar trend for fresh, freeze, sun, and oven-dried jujube. In the case of malic acid, retentions of 82.22%, 55.5%, 58.36% were observed for BS, BH, and BF, while the same for BM increased by 72.79%. This is in agreement with the observations reported by <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Cal&#x000ed;n-S&#x000e1;nchez et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</xref> and <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Gasecka et&#x000a0;al. (2020)</xref> for vacuum microwave, convective, and freeze dried pomegranate and hot air-dried <italic>Hericium erinaceus</italic> (Bull.), respectively. Likewise, citric acid, the amount for succinic acid decreased with processing by 86.31%, 93.45%, 69.51%, and 1.62% for BM, BS, BH, and BF respectively. An insignificant difference was also observed between BP and BF for the succinic acid content (p = 0.55). This is in line with the findings of <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> for fresh, sun, and oven-dried jujube.</p><p id="p0185">During drying the depletion of organic acids was found, which can be explained by decarboxylation and/or dehydration with the evaporation of carboxylic acids (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Chu and Clydesdale, 1976</xref>). While in some of the cases the content surprisingly increased probably due to the formation of organic acid from heat-accelerated reactions between different sugars and nitrogen-free carboxylic acids (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Delgado et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.3"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Vitamin C (ascorbic acid)</title><p id="p0190">L- ascorbic acid (AscA) is a water-soluble nutrient which not only prevents diseases like scurvy but also serves as a biological antioxidant. But, the main problem with ascorbic acid is that it easily degrades, depending on variables such as light, temperature, and the presence of oxygen (<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Santos and Silva, 2009</xref>). Ascorbic acid primarily goes through chemical degradation involving oxidation to form dehydro-ascorbic acid, followed by hydrolysis to 2,3-diketogulonic acid and further polymerization to nutritionally inactivated products (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Chang et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>).</p><p id="p0195">The amount of ascorbic acid was observed to be the highest for BP (8.40 &#x000b1; 0.01 mg/100 g) and due to different drying methods, a significant decrement (p = 4.99 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>) in the content was observed. Here, high aerial oxidation and long drying time may cause higher degradation for BH and BS, only 50.86%, and 44.57% retentions were observed. Also the application of higher temperature speeds up the ascorbic acid oxidation specifically for hot air drying. <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Maharaj and Sanket (1996)</xref> observed higher content of ascorbic acid in case of forced convective drying compared to natural convective drying for Dasheen leaves. Minimal destruction was observed for BF, which may be due to low-temperature processing followed by BM, owing to higher dehydration rate and shorter drying time (<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Qing-guo et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>). For BF and BM, the retentions were 71.44% and 57.28%, respectively. <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Chang et&#x000a0;al. (2006)</xref> found better retention of vitamin C for freeze-dried sample compared to vacuum assisted microwave drying, whereas air drying stood last for carrot slices. Due to the heat-labile characteristics of ascorbic acid, it was expected to have a higher variation between BP, BF, and other dried leathers. Though BH showed high retention (50.83%) of vitamin C, but the result is in agreement within the range of 44.28&#x02013;63.85% previously reported by <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Chang et&#x000a0;al. (2006)</xref> and <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Chan et&#x000a0;al. (1997)</xref> for hot air dried tomatoes (I-Tien-Hung variety) and seaweed, respectively. <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Uribe et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> also reported an increase by 11.05% of vitamin C in the convective dried brown alga. It can be concluded that the retention of vitamin C is also dependent on sample characteristics.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.4"><label>3.2.4</label><title>Vitamin B group</title><p id="p0200">Vitamin B group encompasses a class of water-soluble compounds and consists of 8 major groups which are thiamine (vit B<sub>1</sub>), niacin (vit B<sub>3</sub>), pyridoxine (vit B<sub>6</sub>), pantothenic acid (vit B<sub>5</sub>), biotin (vit B<sub>7</sub>), cobalamins (vit B<sub>12</sub>), riboflavin (vit B<sub>2</sub>), and folate (vit B<sub>9</sub>). Most of these get deteriorated rapidly in UV-light, oxygen, and high temperatures. Riboflavin (vit B<sub>2</sub>) and pantothenic acid (vit B<sub>5</sub>) get deteriorated at a fast pace under higher temperatures while thiamine (B<sub>1</sub>), folate (B<sub>9</sub>) are extremely sensitive to both, oxygenated and high-temperature conditions.</p><p id="p0205">In total 7 standards were used and all were detected for <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> pulp. In our samples, vitamin B<sub>12</sub> was the predominant one, followed by vitamin B<sub>1</sub> and then vitamin B<sub>2</sub>.</p><p id="p0210">Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> is one of the essential vitamins for the transition of homocysteine to methionine. Without cobalamins the transition procedure becomes incompetent and homocysteine amount increases. The higher levels of homocysteine can be harmful to the blood vessels, enhancing the possibilities of cardiovascular diseases (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">He et. al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Ishihara et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). We aimed to have found the best drying method to minimize the vitamin B complex destruction. The levels of vitamin B<sub>12</sub> content in samples ranged from 0.11 to 1.65 mg/100 g DW, where the maximum loss was measured for BH (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>). Due to drying the degradation was significant (p = 7.35 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup>) and the amount decreased by 75.12%, 86.75%, 92.94%, 88.53 % respectively for BM, BS, BH, and BF. Similar result for microwave drying was observed by <xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">Tian et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref>, however, for hot air drying the result was different. <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">Watanabe et&#x000a0;al. (1998)</xref> also studied the effect of microwave drying on several foods (milk, beef, pork) and reported that microwave heating causes an appreciable degradation (30&#x02013;40%) of the vitamin B<sub>12</sub> molecules.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Vitamin B profile of all the samples (BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Vitamin B group (&#x003bc;g/100g)</th><th>BP</th><th>BM</th><th>BS</th><th>BH</th><th>BF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Thiamine (vit B<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>346.29 &#x000b1; 12.80<sup>a</sup></td><td>97.41 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>d</sup></td><td>140.21 &#x000b1; 0.10<sup>c</sup></td><td>375.48 &#x000b1; 13.30<sup>a</sup></td><td>274.32 &#x000b1; 0.13<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Riboflavin (vit B<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>337.68 &#x000b1; 15.27<sup>a</sup></td><td>272.76 &#x000b1; 3.60<sup>b</sup></td><td>224.63 &#x000b1; 5.03<sup>b</sup></td><td>329.72 &#x000b1; 20.81<sup>a</sup></td><td>336.59 &#x000b1; 16.33<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Niacin (vit B<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>145.33 &#x000b1; 0.29<sup>a</sup></td><td>35.95 &#x000b1; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td>26.85 &#x000b1; 0.04<sup>c</sup></td><td>22.67 &#x000b1; 0.43<sup>d</sup></td><td>12.76 &#x000b1; 0.04<sup>e</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Pantothenic acid (vit B<sub>5</sub>)</td><td>42.46 &#x000b1; 2.43<sup>b</sup></td><td>7.05 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>c</sup></td><td>45.73 &#x000b1; 0.56a<sup>b</sup></td><td>46.81 &#x000b1; 0.55<sup>a</sup></td><td>1.76 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Pyridoxine (vit B<sub>6</sub>)</td><td>97.25 &#x000b1; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td>30.16 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>d</sup></td><td>64.66 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>b</sup></td><td>49.75 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>c</sup></td><td>13.08 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>e</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Biotin (vit B<sub>7</sub>)</td><td>179.13 &#x000b1; 3.87<sup>d</sup></td><td>106.52 &#x000b1; 0.09<sup>e</sup></td><td>191.56 &#x000b1; 4.16<sup>c</sup></td><td>236.56 &#x000b1; 0.50<sup>b</sup></td><td>419.68 &#x000b1; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Cobalamins (vit B<sub>12</sub>)</td><td>1650.75 &#x000b1; 50.40<sup>a</sup></td><td>410.60 &#x000b1; 0.06<sup>b</sup></td><td>213.11 &#x000b1; 4.89<sup>c</sup></td><td>116.97 &#x000b1; 0.41<sup>e</sup></td><td>194.35 &#x000b1; 4.58<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>Total value</bold></td><td>2798.89 &#x000b1; 54.38</td><td>960.45 &#x000b1; 3.60</td><td>906.75 &#x000b1; 8.17</td><td>1177.96 &#x000b1; 24.71</td><td>1252.54 &#x000b1; 16.96</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are reported on dry basis. The amounts are provided in the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (s.d.) form, after performing at least triplicate experiments. Total value calculated using &#x0201c;&#x02211;mean &#x000b1; sqrt&#x02211;(s.d.<sup>2</sup>)&#x0201d;. The superscript letters a, b, c, d and e shown in the table represent the significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for the same parameters of the different samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0215">Thiamine (vit B<sub>1</sub>) works as a coenzyme in different decarboxylation reactions (<xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Schnellbaecher et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). Vitamin B<sub>1</sub> content was greater for BH (375.48 &#x000b1; 13.30 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g) than for BP (346.29 &#x000b1; 12.80 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g), however, the change was statistically insignificant (p = 0.06). It was found lowest for microwave drying (97.41 &#x000b1; 0.01 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g), a similar observation was previously reported by <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Alajaji and El-Adawy (2006)</xref> for chickpea. A significant overall reduction in amount was observed due to the drying methods (p = 4.25 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup>). The amount of thiamine decreased by 71.87%, 59.51%, and 20.78% for BM, BS, and BF, respectively. Previously, a similar trend between untreated bulgur, hot air, and sun dried bulgur was also observed (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Kadakal et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>). This may be due to higher aerial oxidation and the presence of light (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Dwivedi and Arnold, 1973</xref>).</p><p id="p0220">Riboflavin (vit B<sub>2</sub>) is one of the essential components required in the enzymatically controlled metabolism of nutrients like lipids, carbohydrates, and amino acids (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Choe et&#x000a0;al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Cardoso et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Combs, 2012</xref>). The amount of vitamin B<sub>2</sub> was maximum for BP (337.68 &#x000b1; 15.27 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g) and minimum for BS (272.76 &#x000b1; 3.60 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g). Here, the amounts for BP, BH, and BF were statistically insignificant (p = 0.83) but, for BM and BS the change was significant (p = 1.76 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>), and the amount reduced by 19.22% and 33.47%, respectively. A similar trend was observed by <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Kadakal et&#x000a0;al. (2007)</xref> for hot air and sun dried bulgur. <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Alajaji and El-Adawy (2006)</xref> also observed a similar trend between raw and microwave dried chickpea.</p><p id="p0225">Other complexes such as niacin, pantothenic acid, pyridoxine, and biotin cover about 15&#x02013;40% of the total amount. For niacin and pyridoxine the change due to drying was significant, while an insignificant change was observed for BP and BS regarding the pantothenic acid (p = 0.09). For biotin, the processing caused an undefined enhancement in amount by 134.28%, 32.06%, and 6.93% for BF, BH, and BS, respectively.</p><p id="p0230">The amount of total vitamin B profile was the lowest for sun drying (906.75 &#x000b1; 8.17 &#x003bc;g/100 g) and the highest for fresh pulp (2798.89 &#x000b1; 54.38 &#x003bc;g/100 g), after processing the maximum retention was observed for freeze dried leather.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.5"><label>3.2.5</label><title>Carotenes</title><p id="p0235">Carotenes are health-beneficial pigments and account for the color-diversity among the variety of fruits. The prominent carotenes for most of the fruits are &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; -carotene, which account for the yellow and orange color, respectively (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Khoo et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>).</p><p id="p0240">There was no published study which compared the &#x003b1;-, &#x003b2;-, &#x003b3;- and &#x003b4;-carotene content of fresh <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) pulp and it's differently dried leathers treated until the present observation. The changes in the amount of these carotenes with different drying are provided in <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>. From the data, we can observe that the presence of &#x003b1;-carotene is highest in the pulp, which decreased by 97.48%, 67.44%, 68.41% for the BS, BH, and BF, respectively. Followed by &#x003b3;- and &#x003b2;-, while &#x003b4;-carotene is the lowest. We found 51.67 &#x000b1; 1.67 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g &#x003b2;-carotene in the pulp, which is in accordance with the study done by <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Panda et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</xref> for <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) fruit must. It was also observed that the values increased in BS (151.58 &#x000b1; 0.34 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g), BF (153.43 &#x000b1; 0.67 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g), and BH (55.38 &#x000b1; 0.16 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/100 g) by 1.93 folds, 1.97 folds, and 7.37%, respectively. <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> also found a similar enhancement in the values between fresh, freeze, sun, and hot air dried jujube fruit. For, &#x003b1;-carotene the content was insignificantly altered for BH and BF, while a similar observation was there for &#x003b2;-, &#x003b3;- and &#x003b4;-carotene during sun and freeze drying. The overall carotene content was observed to be the highest in the pulp, while the overall carotene retention was the highest in BH followed by BF, BS, and BM. Previously, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Bechoff et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</xref> also did a similar study, they observed higher retention of pro-vitamin A for hot air dried sweet potato than for sun drying.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Carotene profile (Provitamin A) of all the samples (BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample) in dry basis.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table&#x000a0;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Carotenes (&#x003bc;g/100g)</th><th>BP</th><th>BM</th><th>BS</th><th>BH</th><th>BF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>&#x003b1;-carotene (alpha C)</td><td>1698.22 &#x000b1; 33.33<sup>a</sup></td><td>nd</td><td>42.76 &#x000b1; 1.15<sup>c</sup></td><td>552.8 &#x000b1; 3.17<sup>b</sup></td><td>536.38 &#x000b1; 6.02<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b2;-carotene (beta C)</td><td>51.67 &#x000b1; 1.67<sup>b</sup></td><td>nd</td><td>151.58 &#x000b1; 0.34<sup>a</sup></td><td>55.38 &#x000b1; 0.16<sup>b</sup></td><td>153.43 &#x000b1; 0.67<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b3;-carotene (gamma C)</td><td>84.05 &#x000b1; 0.90<sup>b</sup></td><td>31.95 &#x000b1; 0.67<sup>c</sup></td><td>22.37 &#x000b1; 1.33<sup>d</sup></td><td>476.17 &#x000b1; 0.30<sup>a</sup></td><td>18.43 &#x000b1; 0.49<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b4;-carotene (delta C)</td><td>nd</td><td>nd</td><td>45.03 &#x000b1; 0.55<sup>a</sup></td><td>nd</td><td>43.74 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>Total value</bold></td><td>1833.94 &#x000b1; 33.38</td><td>31.95 &#x000b1; 0.67</td><td>261.74 &#x000b1; 1.87</td><td>1084.35 &#x000b1; 3.18</td><td>751.98 &#x000b1; 6.08</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are reported on dry basis. The amounts are provided in the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (s.d.) form, after performing at least triplicate experiments. The superscript letters a, b, c, d and e shown in the table represent the significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for the same parameters of the different samples. nd = not detected.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.6"><label>3.2.6</label><title>Tocopherols</title><p id="p0245">Tocopherols are important lipophilic antioxidants, which naturally occur in four isomeric forms (&#x003b4;-, &#x003b3;-, &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-tocopherols). During the biosynthesis of tocopherols, &#x003b3;-tocopherol methyltransferase catalyzes the conversion of &#x003b3;- and &#x003b4;-tocopherols respectively to &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-tocopherols (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Fritsche et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). In this study, we tried to evaluate the effects of different drying techniques on each tocopherol.</p><p id="p0250">The tocopherols composition of <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) pulp and differently dried leathers are presented in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;5</xref>. From the <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;5</xref>, it can be observed that the pulp contains only &#x003b3;- and &#x003b4;-tocopherols and their amount decreased significantly with the microwave, sun, hot and freeze drying by 98.82%, 98.8%, 68.64%, 97.82% and 84.69%, 96.82%, 86.04%, 98.56% respectively. &#x003b3;-tocopherol insignificantly varied for BS and BM (p = 0.62). A significant variation was observed for all the other bael samples. The maximum retention of &#x003b4;-tocopherol was observed in BM (15.18%), while the same for &#x003b3;-tocopherol was observed in BH (31.69%). The relative higher content of the tocopherol in BH and BM might be due to the fact that the occurrence of the tocopherol within the lipid segment of the samples; which by virtue shielded the thermal destruction of tocopherol (<xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Uribe et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Van Hoed et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>). The higher value of standard deviation for BH may have resulted from the uneven distribution of lipid segment and less uniform exposure to degrading drying conditions. A similar observation was also observed by <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Uribe et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> for &#x003b1;-tocopherol. While being absent in BP, &#x003b1;-tocopherol was found for BM (0.07 &#x000b1; 0.00 mg/100 g), BS (0.13 &#x000b1; 0.00 mg/100 g), whereas presence of &#x003b2;-tocopherol was detected in BM (0.48 &#x000b1; 0.01 mg/100 g), BS (0.47 &#x000b1; 0.00 mg/100 g) and BH (0.50 &#x000b1; 0.01 mg/100 g).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Tocopherol (vitamin E) profile of all the samples (BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Tocopherols (mg/100g)</th><th>BP</th><th>BM</th><th>BS</th><th>BH</th><th>BF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>&#x003b1;-tocopherol (alpha T)</td><td>nd</td><td>0.07 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td>0.13 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>a</sup></td><td>nd</td><td>nd</td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b2;-tocopherol (beta T)</td><td>nd</td><td>0.48 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.47 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.50 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td>nd</td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b3;-tocopherol (gamma T)</td><td>27.50 &#x000b1; 0.11<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.32 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>c</sup></td><td>0.32 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>c</sup></td><td>8.71 &#x000b1; 0.23<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.57 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b4;-tocopherol (delta T)</td><td>11.12 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td>1.70 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>c</sup></td><td>0.35 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>d</sup></td><td>1.55 &#x000b1; 0.01<sup>b</sup></td><td>0.15 &#x000b1; 0.00<sup>e</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are reported on dry basis. The amounts are provided in the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (s.d.) form, after performing at least triplicate experiments. The superscript letters a, b, c, d and e shown in the table represent the significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for the same parameters of the different samples. nd = not detected.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0255">Some earlier studies also reported the enhancement of &#x003b1;-tocopherol along with temperature till 60 &#x000b0;C in convective drying (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Laoretani et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Al Juhaimi et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). This may be due to the stability of &#x003b3;-tocopherol methyltransferase enzyme which converts &#x003b3;- and &#x003b4;-tocopherols into &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-tocopherols at ambient and/or higher temperature (&#x0003c;50 &#x000b0;C) (<xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">Shigeoka et&#x000a0;al., 1992</xref>). While in BF, the change in the amount of &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-tocopherol was insignificant with respect to BP, which may be explained as, the optimum temperature for &#x003b3;-tocopherol methyltransferase is about 40 &#x000b0;C, at a lower temperature the enzyme may be deactivated (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000e1;lvez-Valdivieso et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>) as well as the reaction kinetics may be impacted in lower temperature. However, the actual reaction mechanism is yet to be revealed. As some of the earlier studies reported opposite trends also for &#x003b1;-tocopherol in jujube fruit and <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> leaves drying (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Gao et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Saini et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Mineral analysis</title><p id="p0260">Minerals are mainly divided into macro-minerals (major minerals) and micro-minerals (trace minerals). For sample preparation of EDXRF, the sample needs to be dried either by freeze drying as reported by <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Allegretta et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> or, need to be dried in an oven (<xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">Turhan et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>) for reduction of the moisture to such a level that pellet formation is possible. In this study, as the moisture content of all the samples was in the vicinity of 15%, pellet formation was feasible. Here we observed the effect of different drying techniques (BM, BS, BH, and BF) on the result of EDXRF. In total seven minerals were quantified for the dried samples, four macro-minerals (K, Ca, P, and Na) and three micro-minerals (Fe, Cu, and Mn). The amounts of the individual minerals for the samples are listed in <xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;6</xref>. It was observed that BS (7460.18 &#x000b1; 7.43 mg/kg) consists of the highest amount of the total mineral content, while for BH (7439.07 &#x000b1; 26.86 mg/kg) the amount was the lowest. Similar to <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Uribe et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> we also observed an insignificant change for macro-minerals, which was maybe due to the existence of the same amount of solid content in every sample. In the case of Fe, Cu and Mn we found a statistically significant difference between BS, BH (p = 0.2); BH, BF (p = 0.4); and BS, BF (p = 0.3), respectively. Though the differences were statistically significant, these may not have much influence on the nutritional characteristics of bael samples. Previously, some studies (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Sajib et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Islam et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Baliga et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>) observed the mineral content (mg/100 g) of <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) pulp, which varied from 78-600 for K, 30&#x02013;85 for Ca, 31.8 for P, 6.65&#x02013;11.9 for Na, 0.6&#x02013;1.93 for Fe, 0.02&#x02013;0.21 for Cu, and 0.23 for Mn. We also observed similar results with a little variation that may be due to differences in cultivar, soil, harvesting time, and conditions. Though it is the first kind of approach to compare mineral profiles of differently dried food products, it is an established fact that for mineral composition and quantification purposes EDXRF produces results in line with that can be achieved by ICP-AES process (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Feng et&#x000a0;al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">McCarthy et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Hannaker et&#x000a0;al., 1984</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Mineral contents of all the dried samples (BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#x000a0;6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Minerals (mg/kg)</th><th>BM</th><th>BS</th><th>BH</th><th>BF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Potassium (K)</td><td>6343.80 &#x000b1; 3.38<sup>a</sup></td><td>6344.13 &#x000b1; 3.66<sup>a</sup></td><td>6337.13 &#x000b1; 14.53<sup>a</sup></td><td>6337.13 &#x000b1; 8.82<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Calcium (Ca)</td><td>553.10 &#x000b1; 1.33<sup>a</sup></td><td>548.77 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td><td>556.77 &#x000b1; 4.17<sup>a</sup></td><td>563.44 &#x000b1; 6.50<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Phosphorus (P)</td><td>280.15 &#x000b1; 1.15<sup>a</sup></td><td>281.15 &#x000b1; 2.08<sup>a</sup></td><td>278.48 &#x000b1; 8.57<sup>a</sup></td><td>283.15 &#x000b1; 2.64<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Sodium (Na)</td><td>109.79 &#x000b1; 3.17<sup>a</sup></td><td>110.36 &#x000b1; 2.90<sup>a</sup></td><td>106.72 &#x000b1; 1.70<sup>a</sup></td><td>111.16 &#x000b1; 2.88<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Iron (Fe)</td><td>13.89 &#x000b1; 1.45<sup>ab</sup></td><td>17.22 &#x000b1; 0.57<sup>a</sup></td><td>13.56 &#x000b1; 0.88<sup>b</sup></td><td>16.56 &#x000b1; 2.72<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Copper (Cu)</td><td>10.45 &#x000b1; 0.48<sup>ab</sup></td><td>9.62 &#x000b1; 0.41<sup>ab</sup></td><td>5.41 &#x000b1; 2.16<sup>b</sup></td><td>13.08 &#x000b1; 1.59<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Manganese (Mn)</td><td>148.97 &#x000b1; 2.90<sup>ab</sup></td><td>149.64 &#x000b1; 5.33<sup>a</sup></td><td>140.98 &#x000b1; 20.27<sup>ab</sup></td><td>124.31 &#x000b1; 5.77<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td><bold>Total value</bold></td><td>7460.18 &#x000b1; 5.95</td><td>7460.18 &#x000b1; 7.43</td><td>7439.07 &#x000b1; 26.86</td><td>7448.84 &#x000b1; 13.36</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are reported <bold>on</bold> dry basis. The amounts are provided in the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (s.d.) form, after performing at least triplicate experiments. Total value calculated using &#x0201c;&#x02211;mean &#x000b1; sqrt&#x02211;(s.d.<sup>2</sup>)&#x0201d;. The superscript letters a, b, c and d shown in the table represent the significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for the same parameters of the different samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Antioxidant activity</title><p id="p0265">ABTS, FRAP, and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> assay were used to measure the ability of antioxidants to quench hydrophilic ABTS<sup>&#x025cf;+</sup>, Fe<sup>3+</sup>, and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Cano et&#x000a0;al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Jimenez-Alvarez et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). For lipophilic radical scavenging activity DPPH assay was performed (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Kasote et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref><xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">S&#x000e1;nchez-Ria &#x000f1; o et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). During the ABTS assay, an ABTS<sup>&#x025cf;+</sup> of blue-green chromosphere was produced by oxidation due to the addition of potassium persulfate. Here, activity was measured in terms of the amount of decolorized radical and was the highest for BM (86.42 &#x000b1; 0.26%). The lowest activity was observed for BH (79.65 &#x000b1; 0.1%) and an insignificant change was observed among the other two dried (BF and BS) samples (p = 0.07).</p><p id="p0270">In the case of FRAP, ferric ion (Fe<sup>3+</sup>) reduced to the ferrous ion (Fe<sup>2+</sup>) form by accepting an electron, donated by antioxidant under acidic conditions, which with TPTZ (2,4,6-tris(2-pyridyl)-s-triazine) forms a complex to give an intense blue color and shows a strong absorption maximum at 593 nm. Similar to the ABTS assay, in the FRAP assay, the highest reducing power was observed for BM (96.18 &#x000b1; 0.34%), but here the lowest activity was for BF (89.91 &#x000b1; 0.42%). Here, the changes for BP and BH were insignificant (p = 0.06). Previously, a similar trend for both FRAP and ABTS assay of differently dried (freeze, sun, microwave, and hot air) oyster mushroom was reported by <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Piskov et&#x000a0;al. (2020)</xref>. But, exceptionally in case of the ABTS assay, a reverse trend was observed between BH and BF.</p><p id="p0275">The DPPH assay has been done by considering that the antioxidant is a hydrogen donor, owing to the fact that the purple-colored DPPH&#x02022; (&#x003b1;,&#x003b1;-diphenyl-&#x003b2;-picryl hydrazine) is reduced to yellow colored DPPH-H upon the reaction with a hydrogen atom. Here the ability of different extracts of fresh and differently dried samples to donate hydrogen was measured. Among them, BM revealed the highest activity (64.81 &#x000b1; 0.28%), while the BS showed the lowest activity (37.13 &#x000b1; 0.25%). Different drying procedures caused a significant change in the activity (p = 8.21 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;21</sup>). A similar trend was reported previously, by <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen and Le (2018)</xref> for carrot peel. <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">Wijewardana et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</xref> studied DPPH assay for freeze, sun, and air oven-dried <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) pulp and found a similar trend but, the amounts were different, this is maybe due to different variety and different breeding conditions.</p><p id="p0280">Unlike above radicals, which are extraneous matter to biological systems, hydrogen peroxide and superoxide are reactive oxygen species (ROS) that get generated during different biochemical reactions in the living organisms. These ROS are moderately reactive, but they are precursors of other highly reactive radicals which damage cells and generate more new reactive species.</p><p id="p0285">Superoxide (O<sub>2</sub><sup>&#x025cf;-</sup>) is also the precursor of other oxidizing agents, which includes oxidizing radicals, peroxynitrite, oxidized halogens, and singlet oxygen such as hypochlorous acid, which may cause considerable harmful effect on biological systems, so it is important to study the activity against this (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Babior, 1997</xref>). The highest superoxide radical scavenging activity was shown by BF (83.2 &#x000b1; 0.33%), whereas the lowest activity was observed for BH (74.8 &#x000b1; 0.19%). However, the difference between BH and BS was insignificant (p = 0.53). <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Thi and Hwang (2016)</xref> also observed a similar trend for freeze, sun, and oven drying for black chokeberries.</p><p id="p0290">For, the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging assay polyphenols of the extracts may donate electrons to neutralize H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> into water. We observed that BP (64.47 &#x000b1; 0.35%) contained significantly higher (p = 84 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>) H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> activity than BM, though BM possessed higher H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging activity than BF but the difference was statistically insignificant (p = 0.06). Similarly, BH (59.34 &#x000b1; 0.39%) and BS (59.46 &#x000b1; 0.18%) treatment impart statistically insignificant (p = 0.83) differences for the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> activity. A similar trend for H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> activity was reported by <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Novakovi&#x00107; et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</xref> among fresh, air dried, and freeze dried raspberry.</p><p id="p0295"><xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Prathapan et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> reported DPPH and superoxide scavenging activity for baelpulp, however, the content was mentioned as an IC<sub>50</sub> value. <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Rajan et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</xref> reported DPPH, ABTS, Reducing Power, Super Oxide radical and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging activity for different doses (between 20-100 <italic>&#x003bc;</italic>g/ml) of <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) extract, for our samples the activities were greater due to use of higher dose (40 mg/ml).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Anti-inflammatory activity</title><p id="p0300">This investigation was carried out to observe the ability of differently dried and fresh <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) pulp extracts to prevent the thermal protein denaturation and coagulation, to evaluate its anti-inflammatory activity. The denatured protein expressed as antigens, which are associated with Type III hypersensitive reaction causes diseases like, serum sickness, glomerulo-nephritis, rheumatoid arthritis, and systemic lupus erythematosus (<xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">Williams et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). According to the study by <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Gell and Benacerraf (1959)</xref>, it can be concluded that the heat-denatured proteins are potent as native proteins to stimulate delayed hypersensitivity and it was already confirmed by <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Gilman et&#x000a0;al. (1990)</xref> that the conventional Non-Steroidal Anti-Inflammatory Drugs (NSAID) also work by preventing the denaturation of proteins. Thusit can be concluded that the anti-denaturation assay is an appropriate <italic>in vitro</italic> procedure to assess the anti-inflammatory activity. Drying methods significantly affected the BSA (p = 9.41 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;13</sup>) and egg-albumin (p = 2.62 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>) inhibitory activity. The order of BSA and egg-albumin heat-induced protein denaturation inhibitory activity was as follows: BS &#x0003c; BH &#x0003c; BP &#x0003c; BF &#x0003c; BM. With comparison to the fresh pulp, the BSA and egg-albumin denaturation inhibition activity increased by 6.77%, 10.03% and 2.67%, 6.29% for BM and BF respectively, whereas the same was decreased with respect to the BP by 18.68%, 14.49%, and 9.2%, 5.29% for BS and BH respectively. <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et&#x000a0;al. (2006)</xref>; <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Rahman and Parvin (2014)</xref> reported <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.) possessed the <italic>invitro</italic> and <italic>invivo</italic> anti-inflammatory activity. We have found a positive correlation by 0.89, 0.85, and 0.86 respectively with TPC for BSA, egg-albumin denaturation inhibitory activity, and anti-proteinase. The review article of <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> also seconds our observation which mentioned multiple studies that reported anti-inflammatory activities of polyphenols against various <italic>in vitro</italic> models.</p><p id="p0305">Proteinases are mainly linked with arthritic reactions, which are present in the lysosomal granules of neutrophils. The proteinases from leukocytes play a major role in promoting tissue damage during inflammation and it was suggested that the extract may prevent these lysosomal elements such as bactericidal enzymes and proteinases from resisting further damage (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Chou, 1997</xref>). To inhibit these serine proteinases it is essential to have hydroxyl groups at the ortho and para position of the benzene ring attached to the benzopyrone in flavonoids. It is proposed that these hydroxyl groups may form the hydrogen bridges with the amino acid residues located near or, at the active site on the trypsin molecule (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Brinkworth et&#x000a0;al., 1992</xref>)<bold>.</bold> Drying methods significantly affect (p = 5.82 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup>) the anti-proteinase activity. The anti-proteinase activity was increased for BM and BF by 2.66% and 1.64% respectively, while the same was decreased by 2.46% and 5.89% for BH and BS respectively than BP (<xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;7</xref>). <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Behera et&#x000a0;al., (2012)</xref>, reported <italic>invivo</italic> anti-proteinase activity of unripe bael on albino rats.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl7"><label>Table&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Antioxidant activities, anti-diabetic activity, anti-inflammatory activities of all the samples (BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#x000a0;7</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Medicinal Activities (%)</th><th>BP</th><th>BM</th><th>BS</th><th>BH</th><th>BF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6">Anti-diabetic activity<hr/></td></tr><tr><td>&#x003b1;-amylase inhibitory (AD)</td><td>74.59 &#x000b1; 0.57<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>78.85 &#x000b1; 1.54<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>72.38 &#x000b1; 0.88<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>73.93 &#x000b1; 0.75<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>78.7 &#x000b1; 0.71<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><bold>Anti-inflammatory activity</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Bovine-serum denaturation inhibitory (BS)</td><td>39.66 &#x000b1; 1.88<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>42.34 &#x000b1; 0.97<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>32.25 &#x000b1; 1.20<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>36.01 &#x000b1; 0.67<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>40.72 &#x000b1; 0.80<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Egg-albumin denaturation inhibitory (EA)</td><td>57.42 &#x000b1; 0.98<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>63.18 &#x000b1; 0.32<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>49.1 &#x000b1; 0.39<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>54.38 &#x000b1; 1.18<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>61.03 &#x000b1; 0.74<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Anti-proteinase activity (AP)</td><td>80.19 &#x000b1; 1.45<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>82.32 &#x000b1; 0.76<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>75.47 &#x000b1; 0.95<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>78.22 &#x000b1; 2.30<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>81.5 &#x000b1; 0.84<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><bold>Anti-oxidant activity</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>DPPH scavenging activity (DPPH)</td><td>58.95 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>64.81 &#x000b1; 0.28<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>37.13 &#x000b1; 0.25<sup><bold>e</bold></sup></td><td>52.95 &#x000b1; 0.29<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>62.95 &#x000b1; 0.3<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>FRAP assay (FRAP)</td><td>93.81 &#x000b1; 0.49<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>96.18 &#x000b1; 0.34<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>90.29 &#x000b1; 0.42<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>94.44 &#x000b1; 0.4<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>89.91 &#x000b1; 0.42<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging activity (H2O2)</td><td>64.47 &#x000b1; 0.35<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>61.78 &#x000b1; 0.29<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>59.46 &#x000b1; 0.18<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>59.34 &#x000b1; 0.39<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>60.68 &#x000b1; 0.3<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>Super oxide scavenging activity (SO)</td><td>79.21 &#x000b1; 0.25<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>82.49 &#x000b1; 0.42<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>75.9 &#x000b1; 0.27<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>74.8 &#x000b1; 0.19<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>83.2 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td></tr><tr><td>ABTS assay (ABTS)</td><td>83.91 &#x000b1; 0.17<sup><bold>c</bold></sup></td><td>86.42 &#x000b1; 0.26<sup><bold>a</bold></sup></td><td>84.38 &#x000b1; 0.21<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td><td>79.65 &#x000b1; 0.1<sup><bold>d</bold></sup></td><td>83.5 &#x000b1; 0.14<sup><bold>b</bold></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>All values are reported <bold>on</bold> dry basis. The amounts are provided in the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (s.d.) form, after performing at least triplicate experiments. The superscript letters a, b, c, d and e shown in the table represent the significant differences (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for the same parameters of the different samples.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Anti-diabetic activity</title><p id="p0310">It is estimated that the number of diabetic patients will be around 439 million by 2030, out of which 300 million are expecting type-2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) (<xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Shaw et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The awareness of the issue has led to a tendency to screen natural sources for anti-diabetic activity. Starch contains amylase and amylopectin, where, &#x000e1;-amylase splits the &#x000e1;-1,4-glycosidic linkages in amylose to yield maltose and glucose (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">American Diabetes Association, 2014</xref><xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>) and also hydrolyses amylopectin and glycogen to produce a mixture of branched and unbranched oligosaccharides (<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Morton, 2010</xref>), which further in small intestine breaks down into monosaccharides. &#x000e1;-amylase inhibitors (also known as, starch blockers) prevent or reduce down the absorption of starch into the body, by reducing or, inhibiting the activities of &#x000e1;-amylases. Flavonols like quercetin and flavones have an experimentally substantiated effect on &#x000e1;-amylase inhibition activity. Both flavonols and flavones contain a C=O group at the 4<sup>th</sup> carbon atom in the pyrone ring. Therefore the benzopyrone and benzene rings are involved in a pi-electron conjugation system through p-orbital sharing. Hence these two sub-classes of flavonoid groups deliberately provide amended binding property along with &#x000e1;-amylase. Both the benzene rings possess hydroxyl groups in the ortho and meta position, which is the favourable position for a reaction with catalytic enzymes (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Lo Piparo et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). Bael is recognized for decades due to its anti-diabetic property (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Prathapan et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). BM and BF showed significantly higher anti-diabetic activity than BP with 5.71% and 5.51% greater activity with respect to fresh pulp respectively, whereas the same property was significantly lower for BH and BS; 0.89% and 2.96% decrease in anti-diabetic activity pertaining to the fresh pulp, was observed for hot-air and sun drying respectively (<xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;7</xref>). <xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref> observed higher anti-diabetic activity for freeze dried bitter melon than hot-air dried sample. This activity is positively correlated by 0.79 and 0.7 with TPC and TFC.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><label>3.7</label><title>Multivariate analysis</title><p id="p0315">Multivariate analysis is performed if, it is not feasible to proceed with a simple visual assessment to determine the differences between different samples. We used PCA, HCA heat map, and correlation for altogether 43 factors, including bioactive compounds and medicinal activities to study the relative variability among the different <italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (L.)samples. The results of PCA shows that 94.05% of the total variability comprised of the first three components, PC1 (37.82%), PC2 (27.07%), and PC3 (22.29%). From <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>, it can be observed that BS, BH, and BF exist on the positive side of the PC1 while BP and BM contributed to the negative side. BM and BF loading showed similar positive PC2 scores, but the BP, BH, and BS were located differently from the other two samples in the negative quadrant of PC2. The <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref> also suggested that the most of the factors like vitamin B<sub>2</sub> (B2), succinic acid (SA), tartaric acid (TA), citric acid (CA), ascorbic acid (Asc A), vitamin B<sub>12</sub> (B12), vitamin B<sub>3</sub> (B3), &#x003b4;-tocopherol (delta T) and &#x003b1;-carotene (alpha C), went along with the BP, followed by BM where, anti-inflammatory activity, super-oxide activity (SO), bovine-serum activity, egg-albumin activity, anti-diabetic activity, TPC, DPPH formed a cluster and malic acid (MA), ABTS, oxalic acid (OA), TFC are overlapped by both BM and BF. For the BS, vanillic acid (VA), dihydroxy benzoic acid (DHBA), protocatechuic acid (p-CA), &#x003b1;-tocopherol (alpha T), &#x003b2;-tocopherol (beta T), &#x003b2;-carotene (beta C), &#x003b4;-carotene (delta C) formed a cluster separately and only vitamin C went with the BH. Even from the dendrogram of the factors shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>, three main clusters were observed. Based on the characteristics of the investigated factors, the dendrogram of the different samples clearly depicted that BP stands differently, while BF and BM shared a common cluster. For both BH and BS, higher destruction of some of factors was observed due to prolonged processing time, so they were clustered together. The heat map provided a correlation between the samples and factors, which provide a clear summary of the interrelation within the effects of drying and compositional aspects of bael.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Principal component analysis of all the samples (BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample) based on total polyphenols (TPC: Total polyphenol content; TFC: Total flavonoid content), phenolic acids (GA: Gallic acid; DHBA: 2, 3-dihydroxy benzoic acid; CGA: Chlorogenic acid; p-CA: p-Coumaric acid; VA: Vanillic acid), vitamin B group (Vit B1: Thiamine(vitamin B<sub>1</sub>); Vit B3: Niacin(vitamin B<sub>3</sub>); Vit B6: Pyridoxine(vitamin B<sub>6</sub>); Vit B5: Pantothenic acid(vitamin B<sub>5</sub>); Vit B7: Biotin(vitamin B<sub>7</sub>); Vit B12: Cobalamins(vitamin B<sub>12</sub>); Vit B2: Riboflavin(vitamin B<sub>2</sub>)), tocopherols (delta-T: &#x003b4; Tocopherol; gamma-T: &#x003b3; Tocopherol; beta-T: &#x003b2; Tocopherol; alpha-T: &#x003b1; Tocopherol), orgainc acids and vitamin C (OA: Oxalic acid; TA: Tartaric acid; MA: Malic acid; LA: Lactic acid; AA: Acetic acid; CA: Citric acid; PA: Propionic acid; SA: Succinic acid; FA: Fumaric acid; Asc-A: Ascorbic acid), carotenes (alpha-C: &#x003b1; Carotene; beta-C: &#x003b2; Carotene; gamma-C: &#x003b3; Carotene; delta-C: &#x003b4; Carotene), anti-oxidant activities (DPPH: DPPH scavenging activity; FRAP: FRAP assay; H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>: H202 scavenging activity; SO: Super oxide scavenging activity; ABTS: ABTS assay, anti-diabetic activity (AD) and anti-inflammatory activity (EA: egg-albumin denaturation inhibitory activity, BS: bovine-serum denaturation inhibitory activity, AP: anti-proteinase activity.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Hierarchical cluster-heat map analysis of all the samples(BP: fruit pulp; BM: microwave dried sample; BS: sun dried sample, BH: hot air dried sample; BF: freeze dried sample) based on total polyphenols (TPC: Total polyphenol content; TFC: Total flavonoid content), phenolic acids (GA: Gallic acid; DHBA: 2, 3-dihydroxy benzoic acid; CGA: Chlorogenic acid; p-CA: p-Coumaric acid; VA: Vanillic acid), vitamin B group (Vit B1: Thiamine(vitamin B<sub>1</sub>); Vit B3: Niacin(vitamin B<sub>3</sub>); Vit B6: Pyridoxine(vitamin B<sub>6</sub>); Vit B5: Pantothenic acid(vitamin B<sub>5</sub>); Vit B7: Biotin(vitamin B<sub>7</sub>); Vit B12: Cobalamins(vitamin B<sub>12</sub>); Vit B2: Riboflavin(vitamin B<sub>2</sub>)), tocopherols (delta-T: &#x003b4; Tocopherol; gamma-T: &#x003b3; Tocopherol; beta-T: &#x003b2; Tocopherol; alpha-T: &#x003b1; Tocopherol), orgainc acids and vitamin C (OA: Oxalic acid; TA: Tartaric acid; MA: Malic acid; LA: Lactic acid; AA: Acetic acid; CA: Citric acid; PA: Propionic acid; SA: Succinic acid; FA: Fumaric acid; Asc-A: Ascorbic acid), carotenes (alpha-C: &#x003b1; Carotene; beta-C: &#x003b2; Carotene; gamma-C: &#x003b3; Carotene; delta-C: &#x003b4; Carotene), anti-oxidant activities (DPPH: DPPH scavenging activity; FRAP: FRAP assay; H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>: H202 scavenging activity; SO: Super oxide scavenging activity; ABTS: ABTS assay), anti-diabetic activity (AD) and anti-inflammatory activity (EA: egg-albumin denaturation inhibitory activity, BS: bovine-serum denaturation inhibitory activity, AP: anti-proteinase activity).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0320">From the results it can be observed that different components get affected differently depending on the mechanism of the drying like, in BM bound components (mainly polyphenols) get released, so the total content increased with respect to BP and some were destroyed in the lesser amount due lower time of operation. For, BS some enzymes get optimal working conditions, which affected the compounds differently (polyphenols get reduced, whereas tocopherols increased), while surprisingly BH showed enhancements of vitamin (vitamin B<sub>1</sub> and B<sub>5</sub>) and carotene (&#x003b3;-carotene) content. Maximum retention for most of the components was observed in low-temperature treatment (BF). The best result was found in BM, with respect to the medicinal activities. The study also shows that the mineral content doesn't change along with different drying using EDXRF analysis.</p><p id="p0325">This comprehensive study gives a detailed discussion on the effects of drying on different components (in total of 50 factors for each drying technique) and shows the diversity in the behaviour of the factors. It also reveals the proper quantitative composition of bael, many of them not previously revealed. It also reflects light upon the traditional preservation method, which can be used to overproduced pulpy crops.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0330">Sudipta Kumar Hazra: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0335">Tanmay Sarkar: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0340">Molla Salauddin: Performed the experiments; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0345">Hassan I. Sheikh: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0350">Siddhartha Pati: Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0355">Runu Chakraborty: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0360">This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0365">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0370">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abirami</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarani</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddhuraju</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In Vitro antioxidant, anti-diabetic, cholinesterase and tyrosinase inhibitory potential of fresh juice from <italic>Citrushystrix</italic>and <italic>C.maxima</italic> fruits</article-title><source>Food Sci. Hum. Wellness</source><volume>3</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of total phenolic content and other oxidation substrates in plant tissues using Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu reagent</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17446889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al Juhaimi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zcan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uslu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghafoor</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of drying temperatures on antioxidant activity, phenolic compounds, fatty acid composition and tocopherol contents in citrus seed and oils</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Sci. Technol.</source><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29358810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alajaji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Adawy</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional composition of chickpea (<italic>Cicerarietinum</italic> L.) as affected by microwave cooking and other traditional cooking methods</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Compos. Anal.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>812</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allegretta</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gattullo</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renna</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paradiso</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terzano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid multi-element characterization of microgreens via total-reflection X-rayfluorescence (TXRF) spectrometry</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>296</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31202310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis and classification of diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23959568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>AOAC International</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Official Methods of Analysis</chapter-title><edition>fifteenth ed.</edition><year>1990</year><comment>Arlington, Va, USA</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>AOAC International</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Official Methods of Analysis of the Association of the Official Analytical Chemists</chapter-title><edition>seventeenth ed.</edition><year>2000</year><comment>Washington, DC, USA</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of total phenolic and flavonoid content, antimicrobial and antioxidant activity of a root extract of <italic>Arisaemajacquemontii</italic>Blume</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Taibah Univ. Sci.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>454</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babior</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superoxide: a two-edged sword</article-title><source>Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res.</source><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9239299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baliga</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazal</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemistry and medicinal uses of theBael fruit (<italic>Aeglemarmelos Correa</italic>): a concise review</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1768</fpage><lpage>1775</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baliga</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mane</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimmy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Chapter 20 - review on the protective effects of the indigenous Indian medicinal plant, bael (<italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> correa)</chapter-title><source>Gastrointestinal Disorders, Bioactive Food as Dietary Interventions for Liver and Gastrointestinal Disease</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>324</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bechoff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhuique-Mayer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marouz&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Westby</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of hot air, solar and sun drying treatments on provitamin A retention in orange-fleshed sweet potato</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Eng.</source><volume>92</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>171</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramani</surname><given-names>Y.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rath</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pradhan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of aqueous extract of <italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> unripe fruit on inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Indian J. Pharmacol.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzie</surname><given-names>I.F.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ferric reducing ability of plasma (FRAP) as a measure of &#x0201c;antioxidant power&#x0201d;: the FRAP assay</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>239</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8660627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brinkworth</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoermer</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairlie</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavones are inhibitors of HIV-1 proteinase</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source><volume>188</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1992</year><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1445308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cal&#x000ed;n-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figiel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition, antioxidant capacity, and sensory quality of pomegranate (<italic>punicagranatum</italic> L.)Arils and rind as affected by drying method</article-title><source>Food Bioprocess Technol.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1644</fpage><lpage>1654</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcaraz</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnao</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On-line antioxidant activity determination: comparison of hydrophilic and lipophilic antioxidant activity using the ABTS<sup>&#x02022;+</sup> assay</article-title><source>Redox Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12189056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Libardi</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skibsted</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Riboflavin as a photosensitizer. Effects on human health and food quality</article-title><source>Food Funct.</source><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22406738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J.C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>P.C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>P.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative studies on the effect of three drying methods on the nutritional composition of seaweed <italic>Sargassumhemiphyllum</italic> (Turn.) C. Ag.</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>45</volume><issue>8</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>3056</fpage><lpage>3059</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary <italic>in vitro</italic> assessment of anti-inflammatory property of <italic>Mikaniascandens</italic> flower extract</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Adv. Pharm. Educ. Res.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparisons on the antioxidant properties of fresh, freeze-dried and hot-air-dried tomatoes</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Eng.</source><volume>77</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>485</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charoensiddhi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anprung</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive compounds and volatile compounds of Thai bael fruit (<italic>AegleMarmelos</italic> (L.)Correa) as a valuable source for functional food ingredients</article-title><source>Int. Food Res. J.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical reactions and stability of riboflavin in foods</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Sci.</source><volume>70</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>R28</fpage><lpage>R36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anti-inflammatory effect of an extract of <italic>Tripterygiumwilfordii hook F</italic> on adjuvant-induced paw oedema in rats and inflammatory mediators release</article-title><source>Phytother Res.</source><volume>11</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>154</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>N.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clydesdale</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decomposition of organic acids during processing and storage</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Milk Food Technol.</source><volume>39</volume><year>1976</year><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>480</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c7;oklar</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbulut</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of sun, oven and freeze-drying on anthocyanins, phenolic compounds and antioxidant activity of black grape (Ek&#x0015f;ikara) (<italic>Vitisvinifera</italic> L.)</article-title><source>S.&#x000a0;Afr. J. Enol. Vitic.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>272</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Combs</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The Vitamins: Fundamental Aspects in Nutrition and Health</chapter-title><year>2012</year><publisher-name>Elsevier Academic Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramalhosa</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organic acid profile of chestnut (<italic>Castaneasativa</italic> Mill.) as affected by hot air convective drying</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Prop.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>565</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diamante</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fruit leathers: method of preparation and effect of different conditions on qualities</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Sci.</source><volume>2014</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of drying temperature on the sugars, organic acids, limonoids, phenolics, and antioxidant capacities of lemon slices</article-title><source>Food SciBiotechnol</source><volume>26</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1533</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duthie</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duthie</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyle</surname><given-names>J.A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant polyphenols in cancer and heart disease</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>56</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>1084</fpage><lpage>1090</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemistry of thiamine degradation in food products and model systems: a review</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1973</year><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4565919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>X-ray fluorescence application in food, feed, and agricultural science: a critical review</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr.</source><volume>60</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30277800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in our understanding of tocopherol biosynthesis in plants: an overview of key genes, functions, and breeding of vitamin E improved crops</article-title><source>Antioxidants (Basel, Switzerland)</source><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>99</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000e1;lvez-Valdivieso</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carde&#x000f1;osa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x003b3;-Tocopherolmethyltransferase from the green alga <italic>Chlamydomonasreinhardtii</italic>: functional characterization and expression analysis</article-title><source>Physiol. Plantarum</source><volume>143</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>328</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of drying of jujubes (<italic>Ziziphusjujuba</italic> Mill.) on the contents of sugars, organic acids, &#x003b1;-tocopherol, &#x003b2;-carotene, and phenolic compounds</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>60</volume><issue>38</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>9642</fpage><lpage>9648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22958080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasecka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siwulski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magdziak</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Budzy&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuper</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niedzielski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mleczek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of drying temperature on bioactive compounds and antioxidant activity of <italic>Leccinumscabrum</italic> (Bull.) Gray and <italic>Hericiumerinaceus</italic> (Bull.) Pers</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Sci. Technol.</source><volume>57</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32116361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gell</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benacerraf</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on hypersensitivity. II. Delayed hypersensitivity to denatured proteins in Guinea pigs</article-title><source>Immunology</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1959</year><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13640681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chorismic acid: purification and some chemical and physical studies</article-title><source>Biochem. J.</source><volume>90</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1964</year><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5834235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rall</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nies</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insel PA: analgesic-antipyretics and antiinflammatory agents: DrugEmployed in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis and gout</article-title><source>InGoodman Gilman&#x02019;s Pharmacol. Basis Therapeut.</source><year>1990</year><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>681</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunathilake</surname><given-names>K.D.P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranaweera</surname><given-names>K.K.D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupasinghe</surname><given-names>H.P.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of boiling, steaming and frying of selected leafy vegetables on the in vitro anti-inflammation associated biological activities</article-title><source>Plants</source><volume>7</volume><issue>22</issue><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hannaker</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haukka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of ICP-AES and XRF analysis of major and minor constituents on geological materials</article-title><source>Chem. Geol.</source><volume>42</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>324</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salauddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of freeze drying on antioxidant properties of bael fruit (<italic>Aglemarmelos</italic>)</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Biol. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>430</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimm</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stampfer</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ascherio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folate, vitamin B6, and B12 intakes in relation to risk of stroke among men</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>35</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14671243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosseinzadeh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassiri-Asl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of the protective effects of rutin on the metabolic function as an important dietary flavonoid</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Endocrinol. Invest.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24879037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of drying methods on non-volatile taste components of <italic>Strophariarugoso-annulata</italic>mushrooms</article-title><source>LWT</source><volume>127</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>109428</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iso</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokubo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okayama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsugane</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intake of folate, vitamin B6, and vitamin B12 and the risk of CHD: the Japan public health center-based prospective study cohort I</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Am. Coll. Nutr.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18460491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shams</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siraj</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masum</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>J.U.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of minerals content in green and ripe bael (wood apple) powder</article-title><source>Int. J. Basic Appl. Sci.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>136</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jimenez-Alvarez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuffrida</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanrobaeys</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golay</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotting</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lardeau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keely</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput methods to assess lipophilic and hydrophilic antioxidant capacity of food extracts in vitro</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>56</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>3470</fpage><lpage>3477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18433133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadakal</surname><given-names>&#x000c7;.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekinci</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yapar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of cooking and drying on the watersoluble vitamins content of bulgur</article-title><source>Food Sci. Technol. Int.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>354</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamiloglu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capanoglu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyphenol content in figs (<italic>Ficuscarica</italic> L.): effect of sun-drying</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Prop.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>535</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasote</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaprakasha</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf disc assays for rapid measurement of antioxidant activity</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1884</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30760761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidants in fruits and vegetables - the millennium&#x02019;s health</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Sci. Technol.</source><volume>36</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>725</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khoo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>K.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carotenoids and their isomers: color pigments in fruits and vegetables</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>16</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1710</fpage><lpage>1738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21336241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Decarli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vegetable consumption and risk of chronic disease</article-title><source>Epidemiology</source><volume>9</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9504293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laoretani</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crapiste</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolasco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of drying operating conditions on Canola oil tocopherol content</article-title><source>Antioxidants (Basel, Switzerland)</source><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>199</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib112"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optWs3snb7fNS"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>W.C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant capacity of phytochemicals and their potential effects on oxidative status in animals - A review</article-title><source>Asian-Australas. J. Anim. sci.</source><year>2017</year><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27660026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of drying methods on the tasty compounds of <italic>Pleurotuseryngi</italic>i</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>166</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25053068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title><italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic>, Edible Medicinal and Non-medicinal Plants</chapter-title><year>2012</year><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>618</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo Piparo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheib</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavonoids for controlling starch digestion: structural requirements for inhibiting human alpha-amylase</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Med. Chem.</source><volume>51</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>3555</fpage><lpage>3561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18507367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maharaj</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankat</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality changes in dehydrated dasheen leaves: effects of blanching pre-treatments and drying conditions</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>29</volume><issue>5&#x02013;6</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>568</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manandhar</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical profile and pharmacological activity of <italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> Linn</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Integr. Med.</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenelon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Callaghan</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Energydispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry as a tool for the rapid determination of the five major minerals (Na, Mg, K, P and Ca) in skim milk powder</article-title><source>Int. J. Dairy Technol.</source><volume>73</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>467</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neeraj</surname><given-names>B.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johar</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bael (<italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic>) extraordinary species of India: a review</article-title><source>Int. J. Curr. Microbiol. Appl. Sci.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1870</fpage><lpage>1887</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>V.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of various drying conditions on phytochemical compounds and antioxidant activity of carrot peel</article-title><source>Beverages</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>80</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novakovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevanovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorjanovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jovanovic</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Te&#x00161;evi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jankovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su&#x0017e;njevi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes of hydrogen peroxide and radical-scavenging activity of raspberry during osmotic, convective, and freeze-drying</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Sci.</source><volume>76</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>C663</fpage><lpage>C668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22417351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schandra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chataurvedi</surname><given-names>O.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the storage life of bael (<italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> correa)</article-title><source>Int. J. Agric. Invent.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bio-processing of bael [<italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> L.] fruits into wine with antioxidants</article-title><source>Food Biosci.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optbUutknE8HB"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pati</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterji</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raveen</surname><given-names>B.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahimi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atan</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Binti</surname><given-names>T.S.B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanta</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural Characterization and Antioxidant Potential of Chitosan by &#x003b3;-Irradiation from the Carapace of Horseshoe Crab</article-title><source>Polymers</source><volume>12</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2361</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piskov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Timchenko</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rzhepakovsky</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avanesyan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sizonenko</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurchenko</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of various drying methods on some physico-chemical properties and the antioxidant profile and ACE inhibition activity of oyster mushrooms (PleurotusOstreatus)</article-title><source>Foods</source><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>160</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prathapan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisha</surname><given-names>V.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaresan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghu</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyphenol rich fruit pulp of <italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> (L.) Correa exhibits nutraceutical properties to down regulate diabetic complications&#x02014;an in vitro study</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>48</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>690</fpage><lpage>695</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qing-guo</surname><given-names>Hu.</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mujumdar</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei-hua</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin-cai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of different drying methods on the quality changes of granular Edamame</article-title><source>Dry. Technol.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parvin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic potential of <italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> (L.)- an overview</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Trop Dis.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokila</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jency</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindha</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sujatha</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and Phytochemical properties of <italic>AegleMarmelos</italic> fruit pulp</article-title><source>Int. J. Curr. Pharm. Res.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranganna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Handbook of Analysis and Quality Control for Fruit and Vegetable Products</chapter-title><year>1986</year><publisher-name>Tata McGraw-Hill Book Co</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic acids in foods: an overview of analytical methodology</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>2866</fpage><lpage>2887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12720366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitinoja</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>9 - Bael (<italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> (L.) Corr. Serr.),Postharvest Biology and Technology of Tropical and Subtropical Fruits</chapter-title><year>2011</year><publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing</publisher-name><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref77"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saifullah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCullum</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCluskey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of different drying methods on extractable phenolic compounds and antioxidant properties from lemon myrtle dried leaves</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e03044</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giridhar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of dehydration methods on retention of carotenoids, tocopherols, ascorbic acid and antioxidant activity in <italic>Moringaoleifera</italic> leaves and preparation of a RTE product</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Sci. Technol.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>2176</fpage><lpage>2182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25190880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref79"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sajib</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoque</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeasmin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minerals and heavy metals concentration in selected tropical fruits of Bangladesh</article-title><source>Int. Food Res. J.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1731</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juvekar</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambhire</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity of methanol extract of <italic>Oxalis corniculata</italic> Linn</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm. Pharm. Sci.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>155</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref81"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sami</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HPLC analysis of water-soluble vitamins (B2, B3, B6, B12, and C) and fat-soluble vitamins (E, K, D, A, and &#x003b2;-carotene) of Okra (<italic>Abelmoschusesculentus</italic>)</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Chem.</source><volume>2014</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref82"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Ria&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solanilla-Duque</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;ndez-Arteaga</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;quiro-Herrera</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive potential of Colombian feijoa in physiological ripening stage</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Saudi Soc. Agric. Sci.</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref83"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>P.H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of L-ascorbic acid degradation in pineapple drying under ethanolic atmosphere</article-title><source>Dry. Technol.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>954</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref84"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salauddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;novel data science application approach for classification of nutritional composition, instrumental colour, texture and sensory analysis of bael fruit (Aeglemarmelos (L) correa)</article-title><source>Int. J. Intell. Networks</source><volume>1</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref85"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salauddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of cutting edge drying technology on the physicochemical and bioactive components of mango (Langra variety) leather</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Res.</source><year>2020</year><fpage>100074</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref86"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salauddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial neural network modelling approach of drying kinetics evolution for hot air oven, microwave, microwave convective and freeze dried pineapple</article-title><source>SN Appl. Sci.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1621</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib111"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optJkBKpgNOcw"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salauddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-depth pharmacological and nutritional properties of bael (Aegle marmelos): A critical review</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Res.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib114"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optRfijfM8KQs"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salauddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazra</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of raw and differently dried pineapple (Ananas comosus) fortification on the vitamins, organic acid and carotene profile of dairy rasgulla (sweetened cheese ball)</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e05233</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref87"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnellbaecher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellmaine</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamins in cell culture media: stability and stabilization strategies</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Bioeng.</source><volume>116</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1537</fpage><lpage>1555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30793282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref88"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naczk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Food phenolics.Sources, Chemistry, Effects and Applications, Lancaster</chapter-title><year>1995</year><publisher-name>Technomic Pub. Co.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref89"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>History and taxonomy of <italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic>: a review</article-title><source>Int. J. Pure Appl. Biosci.</source><volume>1</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref90"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;review on Bael tree</article-title><source>Nat. Product. Radiance</source><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref91"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sicree</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmet</surname><given-names>P.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global estimates of theprevalence of diabetes for 2010 and 2030</article-title><source>Diabetes Res. Clin. Pract.</source><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19896746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref92"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shigeoka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiko</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsunaga</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and properties of &#x003b3;-tocopherolmethyltransferase in <italic>Euglena gracilis</italic></article-title><source>Biochimicaet Biophysica Acta (BBA) - Lipids Lipid Metabol.</source><volume>1128</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><year>1992</year><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>226</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref93"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slatnar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klancar</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stampar</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veberic</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of drying of figs (<italic>Ficuscarica</italic> L.) on the contents of sugars, organic acids, and phenolic compounds</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>59</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>11696</fpage><lpage>11702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21958361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref94"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>8 - DIGESTION and ABSORPTION, the Digestive System</chapter-title><edition>second ed.</edition><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Churchill Livingstone</publisher-name><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref95"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thi</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of drying methods on contents of bioactive compounds and antioxidant activities of black chokeberries (<italic>Aroniamelanocarpa</italic>)</article-title><source>Food Sci. Biotechnol.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30263236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref96"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of different drying methods on the product quality and volatile compounds of whole shiitake mushrooms</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>197</volume><issue>A</issue><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref97"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turhan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zararslz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karabacak</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of element levels in selected wild mushroom species in Turkey using non-destructive analytical techniques</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Prop.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>731</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref98"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uribe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo-Orellana</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega-G&#x000e1;lvez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ah-Hen</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Past&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubourg</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Effect of Drying Methods on Bioactive Compounds, Nutritional, Antioxidant, and Antidiabetic Potential of Brown Alga <italic>Durvillaeaantarctica</italic>, Drying Technology</chapter-title><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref99"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uribe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega-Galvez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasten</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x00131;guez</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ah-Hen</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical components and amino acid profile of Brown seaweed <italic>Durvillaeaantarctica</italic> as affected by air drying temperature</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Sci. Technol.</source><volume>55</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>4792</fpage><lpage>4801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Hoed</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Clercq</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Echim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adnsjelkovic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leber</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Wettinck</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verh&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Berry seeds: a source of speciality oils with high content of bioactives and nutritional value</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Lipids</source><volume>16</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib113"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optuvhxhQeae3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valadez-Carmona</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plazola-Jacinto</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Ortega</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Navarro</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villarreal</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Necoechea-Mondrag&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz-Moreno</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceballos-Reyes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>, Effects of microwaves, hot air and freeze-drying on the phenolic compounds, antioxidant capacity, enzyme activity and microstructure of cacao pod husks (Theobroma cacao L.)</article-title><source>Innov. Food Sci. Emerg. Technol.</source><volume>41</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>386</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib101"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref101"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Famiani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Warrington</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><series>&#x0201c;Chapter 8.Organic Acids in Fruits: Metabolism, Functions and Contents&#x0201d; in Horticultural Reviews</series><volume>Vol. 45</volume><year>2018</year><publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Inc.</publisher-name><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>430</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib102"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref102"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiemori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of microwave heating on the loss of vitamin B<sub>12</sub> in foods</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10554220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib103"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref103"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wijewardana</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawarathne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunawardane</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasala</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thilakarathne</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retention of physicochemical and antioxidant properties of dehydrated bael (<italic>AegleMarmelos</italic>) and palmyra (<italic>BorassusFlabellifer</italic>) fruit powders</article-title><source>Procedia Food Sci.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib104"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref104"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wildermuth</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Were</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chlorogenic acid oxidation and its reaction with sunflower proteins to form green-colored complexes</article-title><source>Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf.</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Latore</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogler</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The in vitro anti-denaturation effects induced by natural products and non-steroidal compounds in heat treated (Immunogenic) bovine serum albumin is proposed as a screening assay for the detection of anti-inflammatory compounds, without the use of animals, in the early stages of the drug discovery process</article-title><source>W.&#x000a0;Indian Med. J.</source><volume>57</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19566010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib106"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref106"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of SomeEthnomedicinally important constituents of <italic>Aeglemarmelos</italic> fruit during different stages of ripening</article-title><source>Chin. J. Nat. Med.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>209</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib107"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref107"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zadernowski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Czaplicki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naczk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic acid profiles of mangosteen fruits (<italic>Garciniamangostana</italic>)</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>112</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>689</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib108"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref108"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slavin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutterodt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whent</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eskin</surname><given-names>N.A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Chapter 1 - Cereals and Legumes, Biochemistry of Foods</chapter-title><edition>third ed.</edition><year>2013</year><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib109"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref109"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory effects of phytochemicals from fruits, vegetables, and food legumes: a review</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr.</source><volume>58</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1260</fpage><lpage>1270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28605204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of superfine grinding on antidiabetic activity of bitter melon powder</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>14203</fpage><lpage>14218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23203059</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0380">We would like to thank Dr. Dipankar Mondal (Associate Professor (Scientist E), Institute of Nano Science and Technology) for his guidance to perform EDXRF analysis. We also acknowledge Dr. Ramdhan Majhi (MDLC facility, Indian Institute of Chemical Biology) for his continuous support and guidance in HPLC analysis.</p></ack></back></article>