<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The comparative analysis of gene expression between essential oil-treated and untreated cells is the main strategy used to assess genomic changes in the target pathogens induced by essential oils. Myszka et al investigated the ability of thyme essential oil to develop anti-quorum sensing and anti-biofilm formation against the opportunistic pathogen, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Their study found reduced quorum sensing and biofilm formation activity in thyme essential oil-treated 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> using quorum sensing autoinducer and biofilm formation assay.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr41-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>
 </sup> Further evaluation of flagella-related gene 
 <italic>flgA</italic> that regulate quorum sensing activity showed reduce expression upon exposure to thyme essential oil.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr41-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>
 </sup> Kovács et al compared the gene expression of peppermint essential oil-treated and untreated 
 <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> using comparative real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR). A panel of genes related to pathogenic process, stress response, basic metabolism, and transcription regulation were screened and increased expression of oxidative stress response genes was found in essential oil-treated 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr42-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 </sup> Lai et al investigated the effect of lavender essential oil against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> with comparative microarray analysis. Their study reported that lavender essential oil affects the phosphotransferase system and lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis pathway by upregulating genes involved in the pathway mentioned.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr43-1176934320938391" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
 </sup> These revealed signs of membrane damage as increased expressions of phosphotransferase system and lipopolysaccharide biosynthesis genes indicated counter-response in bacterial membrane repair.
</p>
