<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The efficacy of green-synthesized FeNPs and SH essential oil on the growth and proliferation of cancer cell lines was examined by the colorimetric method, methyl thiazol tetrazolium (MTT). Due to the mitochondrial activity of living cells, tetrazolium salts are reduced to Formosan crystals with different absorptions [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. To perform this method, 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of prepared cellular suspension was seeded in each cell of a 96-cell microplate, so that each mL of culture medium contained 10,000 cell lines. After 24 h of incubation, different concentrations (1, 10, 50, 100, 200, and 500 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL) of synthesized FeNPs and SH essential oil were incubated. After 24 h of treating cells with FeNPs, 20 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of MTT color (Sigma Co., Germany) with a concentration of 5 mg/ml was added to each microplate cell, and the plate was incubated in a CO
 <sub>2</sub> incubator at 37°C in dark conditions for 2 h. After this time, the culture medium containing the MTT color was carefully taken out, 54 
 <italic>μ</italic>l of DMSO was added to each well of a microplate and shaken to dissolve the purple crystals Formosan. Finally, the optical absorption of each well, 40 min after incubation, was measured using a microplate reader (Hyperion, model MPR4 Plus) at a wavelength of 570 nm. The results were considered as IC50 in terms of cellular survival and efficacy, which inhibited cell growth by up to 50%. The experiments of this study were repeated three times, Busulfan (Myleran) was used as a positive control, and DMSO was applied as a negative control. The cell viability was computed using the following formula: 
 <disp-formula id="eq1">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="M1">
   <mtable>
    <mtr>
     <mtd>
      <mtext>Cell survival rate</mtext>
      <mo>=</mo>
      <mfenced open="(" close=")">
       <mrow>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mtext>absorption of treated cell lines</mtext>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mtext>absorption of control cell lines</mtext>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
       </mrow>
      </mfenced>
      <mo>×</mo>
      <mn>100</mn>
      <mo>.</mo>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
   </mtable>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
