<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Oxidative stress is one of the causes of many pathological diseases, such as cancer, chronic diseases, and cardiovascular diseases. In a study, the total phenolic components in the leaves of tropical medicinal plant TDG from Sabah have different degrees of antioxidant capacity due to the different extraction solvents, in the order of methanol extract &gt; ethyl acetate extract &gt; chloroform &gt; butanol &gt; hexane extract (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Hossain et al., 2011</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al. (2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">2015)</xref> primitively study the phenolic compounds—especially flavonoids—which are present in TDG leaves or tubers, and proves their good antioxidant activity by chemical based antioxidant tests (DPPH, ABTS, FRAP assays). The test results show that five kinds of flavonoids (catechin, kaempferol-3-rutinoside, rutin, isoquercitrin, and astragalin) may be the main antioxidants. Moreover, oral administration with TDG in rats suggests that phenolic compounds and their metabolites in the leaf of TDG extract are also bioavailable, and its mechanism of action involves the favorable changes in several antioxidant biomarkers and lipid peroxidation product (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2017a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2017b</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">Ye and Liu (2015)</xref> optimize the extraction process of total flavonoids from TDG, and come to a conclusion that flavonoids have remarkable antioxidant and free radical scanning activity. However, the molecular mechanism of anti-oxidation of TDG has not been mentioned in the above studies, so it is necessary to carry out experimental studies in the future. 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2016)</xref> establish in a rat model with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) to explore the protective effect of TDG and its mechanism. The levels of IL-8 and CRP in serum and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) are detected by ELISA, while reducing local MDA levels and increasing superoxide dismutase (SOD) levels in both pulmonary tissue homogenate and BALF, and detected mRNA and protein expression of nuclear factor-carotenoid 2 related factor 2 (Nrf2), are all up-regulated. These effects suggest that the protective effect of TDG may be related to its anti-inflammatory and anti-oxidative capacity through Nrf2 activation, but further research is required. 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al. (2019b)</xref> extract purified polysaccharide from TDG (TVP) with 64.89 kDA, and identify its structural composition by various analytical methods. Then the oxidative stress models induced by EC are constructed in Caco-2 cells and 
 <italic>C. elegans</italic>, results show that TVP could attenuate EC (a carcinogen) -induced cytotoxicity. In this study, three nematode models have also been compared, and daf-16 (−) mutant is assessed to be related to the antioxidant effect of TVP. More data are demanded to support this conjecture. Future research should attempt to find a suitable and available animal model to study the antioxidant activity of TDG extract 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, which will be more conducive to comprehensively explain the relevant mechanism of its antioxidant activity.
</p>
