<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The study also evaluated the effects of sublethal concentrations of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. sativa</italic> EO on 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> virulence traits such as motility, biofilm production, and cell invasion. Motility was assessed by phenotypic (umbrella and soft agar motility assay) and molecular (real time RT-PCR) approaches and by LM and SEM observation. Both motility tests demonstrated that, after growth in presence of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. sativa</italic> EO, all listerial strains became non-motile. Remarkably, flagella staining of treated cells showed aggregates of listeriae with the flagella trapped inside the aggregates; SEM demonstrated that the flagella were adherent to the cell rather than free, as in control specimens. Real time RT-PCR experiments showed a downregulation of flagellar motility genes 
 <italic class="italic">flaA</italic> (encoding flagellin) and 
 <italic class="italic">motA</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">motB</italic> (encoding a part of the flagellar motor). A reduced expression levels of 
 <italic class="italic">prfA</italic>, the transcriptional activator of genes involved in cell invasion, intracellular surviving, and spreading to neighboring cells, was also demonstrated after growth in the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">C. sativa</italic> EO. Inhibition of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> motility by natural products has also been reported with trans-cinnamaldehyde from 
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum zeylandicum</italic>, carvacrol, and thymol, the main components of oregano and thyme EO (Upadhyay et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). In the Gram-negative pathogens 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium and 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7, carvacrol affects motility through loss of flagellum functionality (Inamuco et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) and inhibition of flagellin synthesis (Burt et al., 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>), respectively.
</p>
