<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is cumulative evidence to suggest that 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> extracts have anti-inflammation potential that modulate pro-/anti-inflammatory cytokine secretion profiles. Gwon et al. [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] investigated the inhibitory effect of hexane extract from 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> on the LPS-stimulated RAW 264.7 cells and phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate- (PMA-) induced mouse-ear edema. The hexane fraction of 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> (HFS) inhibits the production of proinflammatory mediators and cytokines. Moreover, the anti-inflammatory effects of HFS on LPS-treated cells are associated with the inactivation of the NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B pathway implicated with the suppression of NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B through the inhibition of MAPKs and Akt (cellular homolog of murine thymoma virus 
 <italic>akt8</italic> oncogene) phosphorylation. Verification of HFS anti-inflammatory activity and relative mechanism at the cellular and molecular levels will be beneficial for its application in therapeutic agents for treating inflammation-mediated diseases. Recently, the grasshopper ketone (GK) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1(b)</xref>) extracted from 
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> showed anti-inflammatory activities in LPS-induced RAW 264.7 murine macrophage cell line. The production of proinflammatory cytokines (IL-6, IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>) was significantly reduced in 0.1-100 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL dose ranges of GK treatment. Furthermore, the dose-dependent and significant inhibition of iNOS and cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) protein expression was confirmed. The GK exerts its anti-inflammatory effect by inhibiting MAPKs (ERK, c-Jun-N-terminal kinase (JNK), and p38 kinase) and NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B p65 phosphorylation [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In another study, GK isolated from SFEE had an inhibitory effect on atopic dermatitis (AD) on 2,4-dinitrochlorobenzene- (DNCB-) induced AD-like skin lesions in BALB/c mice. In this study, SFEE inhibited the development of AD-like skin lesions and decreases serum IgE and cytokine levels (IL-4, IL-5, IL-10, IL-13, IFN-
 <italic>γ</italic>, and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>), while the GK suppressed the expression of IFN-
 <italic>γ</italic> and IL-4 in mouse splenocytes [
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Overall, this study demonstrated that the anti-inflammatory properties of GK on macrophages were achieved by inhibiting the NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B and MAPK pathways, which are associated with the attenuation of cytokine secretion [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
</p>
