<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Taken altogether, our results demonstrate, for the first time, the systemic translocation of trunk-injected EOs in apple plants. Carvone increased in the leaf content and was emitted at a constant rate, and 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde content increased in the leaves but was not found in detectable amounts in the air emissions. The strong spatial heterogeneity combined with the relatively small sampling may also contribute to the variability of the results. However, it appears that the EO translocation within apple tree tissues and its diffusion in ambient air must be conditioned by its own physicochemical properties. Amongst those properties, vapour pressure, organic carbon–water partitioning coefficient (Ko/c), and the octanol water partition coefficient (Ko/w) may explain the differences observed between carvone and 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Doccola and Wild, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Montecchio, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Aćimović, 2014</xref>). Out of these two, 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde was the molecule with the smallest vapour pressure of 15.3 and 3.853 Pa at 25°C for carvone and 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde, respectively (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">European Chemical Agency, 2020</xref>). This molecule, following Henry’s law, has a smaller tendency to volatilise and hence accumulates in the leaves. Moreover, from a histological point of view, they diffuse slowly through aqueous phases in the mesophyll, lipid bilayer membranes and internal airspace (in the substomatal cavity) before release through the stomata (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Calfapietra et al., 2013</xref>). This diffusion is conditioned following the compounds’ octanol water partition coefficients (Ko/w), which are 2.7 for carvone and 2.1 for 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde. It is worth mentioning that other phenomena could concurrently take place, such as the potential transformation or degradation of these xenobiotic compounds by the apple plants. Diverse mechanisms such as reduction/oxidation, esterification or conjugation with carbohydrates (glycosylation) or glutathione (glutathionylation) were demonstrated 
 <italic>in planta</italic> for numerous GLVs and terpenes (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Matsui et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Rivas et al., 2013</xref>) and by diverse microorganisms (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Asakawa et al., 2018</xref>). This was specifically demonstrated for 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> aldehydeoxidase 4 (AAO4) extracted from 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> developing seeds that could convert 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Ibdah et al., 2009</xref>).
</p>
