<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, the distance from the coastline was used as a variable to explore the relationship between the eco-stoichiometric characteristics of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> leaves and soil salinity, soil organic C, and soil eco-stoichiometry characteristics. In addition, we explored the key factors that affect the stoichiometric characteristics of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> leaves. The stoichiometric characteristics of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> leaves and the stoichiometric characteristics and properties of the soil were found to differ significantly between the different tidal levels, and many of the factors were detected at their highest levels at 3 km and at their lowest levels at 5 km, e.g., the leaf total carbon, total nitrogen, and total phosphorus; the soil total carbon, total nitrogen, and total phosphorus; the soil salinity; and the soil organic carbon. Significant correlations were confirmed between the leaf stoichiometry and the soil properties. The N/P ratio of plants was less than 14 and the N/P ratio of soil was less than 1, which was indicative of N limitation in the study area. Soil salinity and the soil C/N ratio were revealed to be the key factors that affect the stoichiometric characteristics of C, N, and P of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> at different distances from the coastline. Considering variable distances from the coastline distance, soil salinity and soil C/N ratio were the key factors that affected the stoichiometric characteristics of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>. Therefore, soil salinity and C/N ratio are important factors to be considered when regulating the growth of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>. These results only represent the preformation of this growth stage. The next step will be to conduct experiments to confirm and explore the nutrient limitation characteristics and main factors of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> eco-stoichiometric in different growth stages and different invasion periods. This conclusion is of great significance for both the management of coastal wetlands and to ensure the health of the ecological functions of the ecosystem at this stage.
</p>
