<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Biological invasion represents a threat to ecosystem management. Many studies have revealed that invasive plants have the ability to adapt to the scarcity in resources such as availability of nutrients, water, light, and various environmental stresses. (te Beest et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Colautti &amp; Barrett, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Rosche et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Thébault, Müller‐Schärer, &amp; Buttler, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Understanding how these plants can invade an ecosystem has therefore been a major challenge for ecologists (Simberloff et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Recently, biological invasion has received increased attention in terms of the factor(s) promoting invasion success (Bock et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Pandit, White, &amp; Pocock, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Consequently, a growing emphasis has been placed on elucidating the mechanisms that lead to higher capabilities of invasiveness in invasive species (Pandit et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Invasive plants frequently possess broader ecological amplitudes and greater plasticity (te Beest et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Si et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), while increasing evidence suggests a higher phenotypic plasticity, which acts as an important determinant for species invasiveness (Amina et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Molina‐Montenegro et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). On the one hand, phenotypic plasticity allows the plant to respond to altered environmental conditions by changing its phenotype, a phenomenon that has been recorded for many species that assume different response traits in variable environments (Ortega‐Mayagoitia, Hernandez‐Martinez, &amp; Ciros‐Perez, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). This characteristic plays a central role in biological invasions by permitting individuals to colonize different environments and establish viable populations (Du, Liu, Yan, Li, &amp; Li, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>).
</p>
