<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6049339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29670149</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">24459</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-24459-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impaired photosynthesis and increased leaf construction
costs may induce floral stress during episodes of global warming over
macroevolutionary timescales</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3225-6620</contrib-id><name><surname>Haworth</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><address><email>haworth@ivalsa.cnr.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>Claire M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Killi</surname><given-names>Dilek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dewhirst</surname><given-names>Rebecca A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Materassi</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raschi</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Centritto</surname><given-names>Mauro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>The Italian National Research Council - Tree and Timber Institute
(CNR-IVALSA) Via Madonna del Piano 10, Sesto Fiorentino, 50019 Florence, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8024</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8391.3</institution-id><institution>University of Exeter wildFIRE Lab, Hatherly Labs Prince Wales Road
Exeter, </institution></institution-wrap>EX PS Devon, England </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1757 2304</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8404.8</institution-id><institution>Department of Agrifood Production and Environmental Sciences
(DiSPAA), </institution><institution>University of Florence Piazzale delle Cascine, </institution></institution-wrap>28 50144 Florence, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>The Italian National Research Council &#x02013; Institute of Biometeorology
(CNR-IBIMET) Via Giovanni Caproni, 8 50145 Florence, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>6206</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a
Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use,
sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as
long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source,
provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.
The images or other third party material in this article are included in the
article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to
the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons
license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds
the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright
holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Global warming events have coincided with turnover of plant species at
intervals in Earth history. As mean global temperatures rise, the number, frequency
and duration of heat-waves will increase. <italic>Ginkgo
biloba</italic> was grown under controlled climatic conditions at two different
day/night temperature regimes (25/20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 35/30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) to investigate the impact of
heat stress. Photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub>-uptake and electron transport
were reduced at the higher temperature, while rates of respiration were greater;
suggesting that the carbon balance of the leaves was adversely affected. Stomatal
conductance and the potential for evaporative cooling of the leaves was reduced at
the higher temperature. Furthermore, the capacity of the leaves to dissipate excess
energy was also reduced at 35/30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, indicating that photo-protective mechanisms
were no longer functioning effectively. Leaf economics were adversely affected by
heat stress, exhibiting an increase in leaf mass per area and leaf construction
costs. This may be consistent with the selective pressures experienced by fossil
Ginkgoales during intervals of global warming such as the Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic
boundary or Early Eocene Climatic Optimum. The physiological and morphological
responses of the <italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves were closely
interrelated; these relationships may be used to infer the leaf economics and
photosynthetic/stress physiology of fossil plants.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Mean global temperatures and the frequency of extreme temperature
events have varied throughout Earth history<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Heat stress may have played a
role in the origination, extinction and diversification of plant species during
episodes of climatic perturbation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>;
yet comparatively little is known about the selective pressures exerted on plants by
growth at higher temperatures and the underlying physiological responses. Controlled
environment experiments have explored the phenotypic responses of living species
with ancient evolutionary origins to reconstruct the likely responses of fossil
plants to the atmospheric concentration of carbon dioxide
([CO<sub>2</sub>])<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>,
the level of oxygen within the atmosphere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, fumigation with toxic atmospheric
gases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>,
changes in the distribution/quality of incident radiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> and a moderate 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C increase in
temperature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. There are comparatively few studies that
investigate the impact of heat stress on the physiology and morphology of extant
species equivalent to those of fossil plants. In this study, we grew the relict
gymnosperm <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> under
controlled environment conditions to examine the impact of heat stress on
photosynthetic physiology and leaf morphology.</p><p id="Par3">Fossil Ginkgoales first appear in the
Palaeozoic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, and are widespread in many
Mesozoic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>
and Tertiary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> sediments. The geographically
and temporally extensive fossil record of the Ginkgoales has led to analysis of
their potential as indicators of palaeo-environmental and palaeo-climatic
conditions. The cuticular micro-morphology of fossil Ginkgoales has been used to
reconstruct palaeo-[CO<sub>2</sub>]<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, indicate the presence of toxic atmospheric
gases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>,
characterise the light environment during leaf development (sun versus shade
leaves)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, estimate photochemical and
non-photochemical usage of light energy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> and reconstruct leaf
economics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.
Analysis of the shape of fossil Ginkgoales has also been used to infer exposure to
toxic volcanic gases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. The use of fossil Ginkgoales to draw inferences
regarding palaeo-climatic conditions, atmospheric composition and plant function has
relied upon the analysis of the responses of <italic>G.
biloba</italic>, the sole extant Ginkgoales, under experimental and natural
conditions to interpret selective pressures faced by fossil plants during global
climatic change<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. However, to the best of our
knowledge, no study to date has investigated the impact of heat stress on <italic>G. biloba</italic>.</p><p id="Par4">Leaf economics provide insights into the physiological
characteristics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and environmental growth
conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>
of a plant. However, it is not possible to directly gauge the leaf economics of
fossil plants. The leaf economics of fossil plants can be estimated using
relationships between petiole width (PW) and leaf area<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> and the number of epidermal
cells (ED) and leaf density<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Few studies of fossil floras have utilised
these allometric patterns in leaf macro- and micro-morphology to interpret the
physiological responses of fossil plants to fluctuations in palaeo-environmental
conditions. One possible explanation may be that the lack of experimental studies
quantifying relationships between the energy balance of leaves and the associated
physiological and morphological characteristics has limited their application in the
reconstruction of the palaeo-physiology of fossil plants.</p><p id="Par5">Episodes of climatic perturbation often accompany extinction events
during Earth history<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.
The Permian &#x02013; Triassic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>,
Cretaceous &#x02013; Tertiary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>,
Early Eocene Climatic Optimum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> and Paleocene-Eocene Thermal
Maximum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>
are all characterised by increased global temperatures. As mean global temperatures
rise, the frequency, duration and severity of heat-waves (transient significant
increases in temperature above the mean) also increase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Increased temperature affects
the carbon and water use efficiencies of plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, and can thus act as a strong selective
pressure. Moreover, heat stress incurred during heat-waves can significantly impair
photosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>
and exacerbate the impact of co-occurring stresses such as
drought<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">As temperatures rise above optimal levels, rates of photosynthesis
(<italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub>) fall due to a decline in the affinity of
ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (RubisCO) for
CO<sub>2</sub> reducing carboxylation and increasing
oxygenation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The activity of RubisCO is also lower at high
temperatures as the function of the enzyme RubisCO activase is
reduced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Photosystem II (PSII) is
strongly affected by high temperatures as the structure and function of the
thylakoid membranes, where electron transport occurs within the chloroplast, are
highly sensitive to heat stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.
Impaired function of PSII during heat stress is evident in reductions in the maximum
(<italic>F</italic>
<sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic>
<sub>m</sub>) and actual (&#x003a6;PSII) quantum efficiencies of electron
transport<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, plants can develop tolerance to
growth at high temperatures through the accumulation of heat shock proteins in the
thylakoid membranes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Heat stress can also affect plant metabolism,
inducing an increase in levels of respiration in the light (<italic>R</italic>
<sub>light</sub>) and dark (<italic>R</italic>
<sub>dark</sub>) relative to <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Higher
temperatures are generally considered to result in greater stomatal conductance
(<italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub>) and increased transpirative
water-loss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. However, longer exposure to high temperatures may
permit adaptation in stomatal behaviour to reduce <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">Heat stress may play a critical role in driving plant evolutionary
responses over geological timescales at intervals of climatic perturbation. For
example, the reduction in thermal stress associated with declining
[CO<sub>2</sub>] in the Devonian may have enabled the development of
large planate leaves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, and the reconstruction of leaf architecture of
fossil Ginkgoales at the Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic boundary is consistent with selective
pressures induced by heat stress leading to a change in leaf shape to reduce the
energy balance of the leaf via lower interception of light<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Short-term controlled
environment experiments cannot replicate the multi-generational genotypic responses
evident in the fossil record associated with natural selection. However, such
experiments can provide valuable insights into the acclimatory responses of plants
to environmental change and the selective pressures that may be exerted. We exposed
the relict gymnosperm <italic>G. biloba</italic> to heat stress
to: i) examine the effect on carbon assimilation and photosynthetic light capture;
ii) determine the stomatal response of <italic>G. biloba</italic>
to higher temperature and potential effects on water use efficiency (WUE), and; iii)
gauge the likely effect of heat stress on leaf construction costs to determine
whether increased temperatures may have adversely affected leaf economic strategies
and thus driven plant evolution during key intervals of climatic change during Earth
history using the Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic boundary as a case study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant Growth Conditions</title><p id="Par8">Two year-old seedlings of <italic>Ginkgo
biloba</italic> were potted into six litre square pots filled with a 5:1
mixture of commercial compost and vermiculite (COMPO Italia, Cesano Maderno,
Italy). The <italic>G. biloba</italic> plants were grown from
seeds collected from a female tree in Pistoia, Central Italy, which has a warm
sub-Mediterranean climate. The seedlings were dormant and leaf development had not
yet begun when the plants were placed into two large walk-in growth rooms in
February 2015. Five plants were placed in each growth room. The plants were
watered to pot capacity every two days and once a week were provided with a
commercial liquid plant fertiliser (COMPO Concime Universale, NPK 7-5-7, B, Cu,
Fe, Mn, Mo, Zn) to facilitate nutrient availability at free access rates. The
growth chambers maintained conditions of 400 ppm [CO<sub>2</sub>],
relative humidity of 60% and 16&#x02009;hours of daylight (14&#x02009;hours at full
photosynthetically active radiation, PAR, levels of 1000&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol
m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> with two one-hour
periods of simulated dawn/dusk where light intensity was incrementally
increased/decreased &#x02013; details of the light spectrum are provided in Supplementary
Information). One chamber operated a day/night time temperature regime of 25/20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C
(hereafter referred to as the 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment) and the second chamber operated a
day/night temperature of 35/30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (hereafter referred to as the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment).
Changes in temperature followed those of PAR, with a one-hour ramping period at
dawn/dusk. To avoid any potential chamber effects the growth rooms were alternated
every two weeks &#x02013; no significant differences were observed in gas exchange
measurements conducted under the same conditions in different growth chambers. The
plants were grown for three months under controlled environment conditions to
allow full leaf development before physiological measurements were performed over
a two week period after the 12<sup>th</sup> week.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Leaf gas exchange, chlorophyll fluorescence and chlorophyll content
analysis</title><p id="Par9">A PP-Systems Ciras-2 attached to a 2&#x02009;cm<sup>2</sup>
PLC6(U) leaf cuvette and LED light unit (PP-Systems, Amesbury, Massachusetts, USA)
was used to analyse leaf gas exchange. A minimum of five leaves were analysed per
plant with five plants for each temperature treatment. Point measurements of
<italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub> were performed using cuvette conditions identical to the
growth conditions of both treatments: a temperature of 25 or 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, PAR of
1000&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and
[CO<sub>2</sub>] of 400 ppm. The instantaneous transpiration
efficiency was calculated as the ratio of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> to <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub>. The maximum rate of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>N max</sub>) of leaves from both treatments was measured using
cuvette conditions of 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 2000&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>
s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> PAR and 2000 ppm [CO<sub>2</sub>].
The Kok<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>
method was used to estimate <italic>R</italic>
<sub>light</sub> by decreasing PAR at low levels of intensity (400,
300, 200, 150, 100, 75, 50, 30, 20 and 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>
s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Respiration in the dark was measured by
switching off the LED light unit after the Kok protocol, shading the plant and
recording the rate of CO<sub>2</sub> efflux from the leaf after values
had remained stable for 5&#x02013;10&#x02009;minutes. Both <italic>R</italic>
<sub>light</sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>dark</sub> were determined at the growth temperature of the
plants in the controlled environment chambers. The effect of variation in
<italic>C</italic>
<sub>i</sub> on <italic>R</italic>
<sub>d</sub> was corrected using the iterative method of Kirschbaum
and Farquhar<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. The maximum (<italic>F</italic>
<sub>v</sub>/<italic>F</italic>
<sub>m</sub>) and actual (&#x003a6;PSII) quantum efficiencies of PSII and
non-photochemical quenching (NPQ) values of each leaf were recorded using a FMS-2
modulated fluorimeter (Hansatech, Norfolk, King&#x02019;s Lynn, UK) (saturating pulse of
10,000&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) and
dark adaptation clips after 30&#x02009;minutes of dark adaptation and exposure to actinic
light of 1000&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
for a minimum of 10&#x02009;minutes after the first saturating
pulse<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Chlorophyll content of each
leaf was estimated from the average of five readings per leaf using a Konica
Minolta SPAD-502 (Konica Minolta, Tokyo, Japan) and the calibration of Marenco,
<italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Leaf economics and construction costs</title><p id="Par10">After physiological measurements, leaves were removed from the
plants, the petiole cut from the leaf and the leaf photographed using a Sony
DSC-T99 14 megapixel camera. Leaf area was calculated from digital images using
ImageJ (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Maryland, USA). The fresh petiole
length and width were recorded using digital callipers with a precision of 0.01&#x02009;mm
(Draper Tools, Hampshire, UK). After digital images were taken of the leaves,
dental impression gel was applied to the adaxial leaf surface for 30&#x02009;minutes. The
dental impression gel was then removed and the leaves were dried for four days at
70&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. After the mass of individual leaves remained stable for a minimum of two
days, indicating that the leaves were dried thoroughly, their weight was recorded.
The leaf mass per area (LMA) of each leaf was calculated as the mass of the leaf
(in grams) divided by its area (expressed as
m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>).</p><p id="Par11">After drying, each leaf was cut into two approximately equal
halves. The half of the leaf designated for elemental analysis was ground in
liquid nitrogen using a pestle and mortar and then the carbon and nitrogen content
was determined using a Carlo Erba NA 1500 CHNS Analyzer (Carlo Erba, Milan,
Italy). The remaining halves of each leaf were used for micro-calorimetry using a
Federal Aviation Adminstration microcalorimeter (Fire Testing Technology, East
Grinstead, UK). The maximum temperature (<italic>T</italic>
<sub>max</sub>: the temperature at which the maximum rate of
decomposition of virgin fuel is reached), peak heat release (pHRR: the most
intense flux of heat during the combustion of the leaf material, this indicates
the maximum decomposition rate of the leaves which is related to the volatile gas
flux of the material), heat capacity (HRCap: the maximum capability of the leaf
material to release combustion heat per degree of temperature during pyrolysis;
this measure provides an indication of the resistance of the leaves to thermal
degradation) and total heat release (THR: the total energy released by the leaf
during combustion) was determined for each leaf on a
g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry mass basis. The THR during combustion and the
amount of carbon and nitrogen within the leaves were used to estimate leaf
construction costs using the method of Williams, <italic>et
al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, termed CC<sub>w</sub>
(equation&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>):<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}
$${\rm{CCw}}=\frac{(0.06968{{\rm{\Delta }}{\rm{H}}}_{{\rm{c}}}-0.065)(1-{\rm{A}})+0.5359{k}{\rm{N}}}{{{\rm{E}}}_{{\rm{G}}}}$$
\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CCw</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.06968</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.065</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5359</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">k</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Where, CC<sub>w</sub> is the energetic cost of tissue
construction (g glu g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry mass);
&#x02206;H<sub>c</sub> is the ash free heat of combustion (KJ
g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>); A is the ash content after combustion;
<italic>k</italic> is the oxidation state of nitrate, a value
of 5 was used following Wullschleger, <italic>et
al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>; N is the nitrogen content (g
g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry mass), and; E<sub>G</sub> is the
efficiency of conversion of dry matter to heat, a value of 0.89 was used following
Williams, <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. The method of de Vries,
<italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> (CC<sub>v</sub>)
that does not incorporate analysis of the energy released during combustion was
also used (equation&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>):<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}
$${{\rm{CC}}}_{{\rm{v}}}=(5.39{\rm{C}}+0.8{\rm{A}}+5.64{{f}}_{{\rm{N}},{\rm{h}}}{\rm{N}}-1.191)(1+{{\rm{r}}}_{{\rm{T}}})$$
\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">CC</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5.39</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.64</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.191</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Where, C is the carbon content (g g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> dry
mass); <italic>f</italic>
<sub>N,h</sub> is the fraction of nitrogen assimilated
heterotrophically, a value of 0.5 was used following Wullschleger, <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>, and; r<sub>T</sub> is the cost of
translocating photosynthates, a value of 5.3% was used<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Volatile compound and lignin analysis</title><p id="Par12">Individual dried leaves were ground in liquid nitrogen using a
pestle and mortar. Volatile compounds were extracted by sonication in <italic>n</italic>-hexane, with butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) added as
an internal standard. The hexane extract was analysed by GC-MS, using an Agilent
7200 series accurate mass Q-TOF GC-MS together with a 7890&#x02009;A GC system (Agilent
Technologies, Santa Clara, USA), equipped with an EI (electron ionisation) ion
source. Then 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of each sample was injected into a non-deactivated, baffled
glass liner with a 12:1 split ratio (14.448 ml min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
split flow) and the inlet temperature was maintained at 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. A Zebron
semi-volatiles (Phenomenex, Torrance, USA) column (30&#x02009;m &#x000d7; 250&#x02009;&#x003bc;m &#x000d7; 0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m)
coupled with a 10&#x02009;m guard column, was maintained at a constant helium flow of
1.2&#x02009;ml&#x02009;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The oven temperature was initially
70&#x02009;&#x000b0;C increasing to 310&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at a rate of 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. It
then remained constant at 310&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 6&#x02009;minutes. The MS emission current and
emission voltage were held at 35&#x02009;&#x003bc;A and 70&#x02009;eV respectively. The mass range was set
from 50 to 600&#x02009;amu, with an acquisition rate of 5 spectra
s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p><p id="Par13">Lignin was analysed using the acetyl bromide
method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. The ground leaves were washed to produce a
protein-free cell wall preparation. Samples (2&#x02009;mg) of the cell wall preparations
were incubated in acetyl bromide (0.5&#x02009;ml, 25% v/v in acetic acid) at 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for two
hours. After incubation, sodium hydroxide (0.9&#x02009;ml, 2&#x02009;M) and hydroxylamine
hydrochloride (0.1&#x02009;ml, 1&#x02009;M) were added, along with acetic acid (5&#x02009;ml). The lignin
content was quantified by measuring the absorbance at 280&#x02009;nm using a UV-1600PC
Spectrophotometer (VWR, Leicestershire, UK).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Leaf micro-morphological analysis</title><p id="Par14">Impressions of the adaxial surface of the <italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves were taken using dental impression gel (Colt&#x000e8;ne
President Light Body Material, Cuyahoga Falls, Ohio, USA). These were then used to
create nail varnish &#x02018;positives&#x02019; that were mounted onto glass
slides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> and imaged using a Leica DM2500 microscope
attached to a Leica DFC300FX camera (Leica Microsystems, Wetzlar, Germany).
Epidermal cell density (ED) counts were consistently performed on cells in the
outer lobe of the <italic>G. biloba</italic> leaf to avoid
concentrations of veins and/or excessively densely packed epidermal cells at the
base of the leaf<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. A 0.16 mm<sup>2</sup> grid
(0.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.4&#x02009;mm) was applied to digital images of the cuticle and ED of 10 images
recorded for each leaf. Rarefraction analysis of the ED counts for extant
<italic>G. biloba</italic> indicated that mean ED values
stabilised after three to five images were counted.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="Par15">Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 20 (IBM, New York,
USA). A one-way ANOVA was used to assess differences in variance between
temperature treatments. Linear regression was used to assess possible
relationships between leaf morphology and physiology.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="Par16">All data generated or analysed during this study are included in
this published article.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par17">Growth at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C strongly influenced the morphology (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), composition (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) and physiology
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) of the leaves of <italic>G. biloba</italic>. Leaf mass per area was significantly increased
by 58% in leaves developed at the higher temperature (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). This higher LMA was associated with increased leaf thickness
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>) and ED (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c,d</xref>). The
ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area was also significantly greater
in leaves from the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Higher growth temperature resulted in 15% lower leaf carbon
content (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>), and a corresponding 79%
increase in the amount of nitrogen (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>)
when measured on the basis of leaf dry weight. Microcalorimetry revealed a ~10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C
difference in the temperature at which the maximum decomposition of the leaf
occurred (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>), indicating that the
compounds in the leaves grown at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C were more easily degradable than those grown
in 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The pHRR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), HRCap
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>) and THR (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>) per unit dry mass were significantly lower in
leaves from the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment. The greater THR in leaves developed at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C,
contributed towards 17% lower construction costs per unit dry mass in leaves from
the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e,f</xref>). However,
when construction costs were calculated on a leaf area basis, leaves that developed
in the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment were on average 36% more expensive than their counterparts
from the 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2g,h</xref>). This
also appears to be reflected in the chemical analyses, where the leaves grown at
35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C had significantly lower lignin content than the leaves grown at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i</xref>). The leaves grown at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C also
generated significantly less volatile waxy compounds than those grown at the lower
temperature (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Box plots representing the effects of growth at 25 and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C on
the morphology of <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> leaves:
(<bold>a</bold>) leaf mass per area (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;41.5; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>); (<bold>b</bold>) leaf thickness (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1502.7; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;40</sup>); (<bold>c</bold>) leaf epidermal cell density (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;53.3; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>); (<bold>d</bold>) ratio of petiole width (PW) to leaf area
(one-way ANOVA F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;52.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>); (<bold>e</bold>) leaf carbon content (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;96.1; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;13</sup>), and; (<bold>f</bold>) leaf nitrogen content (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;316.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>). The box signifies
the distribution of the 25&#x02013;75% quartiles, the median is represented by a
horizontal line within the box, horizontal bars either side of the box
indicate minimum/maximum values. *indicates significant different between
the 25 and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatments at the 0.05 significance level.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1239"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Box plots representing the effects of growth at 25 and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C on
the parameters determined by calorimetry and construction costs of <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> leaves: (<bold>a</bold>) maximum heat release (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.801; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.057); (<bold>b</bold>) peak heat
release (pHRR)(one-way ANOVA F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;58.9; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>);
(<bold>c</bold>) heat release capacity (HRCap)(one-way
ANOVA F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;61.9; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>); (<bold>d</bold>) total heat release (THR)(one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;90.7; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;13</sup>); (<bold>e</bold>) leaf construction cost per unit dry mass
following Williams, <italic>et
al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> (CC<sub>w mass</sub>)
(one-way ANOVA F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;34.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>); (<bold>f</bold>) leaf construction cost per unit dry mass
following de Vries, <italic>et
al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> (CC<sub>v mass</sub>)
(one-way ANOVA F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;65.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup>); (<bold>g</bold>) CC<sub>w</sub> per unit leaf area
(CC<sub>w area</sub>) (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14.5; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>); (<bold>h</bold>) CC<sub>v</sub> per unit leaf area
(CC<sub>v area</sub>) (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.6; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.00195), and; (<bold>i</bold>) lignin
content per unit dry mass (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;114.9; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>). Box plots
presented as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1396"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Example GCMS spectra of lignin and volatile compound content of
<italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> leaves and images of
impressions of the adaxial epidermis grown in the 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>c</bold>) and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C
treatment (<bold>b</bold>,<bold>d</bold>). Scale bar on images of epidermal micromorphology indicates
100&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1422"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Box plots representing the effects of growth at 25 and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C on
the physiology of <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> leaves:
(<bold>a</bold>) photosynthesis (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;157.6; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.7&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;17</sup>); (<bold>b</bold>) stomatal conductance (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;31.3; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.9&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>); (<bold>c</bold>) maximum rate of photosynthesis (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;181.2; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;19</sup>); (<bold>d</bold>) respiration in the light (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;261.1; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;22</sup>); (<bold>e</bold>) respiration in the dark (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;30.1; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>); (<bold>f</bold>) foliar content of chlorophyll a and b (one-way
ANOVA F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;150.1; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;17</sup>); (<bold>g</bold>) maximum quantum yield of PSII (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;52.6; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>); (<bold>h</bold>) actual quantum yield of PSII (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;106.08; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;14</sup>), and; (<bold>i</bold>) non-photochemical quenching (one-way ANOVA
F<sub>1,53</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;250.4; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;23</sup>). Box plots
presented as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1552"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par18">Photosynthesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>),
<italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>) and
<italic>P</italic>
<sub>N max</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>) were
all lower in leaves from the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment. In contrast, rates of respiration in
the light (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>) and dark
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e</xref>) were larger in leaves from the
higher temperature (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d,e</xref>), indicating
that the lower rates of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C were not accompanied by reduced metabolic
activity. Lower <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub> and transpirative water-loss at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C did not translate
into improved transpiration efficiency due to diminished <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub>/<italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub>: 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment&#x02009;=&#x02009;57.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.0&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol
CO<sub>2</sub> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
H<sub>2</sub>O; 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;10.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.0&#x02009;&#x003bc;mol
CO<sub>2</sub> mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
H<sub>2</sub>O). The amount of chlorophyll per unit leaf area was 61%
lower in leaves from the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4f</xref>), and this corresponded to a 72% reduction in &#x003a6;PSII
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4h</xref>). Non-photochemical quenching of
<italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves was reduced by 69% on average
in the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4i</xref>).</p><p id="Par19">The LMA of the <italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves
exhibited significant positive correlations with ED (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>) and the ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). Less strong negative
relationships were observed between construction cost per unit dry mass with LMA
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c,d</xref>), ED (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e</xref>) or the ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to
leaf area (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>). However, when leaf
construction costs were calculated per unit leaf area, slightly more robust positive
relationships were observed with ED (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5g</xref>) and the ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5h</xref>). Relationships between
photosynthetic and protective physiology of the <italic>G.
biloba</italic> leaves were also strongly affected by temperature
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). A strong positive relationship
was observed between <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>), but
<italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> was negatively associated with <italic>R</italic>
<sub>light</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>).
Photosynthesis measured using gas exchange was positively related to &#x003a6;PSII
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>) and NPQ (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d</xref>) measured via chlorophyll fluorescence. The
concentration of chlorophyll within the <italic>G. biloba</italic>
leaves was also positively related to CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation
determined using gas exchange (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e</xref>) and
chlorophyll fluorescence (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6f</xref>)
techniques.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Correlations between leaf macro- and micro-morphology with leaf
economic and construction cost parameters of <italic>Ginkgo
biloba</italic> leaves developed in 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (white fill symbols) and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C
treatments (black fill symbols): (<bold>a</bold>)
relationship between LMA and epidermal cell density (ED); (<bold>b</bold>) relationship between LMA and the ratio of
PW<sup>2</sup> (where PW&#x02009;=&#x02009;petiole width) to leaf area
plotted on a logarithmic scale; (<bold>c</bold>)
relationship between CC<sub>w</sub> per unit dry mass and LMA;
(<bold>d</bold>) relationship between
CC<sub>v</sub> per unit dry mass and LMA; (<bold>e</bold>) relationship between CC<sub>w</sub>
per unit dry mass and ED; (<bold>f</bold>) relationship
between CC<sub>w</sub> per unit dry mass and the ratio of
PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area plotted on a logarithmic
scale; (<bold>g</bold>) relationship between
CC<sub>w</sub> per unit leaf area and ED, and; (<bold>h</bold>) relationship between CC<sub>w</sub>
per unit leaf area and the ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf
area plotted on a logarithmic scale. R<sup>2</sup>, F and
<italic>P</italic> values indicate the results of linear
regression. The central black line indicates the line of best fit. The grey
lines either side of the best-fit line indicate 95% confidence intervals of
the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1816"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The effect of growth at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (white fill symbols) and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C
(black fill symbols) on correlations between physiological parameters in
leaves of <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic>: (<bold>a</bold>) relationship between <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub>; (<bold>b</bold>) relationship
between <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>light</sub>; (<bold>c</bold>)
relationship between <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and &#x003a6;PSII; (<bold>d</bold>)
relationship between <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and NPQ; (<bold>e</bold>)
relationship between <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and foliar chlorophyll content, and; (<bold>f</bold>) relationship between &#x003a6;PSII and foliar
chlorophyll content. R<sup>2</sup>, F and <italic>P</italic> values indicate the results of linear
regression. The central black line indicates the line of best-fit. The grey
lines either side of the best fit line indicate 95% confidence intervals of
the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1898"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par20">The pronounced impact of temperature on the leaves of <italic>G. biloba</italic> was also apparent in relationships of
photosynthetic physiology to LMA and the two possible proxy methods for estimating
the LMA of fossil plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).
Photosynthesis, &#x003a6;PSII and NPQ were negatively related to LMA. Indeed, the
relationship of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> with ED or ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf
area was stronger than that with LMA. Respiration in the light exhibited negative
relationships to LMA, ED and PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area. These
correlations may suggest that the macro- and micro-morphology of <italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves may provide a basis to infer the status
of photosynthetic and protective physiology within the leaf.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Correlations between photosynthesis, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>light</sub>, &#x003a6;PSII and NPQ and morphological
characteristics of leaves of <italic>Ginkgo
biloba</italic> grown at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (white fill symbols) and 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (black
fill symbols). The ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to area is
plotted on a logarithmic scale. R<sup>2</sup>, F and
<italic>P</italic> values indicate the results of linear
regression. The central black line indicates the line of best fit. The grey
lines either side of the best-fit line indicate 95% confidence intervals of
the mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1951"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par21">This study has shown that heat stress impaired <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and affected leaf morphology in <italic>G.
biloba</italic>. The natural habitat of <italic>G.
biloba</italic> is not well defined as the species was restricted to refugia
during Pleistocene glacial episodes and has experienced centuries of managed
planting<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Nonetheless, <italic>G.
biloba</italic> has been cultivated extensively over a wide-range of
environments with differing climates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>, and grows successfully in warm humid climates
with mean summer temperatures of 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C where midday temperatures can exceed
40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.
Indeed, the female tree which was the source of the seeds and the nursery where the
seedlings grew were located in a region with a warm sub-Mediterranean climate,
suggesting that adaptation to cooler temperatures was not associated with the
pronounced response to heat stress observed in the study.- Exposure to 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for
14&#x02009;hours each day may have exceeded the tolerance of <italic>G.
biloba</italic> by progressively degrading the protective physiology. As the use
of energy for photochemistry declines, an increase in the dissipation of energy as
heat is frequently observed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. However, <italic>G.
biloba</italic> grown in the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment showed lower levels of NPQ than
those grown at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, suggesting that this protective mechanism was not functioning
as effectively at the higher temperature (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4i</xref>). The pronounced reduction in &#x003a6;PSII at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C is consistent with
previous studies suggesting that the structure and function of the thylakoid
membrane is particularly vulnerable to heat stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.
The close correlation between &#x003a6;PSII and chlorophyll content indicates that the
increased pigment content in leaves from the 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment enabled greater light
harvesting associated with an increased availability of PSII reaction centres for
electron transport involved in CO<sub>2</sub>
fixation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. The lower levels of photosynthetic
CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation observed in <italic>G.
biloba</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>) may be due to
decreased affinity for CO<sub>2</sub> relative to
O<sub>2</sub> resulting in an increase in photorespiration relative to
<italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub>, reduced solubility of CO<sub>2</sub>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> or reduced activity of RubisCO
activase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>.
This reduced carboxylation would decrease the capacity of photosystem I to accept
electrons from PSII<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>, further exacerbating the deleterious effects of
excess energy on the thylakoid membranes.</p><p id="Par22">Higher temperatures negatively affected the carbon balance of the
<italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves via reduced <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>) and
increased respiration (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d,e</xref>), this is
consistent with the decrease in lignin and volatile waxy compound production in the
leaves grown at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i</xref> and
<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In contrast to previous studies where
a short-term increase in temperature induced an increase in <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub> and transpirative water-loss<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>, a reduction in <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub> at the higher temperature was observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). This stomatal acclimation is consistent with
<italic>Populus nigra</italic> grown for eight weeks at
35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.
Despite the reduced transpirative water-loss at 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, this did not translate into
improved transpiration efficiency due to impaired CO<sub>2</sub>
assimilation. Moreover, the lower transpirative cooling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup> would exacerbate the impact of
growth at the higher temperature on the photosynthetic apparatus. As most plants
experience heat stress over a few hours<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>, the prolonged exposure to higher temperature as
part of a simulated heat-wave in this study likely induced significant damage to
PSII and the protective xanthrophyll cycle (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4i</xref>). This damage to PSII was likely caused by the decline in the
amount of energy utilised in photochemistry due to reduced assimilation of
CO<sub>2</sub> and lower capacity for transpirative cooling associated
with stomatal adaptation to the higher temperature.</p><p id="Par23">The chemical analyses of leaf composition, elemental analysis of
whole leaf carbon and nitrogen content and the microcalorimetry analyses provide
evidence of changes in leaf composition between the two treatments. The decrease in
carbon content, lignin and volatile waxy compounds in the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment <italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves highlights that investment in the
structure of the leaves is altered at the higher temperature. Specifically, fatty
acids and volatile waxes appear to be more limited in the leaves grown at the higher
temperature. This is further reflected in the energy content responses measured by
the microcalorimeter. The leaves from the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment were found to reach
maximum decomposition rate at lower temperatures when heated at the same ramp rate
as leaves grown in the 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment. This indicates that the leaves grown at
35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C contain compounds that are easier to break-down, implying that their
investment is likely to be in short-lived cellulosic compounds rather than
longer-lived lignin (eg. Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i</xref>). There is
also a large difference in pHRR between the two sets of leaves, with the leaves
grown at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C releasing 60&#x02009;W&#x02009;g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> more energy than those
grown at the higher temperature. This is likely related to the significantly lower
abundance of volatile waxy compounds in the higher temperature leaves. The same is
observed for HRCap and THR, which both indicate that the structural investment and
the complexity of compounds is lower in the high temperature leaves; implying that
growth conditions have a significant influence on the energy content of the leaves.
Therefore, the damage induced to the photosynthetic and light harvesting apparatus
appears to have a large influence on investment in the construction of leaves. Not
only are the leaves more costly to produce, but the plants appeared to have more
limited resources to invest in longer chained carbon-based compounds.</p><p id="Par24">Analyses of leaf economics has been suggested to provide insights
into the physiological and morphological adaptations of plants to their
environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. However, the application of leaf economics to
gauge the palaeo-ecology and physiology of fossil plants has been relatively
limited. It is not possible to directly determine the leaf economics of a fossil
plant or its physiological status. Instead, allometric relationships in leaf area
and PW<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> and
the density of epidermal cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> have been used to estimate the LMA of fossil
plants. The results of our growth experiments and analysis suggest that patterns in
leaf morphology correlate closely with physiological parameters such as <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub>, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>light</sub> and &#x003a6;PSII (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) as well as structural investment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) and therefore may provide novel palaeo-physiological data from
observations of leaf fossils. To assess this possibility we have considered changes
in Ginkgoales leaf morphology across the Triassic-Jurassic boundary, global warming
event as preserved at locations in East Greenland<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">At the Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic boundary mean global temperatures are
proposed to have risen by 2.5 to 5.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C due to increased palaeo-atmospheric
[CO<sub>2</sub>]<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref></sup>, with much wider regional
variations of more than 10&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in temperature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. Alongside the increased
incidence of heat-waves<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, this would have adversely affected
CO<sub>2</sub>-uptake in Late Triassic Ginkgoales. Moreover, the leaf
mass per area of fossil Ginkgoales is considered to have increased by 40&#x02013;60% towards
the End Triassic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>,
and leaf architecture adjusted to reduce energy
interception<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Heat stress induced a 57.7% increase in the LMA
of <italic>G. biloba</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>), and a rise in [CO<sub>2</sub>] from 380 to 1500
ppm has been shown to increase the LMA of <italic>G.
biloba</italic> by 30.6%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The results of these observations under
controlled environment conditions would suggest that a rise in LMA of fossil
Ginkgoales at the end of the Triassic was likely due to higher
[CO<sub>2</sub>] and temperature. Nevertheless, it is unclear whether
a combination of heat stress and extremely elevated [CO<sub>2</sub>]
would have a cumulative, synergistic or antagonistic impact on the leaf economics of
<italic>G. biloba</italic>. The controlled environment analysis
conducted in this study indicates that rising temperatures at the Triassic &#x02013;
Jurassic boundary would also have increased the construction cost of foliage per
unit area of the leaf (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In essence,
this equates to greater cost accompanied by diminished returns in the form of
reduced interception of PAR for <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> and less favourable rates of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> to photorespiration. This shift in growth conditions as
temperatures rose would make leaves of Ginkgoales more expensive and with lower
photosynthetic returns; possibly accounting for regional extinctions of Ginkgoales
at the Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic boundary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup> (for a summary of effects see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). The <italic>T</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>), HRCap
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>), lignin content
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2i</xref>) and the abundance of volatile
waxy compounds data indicate a lower structural investment and a lower energy
content of the leaves from the higher temperature. A similar effect of higher
temperatures on leaf development may have affected the combustion
characteristics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>
and preservation potential<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> of fossil plant material during the transition from
the Triassic to Jurassic.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>A summary of the physiological and morphological effects of heat
stress on <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> leaves. Arrows
facing up and down indicate respectively higher and lower values of each
parameter.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e2307"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par26">Heat stress induced a significant reduction in the capacity for
photosynthetic electron transport (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4g,h</xref>) and CO<sub>2</sub> uptake (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a,c</xref>). This lower <italic>P</italic>
<sub>N</sub> resulted in lower transpiration efficiency of <italic>G. biloba</italic> in the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment. If such a scenario were
replicated at episodes of global warming during Earth history this would reduce the
photosynthetic performance of C3 species; in particular, those individuals with
lower transpiration efficiencies, or exposed to high evapotranspirative demand. Some
C3 species may have adapted to higher temperatures via increased levels of RubisCO,
thus countering the impact of reduced RubisCO carboxylation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. However the formation of
RubisCO requires nitrogen, and as nitrogen is limiting in many terrestrial
environments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>,
an increase in RubisCO may not be feasible for many plants faced with heat stress.
The degradation of the protective mechanisms involved in the maintenance and
stabilisation of the thylakoid membranes during heat stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup> would also contribute to plant stress at the
Late Triassic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. This would be compounded by reduced <italic>G</italic>
<sub>s</sub> at high temperatures (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>), resulting in reduced transpirative
cooling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup>. The pattern of leaf economic responses to heat
stress observed under controlled climate conditions are consistent with the
micro<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>-
and macro-morphological<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>
patterns of fossil Ginkgoales at the Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic boundary, suggesting that
heat stress may have potentially played a role in floral turnover recorded at the
boundary<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup>.
Estimates of the leaf economics of fossil Ginkgoales based upon epidermal
micromorphology suggest that LMA values increased by 40.1 (from 71.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.0 to
100.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.5&#x02009;g&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2&#x02009;</sup>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>) to 54.1%
(from 85.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.6 to 132.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1&#x02009;g&#x02009;m<sup>&#x02212;2&#x02009;</sup>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>) at the
Triassic &#x02013; Jurassic boundary. The reconstructed LMA values of the fossil Ginkgoales
are comparable to those observed in the 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>) and <italic>G. biloba</italic>
trees growing in a warm humid sub-Mediterranean climate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Higher temperatures,
especially those significantly above normal levels associated with heat-waves, may
act as a strong selective pressure in the extinction, origination and
diversification of plant species over geological timescales.</p><p id="Par27">Our fossil analysis suggests that the correlations we report between
metabolism and photosynthesis with LMA, lignin content, volatile compounds, ED and
the ratio of PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area may allow inferences to be
drawn regarding the physiological status of fossil plants; particularly in the
context of a stratigraphic sequence where the relative changes in leaf morphology
through the sequence provide context to the physiological responses and the
selective pressures (such as variations in palaeo-[CO<sub>2</sub>] or
-temperature) that may have driven these changes.</p><p id="Par28">Higher temperatures induced a significant increase in the LMA of
<italic>G. biloba</italic> leaves (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>), consistent with observations of higher LMA in
<italic>G. biloba</italic> from warmer
areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>
and controlled environment temperature experiments involving other
species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Heat stress also resulted in the allometric
relationships between LMA and both ED (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>) and PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area
(Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>) becoming more variable. This may
suggest that stress conditions were adversely affecting leaf
development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref></sup>, which is also reflected in the shift to higher
nitrogen contents and lower lignin and volatile compound investment. Nonetheless,
both ED and PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area showed significant
relationships to LMA that could be utilised in the reconstruction of leaf economics
in fossil Ginkgoales during episodes of temperature change for example the Early
Eocene Climatic Optimum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The leaves of <italic>G.
biloba</italic> can either &#x02018;short&#x02019; or &#x02018;long&#x02019; petiole
morphotypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>. All of the leaves analysed in this study were of
the short petiole morphotype. The scaling relationship between
PW<sup>2</sup> to leaf area<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> becomes less robust in
<italic>G. biloba</italic> when a mixture of short and long
petiole leaves are analysed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>. Furthermore, the
PW<sup>2</sup>/leaf area approach relies upon a high degree of
preservation where the entire leaf area is intact with the petiole still attached;
however, many fossil leaves are fragmented during transport prior to deposition eg.
Oldham<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref></sup>, possibly limiting the application of this method.
Nevertheless, <italic>G. biloba</italic> modifies the physiology
and morphology of its leaves in response to heat stress. The photosynthetic
apparatus, leaf morphology and leaf composition are clearly affected by
environmental conditions; moreover, they are intrinsically linked during leaf
development. As such, the interrelated correlations between leaf morphology,
construction costs and physiology can be used to reconstruct the likely responses of
fossil plants to environmental change, and infer the selective pressures that have
shaped plant evolution during episodes of global warming.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec12"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_24459_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>
<bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-24459-z.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral
with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional
affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Luigi P. D&#x02019;Acqui and Alessandro Dodero (CNR &#x02013; ISE) for
carbon and nitrogen analysis. CMB and RAD acknowledge funding from a European
Research Council Starter Grant ERC-2013-StG-335891-ECOFLAM.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>M.H., D.K., A.M., C.M.B., R.A.D. conducted the study. M.H., D.K., C.M.B.,
R.A.D. analysed the data. All authors contributed to the writing of the
manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par29">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zachos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Billups</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends, rhythms, and aberrations in global climate 65
Ma to present</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1059412</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11326091?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkyns</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for rapid climate change in the
Mesozoic-Palaeogene greenhouse world</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London Series A -
Mathematical Physical and Engineering Sciences</source><year>2003</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>1885</fpage><lpage>1916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsta.2003.1240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased fire activity at the Triassic/Jurassic
boundary in Greenland due to climate-driven floral change</article-title><source>Nat. Geosci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ngeo871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McElwain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beerling</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fossil plants and global warming at the
Triassic-Jurassic boundary</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>1386</fpage><lpage>1390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.285.5432.1386</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10464094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10464094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transient floral change and rapid global warming at
the Paleocene-Eocene boundary</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>993</fpage><lpage>996</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116913</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16284173?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16284173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerling</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stomatal responses of the &#x02018;living fossil&#x02019; <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> L. to changes in atmospheric
CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>1998</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1603</fpage><lpage>1607</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Paleobotanical evidence for near present-day levels of
atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> during part of the
Tertiary</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>2310</fpage><lpage>2313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.292.5525.2310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11423657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11423657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bacon, K. L., Haworth, M., Conroy, E. &#x00026; McElwain, J. C. Can
atmospheric composition influence plant fossil preservation potential via changes
in leaf mass per area? A new hypothesis based on simulated palaeoatmosphere
experiments. <italic>Palaeogeogr., Palaeo-climatol.,
Palaeoecol</italic>., 10.1016/j.palaeo.2015.12.006 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Haworth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased atmospheric SO<sub>2</sub>
detected from changes in leaf physiognomy across the Triassic&#x02013;Jurassic boundary
interval of East Greenland</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e60614</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0060614</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23593262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23593262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lomax</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant spore walls as a record of long-term changes in
ultraviolet-B radiation</article-title><source>Nat. Geosci.</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ngeo278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llorens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Beerling</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water-use responses of &#x02018;living fossil&#x02019; conifers to
CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment in a simulated Cretaceous polar
environment</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><year>2009</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcp108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19447810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19447810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;rschner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stulen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>PJC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of palaeobotanical observations with
experimental data on the leaf anatomy of durmast oak [<italic>Quercus petraea</italic> (Fagaceae)] in response to environmental
change</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbo.1998.0605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Seward, A. C. &#x00026; Gowan, J. The Maidenhair Tree (<italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic>, L.) With Plates VIII&#x02013;X. <italic>Ann. Bot</italic>., 109&#x02013;154 (1900).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rothwell, G. W. &#x00026; Holt, B. In <italic>Ginkgo</italic> Biloba A <italic>Global Treasure</italic>
(eds Hori, T. <italic>et al</italic>.) 223&#x02013;230 (Springer,
1997).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harris, T. M., Millington, W. &#x00026; Miller, J. <italic>The Yorkshire Jurassic Flora IV. Ginkgoales and
Czekanowskiales</italic>. 150 (Trustees of the British Museum (Natural
History), 1974).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tralau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary trends in the genus <italic>Ginkgo</italic></article-title><source>Lethaia</source><year>1968</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1502-3931.1968.tb01728.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Basinger</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating paleoatmospheric
pCO<sub>2</sub> during the Early Eocene Climatic Optimum from
stomatal frequency of <italic>Ginkgo</italic>, Okanagan
Highlands, British Columbia, Canada</article-title><source>Palaeogeogr., Palaeoclimatol., Palaeoecol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.palaeo.2010.05.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High resolution estimates of
paleo-CO<sub>2</sub> levels through the Campanian (Late
Cretaceous) based on <italic>Ginkgo</italic>
cuticles</article-title><source>Cretaceous Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cretres.2008.08.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinthorsdottir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeram</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extremely elevated CO<sub>2</sub>
concentrations at the Triassic/Jurassic boundary</article-title><source>Palaeogeog. Palaeoclimatol. Palaeoecol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>308</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.palaeo.2011.05.050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haworth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott-Kingston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sulphur dioxide fumigation effects on stomatal density
and index of non-resistant plants: Implications for the stomatal
palaeo-[CO<sub>2</sub>] proxy method</article-title><source>Rev. Palaeobot. Palynol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.revpalbo.2012.06.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variation in <italic>Ginkgo
biloba</italic> L. leaf characters across a climatic gradient in
China</article-title><source>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>7141</fpage><lpage>7146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1232419100</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12777617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12777617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Haworth, M. <italic>et al</italic>. On the
reconstruction of plant photosynthetic and stress physiology across the Triassic &#x02013;
Jurassic boundary. <italic>Turk. J. Earth Sci</italic>., In
Press (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haworth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raschi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An assessment of the use of epidermal
micro-morphological features to estimate leaf economics of Late Triassic-Early
Jurassic fossil Ginkgoales</article-title><source>Rev. Palaeobot. Palynol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.revpalbo.2014.02.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Palaeo leaf economics reveal a shift in ecosystem
function associated with the end-Triassic mass extinction event</article-title><source>Nature Plants</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>17104</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2017.104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28714942?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28714942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poorter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bongers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf traits are good predictors of plant performance
across 53 rain forest species</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2006</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1733</fpage><lpage>1743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9658(2006)87[1733:LTAGPO]2.0.CO;2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16922323?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16922323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norby</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sholtis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunderson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jawdy</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf dynamics of a deciduous forest canopy: no
response to elevated CO<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2003</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-003-1296-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12811536?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12811536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Killi, D., Bussotti, F., Raschi, A. &#x00026; Haworth, M. Adaptation to
high temperature mitigates the impact of water deficit during combined heat and
drought stress in C3 sunflower and C4 maize varieties with contrasting drought
tolerance. <italic>Physiol. Plant</italic>. In Press. Early
Access, 10.1111/ppl.12490 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fossil leaf economics quantified: calibration, Eocene
case study, and implications</article-title><source>Paleobiology</source><year>2007</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1666/07001.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twitchett</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The palaeoclimatology, palaeoecology and
palaeoenvironmental analysis of mass extinction events</article-title><source>Palaeogeogr., Palaeoclimatol., Palaeoecol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.palaeo.2005.05.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wignall</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large igneous provinces and mass
extinctions</article-title><source>Earth-Sci. Rev.</source><year>2001</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0012-8252(00)00037-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joachimski</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate warming in the latest Permian and the
Permian&#x02013;Triassic mass extinction</article-title><source>Geology</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/G32707.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barras, C. &#x00026; Twitchett, R. J. In <italic>The
Trace-Fossil Record of Major Evolutionary Events: Volume 2:</italic> Mesozoic
<italic>and Cenozoic</italic> (eds Gabriela M&#x000e1;ngano, M. &#x00026;
Luis A. Buatois) 1&#x02013;17 (Springer Netherlands, 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerling</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomax</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Upchurch</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kump</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An atmospheric pCO<sub>2</sub>
reconstruction across the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary from leaf
megafossils</article-title><source>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>7836</fpage><lpage>7840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.122573099</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12060729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12060729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlated terrestrial and marine evidence for global
climate changes before mass extinction at the Cretaceous&#x02013;Paleogene
boundary</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0234701100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;r</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of increasing temperature variability in
European summer heatwaves</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>427</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02300</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14716318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14716318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthetic response and adaptation to temperature
in higher plants</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology</source><year>1980</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pp.31.060180.002423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Centritto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brilli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fodale</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x00026; Loreto, F. Different sensitivity of isoprene
emission, respiration and photosynthesis to high growth temperature coupled with
drought stress in black poplar (<italic>Populus
nigra</italic>) saplings</article-title><source>Tree Physiology</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/treephys/tpq112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21367745?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21367745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crafts-Brandner</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvucci</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rubisco activase constrains the photosynthetic
potential of leaves at high temperature and CO<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>13430</fpage><lpage>13435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.230451497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Crafts-Brandner</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvucci</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderately high temperatures inhibit
ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (rubisco) activase-mediated
activation of rubisco</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.116.2.539</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9490757?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9490757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of drought and high temperature on
photosynthesis and grain-filling of wheat</article-title><source>Plant Soil</source><year>2003</year><volume>257</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1026237816578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of moderate heat stress on photosynthesis:
importance of thylakoid reactions, rubisco deactivation, reactive oxygen
species, and thermotolerance provided by isoprene</article-title><source>Plant Cell and Environment</source><year>2005</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2005.01324.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yordanov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Velikova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsonev</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of drought, high temperature, and carbamide
cytokinin 4-PU-30 on photosynthetic activity of bean plants. 1. Changes in
chlorophyll fluorescence quenching</article-title><source>Photosynthetica</source><year>1999</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1007163928253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crafts-Brandner</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvucci</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensitivity of photosynthesis in a C4 plant, maize, to
heat stress</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>1773</fpage><lpage>1780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.002170</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12177490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heckathorn</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The small, methionine-rich chloroplast heat-shock
protein protects photosystem II electron transport during heat
stress</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.116.1.439</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9449851?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9449851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerling</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaloner</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of leaf-form in land plants linked to
atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> decline in the Late Palaeozoic
era</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>410</volume><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35066546</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11268207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11268207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A critical consideration of the quantum yield of
<italic>Chlorella</italic> photosynthesis</article-title><source>Enzymologia</source><year>1948</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirschbaum</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the CO<sub>2</sub>
dependence of quantum yield and respiration in <italic>Eucalyptus pauciflora</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1987</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1032</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.83.4.1032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16665319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16665319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chlorophyll fluorescence - a practical
guide</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2000</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jexbot/51.345.659</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10938857?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10938857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Briantais</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between the quantum yield of
photosynthetic electron transport and quenching of chlorophyll
fluorescence</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - General
Subjects</source><year>1989</year><volume>990</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4165(89)80016-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marenco</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Antezana-Vera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between specific leaf area, leaf
thickness, leaf water content and SPAD-502 readings in six Amazonian tree
species</article-title><source>Photosynthetica</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11099-009-0031-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Percival</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of tissue construction cost from heat of
combustion and organic nitrogen content</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>1987</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>734</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wullschleger</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Norby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Runck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Energetic costs of tissue construction in
yellow-poplar and white oak trees exposed to long-term
CO<sub>2</sub> enrichment</article-title><source>Ann. Bot.</source><year>1997</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbo.1997.0434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">de Vries, F. W. T. P., Jansen, D. M., ten Berge, H. F. M. &#x00026;
Bakema, A. <italic>Simulation of ecophysiological processes of
growth in several annual crops</italic>. Vol. 29 279 (International Rice
Research Institute, 1989).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vertregt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid method for determining the efficiency of
biosynthesis of plant biomass</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>1987</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5193(87)80034-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreira-Vilar</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The acetyl bromide method is faster, simpler and
presents best recovery of lignin in different herbaceous tissues than klason and
thioglycolic acid methods</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e110000</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25330077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25330077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weyers</surname><given-names>JDB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accurate estimation of stomatal aperture from silicone
rubber impressions</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>1985</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.1985.tb02820.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic variation of <italic>Ginkgo
biloba</italic> L. (Ginkgoaceae) based on cpDNA PCR-RFLPs: inference of
glacial refugia</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>2005</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.hdy.6800616</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15536482?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15536482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Crane, P. R. <italic>Ginkgo: the tree that time
forgot</italic>. 383 (Yale University Press, 2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demmig-Adams</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthesis: Harvesting sunlight
safely</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>303</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35000315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anjum</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brassinolide application improves the drought
tolerance in maize through modulation of enzymatic antioxidants and leaf gas
exchange</article-title><source>Journal of Agronomy and Crop Science</source><year>2011</year><volume>197</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-037X.2010.00459.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogren</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The
CO<sub>2</sub>/O<sub>2</sub> specificity of ribulose
1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase: dependence on ribulosebisphosphate
concentration, pH and temperature</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1984</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00398720</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24253719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24253719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Crafts-Brandner</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition and acclimation of photosynthesis to heat
stress is closely correlated with activation of Ribulose-1,5-Bisphosphate
Carboxylase/Oxygenase</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.120.1.173</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10318695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10318695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pankovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saka&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kevre&#x00161;an</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Plesni&#x0010d;ar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acclimation to long-term water deficit in the leaves
of two sunflower hybrids: photosynthesis, electron transport and carbon
metabolism</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>1999</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/50.330.128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunce</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acclimation of photosynthesis to temperature in eight
cool and warm climate herbaceous C3 species: temperature dependence of
parameters of a biochemical photosynthesis model</article-title><source>Photosynthesis Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006325724086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of thermography for quantitative studies of
spatial and temporal variation of stomatal conductance over leaf
surfaces</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>1999</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3040.1999.00468.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High temperature effects on electron and proton
circuits of photosynthesis</article-title><source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2010.00975.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20666927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20666927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poorter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Niinemets</surname><given-names>&#x000dc;</given-names></name><name><surname>Poorter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causes and consequences of variation in leaf mass per
area (LMA): a meta-analysis</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02830.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19434804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19434804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fossil flora of Scoresby Sound East Greenland,
Part 5. Stratigraphic relations of the plant beds</article-title><source>Meddelelser om Gr&#x000f8;nland</source><year>1937</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berner</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kothavala</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GEOCARB III: A revised model of atmospheric
CO<sub>2</sub> over phanerozoic time</article-title><source>Am. J. Sci.</source><year>2001</year><volume>301</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2475/ajs.301.2.182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rising atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> as a
possible trigger for the end-Triassic mass extinction</article-title><source>Palaeogeog. Palaeoclimatol. Palaeoecol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>217</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.palaeo.2004.12.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mander</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;rschner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An explanation for conflicting records of
Triassic-Jurassic plant diversity</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>15351</fpage><lpage>15356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1004207107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belcher</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of leaf morphology on litter
flammability and its utility for interpreting palaeofire</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B,
Biological Sciences</source><year>2016</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>20150163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2015.0163</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27216520?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27216520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is photosynthesis related to concentrations of
nitrogen and Rubisco in leaves of Australian native plants?</article-title><source>Funct. Plant Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/PP98162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heckathorn</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poeller</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallberg</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen availability and vegetative development
influence the response of Ribulose 1,5-Bisphosphate Carboxylase/Oxygenase,
phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase, and heat-shock protein content to heat stress
in <italic>Zea mays</italic> L</article-title><source>Int. J. Plant Sci.</source><year>1996</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>546</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/297374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinthorsdottir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name><name><surname>Surlyk</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>McElwain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep-time evidence of a link between elevated
CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations and perturbations in the
hydrological cycle via drop in plant transpiration</article-title><source>Geology</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/G33334.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonis</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;rschner</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vegetation history, diversity patterns, andclimate
change across the Triassic/Jurassic boundary</article-title><source>Paleobiology</source><year>2012</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1666/09071.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climatic variation in forage grasses. I. Leaf
development in climatic races of <italic>Lolium</italic> and
<italic>Dactylis</italic></article-title><source>J. Appl. Ecol.</source><year>1964</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2401588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niklas</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in the scaling of area and mass of
<italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> (Ginkgoaceae) leaves and
their relevance to the study of specific leaf area</article-title><source>Am. J. Bot.</source><year>2011</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>1386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1100106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21821596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21821596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldham</surname><given-names>TCB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flora of the Wealden plant debris beds of
England</article-title><source>Palaeontology</source><year>1976</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>502</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>