<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Oviposition Deterrent Test</italic>. To investigate oviposition deterrent activity, the slightly modified method described in previous publication [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] was used. This study used gravid female
 <italic class="italic"> Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes aged 4-5 days obtained from the Division of Entomology, National Institute of Health of Thailand, Department of Medical Sciences, Thailand. They were placed in an oviposition cage. The oviposition deterrent activity of different amounts of
 <italic class="italic"> O. gratissimum</italic> oil against gravid
 <italic class="italic"> Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes under laboratory conditions at a room temperature was studied. Two black plastic cups (250 ml in capacity) were placed in the oviposition cage. One cup was filled with 200 ml of distilled water as a control and the other was treated with empty beads (1 g) and distilled water (200 ml) or
 <italic class="italic"> O. gratissimum </italic>oil at different amounts of 0.1, 0.3, 0.5, and 0.7 g mixed with distilled water with final volume of 200 ml. The final concentrations of the treated essential oil in each treated cup were 0.5, 1.5, 2.5, and 3.5 mg/ml, respectively. Each cup was fitted inside with a white filter paper sheet (7 x 28 cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) for the deposition of mosquito eggs. The paper was located in each cup so that the lower half of the paper was submerged in distilled water. The control and treated cups were placed at diagonally opposite corners in a mosquito cage (30 x 30 x 30 cm
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>) containing 20 gravid female mosquitoes for 24 h. Then, the eggs laid in each cup were counted after the removal of the oviposition paper. Six replicates were made in each case. The percentage of deterrence for each test was calculated by applying the following equation [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>].
 <disp-formula id="EEq4" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">(4)</label>
  <math id="M4" class="math">
   <mtable style="T1" class="mtable">
    <mtr class="mtr">
     <mtd class="mtd">
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">P</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">r</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">c</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">n</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">a</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">g</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</mi>
      <mi class="mi"> </mi>
      <mi class="mi"> </mi>
      <mtext class="mtext">of</mtext>
      <mi class="mi"> </mi>
      <mi class="mi"> </mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">d</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">r</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">r</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">n</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">c</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</mi>
      <mo class="mo">=</mo>
      <mfrac class="mfrac">
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mfenced separators="|" class="mfenced">
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mi class="mi">C</mi>
          <mo class="mo">–</mo>
          <mi class="mi">T</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mfenced>
       </mrow>
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mi class="mi">C</mi>
       </mrow>
      </mfrac>
      <mi class="mi"> </mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">x</mi>
      <mi class="mi"> </mi>
      <mn mathvariant="normal" class="mn">100</mn>
     </mtd>
    </mtr>
   </mtable>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
 <italic class="italic">C</italic> stands for the number of mosquito eggs collected from the control cup and
 <italic class="italic"> T</italic> denotes the number of mosquito eggs collected from the treated cup.
</p>
