<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Terminalia ferdinandiana</italic>, popularly known as Kakadu plum, is native to Australia. Indigenous Australians (Aboriginal people) have been using this plant as a food and medicine for centuries, for example, refreshing drinks are made from fresh or dried fruits in Western Australia [
 <xref rid="B2-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Fruits are traditionally used as an antiseptic, soothing balm, in colds and flu and in treating a headache [
 <xref rid="B4-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. A number of research outcomes have been reported on the antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], antibacterial [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B10-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], anti-apoptotic, cytoprotective and anticancer activities [
 <xref rid="B11-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] of 
 <italic class="italic">T. ferdinandiana</italic> fruits and leaves. Phytochemical analysis has revealed that 
 <italic class="italic">T. ferdinandiana</italic> fruit is a rich source of Ellagic acid and its hydrolysable tannins, ellagitannins [
 <xref rid="B12-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Recently, a food safe extraction method of 
 <italic class="italic">T. ferdinandiana</italic> fruits for commercial use in the food industry has been suggested [
 <xref rid="B4-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Additionally, a systematic evaluation of the changes in quality and bioactivity of the fruits of 
 <italic class="italic">T. ferdinandiana</italic> during processing, packaging and storage has been performed, and key chemical markers have been identified to enable standardized products to be delivered to the consumer [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-07-00060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>].
</p>
