<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0165">A number of experiments aimed at the evaluation of the inhibitory activity and the effects of Chinese medicinal herbs on the S protein and ACE2 interaction have been carried out by T.-Y. Ho et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The herbs were divided by the team into 32 families in order to compare the levels of inhibition through taxonomic characterization. Up to 60–90 % of the binding of S protein to Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) at 1 μg was blocked by six herb families, including 
 <italic>Nelumbonaceae, Labiatae, Magnoliaceae, Oleaceae, Lauraceae,</italic> and 
 <italic>Polygonaceae</italic>. Among the given families, the highest inhibitory effect on the S protein and ACE2 interaction was demonstrated by 
 <italic>Polygonaceae</italic>, with t inhibitory percentage of 86.33 ± 4.55 %, where 
 <italic>Radix et Rhizoma Rheim, Radix Polygoni multiflora</italic>, and 
 <italic>Caulis Polygoni multiflori</italic> pertain to 
 <italic>Polygonaceae</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Emodin, the major components of the genus 
 <italic>Rheum</italic> and 
 <italic>Polygonum</italic>, is the likely active constituent responsible for blocking both the binding of SARS-CoV S protein to ACE2. Emodin (
 <bold>33</bold>) (
 <xref rid="fig0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> ) blocked the binding of S protein to ACE2 in a dose-dependent manner. The IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of emodin is 200 μM. Emodin is an anthraquinone compound consists of three cyclic rings. The anti-psychotic drug promazine (
 <bold>34</bold>) (
 <xref rid="fig0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>), which has been shown to exhibit the significant effect in inhibiting the replication of SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], shared a similar structure with emodin. As compared to emodin, promazine exhibited the highest inhibition. However, the differences between emodin and promazine were not significant.
</p>
