<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] determined that the effect of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs in both the UV and visible range depended on the significant reduction in the transmittance of the nano-biocomposite sheets. The lowest transmittance level was found in the presence of the highest TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanoparticle content, which might be attributed to the increased white coloration of the sheets with the NPs addition to the CS matrix. Goudarzi et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] indicated that high TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> content prompted an increase in the L* value, ΔE, and whiteness index (WI), while the b value displayed a decline. However, Teymourpour et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>] reported that adding TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs to the SSPS film elicited a decline in the L* value, while an increase was evident in a and b. According to Zolfi et al. [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>], a rise in WI and a reduction of ΔE were apparent in the kefiran and whey protein coatings following the addition of of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs. Factors such as the difference in biopolymer type, crystallite type of the nano TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, preparation method, thickness of the film, and size of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> might play an essential role in the color variations of the biopolymer film. Furthermore, Oleyaei et al. [
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>] revealed that TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> were able to restrict more than 90% of UV light while enhancing the opacity and WI of the films. Elevated levels of both TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and MMT content were responsible for a decline in the UVB, UVA, and UVC light transmittance [
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>]. Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>] analyzed the optical characteristics of the films using indicators such as internal transmittance at 450 nm (Ti) including hue (h*), clarity (L*), and chrome (C*). Moreover, a substantial decline was evident in silver-loaded films regarding the transparency (Ti), hue (h*), and luminosity (L*) values, while an increase in the color saturation (C*) was apparent. As indicated by Shankar et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], the gelatin/ZnO NPs composite films displayed a lower level of transparency and presented a slight greenish yellow tint, therefore, significantly increased the total color difference value (DE) following gelatin and ZnO NPs amalgamation. Carvalho et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] indicated that the ZnO thin films exhibited exceptional transparency, achieving a transmittance of approximately 80% in the visible region of the electromagnetic spectrum. On the other hand, Goudarzi et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] and Hasheminya et al. [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] demonstrated that the percentage of light transmission and color specifications were usually enhanced by high nanoparticle density. According to Akbariazam et al. [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>], SSPS/ZnO (4%) films exhibited 0% UV transmittance, as well as over 70% absorption of the near-infrared spectrum. Furthermore, Cano et al. [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>] suggested that only transparency and color variations of the starch-PVA films were affected by the addition of AgNPs. While Arfat et al. [
 <xref rid="B83-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>] determined that FPI/FSG films exhibited a transparency reduction following the addition of BEO and ZnO NP [
 <xref rid="B82-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>].
</p>
