<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A total of 50 sows of three to six parities (Landrace × Yorkshire) with similar body conditions (backfat thickness at 17.8 ± 0.60 mm) were used in this experiment. Sows were evenly allocated by parity into two groups (25 sows/group). The sows were artificially inseminated with semen from a pool of Duroc boars. They were housed in individual gestation stalls (2.13 × 0.61 m). The control sows were fed a control (CON) diet and the sows in the high-fat (HF) group were fed a diet containing 2% soybean oil. The HF diet was formulated by mainly reducing the corn but increasing the wheat bran and soybean oil contents. The experimental diets were formulated to meet or exceed the nutrient requirements of gestating and lactating sows as recommended by National Research Council NRC (2012) (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00125-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="animals-09-00125-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). Daily feed intakes were adjusted to ensure a similar intake of nutrients among diets during gestation (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00125-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). Gestation diets were supplied twice a day (07:00 and 17:30). On day 107 of gestation, sows were transported to farrowing stalls and individually fed. After farrowing, all sows received the same standard lactation diet. During the 24 h post-farrowing, litter sizes were adjusted to nine or 10 piglets by cross-fostering within the same treatment. The lactation diet was supplied three times a day (08:00, 11:30 and 17:30) and started at 2.0 kg/day, then increased by 0.5 kg/day during the first week as previously reported [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Afterwards, sows had free access to the diet until they were weaned on day 20 of lactation. Sows were provided ad libitum access to water during the entire experimental trial. The temperature was maintained at 20~22 °C in the gestating house, while it was 24~26 °C in the lactating house, and supplemental heat was provided to piglets with heat lamps (250 W).
</p>
