<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Antioxidant Activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As previously described, the use of different methods is required when assessing antioxidant activity [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">18</a>]. In this study, the DPPH assay, hydroxyl radical scavenging properties, and inhibition effects on lipid peroxidation were used to examine the
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil antioxidant activity. Vitamin C, vitamin E, quercetin, and 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid are four known natural antioxidants and were used as positive controls. The DPPH assay has been used widely in determining the free radical scavenging properties of plant extracts [
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">15</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1"> Figure 1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a> show the results of the DPPH assay. The results showed that the antioxidant power decreased in the order quercetin ≫ vitamin C &gt; vitamin E &gt;
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil &gt; 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid. Reactive oxygen species, in particular hydroxyl radicals, are implicated in oxidative damage to fatty acids, DNA, proteins, and other cellular components [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">19</a>]. Hydroxyl radicals are the most potent oxidizing species of biological membrane proteins and lipids and have an extremely short half-life [
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">20</a>]. The results of the hydroxyl radical scavenging activity test for the
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil are similar to the DPPH assay results. Here, the antioxidant power decreased in the order quercetin &gt; vitamin C &gt;
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil &gt; vitamin E &gt; 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>). Nonetheless, the hydroxyl radical scavenging activity test showed that the antioxidant activity of
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil is stronger than 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-tocopherol. The TBARS assay is used widely to measure lipid oxidation and antioxidant activity [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">21</a>] and was used here to measure the amount of lipid degradation [
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">15</a>] in the presence of the essential oil from
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span>. The inhibition of lipid peroxidation by the
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil was examined and the results compared with those for quercetin, vitamin C, vitamin E, and 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid. As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>, the antioxidant power decreased in the order quercetin &gt; vitamin E &gt;
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil &gt; vitamin C &gt; 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid. In the present study, we found that, compared with known natural antioxidants, the essential oil from
  <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span> exhibited strong free radical scavenging properties and inhibited lipid peroxidation. These attributes are probably because of the inherent activity of some of the components present in the essential oil, in particular the phenols, which inhibit or reduce the rate of aerobic oxidation of organic matter [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">22</a>]. In fact, it has widely been demonstrated that monoterpene hydrocarbons are better antioxidant compounds with respect to sesquiterpenes and particularly those with strongly activated methylene groups in their structure, such as terpinene-4-ol, 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene, and 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-terpinene, were the most active [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">23</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
