<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results and Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec3.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Chemical Composition of the Melaleuca alternifolia Essential Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil from
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>can be obtained easily from the hydrodistillation of
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>leaves, and the chemical composition is dependent on the extraction method used and crop region the samples are taken from [
   <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">3</a>]. The chemical components of
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil used in this study are presented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>. We identified 14 components representing 92.87% of the oil. Terpinene-4-ol (31.11%), 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene (25.30%), and 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpinene (12.70%) were the major constituents followed by 1,8-cineole (6.83%), 
   <span class="italic">ρ</span>-cymene (4.23%), terpinolene (4.03%), limonene (2.50%), 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpineol (2.35%), aromadendrene (1.75%), and 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>-cadinene (1.41%). As alluded to above, the composition of
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil is influenced by several factors, including local, climatic, seasonal, and experimental conditions. Thus, the biological activities of each essential oil preparation will likely vary [
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">17</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Antioxidant Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As previously described, the use of different methods is required when assessing antioxidant activity [
   <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">18</a>]. In this study, the DPPH assay, hydroxyl radical scavenging properties, and inhibition effects on lipid peroxidation were used to examine the
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil antioxidant activity. Vitamin C, vitamin E, quercetin, and 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid are four known natural antioxidants and were used as positive controls. The DPPH assay has been used widely in determining the free radical scavenging properties of plant extracts [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">15</a>]. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1"> Figure 1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a> show the results of the DPPH assay. The results showed that the antioxidant power decreased in the order quercetin ≫ vitamin C &gt; vitamin E &gt;
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil &gt; 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid. Reactive oxygen species, in particular hydroxyl radicals, are implicated in oxidative damage to fatty acids, DNA, proteins, and other cellular components [
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">19</a>]. Hydroxyl radicals are the most potent oxidizing species of biological membrane proteins and lipids and have an extremely short half-life [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">20</a>]. The results of the hydroxyl radical scavenging activity test for the
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil are similar to the DPPH assay results. Here, the antioxidant power decreased in the order quercetin &gt; vitamin C &gt;
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil &gt; vitamin E &gt; 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>). Nonetheless, the hydroxyl radical scavenging activity test showed that the antioxidant activity of
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil is stronger than 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-tocopherol. The TBARS assay is used widely to measure lipid oxidation and antioxidant activity [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">21</a>] and was used here to measure the amount of lipid degradation [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">15</a>] in the presence of the essential oil from
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span>. The inhibition of lipid peroxidation by the
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil was examined and the results compared with those for quercetin, vitamin C, vitamin E, and 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid. As shown in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a> and 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>, the antioxidant power decreased in the order quercetin &gt; vitamin E &gt;
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil &gt; vitamin C &gt; 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-lipoic acid. In the present study, we found that, compared with known natural antioxidants, the essential oil from
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span> exhibited strong free radical scavenging properties and inhibited lipid peroxidation. These attributes are probably because of the inherent activity of some of the components present in the essential oil, in particular the phenols, which inhibit or reduce the rate of aerobic oxidation of organic matter [
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">22</a>]. In fact, it has widely been demonstrated that monoterpene hydrocarbons are better antioxidant compounds with respect to sesquiterpenes and particularly those with strongly activated methylene groups in their structure, such as terpinene-4-ol, 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene, and 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-terpinene, were the most active [
   <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">23</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Antibacterial Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">E. coli, S. aureus, P. aeruginosa, P. italicum Wehmer, and P. digitatum Sacc.</span> are different types of microorganisms.
   <span class="italic"> E. coli, S. aureus,</span> and
   <span class="italic"> P. aeruginosa</span> are pathogenic bacteria [
   <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">24</a>], whereas
   <span class="italic"> P. italicum Wehmer</span> and
   <span class="italic"> P. digitatum Sacc.</span> are fungi [
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">25</a>]. Because these organisms infect, damage, and destroy material used in manufacturing goods or infect the goods produced; these microorganisms increase economic costs in various industries, including medicinal, cosmetic, agriculture, and food industries. Thus, the antibacterial activity of the essential oil from
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span> was investigated with three different methods: the antimicrobial screening method and the MIC and MBC assays. The results presented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab3" href="#tab3">Table 3</a> clearly show that the essential oil of
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>displayed significant antimicrobial activity against all microorganisms tested. The Gram-positive bacteria were more sensitive to the essential oil than Gram-negative bacteria and fungi.
   <span class="italic"> E. coli</span> had the lowest MIC (2 mg/ml). These data are consistent with previous observations that
   <span class="italic"> Melaleuca alternifolia </span>essential oil possesses antibacterial and antifungal activity [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">11</a>]. According to Cox et al. (2000), the antimicrobial activity of the
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span> terpenes is associated with their strong hydrophobicity. Here, the hydrophobic terpenes interact strongly with the membrane lipids of the pathogenic microorganisms, which affect the permeability of the membrane [
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">10</a>]. Among the main consequences of membrane permeability are (i) modification of the proton-motive force, leading to a deficit in the production of cellular energy caused by the decrease in ATP generation, and (ii) cellular lyses due to leakage or coagulation of the cytoplasm [
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">26</a>, 
   <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">27</a>]. The compound terpinene-4-ol, also identified amongst the main constituents of the Iranian Cymbopogon Olivieri essential oil, has been implicated in the antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive bacteria, Gram-negative bacteria, and the yeast
   <span class="italic"> Candida albicans</span> [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">28</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
