<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Plant Material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia (M. alternifolia)</span> samples were collected in four locations of Zhaoqing City of Guangdong Province at altitudes between 300 and 600 m. Samples were dried in well-ventilated spaces away from sunlight. Samples were then placed at 50°C to dry the samples to a constant, dry weight and disintegrated through a 90-mesh sieve. Air-dried plant materials were hydrodistilled using a Clevenger-type apparatus. The composition of
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span> essential oil was analyzed in the laboratory using Hewlett-Packard 6890 gas chromatograph equipped with a cross-linked 5% PH ME siloxane Hewlett-Packard-5MS capillary column (25 m × 0.25 mm ID, 0.25 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m film thickness), coupled to a Hewlett-Packard 5972A mass spectrometer (Hewlett-Packard Ltd., Bracknell, UK). The GC operating conditions were as follows: helium as carrier gas with a flow rate 2.0 ml/min; column temperature programming from 60°C to 275°C at 4°C/min; injector and FID detector temperatures of 215 and 275°C, respectively. The MS operating parameters were as follows: ionization potential, 70 ev; resolution, 1000; ion source temperature, 250°C. Identification of components was based on GC retention indices and the fragmentation patterns of the mass spectra with those of authentic samples, as well as the NIST 98 and HPCH 2205 GC–MS libraries. Relative percentage amounts were obtained directly from GC peak areas. The composition of the essential oil from
   <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span> is presented in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Antioxidative Activity</div>
  <sec id="sec2.2.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1. DPPH Assay</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This spectrophotometric assay uses the stable 2,2-diphenylpicrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical as a reagent [
    <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">14</a>]. One milliliter of various concentrations of the samples in methanol was added to 3 mL of 100 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>M DPPH dissolved in methanol. After incubation for 30 min at room temperature, the absorbance was measured against a blank at 517 nm. The antioxidant activity was determined using the following equation: (%, elimination of DPPH) = (
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>blank</sub> − 
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>sample</sub>/
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>blank</sub>) × 100. The extract concentration providing 50% elimination (EC50) was calculated from the graph plotting inhibition percentage against extract concentration. Tests were carried out in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.2.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. TBARS Assay</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) method was used as described by [
    <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">15</a>]. One milliliter of various concentrations of the samples in methanol was added to 3 mL of 10% yolk homogenate and incubated for 30 min at room temperature. Then, 0.1 mL of a ferrous sulfate solution was added and the reaction incubated for 30 min at 37°C. Next, 3.0 mL of 10% trichloroacetic acid was added and the reaction centrifuged at 2000
    <span class="italic">g</span> for 5 min. Subsequently, 1.0 mL of the supernatant was mixed with 3.0 mL of a 0.67% TBA solution in 50% glacial acetic acid. The mixture was heated in a boiling water bath for ~30 min. The reaction mixture was centrifuged at 2000
    <span class="italic">g</span> for 5 min if the solution became turbid. Finally, the absorbance was measured at 535 nm. A decrease in absorbance indicates an increase in antioxidant activity. The antioxidant activity was determined using the following equation: (%, inhibition of peroxidation) = (
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>blank</sub> − 
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>sample</sub>/
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>blank</sub>) × 100. The extract concentration providing 50% inhibition (IC50) was calculated from the graph plotting inhibition percentage against extract concentration. Tests were carried out in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.2.3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.3. Hydroxyl Radical Scavenging Activity</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hydroxyl radical scavenging activity was measured by the method described in [
    <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">16</a>]. The reaction mixture (1.0 mL) consisting of 0.1 mL of 2-deoxy-D-ribose (28 mM in 20 mM KH
    <sub>2</sub>PO
    <sub>4</sub>-KOH buffer, pH 7.4), 0.1 mL of various concentrations of the samples, 0.2 mL EDTA (1.04 mM) and 200 
    <span class="italic">μ</span>M FeCl
    <sub>3</sub> (1 : 1 v/v), 0.1 mL of H
    <sub>2</sub>O
    <sub>2</sub> (1.0 mM), and 0.1 mL ascorbic acid (1.0 mM) was incubated at 37°C for 1 h. One milliliter of thiobarbituric acid (1%) and 1.0 mL of trichloroacetic acid (2.8%) were added and the solution incubated at 100°C for 20 min. After cooling, the absorbance was measured at 532 nm. The antioxidant activity was determined using the following equation: (%, elimination of hydroxyl radical) = (
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>blank</sub> − 
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>sample</sub>/
    <span class="italic">A</span>
    <sub>blank</sub>) × 100. The extract concentration providing 50% elimination (EC50) was calculated from the graph plotting inhibition percentage against extract concentration. Tests were carried out in triplicate.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Antibacterial Activity</div>
  <sec id="sec2.3.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1. Microbial Strains</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> ATCC25922
    <span class="italic"> (E. coli), Staphylococcus aureus</span> ATCC25923
    <span class="italic"> (S. aureus)</span>,
    <span class="italic"> Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> ATCC27853
    <span class="italic"> (P. aeruginosa)</span>,
    <span class="italic"> Penicillium italicum Wehmer (P. italicum Wehmer),</span> and
    <span class="italic"> Penicillium digitatum Sacc. (P. digitatum Sacc.)</span> were obtained from the China Center for Type Culture Collection (Wuhan University, China).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.3.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2. Antimicrobial Screening</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Paper disks with 6 mm diameter were soaked with 0.1 mL of the essential oil from
    <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia</span> and placed on the surface of solid media plates previously inoculated with the different microorganisms (6.0 log⁡CFU/mL) tested in this study.
    <span class="italic"> P. italicum Wehmer</span> and
    <span class="italic"> P. digitatum Sacc. </span>were cultured at 28°C and 120 rpm for 48 h, whereas
    <span class="italic"> E. coli</span>,
    <span class="italic"> S. aureus, </span>and
    <span class="italic"> P. aeruginosa </span>were cultured at 37°C and 120 rpm for 24 h. The size of the halo for each microorganism was recorded by measuring the zones of growth inhibition surrounding the disks. Individual samples were examined in triplicate. The size of the halos is presented as means ± standard deviation.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.3.3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3. Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) and Minimum Bactericidal Concentration (MBC)</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A broth microdilution method was used to determine the MIC and MBC. The potato dextrose broth and Mueller Hinton broth were prepared at twice the final concentration.
    <span class="italic"> M. alternifolia </span>essential oil was added to glass tubes to yield final sample media concentrations at 0.2 to 48 mg/mL for the potato dextrose and Mueller Hinton broths, respectively. The control sets were run simultaneously without the addition of an antimicrobial agent. An appropriate volume of inoculum (6.0 log⁡CFU/mL) was added to the media to give an approximate final cell concentration of 4.0 log⁡CFU/mL.
    <span class="italic"> P. italicum Wehmer</span> and
    <span class="italic"> P. digitatum Sacc. </span>cultures in potato dextrose broth were incubated at 28°C and 120 rpm for 48 h, whereas
    <span class="italic"> E. coli</span> and
    <span class="italic"> S. aureus </span>cultures in Mueller Hinton broth were incubated at 37°C and 120 rpm for 24 h. The essential oil concentration that yielded no visible growth for a tested species was considered the MIC for that particular species. Then, 0.1 mL suspension obtained from the above transparent tubes was spread onto either potato dextrose agar (PDA) or Mueller Hinton agar (MHA). After 48 h culturing at 28°C (fungi) or 48 h culturing at 37°C (bacteria), the concentration of inoculated suspension containing the lowest level of antimicrobial agent that showed no colonies on the plate was determined as the MBC.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
