<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Hemicelluloses are usually solubilised during thermal pretreatment, and some acid pretreatments obviously release sufficient amounts of sugar monomers to perform subsequent microbial cultivations on the substrate (e.g. Brandenburg et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2016</xref>). However, it has been pointed out that thermochemical pretreatment in many cases releases oligosaccharides, which cannot be assimilated by most of the relevant fermentation organisms. Therefore, treatment with hemicellulases has a great potential to improve the efficiency of lignocellulose-based processes (Girio et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2010</xref>; Biely et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2016</xref>). Because of the heterogeneity of hemicelluloses in different plant materials, a diverse set of hemicellulases is required, including endo-xylanases, β-xylosidases, α-glucuronidases (various types of GH families in the CAZy classification system) and acetyl xylan esterases (CE family). Alkaline pretreatment of straw yields deesterified arabinoglucuronoxylan, while non-alkaline pretreatments result in partially acetylated saccharides. Accordingly, after acid or steam pretreatment, acetylxylan esterases are required to achieve complete saccharification of straw hemicellulose (Biely et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2016</xref>). Oligosaccharides derived from cereal plant hemicelluloses can also be used as prebiotics (Broekaert et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2011</xref>). Those oligosaccharides are produced by GH11 xylanases. The shortest product of their activity consists of four xylose residues substituted with one or two arabinose residues at the penultimate xylose from the non-reducing end (Biely et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2016</xref>). Interactions of different hemicellulase systems with components of the cell wall have to be further elucidated to develop an optimal system for hemicellulose degradation (Biely et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2016</xref>; Gupta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2016</xref>). After several decades of developmental work, commercial cocktails of both cellulases and hemicellulases are now available, e.g. Cellic® CTec3 from Novozyme or ACCELLERASE® TRIO™ from DuPont, and it has been demonstrated that the presence of hemicellulases also considerably improves the degradation of cellulose by cellulases (Lopes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2018</xref>; Payne et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
