<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diabetes Mellitus has become a worldwide concern, manifesting as one of the most major health issues within the world’s population. There are several forms of diabetes, including gestational diabetes, but Type 1 and Type 2 diabetes are by far the most prevalent. Type 2 diabetes (T2DM), most often associated with obesity, is a particularly widespread disease and many patients from all over the globe are afflicted by this condition. T2DM patients are characterized by impaired β-cell function and insulin secretion together with tissue insulin resistance [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Since the prevalence and associated complications of T2DM are so damaging, more effective therapies are being sought to either delay or prevent the progression of T2DM [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As so, plants are most reliable source as studies to date found that they contain series of potential phytogroups including alkaloids, glycosides, terpenoids, phenolic, flavonoids and plant-derived peptides, each of them has shown potential antidiabetic activity in different experiment [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Besides, the diet of patients with T2DM plays a vital role in helping to maintain blood glucose control involving such factors as energy density, carbohydrate content, dietary fiber and natural products that may directly or indirectly affect the absorption of nutrients or the secretion and action of insulin [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Hormones released by the gut in response to nutrient absorption, most notably GIP and GLP-1, also play an important role in modulating post-prandial hyperglycemia [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. These hormones have a very short circulating half-life due to inactivation by the enzyme DPP-IV that cleaves the first two amino acids from the N-terminals producing GIP (3-42) and GLP-1 (9-36) [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This is why DPP-IV inhibitors are beneficial in the treatment of T2DM. Anti-diabetic drugs like metformin and nateglinide that respectively target insulin action and insulin secretion can, at high concentrations, also suppress DPP IV enzyme activity and such action may partly explain use of nateglinide as prandial insulin releasing agent that augments GLP-1 levels [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
</p>
