<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the treatment of UTIs, drugs with a broad antibacterial spectrum, such as ciprofloxacin and amikacin, are used, which differ in terms of their mode of antimicrobial action. The former blocks the replication process and the latter inhibits the synthesis of bacterial proteins [
 <xref rid="B28-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Unfortunately, their wide use, both for medical and non-medical purposes significantly increases the pool of antibiotics present in the environment, thus contributing to the growth of antibiotic resistance. For this reason, preparations of natural origin that could support the bactericidal effect of antibiotics are being sought. The goldenrod herb is one of the many herbal preparations recommended as an adjuvant in the treatment of UTIs. However, research describing the antibacterial properties of goldenrod is very limited. Authors have focused only on determining the minimum bactericidal concentration values or growth inhibition zones of bacteria [
 <xref rid="B29-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. There are no studies concerning the survival or biofilm formation by bacteria treated with 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> extracts. There is also no research describing the antibacterial activities of 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> extracts in combination with antibiotics. Therefore, the aims of our pioneering study were (i) to determine the effect of 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> herb extract on the survival of planktonic forms and biofilm formation by UPEC; (ii) to determine the type of interaction between goldenrod extract and the antibiotics amikacin and ciprofloxacin; and (iii) to evaluate the influence of 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> extract on the duration of the post-antibiotic effect (PAE) and post-antibiotic sub-MIC effect (PASME) of amikacin and ciprofloxacin.
</p>
