<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Clinical specimens, including pus from a subhepatic abscess as well as drain fluids, were collected from the patient, handled according to standard protocols, directly inoculated on Sabouraud dextrose agars (SDA; Difco, BD Diagnostics Systems, USA) supplemented with chloramphenicol (50 µg/mL; Calbiochem, USA) and incubated at 30°C to obtain the case isolate HKU44
 <sup>T</sup>. Fungal materials were harvested directly from a single colony for subsequent subcultures. Clinical data were collected by retrieving and analysing the hospital record of the patient, and the use of these data was approved by the Institutional Review Board of The University of Hong Kong/Hospital Authority Hong Kong West Cluster. The ex-type strains of 
 <italic>Pleurostoma ochraceum, Pleutostoma repens</italic> and 
 <italic>Pleurostoma richardsiae</italic>, a reference strain of 
 <italic>Pleurostoma ootheca</italic> as well as 23 reference strains of 
 <italic>Pleurostoma richardsiae</italic> originating from clinical sources were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC), USA; the Medical Mycology Research Center (MMRC) of Chiba University (IFM), Japan; the National Collection of Pathogenic Fungi (NCPF), Public Health England (PHE), UK; the UAMH Centre for Global Microfungal Biodiversity, Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto, Canada as well as the Westerdijk Fungal Biodiversity Institute (CBS), the Netherlands (Table S1). The quality control strains for susceptibility testing 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> ATCC 204304, 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> ATCC 204305 and 
 <italic>Candida parapsilosis</italic> ATCC 22019
 <sup>T</sup> were obtained from ATCC; 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> CNM-CL F8555, 
 <italic>Pichia kudriavzevii</italic> (synonym: 
 <italic>Candida krusei</italic>) CNM-CL-3403 and 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> CNM-CM-1813 were obtained from Statens Serum Institut (SSI), Denmark; and 
 <italic>Pichia kudriavzevii</italic> NRRL Y-413 (=ATCC 6258) was obtained from the Agricultural Research Service (ARS) Culture Collection (NRRL), Department of Agriculture, USA.
</p>
