<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flavonoids, especially those consumed in the diet, have become popular as molecules with strong antioxidant potential and beneficial actions in diabetes, cardiovascular disorders, various types of cancer and inflammatory conditions. Although many studies claimed that oxidative stress had a substantial impact on the onset and development of secondary pathology in more than 150 human diseases, not every disease can be linked to oxidative stress. Nevertheless, it has been established that oxidative stress does play a negative role in many human diseases such as the cancer of the stomach, liver, prostate, ovaries and breasts, as well as neurodegenerative diseases, Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s, inflammatory bowel disease, Crohn’s disease, ulcerative colitis and arthrosclerosis. As thoroughly reviewed by Halliwell (2012) [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], flavonoids as antioxidants have failed in the majority of intervention studies to provide any therapeutic benefit and thus have not passed to further phases of clinical trials, let alone used as antioxidants in medical practice. Interestingly, various studies point to a fact that flavonoids might actually act in a pro-oxidant manner in vivo, rather than as antioxidants (such might be the case of resveratrol [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]). Since the human diet may have been relatively rich in flavonoids, humans must have adapted to this evolutionary pressure. Indeed, any specific cellular transporter that would be responsible for the accumulation of flavonoids in particular tissues have not been found yet [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, it seems that these compounds can be readily excreted from biological matrices such as urine or faeces. Some flavonoids might provide a therapeutic benefit in human diseases through a different biological mechanism than that of antioxidant activity. Flavonoids were found to inhibit various enzymes such as cyclin-dependent kinases. Therefore, the question if flavonoids are effective in the treatment of oxidative stress-related diseases, and whether their effect is provided by an antioxidant mechanism is still being debated. The answer to the first part of the question appears to be “maybe”, but to the second “probably not”. Further enlightenment on this problem requires more future research.
</p>
