<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">NMR spectra were recorded using a Bruker Avance DRX-400 and DPX-200 spectrometers (Bruker, Milan, Italy) operating at frequencies of 400 MHz (
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H), 100 MHz (
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C), 200 MHz (
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H), and 50 MHz (
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C). The spectra were measured in CDCl
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> and DMSO-
 <italic class="italic">d</italic>
 <sub class="sub">6</sub>. The 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H- and 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C-NMR chemical shifts (δ) were expressed in ppm with reference to the solvent signals. Coupling constants are given in Hz. GC analyses were performed on a HP 6890N Network GC system (Hewlett Packard, Waldbronn, Germany) equipped with a Hewlett Packard MS 5975 mass selective detector (Hewlett Packard, Waldbronn, Germany) and a capillary column (DB-5MS; 30 m × 0.53 mm i.d., 0.50 μm film thickness, Agilent Technologies Italia, Cernusco sul Naviglio, Milan, Italy). The oven temperature was programmed from 40 °C for 7 min, then increased at 10 °C/min to 270 °C and held for 20 min. Injector and detector temperatures were 250 and 270 °C, respectively. Samples were dissolved in 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexane to give 1 μL/mL solutions and were injected in the splitless mode using helium as carrier gas (1 mL/min); the injection volume was 1 μL. The ionization energy was 70 eV. Percentage compositions of the components were obtained from electronic integration dividing the area of each component by the total area of all components. The percentage values are the mean ± SD of two injections of the sample. All compounds were identified by the comparison of their retention indices (RI) relative to retention times on the DB-5MS column of a homologous series of C8–C20 alkanes with those reported in the literature [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-23-02817" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] and by comparison of mass spectra from the Wiley 275 Mass Spectral Database (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.sisweb.com/software/ms/wiley.htm" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.sisweb.com/software/ms/wiley.htm</uri>). Moreover, whenever possible, identification was confirmed by an injection of a standard commercial sample. All solvents were of analytical grade and were purchased from VWR (Milan, Italy) Deionized water was obtained by Milli-Q water purification system from Merck-Millipore (Milan, Italy). Ionic liquids were synthesized following literature procedures or with original protocols as reported in this manuscript.
</p>
