<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">The low toxicity of citral or geranyl acetate for 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> may be related to the cuticle of this insect, which acts as a barrier, as reported for 
 <italic class="italic">Bombyx mori</italic> Linnaeus (Lepidoptera: Bombycidae) exposed to deltamethrin
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. Cuticular lipids prevent the desiccation and penetration of xenobiotics into insects
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>, as well as promoting thickening and cuticle composition that can delay the penetration of insecticidal molecules into the body of the insect
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>, thus reducing the essential oil effect post-application due to rapid degradation or evaporation in the environment
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. The lack of detoxifying enzymatic activity (inhibitors of cytochrome P450s, esterases or glutathione S-transferases)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup> was observed in 
 <italic class="italic">Trichoplusia ni</italic> (Hübner) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) treated with citral, which penetrated through the cuticular layer
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>. Toxic constituents can affect multiple regions of the insect body, causing necrotic areas which increase progressively throughout the entire insect body
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. One possible explanation for the low toxicity caused in 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> is that there may be differences in the penetration rate of the lemongrass constituents into the body, coupled with the ability of this insect to rapidly detoxify.
</p>
