<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">The short distance traveled in the arenas towards the opposite side from the geranyl acetate by 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> nymphs suggest repellent activity. Various insect pests show altered behavioral responses when exposed to lemongrass essential oil constituents, as reported for 
 <italic class="italic">Bemisia tabaci</italic> Gennadius (Hemiptera: Aleyrodidae)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic class="italic">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> Say (Diptera: Culicidae)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Tribolium castaneum</italic> (Herbst) (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>, influencing the olfactory orientation and insect walking behavior. Insects can identify the presence of compounds, as reported for 
 <italic class="italic">Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic> (Harris) (Hemiptera: Aphididae), after the activation of olfactory receptors in the presence of geranyl acetate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup>. The results indicate that 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> exhibits behavioral avoidance by means of repellence to geranyl acetate, minimizing contact with insecticide-contaminated surfaces. In contrast, nymphs of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic>, exposed in arenas with citral, presented irritability and decreased resting periods, which may be related to intoxication in the octapaminergic system, causing hyperactivity or hyperextension in the legs and abdomen
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>. Essential oils have caused sublethal effects such as increased heart rate, changes in the cAMP level in the nervous system and decreased binding to octopamine receptors, as decribed for 
 <italic class="italic">Periplaneta americana</italic> Linnaeus (Blattodea: Blattidae)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
