<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Biological invasions cause great damage worldwide, especially to fragile ecosystems [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In the case of 
 <italic>X. italicum</italic> invasion, we selected our study site in Xinjiang province, a typical arid region in far northwestern China on the border with Mongolia and Kazakhstan, where the World’s second largest desert—Taklamakan Desert—is located [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Arid ecosystems are relatively simple in structure and function compared with other terrestrial ecosystems, which makes them more susceptible to invasions [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The recent invasion of 
 <italic>X. italicum</italic> has raised concerns regarding the possible ecological consequences it could bring to this arid land [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]; however, the mechanism underlying the successful invasion of this plant remains unclear. There have been many hypotheses attempting to elucidate the mechanism of exotic plant invasions [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]; among them, the “novel weapons hypothesis” has been controversial ever since it was proposed [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This hypothesis posits that some exotic invasive species owe their success to the production of novel allelochemicals that native species have never encountered [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Our previous study revealed that seedling growth of radish and wheat were significantly affected when grown in rhizosphere soil of 
 <italic>X. italicum</italic>, indicating the possible involvement of allelochemicals which might act as a “novel weapon” in the invaded region and thus affect growth of native species (data not shown). Considering the fact that allelopathy is a notoriously difficult mechanism to demonstrate [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], we decide to start with the isolation and identification of phytotoxins in 
 <italic>X. italicum</italic> plant which might work as potential allelochemicals after being released into the environment via leaching, root exudation or litter decomposition. Previous studies on other invasive plants have confirmed the presence of allelochemicals [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-17-04037" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]; if we could verify the presence of potential allelochemicals at levels necessary to influence plant growth in soil beneath 
 <italic>X. italicum</italic> plant, we believe we are at least getting closer to proving the contribution of allelopathy to the successful invasion of 
 <italic>X. italicum</italic>. Moreover, if the putative allelochemicals don’t exist in 
 <italic>X. strumarium</italic>, a native 
 <italic>Xanthium</italic> plant, we could conduct further investigations which might consequently provide evidence to support the “novel weapons hypothesis”. 
</p>
