<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">Despite the small number of respondents, some interesting patterns are evident in the plant and bird naming results. Three of these patterns are discussed in this and the following sections: the relationship between naming performance and respondent age, the difference between respondents’ ability to name plants and birds and differences in the salience of various plant and bird ethnotaxa, as reflected in participants’ ability to recognize and name them. Positive correlations between age and ethnobiological knowledge have been noted in many rural, minority communities around the world (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]), but such a pattern was not seen to a convincing degree in the present dataset. Nor was it the case that knowledge levels plateaued in young adulthood (in a person’s 30s), as suggested by Koster et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], because none of the younger participants (aged 19–56) came close to the performance of the 80-year-old participant, and some older Kune speakers were even outperformed by their much younger relatives (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Further discussion on this issue can be found in the section ‘Personal life history and TEK’. Comparable studies carried out with Australian indigenous communities are rare, but a TEK documentation project of the Kija and Jaru languages of the Kimberleys (also in northern Australia) showed a strong correlation between TEK levels and language proficiency [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Both Kija and Jaru are highly endangered, and for Kija at least, the youngest fluent speakers were in their forties or fifties at the time of the study. Accordingly, the most proficient speakers tended to have the most TEK. The results from the Blythe and Wightman study are not directly comparable to the current Kune study, because of the very different language endangerment situation. Older Kune speakers would probably agree that their younger relatives possessed less TEK than members of their own generation, akin to the older respondents in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. However, this cannot be blamed on an insufficient grasp of Kune, as the language is being transmitted to young children.
</p>
