<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0190">Bulk sweeteners do not need bulking agents like polydextrose and inulin. These compounds can fully replicate the structural role of sucrose as well as give sweetness. Isomalt, a mixture of glucosyl-glucitol and glucosyl-mannitol disaccharides, has been shown to have a similar effect to sucrose on the rheological properties of chocolate. (
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Kiumarsi et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Bender, 2014</xref>). However, isomalt was given a low sensory acceptability for taste and texture in sensory tests; although this could be due to the addition of stevia and the use of a ball mill process to adjust the size distribution of isomalt particles (
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Rad et al., 2019</xref>). Another study showed that xylitol had higher sensory acceptability, but it also increased the viscosity in the liquid chocolate (
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Rad et al., 2019</xref>). This is because sugar alcohols such as xylitol dissolve quicker in the mouth compared to sugar, due to the higher amount of –OH groups in sugar alcohols with high water solubility in the mouth (
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Rad et al., 2019</xref>). The free –OH groups on the xylitol molecule also lead to more interactions with each other, and this causes a high viscosity in liquid chocolate (
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Rad et al., 2019</xref>). Meanwhile, other sweeteners such as maltitol and tagatose could reduce the amount of fat bloom in chocolate compared to sucrose, with tagatose shown to be the most effective at suppressing CB recrystallization in solid chocolate. (
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Son et al., 2018</xref>). Maltitol, isomalt and inulin all resulted in different melting properties for the chocolate compared to sucrose, which would result in different mouth feel and may affect acceptance (
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Kiumarsi et al., 2017</xref>). However, in this study the concentration of all three bulk sweeteners was the same as that of the sucrose in the reference sample, 38% w/w. These sweeteners all have different chemical structures and chemical-physical properties. Therefore, a different concentration may be needed to give the best CB crystallization and rheological properties to novel sugar-free chocolate products. Therefore, looking at different concentrations would give more insight into the way these sweeteners work. A mixture of isomalt and maltose in sucrose-free dark chocolate was shown to give similar properties to sucrose dark chocolate when the tempering method was changed to a CB form V seeded technique (
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">Toker et al., 2019</xref>). Changing tempering techniques should be considered when making novel alternative chocolate products due to the effect on novel ingredients on fat crystallization.
</p>
