<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Plant Mol Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Plant Mol Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Plant Molecular Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0167-4412</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1573-5028</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7892686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33296063</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1098</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11103-020-01098-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>LC&#x02013;MS based metabolic fingerprinting of apricot pistils after self-compatible and self-incompatible pollinations</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e9;n&#x000e1;rt</surname><given-names>J&#x000f3;zsef</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gere</surname><given-names>Attila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Causon</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hann</surname><given-names>Stephan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dernovics</surname><given-names>Mih&#x000e1;ly</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>N&#x000e9;meth</surname><given-names>Olga</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heged&#x00171;s</surname><given-names>Attila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4141-6024</contrib-id><name><surname>Hal&#x000e1;sz</surname><given-names>J&#x000fa;lia</given-names></name><address><email>genetics.prunus@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.129553.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1015 7851</institution-id><institution>Department of Applied Chemistry, Faculty of Food Science, </institution><institution>Szent Istv&#x000e1;n University, </institution></institution-wrap>Vill&#x000e1;nyi &#x000fa;t 29-43, Budapest, 1118 Hungary </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.129553.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1015 7851</institution-id><institution>Department of Genetics and Plant Breeding, Faculty of Horticultural Science, </institution><institution>Szent Istv&#x000e1;n University, </institution></institution-wrap>M&#x000e9;nesi &#x000fa;t 44, Budapest, 1118 Hungary </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.129553.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1015 7851</institution-id><institution>Department of Postharvest Sciences and Sensory Evaluation, Faculty of Food Science, </institution><institution>Szent Istv&#x000e1;n University, </institution></institution-wrap>Vill&#x000e1;nyi &#x000fa;t 29-43, 1118 Budapest, Hungary </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5173.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2298 5320</institution-id><institution>Institute of Analytical Chemistry, </institution><institution>University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Muthgasse 18, 1190 Vienna, Austria </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417760.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2159 124X</institution-id><institution>Department of Plant Physiology, </institution><institution>Agricultural Institute, Centre for Agricultural Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Brunszvik u. 2, Martonv&#x000e1;s&#x000e1;r, 2462 Hungary </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>105</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020, corrected publication 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Key message</title><p>LC-MS based metabolomics approach revealed that putative metabolites other than flavonoids may significantly contribute to the sexual compatibility reactions in <italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic>. Possible mechanisms on related microtubule-stabilizing effects are provided.</p></sec><sec><title>Abstract</title><p id="Par1">Identification of metabolites playing crucial roles in sexual incompatibility reactions in apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic> L.) was the aim of the study. Metabolic fingerprints of self-compatible and self-incompatible apricot pistils were created using liquid chromatography coupled to time-of-flight mass spectrometry followed by untargeted compound search. Multivariate statistical analysis revealed 15 significant differential compounds among the total of 4006 and 1005 aligned metabolites in positive and negative ion modes, respectively. Total explained variance of 89.55% in principal component analysis (PCA) indicated high quality of differential expression analysis. The statistical analysis showed significant differences between genotypes and pollination time as well, which demonstrated high performance of the metabolic fingerprinting and revealed the presence of metabolites with significant influence on the self-incompatibility reactions. Finally, polyketide-based macrolides similar to peloruside A and a hydroxy sphingosine derivative are suggested to be significant differential metabolites in the experiment. These results indicate a strategy of pollen tubes to protect microtubules and avoid growth arrest involved in sexual incompatibility reactions of apricot.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1007/s11103-020-01098-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Apricot</kwd><kwd>Mass spectrometry</kwd><kwd>Metabolic fingerprinting</kwd><kwd>Metabolomics</kwd><kwd>Self-incompatibility</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003549</institution-id><institution>Hungarian Scientific Research Fund</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>(OTKA) K_128874 project (A. Heged&#x00171;s)</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Szent Istv&#x000e1;n University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by Szent Istv&#x000e1;n University.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature B.V. 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Genetic variation creates the basis of evolutionary success of a species allowing natural selection to favor the genotypes most adapted to external conditions. In sexually-reproducing organisms, the sources of genetic variation include mutations and several processes in meiosis. However, in hermaphrodite plants, self-fertilization may result in a serious loss of genetic variability and consequent inbreeding depression (Good-Avila et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2008</xref>; Mart&#x000ed;nez-Garc&#x000ed;a et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2012</xref>). Such plants have elaborated genetically controlled mechanisms to prevent self-fertilization (Kao and Tsukamoto <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2004</xref>). One such mechanism is the gametophytic self-incompatibility (GSI) in the Rosaceae family determined by the self-incompatibility (<italic>S</italic>) locus. Two genes were identified in the <italic>S</italic>-locus with one coding a pistil-specific ribonuclease enzyme (<italic>S</italic>-RNase) and another for an <italic>S</italic>-haplotype-specific F-box (SFB) protein specifically produced in pollen tubes (Matsumoto and Tao <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2019</xref>). Self/non-self-recognition in these plants is mediated by these molecules. Non-self <italic>S</italic>-RNases enter the compatible pollen tubes where they are rapidly degraded through a general inactivation mechanism and hence protein biosynthesis is undisturbed. In contrast, self <italic>S</italic>-RNases are recognized and prevented from degradation (Matsumoto and Tao <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2016</xref>; Sonneveld et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2005</xref>), which results in an incompatible reaction without fruit set.</p><p id="Par3">The precise molecular interactions behind the (in)compatibility reaction and between&#x000a0;the <italic>S</italic>-RNase and SFB are unknown. Interestingly, solanaceous plants also exhibit an <italic>S</italic>-RNase-based GSI system and vacuole stability was reported as a crucial element in the physiological reactions leading to compatible or incompatible mating (Goldraij et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2006</xref>; McClure <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2006</xref>). In solanaceous plants, besides <italic>S</italic>-RNase and SFB, additional non-<italic>S</italic>-specific proteins (e.g., HT-B, 120&#x000a0;K, NaTTS) were determined to play a pivotal role in the incompatibility response. Mutant phenotypes or transgenic experiments allowed clarification that loss-of-function of such factors results in the breakdown of the self-incompatibility barrier in a non-<italic>S</italic>-specific manner. Although such proteins have not been identified in <italic>Prunus</italic> until now, non-<italic>S</italic>-locus factors may also contribute to the incompatibility response. Cachi and W&#x000fc;nsch have found that the locus associated with self-compatibility in &#x02018;Cristobalina&#x02019; sweet cherry is located in LG3, in contrast with the <italic>S</italic>-locus in LG6 (Cachi and W&#x000fc;nsch <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). A loss-of-function mutation in a non-<italic>S</italic> locus gene, also mapped on LG3, was shown to induce self-compatibility in the apricot cultivars &#x02018;Canino&#x02019; and &#x02018;Katy&#x02019;(Mu&#x000f1;oz-Sanz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2017</xref>; Zuriaga et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2013</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">Self-incompatibility and mutations rendering self-compatibility of specific cultivars have been long known in apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic> L.) (Hal&#x000e1;sz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2014</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>; Mu&#x000f1;oz-Sanz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2017</xref>). Proteomic differences were also reported after self- and cross-pollinated self-incompatible (SI) apricots by two-dimensional polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (2D-PAGE) and liquid chromatography-electrospray tandem mass spectrometry (LC&#x02013;ESI&#x02013;MS/MS) (Feng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2006</xref>). In a subsequent study, the same authors extended the number of proteins identified in apricot pistil after self- and cross-pollination of SI genotypes (Feng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2009</xref>). A recent study performed transcriptome analysis in almond pistils after compatible and incompatible pollinations and identified 1357 differentially expressed genes involved in metabolic processes and binding molecular functions, which may have a role in GSI (G&#x000f3;mez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">Metabolomics provides a useful practical tool for bridging the genotype&#x02013;phenotype gap in plants (Hall and Hardy <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2012</xref>). The metabolome represents all of the relevant primary and&#x000a0;secondary metabolites,&#x000a0;typically with molecular masses &#x0003c; 1.5&#x02013;2 kDa, in a given organism. The composition of the metabolome is regarded as a unique fingerprint, which dynamically changes in response to external effects. Consequently, metabolic fingerprinting can give a closer hint how the final phenotypes evolve. Liquid chromatography combined with mass spectrometry (LC&#x02013;MS) based metabolic fingerprinting is proven to be a powerful tool to identify significant differentiating compounds and related metabolic changes in plants (Atkinson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>; Rodrigues-Neto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2018</xref>). There are some databases which are specific to plant metabolites and serve as good sources for substance identification in plant metabolomics, e.g., Dictionary of Natural Products (Quinn et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2008</xref>) contains biologically active small molecules and MoTo DB database (Moco et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2006</xref>), which is specific to tomato metabolites.</p><p id="Par6">Still, metabolite identification is the bottleneck of LC&#x02013;MS based metabolic fingerprinting. The number of metabolites with accurate mass LC&#x02013;MS and LC&#x02013;MS/MS data is relatively limited in metabolite databases compared to libraries intended for GC&#x02013;MS based identification (Weckwerth et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2004</xref>; Xiao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2013</xref>), especially when in silico prediction of LC&#x02013;MS/MS fragmentation fails to provide unambiguous confirmation. Moreover, pollination/germination related issues are seldom covered in metabolomics, as pistils are hardly targeted with LC&#x02013;MS based metabolomic tools because of the highly time-dependent characteristics (Qin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2011</xref>); such analyses are mostly limited to flavonoid research (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2012</xref>; Hanhineva et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2008</xref>).</p><p id="Par7">Indeed, there have been only a few studies dealing with non-flavonoid targeted research in pollination metabolomics in the field of Rosaceae. Cubells-Baeza and co-workers attempted to identify the ligand of Pru p 3, a peach lipid transfer protein (LTP) (Cubells-Baeza et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2017</xref>). However, the study could directly focus on one molecule that could be highly purified through orthogonal chromatographic steps, the instrumental set-up of a MALDI coupled to an ESI-QTOF HR (high resolution) mass spectrometer could only prove that the ligand is a derivative of camptothecin. Facing the need for milligrams of the target analyte to enable NMR-based identification, such a conclusion without reporting an ultimate structure can be regarded as a common event. Concerning a higher level of metabolomics, that is, unknown screening for a non-limited set of metabolites, there has been only one study on Rosaceae: <sup>1</sup>H-NMR-profiling results of non-pollinated and pollinated styles of pear (<italic>Pyrus communis</italic> L.) have been&#x000a0;recently reported (Mandrone et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2019</xref>). The authors could finally frame a set of four molecular classes (e.g., molecules with a kaempferol moiety) and 15 basic (known) molecules that showed relation with pollination metabolism. Clearly, <sup>1</sup>H-NMR-profiling can definitely function as a preliminary screening to shorten the list of potential candidates for a more targeted study, but it is unable to assess the complexity of metabolites and to pinpoint single key molecules&#x02014;if there are any.</p><p id="Par8">To the best of our knowledge, there have been no prior attempts to deduce the self-incompatibility reactions in Rosaceae fruit tree species by LC&#x02013;MS based metabolic fingerprinting. Therefore, the aim of the present study was to compare the metabolic fingerprints of self-pollinated pistils of a SC and SI apricot cultivar to shed light on physiological differences between incompatible and compatible reactions in the <italic>Prunus S</italic>-RNase-based GSI system. We investigated whether biomarkers or key metabolites participating in these reactions can be found and assigned by LC&#x02013;MS based metabolic fingerprinting, which may explain currently unknown aspects of the (in)compatibility reaction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Chemicals and reagents</title><p id="Par9">Tebuconazole (applied as internal standard) and formic acid were purchased from the Merck-Sigma group (St. Louis, MO, USA). HPLC gradient grade acetonitrile, methanol, and HPLC grade ethanol were ordered from Fisher Scientific (VWR, Radnor, PA, USA). Ultra-pure water (&#x0003e;&#x02009;18 M&#x003a9;&#x02022; cm) was obtained from a Merck-Millipore Milli-Q system (Bedford, USA). Peloruside A authentic standard material was gained by chemical synthesis and also&#x000a0;by isolation from <italic>Mycale hentscheli</italic> marine sponge samples with the kind contribution of Dan Sackett (Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, Bethesda, USA) and Peter Northcote (Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand) and their workgroups, respectively. Peloruside A stocks were prepared in ethanol and were stored at&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;18&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par10">Two apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic> L.) genotypes were studied, &#x02018;Cegl&#x000e9;di &#x000f3;ri&#x000e1;s&#x02019; (<italic>S</italic><sub>8</sub><italic>S</italic><sub>9</sub>) and &#x02018;Pann&#x000f3;nia&#x02019; (<italic>S</italic><sub>C</sub><italic>S</italic><sub>C</sub>) as SI and SC species, respectively (Hal&#x000e1;sz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>). Branches (with flower buds) were collected from apricot trees in the orchard (Szigetcs&#x000e9;p, Hungary; 47&#x000b0;15&#x02032;30&#x02033;N 18&#x000b0;58&#x02032;10&#x02033;E) and were subsequently transported into the laboratory and kept in tap water. Collection was performed when flowers were in the balloon stage (pollen grains were not released from the anthers and hence spontaneous pollination was not possible). In a subsequent step, the flowers were emasculated and controlled hand-pollination was performed by collecting pollen grains from the desiccated anthers. After pollination, pistils were collected after 3, 24 and 96&#x000a0;h. Pistils of both species without pollination were also collected and used as a control (0&#x000a0;h). Samples from different species and pollination stages were collected and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sample preparation</title><p id="Par11">The pistils from the fridge were immediately frozen again in liquid nitrogen in a mortar and were disrupted by a pestle. 100&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x000a0;mg portions of the gained powder were weighed on an analytical scale in sterile 1.5&#x000a0;mL Eppendorf tubes. Three biological replicates were made for both species in every pollination stage and a total of 24 samples were obtained. Extraction was performed in the same tubes by 1000 &#x000b5;L 80:20% v/v methanol:ultra-pure water, vortexed thoroughly and shaken in a thermomixer at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min. Before vortexing, 10&#x000a0;ng&#x000a0;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> tebuconazole was added as internal standard. The insoluble plant material was separated by centrifugation at 10,000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Ten-fold dilutions with ultra-pure water were performed on the collected supernatants and the samples were filtered through disposable 0.45&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m PTFE syringe filters before injection into the LC&#x02013;MS system.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>HPLC-ESI-QTOF-MS analysis</title><p id="Par12">The LC&#x02013;MS coupling was carried out with an Agilent 1100 HPLC system (Agilent Technologies, Waldbronn, Germany) and a quadrupole time-of-flight (QTOF) high resolution mass spectrometer (Agilent 6530 Accurate Mass QTOF LC/MS, Palo Alto, CA, USA). 10 &#x000b5;L of the sample extracts were injected on a Zorbax Eclipse XDB-C18 reversed phase column (3.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, 2.1&#x000a0;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;50&#x000a0;mm; Agilent). Water with 0.1% v/v formic acid was used as eluent&#x000a0;A, and acetonitrile with 0.1% v/v formic acid was used as&#x000a0;eluent B; HPLC flow was set to 400 &#x000b5;L min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Gradient elution was set as follows: 0&#x02013;3&#x000a0;min 10% B; 3&#x02013;15&#x000a0;min up to 100% B; 15&#x02013;17&#x000a0;min 100% B, 17&#x02013;18&#x000a0;min down to 10% B; 18&#x02013;22&#x000a0;min 100% B. The QTOF-MS instrument was operated with an Agilent 6220 instrument-derived dual electrospray ionization (ESI) ion source in positive and negative ionization modes. Mass calibration was performed by introducing a mass calibration solution by direct infusion according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions; due to the continuous mass correction, the experienced mass accuracy was&#x02009;~&#x02009;3&#x000a0;ppm and mass resolution was above 10,000 (FWHM) at <italic>m/z</italic> 400. The instrumental parameters and settings are summarized in the Electronic supplementary material in Table S1. All samples were first run to obtain full scan MS spectra, and in addition, some samples were run to obtain MS<sup>2</sup> fragmentations using collision induced dissociation (CID) from the compounds of interest. Data were recorded both in centroid and profile modes in the range <italic>m/z</italic> 100&#x02013;1700.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Data mining strategy</title><p id="Par13">Mass spectrometric data were recorded with Agilent Mass Hunter Data Acquisition B.04.00 and processed with Agilent Mass Hunter Qualitative Analysis software B.06.00. Untargeted compound search (general unknown screening) was performed by the Molecular Feature Extraction (MFE) algorithm. Ions are grouped together to create a given molecular feature whose extracted ion chromatograms (EICs) share similar elution profile and additionally their mass differences can be explained via isotope ratios, adduct or dimer formations or neutral losses and in-source fragmentation events. The software takes into consideration user defined parameters regarding mass accuracy, mass resolution, minimal signal and compound intensities, minimum number of ions per compound, etc.</p><p id="Par14">According to the manufacturer&#x02018;s instructions the so-called recursive feature extraction protocol was applied to enhance the performance of the MFE algorithm. Minimum intensity of precursor ions was set to 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> counts. MFE settings were optimized and the isotope spacing tolerance parameter was reduced from the default value (5 mDa&#x02009;+&#x02009;7&#x000a0;ppm) to 2 mDa&#x02009;+&#x02009;3&#x000a0;ppm. General unknown screening algorithms may result in false positive and negative hits or wrong assignment of monoisotopic masses even after optimization, consequently all metabolites of interest were verified manually regarding the isotopic pattern, adducts, in-source fragments, etc.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Differential expression analysis</title><p id="Par15">Statistical analysis of samples after untargeted compound search was done by Mass Profiler Professional (Agilent, version 12.1) and an LC&#x02013;MS manufacturer independent software XLSTAT (version 2013.1; Addinsoft, USA) running as an add-in of Microsoft Excel software. Recursive feature extraction and compound alignment (including abundance normalization to internal standard) were performed by Mass Profiler Professional while further statistical analyses were carried out with both of the software packages. After compound alignment, the data were exported into comma separated (.csv) format to be handled by Microsoft Excel.</p><p id="Par16">The obtained differential feature list was manually verified to eliminate redundant information and to correct peak integration failures so compounds of very low intensity could be also filtered out. To be able to combine positive and negative ionization data, the final analysis was performed by XLSTAT. Workflow of the complete data evaluation can be seen on Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Both statistical differential expression analyses consisted of the following methods: (i) filtering by frequency (features must be present in 100% of the replicates); (ii) retaining entities that monotonously increase or decrease in time; (iii) significant metabolites were determined by <italic>t</italic>-test at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; (iv) finally a heatmap containing the differential compounds was created and principal component analysis (PCA) was performed in order to visualize how the groups are differentiated and to determine the most significant metabolites.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Workflow of the applied statistical differential expression analysis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Assignment of differential compounds</title><p id="Par17">The elemental composition (molecular formula) of the differential metabolites was determined based on their monoisotopic mass and isotopologue ratios. Free online and commercially available compound databases and in silico fragmentation tools (including Dictionary of Natural Products (DNP); SciFinder, ChemSpider, KnapSack, MassBank, Metlin,&#x000a0;LIPID MAPS, LipidBlast, GNPS, MetFrag and PubChem) were searched individually and with the help of the MassHunter Lipid Annotator software tool (version 1.0, build 1.0.54.0; Agilent; see the Electronic&#x000a0;supplementary material Table S1) against the determined molecular formulae and MS/MS fragments.</p><p id="Par18">The compounds of interest included in the differential feature list were analyzed in a subsequent run on the HPLC-ESI-QTOF-MS system in Auto MS/MS mode to perform fragmentation reactions by CID in order to gain structural information. The user defined parameters of the Auto MS/MS mode are summarized in Table S2 in the Electronic supplementary material.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Detected metabolites</title><p id="Par19">The applied methanolic extraction resulted in a large number of metabolites: the total numbers of aligned compounds were 4006 and 1005 in positive and negative ionization modes, respectively. Because of the large number of metabolites, manual checking of the whole list is not viable. Therefore, incorporation of the recursive feature extraction was required to achieve sufficient metabolite searching performance. Quality control in terms of repeatability by PCA was also checked and no significant outlier samples were found among parallels.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Determination of differential metabolites: combination of software based and manual data reduction steps</title><p id="Par20">Statistical analysis was performed by both software packages in order to check if there was a difference between the performance of the software. Reliability of the statistical evaluation process was indicated by the two different lists containing exactly the same entities. The numbers of differential entities were 72 and 61 in&#x000a0;positive and negative ion modes, respectively. After merging the compounds found in both ionization modes, manual verification was performed on this list and redundant information was removed by checking the mass spectra manually at the entities` corresponding retention time (t<sub>R</sub>) values. When necessary, the integration failures were also corrected by manually integrating the EICs at the monoisotopic masses or, where needed, at the characteristic/abundant adducts. Metabolites having low signal-to-noise ratio and very low abundances were filtered out since their&#x000a0;identification was not considered due to decreased mass accuracy, inaccurate isotope ratio and poor MS<sup>2</sup> product ion spectra. It is also important to highlight that no dedicated list of commonly targeted compounds (e.g., highly abundant flavonoids) was set in order not to bias the statistical evaluation.</p><p id="Par21">Focusing on the entities that showed monotonous decreasing or increasing tendency, the highest abundances of the individual metabolites were checked in the samples collected without pollination (SC 0&#x000a0;h and SI 0&#x000a0;h) or 96&#x000a0;h after pollination (SC 96&#x000a0;h and SI 96&#x000a0;h), respectively. Finally, 15 metabolites were found to be significant. Both the PCA and heatmap indicated reliable differentiation of the samples either by (in)compatible pollination or sampling time after pollination (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>PCA illustration of components differing between incompatible and compatible pollinations and among time intervals (0, 3, 24 and 96&#x000a0;h) after self-pollination. Sampling time (F1) explains most of the total variance</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Heatmap illustration of components differing between incompatible and compatible pollinations and among time intervals (0, 3, 24 and 96&#x000a0;h) after self-pollination. The higher is the intensity of the compound, the darker is its colour</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par22">For the PCA, no computed variables were used, all variables measured the construct in the same direction, appropriate correlations were&#x000a0;present in the dataset and the Kaiser&#x02013;Meyer&#x02013;Olkin measure of sampling adequacy proved to be 0.738, which is interpreted as good. The first two factors explain 89.55% of the total variance (F1:62.76%, F2:26.79%).</p><p id="Par23">Main contributors to F1 and F2 are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The cultivars are differentiated along F2 but the sampling time is differentiated along F1. Based on this observation, we concluded that the metabolites having the highest contribution to F2 could be the most responsible for sexual incompatibility reactions. These metabolites were compounds #4, #5 and #7 having neutral masses of 548.3198, 204.0871 and 315.2773&#x000a0;Da at t<sub>R</sub> 10.07, 0.45 and 9.53&#x000a0;min, respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Squared cosine values of the individual compounds to the principal components in PCA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Compound number</th><th align="left">Contribution to F1</th><th align="left">Contribution to F2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"># 1</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.595</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.346</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 2</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.935</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.045</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 3</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.876</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.063</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 4</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.803</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 5</td><td char="." align="char">0.061</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.785</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 6</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.833</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.131</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 7</td><td char="." align="char">0.373</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.594</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 8</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.957</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 9</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.734</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 10</td><td char="." align="char">0.400</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.542</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 11</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.518</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.363</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 12</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.886</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.081</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 13</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.947</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.025</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 14</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.881</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.099</td></tr><tr><td align="left"># 15</td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.417</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.138</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Bold values indicate the highest cosine values of the actual compound</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Metabolite identification strategy</title><p id="Par24">Showing the highest contribution, compound #4 was found to be the most differentiating compound and the most intensive one in the SI species in positive ion mode (also found in negative ion mode as a differentiating metabolite). During the examination of MS spectra at t<sub>R</sub> 10.07&#x000a0;min&#x000a0;(Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a), several in-source fragments (m/z 217.1949, 253.2166, 285.2429) and adducts ([M&#x02009;+&#x02009;Na]<sup>+</sup> at <italic>m/z</italic> 571.3091 and [M&#x02009;+&#x02009;K]<sup>+</sup> at <italic>m/z</italic> 587.2829) of compound #4 were observed. Perfect similarity of the EICs of in-source fragments indicated their shared origin which was further enhanced by their occurrence in MS<sup>2</sup> spectra of the precursor <italic>m/z</italic> 549.3271 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, c). Based on these observations, <italic>m/z</italic> 549.3269 (average value) was proved to be the protonated form of compound #4. As a result of molecular formula generation (MFG), 18 molecular formulae were found to be potential candidates (nitrogen rule and RDBE were considered, see Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Occurrence of the common mass signals in the full scan spectrum (<bold>a</bold>) and MS<sup>2</sup> spectrum at t<sub>R</sub> 10.07&#x000a0;min of <italic>m/z</italic> 549.3271 (<bold>b</bold>) proves the presence of in-source fragments (<bold>c</bold>). Mass values highlighted in bold indicate common fragments. This observation enabled to determine m/z 549.3271 to be the [M&#x02009;+&#x02009;H]<sup>+</sup> form of compound #4</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Possible molecular formulae of compound #4</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Molecular formula [M&#x02009;+&#x02009;H]<sup>+</sup></th><th align="left">Theoretical <italic>m/z</italic> value</th><th align="left">&#x00394; ppm</th><th align="left">MFG score</th><th align="left">RDBE value<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">C<sub>27</sub>H<sub>49</sub>O<sub>11</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3269</td><td char="." align="char">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">99.14</td><td char="." align="char">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>22</sub>H<sub>46</sub>N<sub>8</sub>O<sub>6</sub>P</td><td char="." align="char">549.3272</td><td char="." align="char">0.9</td><td char="." align="char">98.22</td><td char="." align="char">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>21</sub>H<sub>50</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O<sub>10</sub>P</td><td char="." align="char">549.3259</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">96.81</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>41</sub>N<sub>10</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3256</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td><td char="." align="char">95.88</td><td char="." align="char">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>53</sub>N<sub>6</sub>P<sub>4</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3277</td><td char="." align="char">1.9</td><td char="." align="char">95.54</td><td char="." align="char">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>25</sub>H<sub>37</sub>N<sub>14</sub>O</td><td char="." align="char">549.3269</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td><td char="." align="char">95.35</td><td char="." align="char">15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>51</sub>N<sub>6</sub>O<sub>2</sub>P<sub>2</sub>S</td><td char="." align="char">549.3264</td><td char="." align="char">1.1</td><td char="." align="char">94.99</td><td char="." align="char">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>31</sub>H<sub>51</sub>O<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3257</td><td char="." align="char">1.4</td><td char="." align="char">93.66</td><td char="." align="char">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>19</sub>H<sub>38</sub>N<sub>18</sub>P</td><td char="." align="char">549.3259</td><td char="." align="char">2.0</td><td char="." align="char">93.36</td><td char="." align="char">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>43</sub>N<sub>16</sub>OP<sub>2</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3275</td><td char="." align="char">1.0</td><td char="." align="char">93.20</td><td char="." align="char">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>28</sub>H<sub>45</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O<sub>7</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3283</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td char="." align="char">92.43</td><td char="." align="char">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>25</sub>H<sub>52</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O<sub>3</sub>P<sub>3</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3247</td><td char="." align="char">3.5</td><td char="." align="char">92.05</td><td char="." align="char">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>23</sub>H<sub>42</sub>N<sub>12</sub>O<sub>2</sub>P</td><td char="." align="char">549.3286</td><td char="." align="char">3.3</td><td char="." align="char">91.97</td><td char="." align="char">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>30</sub>H<sub>50</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>PS</td><td char="." align="char">549.3274</td><td char="." align="char">1.1</td><td char="." align="char">91.89</td><td char="." align="char">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>20</sub>H<sub>49</sub>N<sub>6</sub>O<sub>9</sub>S</td><td char="." align="char">549.3276</td><td char="." align="char">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">91.68</td><td char="." align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>32</sub>H<sub>46</sub>N<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3271</td><td char="." align="char">0.9</td><td char="." align="char">90.60</td><td char="." align="char">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>41</sub>N<sub>16</sub>O<sub>3</sub>S</td><td char="." align="char">549.3263</td><td char="." align="char">1.8</td><td char="." align="char">89.80</td><td char="." align="char">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C<sub>23</sub>H<sub>45</sub>NO<sub>9</sub></td><td char="." align="char">549.3243</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td><td char="." align="char">89.79</td><td char="." align="char">5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>RDBE values refer to neutral molecular formulae</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par25">In order to filter out the correct one from the list, the molecular formula of the in-source fragment (<italic>m/z</italic> 285.2425) was considered, which was found to be C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>33</sub>O<sub>3</sub> (theoretical <italic>m/z</italic> value: 285.2424, &#x00394;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;ppm, MFG score&#x02009;=&#x02009;99.45). Other candidates for this in-source fragment had far worse parameters. Taking this information into account, molecular formulae for compound #4 having less than 17 carbon atoms were excluded. In a subsequent step the approximate number of carbon atoms were determined based on the (A&#x02009;+&#x02009;1)/A ratio (28.6%) and a value of 26.48 was gained (28.60/1.08). This showed that the right molecular formula must contain 25&#x02013;28 carbon atoms.</p><p id="Par26">From the fragments, three neutral losses of H<sub>2</sub>O and one of &#x02013;CH<sub>2</sub> could be clearly observed indicating the presence of three &#x02013;OH and a methyl or &#x02013;<italic>O</italic>-methyl groups on the C<sub>17</sub> aliphatic chain. This observation provided information about the presence of at least four oxygen atoms (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), consequently the hits having less oxygen could also be excluded. Finally, from the two remaining formulae C<sub>28</sub>H<sub>45</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O<sub>7</sub> was also filtered out based on the substantially worse values of all listed parameters compared to those of C<sub>27</sub>H<sub>49</sub>O<sub>11</sub> ([M&#x02009;+&#x02009;H]<sup>+</sup>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>In-source fragments of compound #4</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Fragment number</th><th align="left"><italic>m/z</italic> value</th><th align="left">Molecular formula, (M&#x02009;+&#x02009;H)<sup>+</sup></th><th align="left">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char">531.31591</td><td align="left">C<sub>27</sub>H<sub>47</sub>O<sub>10</sub></td><td align="left">(M&#x02009;+&#x02009;H)<sup>+</sup>&#x02013;H<sub>2</sub>O</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char">285.2429</td><td align="left">C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>33</sub>O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td char="." align="char">267.2320</td><td align="left">C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>31</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left">&#x02013;H<sub>2</sub>O</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char">253.2166</td><td align="left">C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>29</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td char="." align="char">235.2075</td><td align="left">C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>27</sub>O</td><td align="left">&#x02013;H<sub>2</sub>O</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td char="." align="char">217.1949</td><td align="left">C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>25</sub></td><td align="left">&#x02013;H<sub>2</sub>O</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par27">Three hits based on this latter&#x000a0;formula were found in the DNP, 27 in SciFinder and four in the ChemSpider databases, respectively. Based on the previously mentioned observations, a compound named peloruside A was supposed to be the most probable candidate, showing ten isomers from the list of 27 hits in SciFinder database. Additional information was also gained that further enhanced the probability of compound #4 being peloruside A. Namely, when examining another significant and abundant differentiating metabolite (compound #1) its molecular formula was found to be C<sub>26</sub>H<sub>46</sub>O<sub>11</sub>, which could correspond to peloruside B in DNP, a natural congener of peloruside A, differing in one methyl group (see Electronic supplementary material Fig. S2). These entities were found to be highly up-regulated in case of SI pollination, showing an increasing intensity over time.</p><p id="Par29">Standard solutions&#x000a0;of peloruside A (both natural and synthetic) were injected and two isomers of peloruside A were observed at 7.43 and 7.70&#x000a0;min both showing signals at <italic>m/z</italic> 571.3091, <italic>m/z</italic> 587.2828, <italic>m/z</italic> 1119.6275 and <italic>m/z</italic> 1135.6026 corresponding to its M&#x02009;+&#x02009;Na<sup>+</sup>, M&#x02009;+&#x02009;K<sup>+</sup>, 2&#x000a0;M&#x02009;+&#x02009;Na<sup>+</sup> and 2&#x000a0;M&#x02009;+&#x02009;K<sup>+</sup> forms, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Full scan spectrum at t<sub>R</sub> 7.70&#x000a0;min corresponding to peloruside A (<bold>a</bold>). In the lack of its protonated form, the sodium, potassium adducts and its dimer are the most abundant. EICs confirm that&#x000a0;the coeluting molecules are indeed the in-source fragments of peloruside A (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par30">However, in a subsequent step when the SI 96&#x000a0;h samples were spiked with solutions containing 2 and 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL peloruside A, increases in signal intensities in the spiked samples were also observed at 7.43 and 7.70&#x000a0;min, which confirmed that compound #4 was not peloruside A. MS<sup>2</sup> experiments were performed where the sodium adduct was subjected to CID fragmentation (in the absence of the protonated form). MS<sup>2</sup> spectra and chromatograms can be found in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>EICs of <italic>m/z</italic> 571.3091 in the spiked and non-spiked samples (<bold>a</bold>) show increasing signal intensity at t<sub>R</sub> 7.43 and 7.70&#x000a0;min but not at the expected t<sub>R</sub> 10.07&#x000a0;min. Differences in the MS<sup>2</sup> spectra of peloruside A (<bold>b</bold>) and compound #4 (<bold>c</bold>) of their Na adducts at <italic>m/z</italic> 571.3091 indicate the mismatch of the two molecules</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par31">Based on the observations made, it can be assumed that compound #4 is not peloruside A, although based on its accurate mass, molecular formula, the dominant sodium adduct and its known&#x000a0;microtubule stabilizing effect, it seemed to be a highly likely candidate. However, considering all of these observations, it could be putatively assumed that both compounds #1 and #4 belong also to the compound class of polyketide-based macrolides, which may have similar effects to peloruside congeners. Additional full scan and MS<sup>2</sup> spectra of peloruside A and compounds #1 and #4 can be found in the Electronic supplementary material (Fig. S1&#x02013;S4).</p><p id="Par32">Having the second highest squared cosines value in F2, compound #5 should be also examined, but as it eluted in the void volume of the chromatographic system and showed low abundance, no attempts for identification were made.</p><p id="Par33">The third highest squared cosines value of F2 is owned by compound #7 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The molecular formula was found to be C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>37</sub>NO<sub>3</sub> (theoretical M&#x02009;+&#x02009;H<sup>+</sup>
<italic>m/z</italic> 316.28462, &#x00394;ppm&#x02009;=&#x02009;-0.38, t<sub>R</sub> 9.53&#x000a0;min) and was searched against databases, taking into account the high degree of CH saturation and that negative mode data were not abundant for this compound. LIPID MAPS&#x000a0;provided three possible hits within the class of&#x000a0;sphingoid bases (that is, non-phosphorylated plant sphingolipids: 4-hydroxy-8cis-sphingenine, dehydrophytosphingosine and 6-hydroxysphingosine), which is supported by the fact that long-chain base type sphingolipids are ionized well in ESI positive mode (Colsch et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2004</xref>). MetFrag (using structures from PubChem) revealed hits with very similar structures related to basic sphingoid species, dehydrophytosphingosine and 6-hydroxysphingosine. Among these latter two compounds, none of the available experimental fragmentation patterns match that of compound #7, according to Tsugawa et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2019</xref>) and Yadav et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2003</xref>), respectively.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>LC-ESI-QTOF-MS full scan spectrum of the <italic>m/z</italic> 316.2845 compound from the SC96 sample, recorded at t<sub>R</sub> 9.53&#x000a0;min (<bold>a</bold>), with its extracted ion chromatogram (<bold>b</bold>) and MS<sup>2</sup> spectrum (<bold>c</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">Altogether, compound #7 might be a member of the hydroxy sphingosine family due to the determined molecular formula, relatively high retention time, ESI+&#x02009;ionization behavior and correspondence with similar database hits. Although, as no standard is commercially available for 4-hydroxy-8cis-sphingenine, it is not possible to confirm the identity of this compound without new experimental MS/MS results for the sum formula apart from what is available for dehydrophytosphingosine and 6-hydroxysphingosine.</p><p id="Par35">Other differentiating compounds were not subjected to further MS<sup>2</sup> experiments mostly because of their low abundance that may cause inaccuracy of <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> values&#x000a0;and the isotopic patterns leading to ambiguous molecular formulae. It is&#x000a0;noted that Lipid Annotator software could not support or invalidate the proposed putative identification of the compounds #1, #4 and #7 as the MS/MS fragmentation results were not corresponding to any lipid species contained in the extensive LipidBlast database also used by this software package.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par36">The self-incompatibility reaction in pollen tubes of <italic>Prunus</italic> fruit trees is mediated by the specific recognition between pollen SFBs and pistil <italic>S</italic>-RNases that enter the pollen tube (Matsumoto and Tao <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2019</xref>; Sonneveld et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2005</xref>). In incompatible pollen tubes, RNA degradation may result in the cessation of protein biosynthesis, but far less is known about the downstream physiological reactions leading to the growth arrest of incompatible pollen tubes. Compound identification is a major drawback of LC&#x02013;MS based metabolic fingerprinting experiments, because the number of available metabolites in the recent databases is still limited. Although the unambiguous identification of compounds #1 and #4 was not possible due to the limited availability of specific standard compounds, our study revealed that peloruside-like compounds predominantly accumulate in self-pollinated pistils of the SI apricot cultivar &#x02018;Cegl&#x000e9;di &#x000f3;ri&#x000e1;s&#x02019; (<italic>S</italic><sub>8</sub><italic>S</italic><sub>9</sub>) and their accumulation increases throughout the first 96&#x000a0;h of pollen tube growth. In addition, such compounds were not detected (or had significantly lower abundance) in &#x02018;Cegl&#x000e9;di &#x000f3;ri&#x000e1;s&#x02019; pistils without pollination.</p><p id="Par37">Peloruside A, a secondary metabolite of a New Zealand marine sponge is known for having microtubule-stabilizing effects through binding to the tubulin dimers (Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2010</xref>). In the <italic>Papaver</italic>-type GSI system, the massive depolymerisation of actin microfilaments upon SI stimulus is evident, which then rapidly triggers depolymerisation of microtubules (Poulter et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2008</xref>). Interestingly, proteomic studies revealed that several actins were detected to accumulate in apricot pistils only after incompatible pollination (Feng et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2009</xref>). In addition, binding of the reduced <italic>S</italic>-RNase to actins in <italic>P. avium</italic> pollen tubes was shown by yeast&#x000a0;two-hybrid analysis and hence <italic>S</italic>-RNases may disrupt actin dynamics (Matsumoto and Tao <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2012</xref>). Apple <italic>S</italic>&#x02010;RNases, by interacting with an actin-binding protein, were also found to disrupt normal F-actin circulation and reduce the growth of self-pollen tubes (Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2018</xref>). If a link between microfilament and microtubule degradation is presumed in <italic>Prunus</italic> similarly to the <italic>Papaver</italic> GSI response, a strategy to protect microtubules with specific compounds like pelorusides seems indispensable for maintaining pollen tube activity since it was also shown that disintegrated microtubules do not reorganise later (Poulter et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2008</xref>).</p><p id="Par38">However, another equally plausible mechanism for peloruside-like compounds in self-incompatibility might be a microtubule-targeted growth arrest. The accumulation of an agent with putative microtubule-stabilizing effects may induce cell cycle arrest, apoptosis (Hood et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2002</xref>), accelerated senescence (Chan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2017</xref>), or the suppression of microtubule dynamics (Chan et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2011</xref>; Huzil et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2008</xref>). In addition, the uneven distribution of organelles in pollen tubes that is required for tip growth is likely a consequence of mechanisms including the regulation of myosin activity, the local fine&#x02010;scale organization of actin, and the dynamics of microtubules (Cai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2015</xref>).</p><p id="Par39">Regardless of the fact whether peloruside congeners are accumulating in response to a stress effect induced by self-incompatibility and help maintain the intact cytoskeleton that is essential for pollen germination and tip growth (Bove et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2008</xref>; Taylor and Hepler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1997</xref>) or they form a part of the degradatory mechanisms leading to pollen tube growth arrest, their exclusive occurrence in self-incompatible pollen tubes might be of crucial importance. Since it was previously determined that the pollen tube growth of incompatible apricot pollen tubes is arrested in the lower quarter of the pistils to prevent fertilization (Kodad et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2013</xref>), this phenomenon might be coupled with the microtubule stabilizing effects of peloruside A and its congeners. Several peloruside congeners and analogues were shown to have similar bioactivity to peloruside A (Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2010</xref>) and hence compounds #1 and #4 that are accumulating in incompatible pollen tubes may be associated with similar physiological consequences. The metabolome analysis of pistils after incompatible and compatible pollination may shed light on the less known aspects of pollen tube growth and downstream reactions of the self/non-self-recognition in <italic>Prunus</italic> GSI system.</p><p id="Par40">Concerning compound #7, it had been present in the pistils of both SC and SI cultivars before pollination. However, their quantities changed in a strikingly different way after self-compatible and self-incompatible pollinations. Compared to its practically unchanged levels in self-pollinated pistils of the SC cultivar &#x02018;Pann&#x000f3;nia&#x02019;, the quantity of #7 followed a gradually decreasing trend in the pistils of self-pollinated SI plants (&#x02018;Cegl&#x000e9;di &#x000f3;ri&#x000e1;s&#x02019;). This compound was proposed to be a plant sphingolipid, a member of the hydroxy sphingosine family. Sphingosine compounds were shown to take part in signalling pathways (Luttgeharm et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2016</xref>) and the presence of such compounds was also confirmed in <italic>Prunus</italic>, i.e., almond kernels (Rubino et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2020</xref>).</p><p id="Par41">The biosynthesis of plant sphingosine compounds includes the transportation of ceramide to Golgi apparatus, where ceramidases hydrolyse them&#x000a0;to yield sphingosine and fatty acid. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, the <italic>TurgOr regulation Defect 1</italic> (<italic>TOD1</italic>) gene was shown to encode a Golgi-localized protein with ceramidase activity, which was preferentially expressed in pollen tubes. In addition, loss-of-function mutation of <italic>TOD1</italic> resulted in pollen tubes having higher than normal turgor and showing growth retardation (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2015</xref>). Since pollen tube growth of mutant plants could be restored by the application of sphingosine and sphingosine-1-phosphate, it confirms that sphingolipids in pollen tubes are crucial for the maintenance of turgor pressure and tip growth. <italic>S</italic>-RNase cytotoxicity by stopping protein biosynthesis may have a very similar physiological consequence as the loss of <italic>TOD1</italic> gene function, which is expected to contribute to the growth arrest of incompatible pollen tubes. However, the considerably lower quantity of such compounds in samples containing both pollen tubes and pistil tissues requires further investigation. The physiological basis of growth arrest in incompatible pollen tubes is well known (McClure et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1990</xref>), but a detailed mechanism leading to this phenotype is still to be elucidated. A great number (1357) of genes were shown to be differentially expressed after self-compatible and incompatible pollination in almond (G&#x000f3;mez et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2019</xref>), including the increased expression of an ATP-binding cassette (ABC) transporter G family protein coding gene in incompatible pollination. ABCG transporters are presumed to regulate lipid constituents in pistil tissues (Chang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2016</xref>) and hence changes in lipids may be equally important elements or consequences of incompatibility reactions.</p><p id="Par42">Further experiments including compound purification followed by NMR spectroscopy based identification are required for the unambiguous structural identification of such compounds and the verification of their role in sexual incompatibility-induced pollen tube arrest. It is, however, difficult not to overestimate the labour and plant biomass requirements that can provide sufficient and adequately pure analyte from such a small plant organ from a non-typical model organism (fruit tree) for the ultimate structural identification. An indirect approach, that is, systematically knocking out genes and checking for the disappearance of a metabolite can only be addressed in model plants with short life cycles (Blomstedt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2016</xref>). On the other hand, our study revealed for the first time with an LC&#x02013;MS based metabolomic approach that such&#x000a0;putative metabolites may significantly contribute to the sexual compatibility reactions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="11103_2020_1098_MOESM1_ESM.pptx"><caption><p>Electronic supplementary material 1 (PPTX 126&#x000a0;kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>The original version of this article was revised: Figure 3 was incorrect (the panels for SC and SI cultivars were transposed)</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Change history</bold></p><p>2/18/2021</p><p>A Correction to this paper has been published: 10.1007/s11103-020-01110-y</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was partially funded by the National Research, Development and Innovation Office (OTKA) K_128874 project (A. Heged&#x00171;s). The authors greatly acknowledge the help of Dr. Dan Sackett (Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, Bethesda, USA) and Dr. Peter Northcote (Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand) for providing the peloruside A standard material.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Experiments were designed by JH and AH. Sample collection and sample preparation were conducted by JH and ON. LC&#x02013;MS analyses were designed and carried out by JL and MD. LC&#x02013;MS data evaluation was conducted by JL, TC and SH. Statistical data evaluation was carried out by AG. The manuscript was written by JL and MD and edited by AH and MD. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by Szent Istv&#x000e1;n University.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>RRL</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrell</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rees</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A non-targeted metabolomics approach to quantifying differences in root storage between fast- and slow-growing plants</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2012</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22924406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22924406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blomstedt</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjarnholt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamill</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f8;ller</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gleadow</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic consequences of knocking out UGT85B1, the gene encoding the glucosyltransferase required for synthesis of dhurrin in <italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic> (L. Moench)</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>386</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26493517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26493517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bove</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaillancourt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroeger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hepler</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiseman</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Geitmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnitude and direction of vesicle dynamics in growing pollen tubes using spatiotemporal image correlation spectroscopy and fluorescence recovery after photobleaching</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>1646</fpage><lpage>1658</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18508956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18508956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cachi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;nsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and mapping of non-<italic>S</italic> gametophytic self-compatibility in sweet cherry (<italic>Prunus avium</italic> L.)</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1847</fpage><lpage>1856</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21127024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21127024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrotta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cresti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organelle trafficking, the cytoskeleton, and pollen tube growth</article-title><source>J Integr Plant Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25263392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25263392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreae</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Northcote</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peloruside A inhibits microtubule dynamics in a breast cancer cell line MCF7</article-title><source>Invest New Drug</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>626</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilfillan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Templeton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Northcote</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of accelerated senescence by the microtubule-stabilizing agent peloruside A</article-title><source>Invest New Drug</source><year>2017</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>706</fpage><lpage>717</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An ABC transporter, OsABCG26, is required for anther cuticle and pollen exine formation and pollen-pistil interactions in rice</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>253</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27968990?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27968990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous qualitative assessment and quantitative analysis of flavonoids in various tissues of lotus (<italic>Nelumbo nucifera</italic>) using high performance liquid chromatography coupled with triple quad mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Anal Chim Acta</source><year>2012</year><volume>724</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22483220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22483220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>DQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis alkaline ceramidase TOD1 is a key turgor pressure regulator in plant cells</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Popa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Portoukalian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabet</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the ceramide moieties of sphingoglycolipids from mouse brain by ESI-MS/MS: identification of ceramides containing sphingadienine</article-title><source>J Lipid Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14595000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14595000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cubells-Baeza</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of the ligand of Pru p 3, a peach LTP</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28299506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28299506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection and transcript expression of S-RNase gene associated with self-incompatibility in apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Mol Biol Rep</source><year>2006</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16850191?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16850191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ci</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary molecular features of self-incompatible and self-compatible F1 seedling from apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic> L.) Katy x Xinshiji</article-title><source>Mol Biol Rep</source><year>2009</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17987401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17987401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldraij</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compartmentalization of <italic>S</italic>-RNase and HT-B degradation in self-incompatible <italic>Nicotiana</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>439</volume><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16482149?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16482149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicenta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of pollen-pistil interactions in almond (<italic>Prunus dulcis</italic>) identifies candidate genes for components of gametophytic self-incompatibility</article-title><source>Tree Genet Genomes</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>e53</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Good-Avila</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mena-Ali</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Franklin-Tong</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and environmental causes and evolutionary consequences of variations in self-fertility in self incompatible species</article-title><source>Self-incompatibility in flowering plants</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hal&#x000e1;sz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedryc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heged&#x00171;s</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin and dissemination of the pollen-part mutated <italic>S</italic><sub>C</sub>-haplotype which confers self-compatibility in apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic>)</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2007</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17850250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17850250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hal&#x000e1;sz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodad</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Heged&#x00171;s</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a recently active <italic>Prunus</italic>-specific non-autonomous Mutator element with considerable genome shaping force</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2014</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24813246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24813246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical applications of metabolomics in plant biology</article-title><source>Annu Plant Rev Online</source><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-61779-594-7_1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanhineva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogachev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintz-Oron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Venger</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000e4;renlampi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-targeted analysis of spatial metabolite composition in strawberry (<italic>Fragaria &#x000d7; ananassa</italic>) flowers</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>2463</fpage><lpage>2481</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18774147?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18774147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouw&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Northcote</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakefield</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peloruside A, a novel antimitotic agent with paclitaxel-like microtubule-stabilizing activity</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>3356</fpage><lpage>3360</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12067973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12067973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huzil</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A unique mode of microtubule stabilization induced by Peloruside A</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>1016</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18405918?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18405918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular and genetic bases of <italic>S</italic>-RNase-based self-incompatibility</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>S72</fpage><lpage>S83</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15010517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15010517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kodad</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hal&#x000e1;sz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heged&#x00171;s</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Messaoudi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedryc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Socias</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-(in)compatibility and fruit set in 19 local Moroccan apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic> L.) genotypes</article-title><source>J Hortic Sci Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>461</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luttgeharm</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimberlin</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li-Beisson</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant sphingolipid metabolism and function</article-title><source>Lipids in plant and algae development. Subcellular biochemistry</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>286</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandrone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compatible and incompatible pollen-styles interaction in <italic>Pyrus communis</italic> L. show different transglutaminase features, polyamine pattern and metabolomics profiles</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e741</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicenta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anomalous embryo sac development and fruit abortion caused by inbreeding depression in almond (<italic>Prunus dulcis</italic>)</article-title><source>Sci Hortic-Amsterdam</source><year>2012</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of pollen-expressed actin as a candidate protein interacting with <italic>S</italic>-RNase in <italic>Prunus avium</italic> L</article-title><source>J Jpn Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of a wide-range of <italic>S</italic>-RNases by <italic>S</italic> locus F-box like 2, a general-inhibitor candidate in the <italic>Prunus</italic>-specific <italic>S</italic>-RNase-based self-incompatibility system</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27071402?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27071402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of <italic>S</italic>-RNases by an <italic>S</italic> locus F-box like protein and an S haplotype-specific F-box like protein in the <italic>Prunus</italic>-specific self-incompatibility system</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30937702?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30937702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New views of <italic>S</italic>-RNase-based self-incompatibility</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17027324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17027324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-incompatibility in <italic>Nicotiana alata</italic> involves degradation of pollen rRNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>760</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Northcote</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microtubule-stabilizing drugs from marine sponges: focus on Peloruside A and Zampanolide</article-title><source>Mar Drugs</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20479967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20479967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry-based metabolome database for tomato</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1205</fpage><lpage>1218</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16896233?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16896233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Sanz</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuriaga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Badenes</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-(in)compatibility in apricot germplasm is controlled by two major loci, S and M</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>e82</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poulter</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vatovec</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin-Tong</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microtubules are a target for self-incompatibility signaling in <italic>Papaver</italic> pollen</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1367</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18192439?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18192439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sulfinylated azadecalins act as functional mimics of a pollen germination stimulant in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> pistils</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2011</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>800</fpage><lpage>815</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21801250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21801250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Developing a drug-like natural product library</article-title><source>J Nat Prod</source><year>2008</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18257534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18257534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodrigues-Neto</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolic fingerprinting analysis of oil palm reveals a set of differentially expressed metabolites in fatal yellowing symptomatic and non-symptomatic plants</article-title><source>Metabolomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>e142</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubino</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cas</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bignotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghidoni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iriti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paroni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery of unexpected sphingolipids in almonds and pistachios with an innovative use of triple quadrupole tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>110</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonneveld</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobutt</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of pollen-S function in two self-compatible selections of <italic>Prunus avium</italic> is associated with deletion/mutation of an <italic>S haplotype-specific F-box</italic> gene</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15598801?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15598801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hepler</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pollen germination and tube growth</article-title><source>Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>491</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15012271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsugawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A cheminformatics approach to characterize metabolomes in stable-isotope-labeled organisms</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30923379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weckwerth</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Loureiro</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential metabolic networks unravel the effects of silent plant phenotypes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>7809</fpage><lpage>7814</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15136733?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15136733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ressom</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolite identification and quantitation in LC-MS/MS-based metabolomics</article-title><source>TrAC-Trend Anal Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Geetha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Raju</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnaneshwar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The first total synthesis of the 6-hydroxy-4E-sphingenines</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>2983</fpage><lpage>2985</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apple <italic>S-</italic>RNase interacts with an actin-binding protein, <italic>Md</italic>MVG, to reduce pollen tube growth by inhibiting its actin-severing activity at the early stage of self-pollination induction</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2018</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29667261?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29667261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuriaga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Badenes</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical mapping of a pollen modifier locus controlling self-incompatibility in apricot and synteny analysis within the Rosaceae</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22481163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22481163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuriaga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz-Sanz</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gisbert</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Badenes</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An <italic>S</italic>-locus independent pollen factor confers self-compatibility in KatyTM apricot</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e53947</fpage><?supplied-pmid 23342044?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23342044</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>