<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Non-enzymatic glycosylation of proteins is considered as the major cause of diabetic complications. It seems that protein glycosylation can be inhibited effectively by antioxidants. Hence, in one of the studies, biochanin A was selected to determine its antioxidant effects on in vitro insulin, hemoglobin, and albumin glycosylation. The optimal glucose concentration and incubation time were obtained for each protein. Then, the inhibition percentage of protein glycosylation was measured in the presence of three different concentrations (0.5, 5, and 10 µg/mL) of biochanin A by a colorimetric method. The results demonstrated that biochanin A strongly inhibits insulin and hemoglobin glycosylation by inhibiting their glycosylation 100% and 60%, respectively. Biochanin A also inhibited glycosylation of albumin 100%. Therefore, it seems probable that plants containing isoflavonoids may have preventive effects in diabetic complications [
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In an another study, biochanin A showed an antihyperglycemic effect in streptozocin-diabetic rats [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. This statement was correlated and agreed with another study carried out by Azizi et al. [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], who mentioned that biochanin A showed a beneficial effect on the reduction of fasting blood glucose (FBG), body weight, reduction of glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c), lipid profile, and serum enzymes in streptozocin-induced diabetic rats. Furthermore, several studies have also highlighted the potential antidiabetic effect of isoflavonoids, in which they have been reported to be able to regulate postprandial glycemia and inhibit development of glucose intolerance by facilitating insulin response as well as inducing insulin secretion. Vedavanam et al. [
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] mentioned that soya extract containing genistein and daidzein, in particular, acts as an inhibitor of intestinal glucose-uptake and as a preventive agent for glucose-induced lipid peroxidation in vitro. Kwon et al. [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] reported that daidzein is capable of generating insulinotropic action by stimulating glucagon-like peptide 1 secretion in enteroendocrine NCI-H716 cells. This was, however, not in line with the work carried out by Higashi and Ogawara [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], who stated that daidzein inhibits insulin like growth factor 1 mediated signaling in cell cycle progression of Swiss 3T3 cells. This statement, however, was not consistent with Kwon et al. [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], who stated that daidzein could enhance insulin-stimulated glucose uptake in 3T3-L1 adipocytes. Meanwhile, this statement is supported through an in vivo study done by Oh et al. [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], who claimed that daidzein decreased blood glucose levels in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats. Later, Cheong et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] reported that daidzein improved glucose homeostasis in type 2 diabetic mice model, thereby suggesting its role as an antidiabetic agent. Interestingly, a systematic study done by Getek et al. [
 <xref rid="B70-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] further confirmed that leguminous plants particularly containing genistein and daidzein exhibited in vitro and in vivo antidiabetic activities. Hence, they emphasized that such leguminous plants should be employed in the promotion of a healthy lifestyle as a form of functional food and should constitute a permanent dietary element in a balanced diet, especially with type 2 diabetic patients. More recently, Lee et al. [
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-25-05491" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] isolated formononetin from 
 <italic>A. membranaceus</italic> and examined on glucose-stimulated insulin secretion (GSIS) from pancreatic β-cell. It was found to stimulate insulin secretion in INS-1 cells without inducing cytotoxicity. A further evaluation demonstrated that formononetin enhanced the phosphorylation of total insulin receptor substrate-2 (IRS-2), phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K), and Akt, and activated pancreatic and duodenal homeobox-1 (PDX-1) and PPAR-γ, which are associated with β-cell function and insulin secretion. The data suggest that formononetin has the potential to improve insulin secretion in β-cell, representing the first step toward the development of potent antidiabetic drugs.
</p>
