<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0080" class="p">Oil production is the major anthropogenic factor influencing microbial communities in oil reservoirs. This includes drilling, flooding, hot steam and water injections, all of which lead to a high potential of invasion of external microorganisms into the original microbial communities [
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Water injections are necessary in secondary oil production stages to increase reservoir pressure. The amount of injected water depends on the reservoir pressure, well age or water progressing within the reservoir. Oil companies use different types of injection waters consisting of either seawater, fresh water or recycled formation water. Offshore fields are mostly supplied with seawater [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>] whereas in other oil fields groundwater [
 <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>] or surface water [
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] are used. In some reservoirs, injection waters are enriched with chemicals or nutrients in order to manipulate the indigenous microbial community. For instance, nitrate and nitrite injections are used to suppress reservoir souring by microbial H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>S production. Oxygen injections can stimulate the aerobic hydrocarbon metabolism and mobilize the oil within the well by lowering the interfacial tension between oil and water phase through biosurfactant producing microbes or changes in the oil matrix [
 <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Alternatively, fermentative bacteria and carbohydrate injection lead to the generation of acids, gases and solvents, which increases oil output, so called enhanced oil recovery (EOR) [
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Water injections decrease the temperature of the oil field and build up a temperature gradient. The injection volume also affects the chemical composition of the production water, as it decreases the concentrations of magnesium, potassium, nitrate, nitrite and sulfate [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Production water is a byproduct of oil production and has been transported through the oil phase and pumped to the surface; it can be a mixture of formation and injection water and can contain particles and soluble compounds from oil [
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>] (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). Two comparative studies have demonstrated higher concentrations of ammonium and fatty acids in formation water compared to production water [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Produced fluids with less than 10% injection water content did not have significant influence on microbial composition and metabolic potential. In contrast, fluids with a higher injection water cut indicated that the community composition and metabolic potential can be altered by the water composition. A close correlation was calculated between the relative abundance of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Flexistipes</italic>, family 
 <italic class="italic">Deferribacteres</italic> and the proportion of injected seawater and the concentrations of magnesium, potassium, nitrate, nitrite, and sulfate. 
 <italic class="italic">Epsilonproteobacteria</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Gammaproteobacteria</italic> were isolated in greater abundance from sample wells with the highest water injection rate [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Several studies have reported a relationship between the chemical composition of the oil reservoirs and the operational taxonomic units (OTUs) found therein. In Algerian oil reservoirs, production waters revealed significant correlations between the relative abundance of bacterial OTUs or phyla and Cl
 <sup class="sup">−</sup> and K
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> ions. However, it is not clear if this correlation is causative. It may well be that the real causes for microbial community differences are for example differences in water content and structure of the reservoir and that the ion composition is just an indication of geological differences. Significant differences between microbial community composition of production and injection waters were observed for waters from Algerian oilfields and the offshore Halfdan oil field in the Danish North Sea. The Algerian oilfield injection water was richer in cells and dominated by bacteria, whereas the production water contained ten times fewer cells and was dominated by Archaea [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. This difference indicates a trivial correlation between oil degradation processes in the methanogenesis-dominated reservoir and the microbial community composition in the production water.
</p>
