<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Alternative methods have been used to hydrolyze agar, such as enzymatic, physical and chemical degradation. Enzymatic hydrolysis, which can be performed by agarases [
 <xref rid="B77-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>], show disadvantages such as the low activity, low stability and productivity, which limit their wide application in industry. However, chemical degradation, especially acid hydrolysis, is available for industrial preparation because of its simplicity, rapidity, low cost and high yield [
 <xref rid="B77-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. Different bacteria have been used as a source of agarolytic enzymes, i.e., 
 <italic class="italic">Flammeovirga pacifica</italic> [
 <xref rid="B83-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">Streptomyces coelicolor</italic> [
 <xref rid="B45-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] or 
 <italic class="italic">Agarivorans</italic> sp. JA-1 [
 <xref rid="B84-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. Agar oligosaccharides can be produced by hydrolysis using chemicals or agarolytic enzymes. Since agarose comprises alternating 
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-AHG and 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-galactose units linked by α-1,3- and β-1,4-glycosidic bonds, two types of agarases exist: α-agarases cleave the α-1,3 linkages of agarose endolytically and produce agaro-oligosaccharides AOSs as the reaction products. Neoagarooligosaccharides are prepared from agar by β-agarase hydrolysis, by cleaving the β-1,4-glycosidic linkages of agarose endolytically or exolytically, and also releases neoagarooligosaccharides with neoagarobiose or neogarobiose alone, respectively. Agaro-oligosaccharides obtained by enzymatic degradation exhibited high solubility percentages, water and oil absorption capacities, as well as considerable 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and 2,2′-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulphonic acid (ABTS
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>) radical scavenging and ferric reducing antioxidant activities, depending on the degree hydrolysis [
 <xref rid="B94-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>]. Kazłowski et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>] prepared neoagaro-oligosaccharides by β-agarase digestion and agaro-oligosaccharides by HCl hydrolysis from agarose and observed that the enzymatically prepared oligosaccharides usually show a low DP and a broad range of bioactivities, whereas those from acid hydrolysis contain only oligosaccharides with odd numbers of sugar unit [
 <xref rid="B83-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>].
</p>
