<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, functional group identity determined biotic resistance to invasion by 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic>, but the species identity effect was redundant within each functional group. The most resistant functional group was FG1 (fast‐growing annuals), which was a different functional group from 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> (FG2). Thus, this result did not support the role of limiting similarity in biotic resistance. However, a significant role of functional groups in biotic resistance was found, with some exceptions (Von Holle &amp; Simberloff, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0116" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>), in other studies that tested functional groups based on various plant traits such as life longevity, growth form, root structure, plant height, or phytosynthetic pathways (Byun et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Prieur‐Richard, Lavorel, Dos Santos, &amp; Grigulis, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">2002b</xref>; Prieur‐Richard, Lavorel, Linhart, &amp; Dos Santos, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0090" ref-type="ref">2002a</xref>; Sheley &amp; James, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Wang, Ge, Zhang, Bai, &amp; Du, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0117" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The functional group that most resisted invasion was not always consistent among those studies. In some cases, the functional group most similar to the invasive plant offers the most resistance (Bakker &amp; Wilson, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Dukes, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Fargione, Brown, &amp; Tilman, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Hooper &amp; Dukes, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Mwangi et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Pokorny et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0087" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Turnbull et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>), indicating limiting similarity, whereas, in other cases, different functional groups offer the most resistance to invasion (Byun et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Lulow, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Sheley &amp; James, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), suggesting fitness inequality as one of the key mechanisms of resistance. Invasion success may depend on both fitness and niche differences with resident species (MacDougall et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). We demonstrated the important role of a pre‐emptive effect (first come, first served) in the control of invasive plants which is consistent with another study (Stuble &amp; Souza, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0106" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), and early emergence increased components of plant fitness, such as seedling growth, in a controlled experiment (Verd &amp; Traveset, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>).
</p>
