<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The fatty acid profile was determined only for the 
 <italic class="italic">C. integerrima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. salicifolia</italic> oils as fatty acid methyl esters by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. The methyl esters were prepared using the method described by Morrison and Smith [
 <xref rid="B31-materials-11-02244" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. The separation of the fatty acid esters was performed using QP 5000 Shimadzu (Kyoto, Japan) gas chromatographer with mass spectrometer and autosampler was used, as well as the 1.2 Class-5000. A fused-silica column, coated with the DB-5 stationary phase, was utilized (30 m × 0.2 mm inner diameter, dry film thickness of 0.25 µm, J &amp; W Scientific). The initial oven temperature was 60 °C, which was kept for 5 min; a 2 °C min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> temperature increase was programed until it reached 220 °C; this temperature was kept for 30 min. The injector temperature was 220 °C. Helium was used as a carrier gas with a 1.0 mL min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> flow. The injection volume was 1 µL (1% solution in CH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>Cl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) with a 1:10 split ratio. Column pressure was 100 kPa. Mass detector conditions were the following: source temperature, 240 °C; electron impact mode (EI), 70 eV; scan rate of 1 scan s
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>; and acquisition range, 29–450 u. Components were identified by comparing retention times related to a linear standard made with Supelco
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> 37 Component FAME Mix in dichloromethane (varied concentrations) of an alkane series (C9–C24) and their mass spectra to those from the Wiley 330000 database and the ones reviewed from the literature. In addition, with the percentage of unsaturated fatty acids, we calculated the oxidizability values (Cox) of 
 <italic class="italic">C. integerrima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. salicifolia</italic> oils, applying the formula proposed by Fatemi et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-materials-11-02244" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]:
 <disp-formula id="FD1-materials-11-02244" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">(1)</label>
  <math id="mm1" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">C</mi>
     <mi class="mi">o</mi>
     <mi class="mi">x</mi>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mrow class="mrow">
        <mo class="mo">[</mo>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mn class="mn">1</mn>
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mo class="mo">(</mo>
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mn class="mn">16</mn>
           <mo class="mo">:</mo>
           <mn class="mn">1</mn>
           <mo class="mo">%</mo>
           <mo class="mo">+</mo>
           <mn class="mn">18</mn>
           <mo class="mo">:</mo>
           <mn class="mn">1</mn>
           <mo class="mo">%</mo>
           <mo class="mo">+</mo>
           <mn class="mn">20.1</mn>
           <mo class="mo">%</mo>
          </mrow>
          <mo class="mo">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mo class="mo">+</mo>
         <mn class="mn">10.3</mn>
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mo class="mo">(</mo>
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mn class="mn">18</mn>
           <mo class="mo">:</mo>
           <mn class="mn">2</mn>
           <mo class="mo">%</mo>
           <mo class="mo">+</mo>
           <mn class="mn">20</mn>
           <mo class="mo">:</mo>
           <mn class="mn">2</mn>
           <mo class="mo">%</mo>
          </mrow>
          <mo class="mo">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mo class="mo">+</mo>
         <mn class="mn">21.6</mn>
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mo class="mo">(</mo>
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mn class="mn">18</mn>
           <mo class="mo">:</mo>
           <mn class="mn">3</mn>
           <mo class="mo">%</mo>
          </mrow>
          <mo class="mo">)</mo>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo class="mo">]</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mn class="mn">100</mn>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
