<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The structure of samples (
 <italic class="italic">C. integerrima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. salicifolia</italic> oils and polyols) were analyzed by 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H and
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C NMR, and FTIR spectroscopy, combined with hydroxyl number measurement. 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H and 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C NMR spectra were conducted with a Varian Inova 300 (Varian, Inc., Palo Alto, CA, USA), 300 MHz, using CDCl
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> as a solvent and tetramethylsilane as an internal reference. FTIR spectra were recorded using an Agilent Cary 360 FTIR in the range of 4000 to 650 cm
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> at a resolution of 4 cm
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> with 32 scans on ATR (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA). Two milliliters of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. integerrima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. salicifolia</italic> oil and polyol samples were put directly on the equipment plate without any previous treatment. The hydroxyl number of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. integerrima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. salicifolia</italic> polyols was determined according to ASTM 4274-05 [
 <xref rid="B36-materials-11-02244" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. The viscosity of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. integerrima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. salicifolia</italic> oil and polyol samples were measured by Brookfield viscometer (LVDV-II, Brookfield Engineering Laboratories, Inc., Stoughton, Massachusetts) at 25 ± 0.5 °C. The density of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. integerrima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. salicifolia</italic> oil and polyol samples were measured by means of a pycnometer at 25 ± 0.5 °C. Finally, thermal stability of the oils and polyols were performed in a thermogravimetric analyzer NETZSCH TG 209F1 Iris (NETZSCH Company, Germany) with 10 °C min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> constant heating rate. The heating was from 30 °C to 500 °C in inert atmosphere with a flow rate of 60 mL min
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>.
</p>
