<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic>, derived from two Latin words “cord” and “ceps” representing ‘club’ and ‘head’ respectively, describing it as club fungi. It is an entomopathogenic fungus where extensions of the stroma and fruiting body arise from insect larvae carcasses [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> predominantly lives on the head of larvae of a particular moth species, 
 <italic>Hepialus armoricanus Oberthur</italic> (Lepidoptera). It belongs to the Ascomycetes family and has been a very well-known fungus in Chinese traditional medicine for the last 300 years. 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> is also known as ‘Dong Chong Xia Cao’, which means ‘Worm in winter and grass in summer’ in China [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. According to the previous reports, around 1200 types of entomopathogenic fungi are known, out of which, 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> is considered as one of the largest genus containing approximately 500 species. Several species of 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> have been cultivated for their therapeutic properties such as 
 <italic>Cordyceps sinensis, Cordyceps sobolifera, Cordyceps cicadicola, Cordyceps liangshanesis, Cordyceps ophioglossoides and Cordyceps militaris</italic> [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. On the other hand, keeping in mind the therapeutic value, its major distribution location at approximately 14,000 ft altitude in the Himalayan regions of China, Nepal, Tibet and India makes it very expensive at around USD ($) 12,000 kg
 <sup>−1</sup> [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Moreover, despite the harvesting difficulties and distribution, it is still considered a highly valued mushroom because of its abundant natural bioactive component resources with various potent biological activities and nutraceutical importance [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. For hundreds of years, 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> were used as a folk tonic food, but only in recent times, its potential pharmaceutical as well as nutraceutical application have been explored, which has attracted food scientists globally [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
