<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pancreatic lipase, secreted from the pancreas, is an important enzyme responsible for the digestion of 70% of fats into monoglycerides and free fatty acids. Inhibition of this enzyme helps to reduce fat accumulation in adipose tissues [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-04935" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Alternatively, lipoprotein lipase is an enzyme that catalyzes hydrolysis of triglycerides rich lipoproteins, very low density lipoproteins and chylomicrons resulting in release of nonesterified fatty acids and monoacylglycerol. An imbalance in lipoprotein lipase activity can affect the distribution of triglycerides between adipose tissues and muscles to cause obesity [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-04935" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Therefore, the substances that can reduce the activity of lipases are considered to act as antiobesity agents. Escalation in oxidative stress can cause oxidative damage, which plays a leading role in the pathogenesis of many disorders such as cancer, obesity, diabetes, neurodegenerative diseases and atherosclerosis. Any action that can decrease oxidative stress would be therapeutically valuable. It is imperative to correlate the antioxidant and antiobesity properties of medicinal plants that are generally used in local medicinal systems to counter oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-04935" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Prevention and treatment of obesity is crucial for healthcare systems, whose aim is to decrease the prevalence of obesity, overweight and related complications [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04935" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Obesity can be treated in number of different ways by physicians and other health care professionals including, diet regimes, exercise and pharmacotherapy. Currently used synthetic antiobesity drugs such as sibutramine and orlistat can be categorized into two major classes. Orlistat is synthetic inhibitor of gastrointestinal lipase that restricts the hydrolysis of triglycerides to reduce the subsequent absorption of monoglycerides and free fatty acids in intestine [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-04935" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
