<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We investigated the bacterial and fungal communities in the mangrove community (MC), the 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>–mangrove mixed community (TC), and the 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> community (SC) in Zhangjiangkou National Mangrove Wetland Nature Reserve. In this study, we find that the bacterial community diversity indices in the two soil layers show a trend of SC &gt; MC &gt; TC, which is consistent with previous studies on the 
 <italic>Kandelia candel</italic> rhizospheric bacterial community invaded by 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> [
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Soil pH has been proven to be a key factor in regulating soil microbial communities [
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. On the one hand, the pH value can select species with compatible growth strategies [
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. On the other hand, studies have shown that acidic soils can inhibit SOM decomposition and C mineralization [
 <xref rid="B29-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Our data show that the TC community has the lowest soil bacterial diversity indices and soil pH and the highest MOC content, which indicate that the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> may reduce the soil bacterial community diversity by changing the soil pH value, thereby inhibiting C mineralization. However, only the Chao1, Sobs, and Shannon indices in the 15–30 cm soil layer are significantly higher in the SC community than in the TC community, and other differences are not significant (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The reason for this phenomenon may be that the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> affects the soil bacterial diversity of mangroves more obviously in the rhizosphere. For the fungal community, we find that there is no significant difference in the diversity indices of fungi in the two soil layers, but all the diversity indices in the 15–30 cm soil layer show a trend of TC &gt; MC &gt; SC, which is consistent with the significant trend of soil water content in the 15–30 cm soil layer. Research by Yang et al. has shown that the diversity of soil fungal community decreases with the time sequence of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion and has a significant positive correlation with soil moisture and litter biomass. They have also proved that litter biomass is significantly positively correlated with soil moisture [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], which was consistent with our research. PCoA show that the bacterial communities are clearly separated between the two communities, and no significant differences among the three communities are observed in the fungal community, which indicate that the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> mainly changed the community structure of soil bacteria(
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-microorganisms-09-00138">Tables S6 and S7</xref>).
</p>
