<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Different from the results of the bacterial community, the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> only caused a significant increase in few fungal taxa during the invasion process, and these taxa were at some lower levels (such as family, genus, and species) and classified into the phylum Ascomycota, namely, our results indicate that the response of mangrove soil fungal taxa to 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion mainly concentrated on Ascomycota. Ascomycota is a class of fungi that can participate in critical degradation activities [
 <xref rid="B53-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Additionally, a few taxa of Ascomycota are dominant in the global soil fungal community [
 <xref rid="B54-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Moreover, Ascomycetes have been reported as oligotrophic fungi with the ability to withstand stressful environments (e.g., low nutrient availability and drought stress) [
 <xref rid="B55-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Our previous study also found that the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> caused an increase in the decomposition of mangrove soil organic carbon, which hindered the accumulation of soil organic carbon [
 <xref rid="B10-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The reduction of organic carbon in mangrove soil after 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> invasion may be a large part of the reason for the change of soil microbial community structure. In addition, many taxa with significant changes have been reported as animal, plant, or human pathogens, such as the genus Sporothrix and Phialemonium [
 <xref rid="B58-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-microorganisms-09-00138" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Therefore, the invasion of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic> may alter the physical and chemical properties of soil and the structure of flora and fauna by changing the community structure of soil microorganisms.
</p>
