<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Introduction:</title>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">Ziziphora Clinopodioides</italic> has been used widely for various therapeutic purposes in Iranian folk medicine. The current study aimed to determine interaction of antinociceptive effect of the Essential Oil of 
   <italic class="italic">Ziziphora Clinopodioides</italic> (EOZC) and opioidergic system in male rats using formalin test.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods:</title>
  <p class="p">Sixty-four male Wistar rats were divided into eight groups. The groups 1 to 7 were injected with normal saline, vehicle (Tween-80, 0.5%), 10, 20, 40 mg/kg of the EOZC, morphine (5 mg/kg) and naloxone (2 mg/kg), respectively. Thirty minutes later, the formalin test was performed by intraplantar injection of formalin (50 μL, 2%). In group 8, naloxone (2 mg/kg) was injected 15 min before injection of EOZC (20 mg/kg), followed by formalin at 15 min later. The formalin test was done as time spent for licking and biting of the injected paw. Formalin induced a biphasic pain reaction. The chemical composition of EOZC was identified using Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results:</title>
  <p class="p">EOZC (10, 20, and 40 mg/kg) dose dependently and morphine (5 mg/kg) reduced pain responses in the both phases of pain (P&lt;0.05). Naloxone (2 mg/kg) alone had no effect on the severity of pain (P&gt;0.05) but pretreatment with naloxone inhibited EOZC-induced antinociception activity (P&lt;0.05). Based on the GC-MS results, EOZC comprised 65.22% carvacrol, 19.51% thymol, 4.86% p-cymene and 4.63% γ-terpinene.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion:</title>
  <p class="p">These results demonstrate that EOZC has antinociceptive effect and this effect might mediate via opioidergic pathways.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
