<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The leaves of 
 <italic>Bersama abyssinica</italic> was thoroughly washed with distilled water to remove dirt and dried at room temperature (25–27°C). The plant material was coarsely grounded into powder by the electrical mill. Then, the powdered plant material was macerated separately in methanol for about 72 hrs., then the plant material was filtered via Whatman filter paper. Likewise, fresh methanol was used to re-macerate the marc, and then the filtrate of each successive maceration was concentrated by using a rotary evaporator. Lastly, the semi-dried residue was frozen in the refrigerator and dried using a lyophilizer (Lab freez, China) to entirely confiscate the remaining solvent.
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Solvent fractionation of the leaves extract of 
 <italic>Bersama abyssinica</italic> was carried out using water, ethyl acetate, and chloroform. Briefly, the leaves extract of 
 <italic>Bersama abyssinica</italic> was dissolved in 400 mL of distilled water and this solution was transferred to a separating funnel. An equal volume of chloroform was added to it and was shaken vigorously. The mixture was separated into two layers, and then chloroform was removed. The partition with chloroform was repeated two times. The chloroform layer was combined and subjected to evaporation using a hot air oven set at 40°C to get the chloroform fraction. To the separating funnel containing aqueous layer, 400 mL of ethyl acetate was added. The mixture was separated into two layers, and then the ethyl acetate was separated and the procedure was repeated two times. The ethyl acetate layer was pooled and concentrated using a hot air oven set at 40°C to obtain the ethyl acetate fraction. The remaining aqueous layer was concentrated using a hot air oven set at 40°C and frozen in a refrigerator overnight and then, concentrated in a lyophilizer to remove the water. After drying, the solvent fractions were stored in a desiccator until used for the experiment.
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
</p>
