<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0400">AR or its compounds have certain biological activities on the nervous system, lung, glucose, and lipid metabolism. The pharmacological activity of the AR on the central nervous system has been demonstrated in various animal models with regards to its effects on the general behavior and spontaneous movement, potentiation of hypnotic action of hexobarbital sodium, and anti-electroshock convulsion. 
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Murayama et al. (2014)</xref> indicated that water extract of 
 <italic>A. japonica</italic> showed a stronger inhibitory effect on 1-(2, 5-dimethoxy-4-iodophenyl)-2-aminopropane (DOI)-induced head-twitch response than that of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> corresponding to their major constituents of atractylenolide III and β-eudesmol, and suggested that the major constituents should be active constituents contributing to the antihallucination effects of Byaku- and So-jutsu. Besides, the part B–C ring (butenolide) in ATL III was found to be similar to the structure of serotonin and suggested that the B–C ring may partially play role in antagonistic activity against serotonin receptors. Thus, a rational design of butenolide-related compounds may produce potential lead compounds for new drug development (
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Murayama et al., 2014</xref>). ATL-III presented a neuroprotective effect on learning and memory impairment rats by decreasing ROS production and protein kinase C level (
 <xref rid="bib140" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2015</xref>). The neurological activity of β-eudesmol, including its antagonistic effect on neostigmine-induced neuromuscular failure, was demonstrated in previous studies on the accelerating effect of desensitization of the nicotinic acetylcholine receptor and blockage action during the closed state of the receptor channel or nerve-evoked contraction at the neuromuscular junction (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Chiou and Chang, 1992</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Ohara et al. (2018)</xref> showed that β-eudesmol could inhibit the efferent activity of the adrenal sympathetic nerve in rats through transient receptor potential cation channel subfamily a member 1 (TRPA1) and afferent vagus nerve. 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. (2016)</xref> found that atractylone (40 mg/kg for 5 days) could decrease influenza A virus (IAV)-induced pulmonary injury in mice by inhibiting IL-6, TNF-α, and IL-1β, but promoting TLR7, IFN-β, myeloid differentiation primary response 88 (MYD88) expression. Stigmasterol possessed anti-diabetic activity in vitro and in vivo. Which could reduce and oral glucose tolerance by decreasing blood glucose levels and blood lipid indexes, and alleviating insulin resistance in vivo while increasing glucose transporter type 4 (GLUT-4) translocation and expression in vitro (
 <xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). A water extract of the oriental crude drug Atractylodes Japonica Rhizomes showed hypoglycemic activity in mice. The extract was fractionated by monitoring the pharmacological activity to obtain three glycans, atractans A, B and C. These constituents exerted significant hypoglycemic actions in normal and alloxan-induced hyperglycemic mice. The 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> ethanol extracts exhibited an inhibitory effect on lipase with the IC
 <sub>50</sub> 9.06 μg/mL and anti-obesity effect on the obesity mice was presented on the high concentration (500 mg/kg) (
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Jiao et al., 2014</xref>). Water extracts from 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> reduced triptolide-induced toxicity via down-regulated hepatic cytochrome P450 3A (CYP3A) expression and improved anti-inflammatory activity of triptolide. This suggested that 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> could inhibit toxicity and increase the therapeutic activity of triptolide (
 <xref rid="bib128" ref-type="bibr">Yenn et al., 2017</xref>). Additionally, ATL-I could inhibit 5-lipoxygenase (5-LOX) production to decrease allergic responses (
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2012</xref>). The pharmacological interaction between the constituents of Keishi-ka-zyutubu-tō (composed of seven crude drugs, namely Glycyrrhizae Radix et Rhizoma, Cinnamomi Cortex, Zingiberis Rhizoma Recens, Atractylodis Rhizoma, etc.) was investigated in in-situ sciatic nerve-gastrocnemius muscle preparations by genetically diabetic KK-CAy mice. When administered intra-arterially, the drug caused a degree of inhibition of the diabetic neuromuscular junction 280 times greater than normal. When further combined with Paeoniae Radix Alba and Glycyrrhizae Radix et Rhizoma, the potency ratio was increased 4.9 times for Cinnamomi Cortex, 5.9 times for Zingiberis Rhizoma Recens, and 8.7 times for Atractylodis Rhizoma. In combination with the representative compounds, the potency ratio of paeoniflorin and glycyrrhizin was increased 6.6 times for cinnamaldehyde, 6.1 times for 8-gingerol and 14 times for β-eudesmol in diabetic muscles. The single effect of β-eudesmol or 8-gingerol was 5.2 times or 3.7 times more potent, respectively, on diabetic muscles than on normal muscles. These results indicated that the preferentially more potent neuromuscular blocking effects of Keishi-ka-zyutubu-tō in diabetic muscles were mainly attributable to β-eudesmol, a major component of Atractylodis Rhizoma (
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Kimura et al., 1987</xref>).
</p>
