<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgements</div>
 <p>The authors would like to acknowledge Karianne Skogland Enerstvedt, Mari Mæland Nilsen, Azin Bayat, and Mads Busvold for their help with the exposure set-up and sampling. The sequencing service was provided by the Norwegian Sequencing Centre (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sequencing.uio.no" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.sequencing.uio.no</span>), a national technology platform hosted by the University of Oslo and supported by the “Functional Genomics” and “Infrastructure” programs of the Research Council of Norway and the South-eastern Regional Health Authorities.
 </p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Funding</div>
  <p id="Par73" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Research Council of Norway, PETROMAKS 2 (project # 229153), is gratefully acknowledged for financial support. Additional funding was obtained from the research program: Bioactive, University of Stavanger, Stavanger, Norway. The funding bodies had no role in the design of the study, collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Availability of data and materials</div>
  <p id="Par74" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dataset (raw sequencing data) analysed during the current study are available in the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) repository, 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/PRJEB21667" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/PRJEB21667</span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par75" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All supporting data generated during this study are included in this published article and its additional files.</p>
 </sec>
</div>
