<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gastrointestinal microbial community</div>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA extraction</div>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GI tract of three fishes from each exposure group were used for microbial community composition analysis. After thawing on ice, each GI tract sample was cut into small pieces using sterile scissors and tweezer and placed in 15 mL sterile tubes with 3 mL ATL lysis buffer (Qiagen). Samples were vortexed vigorously several times and kept at room temperature (approx. 22 °C), then centrifuged briefly at 10,000 rpm. The liquid phase was decanted into a fresh 15 mL tube and contents were lysed overnight at 55 °C. Following this overnight incubation, a 30 min RNA digestion was carried out at 37 °C by adding 20 μL RNAse A solution (100 mg/mL, Qiagen) to each sample. DNA was then purified using phenol:chlorophorm:isoamylalcohol (PCI, 25:24:1, Sigma) extraction and ethanol precipitation. Briefly, to each lysate (approx. 3 mL), 5 mL of PCI was added and mixed vigorously. Samples were kept on ice followed by centrifugation at 5000 rpm (4 °C) for 15 min. The supernatant was pipetted into a new tube before the extraction was repeated one more time with PCI (5 mL) and then once with 5 mL chlorophorm:isoamylalcohol (CI, 24:1, Sigma). The DNA was finally precipitated with ice-cold ethanol (2 volumes of 100%) in the presence of sodium acetate (0.3 mM, pH 5.3). Samples were gently mixed and then incubated at − 20 °C for a minimum of 4 h. Falcon tubes were centrifuged at 5000 rpm for 30 min to collect the DNA pellet. Ethanol was discarded, a washing step with 70% ethanol was carried out and pellets were re-suspended in Tris-EDTA buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, 1 mM EDTA, pH 7.8). Finally, an additional clean-up was performed using Genomic DNA Clean &amp; Concentrator (Zymo Research) according to the manufacturer’s instructions, to completely remove inhibitors and resuspend DNA in molecular grade water.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PCR-DGGE</div>
  <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polymerase chain reaction-denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (PCR-DGGE) was carried out on all individual genomic DNA samples and on pooled genomic DNA samples which were from the same exposure group. The V3-V5 region of the 16S rDNA was amplified as described previously [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>] (forward primer 341f: 5‘-CCTACGGGAGGCAGCAG-3’ with a GC-clamp 5′- CGCCCGGGGCGCGCCCCGGGCGGGGCGGGGGCACGGGGGG-3′ attached at the 5′-end and reverse primer 907r: 5′- CCGTCAATTCMTTTGAGTTT-3′). Each 50 μL PCR mix was composed of molecular grade water, 5 μL PCR buffer (5 Prime), 0.1 mM of each dNTP’s, 10 pM of each primer, 1 μL of genomic DNA and 0.25 μL of Taq polymerase (5 U/μL, 5 Prime). The PCR program was as follows: initial activation at 94 °C for 2 min, followed by 25 cycles of: (1) denaturation at 94 °C for 30 s, (2) annealing at 55 °C for 40 s and (3) elongation at 72 °C for 1 min. A final elongation step at 72 °C for 7 min was also included. The DGGE was carried out on a 6% acrylamide gel containing denaturing agents, urea and formamide, in a gradient of 20–80% prepared by using the IngenyPhorU gradient former. Equal amounts of PCR products were loaded into each well (confirmed by agarose gel electrophoresis). The run was performed using an IngenyPhorU (Ingeny International BV, Goes, The Netherlands) system (17 L volume, 1 x TAE as buffer, temperature at 60 °C) at 90 V for 18 h. Bands were visualized using post-staining (GelRed in TAE) for 60 min prior to imaging.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amplicon sequencing and bioinformatics analysis</div>
  <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amplicon libraries were prepared using BioScientific’s NEXTflex V4 library preparation kit following the manufacturer’s instructions with minor modifications. All DNA samples were diluted 10 times prior to first PCR step. Primer and barcode sequences are shown as additional file [see Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>]. Instead of the recommended 10 cycles, 25 cycles were used during the first PCR reaction in order to obtain sufficient amount of products. PCR clean-up was then performed using MinElute Column Clean-up kit (Qiagen) and cleaned reaction mixes were diluted. The second PCR step was performed using 25 cycles as well. Approximately 40 μL of PCR products were loaded on a 2% agarose gel, bands corresponding to expected product size were excised and the second cleanup step was performed with MinElute Gel Extraction kit (Quiagen). DNA concentration was then measured with a NanoVue instrument (GE Healthcare). Products from three repeated library preparation rounds were pooled together prior to amplicon sequencing. Finally, the amplicons were sequenced by the Norwegian Sequencing Center (NSC) using Illumina MiSeq (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) V3 chemistry reagents (600 cycle, paired end). PhiX was blended in at 30% and a maximum of 1 bp mismatch was allowed during demultiplexing. All sequences have been deposited in the European Nucleotide Archive (ENA), acc. nr. PRJEB21667.
  </p>
  <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Read qualities were analysed using FastQC [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>], primer and adapter sequences were removed using “cutadapt” [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>] (standard parameters with primer sequences), before remaining phiX sequences were removed by mapping the reads to the phiX reference genome (Genbank acc. nr. J02482.1) using “BWA mem” with default settings [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. Reads aligning were removed using seqtk with the 
   <span class="italic">subseq</span> command [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Downstream processing and sequence analysis was performed using Mothur (v. 1.36.1) according to the Mothur Illumina MiSeq SOP [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Briefly, paired-end reads were joined using “make.contigs” and filtered based upon a minimum average Phred quality score of 25, contig length (max 289 bp) and a zero-tolerance to ambiguous base pairs. Chimeras were removed using the UCHIME algorithm [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>] implemented in Mothur, before the sequences (V4 region) were aligned and classified using the Silva SEED bacterial database (v. 119) as reference. The dataset was clustered into OTUs based on a 97% similarity sequence similarity using average neighbour clustering. The OTU table output of Mothur was imported into R studio [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>] (based on R (v. 3.2.3) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]) for further processing using the R package “phyloseq” (v. 1.14.0) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Results were visualized using the R package “ggplot2” (2.0.0) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A common scaling procedure [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>] normalized the OTU count in a given library with a factor corresponding to the ratio of the smallest library size in the dataset to the library size of the OTU in question. This replaces rarefying (i.e. random sub-sampling to the lowest number of reads) as it effectively results in the library scaling one would achieve by averaging an infinite number of repeated sub-samplings. We then excluded all OTUs present in only one sample from the dataset. Next, rarefaction curves were calculated on the observed number of reads to confirm a sufficient sequencing effort using an R script from the Phyloseq repository website [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. Finally, alpha diversity measures and ordination distances for non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS) plots were calculated in Phyloseq. Distances were calculated based on OTUs with more than 10 reads (&gt; 99% of total number of reads).
  </p>
  <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in within-sample (fish specimen) diversity (alpha diversity) were tested using both analysis of variance (ANOVA) and the Wilcoxon rank-sum test. Further, differences in bacterial community composition (beta diversity) between the exposure groups were assessed using Permutational Multivariate Analysis of Variance (PERMANOVA) using the “adonis” function in the R package “Vegan” [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. The test was run with 20,000 permutations, applying both OTU-based (Bray-Curtis/Jaccard) and phylogeny-based (weighted and unweighted UniFrac) measures. PERMANOVA was also applied to test for differences in PAH metabolites between the exposure groups. PERMANOVA assumes the multivariate dispersion in the compared groups to be homogeneous; this was verified using the “betadisper” function in “Vegan”. Similarity percentage (SIMPER) procedure implemented in “Vegan” was used to quantify the contribution of individual OTUs to the overall Bray-Curtis dissimilarity between the groups. “MetaStats” [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>] was used to test for OTUs and orders with statistically significant differential abundances between the exposure groups. Only OTUs containing more than 0.1% of the total number of reads in the normalized and filtered dataset were used in this analysis. Finally, a correspondence analysis (CA) (“
   <span class="italic">cca</span>” in Vegan) was performed to explore the gut microbial community structure. Environmental parameters (order abundances) that significantly (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01) correlated with the ordination were fitted onto the CA plot using the “
   <span class="italic">envfit</span>” command in Vegan.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
