<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Locally known as “Mawal”, 
 <italic>C. cristata</italic> is an herbaceous plant belonging to the family Amaranthaceae (Caryophyllales). It is grown as an ornamental plant in most of the parts of the world because of the attractive and vibrant colored inflorescences. In some parts of the World like Africa, China, Indonesia, India, and other parts of Asia, its leaves and inflorescences are eaten as vegetables (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">National Research Council, 2006</xref>). The plant, in general, was found to contain phenolic compounds, tannins, flavonoids, and sterols. Various authors have published reports on identification and isolation of different compounds from the seeds and leaves of the plant. These include saponins (cristatain, celosin A, celosin B, celosin C, and celosin D, semenoside A), glycoproteins (CCP-25 and CCP-27), 4-hydroxyphenethyl alcohol, β-sitosterol, 2-hydrox-yoctadecanoic acid, and stigmasterol (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Gholizadeh and Kapoor, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Chi et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>). The dried inflorescences, seeds, and leaves are reportedly used in African, Indian (Ayurvedic and Yunani) and Chinese traditional medicinal systems to cure various ailments (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kirtikar and Basu, 1918</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">National Research Council, 2006</xref>). For use in ethnomedicine different parts of 
 <italic>C. cristata</italic> are used by traditional healers. The dried red flowers are effective against hematuria, abdominal pains, leucorrhea, heavy menstrual bleeding, hemoptysis, hemorrhoid bleeding and osteoporosis (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Anderson, 1986</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Foster and Chongxi, 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Motaleb et al., 2015</xref>). Apart from its use in folklore medicine, scientific investigations have reported its hepatoprotective, antimicrobial, anthelmintic, antimelanocyte, antinoceceptive, anti-oxidant, anti-aging and adipogenesis reduction activities (
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Yun et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Woo et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Jayanthy and Shafna, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Fitoussi et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Islam et al., 2016</xref>). Traditional healers (hakims) practicing in the Kashmir Valley mostly follow the Yunani system of medicine and use dried, powdered red inflorescences and seeds of 
 <italic>C. cristata</italic> in accurately measured proportions (depending upon the ailment being targeted) in most of their traditional remedies. Besides being used in traditional medicine, the inhabitants of the Kashmir valley have found a novel way of using this edible flower. It is used as a natural food colorant in local dishes to impart a fiery hot color to gravies, without affecting taste and aroma. The coloring property of 
 <italic>C. cristata</italic> flower is due to the presence of betalains, which are water soluble pigments found in plants belonging to the family Amaranthaceae (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al., 1998</xref>). Although the cultural significance of the flower is high, to our best knowledge no study has been carried out to assess the nutritional composition, phytochemicals and antioxidant activity of red inflorescences of 
 <italic>C. cristata</italic> found in Kashmir. In the present study, our aim was to investigate the nutrient, bioactive composition and antioxidant activity of this underexploited flower grown in Kashmir valley.
</p>
