<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Essential oils are complex mixtures of volatile components produced by the plant secondary metabolism and consist mainly of monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes and, to a minor extent, of aromatic and aliphatic compounds. They are exploited in several fields such as perfumery, food, pharmaceutics, and cosmetics. Essential oils have long-standing uses in the treatment of infectious diseases and parasitosis in humans and animals. In this regard, their therapeutic potential against human African trypanosomiasis (HAT) has not been fully explored. In the present work, we have selected six medicinal and aromatic plants (
  <italic class="italic">Azadirachta indica</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Aframomum melegueta</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Aframomum daniellii</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Clausena anisata</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Dichrostachys cinerea</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Echinops giganteus</italic>) traditionally used in Cameroon to treat several disorders, including infections and parasitic diseases, and evaluated the activity of their essential oils against 
  <italic class="italic">Trypanosma brucei</italic> TC221. Their selectivity was also determined with Balb/3T3 (mouse embryonic fibroblast cell line) cells as a reference. The results showed that the essential oils from 
  <italic class="italic">A. indica</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">A. daniellii</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">E. giganteus</italic> were the most active ones, with half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC
  <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub>) values of 15.21, 7.65, and 10.50 µg/mL, respectively. These essential oils were characterized by different chemical compounds such as sesquiterpene hydrocarbons, monoterpene hydrocarbons, and oxygenated sesquiterpenes. Some of their main components were assayed as well on 
  <italic class="italic">T. brucei</italic> TC221, and their effects were linked to those of essential oils.
 </p>
</abstract>
