<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As in our previous study [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], total RNA was extracted from frozen ileal samples using TRIzol reagent (TaKaRa Biotechnology Co. Ltd., Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The quality and purity of the RNA samples were assessed by agarose gel (1.0%) electrophoresis and nucleic acid analyzer (A260/A280, Beckman DU-800; Beckman Coulter, Inc., Brea, CA, USA), respectively. A commercial reverse transcription (RT) kit (TaKaRa Biotechnology Co. Ltd., Dalian, China) was used in the synthesis of cDNA. cDNA was amplified using a real-time PCR system (ABI 7900HT, Applied Biosystems, USA). The reaction mixture (10 µL) contained 5.0 µL of freshly SYBR
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> Premix Ex Taq II (Tli RNaseH Plus), 0.4 µL forward primer (10 μM), 0.4 µL reverse primer (10 μM), 0.2 µL ROX Reference Dye (50×), 1.0 µL cDNA and 3.0 µL double distilled water. Cycling conditions were 95 °C for 30 s, followed by 40 cycles of 95 °C for 5 s and 60 °C for 34 s. At the end of amplification, melting curves were performed to identify the specificity of PCR-amplified product. The 2
 <sup class="sup">−ΔΔCt</sup> method was used to process the real-time PCR results as described previously [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Evaluation of 
 <italic class="italic">β-actin</italic> C
 <sub class="sub">T</sub> values across samples showed that there was no effect of treatment on 
 <italic class="italic">β-actin</italic> expression (i.e., 
 <italic class="italic">β-actin</italic> was acceptable as a housekeeping gene). All samples were measured in triplicate. The sequences of the primers are listed below. 
 <italic class="italic">TLR-2</italic> forward TCGAAAAGAGCCAGAAAACCAT and reverse CTTGCACCACTCGCTCTTCA; 
 <italic class="italic">TLR-4</italic>, forward AGAAAATATGGCAGAGGTGAAAGC and reverse CTTCGTCCTGGCTGGAGTAGA; 
 <italic class="italic">TLR-9</italic>, forward AATCCAGTCGGAGATGTTTGCT and reverse GACCGCCTGGGAGATGCT; 
 <italic class="italic">MyD88</italic>, forward GTGCCGTCGGATGGTAGTG and reverse TCTGGAAGTCACATTCCTTGCTT; 
 <italic class="italic">TRAF-6</italic>, forward GCTGCATCTATGGCATTTGAAG and reverse CCACAGATAACATTTGCCAAAGG; 
 <italic class="italic">NF-κB</italic>, forward TGCTGGACCCAAGGACATG and reverse CTCCCTTCTGCAACAACACGTA; 
 <italic class="italic">IL-1β</italic>, forward TCTGCCCTGTACCCCAACTG and reverse CCAGGAAGACGGGCTTTTG; 
 <italic class="italic">IL-6</italic>, forward GATGCTTCCAATCTGGGTTCA and reverse CACAAGACCGGTGGTGATTCT; 
 <italic class="italic">SIGIRR</italic>, forward ACCTGGGCTCCCGAAACTAC and reverse GTCATCTTCTGACACCAGGCAAT; 
 <italic class="italic">β-Actin</italic>, forward GGCGCCCAGCACGAT and reverse CCGATCCACACGGAGTACTTG.
</p>
