<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Simple Summary</title>
  <p class="p">The black soldier fly 
   <italic class="italic">Hermetia illucens</italic> (L.) (Diptera: Stratiomydiae) is an important resource and environmental protection insect with a large biomass, a high food conversion efficiency, and a high reproductive rate. 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> can be applied in environmental ecology and as an effective treatment for organic waste. Due to its broad feeding range, many types of organic waste (such as kitchen waste, livestock excrement, deteriorated fruits and vegetables, crop waste, and food-processing waste) can be converted into proteins, lipids, peptides, amino acids, chitin, vitamins, and polypides. The proteins and amino acids have been used to produce aquaculture feed and feedstuffs with high digestibility. In addition, the grease from 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> digestion has been successfully used as a raw material for biodiesel with good performance. Furthermore, the antimicrobial peptides and chitin extracted from 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> have high medicinal value. For the full development and utilization of this resource, studies of the biological characteristics of the 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>, its resource utilization of proteins and grease, and its environmental applications are crucial.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Abstract</title>
  <p class="p">The black soldier fly, 
   <italic class="italic">Hermetia illucens</italic> (L.) (Diptera: Stratiomyidae), is a saprophytic insect that can digest organic wastes, such as animal manure, plant residues, and food and agricultural wastes. In the degradation process, organic wastes are converted into protein, grease, and polypeptides, which can be applied in medicine, the refining of chemicals, and the manufacturing of feedstuffs. After their conversion by the 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>, organic wastes not only become useful but also environmentally friendly. To date, the 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> has been widely used to treat food waste and to render manure harmless. The protein and grease obtained via this insect have been successfully used to produce livestock feed and biodiesel. In this article, the biological characteristics, resource utilization of protein and grease, and environmental functions of the 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> are summarized. This article provides a theoretical basis for investigating potential applications of the 
   <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
