<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the present study, the beneficial and potentially harmful effects of different concentrations of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> essential oil on rooster semen stored at 4°C for 48 h were investigated. The results demonstrated that semen quality (revealed through progressive motility and gametes velocities) was significantly preserved, especially with the lowest concentrations of the essential oil (87 µg/ml and 8.7 µg/ml). The highest dose (870 µg/ml) showed a complete spermicidal effect evidenced after 24 h of storage. This concentration caused alterations probably similar to those described in bacteria [
 <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The mechanism described in bacteria was the ability of the essential oil to disrupt and penetrate the lipid structure of the cell wall leading to the destruction of the membranes [
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Chaftar 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>] reported that 
 <italic class="italic">R. officinalis</italic> essential oil was active against several strains of 
 <italic class="italic">Legionella pneumophila</italic> with a concentration of &lt;0.55 mg/mL. As well, Outaleb 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] indicated that rosemary essential oil exhibited appreciate antibacterial activities with concentrations ranging only from 4 to 20 µg/ml. Similarly, it is reported that spermicidal activity in numerous animal species is associated with considerable damages on different spermatozoa structures including cell membranes and acrosome integrity [
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>].
</p>
