<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rosemary has been used as an additive for the preservation of boar, goat, ram, and rooster sperm. In boar [
 <xref rid="B62-antioxidants-10-00772" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], rosemary has been used as an additive for semen cryopreservation at a concentration of 1 mg/mL. Several sperm parameters were evaluated at 0, 1, 2, and 3 h after thawing of semen incubated at 37 °C. Rosemary extract exerted positive effects on sperm viability, motility, and plasma membrane and acrosome integrity. In addition, the sperm samples treated with this plant showed better performance on in vitro fertilization trials. In the same species [
 <xref rid="B63-antioxidants-10-00772" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-antioxidants-10-00772" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], this plant has been used in fresh semen incubated at 16 °C for 3 h. Ten extract concentrations were added to the semen extender, ranging from 0.2 to 2 mg/mL. While some concentrations did not significantly alter sperm parameters (up to 0.6 mg/mL), the highest concentrations (starting from 0.8 mg/mL) had a negative impact. On the other hand, even though a concentration of 0.4 mg/L did not show an enhancement on sperm parameters, it exerted an antimicrobial effect similar to that of ampicillin against 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. In goat [
 <xref rid="B65-antioxidants-10-00772" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], this plant extract has been used for semen cryopreservation at 2%, 4%, and 6%. Positive effects were found on sperm viability, motility, and plasma membrane integrity. Moreover, an extract concentration of 2% reduced the MDA content in the sperm samples when compared with the control group. In general, the 4% concentration showed the best effects on sperm function. However, the highest extract concentration (6%) exerted negative effects on some sperm parameters. Similar results were obtained in ram [
 <xref rid="B66-antioxidants-10-00772" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], where the semen was cryopreserved by using four concentrations of rosemary extract (2%, 4%, 6%, and 8%). Thus, this plant extract enhanced several sperm parameters, such as viability, motility, and plasma membrane integrity, and reduced the MDA content. The best results were obtained by the use of 4% and 6% of plant extract, whereas the highest (8%) concentration had deleterious effects on some sperm parameters when compared with the control group. Finally, rosemary extract was used as an additive for the preservation of rooster semen [
 <xref rid="B67-antioxidants-10-00772" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] at 4 °C for 48 h. The sperm motility and kinetics were improved during semen storage. The best results were obtained by using a concentration of 8.7 and 87 µg/mL (especially at 6 h of semen storage), while a concentration of 870 µg/mL was detrimental for sperm function.
</p>
