<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used non-metric multidimensional scaling analysis (NMDS) to assess the potential impact of 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgare</italic> on species composition. Abundance data pooled across sites was subjected to NMDS based on Bray-Curtis dissimilarity matrix to account for variation in the species composition by invasion status (invaded vs uninvaded). Prior to NMDS, we excluded the rare species that occurred in only one or two quadrats from subsequent analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Also, we excluded 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgare</italic> from the analysis, as our aim was to examine the variations in the species composition as a result of invasion by 
 <italic>L</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgare</italic>. The range of clustering of sites and plots in response to invasion were assessed by analysis of similarity (ANOSIM) and similarity percentage (SIMPER). ANOSIM relates mean difference of ranks between and within groups, generating the Global statistic (R). Since the values of Global statistic (R) range from -1 to +1, values approaching 0 and negative values indicate similarity among groups and values approaching +1 indicate a strong dissimilarity among groups [
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. SIMPER identified species contributed most to average dissimilarity between groups (invaded and uninvaded plots). This technique calculates average impact of each species contributing to dissimilarity between groups [
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Values of percentage similarity between groups range from 0 to 100, with 100 stating maximum similarity. Therefore, to estimate the amount of variation in the community composition and to identify species contributing to those differences we performed similarity percentage test (SIMPER) [
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246665.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The analysis was carried using the PAST software.
</p>
