<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6528223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-019-1815-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>RNA-seq data reveals a coordinated regulation mechanism of multigenes involved in the high accumulation of palmitoleic acid and oil in sea buckthorn berry pulp</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><address><email>dingjian@dlnu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8580-593X</contrib-id><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Chengjiang</given-names></name><address><email>ruan@dlnu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><address><email>duwei@dlnu.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><address><email>guanying5945@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9927 2735</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.440687.9</institution-id><institution>Key Laboratory of Biotechnology and Bioresources Utilization, Ministry of Education, </institution><institution>Institute of Plant Resources, Dalian Minzu University, </institution></institution-wrap>18 Liaohe West Road, Dalian, 116600 Liaoning China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452609.c</institution-id><institution>Institute of Berries, Heilongjiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>5 Fansheng Street, Suiling, Heilongjiang, 152230 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>207</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Sea buckthorn is a woody oil crop in which palmitoleic acid (C16:1n7, an omega-7 fatty acid (FA)) contributes approximately 40% of the total FA content in berry pulp (non-seed tissue). However, the molecular mechanisms contributing to the high accumulation of C16:1n7 in developing sea buckthorn berry pulp (SBP) remain poorly understood.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">We identified 1737 unigenes associated with lipid metabolism through RNA-sequencing analysis of the four developmental stages of berry pulp in two sea buckthorn lines, &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;; 139 differentially expressed genes were detected between the different berry pulp developmental stages in the two lines. Analyses of the FA composition showed that the C16:1n7 contents were significantly higher in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; than in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; in the mid-late developmental stages of SBP. Additionally, qRT-PCR analyses of 15 genes involved in FA and triacylglycerol (TAG) biosynthesis in both lines revealed that delta9-ACP-desaturase (<italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic>) competed with 3-ketoacyl-ACP-synthase II (<italic>KASII</italic>) for the substrate C16:0-ACP and that <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and delta9-CoA-desaturase (<italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic>) gene expression positively correlated with C16:1n7 content; <italic>KASII</italic> and fatty acid elongation 1 (<italic>FAE1</italic>) gene expression positively correlated with C18:0 content in developing SBP. Specifically, the abundance of <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> transcripts in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, which had a higher C16:1n7 content than line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, suggests that these two genes play an important role in C16:1n7 biosynthesis. Furthermore, the high expressions of the glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (<italic>GPD1</italic>) gene and the WRINKLED1 (WRI1) transcription factor contributed to increased biosynthesis of TAG precursor and FAs, respectively, in the early developmental stages of SBP, and the high expression of the diacylglycerol O-acyltransferase 1 (<italic>DGAT1</italic>) gene increased TAG assembly in the later developmental stages of SBP. Overall, we concluded that increased <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> levels coupled with decreased <italic>KASII</italic> and <italic>FAE1</italic> activity is a critical event for high C16:1n7 accumulation and that the coordinated high expression of <italic>WRI1</italic>, <italic>GPD1</italic>, and <italic>DGAT1</italic> genes resulted in high oil accumulation in SBP.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">Our results provide a scientific basis for understanding the mechanism of high C16:1n7 accumulation in berry pulp (non-seed tissue) and are valuable to the genetic breeding programme for achieving a high quality and yield of SBP oil.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-019-1815-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Palmitoleic acid</kwd><kwd><italic>Hippophae</italic> L.</kwd><kwd>Fatty acid biosynthesis</kwd><kwd>Oil accumulation</kwd><kwd>Berry pulp oil</kwd><kwd>Non-seed tissue</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution></funding-source><award-id>31570681</award-id><award-id>31800574</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Chengjiang</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Dalian Minzu University Doctor Scientific Research Foundation</institution></funding-source><award-id>0701110152</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>University Innovation Groups Foundation of Dalian</institution></funding-source><award-id>201865</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par33">Sea buckthorn is a perennial shrub or small tree belonging to the genus <italic>Hippophae</italic> L. in the family Elaeagnaceae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Sea buckthorn is one of the nutritionally and ecologically most important woody oil crops and has gained popularity worldwide due to berry pulp oil, which contains uniquely bioactive compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. SBP is a good source of edible oil. Bioactive oils (2&#x02013;38%) with high levels of the uncommon fatty acid (FA) palmitoleic acid (approximately 40%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], carotenoids, flavonol glycosides, and tocopherol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], can be extracted from the orange or red berry pulp.</p><p id="Par34">Plant oils, mainly composed of triacylglycerols (TAGs), are an essential component of human diets. The common vegetable oils extracted from palm, soybean, rapeseed and sunflower contain five main FAs: palmitic (C16:0), stearic (C18:0), oleic (C18:1), linoleic (C18:2) and &#x003b1;-linolenic (C18:3) acids. In addition, many uncommon FAs are synthesized. Palmitoleic acid (<italic>cis</italic>-&#x00394;9&#x02013;16:1 or C16:1n7) is an important unusual omega-7 FA that has good oxidative stability for food production and provides human health benefits, such as increasing cell membrane fluidity and tissue regeneration, reducing inflammation, protecting the cardiovascular system, inhibiting oncogenesis, and treating hypertriglyceridaemia, with the additional benefits of decreasing low-density lipoprotein cholesterol and increasing high-density lipoprotein cholesterol levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. C16:1n7 is rarely synthesized in common oil crops, and few plants are known to accumulate C16:1n7. Those that do include cat&#x02019;s claw (<italic>Doxantha unguis-cati</italic>), which contains 64% C16:1n7 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], followed by Tasmanian waratah (<italic>Telopea truncata</italic>) (45%) and macadamia nuts (<italic>Macadamia integrifolia</italic>) (30%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. However, the seeds of these plants are the source of C16:1n7, and no reports have addressed C16:1n7 biosynthesis and accumulation mechanisms in SBP and non-seed tissues.</p><p id="Par35">FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in plant seeds involve multiple subcellular organelles and several enzymatic reactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The first step in FA biosynthesis is the conversion of acetyl coenzyme A (acetyl-CoA) into malonyl-acyl carrier protein (ACP) by acetyl-CoA carboxylase (ACC, EC 6.4.1.2 from KEGG database) and ACP-S-malonyl transferase (MAT). Malonyl-ACP is elongated to palmitoyl (C16:0)-ACP by the addition of two carbons at a time (six cycles of four reactions) via the fatty acid synthase (FAS) complex [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and C16:0-ACP is the converted to C18:0-ACP and C16:1n7-ACP by 3-ketoacyl-ACP-synthase II (KAS II, EC 2.3.1.179) and delta-9 desaturase (&#x00394;9D, EC 1.14.19.1), respectively. In plastids, these free FAs (C16:0, C16:1n7, C18:0, and C18:1n9) released from ACP by thioesterases are subsequently exported to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) in the form of acyl-coenzyme A (acyl-CoA) esters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Acyl-CoAs can be further desaturated to C18:1n7, C18:2n6, and C18:3n3 in the ER by fatty acid elongation 1 (FAE1, EC 2.3.1.199) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], fatty acid desaturase 2 (FAD2, EC 1.14.19.6), and fatty acid desaturase 3 (FAD3, EC 1.14.19.25), respectively, or utilized in the acylation of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate (G3P), which is a primary substrate for TAG biosynthesis, and can be produced via a reaction catalysed by glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GPD1, EC 1.1.1.8) during glycerol synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. There are two TAG biosynthesis pathways. The Kennedy pathway is a major pathway for TAG biosynthesis in plants. In this process, the assembly of TAG from G3P and acyl-CoA involves three sequential acylations; the first two acylations of G3P are catalysed by glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase (GPAT, EC 2.3.1.15) and lysophosphatidic acid acyltransferase (LPAT, EC 2.3.1.51), respectively, followed by dephosphorylation by phosphatidate phosphatase (LPIN, EC 3.1.3.4) to produce DAG, and the third and final acylation is catalysed by diacylglycerol O-acyltransferase (DGAT, EC 2.3.1.20) to produce TAG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. In the second pathway, phosphatidylcholine (PC) is formed first, and its acyl residues are further desaturated. The choline phosphate residue is then liberated by hydrolysis, and the corresponding DAG is acylated. The phospholipid: diacylglycerol acyltransferase (PDAT, EC 2.3.1.158) results in the conversion of DAG to TAG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Final TAG storage occurs in ER-derived oil bodies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In addition, transcription factors (TFs) including WRINKLED1 (WRI1), LEAFY COTYLEDON (LEC), and FUSCA 3 (FUS3) positively regulate the expression of genes involved in FA biosynthesis and control plant oil levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The mechanism of normal FA biosynthesis and accumulation has been widely understood in model plant seeds in previous studies, such as <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Glycine max</italic> and <italic>Brassica napus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], but the regulatory mechanism of unusual omega-7 FAs (such as C16:1n7) biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in sea buckthorn, especially in non-seed tissue, is poorly understood.</p><p id="Par36">To identify genes related to C16:1n7 biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in SBP, we first generated a comprehensive transcriptome of berry pulp in four developmental stages from two lines, &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, that displayed substantial changes in oil content and FA composition. We identified 16 sets of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) during the development of berry pulp and identified the transcriptional patterns of DEGs involved in lipid metabolism. Furthermore, expression analysis of key genes in FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation revealed that the high expression of <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> coupled with the downregulation of <italic>KASII</italic> and <italic>FAE1</italic> is a critical event for high C16:1n7 accumulation, and the coordinated high expression of <italic>GPD1</italic> and <italic>WRI1</italic> in the mid-early developmental stages and <italic>DGAT1</italic> in the mid-late stages increased TAG assembly in SBP. These results provide a scientific basis for understanding the mechanism of C16:1n7 biosynthesis and accumulation in berry pulp (non-seed tissue) and are valuable to the genetic breeding programme for achieving a high quality and yield of SBP oil.</p><sec id="Sec2"><title>Oil extraction and analysis</title><p id="Par37">Total oils were extracted from SBP as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Briefly, 0.3&#x02009;g of dried pulp powder (<italic>m</italic><sub>1</sub>) was homogenized in 6&#x02009;mL chloroform-methanol (2:1, v/v) for 2&#x02009;min. The mixtures were sonicated in an ultrasonic bath for 30&#x02009;min, centrifuged and filtered. The solid residues were re-suspended in 4&#x02009;mL chloroform-methanol (2:1, v/v), homogenized for 3&#x02009;min and filtered. A volume of 1&#x02009;mL 0.88% KCl was added to the combined filtrates, and the mixtures were mixed thoroughly by vortexing and were then centrifuged. The lower phase containing the purified oils (<italic>m</italic><sub>2</sub>) was collected and evaporated under nitrogen. The oil content was calculated as follows: oil content (%)&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>m</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic>m</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100%.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Fatty acid methyl ester (FAME) and gas chromatography time-of-flight mass spectrometry (GC-TOF/MS) analyses of berry pulp</title><p id="Par38">The FA composition was determined by FAMEs extraction with boron trifluoride in methanol as a catalyst according to previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Briefly, 0.2&#x02009;g of the dried powder samples was transferred into a glass test tube, followed by the addition of 2&#x02009;mL n-hexane and 5&#x02009;mL methanol-potassium hydroxide solution (1&#x02009;M). The mixture was placed in a vibrating water bath at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min. After the reaction was complete, 10&#x02009;mL boron trifluoride in methanol was added to the mixture, and the samples were left at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min. Two millilitres of saturated sodium chloride solution and 2&#x02009;mL n-hexane were added, and FAMEs were then extracted by vigorous shaking for approximately 1&#x02009;min. Following centrifugation, the aliquots were dried with anhydrous sodium sulfate, and the top layer was transferred into a vial, which was flushed with nitrogen; the vials were stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until analysed by gas chromatography. The analyses were conducted in triplicate.</p><p id="Par39">GC-TOF/MS analysis of FAMEs was performed on a Clarus 680 GC coupled to an AxION iQT TOF/MS system (PerkinElmer, Shelton, USA). The system was equipped with an Agilent J&#x00026;W DB-23 capillary column (60&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m). Helium was used as a carrier gas (flow rate: 1&#x02009;mL&#x000b7;min<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>). The injector was operated in split mode (1:20). The inlet and transfer line temperatures were 230&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and 215&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, respectively. The temperature program was as follows: the initial temperature of 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C was raised by 15&#x02009;&#x000b0;C&#x000b7;min<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> to 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, increased by 3&#x02009;&#x000b0;C&#x000b7;min<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> to 215&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and finally increased to 230&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min. For the detection of the mass spectrum, the temperature of the ion source was 230&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The operation parameters were an electron ionization (EI) ion source, electron energy of 70&#x02009;eV, electron multiplier of 1.5&#x02009;kV, solvent delay of 5&#x02009;min, scanning range of 45&#x02013;400&#x02009;amu, and injection volume of 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;L using the full-scan mode. FAs were identified by comparison with the retention times in the total ion chromatography (TIC) spectra and the mass-to-charge ratio (m/z) in the mass spectra of 37 FAME standards (Sigma-Aldrich, Steinheim, Germany). The FA composition was expressed as the weight percentage of each FA in the total FA content.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Total RNA extraction, cDNA library construction and RNA-seq analysis</title><p id="Par40">Total RNA was isolated from berry pulp in four developmental stages using a TRIzol RNA Extraction Kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Total RNA was quantified and qualified by 1% gel electrophoresis, a NanoDrop (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc.) and an Agilent 2100 bioanalyser (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA). RNA samples with an A260/A280 ratio between 1.9 and 2.1, an A260/A230 ratio between 2.0 and 2.5 and a RIN (RNA integrity number) of &#x02265;8.0 were processed for further analysis.</p><p id="Par41">Total RNA from three biological replicates of each sample was used for cDNA preparation. Next-generation sequencing library preparations were constructed according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (NEBNext Ultra&#x02122; RNA Library Prep Kit for Illumina). mRNA enrichment, fragment interruption, adapter addition, size selection and PCR amplification were performed by GENEWIZ Inc. (Beijing, China), and RNA-seq was conducted by an Illumina HiSeq2500 system. Briefly, mRNA was purified from 3&#x02009;&#x003bc;g total RNA from berry pulp at each developmental stage from the two lines using oligo (dT) magnetic beads. Next, using these short fragments as templates, first-strand cDNA synthesis was carried out with random primers. Third, the ends of double-stranded cDNA fragments were further modified with DNA polymerase. After the end-repair process and adapter ligation, the products were enriched by PCR to construct the final cDNA library. The cDNA library was examined using an Agilent 2100 bioanalyser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Finally, the eight berry pulp samples, from the four developmental stages of the two lines, were sequenced.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Assembly and functional annotation of unigenes</title><p id="Par42">Eight RNA-seq libraries were constructed, and de novo transcriptome libraries were assembled from all samples. Ambiguous nucleotides (N) and low-quality bases in raw reads were removed based on the Q20, Q30, N and GC parentages to obtain clean reads. De novo assembly was performed using Trinity software r2013-02-25 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The total and average lengths of the assembled contigs were important criteria for assessing transcriptome quality. Unigenes were defined after removing redundant and short contigs from the assembly.</p><p id="Par43">Reads were mapped against the assembled de novo transcriptome using Bowtie2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. All unigenes from sea buckthorn were aligned using BLAST to identify homologous genes and to the non-redundant protein (nr), Clusters of Orthologous Groups (COG), Swiss-Prot (an annotated protein sequence database) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) databases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] using Blastx algorithms with a threshold E-value of &#x02264;10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;5</sup>. The unigenes were mapped to the KEGG metabolic pathway database to elucidate the complex biological behaviours of unigenes using KEGG Automatic Annotation Server (KASS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Using the COG database, orthologous gene products were classified, and the functions of unigenes were predicted.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Identification of DEGs involved in FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation</title><p id="Par44">DEGs were identified from the unigenes for digital gene expression profile analysis, which was performed with a modified procedure using a rigorous algorithm. The normalization and calculation of unigene expression was performed by the fragments per kilobase of exon model per million mapped fragments (FPKM) method. A <italic>p</italic> value of &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and an absolute value of the log<sub>2</sub> (fold change) of &#x0003e;&#x02009;1 were the thresholds for significant differences in gene expression.</p><p id="Par45">The significant DEGs involved in FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation were screened based on alignments against the lipid metabolism pathways in the KEGG database. We first compared transcriptome differences among the four developmental stages of pulp in sea buckthorn berries specifically by analysing the transcript profiles of multigenes (<italic>ACC</italic>, <italic>KAR</italic>, <italic>FATA</italic>, <italic>KASII</italic>, <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic>, <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic>, <italic>FAE1</italic>, <italic>FAD2</italic>, <italic>FAD3</italic>, <italic>GPD1, GPAT</italic>, <italic>LPAT</italic>, <italic>DGAT1</italic>, <italic>PDAT</italic>, and <italic>WRI1</italic>) associated with C16:1n7 biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in berry pulp.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>qRT-PCR analysis</title><p id="Par46">The RNA samples used for qRT-PCR analysis were the same as those used for the RNA-seq, oil content and FA composition analyses. The first-strand cDNA used for qRT-PCR was synthesized from RNAs using a PrimeScript RT reagent kit with gDNA Eraser (TaKaRa, Dalian, China).</p><p id="Par47">Primer pairs were designed according to the selected multigenes coding for FA and TAG biosynthesis enzymes/proteins using Primer 5.0 software (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The <italic>UBQ5</italic> gene was used as a reference gene for quantitative gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The qRT-PCR reactions were performed in 96-well plates using an ABI 7500 Real-Time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, Foster, United States) and a SYBR Premix Ex Taq II Kit (TaKaRa, Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. qRT-PCR was carried out on three replicates per sample, and the relative expression level of each gene was calculated by the 2<sup><italic>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</italic></sup> method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Characterization of oil content and FA composition during berry pulp development in sea buckthorn</title><p id="Par48">Oil content and FA composition across four developmental stages (S1, S2, S3, and S4) of SBP lines, &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; and &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a), were explored. The oil contents in the developing berry pulp of line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; exhibited rapid accumulation from 9.31% at S1 stage to 35.42% at S3 stage and were significantly higher than those in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (4.84&#x02013;8.48%). During S3 to S4, the SBP oil contents of both lines remained stable (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Phenotypic observations and oil content in the developing berry pulp of the two sea buckthorn lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;. <bold>a</bold> The developmental progress of fruits from lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (S1&#x02013;S4). S1, S2, S3 and S4 indicate the developmental stage of berry pulp collected on July 6, July 28, August 19 and September 10, respectively. <bold>b</bold> Oil content was measured at four developmental stages during pulp development in lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;. * indicate significant differences of data between the two lines at the same developmental stage at the level of 0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par49">To reveal the FA composition in SBP, we performed GC-TOF/MS analyses to measure the FA composition at four developmental stages. Eleven and seven kinds of FAs were measured in the berry pulp from lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, respectively. C16:0, C16:1n7, C18:0, oleic (C18:1n9), vaccenic (C18:1n7), C18:2n6 and C18:3n3 were identified in both lines; four other FAs (myristic, pentadecanoic, hexadecadienoic and arachidic acids) were also detected in the berry pulp from line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>FA composition in SBP from lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; at four developmental stages. <bold>a</bold> Changes in the composition of various FAs in each line. <bold>b</bold> Comparison of five major FAs between two lines. The error bars indicate the standard deviations of three biological replicates. * indicate significant differences of FA composition between the two lines at the same developmental stages at the level of 0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par50">Of the saturated fatty acids (SFAs), C16:0 was the most abundant in SBP, accounting for the highest (30.21% in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and 39.22% in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;) percentage of all FAs; furthermore, the C16:0 content was higher in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; than in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; at every stage (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). However, the C18:0 content in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; were significantly lower than the C16:0 content in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; and lower than the C18:0 content in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; in developing berry pulp. The monounsaturated fatty acid (MUFA) (C16:1n7, C18:1n9, and C18:1n7) contents, accounting for 36.19&#x02013;51.91% and 39.17&#x02013;55.68% of all FAs in lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, respectively, were much higher than those of SFAs and polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) in each line for all four berry pulp developmental stages (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). In particular, the C16:1n7 content in both lines was predominant among the MUFAs, accounting for 13.31&#x02013;41.30% in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and 12.57&#x02013;39.03% in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; and increasing during berry pulp development, and the C16:1n7 contents in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; were higher than those in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; from S2 to S4 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). The contents of C18:1n9 in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (1.98&#x02013;12.35%) were significantly lower than those in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (9.60&#x02013;19.92%) and decreased from S1 to S4, but the C18:1n7 contents in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (7.34&#x02013;10.53%) were higher than those in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (5.32&#x02013;7.05%) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). For the PUFAs, the contents of C18:2n6 and C18:3n3 decreased greatly from S1 to S3, and these two FAs were much more abundant in developing berry pulp from line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; than from line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Sequencing, de novo transcriptome assembly and functional annotation</title><p id="Par51">To obtain an overview of the sea buckthorn transcriptome in developing berry pulp and identify key candidate genes involved in lipid biosynthesis and accumulation in berry pulp (non-seed tissue), we performed transcriptome sequencing of berry pulps in four developmental stages (S1, S2, S3 and S4) from two sea buckthorn lines, &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;. After removing adapter sequences, duplicated sequences, ambiguous reads and low-quality reads, a total of 397,823,136 clean reads were generated; 99.27&#x02013;99.58% of bases had a Q of &#x02265;20, and the reads had a 41.1&#x02013;41.8% GC content (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The reads in each library were assembled into unigenes using the program Trinity. As a result, 323,881 unigenes were generated (&#x02265; 200&#x02009;bp), with an average size of 593.25&#x02009;bp and an N50 length of 856&#x02009;bp. In total, 98,829 unigenes (30.51%) were longer than 500&#x02009;bp (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The mapping rates of clean reads mapped to unigenes were 54.84&#x02013;66.25% (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Quality analysis of clean reads of RNA-seq</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sample</th><th>Stage</th><th>Length of read</th><th>Number of reads</th><th>Total bases</th><th>Q20 (%)</th><th>Q30 (%)</th><th>GC (%)</th><th>N (ppm)</th><th>Mapped (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">Line Za56 pulp</td><td>S1</td><td>142.36</td><td>42,719,700</td><td>6,081,446,055</td><td>99.33</td><td>97.53</td><td>41.10</td><td>2.24</td><td>60.86</td></tr><tr><td>S2</td><td>139.48</td><td>41,463,302</td><td>5,783,400,256</td><td>99.27</td><td>97.21</td><td>41.56</td><td>3.23</td><td>54.84</td></tr><tr><td>S3</td><td>142.98</td><td>43,184,998</td><td>6,174,487,450</td><td>99.29</td><td>97.40</td><td>41.48</td><td>2.04</td><td>64.66</td></tr><tr><td>S4</td><td>143.46</td><td>55,867,418</td><td>8,014,903,918</td><td>99.53</td><td>98.05</td><td>41.36</td><td>8.45</td><td>64.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Line TF2&#x02013;36 pulp</td><td>S1</td><td>144.18</td><td>48,471,784</td><td>6,988,472,233</td><td>99.58</td><td>98.25</td><td>41.80</td><td>5.70</td><td>66.25</td></tr><tr><td>S2</td><td>143.69</td><td>60,647,368</td><td>8,714,191,825</td><td>99.57</td><td>98.21</td><td>41.21</td><td>5.81</td><td>64.87</td></tr><tr><td>S3</td><td>143.59</td><td>59,674,434</td><td>8,568,834,801</td><td>99.54</td><td>98.08</td><td>41.41</td><td>4.20</td><td>65.35</td></tr><tr><td>S4</td><td>143.01</td><td>45,794,132</td><td>6,548,950,087</td><td>99.56</td><td>98.14</td><td>41.35</td><td>4.28</td><td>63.36</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Length distributions of assembled unigenes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par52">There were 79,413 unigenes (24.52%) annotated in the nr database, 69,924 unigenes (21.59%) annotated in the COG database, 24,456 unigenes (7.55%) annotated in the Gene Ontology (GO) database, 99,916 unigenes (30.85%) annotated in the Swiss-Prot database and 28,579 unigenes (8.82%) annotated in the KEGG database. Thus, a total of 122,305 (37.76%) unigenes were annotated in one or more public databases (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S3), and 15,997 unigenes were annotated in all four databases.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Functional annotation of the sea buckthorn transcriptome</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Public database</th><th>Number of unigenes</th><th>Percentage (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>nr</td><td>79,413</td><td>24.52</td></tr><tr><td>COG</td><td>69,924</td><td>21.59</td></tr><tr><td>GO</td><td>24,456</td><td>7.55</td></tr><tr><td>Swiss-Prot</td><td>99,916</td><td>30.85</td></tr><tr><td>KEGG</td><td>28,579</td><td>8.82</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>122,305</td><td>37.76</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par53">Some unigenes were annotated with multiple COG functions; therefore, 77,713 functional annotations were assigned to 25 COG clusters, which were grouped into four larger categories, namely, &#x0201c;cellular processes and signalling&#x0201d; (26,396 unigenes, 33.97%); &#x0201c;information storage and processing&#x0201d; (16,402, 21.11%); &#x0201c;metabolism&#x0201d; (22,202, 28.57%), containing 3153 unigenes involved in &#x0201c;lipid transport and metabolism&#x0201d; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a); and &#x0201c;poorly characterized&#x0201d; (12,713, 16.36%).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Functional classifications and annotation of unigenes. <bold>a</bold> COG classification: A, RNA processing and modifications; B, Chromatin structure and dynamics; C, Energy production and conversion; D, Cell cycle control, cell division, chromosome partitioning; E, Amino acid transport and metabolism; F, Nucleotide transport and metabolism; G, Carbohydrate transport and metabolism; H, Coenzyme transport and metabolism; I, Lipid transport and metabolism; J, Translation, ribosomal structure and biogenesis; K, Transcription; L, Replication, recombination and repair; M, Cell wall/membrane/envelope biogenesis; N, Cell motility; O, Posttranslational modification, protein turnover, chaperones; P, Inorganic ion transport and metabolism; Q, Secondary metabolites biosynthesis, transport and catabolism; R, General function prediction only; S, Function unknown; T, Signal transduction mechanisms; U, Intracellular trafficking, secretion, and vesicular transport; V, Defence mechanisms; W, Extracellular structures; Y, Nuclear structure; Z, Cytoskeleton. <bold>b</bold> KEGG classifications</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par54">The KEGG pathway database with the KAAS was used to predict the metabolic network of sea buckthorn. Using Blast2GO, all unigenes were mapped against the KEGG database, resulting in 28,579 unigenes grouped into 374 KEGG pathways and 43 pathway categories, which were grouped into six groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). The groups most enriched in unigenes were metabolism (17,572 unigenes). We focused on the &#x0201c;lipid metabolism&#x0201d; category, containing 1737 unigenes grouped into 17 pathways. The maximum number of unigenes involved in glycerophospholipid metabolism (ko00564) was 342; 222 unigenes were involved in glycerolipid metabolism (ko00561), and 141 unigenes were involved in FA biosynthesis (ko00061). Furthermore, 131 were related to the biosynthesis of unsaturated fatty acids (ko01040), 83 were in the FA elongation pathway (ko00062) and 189 were in the FA degradation pathway (ko00071).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Identification of DEGs involved in palmitoleic acid biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in SBP</title><p id="Par55">To investigate the regulatory mechanism of FAs and TAG biosynthesis, especially the high accumulation of C16:1n7 in berry pulp (non-seed tissue), lipid metabolism pathways with unigenes identified in the SBP transcriptome were evaluated. We compared the normalized read counts of the unigenes and identified significant DEGs (<italic>p</italic> value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) among the developing SBP of lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;. The significant DEGs were compared between the libraries of two different developmental stages (16 pairwise comparison groups, in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S4). A total of 30,530 downregulated and 27,430 upregulated DEGs were identified among the 16 pairwise comparison groups (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Compared to the number of DEGs in S1, the number of DEGs increased from S2 to S4. C16:1n7 and oils mostly accumulated in SBP during the period from S2 to S4 (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). In the S1 vs. S4 comparison for each line (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a, b</xref>), we found the highest number of DEGs (3888 and 4079 in lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, respectively). A total of 3890, 3435, 3843 and 3665 DEGs were identified in the four pairwise comparison groups (S1, S2, S3 and S4, respectively) between lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Numbers of upregulated and downregulated DEGs in the two sea buckthorn lines. <bold>a</bold> Numbers of DEGs in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; by pairwise comparisons of four developmental stages. <bold>b</bold> Numbers of DEGs in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; by pairwise comparisons of four developmental stages. <bold>c</bold> Numbers of DEGs between the two lines at the same developmental stage</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par56">Based on alignments against the KEGG pathway analysis, 139 DEGs (42 functional genes) were related to lipid metabolism (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref><bold>)</bold>. Of these, 65 were involved in FA biosynthesis pathways in plastids, and 74 were associated with TAG biosynthesis (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Table S5). ACC is a key enzyme of FA precursor biosynthesis. The FPKMs of <italic>ACC</italic> (two homologous DEGs) were first upregulated from S2 to S3 and then downregulated from S3 to S4 in developing SBP of line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, and the total FPKM of line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; was much lower than that in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>), which could provide more FA substrates for the assembly of TAG. To investigate the high level of C16:1n7 accumulation in SBP, we focused on several key enzymes related to C16:1n7 biosynthesis, which involves desaturation by two distinct classes of <italic>&#x00394;9D</italic> genes, designated <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> gene catalyses the conversion of C16:0-ACP to C16:1n7-ACP, and the <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> gene catalyses the conversion of C16:0-CoA to C16:1n7-CoA, which have two and one homologous DEGs, respectively, and a total FPKM value of greater than 20 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). The FPKMs of these three unigenes increased and then decreased, and the expression profiles of these genes correlated with the C16:1n7 content in both lines. In particular, the peak expression of these genes in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, with a high C16:1n7 content, was higher than that in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, with a low C16:1n7 content, during berry pulp development (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). Notably, two homologous DEGs of <italic>KASII</italic>, catalysing the conversion of C16:0-ACP to C18:0-ACP and/or C16:1n7-ACP to C18:1n7-ACP (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), had downregulated expression patterns with low levels in the mid-late stages (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a), and the C18:0 contents in both lines were less than 1% (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Furthermore, the downregulation of <italic>FAE1</italic>, elongating of C16:1n7-CoA to C18:1n7-CoA, coordinated with low expression of <italic>KASII</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a), which was responsible for the low contents of C18:1n7 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). The transcription of <italic>FAD2</italic> and <italic>FAD3</italic> was also downregulated (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). These <italic>&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>KASII</italic> genes regulated the reaction direction of C16:0-ACP conversion to C16:1n7-ACP and/or C18:0-ACP, suggesting a critically synergistic regulatory mechanism involved in high C16:1n7 accumulation in SBP.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Differentially expressed genes involved in fatty acid and triacylglycerol biosynthesis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Function</th><th colspan="2">Enzyme</th><th rowspan="2">Unigene name</th></tr><tr><th>Description</th><th>Abbr.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="20">Fatty acid biosynthesis</td><td>acetyl-CoA carboxylase</td><td>
<italic>ACC</italic>
</td><td>c103701_g1_i1, c135286_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>long-chain acyl-CoA synthetase</td><td>
<italic>ACSL</italic>
</td><td>c128996_g1_i1, c147409_g1_i3, c128996_g1_i1, c144079_g1_i3, c141518_g1_i4, c144079_g1_i3, c251011_g1_i1, c136897_g1_i3</td></tr><tr><td>delta9-ACP desaturase</td><td>
<italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic>
</td><td>c108934_g1_i3, c129231_g1_i1, c129231_g1_i2, c139467_g4_i2, c139467_g4_i3, c139467_g4_i4</td></tr><tr><td>delta9-CoA desaturase</td><td>
<italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic>
</td><td>c119361_g2_i1, c141805_g5_i1, c99943_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>3-ketoacyl-ACP synthase II</td><td>
<italic>KAS II</italic>
</td><td>c147281_g2_i4, c147281_g2_i3</td></tr><tr><td>3-ketoacyl-ACP reductase</td><td>
<italic>KAR</italic>
</td><td>c74284_g1_i1, c129736_g2_i1, c119073_g1_i1, c89810_g1_i1, c74284_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>fatty acid elongation 1</td><td>
<italic>FAE1</italic>
</td><td>c120999_g2_i1</td></tr><tr><td>3-ketoacyl-ACP synthase III</td><td>
<italic>KAS III</italic>
</td><td>c142490_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>enoyl-ACP reductase</td><td>
<italic>EAR</italic>
</td><td>c68113_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>fatty acyl-ACP thioesterase A</td><td>
<italic>FATA</italic>
</td><td>c141493_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>fatty acid desaturase 2</td><td>
<italic>FAD2</italic>
</td><td>c129094_g1_i1, c108838_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>fatty acid desaturase 3</td><td>
<italic>FAD3</italic>
</td><td>c146563_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>fatty acid desaturase 7</td><td>
<italic>FAD7</italic>
</td><td>c136784_g1_i3, c136784_g1_i5, c68263_g1_i1, c136784_g2_i5</td></tr><tr><td>fatty acid desaturase 8</td><td>
<italic>FAD8</italic>
</td><td>c136784_g2_i1, c136784_g2_i4, c136784_g2_i2</td></tr><tr><td>3-ketoacyl-CoA synthase</td><td>
<italic>KCS</italic>
</td><td>c127448_g1_i1, c144156_g2_i1, c144156_g3_i1, c108825_g1_i1, c144156_g3_i2, c133459_g1_i2, c144156_g2_i2</td></tr><tr><td>mitochondrial trans-2-enoyl-CoA reductase</td><td>
<italic>MECR</italic>
</td><td>c128870_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>long-chain-3-hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydratase</td><td>
<italic>PAS2</italic>
</td><td>c129950_g1_i2, c138653_g1_i3, c138653_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>long-chain enoyl-CoA reductase</td><td>
<italic>CER10</italic>
</td><td>c144040_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>acyl-CoA oxidase</td><td>
<italic>ACOX</italic>
</td><td>c145203_g1_i3, c126961_g1_i2, c145203_g1_i1, c142258_g1_i1, c145203_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>acetyl-CoA acyltransferase 1</td><td>
<italic>ACAA1</italic>
</td><td>c118938_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="22">TAG biosynthesis</td><td>alcohol dehydrogenase</td><td>
<italic>adh</italic>
</td><td>c81969_g1_i1, c144472_g1_i1, c134965_g1_i1, c281911_g1_i1, c144736_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>aldehyde dehydrogenase</td><td>
<italic>adhE</italic>
</td><td>c124326_g1_i1, c141482_g2_i6, c141482_g2_i2, c119206_g1_i1, c133702_g1_i1, c124761_g1_i1, c133123_g1_i1, c106355_g1_i1, c144329_g2_i1, c174192_g1_i1, c225983_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>diacylglycerol O-acyltransferase 1</td><td>
<italic>DGAT1</italic>
</td><td>c144982_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>diacylglycerol kinase</td><td>
<italic>DGK</italic>
</td><td>c134987_g1_i3, c141410_g1_i7, c142032_g1_i4, c142032_g1_i2, c134987_g3_i1</td></tr><tr><td>1,2-diacylglycerol 3-beta-galactosyltransferase</td><td>
<italic>MGD</italic>
</td><td>c124343_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>alpha-galactosidase</td><td>
<italic>GLA</italic>
</td><td>c125189_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase</td><td>
<italic>GPAT</italic>
</td><td>c131894_g1_i1, c138865_g2_i1, c131644_g1_i1, c4490_g1_i1, c127068_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>phosphatidate phosphatase</td><td>
<italic>LPIN</italic>
</td><td>c141781_g2_i2, c146679_g2_i8, c146679_g2_i7, c143717_g1_i3</td></tr><tr><td>lysophospholipid acyltransferase</td><td>
<italic>LPAT</italic>
</td><td>c129657_g2_i1, c129657_g2_i2</td></tr><tr><td>acylglycerol lipase</td><td>
<italic>MGL</italic>
</td><td>c119722_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>1-acyl-sn-glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase</td><td>
<italic>plsC</italic>
</td><td>c143245_g2_i1</td></tr><tr><td>glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</td><td>
<italic>GPD1</italic>
</td><td>c145910_g1_i1, c138230_g1_i3, c121789_g1_i1, c278707_g1_i1, c71276_g1_i1, c138230_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>phosphatidylglycerol phospholipase C</td><td>
<italic>plcC</italic>
</td><td>c140114_g1_i1, c126915_g1_i1, c140382_g1_i1, c137829_g1_i5, c137829_g1_i2</td></tr><tr><td>phospholipase D1/2</td><td>
<italic>PLD1_2</italic>
</td><td>c146964_g1_i5, c133909_g1_i1, c146964_g1_i11, c133909_g1_i2, c146964_g1_i10, c146964_g1_i3, c146964_g1_i7, c146964_g1_i6, c146964_g1_i8</td></tr><tr><td>phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase</td><td>
<italic>PDAT</italic>
</td><td>c133634_g3_i4, c133634_g3_i6, c133634_g3_i7, c133634_g3_i1</td></tr><tr><td>phosphatidyl glycerophosphatase</td><td>
<italic>GEP4</italic>
</td><td>c138502_g1_i3</td></tr><tr><td>phosphoethanolamine N-methyltransferase</td><td>
<italic>NMT</italic>
</td><td>c133930_g1_i1</td></tr><tr><td>glycerophosphocholine phosphodiesterase</td><td>
<italic>GPCPD1</italic>
</td><td>c126428_g1_i4</td></tr><tr><td>lysophospholipase II</td><td>
<italic>LYPLA2</italic>
</td><td>c144211_g2_i4</td></tr><tr><td>ethanolamine phosphotransferase</td><td>
<italic>EPT1</italic>
</td><td>c146531_g1_i3</td></tr><tr><td>CDP-diacylglycerol-glycerol-3-phosphate 3-phosphatidyltransferase</td><td>
<italic>PGS1</italic>
</td><td>c139239_g1_i6, c139239_g1_i9</td></tr><tr><td>phosphatidylserine synthase 2</td><td>
<italic>PTDSS2</italic>
</td><td>c147897_g1_i8, c147897_g1_i7, c147897_g1_i6, c147897_g1_i4, c147897_g1_i1, c147897_g1_i2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significant DEGs were identified based on a log<sub>2</sub> (fold change)&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1 and a <italic>p</italic> value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram representing palmitoleic acid biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in SBP. The bold arrows in red indicate the metabolic flux from C16:0-ACP to C16:1n7-TAG. The red (upregulation) and green (downregulation) boxes indicate the key genes in C16:1 biosynthesis and its accumulation in TAG. The violet arrows indicate the Kennedy pathways in TAG assembly. The blue arrows indicate the phosphatidylcholine acyl pathways in TAG assembly. The enzymes are shown in boxes and abbreviated as follow: ACC, acetyl-CoA carboxylase; KAS, 3-ketoacyl-ACP synthase (KAS I, KAS II, KAS III); KAR, 3-ketoacyl-ACP reductase; HAD, &#x003b2;-hydroxyacyl-ACP dehydrase; EAR, enoyl-ACP reductase; FATA, acyl-ACP thioesterase A; FATB, acyl-ACP thioesterase B; &#x00394;9D, delta-9 desaturase; FAE1, fatty acid elongation 1; FAD2, fatty acid desaturase 2; FAD3, fatty acid desaturase 3; GPD1, glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase; GPAT, glycerol-3-phosphate O-acyltransferase; LPAT, lysophosphatidic acid acyltransferase; LPIN, phosphatidate phosphatase; DGAT, diacylglycerol O-acyltransferase; plcC, phospholipase C; PDAT, phopholipid:diacyglycerol acyltransferase. The names of key intermediates are abbreviated as follows: G3P, glycerol-3-phosphate; LPA, lysophosphatidic acid; PA, phosphatidic acid; DAG, diacylglycerol; TAG, triacylglycerol</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Heat maps of unigenes involved in FA biosynthesis (<bold>a</bold>) and TAG accumulation (<bold>b</bold>) in SBP. The expression value (in FPKM) for the unigenes during berry pulp development in both lines was log<sub>2</sub> transformed, and the total FPKM value was greater than 20</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par57">TAG assembly is an important step in oil accumulation. G3P is a primary substrate, converted into TAG by three sequential acylations by GPAT, LPAT and DGAT (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Nine DEGs, including 3 <italic>GPD1</italic>, 2 <italic>GPAT</italic>, 1 <italic>LPAT</italic>, 2 <italic>LPIN</italic>, and 1 <italic>DGAT1</italic> (the total FPKM of each transcript was greater than 20), were identified in the developing berry pulp transcriptome of sea buckthorn (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b). <italic>GPD1</italic>, a rate-limiting enzyme in G3P synthesis, had the highest expression level in the mid-early stages (S1&#x02013;S2), and the transcript levels in developing berry pulp from line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, with a high oil content, were higher than those in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, with a low oil content (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). <italic>GPAT</italic> and <italic>LPAT</italic> had the highest transcript levels in S1, and the transcripts of these two genes in developing berry pulp of line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; were higher than those in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;. <italic>DGAT1</italic>, a rate-limiting enzyme in TAG assembly, had the highest expression level in the mid-late stages (S3&#x02013;S4) and its transcript level was higher in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; than in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). In addition, we identified two significant difference expression <italic>WRI1</italic> (c141864_g1_i1 and c141864_g1_i2) TF in de novo transcriptome library of SBP, the FPKMs of <italic>WRI1</italic> (c141864_g1_i1) in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; berry pulp from S1 to S4 (30.3, 53.3, 31.2, and 10.7, respectively) were always higher than those in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (10.7, 8.2, 9.8, and 5.0, respectively). These results indicated that the high expression of the multigenes (<italic>GPD1</italic>, <italic>GPAT</italic>, <italic>LPAT</italic>, <italic>LPIN</italic>, <italic>DGAT1</italic>, and <italic>WRI1</italic>) contributed to TAG biosynthesis and accumulation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>qRT-PCR analysis reveals differential transcript abundances during berry pulp development in sea buckthorn</title><p id="Par58">In plants, FA and oil accumulation in non-seed tissues involve several organelles and multiple enzymatic reactions, and there is no available genetic information on the regulatory mechanism of C16:1n7 and TAG biosynthesis in SBP (non-seed tissue). Based on previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and the KEGG pathway analysis results (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Table S5), we selected 15 DEGs to determine by qRT-PCR whether the expression pattern during SBP development in lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; correlated with C16:1n7 biosynthesis and the changes in oil content. Nine candidate genes were involved in the FA biosynthesis pathway, namely, <italic>ACC</italic> (c135286_g1_i2), <italic>KAR</italic> (c119073_g1_i1), <italic>FATA</italic> (c141493_g1_i2), <italic>KAS II</italic> (c147281_g2_i3), <italic>FAE1</italic> (c108825_g1_i1), <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> (c108934_g1_i3), <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> (c119361_g2_i1), <italic>FAD2</italic> (c129094_g1_i1), and <italic>FAD3</italic> (c146563_g1_i2). Five candidate genes, namely, <italic>GPD1</italic> (c138230_g1_i1), <italic>GPAT</italic> (c131644_g1_i1), <italic>LPAT</italic> (c129657_g2_i2), <italic>DGAT1</italic> (c144982_g1_i2), and <italic>PDAT</italic> (c133634_g3_i1), were involved in the TAG biosynthesis pathway (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). One TF <italic>WRI1</italic> (c141864_g1_i1) was associated with FA and oil biosynthesis-related genes expression and regulation. The expression levels of these 15 unigenes in S1, S2, S3, and S4 were mostly consistent between the qRT-PCR and RNA-seq experiments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>), which indicated that the expression profiles in our transcriptomics results had a high confidence level.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>qRT-PCR analysis of genes involved in C16:1n7 biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; at four different developmental stages</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p><p id="Par59"><italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic>, <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic>, <italic>KASII</italic>, and <italic>FAE1</italic> were important coordinated regulatory genes related to C16:1n7 biosynthesis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The relative expression levels of <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> first increased from S1 to S3 and then decreased in the berry pulp from both lines (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). In particular, the peak expression of these two genes in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, with a high C16:1n7 content, were higher than those in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, with a low C16:1n7 content, in S3 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, <italic>KASII</italic> and <italic>FAE1</italic> expression in both lines were significantly downregulated from S1 to S4, which corresponded to the decreasing trend in C18:0 and C18:1n7 contents (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The <italic>ACC</italic> expression in developing berry pulp from line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; was significantly higher than that in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, and the peak <italic>KAR</italic> expression in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; was higher than that in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, with lower C16:0 contents. The expression of the <italic>FATA</italic> gene in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; berry pulp was higher than that in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; in S3 and S4. The downregulated expression of the <italic>FAD2</italic> and <italic>FAD3</italic> genes during berry pulp development in both lines was consistent with the decreasing contents of C18:2 and C18:3, respectively (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par60"><italic>GPD1</italic> first increased at S1&#x02013;S2 and then declined from S3 to S4 in developing berry pulp from both lines (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). The expression levels of <italic>GPAT</italic>, <italic>LPAT</italic>, and <italic>PDAT</italic> in both lines decreased from S1 to S4. In developing berry pulps of line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; <italic>DGAT1</italic> expression increased from S1 to S3 but increased from S2 to S4 in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;. <italic>WRI1</italic> in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; sharply increased at S1&#x02013;S2 and then declined from S2 to S4, which was similar to the expression pattern of <italic>GPD1</italic> in developing berry pulps of line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;. The relative expression levels of <italic>GPD1</italic>, <italic>GPAT</italic>, <italic>LPAT</italic>, <italic>DGAT1</italic>, <italic>PDAT</italic>, and <italic>WRI1</italic> in developing berry pulp from line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, with a high oil content, were higher in every stages than those in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019;, with a low oil content (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Interestingly, the coordinated high expression of <italic>GPD1</italic> and <italic>WRI1</italic> in the mid-early developmental stages and <italic>DGAT1</italic> in the mid-late stages contributed to increased biosynthesis of the TAG in SBP.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par61">Palmitoleic acid, an omega-7 FA, has numerous health benefits, such as protecting the cardiovascular system and inhibiting oncogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Due to the high value of and growing demand for omega-7 FAs, exploiting oleaginous resources and dissecting the mechanism of C16:1n7 biosynthesis and oil accumulation have been extensively pursued [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Recently, sea buckthorn has gained popularity as a resource in the food and nutraceutical industries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] because C16:1n7 is synthesized at very low levels in common oil crop seeds but can accumulate to 0.1&#x02013;12% of all FAs in sea buckthorn seed oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and, more notably, accounts for 12&#x02013;52% of all FAs in SBP oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], with a ratio of MUFA to SFA of approximately 1:1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. SBP oil with a high C16:1n7 content is a very balanced source of MUFAs for human health and nutrition, but the molecular mechanism of high C16:1n7 accumulation is still poorly understood. Therefore, considerable research efforts related to the exploration of C16:1n7 biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in SBP (non-seed tissue) are urgently needed. To explore whether transcriptional regulation is involved in controlling C16:1n7 biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in SBP, we analysed the dynamic patterns in oil content and FA composition, especially for C16:1n7, in developing berry pulps from lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Of these two lines, line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; has a higher C16:1n7 content than that in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;. We carried out comparative transcriptomics analysis in the two lines at four berry pulp developmental stages and generated 183,235,418 and 214,587,718 clean reads for lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, respectively (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Bioinformatics analysis identified a total of 323,881 unigenes, 122,305 of which were annotated, in developing SBP. A total of 139 DEGs (42 functional genes) were found to be involved in lipid metabolism. Of these, 65 were involved in FA biosynthesis and 74 were associated with TAG accumulation (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), suggesting that these DEGs regulate FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in SBP. The coordinated expression of genes involved in FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation (<italic>ACC</italic>, <italic>KAR</italic>, <italic>FATA</italic>, <italic>KAS II</italic>, <italic>FAE1</italic>, <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic>, <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic>, <italic>FAD2</italic>, <italic>FAD3</italic>, <italic>GPD1</italic>, <italic>GPAT</italic>, <italic>LPAT</italic>, <italic>DGAT1</italic>, <italic>PDAT</italic>, and <italic>WRI1</italic>) contributes to the high levels of C16:1n7 in SBP oil. These results provide a scientific basis for understanding the mechanisms of C16:1n7 biosynthesis and accumulation in berry pulp (non-seed tissue) and are valuable to the genetic breeding programme for achieving a high quality and yield of SBP oil.</p><sec id="Sec14"><title>FA composition and oil content during berry pulp development in sea buckthorn</title><p id="Par62">Because berry pulp and seed oils have unique bioactive compounds (FAs, phytosterols, carotenoids, and tocopherols), sea buckthorn berries have been used for hundreds of years in Russia and China for medicinal and nutritional purposes. Monounsaturated palmitoleic acid is rare in oil crops, such as soybean (relative C16:1n7 content&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.14%), rapeseed (0.24%), and olive (0.73) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], and a few rare plants, such as <italic>Kermadecia sinuate</italic> (70%), <italic>Doxantha unguis-cati</italic> (64%), and <italic>Tasmanian waratah</italic> (45%), are known to accumulate C16:1n7 in the seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. However, unlike these plants that accumulate C16:1n7 in the seeds, SBP oil has a C16:1n7 content of approximately 40% suitable for commercial extraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] In fact, approximately 40% of plant oils are extracted from non-seed tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], and different amounts of C16:1n7 can be synthesized in different non-seed tissues, for example, 5.36% in the pericarp of bayberry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], 0.41% in the leaves of tobacco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], and trace amounts in the mesocarp of oil palm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and Chinese tallow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]<italic>.</italic> Regarding C16:1n7 biosynthesis, the underlying mechanistic details are not yet well understood, particularly in non-seed tissue with high C16:1n7 accumulation.</p><p id="Par63">Sea buckthorn is a unique species with a high accumulation of C16:1n7 in non-seed tissue (berry pulp) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], and the molecular mechanism of C16:1n7 biosynthesis and accumulation in berry pulp has not yet been reported. In this study, we measured the composition of the main FAs, especially C16:1n7, and the oil contents in developing berry pulp from the sea buckthorn lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (hybrid progeny of ssp. <italic>mongolica</italic> and ssp. <italic>sinensis</italic>) and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (ssp. <italic>mongolica</italic>), with a closed genetic relationship [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The C16:1n7 content was the highest among all FAs in mature berry pulp from both line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (41%), with a low oil content (4.8&#x02013;8.5%), and line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (39%), with a high oil content (9.3&#x02013;35.4%) (Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The contents of C16 FAs (C16:0 and C16:1n7) in mature pulp (S4) were significantly higher than those in immature pulp (S1) from both lines, while the contents of C18 FAs (C18:0, C18:1n9, C18:2, and C18:3) sharply decreased during berry pulp development (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). As reported previously, the content of C16 FAs sharply decreased from 28.77 to 6.06% in developing seeds of sea buckthorn line &#x02018;SJ1&#x02019;, and C18 FAs accumulated to high levels in mature seeds (93.94%), which were much higher than those in immature seeds (71.23%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. We also found similar accumulation patterns of C16 and C18 FAs between the two tissues in one line, &#x02018;XE3&#x02019; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The results of comparative analysis among these selected samples indicate that the metabolic flux from C16:0 to C16:1n7 or C18:0 plays an important role in determining the composition of FAs and TAG and provide the critical basis for understanding the biosynthesis and accumulation mechanism of berry pulp (non-seed tissue) with a high oil content.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Coordinated regulation of multigenes contributes to C16:1n7 accumulation in SBP</title><p id="Par64">The sea buckthorn transcriptome libraries for developing berry pulps were first constructed, and 65 DEGs involved in FA biosynthesis and 74 DEGs associated with TAG accumulation were revealed (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). We focused on C16:1n7 biosynthesis and the associated TAG accumulation pathway (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) to confirm the gene expression patterns of related key enzymes in developing berry pulp from sea buckthorn lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).</p><p id="Par65">The key steps in the biosynthesis and accumulation of C16:1n7 and TAG in SBP are outlined in red in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. Three major biosynthesis events occur during the production of C16:1n7. The first involves the biosynthesis of C16:0-ACP and/or C16:1n7-ACP in plastids and the export of these molecules to the cytosol. The second involves the formation of C16:0-CoA and/or C16:1n7-CoA and the transfer of these products to the ER, where C16:0-CoA can be further converted to C16:1n7-CoA. The third involves the incorporation of nascent C16:1n7 into TAGs, which subsequently accumulate in oil bodies. Previous studies revealed that the &#x00394;9D enzyme catalyses the desaturation of C16:0 to form C16:1n7, and some &#x00394;9D enzymes can also convert C18:0 to C18:1n9 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Numerous <italic>&#x00394;9D</italic> genes from various plants have been cloned and characterized so far [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], and many studies have verified the expression of <italic>&#x00394;9D</italic> genes capable of converting C16:0 to C16:1n7 in transgenic plants, including <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>, <italic>Glycine max</italic>, and <italic>Brassica napus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. In this study, we discovered two distinct classes of &#x00394;9D enzymes, designated ACP-&#x00394;9D (soluble) and CoA-&#x00394;9D (membrane-bound), in SBP. The higher levels of <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> (1&#x02013;53.2) and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> (1&#x02013;5.5) expression in developing SBP from line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; than in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (1&#x02013;46.4 and 1&#x02013;2.8, respectively) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>) were consistent with the higher accumulation of C16:1n7 in &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (13.3&#x02013;41.3%) than in &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (12.6&#x02013;39.0%) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). Gao et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] found that the ACP-&#x00394;9D enzyme desaturated C16:0 to C16:1n7 with high activity and that the C16:1n7 content in transgenic tobacco leaves overexpressing the <italic>Macfadyena unguis-cati ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> gene significantly increased to 16.4&#x02013;20.4% compared to that in wild-type leaves (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.4%). Cytosolic <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> can also function in plastids of plant cells; seed-specific expression of a yeast <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> in soybean seeds resulted in (10.5%) plastid C16:1 n7 production higher than that in wild-type soybean seeds (&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Furthermore, co-expression of a castor <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> gene in plastids and two fungal (<italic>Stagonospora nodorum</italic> and <italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic>) <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> genes in the ER can increase the C16:1n7 content from 1.9 to 43% in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par66">However, we found that the coordinated upregulation of <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> and downregulation of <italic>KASII</italic> and <italic>FAE1</italic> was critical in SBP oil biosynthesis to achieve high C16:1n7 accumulation (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). During the development of SBP, an increasing total C16 FA (C16:0 and C16:1n7) content coupled with a sharp decline in C18 FA content; the content of C16 FAs was significantly higher than that of C18 FAs in S2&#x02013;S4 (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Table S2). The length and desaturation of FA carbon chains are regulated by the activity of <italic>KASII</italic>, <italic>FAE1</italic>, <italic>&#x00394;9D, FAD2</italic>, and <italic>FAD3</italic>. <italic>KASII</italic> competes with <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> for substrate and elongates the majority of C16:0-ACP to C18:0-ACP and/or C16:1n7-ACP to C18:1n7-ACP; <italic>FAE1</italic> is responsible for the extraplastidial elongation of C16:1n7-CoA to C18:1n7-CoA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Therefore, <italic>KASII</italic> was strongly downregulated in developing SBP, resulting in an increased accumulation of C16:0-ACP, which is then desaturated by ACP-&#x00394;9D to produce C16:1n7-ACP. Furthermore, the higher CoA-&#x00394;9D activity coordinated with the downregulation of <italic>FAE1</italic> led to the increasing accumulation of C16:1n7-CoA. Previous studies revealed that high <italic>KAS II</italic> expression was consistent with the high proportion of C18 FAs in peony seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] and that the suppression of <italic>KAS II</italic> by short hairpin RNAi led to an increase in C16:0 accumulation in palm seed oil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Expression of castor <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> gene in wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds increased C16:1n7 accumulation from 0.1 to 1.6%, yielding a total of 14.4% omega-7 FA, furthermore, the overexpression of <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> in a <italic>fab1</italic> (KASII) mutant increased the accumulation of C16:1n7 to 23.5%, and the expression of <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> in the <italic>fab1 fae1</italic> double mutant resulted in an increase in C16:1n7 to 26.2% in transgenic seeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par67">The downregulation of <italic>KASII</italic> correlated with the decreased content of C18:0, which was only approximately 0.8% in mature berry pulp (S4). Moreover, the content of C18 unsaturated fatty acids (UFAs) (C18:1n9, C18:1n7, C18:2n6, and C18:3n6) also sharply declined (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Although ACP-&#x00394;9D also catalyses the conversion of C18:0-ACP to C18:1n9-ACP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], storage lipid synthesis is restricted by the supply of precursors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Therefore, the sharp decline in C18:1n9 content in developing SBP was due to a lack of the C18:0-ACP substrate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, the decreased contents of C18:2n3 and C18:3n6 in berry pulp from both sea buckthorn lines were associated with the downregulation of the <italic>FAD2</italic> and <italic>FAD3</italic> genes, respectively (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Interestingly, in our previous study, we found that the high accumulation of C18 UFAs (88% of the total FAs) in sea buckthorn seed oil was due to low expression of the <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> gene coordinated with high expression of the <italic>KAS II</italic>, <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic>, <italic>FAD2</italic>, and <italic>FAD3</italic> genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. These results are significant for understanding the mechanism of high C16:1n7 accumulation in SBP (non-seed tissue) and provide a scientific basis for enhancing C16:1n7 biosynthesis in non-seed tissues by means such as overexpressing <italic>&#x00394;9D</italic>, downregulating <italic>KASII</italic>, co-expressing <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> in plastids and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> in the ER, and optimizing the metabolic flux toward TAG assembly.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Source and sink genes control TAG biosynthesis and assembly in SBP</title><p id="Par68">The glycerol or G3P supply is co-limiting for lipid synthesis; attempts to improve TAG synthesis solely by increasing the FA supply may not be successful and will need approaches that lead to a simultaneous increase in both FAs and G3P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. <italic>GPD1</italic> and <italic>DGAT</italic> are described as the &#x02018;source&#x02019; and &#x02018;sink&#x02019; genes, respectively, in TAG biosynthesis; regulating the expression of these two genes can increase oil content in plant tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. GPD1 is a rate-limiting enzyme in lipid synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], and G3P, a primary substrate for TAG biosynthesis, can be produced via a reaction catalysed by <italic>GPD1</italic> during glycerol synthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. DGAT and PDAT catalyse the conversion of DAG to TAG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. In addition, WRI1 TF regulates the expression of genes involved in FA and TAG biosynthesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In the present study, we confirmed the differential expression levels of genes involved in TAG biosynthesis and accumulation in the developing pulp of two sea buckthorn lines, &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;. The <italic>GPD1</italic>, <italic>GPAT</italic>, <italic>LPAT</italic>, <italic>DGAT1</italic>, and <italic>PDAT</italic> genes were more highly expressed in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (with a high pulp oil content) than in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (with a low pulp oil content) by qRT-PCR (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>), consistent with the data for the oil contents in the berry pulp from the two lines (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, the expressions of <italic>GPD1</italic> and <italic>DGAT1</italic> genes had obviously upregulated trend, and <italic>GPAT</italic>, <italic>LPAT</italic>, and <italic>PDAT</italic> expressions always decreased during the development stages of both lines (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Therefore, we concluded that the coordinated high expression of <italic>GPD1</italic> and <italic>DGAT1</italic> genes resulted in high oil accumulation in SBP.</p><p id="Par69">The peak <italic>GPD1</italic> expression in lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; appeared during the period of rapid oil biosynthesis (mid-early stages), and the highest oil contents in the pulp were 8.48 and 35.42%, respectively, in S3 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), which was after the stage of peak <italic>GPD1</italic> expression (S2) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Therefore, the high expression of the <italic>GPD1</italic> gene contributed to increased synthesis of the TAG precursor G3P in the early stages of berry pulp development. <italic>In planta</italic> feeding, glycerol leads to increased levels of G3P and TAG in developing <italic>Brassica napus</italic> seeds, and the oil content peak lagged behind that of G3P for 15 d [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In addition, Vigeolas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] found that a twofold overexpression of the yeast gene coding for GPD1 led to a three- to fourfold increase in the level of G3P in transgenic <italic>Brassica napus</italic> seeds, resulting in a 40% increase in oil content, with the protein content remaining substantially unchanged. Overexpression of maize <italic>GPD1</italic> remarkably enhanced the G3P production and the salinity/osmotic stress tolerance in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, and the transgenic lines showed no aberrant phenotype under normal growth conditions, no matter in the vegetative growth phase or reproductive developmental stages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Overexpression of the yeast <italic>GPD1</italic> increased <italic>Camelina sativa</italic> seed oil content about 5.4% but cause no change in seed protein content and no effect on seed germination and seedling growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].</p><p id="Par70">The peak <italic>DGAT1</italic> expression in berry pulp from line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (with a high oil content) appeared during the period of stable oil accumulation (mid-late stages) and was significantly higher than that in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (with a low oil content) in S3. Therefore, the high expression of <italic>DGAT1</italic> catalysed the robust assembly of acyl-CoA FAs and DAG to form TAG in the late stages of berry pulp development. Li et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] found that <italic>DGAT1</italic> appears to be a major enzyme for seed oil accumulation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and soybeans. Overexpression of DGAT cDNA in wild-type <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds increased the oil content by 11&#x02013;28% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. In addition, seed-specific overexpression of <italic>AtDGAT1</italic> in <italic>Brassica juncea</italic> seed improved the oil content significantly, with a maximum oil content increase of 8.3% in the transgenic plants compared to that in the wild-type plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. In addition, we examined the expression profiles of the <italic>GPD1</italic> and <italic>DGAT1</italic> genes in seeds and berry pulp tissues of one sea buckthorn line, &#x02018;XE3&#x02019;, and found that these two genes had higher expression in pulp (with an oil content of 36.90%) than in seeds (14.15%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>].</p><p id="Par71">Metabolic engineering strategies for increasing plant lipids can be described as the surprising synergy when &#x02018;Push&#x02019; approach (up-regulation of substrate biosynthesis by <italic>WRI1</italic>) and a &#x02018;Pull&#x02019; approach (increasing TAG assembly by <italic>DGAT</italic>) are combined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. This strategy corresponded to the coordinated high expression of source gene (<italic>GPD1</italic>) and sink gene (<italic>DGAT</italic>) contributes to increase oil content in plant tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. In developing SBP, we found similar expression patterns between <italic>WRI1</italic> and <italic>GPD1</italic>, and their expressions of line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; were higher than those in line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; with a sharp increase in the mid-early stages (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). The coordinated high expressions of <italic>WRI1</italic> and <italic>GPD1</italic> in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, with a high oil content, suggested to play a major role in the high levels of storage oils in SBP. Overexpression of the <italic>WRI1</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and maize yielded higher TAG levels in seed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>] while an <italic>Arabidopsis wri1</italic> knockout mutant exhibit reduced seed oil content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Vanhercke et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] found that overexpression of the <italic>Arabidopsis WRI1</italic> gene led to a 22-fold increase TAG levels in transgenic <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> dry leave, and the C16:1 content increased from 0.4 to 0.9%. Furthermore, when both the <italic>Arabidopsis WRI1</italic> and <italic>DGAT1</italic> genes were co-infiltrated (push and pull approach), a significant synergistic effect on leaf oil accumulation was observed with TAG levels increasing almost 100-fold and making up 2.48% of the leaf dry weight. In addition, <italic>Camelina sativa</italic> plants co-expressing a yeast cytosolic <italic>GPD1</italic> and the <italic>Arabidopsis DGAT1</italic> genes exhibited up to 13% higher seed oil content compared to wild-type plants, and these coexpressing lines showed significantly higher seed oil yields than the plants expressing <italic>GPD1</italic> and <italic>DGAT1</italic> alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Therefore, combining the overexpression of lipid biosynthetic genes, <italic>WRI1</italic>, <italic>GPD1</italic>, and <italic>DGAT1</italic>, appears to be a positive strategy to achieve a synergistic effect on the flux through the TAG biosynthesis pathway, and thereby further increase the oil yield. This finding suggests that the coordinated high expression of <italic>WRI1</italic> and <italic>GPD1</italic> in the mid-early stages and <italic>DGAT1</italic> genes in the mid-late stages resulted in TAG assembly and oil accumulation in SBP.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par72">Palmitoleic acid (an omega-7 FA) is rarely synthesized in common oil crops [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] but is an essential unusual FA that has a wide range of biological activities and benefits to human health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. SBP is a good source of bioactive edible oil (2&#x02013;38%) with a high level of C16:1n7 (approximately 40%), and the global demand for sea buckthorn pulp oil is increasing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. However, the regulatory mechanism of C16:1n7 biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in SBP is poorly understood. In this study, we first generated a comprehensive transcriptome of berry pulp from two lines, &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;, in four developmental stages. Oils and C16:1n7 predominantly accumulated in mature berry pulp stages, and the C16:1n7 contents in developing berry pulp from line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; (with a low oil content) were higher than those in line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; (with a high oil content). We identified 139 DEGs involved in lipid metabolism between the different developmental stages of berry pulp in the two lines. Furthermore, expression analysis of some key genes involved in FA biosynthesis and TAG assembly revealed that high expression of the <italic>ACP-&#x00394;9D</italic> and <italic>CoA-&#x00394;9D</italic> genes coordinated with downregulation of the <italic>KASII</italic> and <italic>FAE1</italic> genes is a critical event for high C16:1n7 accumulation and that the coordinated high expression of <italic>GPD1</italic>, <italic>WRI1</italic>, and <italic>DGAT1</italic> accelerated TAG accumulation in SBP. These results provide the first scientific basis for understanding the mechanism of C16:1n7 biosynthesis and accumulation in SBP (non-seed tissue) and are valuable to the genetic breeding programme for achieving a high quality and yield of SBP oil with a high level of C16:1n7.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>Plant materials</title><p id="Par73">Samples were collected from cultivated <italic>Hippophae</italic> L. trees (lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019;) growing in Institute of Berries at Heilongjiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences (voucher No. 02901, identified by Jin-you Shan and deposited at HAAS), Suiling county, Heilongjiang, China (47&#x000b0;14&#x02032;12.3&#x0201c; north latitude, 127&#x000b0;05&#x02019;39.9&#x0201d; east longitude) under natural climate conditions. The orchard had a mean annual rainfall of 570.6&#x02009;mm, a mean annual temperature of 2.0&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, a mean annual evaporation capacity of 1242.5&#x02009;mm and an effective accumulative temperature of 2460.4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. The collection of all samples completely complies with local and national legislation permission. Line &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; was selected from seedlings of the hybrid progeny of ssp. <italic>mongolica</italic> (&#x02640;) and ssp. <italic>sinensis</italic> (&#x02642;), and line &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02032; was selected from seedlings of ssp. <italic>mongolica</italic>. The molecular marker-based genetic similarity of these two lines is 0.752 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The three trees of each line selected as biological triplicates for fruit collection were cutting seedlings. The developing fruits of lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02032; were collected on July 6 (S1), July 28 (S2), August 19 (S3) and September 10 (S4), 2015. These samples were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until use. Eight RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) transcriptome libraries were constructed based on the developmental berry pulp from these two lines.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec20"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Primers used for qRT-PCR of multigenes involved in FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation in sea buckthorn berry pulp. (XLSX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> FA composition in sea buckthorn berry pulp from lines &#x02018;Za56&#x02019; and &#x02018;TF2&#x02013;36&#x02019; at four developmental stages. (XLSX 13 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S3.</bold> Functional classifications of unigenes in developing berry pulps of sea buckthorn based on COG category and KEGG pathway. (XLSX 12 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S4.</bold> Differentially expressed genes for each of the 16 pairwise comparison groups. (XLSX 3263 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12870_2019_1815_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S5.</bold> Unigenes involved in FA biosynthesis and TAG accumulation based on KEGG pathway analysis. (XLSX 44 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ACC</term><def><p id="Par4">Acetyl-CoA carboxylase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ACP</term><def><p id="Par5">Acyl carrier protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ACP-&#x00394;9D</term><def><p id="Par6">Delta9-ACP desaturase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CoA-&#x00394;9D</term><def><p id="Par7">Delta9-CoA desaturase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEG</term><def><p id="Par8">Differentially expressed gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DGAT1</term><def><p id="Par9">Diacylglycerol O-acyltransferase 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER</term><def><p id="Par10">Endoplasmic reticulum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FA</term><def><p id="Par11">Fatty acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAD2</term><def><p id="Par12">Fatty acid desaturase 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAD3</term><def><p id="Par13">Fatty acid desaturase 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAE1</term><def><p id="Par14">Fatty acid elongation 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FAME</term><def><p id="Par15">Fatty acid methyl ester</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FATA</term><def><p id="Par16">Fatty acyl-ACP thioesterase A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FPKM</term><def><p id="Par17">Fragments per kilobase of exon model per million mapped fragments</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>G3P</term><def><p id="Par18">Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC-TOF/MS</term><def><p id="Par19">Gas chromatography time-of-flight mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPAT</term><def><p id="Par20">Glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPD1</term><def><p id="Par21">Glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KAR</term><def><p id="Par22">3-ketoacyl-ACP reductase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KAS II</term><def><p id="Par23">3-ketoacyl-ACP synthase II</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LPAT</term><def><p id="Par24">Lysophosphatidic acid acyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MUFA</term><def><p id="Par25">Monounsaturated fatty acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PDAT</term><def><p id="Par26">phospholipid diacylglycerol acyltransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PUFA</term><def><p id="Par27">Polyunsaturated fatty acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SFA</term><def><p id="Par28">Saturated fatty acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TAG</term><def><p id="Par29">Triacylglycerol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TIC</term><def><p id="Par30">Total ion chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UBQ5</term><def><p id="Par31">Ubiquitin 5</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WRI1</term><def><p id="Par32">WRINKLED1</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Jinyou Shan and Ke Tang for their assistance in collecting plant materials.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par74">This work was financially supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31570681 and 31800574). CR, the funder of NSF (31570681) conceived this study. JD, the funder of NSF (31800574), Dalian Minzu University Doctor Scientific Research Foundation (0701110152), and University Innovation Groups Foundation of Dalian (201865) performed the experiments and wrote the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par75">The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JD designed and carried out the experiment of this study, and wrote the manuscript. CR conceived the study. WD and YG carried out the experiment of this study. All authors read and approved the manuscript in its final form.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par76">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par77">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par78">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><notes><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par79">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumpunen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nybom</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in improvement of quality and resistance in a multipurpose crop: sea buckthorn</article-title><source>Crit Rev Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22676076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of oil contents and fatty acid composition between developing sea buckthorn pulp and seed</article-title><source>China Oil and Fats</source><year>2017</year><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>144</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid composition of lipids in sea buckthorn (<italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> L.) berries of different origins</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>49</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1939</fpage><lpage>1947</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11308350?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11308350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Datla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wishart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid composition of developing sea buckthorn (<italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> L.) berry and the transcriptome of the mature seed</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e34099</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22558083?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22558083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira da Silva</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NMR metabolomics of berry quality in sea buckthorn (<italic>Hippophae</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Mol Breeding</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teleszko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojdylo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudzinska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oszmianski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Golis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of lipophilic and hydrophilic bioactive compounds content in sea buckthorn (<italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> L.) berries</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>4120</fpage><lpage>4129</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25893239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25893239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gornas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Misina</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Seglina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tocopherol and tocotrienol contents in the sea buckthorn berry beverages in Baltic countries: impact of the cultivar</article-title><source>Fruits.</source><year>2016</year><volume>71</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>405</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis and metabolic engineering of palmitoleate production, an important contributor to human health and sustainable industry</article-title><source>Prog Lipid Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>51</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22658963?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22658963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roizen</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purified palmitoleic acid for the reduction of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein and serum lipids: a double-blinded, randomized, placebo controlled study</article-title><source>J Clin Lipidol</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25499944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25499944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis reveals crucial genes involved in the biosynthesis of nervonic acid in woody <italic>Malania oleifera</italic> oilseeds</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>247</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30340521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30340521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sea buckthorn as a source of important bioactive compounds in cardiovascular diseases</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2016</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27616182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27616182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bondaruk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Degafu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boora</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilodeau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of a cDNA encoding palmitoyl-acyl carrier protein desaturase from cat's claw (<italic>Doxantha unguis-cati</italic> L.) in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Brassiea napus</italic> leads to accumulation of unusual unsaturated fatty acids and increased stearic acid content in the seed oil</article-title><source>Plant Breed</source><year>2007</year><volume>126</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>194</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vickery</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fatty acid composition of seed oils of proteaceae: a chemotaxonomic study</article-title><source>Phytochemistry.</source><year>1971</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gummeson</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stymne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterisation of acyl-ACP desaturases from <italic>Macadamia integrifolia</italic> Maiden &#x00026; Betche and <italic>Nerium oleander</italic> L</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10725558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The significance of different diacylglycerol synthesis pathways on plant oil composition and bioengineering</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>147</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22783267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22783267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis of the oil-rich tea plant, <italic>Camellia oleifera</italic>, reveals candidate genes related to lipid metabolism</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>e104150</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25136805?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25136805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourgis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilaru</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngando-Ebongue</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Drira</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative transcriptome and metabolite analysis of oil palm and date palm mesocarp that differ dramatically in carbon partitioning</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><issue>44</issue><fpage>12527</fpage><lpage>12532</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21709233?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21709233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilaru</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid and associated gene expression analyses of three tree peony species reveal key genes for &#x003b1;-linolenic acid synthesis in seeds</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>106</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29459881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29459881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigeolas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Geigenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased levels of glycerol-3-phosphate lead to a stimulation of flux into triacylglycerol synthesis after supplying glycerol to developing seeds of <italic>Brassica napus</italic> L. in planta</article-title><source>Planta.</source><year>2004</year><volume>219</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15107995?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15107995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>DGAT1</italic>, <italic>DGAT2</italic> and <italic>PDAT</italic> expression in seeds and other tissues of epoxy and hydroxy fatty acid accumulating plants</article-title><source>Lipids.</source><year>2010</year><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20101470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20101470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WRINKLED1 rescues feedback inhibition of fatty acid synthesis in hydroxylase-expressing seeds</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>171</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27208047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Haq</surname><given-names>BU</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Soybean LEC2 regulates subsets of genes involved in controlling the biosynthesis and catabolism of seed storage substances and seed development</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28979275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28979275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elahi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stasolla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased seed oil production in FUSCA3 <italic>Brassica napus</italic> mutant plants</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><year>2015</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26302483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26302483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Banas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stymne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid distribution and lipid metabolism in developing seeds of laurate-producing rape (<italic>Brassica napus</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Planta.</source><year>1997</year><volume>203</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9431681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9431681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soybean oil: genetic approaches for modification of functionality and total content</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19783644?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19783644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of key genes involved in lipid biosynthesis and accumulation during seeds formation and development in <italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic></article-title><source>Acta Bot Boreal -Occident Sin.</source><year>2016</year><volume>36</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1642</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Salcedo</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sendra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbonell-Barrachina</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acids composition of Spanish black (<italic>Morus nigra</italic> L.) and white (<italic>Morus alba</italic> L.) mulberries</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2016</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26213011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26213011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordinated regulation mechanism of multigenes involved in high accumulation of C18 unsaturated fatty acids in sea buckthorn seed</article-title><source>Acta Bot Boreal -Occident Sin</source><year>2017</year><volume>37</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1080</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome using Illumina sequencing reveals the traits of spermatogenesis and developing testes in <italic>Eriocheir sinensis</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e0172478</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28212420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28212420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>644</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21572440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3322381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatusov</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Natale</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garkavtsev</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatusova</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankavaram</surname><given-names>UT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The COG database: new developments in phylogenetic classification of proteins from complete genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11125040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The KEGG resource for deciphering the genome</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>D277</fpage><lpage>D280</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14681412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14681412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method</article-title><source>Methods.</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11846609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of microRNAs involved in lipid biosynthesis and seed size in developing sea buckthorn seeds using high-throughput sequencing</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>4022</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29507325?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29507325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of yeast acyl-CoA-&#x02206;9 desaturase leads to accumulation of unusual monounsaturated fatty acids in soybean seeds</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2013</year><volume>35</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23397267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23397267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Troncoso-Ponce</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthole</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tremblais</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><collab>To A</collab><name><surname>Miquel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional activation of two delta-9 palmitoyl-ACP desaturase genes by MYB115 and MYB118 is critical for biosynthesis of omega-7 monounsaturated fatty acids in the endosperm of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>28</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2666</fpage><lpage>2682</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27681170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27681170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ettaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Troncoso-Ponce</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><collab>To A</collab><name><surname>Barthole</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of <italic>MYB115</italic>, <italic>AAD2</italic>, or <italic>AAD3</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seeds yields contrasting omega-7 contents</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0192156</fpage><?supplied-pmid 29381741?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29381741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cakir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil and fatty acid composition of the fruits of <italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> L. (sea buckthorn) and <italic>Myrtus communis</italic> L. from Turkey</article-title><source>Biochem Syst Ecol</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>816</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dulf</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acids in berry lipids of six sea buckthorn (<italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> L., subspecies carpatica) cultivars grown in Romania</article-title><source>Chem Cent J</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>106</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22995716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22995716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranjitha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarin-Kumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Venugopalan</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Arumughan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawhney</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acids, tocols, and carotenoids in pulp oil of three sea buckthorn species (<italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic>, <italic>H. salicifolia</italic>, and <italic>H. tibetana</italic>) grown in the Indian Himalayas</article-title><source>J Am Oil Chem Soc</source><year>2006</year><volume>83</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>364</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of fatty acid profiles in fifteen kinds of edible vegetable oil by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Food Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>214</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlsson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Stymne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Horfvander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Replacing fossil oil with fresh oil - with what and for what?</article-title><source>Eur J Lipid Sci Technol</source><year>2011</year><volume>113</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22102794?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22102794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>De novo</italic> assembly and characterization of the fruit transcriptome of <italic>Idesia polycarpa</italic> reveals candidate genes for lipid biosynthesis</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>801</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27375655?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27375655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of yeast acyl-CoA-&#x02206;9 desaturase for fatty acids biosynthesis in tobacco</article-title><source>Chin J Biotech</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>645</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Warden</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>El Tahchy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative lipidomics and proteomics of lipid droplets in the mesocarp and seed tissues of Chinese tallow (<italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>)</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><?supplied-pmid 28824675?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28824675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of triacylglycerols of seeds and berries of sea buckthorn (<italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic>) of different origins by mass spectrometry and tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Lipids.</source><year>2006</year><volume>41</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16808152?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16808152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of genetic relationships in sea buckthorn (<italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic>) germplasm from China and other countries using ISSR markers</article-title><source>J Hortic Sci Biotechnol</source><year>2015</year><volume>90</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shanklin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerville</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stearoyl-acyl-carrier-protein desaturase from higher plants is structurally unrelated to the animal and fungal homologs</article-title><source>Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1991</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>2510</fpage><lpage>2514</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modification of the fatty acid composition in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and maize seeds using a stearoyl-acyl carrier protein desaturase-1 (<italic>ZmSAD1</italic>) gene</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>137</fpage><?supplied-pmid 27297560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27297560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pidkowich</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlo</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolic engineering of seeds can achieve levels of omega-7 fatty acids comparable with the highest levels found in natural plant sources</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>154</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1897</fpage><lpage>1904</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20943853?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20943853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of overexpression of MucACP-&#x00394;9 desaturase on lipid synthesis in tobacco leaves tissuse</article-title><source>Plant Physiol J</source><year>2016</year><volume>52</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1333</fpage><lpage>1340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid composition of developing tree peony (<italic>Paeonia section Moutan</italic> DC.) seeds and transcriptome analysis during seed development</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>208</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25887415?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pidkowich</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ischebeck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanklin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulating seed beta-ketoacyl-acyl carrier protein synthase II level converts the composition of a temperate seed oil to that of a palm-like tropical oil</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4742</fpage><lpage>4747</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17360594?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and expression of a stearoyl-ACP desaturase gene responsible for oleic acid accumulation in <italic>Xanthoceras sorbifolia</italic> seeds which plays a key role in determining the ratio of saturated to unsaturated fatty acids</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Bioch</source><year>2014</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sellwood</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Slabas</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawsthorne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of manipulating expression of acetyl-CoA carboxylase I in <italic>Brassica napus</italic> L. embryos</article-title><source>Biochem Soc Trans</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11171139?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11171139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Status of oil content control in seed by genetic regulation and the strategy for improving the gene of <italic>Kosteletzkya</italic> for biodiesel production</article-title><source>Renew Energy Resour</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Remize</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnavon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dequin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glycerol export and glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase, but not glycerol phosphatase, are rate limiting for glycerol production in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title><source>Metab Eng</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11676566?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11676566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanism of the extended oil accumulation phase contributing to the high seed oil content for the genotype of tung tree (<italic>Vernicia fordii</italic>)</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>248</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30340540?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30340540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Two novel diacylglycerol acyltransferase genes from <italic>Xanthoceras sorbifolia</italic> are responsible for its seed oil content</article-title><source>Gene.</source><year>2013</year><volume>527</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23769928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23769928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigeolas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldeck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorsten</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Geigenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing seed oil content in oil-seed rape (<italic>Brassica napus</italic> L.) by over-expression of a yeast glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase under the control of a seed-specific promoter</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17430545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17430545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A cytosolic NAD<sup>+</sup>-dependent GPDH from maize (<italic>ZmGPDH1</italic>) is involved in conferring salt and osmotic stress tolerance</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>16</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30626322?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chhikara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhankher</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering <italic>Camelina sativa</italic> (L.) Crantz for enhanced oil and seed yields by combining diacylglycerol acyltransferase1 and glycerol-3-phosphate dehydrogenase expression</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1034</fpage><lpage>1045</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28975735?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28975735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jako</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Giblin</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Seed-specific over-expression of an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cDNA encoding a diacylglycerol acyltransferase enhances seed oil content and seed weight</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11402213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11402213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Naresh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seed-specific overexpression of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> DGAT1 in Indian mustard (<italic>Brassica juncea</italic>) increases seed oil content and seed weight</article-title><source>Botany.</source><year>2015</year><volume>94</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>184</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative transcriptome analysis of lipid biosynthesis in seeds and non-seed tissues of sea buckthorn</article-title><source>Genes Genom</source><year>2017</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1033</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanhercke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahchy</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XR</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic effect of WRI1 and DGAT1 coexpression on triacylglycerol biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2013</year><volume>587</volume><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23313251?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23313251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Glassman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of <italic>ZmLEC1</italic> and <italic>ZmWRI1</italic> increases seed oil production in maize</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>987</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20488892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20488892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increasing seed mass and oil content in transgenic <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by the overexpression of <italic>wri1</italic>-like gene from <italic>Brassica napus</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><year>2010</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19828328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Focks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wrinkled1: a novel, low-seed-oil mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> with a deficiency in the seed-specific regulation of carbohydrate metabolism</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9733529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evaluation for introduced sea buckthorn adaptation of the third Russia&#x02019;s generation in northeast black soil area</article-title><source>Global Seabuckthorn Res Dev</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>