<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The main advantages of utilizing hyperspectral data are that detailed spectral profiles can be developed for native and non-native plants, and that specific spectral regions can be analyzed that are most sensitive to the abundance of the species of interest [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52-sensors-09-04869">52</xref>]. Williams and Hunt [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53-sensors-09-04869">53</xref>] applied a specialized spectral mixture analysis (SMA) to enhance the spectral signals of a European herbaceous perennial plant 
 <italic>Euphorbia esula</italic> from AVIRIS images of the Great Plains, USA. The result was correlated with field data, but the model agreement was also influenced by topography and vegetation types. With the enhancement of remote sensing data acquisition and processing procedures (e.g., see details of AVIRIS instruments, platforms and pre-processing procedures: URL: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aviris.jpl.nasa.gov/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://aviris.jpl.nasa.gov/</ext-link>), a hyperspectral sensor can now acquire images with a very fine GSI flown at low altitude. For instance, researchers detected European herbaceous plants (
 <italic>E. esula</italic> and 
 <italic>Cardaria dra</italic>) in low density (∼ 10%) settings in Idaho, USA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54-sensors-09-04869">54</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55-sensors-09-04869">55</xref>], and precisely identified several riparian and aquatic weeds in Northern California, USA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56-sensors-09-04869">56</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57-sensors-09-04869">57</xref>] using the HyMAP (GSI ≤ 3.5 m) sensor. Miao 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58-sensors-09-04869">58</xref>] applied SMA to extract signals of an annual Eurasian weed 
 <italic>Centaurea solstitialis</italic> in Northern California from CASI-2 (GSI = 3 m) selected bands by referring to data dimension reduction analyses.
</p>
