<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Uses of hyperspectral data are not limited to studies of the presence and/or abundance of alien species, but can be further extended to study the invasion-induced alteration of nutrient fluxes in ecosystems, and also the relationships between alien and native plant spectral profiles and leaf pigment, nutrient and structural properties. Asner and Vitousek [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59-sensors-09-04869">59</xref>] combined AVIRIS measures and photon transport modeling to investigate how non-native N-fixing tree 
 <italic>M. faya</italic> and Himalayan understory herb 
 <italic>Hedychium gardnerianum</italic> altered the chemistry of forest canopies across a Hawaiian montane rain forest landscape. They found that 
 <italic>M. faya</italic> significantly increased canopy N concentrations and water content in invaded sites. In contrast, 
 <italic>H. gardnerianum</italic> substantially reduced N concentrations in the overstory tree canopies and enhanced aboveground water content. Once 
 <italic>M. faya</italic> dominated a system, the species also affected nitrification and N-oxide emissions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60-sensors-09-04869">60</xref>]. Asner 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61-sensors-09-04869">61</xref>] further studied the uniqueness of hyperspectral signatures of 43 Hawaiian native and alien (invasive and non-invasive) trees. They found that: (
 <italic>i</italic>) Non-native N-fixing trees were spectrally unique from other groups of non-fixing trees; (
 <italic>ii</italic>) there were detectable spectral differences in highly invasive trees in comparison to other introduced plants; and (
 <italic>iii</italic>) there were relationships between the observed differences in canopy spectral signatures and relative differences in measured leaf pigments, nutrients, and structural and biophysical properties. They concluded that it is possible to utilize the full AVIRIS spectrum to differentiate these three Hawaiian tree groups, which they exercised in a subsequent operational mapping study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62-sensors-09-04869">62</xref>].
</p>
