<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Expression analysis of antioxidant enzymes genes and abiotic stress-responsive genes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The expression levels of APX gene, 3 SOD genes and 4 genes conferring tolerance to salinity (bZIP62, DREB2, ERF3, and OLPb) were assessed in the rosemary plants subjected to different SA treatments (0, 100, 200, 300 ppm) under different saline conditions (640, 2,000, 4,000 ppm). The results showed that the APX and 3 SOD genes revealed higher levels in SA-treated rosemary under saline, with respect to non-sprayed plants (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">4</a>), indicating the important roles of salicylic acid and antioxidant enzymes under abiotic stresses. SA treatment at 3,000 ppm showed the highest expression level for all the antioxidant enzymes genes.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Gene expression levels of APX 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span>, Cu/ZnSOD 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span>, FeSOD 
    <span class="bold">(C)</span>, and MnSOD 
    <span class="bold">(D)</span> in rosemary plants subjected to different SA treatments under saline conditions. Data are means ± 
    <span class="italic">SD</span> (
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 3).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fphys-08-00716-g0004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, the expression levels of the genes conferring tolerance to salinity (bZIP62, DREB2, ERF3, and OLPb) were evaluated using qRT-PCR. All the genes revealed higher levels in SA-treated rosemary under salt stress, as compared to non-sprayed plants (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">5</a>). SA treatment at 3,000 ppm showed the highest expression level for all the stress-related genes. This indicates that SA treatment modulated the abiotic stress responsive gene expression in rosemary which in turn enhanced its tolerance to salinity stress.
 </p>
 <div id="F5" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Gene expression levels of bZIP62 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span>, DREB2 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span>, ERF3 
    <span class="bold">(C)</span>, and OLPb 
    <span class="bold">(D)</span> in rosemary plants subjected to different SA treatments under saline conditions. Data are means ± 
    <span class="italic">SD</span> (
    <span class="italic">n</span> = 3).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fphys-08-00716-g0005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
