<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Salinity as abiotic stress is a permanent major threat to the agriculture industry worldwide and usually associated with morphological (e.g., reduced growth and productivity), physiological (e.g., reduction of gas exchange parameters and homeostasis), and biochemical (e.g., oxidative stress with elevated reactive oxygen species content) responses (Nazar et al., 
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">2011</a>; Gupta and Huang, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">2014</a>; Khan et al., 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2014</a>; Acosta-Motos et al., 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">2017</a>; Quan et al., 
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">2017</a>). The accumulation of Na
  <span class="sup">+</span> and Cl
  <span class="sup">−</span> during saline conditions is a detrimental factor that may lead to ion imbalance, ion toxicity, and physiological disorder (Gupta and Huang, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">2014</a>). Several approaches had been adopted to control salinity adverse effects on plants including breeding programs and utilization of transgenic plants (Bhatnagar-Mathur et al., 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">2008</a>), chemical priming (Savvides et al., 
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">2016</a>), microorganisms (Jha et al., 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2011</a>), and salicylic acid (Fayez and Bazaid, 
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Salicylic acid (SA) plays a crucial role in plant development, disease resistance, stress tolerance, and fruit yield (Horváth et al., 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">2007</a>; Rivas-San Vicente and Plasencia, 
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">2011</a>; Liu et al., 
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">2015</a>). Several investigations indicated that salicylic acid influences gas exchange parameters and water composition (Stevens et al., 
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">2006</a>), increases phenolics accumulation (Kovácik et al., 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">2009</a>), enhances the oxidative stress tolerance (Li et al., 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">2014</a>), and may alleviate osmotic stress (Nazar et al., 
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">2011</a>). SA effects are largely dependent on genetic and environmental factors (Idrees et al., 
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">2010</a>) as well as on method and dose of application (Horváth et al., 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">2007</a>). Some investigations indicated that plant secondary metabolites might be influenced by SA treatments such as the essential oils in 
  <span class="italic">Ocimum basilicum</span> L. (Mirzajani et al., 
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">2015</a>), oleoresins in 
  <span class="italic">Pinus</span> (Rodrigues and Fett-Neto, 
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">2009</a>), and triterpenes in 
  <span class="italic">Nigella</span> (Elyasi et al., 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinallis</span> L. (Lamiaceae), commercially known as rosemary, is produced in the Mediterranean region such as in Egypt (Domokos et al., 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">1997</a>; Elansary and Mahmoud, 
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">2015</a>). Rosemary leaves are consumed fresh or dried and might be used for essential oils production as well as for cosmetic and pharmaceutical industries (Elansary et al., 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">2015</a>; Habtemariam, 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">2016</a>). Previous investigations have shown that rosemary has antioxidant, antibacterial and anticancer activities (Bozin et al., 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">2007</a>; Elansary and Mahmoud, 
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">2015</a>). However, there is insufficient information on rosemary bioactivity and its anti-oxidative mechanisms during salt stress and SA treatments. Therefore, the main objective of this study was to investigate the effect of exogenous SA treatment on rosemary performance under saline conditions. Several important traits of rosemary such as morphological (e.g., plant heights, branches number, and fresh and dry weights), physiological (essential oil ratio and constitutes, phenolics, carbohydrates, chlorophyll, proline, and Na
  <span class="sup">+</span> and Cl
  <span class="sup">−</span> of leaves), biochemical (antioxidant mechanisms) and genetic (expression of antioxidants genes and genes conferring tolerance to salinity) markers have been investigated in this study. Furthermore, the inhibitory activities against wide spectrum bacteria were investigated as an economic application.
 </p>
</sec>
