<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>Following its first detection in North Italy in 2012, 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> has become a serious threat in many crops, including hazelnut. Since favorite host plants and dispersal behavior of overwintered adults of 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> before crop colonization are little known, research was carried out in four polyculture areas (from 14 to 50 ha) in north-western Italy in 2018, by using (i) pheromone-baited traps, (ii) visual inspection and beating sheet sampling, and (iii) immunomarking-capture technique. After overwintering, adults responded to pheromone; the host plants of the same species hosted higher numbers of 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> when they were near a pheromone trap. Adults were capable of both short- and long-range dispersal from overwintering sites and/or early host plants to wild and crop plants. Their movement patterns depended on the ecosystem features, and plant host distribution and availability. This knowledge together with the interaction between pheromone and early host plants might contribute to the management of post-overwintering adults before crop colonization.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>Following its first detection in North Italy in 2012, 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> has become a serious threat in many crops, including hazelnut. The present study aimed at investigating dispersal capacity and behavior in relation to host plants of overwintered adults of 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> before the colonization of hazelnut crop. Research was carried out in four polyculture areas (from 14 to 50 ha) in north-western Italy in 2018, by using (i) pheromone-baited traps, (ii) visual inspection and beating sheet sampling, and (iii) immunomarking-capture technique. The relative abundance of 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> was similar between and within the study areas, and the early attractiveness of lures to adults after overwintering was confirmed; the host plants near a pheromone trap (less than 5 m) hosted higher numbers of 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> than the same plant species far away. Hybrid plane, European spindletree, walnut, oak, and European elder were the first plants on which adult bugs were observed to feed. By immunomarking-capture technique, 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> showed both short- and long-range dispersal from overwintering sites and/or early host plants to wild and crop plants. Marked adults were found in all zones of each area, irrespective of the distance from the protein treatment. Therefore, 
   <italic>H. halys</italic> movement patterns depend on the ecosystem features, and plant host distribution and availability. This knowledge together with the interaction between pheromone and early host plants might contribute to the management of post-overwintering adults.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
