<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Supportive Effect of
  <span class="italic"> C. operculatus</span> Essential Oil on Burn Wound Model
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that both tamanu oil and essential oil accelerated the wound contraction rate of burn wound after 10 days and 20 days (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05). At the beginning of the experiment, all burn wounds were of similar sizes in three groups. In day 10, burn wound areas of tamanu oil and CLO treated mice (0.57 ± 0.04 and 0.43 ± 0.03 mm
  <span class="sup">2</span>, accordingly) were smaller than saline treated group (0.73 ± 0.04 cm
  <span class="sup">2</span>), and the significant difference of wound contraction between tamanu oil and essential oil treated mice was observed (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05). Furthermore, essential oil group was fully recovered whereas the burn areas of tamanu oil treated and control groups remained after 20 days. Of note, wound healing process of tamanu oil treated mice was also significantly higher than control mice at this time-point (0.22 ± 0.03 versus 0.31 ± 0.02 cm
  <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05). These results implied that
  <span class="italic"> C. operculatus </span>essential oil has supportive effect on wound healing process and its efficiency was higher than the commercial tamanu oil (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For reconfirmation of efficiency of essential oil on wound healing process, we investigated the microscopic structure of skin from burn wounds treated with essential oil, tamanu oil, and saline via histological examination (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Figure 5</a>). Histology studies revealed that burn wounds treated with essential oil developed complete epidermal structure: squamous epithelium covered on epidermis, the stratum spinosum keratinized, observation of matured hair follicles, thick and neatly arranged fibers, and scattered immune cells. That proved that burn wound treated with essential oil was fully recovered. In tamanu oil treated mice, wounds were partially recovered with existence of coagulative necrosis region on epidermis and vascular congestion, swollen stromal tissue, and no matured hair follicles. On the contrary, saline treated mice formed uneven epidermal layer with the necrotic ulcer on epidermis layer, infiltration of lymphocytes, plasmatocytes and multinuclear leukocytes, existence of granulation tissue, and fibrosis region. These results suggested that
  <span class="italic"> C. operculatus </span>essential oil did not only accelerate the wound healing rate but also helped the wound recovery with normal structure.
 </p>
</sec>
