<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Collection and Preparation of
   <span class="italic"> Cleistocalyx operculatus</span> Essential Oil
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Cleistocalyx operculatus</span> leaves were purchased from local herbal supplier in Go Vap District, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam (Thanh Binh Medicinal Plants and Herbals Co., Vietnam). Air-dried and ground leaves were subjected to hydrodistillation for 4 hours at 100°C in 15% NaCl solution using a Clevenger apparatus [
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">20</a>]. The essential oils were collected over aqueous phase amd transferred into 1.5 mL tube, after which essential oil was stored in dark chamber at 4°C prior to GC/MS analysis and bioactivities testing.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry (GC-MS) Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GC-MS analysis of the essential oil was performed at Department of Analytical Chemistry, University of Science, Vietnam National University of Ho Chi Minh City with the given protocol. Briefly, chemical compositions of essential oil were analyzed on a GC-MS Aligent 6890 system equipped with a splitless mode injector and DB–5MS column (30 m × 0.25 mm ID, film thickness 0.25 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m from Aligent Technologies, USA). The GC injector temperature was set at 250°C. A 1 mL volume of 2,000 ppm oil solution (1 hot water: 10 methanol) was injected. Helium in constant pressure was used as carrier gas at flow rate of 1.0 mL/min. The oven initial temperature was maintained 60°C for 1 min and heated at 10°C/min until oven temperature reached 200°C, and the oven was kept in this temperature for 5 min. Then oven was heated at 20°C/min to 280°C and then kept for 1 min. The temperature of transfer line was set at 280°C. For GC-MS analysis, an electron ionization with ionization energy of 1700 eV was used, covering a mass range from 40 to 450 mz. The compounds were identified by NIST MS Search version 2.0.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Antimicrobial Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antimicrobial activity of essential oil was determined by the agar diffusion method. The following bacterial strains
   <span class="italic"> Staphylococcus aureus</span> ATCC 6538 and
   <span class="italic"> Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> ATCC 9027, which are considered as two common opportunistic bacteria in skin and mucous membrane [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">21</a>], were employed for screening the antimicrobial activity of
   <span class="italic"> C. operculatus </span>essential oil. Briefly, the tested microorganisms (0.1 ml of 1 × 10
   <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/ml) were inoculated on LB agar. Then the sterilized filter paper discs (6 mm in diameter) were impregnated with 20 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L of
   <span class="italic"> Cleistocalyx operculatus</span> essential oil or tamanu oil. The discs were placed in LB agar plates, after which the plates were incubated at 37°C for 24 hours. The commercial antibiotic discs (Gentamycin, Nam Khoa Biotek Co.) and tamanu oil (Inopilo, Binh Minh Pharmaceutical Joint Co. Ltd.) were used as positive controls. The diameters of inhibition zones were measured in millimeters.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Establishment of Burned Mouse Model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eight-week-old male Swiss albino mice were obtained from Pasteur Institute of Ho Chi Minh City, weighing approximately 30–32 g. The animals were randomly divided into polycarbonate cages with 4 mice for each cage. They were housed under standard husbandry conditions with 12 h light-dark cycle (8:00–20:00) for at least 1 week to acclimate with laboratory environment. They were supplied ad libitum with standard chow and distilled water. The experimental procedure was strictly in compliance with the Declaration of Helsinki (1964). Briefly, twelve healthy mice were randomly divided into 3 groups with 4 mice per group and treated as the protocol of Tavares Pereira et al. (2012) with some modifications [
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">22</a>]. Mice were anesthetized with diethyl ether for 3 min, then the hair on back of mice was removed using razor. The dorsal proximal region was antisepsis with polyvinyl pyrrolidone iodine. Thermal lesion was generated by a massive aluminum bar 10 mm in diameter preheated to 100 ± 5°C/10 min. The probe was kept to contact with mouse skin for 15 sec. After that, the burn wound was treated with an indicated volume of saline, tamanu oil, or diluted
   <span class="italic"> C. operculatus</span> essential oil (50 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l/lesion) once per day for 20 days. Tamanu oil (Inopilo, Binh Minh Pharmaceutical Joint Co. Ltd.) was used as reference treatment. Diluted
   <span class="italic"> C. operculatus</span> essential oil (1% solution) was prepared by dissolving the essential oil in 0.1% DMSO and Tween 20 solution. The burned area of mice was measured after 10 days and 20 days and the results were presented as square centimeter (cm
   <span class="sup">2</span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Histological Study</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the end of experiment (20 days), all mice were anesthetized with diethyl ether and then euthanized by carbon dioxide. The skin of burned area was collected and preserved in 10% formalin. The sample was processed for histological studies with Hematoxylin and Eosin staining in Division of Pathological Anatomy, the Cancer Diagnosis and Treatment Centre of Military Hospital 175 with given protocol [
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">23</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All experiments were repeated in triplicate. Statistical analysis was performed using Statgraphics Centurion XVI software (Statpoint Technologies Inc., Warrenton, Virginia, USA). The data were presented as mean ± standard deviation. Differences between means of different groups were analyzed using ANOVA variance analysis followed with multiple range tests, and the criterion of statistical significance was set as 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
