<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to our results, it is expected that increasing N deposition in soil causes completion of germination-dependent drift in seedling recruitments. As soil N content rises up to maximal values observed in inland sand dunes, disappearance of 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>vulgare</italic>, 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>perforatum</italic> and 
 <italic>J</italic>. 
 <italic>montana</italic> can be predicted. Increase in N can cause alternations in micro-habitats, negatively affecting ability to complete germination of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>minima</italic>, 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>montanum</italic>, 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>arenarium</italic> and 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>morisonii</italic> seeds. This leads to the conclusion, that germination requirements of these species are fitted to low N status of poor soils (e.g. Podzols). Similar conclusion was drawn regarding some woodland species from Spain [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and some species from temperate thermophilous oak forest [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Only a few of the species we studied (
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>scabiosa</italic>, 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> and 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>radicata</italic>) can efficiently complete germination under high N concentrations, even in 100 mM NH
 <sub>4</sub>NO
 <sub>3</sub> solution. As 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] and 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>radicata</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] were listed as invasive species, these results partially explain their invasiveness but also show their capability of fast and successful establishment in a wide range of environmental conditions, including inland sand dunes (also those in advanced succession stage). In the case of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>scabiosa</italic>, ability to complete germination in a wide range of conditions observed in our study supports the conception of ‘stress-tolerance’ strategy of this species [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], but probably not inclinations for invasive behavior (due to stable FGP &lt; 50%). It must be however highlighted that data pertaining to multi-species comparisons should be interpreted with caution due to possible dissonance between results of experiments conducted under a given conditions and individual optima of the species. Low germination indices observed in the presented study in several species subjected to control conditions suggest that 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions (physical and/or chemical factors) do not fully match environmental optimum for completion of germination [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
