<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results suggest that 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>montanum</italic> does not tolerate NH
 <sub>4</sub>
 <sup>+</sup> as a sole N source, but this effect can be greatly minimized by an equivalent amount of NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup>, or even under specific circumstances (10 mM), additional NH
 <sub>4</sub>
 <sup>+</sup> can be beneficial. The presented study strongly suggests meso-stenotopic behavior of this species regarding both N type and dose. Surprisingly, we did not record completion of germination of this species in the control treatment (H
 <sub>2</sub>O). It is in contrast to the study [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] showing high completion of germination of seeds in distilled water. Such diametrical difference may be due to provenance of seeds, altered environmental conditions affecting development of seeds or to genetic differences between populations from various geographic locations, as it was reported for 
 <italic>Rumex crispus</italic> L. [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. However, the results similar to ours were presented before [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] regarding the study conducted in 32/20°C thermoperiod in 12/12 h photoperiod. In the same study lower temperature (20/10 and 8/4°C) greatly promoted completion of germination (100 and 56% respectively), which indicates thermoinhibition of germination process in this species. This shows that completion of germination in 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>montanum</italic> is under thermal control (this species needs at least cooler night temperature or temperatures characteristic of early spring) but adequate N type and dose substitute for those requirements. Very similar abolition of thermoinhibition by NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup> treatment was presented in the studies on 
 <italic>Lactuca sativa</italic> L. [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The authors pointed that the stimulant role of NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup> consisted in induction of NO-dependent signaling transduction pathways and suppression of ABA-dependent regulation of dormancy. This mutual antagonism of NO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>‒</sup>-dependent induction of germination and ABA-dependent suppression was widely described before [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. We can also see strong ecological advantage of this adaptation, as it allows to avoid failure of establishment, e.g. when seeds are deeply buried in sandy soil (low N status [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]) or sown on bare sand (temperature exceeding thermal requirements for completion of germination; even up to 70°C [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]). Our observation can also partially explain why in central Europe (e.g. Poland) 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>montanum</italic> can be found on fluvial sands [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], which contain greater amount of nutrients (from alluvial deposits) than aeolic ones [
 <xref rid="pone.0244737.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. However, 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>montanum</italic> is often assigned as a species from alkaline xerothermic grasslands, thus in our opinion habitat preference of this species needs further elucidation.
</p>
