<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec>
  <title>Context</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Salvia semiatrata</italic> Zucc. (Lamiaceae) is a species used as a tranquilizer and to relieve pain in folk medicine in Santiago Huauclilla, Oaxaca, Mexico.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Objective</title>
  <p>To evaluate the antinociceptive and anxiolytic-like effects of 
   <italic>S. semiatrata</italic> extracts and identify a bioactive metabolite.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Materials and methods</title>
  <p>The extracts were obtained by maceration of 
   <italic>S. semiatrata</italic> aerial parts using solvents in increasing polarity (hexane, ethyl acetate and methanol). A 
   <italic>neo-</italic>clerodane diterpene was extracted from the ethyl acetate fraction using open column chromatography. Identification of this metabolite was performed by crystallography, 
   <sup>1</sup>H NMR, 
   <sup>13</sup>C NMR, ATR-IR, ECD, MS and elemental analysis. The antinociceptive activity was explored using the writhing and formalin tests. Whereas, the anxiolytic-like responses were analysed in the open-field, hole-board and plus-maze tests. All the treatments were administered using oral gavage in male CD1 mice and explored 30 min after administration of the individual extracts (300 mg/kg) or the compound 
   <bold>1</bold> (0.1, 1 or 10 mg/kg).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>All the extracts produced significant reduction in the nociceptive and anxiety-like behaviour compared to mice treated with the vehicle (0.5% tween 80 in saline solution). The spectroscopic analysis corroborated the presence of the 
   <italic>neo</italic>-clerodane diterpene 7-keto-neoclerodan-3,13-dien-18,19:15,16-diolide (
   <bold>1</bold>), as partial responsible of the antinociceptive and anxiolytic-like effects, which produced a dose-dependent response in the writhing test with an ED
   <sub>50</sub>=4.15 mg/kg.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Discussion and conclusions:</bold> These results reinforce the medicinal properties of 
   <italic>S. semiatrata</italic> in folk medicine, where participation of a 
   <italic>neo</italic>-clerodane diterpene was evidenced in the inhibitory central nervous system activity of this species.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
