<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Diets throughout the world are based on two dozen crops with a dominant proportion of the “big three” cereals: wheat (
 <italic class="italic">Triticum aestivum</italic>), maize 
 <italic class="italic">(Zea mays</italic>), and rice (
 <italic class="italic">Oryza sativa</italic>), which contribute to approximately 60% of the total caloric intake (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>). However, these crops may not intrinsically be the best-suited species to face up to extreme weather events that are becoming more frequent due to climate change; thus, world grain production per capita is expected to decline by at least 14% between 2008 and 2030 (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). The rapid growth of the world population and per capita food consumption worldwide puts great pressure on the food industry to produce more food (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>). The food supply must double by 2050 to counterbalance the effects of climate change and population pressure on global food systems and thus novel food sources must be found (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>). Less than 0.6% of plant species that are suitable for human consumption have reached the world markets (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>). The diversification of main crops and the systems in which they grow is essential for agriculture to be sustainable, resilient, and suitable for local environments and soils in the future. One critical measure to ensure future food availability for all is to provide more diverse food sources and develop agricultural systems that are resistant to climate change. Furthermore, the new challenge for the food industries and scientific areas such as chemistry, biology, medicine, pharmacology, and food technology is to obtain foods with a higher nutritional value that also possess functional properties which go beyond traditional health requirements. In response to this issue, one of the leading strategies is unlocking the potential of underutilized crops. Most of these crops have high nutritional value, resilience traits, with the ability to withstand drought, flooding, extreme temperatures, and pests and diseases better than current major staples and thus they should be investigated, developed, and now more than ever used (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>). Current emphasis is now placed on the use of ancient cereals and pseudocereals that include amaranth, buckwheat, quinoa, teff, millets amongst others.
</p>
