<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CHEMICAL RELATIONS OF COMPOUNDS AND BIOLOGICAL EFFECT</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the results of the other studies, 
  <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> genus is the source of phenolic compounds and flavonoids that they have strong antioxidant activity.[
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>
  <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>
  <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>] Phenolic compounds are the known representative of giving hydrogen to free radicals and thus break the chain reactions of oxidation of lipids in the first step. This high potential of phenolic compounds is to inhibit free radicals related to the phenolic hydroxyl group.[
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>] Thus, antioxidant properties of phenolic compounds depend on their ability to give electrons to trap and remove free radicals by the formation of stable phenoxyl compounds.[
  <a rid="ref86" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref86">86</a>] Antibacterial effects of essential oil of this plant can be associated with materials such as carvacrol, linalool, p-cymene, α-pinene, and terpinene.[
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>] In another study, the antibacterial activity of the essential oil was associated to ocimene, α-pinene, myrcene, and α-phellandrene.[
  <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">35</a>] Other research has shown that this plant has saponins, alkaloids, and flavonoids compounds, so it has the antibacterial and antifungal effect of 
  <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> methanol extract.[
  <a rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref33">33</a>] In other studies, the main components of essential oil in other reviews such as trans-β-ocimene, 2-furanone, myrcene, linalool, cis-β-ocimene,[
  <a rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref75">75</a>] asarone, anethole, eugenol, dimethyl styrene, dimethyl styrene isomer, nuciferol, cedran, and isosafrole have antibacterial effects.[
  <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">37</a>] Various chemical substances use multiple different mechanisms to destroy microorganisms. Among them, the most important feature of this group is its being hydrophobic so that by entry to the membrane of the bacteria cell and mitochondria, the performance of the cells disrupts and the permeability increases, and thus, ions and other cell compounds exit, which lead to the death of microorganisms.[
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>] The anticancer and cytotoxic activity of 
  <span class="italic">E. platyloba</span> has been reported because this plant is the rich source of monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and phytochemical compounds such as betulinic acid and ursolic acid, which lead to induce apoptosis or cell death.[
  <a rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref53">53</a>] Studies have shown that plant compounds such as flavonoids directly affect the pituitary gland, especially the part that secretes the hormone LH, and lead to increased levels of progesterone. This can result in somehow moderate disorders and consequently loss of hormones in the menstrual, such as premenstrual syndrome and dysmenorrhea.[
  <a rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref47">47</a>
  <a rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref54">54</a>
  <a rid="ref87" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref87">87</a>] Since the muscles in the human uterus are smooth muscles, the extract of this plant can probably apply its antispasmodic effect on it, resulting in the pain reduction during menstruation.[
  <a rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref57">57</a>] Compounds such as saponins, alkaloids, flavonoids, and terpenes in this plant can reduce body weight and blood fat and protect liver and kidney. Moreover, the extract of this plant has antioxidant compounds such as coumarin, polyacetylenes, flavonoids, sesquiterpenes, and phthalides which can reduce malondialdehyde and inhibits lipid peroxidation. On the other hand, lactase enzyme increases and enzymes in the liver decrease. Polyphenolic compounds and flavonoids can also revive the cells against glutathione depletion and protect them by increasing the capacity of anti-oxidant enzymes (glutathione, glutathione reductase, glutathione peroxidase, and catalase). Thus, it may strengthen the antioxidant properties to deal with oxidative stress may boost and may have protective effects on the liver and kidneys functioning. Some plant compounds through energy consumption and some compounds such as quercetin and linoleic acid inhibit adipogenesis and induce apoptosis in cells as lipid-lowering blood fat goes away. Moreover, the extract components (phytochemicals) may reduce fat absorption from food, proliferation, and differentiation of precursor fat cells to reduce energy consumption and increase the breakdown of fat accumulated in the body.[
  <a rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref60">60</a>] It seems that the analgesic effect of the extract is due to opioid receptors. Flavonoids by inhibiting the activity of N-methyl D-aspartate receptor activity reduce intracellular calcium followed by a decline in nitric oxide synthase enzyme activity and calcium-dependent phospholipase A
  <sub>2</sub> to secular. As a result, by the reduction of nitric oxide and prostaglandins, especially prostaglandin E
  <sub>2</sub> and F
  <sub>2</sub>α, they show analgesic effect. Moreover, analgesic effects of saponins inhibit the enzyme synthesis inducing analgesic effects of nitric oxide (iNOS) and cyclooxygenase synthesis (COX-2). Hence, the extract of 
  <span class="italic">E. platyloba</span> with both environmentally and centrally moderates pain leads to increased resistance to pain and decreased responsiveness to acute and chronic pains.[
  <a rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref65">65</a>] Flavonoids and phenolic compounds in the extracts of 
  <span class="italic">Echinophora</span> with their antioxidant effects increase the speed of healing of open ulcer of skin. Therefore, the topical use of an ointment containing 
  <span class="italic">E. platyloba</span> leaf extract boosts the main restoration phase cells (macrophages) and a significant increase in vascular regeneration in the first phase of wound healing. It can also reduce inflammation due to the antibacterial properties. In the second phase of wound healing process by cell proliferation due to increase in migration of fibroblasts and the beginning of regeneration of cover tissue and finally stage of wound healing, epithelial tissue significantly increases secretion of collagen at the wound site and the thickness of the coating and consequently increases the speed of recovery in the final process of wound healing.[
  <a rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref64">64</a>]
 </p>
</sec>
