<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>This study was possible with the help of friendly people from Artvin, Ardahan, Adjara and Samtskhe Javakheti who shared their knowledge and experience. We are grateful to them for their willingness to interview and allocating significant time for us. Heartfelt thanks to all of them. We would like to thank to our friends Nikita Ivanov, Shota Gelashvili, Nini Khuroshvili, Oli Lamm, Tamar Nadiradze, Sopo Kiknavelidze and Natalie Kuljanishvili for their translation of the interviews and field assistance during the surveys in Georgia. We also thank to our friends Zeynep Türkmen, Nihan Dilşad Dağtaş, Kasım Kırlangıç, Dr. Ali Haydar Altuğ, Muharrem Çavuşoğlu, Birsen Civelek, Utkan Bugay, Bilgen Kazancı and Çağla Kazancı for their valuable assistance and support during our fieldworks in Turkey. Many thanks to Prof. Özgür Eminağaoğlu and Dr. Hayal Akyıldırım Beğen for providing us a work environment in the Herbarium of Artvin Çoruh University in Turkey and for their help during identification of the plant specimens. Thanks to Çağatay Altın and Nature Conservation and National Park Branch of Ardahan for their concerns during our fieldwork in Turkey. Moreover, many thanks to Dr. Temur Vasadze, Dr. Nino Memiadze and the staff of the Batumi Botanical Garden, Goderdzi Alpine Botanical Garden; Dr. Manana Khutsishvili, Eto Svanidze, and the staff of the National Herbarium of Georgia, Javakheti Protected Areas Administration and Border police and army in Georgia. Many thanks to Prof. Zaal Kikvidze for his interest and kind support during funding applications in Georgia and to all funders including hundreds of nature and culture lovers who valued and made precious contributions to our study with their small drops via crowdfunding. We are also indebted to Dr. Füsun Ertuğ for her long-termed encouragement, love and support for our ethnobotanical research. We also appreciate the comments and suggestions of Dr. Marco Leonti and an anonymous reviewer from JEP, Dr. Andrea Pieroni and anonymous reviewers from JEE leading us to improve our manuscript. Many thanks to Claire Özel for her comment and efforts for the revision of the English.</p>
</ack>
