<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A subsequent research done by Tanaporn et al. further investigated the potential of 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> ethanolic extract on adiponectin secretion and explored the mechanism underlying the anti-adipogenesis effects exerted by the 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> ethanolic extract [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Adiponectin is a protein hormone involves in regulating glucose levels as well as fatty acid breakdown. This hormone also plays significant roles in the proliferation and differentiation of adipocytes by increasing the lipid accumulation and glucose transportation in adipocytes. The study found that 200 μg/mL 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> methanolic extract treatment was able to significantly lower the level of adiponectin by 2-fold as compared to the non-treated group. Decreased circulating adiponectin levels have been found to suppress the differentiation of 3T3-L1 pre-adipocytes to adipocytes. In addition, the researchers also proved that the 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> extract exerted anti-adipogenesis effects via the downregulation of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma 2 (PPARγ2), an adipocyte-specific nuclear hormone receptor which plays a crucial role in the differentiation of pre-adipocyte to mature adipocyte; sterol regulatory element-binding transcription factor 1c (SREBP-1c), a transcription factor which is required in fatty acid metabolism and de novo lipogenesis; fatty acid synthase (FAS), an enzyme which is the crucial for intracellular triglyceride synthesis; glucose transporter type 4 (GLUT-4), a glucose carrier protein which facilitates glucose transportation into the cells and last but not least, the leptin, a hormone which regulates appetite, food intake and body weight [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The inhibition of all these five key factors has been found to significantly prevent the adipogenic processes in 3T3-L1 cells. These results are the indicators that baicalein in 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> possess the anti-obesity potential and may be developed as a novel natural product-based product for obesity prevention.
</p>
