<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0535">This review included all of the microbial genetic content of genomics studies based on genome sequencing and bioinformatics analysis to reveal potential specific active targets for antigen discovery and support the production of known antibacterial agents and new vaccine strains. The first TB study was carried out on the MTB H37Rv strain. This study showed the attribution of specific functions (∼40% of 4000 genes). Once information was available for active genes, the exact target drug was determined on the basis of its proposed metabolic production pathway (
 <xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">Freiberg et al., 2004</xref>). Gene expression analysis may represent a helpful tool for achieving three goals in drug discovery: (i) determining specific targets, (ii) studying antibiotic activity and (iii) proposing new types of bioassays (
 <xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">Freiberg et al., 2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0570" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2013b</xref>). Extensive variations in genomic molecular targets lead to the different results of anti-TB drugs, and novel molecules should inhibit the active genes involved in the bacterial life cycle (
 <xref rid="b0975" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2006</xref>). Protein production is the last step in the molecular gene process. DNA chip technology is overcoming the problems of protein production, which can be considered as a key factor in antimycobacterial drug discovery (
 <xref rid="b0570" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2013b</xref>). Approximately 263 proteins from 
 <italic>M. bovis</italic> BCG and MTB strains have been determined through two-dimensional gel electrophoresis coupled with mass spectrometry. This protein analysis technique provides good results with the assistance of whole-genome sequence databases (
 <xref rid="b0565" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2013a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0940" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Marcotte, 2008</xref>). Different mechanisms that interrupt bacterial biosynthetic pathways, such as protein, cell wall and DNA synthesis pathways, are considered in the discovery of antitubercular agents with specific targets (
 <xref rid="b0615" ref-type="bibr">Manjunatha and Smith, 2015</xref>).
</p>
