<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The general description of moderate spatial/spectral resolution remote sensing involves data collection at a ground sampling interval (GSI) of 10-100 m in less than 20 channels (bands). Imagery such as from Landsat Thematic Mapper (TM)/Enhanced Thematic Mapper Plus (ETM+), Satellite Pour l'Observation de la Terre (SPOT) and Advanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission and Reflection Radiometer (ASTER) have been heavily utilized in studies of terrestrial vegetation. However, alien plants are often obscured in a backdrop of natural vegetation, and are thus difficult to discern using moderate spatial/spectral resolution images. We found a very limited amount of literature utilizing moderate resolution imagery to observe non-native plants; possibly the only way to make this type of data effective is to detect large stands and patches during the right phenological time for the species of concern. For example, Resasco 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22-sensors-09-04869">22</xref>] used Landsat TM and ETM+ images acquired in late fall to map an Asian understory shrub 
 <italic>Lonicera maackii</italic> in deciduous forests in Ohio, USA when overstory trees were leafless. Peterson [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23-sensors-09-04869">23</xref>] combined field survey data and multi-seasonal ETM+ images to estimate an annual Eurasian grass 
 <italic>Bromus tectorum</italic> in the Great Basin, USA using a specific regression model; the images were collected during the green (late April-early May) and senescent (late June, while native grasses were still green) time periods in 
 <italic>B. tectorum</italic>-infested grasslands. Groeneveld and Watson [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24-sensors-09-04869">24</xref>] used the late fall Landsat TM near-infrared band to map the branches of a Eurasian riparian tree 
 <italic>Tamarix ramosissima</italic> in Colorado, USA when the plants were leafless. Despite these successes, in most cases, observing alien plants requires data collected from sensors pushing the limits of at least one type of resolution (spatial, temporal or spectral resolution) since the profiles of these species may be quite similar to those of native plants, from a remote sensing perspective [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25-sensors-09-04869">25</xref>].
</p>
