<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">The assay for α-amylase inhibition was conducted using the process of 3,5-dinitrosalicylic acid (DNSA). Safrole oil was dissolved in a minimum of 10% DMSO and subsequently dissolved in the buffer (Na
 <sub>2</sub>HPO
 <sub>4</sub>/NaH
 <sub>2</sub>PO
 <sub>4</sub>; 0.02 M), NaCl (0.006 M) at pH 6.9 to yield 1000 μg/ml concentrations, from which the following dilution was prepared: 10, 50, 70, 100, 500 μg/ml. A 200 μl volume of the porcine pancreatic α-amylase enzyme solution (2 units / ml) was combined with 200 μl of safrole oil, and incubated at 30 °C for 10 min. Two hundred microlitres of the freshly prepared starch solution (1% in water [w/v]) was then added to each tube, and the solution was incubated for 3 min. Termination of the reaction was carried by adding 200 μl of DNSA reagent (12 g of sodium potassium tartrate tetrahydrate in 8.0 mL of 2 M NaOH and 20 mL of 96 mM of 3.5-dinitrosalicylic acid solution) and then diluted with 5 ml of distilled water and boiled in a water bath at 85–90 °C for 10 min. The mixture was cooled to ambient temperature. Then using a UV-Visible spectrophotometer, the absorbance was taken at 540 nm. The blank with 100% enzyme activity was primed with 200 μl of the buffer to replace the safrole oil. A blank reaction in the absence of the enzyme solution was similarly prepared using safrole oil at each concentration [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. By following the steps outlined above, a positive control sample was created using acarbose, and the reaction was similar to the reaction with plant fractions mentioned above The α-amylase inhibitory activity was expressed as the percent inhibition and was calculated using the equation given below: 
 <disp-formula id="Equb">
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{of}\ \alpha -\mathrm{amylase}\ \mathrm{inhibition}=\left(\mathrm{B}-\mathrm{S}\right)/\mathrm{B}\ast 100\% $$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M4" display="block">
    <mo>%</mo>
    <mtext>of</mtext>
    <mspace width="0.25em"/>
    <mi>α</mi>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mtext>amylase inhibition</mtext>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mfenced close=")" open="(">
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">B</mi>
      <mo>-</mo>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">S</mi>
     </mrow>
    </mfenced>
    <mo>/</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal">B</mi>
    <mo>∗</mo>
    <mn>100</mn>
    <mo>%</mo>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="12906_2021_3324_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
