<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemicals, plant material, and treatments</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All chemicals were HPLC grade (Sigma, Egypt). Uniform 
   <span class="italic">R. officinallis</span> L. plants that have 16 cm stems were obtained from local commercial nurseries. The plants were identified and voucher specimen were maintained at Alexandria University, Egypt. The plants were cultivated in a greenhouse and the experiments were repeated for two successive seasons in January 2016 and 2017. Plants were transplanted into 3.1 L pots containing coarse sand and 2 g L
   <span class="sup">−1</span> media of commercial compound fertilizer (Crystalon®, 19% N: 19% P: 19% K). Plants were maintained under moderate temperatures (15.1–24.5°C); relative humidity (68–81%) and photosynthetically active radiation (900 W m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> at 12.00 p.m.). The plants were irrigated with 250–300 mL plant
   <span class="sup">−1</span> of saline water every 2 days (640, 2,000, and 4,000 ppm NaCl) and 4 biweekly sprays of salicylic acid (SA) at 0, 100, 200, and 300 ppm until drop off for 8 weeks. Plants subjected to salinity of 640 ppm NaCl (tap water) and 0 ppm salicylic acid sprays were considered as control. The plants were distributed on three blocks and each treatment was represented by six replicates with a total number of plants of 216. After 8 weeks, plant heights (cm) were measured then all plants were harvested. Number of branches per plant was counted and the fresh weight (g) was measured then the dry weight (g) was obtained following drying at room temperature (20°C) as reported by Elansary and Mahmoud (
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">2015</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil extraction, GC-MS analysis, and preparation of leaf extracts</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For essential oil extraction, a Clevenger-type apparatus was used for the hydrodistillation of dried ground leaf samples for 1 h, then the oil was dried, filtered, and finally kept at 4°C in dark conditions (Elansary et al., 
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">2016</a>). The essential oils were subjected to Thermo Scientific Gas Chromatograph Mass Spectrometer equipped with TG-1MS column. The carrier gas was helium, and temperature ramped from 45–165°C at 4°C min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> for 2 min, then gradual increase to end temperature of 280°C for 15 min. The same column and temperatures were used for GC-FID analysis. Chemical compounds were identified using their retention time and retention indices of 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes (C
   <sub>10</sub>–C
   <sub>36</sub>) and computer matching using NIST mass spectra ver. 2.0 and WILEY libraries as well as literature references (Chalchat et al., 
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">1993</a>; Adams, 
   <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">2007</a>). For the preparation of leaf extracts, ground dried leaves were dissolved in methanol (99%, 3 mL), maintained on a shaker in dark conditions for 1 h, then centrifuged for 5 min (4°C, 7,000x 
   <span class="italic">gr</span>) and the supernatant was kept at −80°C for further analyses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antioxidants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2,2′-diphenypicrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and β-carotene-linoleic acid assays were used following Elansary et al. (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2017</a>) to determine essential oils free radical scavenging activity of each sample which was expressed as IC
   <sub>50</sub> (μg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) or the sample concentration required to scavenge 50% of DPPH/β-carotene-linoleic acid. Total and free ascorbate (non-enzymatic antioxidants) were quantified in ground frozen leaves following Elansary et al. (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The enzymes activities of ascorbate peroxidase (APX), catalase (CAT), and superoxide dismutase (SOD) were quantified in leaves tissues according to Zhang and Kirkham (
   <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">1996</a>) and Elansary et al. (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2017</a>). ROS accumulation was determined by quantifying H
   <sub>2</sub>O
   <sub>2</sub> composition in leaves following Elansary et al. (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2017</a>) and using the Beyotime Colorimetric Assay Kit (Beyotime, China).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total phenolic, proline, chlorophyll, carbohydrate, sodium and chloride compositions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total phenolics were quantified in leaves according to Amerine and Ough (
   <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">1988</a>) and Singleton and Rossi (
   <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">1965</a>) using a Folin-Ciocalteau method. The proline was quantified in 0.5 g (% of dry matter) following Bates et al. (
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">1973</a>) spectrophotometrically at 520 nm. The chemical constituents of the soil (sandy) used were quantified following Jackson (
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">1958</a>) (Table 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" href="#SM1">S1</a>). Total chlorophyll content was determined following Moran and Porath (
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">1980</a>). Total carbohydrates (%) in the leaves was determined according to Dubios et al. (
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">1956</a>). Sodium and chloride contents (mg g
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) in the leaves were determined according to Piper (
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">1947</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RNA isolation and quantitative real-time PCR</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative real-time PCR was conducted to evaluate the expression levels of APX gene, 3 SOD genes (FeSOD, Cu/ZnSOD, MnSOD) and 4 genes conferring tolerance to salinity (bZIP62, DREB2, ERF3, and OLPb) in the rosemary plants subjected to different SA treatments (0, 100, 200, 300 ppm) under different saline conditions (640, 2,000, 4,000 ppm). RNeasy Plant Mini kit (Qiagen) was used to isolate the total RNA from these plant tissues. Contaminating DNA was then removed. cDNA was synthesized by using Reverse Transcription kit, and qRT-PCR was then carried out in triplicates using QuantiTect SYBR Green PCR kit. The conditions for PCR amplification were 95°C for 10 min; 50 cycles of 95°C for 30 s, 62°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 2 min; then at 72°C for 3 min. Melting curve analysis was applied to test the amplification specificity. Gene-specific primers of Radyukina et al. (
   <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">2011</a>), Elansary et al. (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2017</a>), and Kim et al. (
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">2017</a>) were used for genes amplification. 
   <span class="italic">Actin</span> (Radyukina et al., 
   <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">2011</a>) was used as a housekeeping gene, and the relative expression levels were determined using 2
   <span class="sup">−ΔΔCt</span> method.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antibacterial activities of leaf extracts</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explore the antibacterial activities of SA treated compared to control plants under saline conditions, Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacterial were screened against essential oils of different treatments (season 2016). 
   <span class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</span> (clinical isolate), 
   <span class="italic">Bacillus cereus</span> (ATCC 14579), 
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (ATCC 6538), 
   <span class="italic">Micrococcus flavus</span> (ATCC 10240), 
   <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> (ATCC 35210), and 
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> (ATCC 27853) were examined against essential oils of different treatments using the micro-dilution method (Elansary et al., 
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">2016</a>). In microtiter plates, known concentration of essential oil was mixed with bacterial inoculum in Triptic Soy broth, then kept at 37°C for 24 h in a rotary shaker to determine the minimum inhibitory and bactericidal concentrations (MICs and MBCs). The MBC was determined using serial sub-cultivation of each essential oil (2 μL) with each bacterium then incubated 24 h at 37°C and the MBC was defined as the minimum concentration of the essential oil indicated killing off 99.5% of the of the inoculum. The density was determined at 655 nm and all experiments were performed twice in triplicates. Positive control (streptomycin and ampicillin, 0.01–10 mg/ mL) as well as the DMSO (5%) negative controls were used.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Salinity was the main plot and Salicylic acid was the subplot in split plot experimental design. Experiments were repeated twice in January 2016 and 2017. The data of each season were presented as means and subjected to Least significant differences (LSD) test in ANOVA test using SPSS (PASW Ver. 21).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
