<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="brief-report"><?OLF?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arch Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Arch Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Archives of Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0302-8933</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-072X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8164493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2393</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-021-02393-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chemical composition and potentiating action of Norfloxacin mediated by the essential oil of <italic>Piper caldense</italic> C.D.C. against <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains overexpressing efflux pump genes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>Antonio Linkoln Alves Borges</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bezerra</surname><given-names>Camila Fonseca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Confortin</surname><given-names>Camila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>Luiz Everson</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marinho</surname><given-names>Emanuelle Machado</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marinho</surname><given-names>M&#x000e1;rcia Machado</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>Mayron Alves</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da&#x000a0;Silva</surname><given-names>Terezinha Gon&#x000e7;alves</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marinho</surname><given-names>Emmanuel Silva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>Alexandre Magno Rodrigues</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>Henrique Douglas Melo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>Humberto Medeiros</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5527-164X</contrib-id><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>H&#x000e9;lcio Silva</given-names></name><address><email>helciodossantos@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412405.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9823 4235</institution-id><institution>Department of Biological Chemistry, </institution><institution>Regional University of Cariri, </institution></institution-wrap>Crato, CE Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412380.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2176 3398</institution-id><institution>Department of Microbiology and Parasitolog, </institution><institution>Federal University of Piaui, </institution></institution-wrap>Teresina, PI Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411227.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0670 7996</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Sciences, </institution><institution>Federal University of Pernambuco, </institution></institution-wrap>Recife, PE Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Center for Exact Sciences and Technology, Vale do Acarau State University, Sobral, CE Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8395.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2160 0329</institution-id><institution>Department of Analytical Chemistry and Physical Chemistry, </institution><institution>Federal University of Cear&#x000e1;, </institution></institution-wrap>Fortaleza, CE Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412327.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9141 3257</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Education, Science and Letters of Iguatu, </institution><institution>State University of Cear&#x000e1;, </institution></institution-wrap>Iguatu, CE Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442085.f</institution-id><institution>Minas Gerais State University, </institution></institution-wrap>Divin&#x000f3;polis Unit, MG Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411227.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0670 7996</institution-id><institution>Department of Antibiotics, Drug Planning and Synthesis Laboratory-LPSF, </institution><institution>Federal University of Pernambuco, Cidade Universit&#x000e1;ria, </institution></institution-wrap>Recife, PE Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412327.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9141 3257</institution-id><institution>Group of Theoretical Chemistry and Electrochemistry, </institution><institution>State University of Cear&#x000e1;, </institution></institution-wrap>Campus FAFIDAM, Limoeiro do Norte, Fortaleza, CE Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label>10</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.20736.30</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1941 472X</institution-id><institution>Postgraduate Programme in Sustainable Territorial, Federal University of Paran&#x000e1;, </institution></institution-wrap>Curitiba, PR Brazil </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by Erko Stackebrandt.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s), under exclusive licence to Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2021</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Infectious diseases caused by multidrug-resistant microorganisms has increased in the last years. <italic>Piper</italic> species have been reported as a natural source of phytochemicals that can help in combating fungal and bacterial infections. This study had as objectives characterize the chemical composition of the essential oil from <italic>Piper caldense</italic> (EOPC), evaluate its potential antimicrobial activity, and investigate the synergistic effect with Norfloxacin against multidrug-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> overproducing efflux pumps, as well as, verify the EOPC ability to inhibit the <italic>Candida albicans</italic> filamentation. EOPC was extracted by hydrodistillation, and the chemical constituents were identified by gas chromatography, allowing the identification of 24 compounds (91.9%) classified as hydrocarbon sesquiterpenes (49.6%) and oxygenated sesquiterpenes (39.5%). Antimicrobial tests were performed using a 96-well plate microdilution method against <italic>C. albicans</italic> ATCC 10231, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 25922 and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 25923 standard strains, as well as against multidrug-resistant strains <italic>S. aureus</italic> SA1199B (overexpressing <italic>norA</italic> gene), <italic>S. aureus</italic> K2068 (overexpressing <italic>mepA</italic> gene) and <italic>S. aureus</italic> K4100 (overexpressing <italic>qacC</italic> gene). The oil showed activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic> ATCC 10231 (&#x02265;&#x02009;512&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL) and was able to inhibit hyphae formation, an important mechanism of virulence of <italic>C. albicans</italic>. On the other hand, EOPC was inactive against all bacterial strains tested (&#x02264;&#x02009;1,024&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g&#x000a0;mL). However, when combined with Norfloxacin at subinhibitory concentration EOPC reduced the Norfloxacin and Ethidium bromide MIC values against <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains SA1199B, K2068 and K4100. These results indicate that EOPC is a source of phytochemicals acting as NorA, MepA and QacC inhibitors.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd><italic>Piper caldense</italic></kwd><kwd>Antibacterial</kwd><kwd>Efflux pump inhibitors</kwd><kwd>Antifungal</kwd><kwd>Fungal dimorphism</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>FUNCAP</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>CNPq</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>CAPES</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Infectious diseases caused by multidrug-resistant microorganisms has become a global public health concern (Guschin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2015</xref>). Multidrug-resistant bacteria have been isolated with high frequencies from community or hospital-acquired infections (Klein et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2020</xref>; Xiang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2020</xref>), as well as, from infections of veterinary importance (Lima et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2012</xref>). On the other hand, infections caused by resistant fungi are more and more prevalent in hospitals, being known as a sleeping giant, for never having completely solved the problem of ineffective antifungals (Ver&#x000ed;ssimo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2016</xref>). In fact, antimicrobial resistance it was predicted to reach pandemic proportions by 2050, accounting for 10 million deaths annually (Sugden et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2016</xref>).</p><p id="Par3">Antibiotic resistance can acquired by a mutation that generate a change in a target protein with lower for affinity for antibiotic or through acquisition of resistance placed in plasmids, transposons or phage DNA that often involves inactivation, antibiotic degradation or extrusion by active efflux pumps (Santos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2007</xref>). Efflux pumps are transmembrane proteins that become both bacteria and fungi resistant, because they are able to extrude antibiotics and biocide reducing their intracellular concentrations using ATP or proton gradient as energy source (Du et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par4">Traditionally used antibiotics have been losing their effectiveness because of increased microbial resistance (Mayers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2009</xref>). Epidemiological studies warn of the importance of further research for discovery of new drugs or compounds with therapeutic properties (Balouiri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2016</xref>). Another important point, to combat infections caused by resistant microorganisms, is the discover of compound acting as efflux pump inhibitors to provide new ways to reverse bacterial and fungal resistance (Rezende-J&#x000fa;nior et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2020</xref>). In this way, alternative forms such as in vitro methods in antimicrobial tests to assess the potential of extracts, essential oils, and isolated compounds have been intensified, revealing potential antimicrobial agents or even enhancing the activity of antibiotics used in clinical practice (Balouiri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2016</xref>; Coutinho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2010</xref>; Matias et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2013</xref>; Costa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2017</xref>; Siebra et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2018</xref>). The association of natural products as well as the use of these combined with antimicrobials, has been widely discussed in the scientific literature, given the ability to provide antimicrobial efficacy in previously ineffective doses due to the antimicrobial resistance presented by some strains (Guimaraes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2010</xref>; Silva et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2014</xref>; Tulgar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2018</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">The inhibition of the production of virulence factors by pathogenic microorganisms is also an approach that can be useful in the treatment of infectious diseases. <italic>Candida</italic> species, produce infections ranging from skin and mucous infections, to deep and generalized infections, they make use of alternative mechanisms to invade the host organism and develop virulence factors, where they colonize significantly, leaving the responses to aggression, weakened (Egue et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2018</xref>). <italic>C. albicans</italic> is the species responsible for about 50&#x02013;70% of the cases of invasive candidiasis (Castro et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2016</xref>). <italic>C. albicans</italic> is a yeast species capable of producing hyphae or pseudo-hyphae able to invade host tissues leading to candidiasis (Fernandes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2020</xref>; Sellam and Whiteway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2016</xref>). The ability to alter structural morphology from yeast to filamentous cells, is known as one of the main mechanisms of fungal virulence (Hou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2011</xref>; S&#x000e1;nchez-Mart&#x000ed;nez and P&#x000e9;rez-Mart&#x000ed;n <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2001</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">Natural products with antimicrobial properties represent an alternative to the use of traditional antimicrobial agents. <italic>Piper caldense</italic> C.D.C. (Piperaceae) is a shrub popularly known as &#x0201c;pimenta d&#x02019;agua&#x0201d; that has been used in some Brazilian regions as a sedative agent (Cardozo J&#x000fa;nior and Chaves <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2003</xref>). This study aimed to characterize the chemical composition of the essential oil from the leaves of <italic>Piper caldense</italic> (EOPC), as well as, its antimicrobial activity against bacteria and yeast strains. The ability of the EOPC to inhibit cell dimorphism in <italic>C. albicans</italic> was also assessed. Futhermore, the effect of the EOPC on the activity of Norfloxacin against multidrug-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> SA1199B, <italic>S. aureus</italic> K2068 and <italic>S. aureus</italic> K4100 strains was assessed to evaluate its potential as inhibitor of the NorA, MepA or QacC efflux pumps.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Botanical material</title><p id="Par7">Plant material was collected in the dense lowland rainforest, Antonina, PR 2015/2106, Brazil, under coordinates 25&#x000b0;&#x000a0;17&#x02032;&#x000a0;51.9&#x02032;&#x02032;&#x000a0;S and 48&#x000b0;&#x000a0;40&#x02032;&#x000a0;51.4&#x02032;&#x02032; W at 14&#x000a0;m elevation, during the spring. Material collection was carried out under license from the Environmental Institute of the Paran&#x000e1; State, number 284/11, and an exsiccata was deposited at the Herbarium of the Municipal Botanical Museum (MBM) in Curitiba, PR, under No. 267636. Fresh leaves of <italic>P. caldense</italic> were used to extract the oil without any indication of contamination by parasites.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Extraction of the essential oil</title><p id="Par8">The oil was prepared by hydrodistillation using a Clevenger graduated device. The proportion of fresh leaves was 100&#x000a0;g/L of distilled water, following the methodology described by Wasicky (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">1963</xref>). An electric dryer model&#x02014;FANEM 320 SE was used, with air circulation at 40&#x000ba; C for 24&#x000a0;h to dry the leaves. Following to determine the moisture content at the time of extraction, samples of 20&#x000a0;g were collected in triplicates, submitted to drying in an electric dryer model FANEM 320 SE with air circulation at 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until reaching constant weight. After extraction, the samples were collected with a precision pipette and placed in a freezer where they remained until the time of the chromatographic analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Strains and chemicals</title><p id="Par9">Evaluation of the intrinsic antimicrobial activity of the EOPC was performed against standard microbial strains <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 25923, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 25922 and <italic>Candida albicans</italic> ATCC 10231, as well as, against multidrug-resistant strains <italic>S. aureus</italic> SA1199B overexpressing the <italic>norA</italic> gene (Kaatz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1993</xref>), <italic>S. aureus</italic> K2068 overexpressing the <italic>mepA</italic> gene (Kaatz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2005</xref>) and <italic>S. aureus</italic> K4100 overexpressing the <italic>qacC</italic> gene (Littlejohn et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1991</xref>). Assays for evaluation of the modulating effect on drug resistance were performed only with drug-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> SA1199B, K2068 and K4100 strains. Assays for evaluation of the ability to inhibit the cellular dimorphism were conducted against <italic>C. albicans</italic> ATCC 10231 strain. Bacterial and yeast strains were maintained on Brain Heart Infusion Agar (BHIA, Himedia, India) slants at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, and prior to assay the cells were grown overnight at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in Brain Heart Infusion (BHI, Himedia, India). Subsequently, an aliquot of each microbial culture was removed and diluted in 3&#x000a0;mL of 0.9% saline, and the turbidity adjusted to the McFarland 0.5 scale.</p><p id="Par10">Norfloxacin (Nor), Ethidium Bromide (EtBr) and Chlorpromazine (CPZ) were obtained from Sigma Chemical Corp., St. Louis. With the exception of Nor that was dissolved in a mixture of 1&#x000a0;M NaOH and sterile distilled water (1:9 proportion), EtBr and CPZ were dissolved in sterile water.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Determination of the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC).</title><p id="Par11">Initially, the essential oil was diluted in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) at a concentration of 10,000&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL. Subsequently, this solution was diluted in sterile distilled water to a concentration of 1024&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL. The minimum inhibitory concentration of EOPC against bacteria and fungi strains was determined using the 96-well plate microdilution technique. Initially, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of essential oil was diluted serially in BHI 10% medium in concentrations that ranged from 1024 to 8&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL. Subsequently, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of the microbial suspension (bacteria or fungi) in BHI 10% was added. For the control of microbial growth, BHI 10% was composed and microbial suspension in the absence of essential oil (Leal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2019a</xref>)&#x000a0;The plates were incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x000a0;h, and the MIC was identified by adding 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of sodium resazurin to each well and after 1&#x000a0;h visually checking the presence or absence of colorimetric change.</p><p id="Par12">Fungal viability was achieved by adding a sterilized stem to each well that did not show fungal growth and subculturing in an Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (SDA, Himedia, India) petri dish. The plates were incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x000a0;h and, subsequently, the development or suppression of fungal colonies (Morais-Braga et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2016</xref>) was verified.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Modulating effect of the antibiotic resistance</title><p id="Par13">To evaluate if the EOPC was able to modulate antibiotic resistance in <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains overexpressing specific efflux pump genes, antibiotic MICs were determined in the presence or absence of subinhibitory concentrations of EOPC (1/8 or 1/4 MICs). Antibiotic concentrations ranged from 0.125 to 128&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL. The microtiter plates were incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x000a0;h and readings were performed with resazurin as described above. To verify whether the modulation of drug resistance occurred due to inhibition of the efflux pump, the modulation assay was performed by substituting antibiotics for EtBr, which is a known substrate of efflux pumps (Markham et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1999</xref>), used herein as inhibition of the pump. Control trials were also performed, replacing each natural product with CPZ, which is a known efflux pump inhibitor (Neyfakh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1993</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Effect of <italic>P. caldense </italic>essential oil on <italic>C. albicans</italic> micromorphology</title><p id="Par14">The tests were performed according to Sidrim and Rocha (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2010</xref>), with some modifications. In this test, the effect of the EOPC on the suppression of the filament of <italic>C. albicans</italic> was verified. Depleted Potato Dextrose Agar (PDA) was placed inside of Falcon tubes and, then the EOPC was added varying the concentration according to MIC as follow: MIC (512&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), MIC 1/2 (256&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) and MIC 1/4 (128&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL). Then, PDA was immediately poured in a slide. Petri dishes with a blade were inoculated by a calibrated loop (1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g), where two parallel streaks were made in the medium already solidified and then covered by a sterile microscopic sheet. After incubation at 24&#x000a0;h (37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C), the culture was visualized by optical microscopy. A control without the EOPC was made for the growth of yeasts whose hyphae emission was stimulated by the impoverishment of the medium, once stress caused by starvation leads to hyphae emission.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par15">Data were analyzed using the statistical program GraphPad Prisma 6.0. Differences between treatment with Norfloxacin and treatment with Norfloxacin combined with EOPC (or Chlorpromazine) were analyzed using a two-way ANOVA test, using the geometric mean of the triplicates as the central data and standard deviation. Then, a post hoc Bonferroni test was performed and <italic>p</italic> values&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Chemical composition</title><p id="Par16">The content of the EOPC was 14.74% and 24 constituents (91.9%) were identified (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Chemical compounds were separated into groups, according to their chemical classification as hydrocarbon sesquiterpenes (49.6%), oxygenated sesquiterpenes (39.5%) and hydrocarbon monoterpenes (2.9%). Oxygenated monoterpenes were not found in the EOPC. Caryophyllene oxide (11.9%) was the major constituent found, followed by &#x003b4;-Cadinene (9.6%) and Spathulenol (9.1%) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Chemical composition of the EOPC used in the present study (from Antonina, PR at 14&#x000a0;m elevation) was different to that verified by the EOPC from Piraquara, PR (528&#x000a0;m elevation), with nine different compounds as follow: trans-Caryophyllene, &#x003b2;-Copaene, Trans-&#x003b1;-bergamotene, &#x003b1;-Amorfene, &#x003b2;-Selinene and Valencene (Bezerra et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2020</xref>). Variations in the chemical composition of the EOPC are probably associated with different edaphomatic and rainfall conditions in the region where the specimen was found (Viana et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2019</xref>). Seasonality, circadian rhythm, temperature and brightness, as well as the stage of development and nutritional factors, are all likely to influence the chemical composition of essential oils.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Relative percentage of essential oil components from fresh samples of native species of <italic>Piper caldense</italic> collected in the lowland rainforest, Antonina, PR&#x02014;Brazil</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Compounds</th><th align="left">IR<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">IR<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Pinene</td><td char="." align="char">939</td><td char="." align="char">932</td><td char="." align="char">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Camphene</td><td char="." align="char">952</td><td char="." align="char">946</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Copaene</td><td char="." align="char">1375</td><td char="." align="char">1374</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">trans-Caryophyllene</td><td char="." align="char">1417</td><td char="." align="char">1417</td><td char="." align="char">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-Copaene</td><td char="." align="char">1427</td><td char="." align="char">1430</td><td char="." align="char">0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Trans-&#x003b1;-bergamotene</td><td char="." align="char">1435</td><td char="." align="char">1432</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b3;-Muurolene</td><td char="." align="char">1475</td><td char="." align="char">1478</td><td char="." align="char">6.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Amorfene</td><td char="." align="char">1479</td><td char="." align="char">1483</td><td char="." align="char">3.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-Selinene</td><td char="." align="char">1483</td><td char="." align="char">1489</td><td char="." align="char">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Valencene</td><td char="." align="char">1492</td><td char="." align="char">1496</td><td char="." align="char">6.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1; Muurolene</td><td char="." align="char">1498</td><td char="." align="char">1500</td><td char="." align="char">4.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b4;-Cadinene</td><td char="." align="char">1512</td><td char="." align="char">1522</td><td char="." align="char">13.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Humulene epoxide II</td><td char="." align="char">1605</td><td char="." align="char">1608</td><td char="." align="char">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Calacorene</td><td char="." align="char">1541</td><td char="." align="char">1544</td><td char="." align="char">1.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-Calacorene</td><td char="." align="char">1564</td><td char="." align="char">1564</td><td char="." align="char">1.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spathulenol</td><td char="." align="char">1575</td><td char="." align="char">1577</td><td char="." align="char">9.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caryophyllene oxide</td><td char="." align="char">1579</td><td char="." align="char">1582</td><td char="." align="char">11.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rosifoliol</td><td char="." align="char">1597</td><td char="." align="char">1600</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1,10 di-epi-Cubebol</td><td char="." align="char">1611</td><td char="." align="char">1618</td><td char="." align="char">1.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1-epi-Cubenol</td><td char="." align="char">1625</td><td char="." align="char">1627</td><td char="." align="char">3.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">epi-&#x003b1;-Muurolol</td><td char="." align="char">1639</td><td char="." align="char">1640</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Muurolol</td><td char="." align="char">1644</td><td char="." align="char">1644</td><td char="." align="char">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-Cadinol</td><td char="." align="char">1652</td><td char="." align="char">1652</td><td char="." align="char">4.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cadalene</td><td char="." align="char">1672</td><td char="." align="char">1675</td><td char="." align="char">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Total identified (%)</td><td char="." align="char">91.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>I.R&#x02009;=&#x02009;Calculated Retention Index</p><p><sup>b</sup>I.R&#x02009;=&#x02009;Literature Retention Index</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.1</label><caption><p>Majority constituents of essential oil of <italic>Piper caldense</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="203_2021_2393_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Evaluation of the antimicrobial activity</title><p id="Par17">MIC values above 1000&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL for plant extracts have been considered as clinically irrelevant, because it may be impracticable to extrapolate the dose from that giving activity in vitro, to that which would be required in equivalence for the size of a human adult (Houghton et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2007</xref>). Using this value as a cutoff point, the EOPC did not show antimicrobial activity against bacterial strains tested (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Similar results were verified for other <italic>Piper</italic> species, such as, <italic>P. rivinoides</italic> (Leal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2019b</xref>) and <italic>Piper cernuum</italic> (Leal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2019a</xref>) that also did not present activity against both <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic>. However, a previous studies found a diferente result where the EOPC showed activity against Gram-negative <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, as well as, against Gram-positive species <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (Rocha et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) values obtained for <italic>P. caldense</italic> essential oil (EOPC) against microbial strains tested</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Strains</th><th align="left">MIC (&#x000b5;g/mL)</th><th align="left">Effect</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> SA1199B</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1024</td><td align="left">Inactive<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> K2068</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1024</td><td align="left">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> K4100</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1024</td><td align="left">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 25923</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1024</td><td align="left">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 25922</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1024</td><td align="left">Inactive</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Candida albicans</italic> ATCC 10231</td><td char="." align="char">512</td><td align="left">Active</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>MIC values upper than 1000&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL were considered inactives (Houghton et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2007</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">EOPC tested in the present showed a weak antifungal activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic> ATCC 10231 (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This antifungal activity could be related with the presence of some constituents such as Caryophyllene oxide, a compound described as showing antifungal activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic> and dermatophyte fungi (Ghavam et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2020</xref>; Schmidt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2010</xref>; Yang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">1999</xref>). However, the Caryophyllene oxide content found in the oil tested in the present study was lower (11.9%) than that verified for the EOPC from Piraquara, PR (13.9%), which did not show activity against <italic>C. albicans</italic> INCQ40006 and <italic>C. albicans</italic> URM4387 (Bezerra et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2020</xref>). Thus, we cannot rule out that other oil constituents acting isolatelly or synergistically could be related with the antifungal activity showed by the EOPC tested in the present study. As an example, Spathulenol, a sesquiterpene reported to be between major volatile components of the essential oils of several aromatic Piperaceae species, has some biological activities, including antimicrobial activity (Dib et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2017</xref>). Coming from the cyclization of nerolidine pyrophosphate, &#x003b4;-cadinene presents a cadinane skeleton, which the precursor is the farnesyl pyrophosphate (RuizReyes and Suarez <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2015</xref>). Among the activities reported in the literature for &#x003b4;-cadinene can be mentioned the antitumor activity (Wright and Sutherland <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2007</xref>), antimicrobial activity (Skaltsa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2003</xref>). Thus, the antifungal activity observed in our approach could be associated to the levels of the compounds related to the local environments and conditions to which the assayed plant was exposed, acting possibly by a synergistic effect.</p><p id="Par19">However studies with essential oils with species of <italic>Piper cernuum</italic> and <italic>P. caldense</italic> made by Duarte et al. (Duarte et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2016</xref>) and Constantin et al. (Costantin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2001</xref>) present compounds that present several properties, among them antifungal, antibacterial and even capable of potentiating antibiotic effect. However, Costantin et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2001</xref>) who used the essential oil of <italic>P. cernnum</italic> and the compound Eugenol, demonstrated antifungal activity on <italic>C. albicans</italic>. The oil presented an inhibition halo of 12.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6&#x000a0;mm in diameter, and the Eugenol isolate 28.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3&#x000a0;mm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Evaluation of the modulating effect of the antibiotic resistance</title><p id="Par20">EOPC potentiated the activity of Norfloxacin against <italic>S. aureus</italic> SA1199B overproducing NorA, as well as, against <italic>S. aureus</italic> K2068 overproducing MepA at subinhibitory concentrations. MIC values for Norfloxacin against SA1199B decreased eightfold in the presence of the oil from 64 to 8&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). For K2068 strain, MIC values for Norfloxacin also were reduced eightfold when the EOPC was added to the growth medium from 16 to 2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). These results indicate that EOPC contains phytochemicals able to modulate the Norfloxacin resistance, probably by inhibition of the NorA and MepA efflux pumps.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>MIC values of Norfloxacin (Nor) (<bold>A</bold>) and Ethidium Bromide (EtBr) (<bold>B</bold>) against <italic>S. aureus</italic> SA1199B (<italic>norA</italic>) in absence or presence of the essential oil from the leaves of <italic>P. caldense</italic> (EOPC) or Chlorpromazine (CPZ). Each result represents the geometric mean of three simultaneous experiments. (***) Statistically significant values (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="203_2021_2393_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>MIC values of Norfloxacin (Nor) (<bold>A</bold>) and Ethidium Bromide (EtBr) (<bold>B</bold>) against <italic>S. aureus</italic> K2068 (<italic>mepA</italic>) in absence or presence of the essential oil from the leaves of <italic>P. caldense</italic> (EOPC) or Chlorpromazine (CPZ). Each result represents the geometric mean of three simultaneous experiments. (***) Statistically significant values (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="203_2021_2393_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">To verify if the modulating effect is related with efflux pump inhibition, assays were performed replacing Norfloxacin by EtBr. As the only known mechanism of bacterial resistance to EtBr is mediated by efflux pumps (Markham et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1999</xref>), this DNA-intercalating dye have been used to evaluate the potential efflux pump inhibitory activity of natural products (Silva et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2021a</xref>), isolated phytochemicals (Silva et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2021b</xref>) and synthetic compounds (Faillace et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2021</xref>; Costa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2016</xref>). Results showed that EOPC was also able to modulate the resistance to EtBr in both SA1199B (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B) and K2068 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B) strains. These results indicate the presence of compounds acting as NorA and MepA inhibitors which could be used against Norfloxacin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains overproducers of efflux pumps, leading to a higher antibiotic accumulation in the bacterial cell.</p><p id="Par22">NorA is a proton motive-dependent efflux pump belongs to Major Facilitator Superfamily (MFS), meanwhile MepA is a member of the Multidrug and Toxin Extrusion (MATE) superfamily, which is dependent of H<sup>+</sup> or Na<sup>+</sup> gradient to extrude Norfloxacin or EtBr (Schindler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2014</xref>). To guarantee the integrity and functioning of NorA, there must be a continuous proton-driving force, integrity of DNA zones responsible for the synthesis of membrane proteins and balance in the permeability of substances inside the cell (Thai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>). The modulating effect verified for EOPC could be provoked by interaction of their hydrophobic monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes constituents, leading to plasma membrane damage and dissipation of the proton gradient (Souza et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2013</xref>; Ahmad et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2013</xref>), resulting in the NorA and MepA inhibition. As a consequence, the intracellular concentrations of Norfloxacin becomes enough to inactivate their intracellular targets increasing its antibacterial effect against the <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains tested. Thus, the EOPC could be used in combination to Norfloxacin aiming to enhancing the effectiveness of this antibiotic against multidrug-resistent <italic>S. aureus</italic> overproducers of NorA or MepA.</p><p id="Par23">Similar results were found for <italic>S. aureus</italic> K4100 overexpressing the <italic>qacC</italic> gene (Littlejohn et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1991</xref>) once the EOPC potentiate the activity of EtBr, indicating that the oil is able to inhibit QacC. MIC values for EtBr against K4100 decreased eightfold in the presence of the oil from 32 to 4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). QacC is a proton motive-dependent efflux pump that confer resistance to EtBr and quaternary ammonium compounds (QACs), as Benzalkonium Chloride (Schindler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2014</xref>). Biocide agents such as QACs are widely used in the disinfection of surfaces mainly in hospitals, outpatient clinics, dentist offices, as well as, veterinary clinics, being including effectiveness in the SARS-CoV inactivation (Kamp et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2020</xref>). This intensive use can contribute for emergence of QAC-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains overproducers of QacC (Schindler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2014</xref>). Thus, the EOPC could be used in association with QACs aiming to eliminate these multidrug strains present in surfaces preventing outbreaks of <italic>S. aureus</italic> infections in hospital environments.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>MIC values of Ethidium Bromide (EtBr) against <italic>S. aureus</italic> K4100 (<italic>qacC</italic>) in absence or presence of the essential oil from the leaves of <italic>P. caldense</italic> (EOPC) or Chlorpromazine (CPZ). Each result represents the geometric mean of three simultaneous experiments. (***) Statistically significant values (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="203_2021_2393_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Inhibition of the cellular dimorphism in <italic>C. albicans</italic></title><p id="Par24">Assays for evaluation of morphological transition of <italic>C. albicans</italic> were performed in the presence and absence of subinhibitory concentrations of EOPC. The fungus grown in the absence of oil showed a clear morphological transition, being possible to observe the presence of blastospores and hyphae (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). On the other hand, EOPC showed potential to inhibit fungal dimorphism at 512&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL (MIC) and at subinhibitory concentration 256&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL (MIC 1/2). However, at 128&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL, it was possible to observe the presence of pseudo-hyphae. Thus, besides antifungal activity, EOPC demonstrating a clear inhibition of the morphological transition in <italic>C. albicans</italic> ATCC 10231. Results found for EOPC tested in the present study were better than those found by Bezerra et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2020</xref>) once they verified inhibition of hyphae projection just at 2048&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Morphological transition of <italic>C. albincans</italic> in presence of subinhibitory concentrations of <italic>Piper caldense</italic> C.D.C. essential oil; Micrography was performed through 40X objective optical microscopy; photographic image captured in digital camera with 4X zoom and resized for better computer resolution. Growth control (<bold>A</bold>); P.caldense essential oil at 128&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL (<bold>B</bold>); 256&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL (<bold>C</bold>) and 512&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="203_2021_2393_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par25">Hyphae projection by fungi such as <italic>C. albicans</italic> is an adaptation process to environmental changes such as temperature, pH or nutrient depletion, and filamentous forms generally promote invasive diseases and hinder the action of antifungals (Wightman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2004</xref>; Barbedo and Sgarbi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2010</xref>; Veses and Gow <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2014</xref>). Development of pseudo-hyphae by <italic>C. albicans</italic> increases its ability to adhere to the host tissues, increasing its contact surface, leading to a higher propagation and developing of virulence factors (Giolo and Svidzinski <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2010</xref>). Under stress, <italic>C. albicans</italic> change from yeast form to hyphae, that it is closely interconnected with its pathogenicity, given that filamentous fungi present better adherence to the tissue since at the end of hyphae, there are enzymes that, when secreted, can degrade proteins, lipids and other components of host cells, facilitating the invasion process (Costa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2011</xref>).</p><p id="Par26">The emission of hyphae is considerably relevant in what concerns the mechanism of candidiasis virulence since the pathogenicity of the fungus is due to the fact that it presents dimorphism, this appears as an aptitude method in the development of superficial and systemic infections that hyphae spread, promoting the pathogenicity of the infectious form (Morais-Braga et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2016</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">Although there are several antifungals available on the market, the high frequency of resistant strains becomes worrying and borderline in several clinical conditions. Thus, the EOPC tested in the present study could be applied as an agent able to inhibit the conversion of commensal yeast cells of <italic>C. albicans</italic> in filamentous and pathogenic forms, in the treatment or prevention of candidiasis. It is important to note that cell differentiation is regulated by intracellular signaling pathways, including cAMP-PKA and MAPK pathways (Han et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2011</xref>). Regarding the inhibition of the filamentous form of fungi, it is suggested that inhibition of the Efg1 transcription factor associated with the PKA pathway, which stimulates the transcription of genes that participate in the formation of hyphae (Stoldt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1997</xref>; Nobile et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par28">EOPC showed antifungal action and it was able to inhibit the hyphae projection by <italic>C. albicans</italic> ATCC 10231, indicating a promise use in the treatment of candidiasis. In addition, the essential oil potentiating the activity of Norfloxacin decreasing its MIC values for resistant strains overexpressing NorA or MepA efflux pumps. Futhermore, EOPC promoted a significant reduction of the MIC values for EtBr indicating that the modulating effect could be related to its ability to cause inhibition of this efflux pumps. These results point to a potential of the EOPC as an adjuvant of Norfloxacin in the treatment of infections caused by <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains overproducing NorA or MepA efflux pumps, a protein overexpressed in <italic>S. aureus</italic> SA1199B. Besides NorA and MepA, EOPC was also to act as a QacC efflux pump inhibitor compound indicating a potential technological application in association with quaternary ammonia compounds for elimination of QacC overproducing <italic>S. aureus</italic> strains in both human and veterinary clinical environments.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was supported by the Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel&#x02014;Brazil (CAPES), by the National Council for Scientific and Technological Development&#x02014;Brazil (CNPq), by the Cearense Foundation for Scientific and Technological Development Support&#x02014;Brazil (FUNCAP) and by the Piau&#x000ed; Research Foundation (FAPEPI).</p></ack><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Council for Scientific and Technological Development&#x02014;Brazil (CNPq) under Grant (no. 305719/2018-1) and by the Piau&#x000ed; Research Foundation (FAPEPI) under Grant (no. 050/2019).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All materials and data are stored at Department of Biological Chemistry, Regional University of Cariri, Cear&#x000e1;. Brazil, and may be shared upon request directed to the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par29">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par30">No individual data are presented in this manuscript.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzoor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reversal of efflux mediated antifungal resistance underlies synergistic activity of two monoterpenes with fluconazole</article-title><source>Eur J Pharm Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejps.2012.09.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23111348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23111348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balouiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibnsouda</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for in vitro evaluating antimicrobial activity: a review</article-title><source>J Pharm Anal</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpha.2015.11.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29403965?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29403965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbedo</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sgarbi</surname><given-names>DBG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candid&#x000ed;ase</article-title><source>DST-J Brasileiro De Doen&#x000e7;as Sex Transm</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bezerra JWAB, Rodrigues FC, Da Cruz RP et al (2020) Antibiotic Potential and Chemical Composition of the Essential Oil of <italic>Piper caldense</italic> C. DC. (Piperaceae). Appl Sci 10:631</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardozo J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>MCO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caldensin, a new natural n-Methylaristolactam from <italic>Piper caldense</italic></article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1076/phbi.41.3.216.15091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>IMN</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasconcelos Junior</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activity comparison of imidazole and triazole antifungals aga-inst <italic>Candida albicans</italic></article-title><source>Revista Brasileira De An&#x000e1;l Cl&#x000ed;n</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>LKHe</given-names></name><name><surname>Ata&#x000ed;des</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular analysis and dimorphism of azole-susceptible and resistant <italic>Candida albicans</italic> isolates</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source><year>2011</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>740</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0037-86822011005000056</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22094708?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22094708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>de Macedo</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>FAA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of the NorA efflux pump of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> by synthetic riparins</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>1312</fpage><lpage>1322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.13258</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27537678?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27537678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lima</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>KRR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Rhaphiodon echinus</italic> (Nees &#x00026; Mart.) Schauer: chemical, toxicological activity and increased antibiotic activity of antifungal drug activity and antibacterial</article-title><source>Microb Pathog</source><year>2017</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2017.04.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28385578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28385578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costantin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Limberger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Essential oils from <italic>Piper cernuum</italic> and <italic>Piper regnellii</italic>: antimicrobial activities and analysis by GC/MS and 13C-NMR</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2001-18363</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11731928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>HDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JGM</given-names></name><name><surname>Siqueira-J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vitro anti-staphylococcal activity of <italic>Hyptis martiusii</italic> Benth against methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>: MRSA strains</article-title><source>Rev Bras Farmacog</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>670</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-695X2008000500005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>HDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JGM</given-names></name><name><surname>Falc&#x000e3;o-Silva</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> L. in the resistance to aminoglycosides in methicilin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Comp Immunol, Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cimid.2009.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19732954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dib I, Fauconnier ML, Sindic M et al (2017) Chemical composition, vasorelaxant, antioxidant and antiplatelet effects of essential oil of <italic>Artemisia campestris</italic> L. from Oriental Morocco. BMC Comp Alt Med 17:1&#x02013;15</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang-Kan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuberger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multidrug efflux pumps: structure, function and regulation</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiology</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-018-0048-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30002505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30002505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Duarte AE, de Menezes IR, Bezerra Morais Braga MF et al (2016) Antimicrobial activity and modulatory effect of essential oil from the leaf of <italic>Rhaphiodon echinus</italic> (Nees &#x00026; Mart) Schauer on some antimicrobial drugs. Molecules 21:743</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egue</surname><given-names>LAN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouatenin</surname><given-names>J-PKM</given-names></name><name><surname>N'Guessan</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Virulence factors and determination of antifungal susceptibilities of <italic>Candida</italic> species isolated from palm wine and sorghum beer</article-title><source>Microb Pathog</source><year>2018</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.08.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30092261?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30092261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faillace</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>ALAB</given-names></name><name><surname>Alc&#x000e2;ntara</surname><given-names>FAO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JHL</given-names></name><name><surname>Siqueira-J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>CES</given-names></name><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pel&#x000e1;ez</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of the NorA efflux pump of <italic>S. aureus</italic> by (Z)-5-(4-fluorobenzylidene)-imidazolinines</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem Lett</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>127670</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmcl.2020.127670</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 33161124?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33161124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fernandes L, Ribeiro H, Oliveira A et al (2020) Portuguese honeys as antimicrobial agents against <italic>Candida</italic> species. J Trad Compl Med 11:130&#x02013;136</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ghavam M, Manca ML, Manconi M et al (2020) Chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of essential oils obtained from leaves and flowers of <italic>Salvia hydrangea</italic> DC. ex Benth. Sci Rep 10:15647</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giolo</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Svidzinski</surname><given-names>TIE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fisiopatogenia, epidemiologia e diagn&#x000f3;stico laboratorial da candidemia</article-title><source>J Bras Patol Med Lab</source><year>2010</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1676-24442010000300009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guimaraes</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Momesso</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pupo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotics: therapeutic importance and perspectives for the discovery and development of new agents</article-title><source>Quim Nova</source><year>2010</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>679</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0100-40422010000300035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guschin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryzhikh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rumyantseva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Treatment efficacy, treatment failures and selection of macrolide resistance in patients with high load of <italic>Mycoplasma genitalium</italic> during treatment of male urethritis with josamycin</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>40</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-015-0781-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25645440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25645440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Villas-B&#x000f4;as</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The metabolic basis of <italic>Candida albicans</italic> morphogenesis and quorum sensing</article-title><source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fgb.2011.04.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21513811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21513811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of environmental factors on dimorphic transition of the jelly mushroom <italic>Tremella fuciformis</italic></article-title><source>Cryptogam, Mycol</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7872/crym.v32.iss4.2011.421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Steventon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uses and abuses of in vitro tests in ethnopharmacology: visualizing an elephant</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2007</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2007.01.032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17317057?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17317057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaatz</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruble</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efflux-mediated fluoroquinolone resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1993</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1086</fpage><lpage>1094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.37.5.1086</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8517696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8517696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaatz</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>McAleese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidrug resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> due to overexpression of a novel multidrug and toxin extrusion (MATE) transport protein</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1857</fpage><lpage>1864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.49.5.1857-1864.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15855507?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Todt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaender</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistence of coronaviruses on inanimate surfaces and their inactivation with biocidal agents</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2020.01.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32035997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannesen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Entry of Panton-Valentine leukocidin-positive methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> into the hospital: prevalence and population structure in Heidelberg, Germany 2015&#x02013;2018</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>13243</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31913322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leal ALAB, Bezerra CF, Rocha JE et al (2019a) <italic>Piper cernuum</italic> Vell.: Chemical profile and antimicrobial potential evaluation. Ind Crops Prod 140:111577</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Leal ALAB, Machado AJT, Bezerra CF et al (2019b) Chemical identification and antimicrobial potential of essential oil of <italic>Piper rivinoides</italic> kunth (BETIS-WHITE). Food Chem Toxicol 131:10559</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>LFA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lira</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>HDM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial resistance in staphylococci isolated from canine pyoderma</article-title><source>Comun Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>185</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Littlejohn</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>DiBerardino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Messerotti</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiers</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Skurray</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and evolution of a family of genes encoding antiseptic and disinfectant resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1991</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(91)90224-Y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1840534?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1840534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhaus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Klyachko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple novel inhibitors of the NorA multidrug transporter of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1999</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2404</fpage><lpage>2408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.43.10.2404</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10508015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matias</surname><given-names>EFF</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Falc&#x000e3;o-Silva</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modulation of the norfloxacin resistance in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> by <italic>Cordia verbenaceae</italic> DC Modula&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da resist&#x000ea;ncia &#x000e0; norfloxacina em <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> por <italic>Cordia verbenaceae</italic> DC</article-title><source>Indian J Med Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23481069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23481069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayers</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouellette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Antimicrobial drug resistance c: clinical and epidemiological aspects</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Dordrecht Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morais-Braga</surname><given-names>MFB</given-names></name><name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>JNP</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>AJT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-performance liquid chromatography-diodic array detector, fungistatic, and anti-morphogenical analysis of extracts from <italic>Psidium brownianum</italic> Mart. ex DC. against yeasts of the genus <italic>Candida</italic></article-title><source>Int J Food Prop</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1837</fpage><lpage>1851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10942912.2015.1079786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neyfakh</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Borsch</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaatz</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluoroquinolone resistance protein NorA of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is a multidrug efflux transporter</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1993</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.37.1.128</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8431010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8431010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nobile</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Andes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nett</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Critical role of Bcr1-dependent adhesins in <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm formation in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e63</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0020063</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16839200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16839200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezende-J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>LMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>ALAB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chalcones isolated from <italic>Arrabidaea brachypoda</italic> flowers as inhibitors of NorA and MepA multidrug efflux pumps of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title><source>Antibiotics</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>351</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>DMAF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potential antimicrobial and chemical composition of essential oils from <italic>Piper caldense</italic> Tissues</article-title><source>J Mex Chem Soc</source><year>2016</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>151</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ruiz-Reyes E, Suarez M (2015) Lactonas sesquiterp&#x000e9;nicas. Diversidad estructural y sus actividades biol&#x000f3;gicas. Rev CENIC Cienc Biol 46:9&#x02013;24</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dimorphism in fungal pathogens: <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and <italic>Ustilago maydis&#x02014;</italic>similar inputs, different outputs</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5274(00)00191-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11282479?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11282479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>ALd</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>CCd</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>: visitando uma cepa de import&#x000e2;ncia hospitalar</article-title><source>J Bras Patol Med Lab</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1676-24442007000600005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bail</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedl</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activities of single aroma compounds</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1934578X1000500906</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schindler BD, Frempong-Manso E, DeMarco CE et al (2014) Analyses of Multidrug Efflux Pump-Like Proteins Encoded on the <italic>Staphylococcus aureus </italic>Chromosome. Antimicrob Agents Chemother 59:747&#x02013;748</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sellam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteway</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Recent advances on <italic>Candida albicans</italic> biology and virulence</source><year>2016</year><publisher-name>F1000Research</publisher-name><fpage>2582</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidrin</surname><given-names>JJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>MFG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Micologia m&#x000e9;dica &#x000e0; luz de autores contempor&#x000e2;neos</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Guanabara Koogan</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siebra</surname><given-names>ALA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>AOBPB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potentiation of antibiotic activity by <italic>Passiflora cincinnata</italic> Mast. front of strains <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Saudi J Biol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2016.01.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29379354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29379354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Atividade antioxidante de <italic>Piper arboreum</italic>, <italic>Piper dilatatum</italic> e <italic>Piper divaricatum</italic></article-title><source>Rev Bras Pl Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>700</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1983-084x/13_097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AKF</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>EEA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modulation of the drug resistance by <italic>Platonia insignis</italic> Mart. extract, ethyl acetate fraction and Morelloflavone/Volkensiflavone (Biflavonoids) in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains overexpressing efflux pump genes</article-title><source>Curr Drug Metab</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389200221666200523155617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32445452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, spectroscopic characterization and antibacterial evaluation by chalcones derived of acetophenone isolated from Croton anisodontus M&#x000fc;ll.Arg</article-title><source>J Mol Structure</source><year>2021</year><volume>1226</volume><fpage>129403</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molstruc.2020.129403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Skaltsa HD, Demetzos C, Lazari D et al (2003) Essential oil analysis and antimicrobial activity of eight <italic>Stachys</italic> species from Greece. Phytochemistry 64:743&#x02013;752</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>CEV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamford</surname><given-names>TLM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influence of carvacrol and thymol on the physiological attributes, enterotoxin production and surface characteristics of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains isolated from foods</article-title><source>Brazilian J Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-83822013005000001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoldt</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonneborn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leuker</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efg1p, an essential regulator of morphogenesis of the human pathogen <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, is a member of a conserved class of bHLH proteins regulating morphogenetic processes in fungi</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1997</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1982</fpage><lpage>1991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/16.8.1982</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9155024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9155024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combatting antimicrobial resistance globally</article-title><source>Nat Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>16187</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmicrobiol.2016.187</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27670123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27670123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thai</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Virtual screening for novel <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> NorA efflux pump inhibitors from natural products</article-title><source>Med Chem</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1573406410666140902110903</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25181985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25181985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tulgar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alasehir</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The antimicrobial activity of ephedrine and admixture of ephedrine and propofol: an in vitro study</article-title><source>Rev Bras Anestesiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjan.2017.08.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ver&#x000ed;ssimo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fungal infections in Portugal - The sleeping giant</article-title><source>Infec&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Sepsis</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>19</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Veses V, Gow NA (2014) Pseudohypha budding patterns of <italic>Candida albicans</italic>. Med Mycol 47:268&#x02013;275</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viana</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutterbach</surname><given-names>MTS</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and antibiofilm activity of essential oil of <italic>Lippia gracilis</italic> Schauer on <italic>Clostridium bifermentans</italic> and fungal-containing biofilms</article-title><source>Austin Chem Eng</source><year>2019</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1066</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasicky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uma modifica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o do aparelho de Clevenger para extra&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de &#x000f3;leos essenciais</article-title><source>Rev Farm Bioquim</source><year>1963</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wightman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amornrrattanapan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, the Nim1 kinases Gin4 and Hsl1 negatively regulate pseudohypha formation and Gin4 also controls septin organization</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200307176</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14769857?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wright GD, Sutherland AD (2007) New strategies for combating multidrug-resistant bacteria. Trends Mol Med 13:260&#x02013;267</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of a salmonellosis outbreak caused by multidrug resistant <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium in China</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32082274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaumont</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of caryophyllene oxide as an antifungal agent in an in vitro experimental model of onychomycosis</article-title><source>Mycopathologia</source><year>1999</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1007178924408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11189747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11189747</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>