<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chitosan is poorly soluble in organic solvents, which may limit its potential use. To adjust the physicochemical properties for specific applications, chitosan’s amino and hydroxyl groups can undergo various modifications. Amine groups readily react with aldehydes and ketones to form Schiff bases. Hamed et al. [
 <xref rid="B19-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] obtained three new Shiff base chitosan derivatives with reactions with a pyrazole heterocycle compound. The chitosan derivatives showed strong antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Klebsiella</italic> as Gram-negative bacteria, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> as Gram-positive bacteria as well as 
 <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> as fungi. Moreover, the MMT test did not show any cytotoxic activity against normal retinal cells. N-selective chitosan derivatives were obtained: N-methylchitosan (NMC), trimethylchitosan (TMC), diethylmethyl chitosan (DEMC), and carboxymethyl chitosan (CMC). The replacement of the alkyl groups enhanced the antimicrobial activity of chitosan. However, TMC showed the best antimicrobial response against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, which may be due to the presence of positive charges on the chitosan skeleton. The results indicate that the quaternary derivative, O-methyl free N,N,N-trimethyl chitosan (TMC), had the best antimicrobial properties and good biocompatibility [
 <xref rid="B20-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Salama et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-18-00627" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] synthesized chitosan derivatives having guanidinium functions. Of the four derivatives, N-guanidinium chitosan acetate showed the best antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>B. subtilis</italic>, and 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, and they reported low minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) values for all the microorganisms.
</p>
