<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The broth microdilution method was determined as being the preferred method for investigating carrier oil activity [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The carrier oils alone and in combination with essential oils were tested in 1:1 ratios using the broth microdilution assay as detailed in [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. After the aseptic preparation of 100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L of sterile, distilled water was added to each of the 96 wells of a microtitre plate, followed by 100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L of the carrier oil, or 50 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L essential oil with 50 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L carrier oil for the combinations, to the first row. This was serially diluted descending down the microtitre plate columns. Antimicrobial susceptibility was confirmed with the inclusion of 0.01 mg/mL ciprofloxacin (Sigma Aldrich®) (for bacteria) or 0.10 mg/mL amphotericin B (Sigma Aldrich®) (for
 <italic class="italic"> C. albicans</italic>). A negative control of 32.0 mg/mL water in acetone was included to ensure the antimicrobial activity was not as a result of the solvent. The respective growth media of each pathogen were also included to ensure the support of microbial growth. After the preparation of an approximate inoculum concentration of 1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> colony forming units per mL (CFU mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) for each microorganism, 100 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L was added to each well. Sterile adhesive sealing film was used to seal each microtitre plate and the plates were incubated accordingly. After incubation, 40 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>L of 0.04% (w/v)
 <italic class="italic"> p</italic>-iodonitrotetrazolium violet solution (INT) (Sigma Aldrich®) was added to each well. A colour change of the indicator to pink or purple was indicative of microbial growth; thus the lowest concentration displaying no growth was taken as the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC). Each sample and combination was tested in triplicate and the mean taken. The MIC values were recorded and, for the combinations, the fractional inhibitory concentration index (ΣFIC) was calculated [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>].
</p>
