<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although it has been reported that 
 <italic>T. officinale</italic> may reduce the fitness of native herbs in many ways 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-MolinaMontenegro2" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Overgaard1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, little is known about the mechanisms associated with its wide distribution (but see 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Quiroz1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>.) Based on our results we suggest that 
 <italic>T. officinale</italic> is capable of invading a broad latitudinal gradient mainly because, being an r-selected species, this species is also able to exhibit a great level of phenotypic plasticity. In fact, in a recent paper Richards et al. (2006) 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Richards1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref> suggested that biological invasions would be driven by phenotypic plasticity, playing an important role in successful plant invasions in wide clines. Thus plasticity in functional traits may enhance ecological niche breadth and therefore confer a fitness advantage 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Richards1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Geographic gradients in abiotic conditions across a wide range could impose divergent selection pressures and promote genetically based differentiation among introduced populations. A classic manifestation of this is the evolution of geographic clines, often found in native species occurring across altitudinal gradients 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Jonas1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Neuffer1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. However, whether introduced plant populations rapidly evolve clines in response to environmental conditions across their introduced range has seldom been studied 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Neuffer1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Maron1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. Furthermore, whether clines in traits among introduced plant populations broadly converge on those expressed among native conspecifics occurring over similar latitudinal or altitudinal gradients is unknown. Nevertheless, this may be the case for 
 <italic>T. officinale</italic>, which shows not only high plasticity, but also local adaptation along a broad latitudinal gradient. Phenotypic plasticity and ecotypic differentiation are two complementary strategies to face environmental heterogeneity 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Counts1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Maron1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Sexton1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. It has been shown that plasticity can initially allow exotic species to become naturalized across the non-native range 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Sexton1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref> and, once naturalized, genetic recombination of heritable phenotypes may respond to local selection pressures giving rise to ecotypes with higher fitness 
 <xref rid="pone.0047620-Ellstrand1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>.
</p>
