<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A previous study observed that higher culturable endophytic bacterial diversity was associated with a higher likelihood of the host plant exhibiting antimicrobial properties (Egamberdieva 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). However, in contrast to bacterial diversity, this study also reported that the total bacterial cell numbers of colonizing microbes maybe higher in plants that have poor antimicrobial activity (Egamberdieva 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Presumably, this is due to less stringent conditions encountered in these plants which allows for high numbers of colonizing bacteria to proliferate due to the lack of competition and lower concentrations of antimicrobials. In our study, only a tentative relationship was observed, linking high culturable microbial diversity to previously known medicinal properties for the treatment of bacteria-associated disease or known antibacterial activity. The medicinal plants with the highest culturable bacterial diversity, 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> spp., 
 <italic>Ventilago</italic> sp. and 
 <italic>Salacia</italic> spp. are used to treat bacterial diseases and leaf extracts of 
 <italic>Coix lacryma-jobi</italic> and 
 <italic>Coscinium fenestratum</italic> (Nair 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Das 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) have been reported to have antimicrobial properties. However, we also observed plants with similar medicinal uses to have a low culturable diversity of ME isolates, namely 
 <italic>Calophyllum inophyllum</italic> and 
 <italic>Memecylon malabaricum</italic> (Table S1, Supporting Information). It should be noted that total bacterial numbers found within the leaves were not counted in our study. Further studies may be necessary to address the issue of achieving full culturable diversity, through focused efforts to isolate and count other endophytic community members including slow growing bacteria and fungi through the use of less complex and/or specific media (Eevers 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Martinez-Klimova, Rodríguez-Peña and Sánchez 
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).
</p>
