<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The biosynthetic pathway of khusimol should be possible in 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> because of the positive results for the in vivo production of many sesquiterpenes [
 <xref rid="B11-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Contrary to plants, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> produces endogenous FDP exclusively by the MEP pathway and is vital for the biosynthesis of the intermediates undecaprenyl diphosphate (UDP) and octaprenyl diphosphate (ODP) [
 <xref rid="B12-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Accordingly, UDP is the direct precursor of peptidoglycans, used for cell wall formation [
 <xref rid="B13-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], and ODP is involved in the respiratory chain for the biosynthesis of distinct quinones [
 <xref rid="B14-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Consequently, amounts of FDP in 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> are limited; thus, efforts have been made to engineer the MEP pathway to enhance the supply of FDP. As an example, the overexpression of the MEP pathway genes 1-Deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase (DXS) and 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase (DXR) increased the FDP levels and improved the amounts of lycopene up to 22 mg L
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> [
 <xref rid="B15-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Similarly, overexpression of the DXS synthase and additionally, the isoprenyl diphosphate isomerase (Idi) with the farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase (FPS) reached valerenadiene titers of 2.09 mg L
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> [
 <xref rid="B12-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Although overexpression of the MEP pathway improved the precursor supply, the terpene titers did not reach industrial levels, possibly due to control mechanisms of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> or the formation of intermediates that limited the precursor supply [
 <xref rid="B16-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-genes-10-00478" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
