<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The potential of polyphenols as natural antiplatelet, anti-inflammatory, and anticoagulant agents has prompted their analysis from a cardioprotective point of view. In this sense, numerous studies have demonstrated the beneficial cardiac effects of the walnut (
 <italic>J. regia</italic>). The major phenolic compounds present in 
 <italic>J. regia</italic> are ETs, including HHDP derivatives which are capable of releasing EA, a well-known antioxidant related to different health benefits [
 <xref rid="B46-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. A work based on human aorta endothelial cells analyzed the effects of an extract from peeled fruits of 
 <italic>J. regia.</italic> Initially, inflammatory processes were induced in the cultured cells by their exposure to TNF-α, which prompted the maximal expression of vascular cell adhesion protein (VCAM-1) and ICAM-1. The co-treatment of cells with 
 <italic>J. regia</italic> extracts or with purified EA, one of their major components, inhibited both inflammatory biomarkers [
 <xref rid="B47-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Another experiment (in vivo) utilized isoproterenol, a synthetic catecholamine capable of producing myocardium pathologies, to induce myocardial infarction. This catecholamine was administered individually or in combination with 
 <italic>J. regia</italic> extracts. The presence of walnut extracts reduced the severity of the myocardial infarction in a dose-dependent manner, quantified through serum creatine kinase myocardial band- levels and the activity of lactate dehydrogenase. Additionally, the administration of 
 <italic>J. regia</italic> extracts was able to reverse the negative effects of isoproterenol on oxidative markers, myocardial tissue lipids and at a histopathological level [
 <xref rid="B48-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Thus, these works, among many others, demonstrated the antiatherogenic and cardioprotective potential of the consumption of 
 <italic>J. regia.</italic>
</p>
