<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Other plants have also been evaluated in terms of cardioprotective activity. For instance, extracts obtained from leaves of 
 <italic>R. idaeus</italic> were evaluated through a blood ADP assay to determine how they modify blood platelet aggregation. The results showed that 
 <italic>R. idaeus</italic> reduced, by more than 20%, the expression of the glycoprotein IIb/IIIa, which is involved in the reception of fibrinogen and the activation of platelets. The activation of the aggregation was nearly inhibited to 50% by the presence of the extract. When the antiplatelet activity of the extracts was tested in blood, the inhibition of platelet aggregation was reduced to less than 20% [
 <xref rid="B83-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Ethanolic extracts from seeds of 
 <italic>Acacia senegal</italic> were tested as antiatherosclerotic and cardioprotective agents in an in vivo experiment with rabbits subjected to a hypercholesterolemic diet. The administration of the extract reduced the levels of the total cholesterol, low- and very low-density lipoprotein (LDL and VLDL) cholesterol and triglycerides in blood. Besides, 
 <italic>Acacia</italic>-treated subjects showed a lower atherogenic index accompanied by a reversion in lipid oxidation markers and histological damage [
 <xref rid="B84-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Finally, bark extracts from 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> were assayed using primary cultures of neonatal rat cardiomyocytes and cardiac tissues isolated from guinea pigs. Cardiomyocytes were exposed to H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> to induce oxidation states, while cardiac tissues were incubated with carbachol for testing the muscarinic activity, propranolol for the adrenergic/cholinergic activities and noradrenaline for evaluating aortic muscle behavior. 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic>-treated cardiomyocytes showed a dose-dependent reduction of intracellular ROS production, which directly improved cell viability. The aortic noradrenaline-induced contraction was reduced by the 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> extract, which also reduced heart rate and produced a positive inotropic effect in the left atrium/papillary (adrenergic receptor involvement was demonstrated) and negative chronotropic effect (not mediated by cholinergic receptors). Thus, the results supported the use of 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> extracts as dietary supplements since they may provide synergic beneficial effects as cardioprotective and antioxidant agents [
 <xref rid="B40-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
