<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Several studies have investigated the effect of growth conditions on rosemary yield and essential oil composition
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup> and their results implicate fertiliser application and dose as important agronomic factors. However, very few studies have been reported of the effect of fertiliser type and application rate on the characteristics of rosemary plants
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup> and these studies mainly focused on yield and oil quality. Several groups have reported that the use of fertilisers and/or amendments may alter vegetal cell wall content and composition
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>, but there is little or no knowledge of the effect of organic fertilisers on the composition of rosemary. Primary and secondary metabolites are the intermediate or ultimate products of complex networks of biochemical pathways
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>, whose functioning depends on substrates availability and/or enzyme activities, which at the same time are highly dependent on micro and macronutrient availability. As organic fertilizers are sustained sources of nutrients due to slow release during decomposition, soil nutrients are more available to plants over the time. Changes in macronutrient availability (e.g. N, P and K) indeed has a direct effect on metabolism, since macronutrients are directly involved in essential cellular processes, and in many cases the biosynthesis of important organic molecules e.g. proteins, nucleic acids, co-enzymes, phytohormones and secondary metabolites. Even elements that at first inspection would appear to be required in only very small amounts i.e. the micronutrients e.g. Mn, Fe, Zn and Cu, can have major influence on tissue composition and metabolism due to their requirement as cofactors for enzyme activity.
</p>
