<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">The methods used in this study all provide rich data on different aspects of sample composition, and are therefore orthogonal and complementary in nature. Gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry (GC/MS) is a fast and accurate technique widely used to characterise a great variety of biological and chemical samples. The strength of the technique lies in the combination of exceptional chromatographic resolution of chemical components in the sample coupled to mass spectral information that directly reflects molecular structure. The robustness and reproducibility of GC/MS has favoured adoption of GC/MS for many metabolomics studies, in which complex multivariate chemical relationships between samples are detected by multivariate data analysis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>. Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) also provides complex chemical data on sample composition, and mid-IR spectra informs of chemical bonds present in pure samples. Whilst it is possible to quantify primary and secondary metabolite concentrations in samples and tissues using regression models {Allison, 2011 #57;Schulz, 2005 #41;Allison, 2009 #2;Allison, 2009 56}. Lastly, we have used thermogravimetric analysis (TGA) to provide information on mass-fraction i.e. moisture, volatile and fixed carbon content as samples are heated in the absence of oxygen. TGA has been used to characterise organic wastes and composts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>, soils
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, lignocellulose composition and energy grass feedstock quality
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>, and the technique provides valuable information on the kinetics of thermal decomposition
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. We have used these methods to provide orthogonal, chemically meaningful data for chemometric analyses to visualise chemical/compositional relationships between samples and thereby investigate the effect of fertiliser dose and type on rosemary plants in a global context. This study aims to increase our understanding of the likely compositional effects of organic fertiliser application on rosemary crops and on populations grown in semi-wild regions for the purpose of soil stabilisation.
</p>
