<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Being a rich source for bioactive molecules, medicinal plants provide hope for development of novel antidepressant drugs [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. An alternative approach might come from aromatic plants. Although certain essential oils found in plants have been used as traditional medicines, little scientific evidence supports their use. Essential oils are complex mixtures of volatile compounds produced by aromatic plants [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Recent clinical studies show that essential oils, inhaled or orally administered, enter the blood stream and exert psychological effects, thus complementing pharmacodynamic mediation. For instance, inhalation, or oral administration of essential oils improves the quality of sleep [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], attenuates symptoms of dementia [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], negative affect [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], anxiety [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], nicotine craving [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>], post-traumatic stress disorder [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] and Alzheimer’s disease [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Preclinical pharmacological studies of essential oils and/or their isolated chemical constituents are becoming more common [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. In fact, several studies have shown that the aromatherapy could to be used as a complementary and alternative therapy for patients with depression and secondary depressive symptoms [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], including anxiety disorders [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. In a review published on plants used in aromatherapy for anxiety treatment, the contributions of the chemical constituents of their essential oils in this therapeutic effect are discussed [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], while a recent systematic review discusses the anxiolytic action of essential oils and their constituents [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-01290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. The objective for this review is to discuss certain essential oils and their isolated constituents being tested in humans and rodents for treatment of major depression. These essential oils and their constituents have been pre-clinically tested for their antidepressant activity and are, respectively, illustrated in 
 <xref rid="molecules-22-01290-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="molecules-22-01290-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>. In addition, the proposed mechanisms by which essential oils and their isolated compounds produce antidepressant actions are also discussed. Considering all of the information herewith presented, essential oils might well be an alternative source of therapy for the relief of major depression symptoms.
</p>
