<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infectious diseases are considered as one of the growing concerns in medical science worldwide [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>] and, in the latter respect, the microorganisms such as pathogenic bacterial and fungal strains are major agents of infectious diseases. Importantly, most such microorganisms have the ability to survive under harsh environmental conditions and can develop multidrug resistance. Regardless of the availability and use of effective antibiotic drugs, a range of multidrug-resistant strains of microorganisms have been posing health threats [
 <xref rid="B98-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Moreover, in the developing and underdeveloped countries, synthetic drugs are not only expensive and available in limited amount to treat infectious diseases, but they are often under the standard requirements and exhibit the lowest and/or side effects. Therefore, there is the need to search for novel and safer natural antimicrobial agents to control and fight against microbial infections [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Plant-based drugs and phytomedicines not only act as natural remedies to treat different diseases, but also serve as prototype to develop novel, safer, and effective modern medicines. The antimicrobial activities of 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> EOs have mainly been attributed to volatile bioactives such as oxygenated monoterpenoids along with monoterpene hydrocarbons (MHs) and sesquiterne hydrocarbons [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. 
 <italic>Mentha</italic> EOs are found to exhibit antibacterial activities against pathogenic bacteria including both Gram- negative and Gram-positive, such as 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aerogenosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Serratia marcesens</italic>, and 
 <italic>Streptococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Saba and collaborators reported the 
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> broad spectrum antibacterial activity against bacterial strains, such as 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella typhius</italic>, 
 <italic>B. subtilius</italic>, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermititis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Klebsiella pneumonia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. According to another study, MLEO exhibited strong antibacterial effects especially against Gram-negative strains including 
 <italic>P. aerginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, and 
 <italic>S. enteric</italic> [
 <xref rid="B100-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Mahady et al. found that methanol extract from peppermint was weakly active against 15 strains of 
 <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> with minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) in the range of 25–100 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="B101-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. However, the reported antibacterial effects of peppermint oil against different bacteria are random type, possibly due to difference of the plant varieties and bacterial strain used and/or testing conditions. In Anwar et al.’s investigation, MLEOs showed a natural antimicrobial effect against different strains of bacteria, but their activity varied with respect to the concentration of volatile chemical constituents [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The antibacterial potential of the oils tested was comparable with synthetic drug and its major chemical constituent, carvone. In another report, the EO isolated by supercritical fluid extraction (SCFE) from 
 <italic>Mentha spicata</italic> leaves also revealed good antibacterial potential against selected strains of bacteria such as 
 <italic>E. coli, S. aureus, B. aereus, B. pumilis, B. subtilis, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and 
 <italic>S. poona</italic> [
 <xref rid="B102-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. The authors noted that the antibacterial activity of the tested oils varied with respect to the oil composition depending on harvesting regions; however, it was relatively comparable with positive control (synthetic drug). Generally, the oil extracted from drought stressed spearmint populations showed greater antimicrobial activity and those from colder/hilly region exhibited a greater antioxidant activity and total phenolics and flavonoids content [
 <xref rid="B103-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Similarly, Ed-Dra et al. evaluated the antimicrobial effect of 
 <italic>Mentha suaveolens</italic> EO against pathogenic bacteria, showing that the EO of this species has antibacterial effect against Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria and hence could be used as a food additive to enhance the shelf- life of food products [
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-26-01118" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>].
</p>
