<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous genetic studies mapped both protein and oil QTLs to the 4.0 Mb region on chr15 [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], whereas, whether these traits were controlled by one gene was unknown. Here, we revealed that the complex and highly correlated protein and oil traits were controlled by a single gene 
 <italic>GmSWEET39</italic> with two major types of alleles carrying CC- and CC+ that were highly associated with high oil and high protein, respectively. Differing from the two contemporary studies locating 
 <italic>GmSWEET39</italic> using genetic sweep-inferred approach followed by functional validation [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], we identified 
 <italic>GmSWEET39</italic> and its causative allele (CC Indel) underlying the long-pursued chr15 QTL using the classic genetics and high-resolution GWAS followed by uncovering its dual role for oil and protein improvement. Uncovering the causative gene and alleles for the long-pursued chr15 QTL and the dual functions of the 
 <italic>GmSWEET39</italic> alleles allows us to associate it tightly with soybean decades’ breeding practices and highlight its importance in increasing oil or protein during soybean domestication and improvement. Its agricultural importance was evidenced by the fixation of CC- allele in the US cultivars during the 90-year soybean breeding and its extensive uses in soybean improvement worldwide. Our study demonstrated that the H1 and H3 account for almost all variation of 
 <italic>GmSWEET39</italic> (98.8%) in cultivated soybean and contribute to high oil and high protein respectively. It fits the pleiotropic role of chr15 QTL on seed protein and oil content as revealed in our and previous studies [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. It is likely that different selection pressures on H1 (CC-) and H3 (CC+), based on distinct needs for high oil, high protein soybean cultivars, consequently affected their allelic frequencies in soybean population.
</p>
