<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In another experiment, Cos et al. (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Cos et al., 2002b</xref>) investigated the antiviral activity of certain Rwandan plants against human immunodeficiency virus type-1. They showed that ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Aspilia pluriseta</italic> Schweinf. ex Engl. (Asteraceae) exhibited pronounced antiviral activity by enabling an absolute cell-resilient against HIV-induced cytopathic effect compared to the controls. The selective index value of the extract was found to be greater than 12 (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Cos et al., 2002b</xref>). Also, thiarubrine-A 
 <bold>(93)</bold> isolated from the leaves of 
 <italic>A. pluriseta</italic> demonstrated phototoxic activity against enveloped viruses such as cytomegalovirus and Sindbis virus (
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">Hudson et al., 1986</xref>). The ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Rumex nepalensis</italic> Spreng. (Polygonaceae) with a selective index of 11 was able to achieve 89% cell protection against HIV-induced cytopathic effect. The residue obtained when ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Tithonia diversifolia</italic> (Hemsl.) A. Gray (Asteraceae) was suspended in 60% methanol and was subsequently extracted with petroleum ether and ethyl acetate concurrently: it displayed significant inhibitory effect as anti-HIV-1 agent having a selective index greater than 461 (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Cos et al., 2002b</xref>). In addition, the aqueous fraction showed pronounced anti-HIV-1 activities at concentrations of 200, 40, 8, 1.6 and 0.32 μg/ml. Furthermore, isolation of sesquiterpene lactones such as diversifolin 
 <bold>(91),</bold> diversifolin methyl ether, and tirotundin 
 <bold>(92)</bold> from 
 <italic>T. diversifolia</italic> has been reported with relevant pharmacological properties (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Asres et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Cos et al., 2002b</xref>). The mode of action of these compounds is associated with decline in the production of inflammatory mediators including cytokines and chemokines. The reported mechanism involves the interference with the DNA binding activity of the transcription factor NF-ҡB (
 <xref rid="B233" ref-type="bibr">Rüngeler et al., 1998</xref>). The fact that some of these products exhibit biological activities involving host inflammatory response may indicate their potential treatment potentials in COVID-19 with its reported inflammatory undertone [
 <bold>Level III, V</bold>]. Another bioactive compound with anti-HIV-1 activity isolated from the mature stems of 
 <italic>T. diversifolia</italic> is an artemisinic acid derivative (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Bordoloi et al., 1996</xref>). Artemisinic acid is a sesquiterpenoid precursor of artemisinin and the semi-synthetic product 12-
 <italic>N</italic>-butyl deoxoartemisinin has been reported to inhibit HIV activity (
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2012</xref>). It should however be pointed out that in-depth 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and clinical investigations will need to be conducted to objectively establish the clinical relevance of these plant products. Interestingly however, the major component of the Madagascar’s COVID organics (CVO), a herbal formulation containing 
 <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> L. (Asteraceae), is the antimalarial compound artemisinin. Although the efficacy and safety of CVO is yet to be clinically validated, the overwhelming willingness of other African countries to participate in the clinical trials highlights the priority accorded plant-derived medicines in Africa. The WHO and African Health Ministers have agreed to allow herbal and indigenous health products to go through requisite clinical trials to establish their efficacy and safety prior to adoption as treatment options for COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B274" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020</xref>). Increasing evidence suggests that these plant-derived antimalarial sesquiterpene lactones, an active component 
 <italic>T. diversifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>A. annua</italic> may hold a promise in COVID-19 treatment provided further research attention is given to support efficacy and safety (
 <xref rid="B224" ref-type="bibr">Rahman et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">da Silva Antonio et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
