<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Helichrysum foetidum</italic> Moench (Asteraceae) is one of the selected Rwandan medicinal plants (
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr">Sindambiwe et al., 1999</xref>) whose ethanol extract (200 mg/ml), after a 10-fold dilution produced antiviral activity by limiting the extracellular viability of herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV 1) and Semliki forest virus A7 (SF A7) while 
 <italic>Chamaecrista mimosoides</italic> (L.) Greene (Fabaceae) and 
 <italic>Ipomoea involucrata</italic> P.Beauv. (Convolvulaceae) under the same experimental conditions and concentration displayed high antiviral potential against HSV 1
 <italic>. Ipomoea involucrata</italic> was potent as a virucidal agent against vesicular stomatitis virus T2 (VSV T2), SF A7 and measles virus strain Edmonston A (MV-EA). Findings from this study showed that 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>mimosoides</italic>, 
 <italic>Rotheca myricoides</italic> (Hochst.) Steane and Mabb. (Lamiaceae) and 
 <italic>Helichrysum cymosum</italic> (L.). D. Don ex G. Don (Asteraceae) demonstrated virucidal activity against HSV 1, measles virus strain Edmonston A (MV-EA), and Semliki forest virus A7. In addition, the study highlights the virucidal activity of 
 <italic>Maesa lanceolata</italic> Forssk. (Primulaceae) against the screened enveloped viruses which was exceptional compared to the other tested plants, making this plant an interesting candidate for further research consideration against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <bold>Level V</bold>]. Also investigated is a mixture isolated from methanol extract of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>lanceolata</italic> (leaves) termed maesasaponin mixture A. This mixture was found to reduce the titer and infectivity of herpes simplex virus type 2 (HSV 2) at concentrations of 100 μg/ml and 250 μg/ml, respectively. More so, it incapacitated the virus at 500 μg/ml concentration. Maesasaponin mixture A also repressed the activity of vesicular stomatitis virus T2 (VSV T2) (
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr">Sindambiwe et al., 1999</xref>). Maesasaponin mixture A may be a promising potential source of active antiviral metabolites which may produce activity against SARS-CoV-2 following a more elaborate preclinical, clinical investigations and phytochemical standardization of extracts which are lacking in the study under review [
 <bold>Level V</bold>].
</p>
