<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot7-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Chromatographic Analyses of the Essential Oil of Lemongrass</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The qualitative and quantitative analyses of the essential oils were realized by chromatography in gas phase, attached to the mass spectrometry CG-MS. The chromatograph utilized was the model Shimadzu GC-210, equipped with mass selective detector model QP2010 Plus, and was operated in these conditions: capillary column of fused silica TRX-5MS (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm of film thickness); with the following programming of the temperature on the column: 60–240 °C (3 °C min
  <span class="sup">−1</span>); injector temperature: 220 °C; carrier gas helium; and, splitless injection with injected volume of 1 μL of a solution 1:1000 in hexane. For the mass spectrometer (MS), there were utilized the following conditions: impact energy of 70 eV; ion source, and interface temperature: 200 °C. There was injected, at the sample conditions, a homologous series of n-alkanes (C
  <sub>9</sub>H
  <sub>20</sub>… C
  <sub>26</sub>H
  <sub>54</sub>). The obtained specters were compared with the Nist and Wiley 229 Library’s database and the retention rate calculated to each component was compared to the tabulated, according to [
  <a rid="B15-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-medicines-04-00062">15</a>]. The quantification of essential oils compounds levels were obtained with a gas chromatograph equipped with a flame ionization detector (FIT) using a Shimadzu GC-210 device, in the following methodology: capillary column RTX-5MS (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm of film thickness); injector temperature: 220 °C; FIT temperature: 300 °C; with column programming: initial temperature of 60 °C with a heating rate of 3 °C min
  <span class="sup">−1</span> until 240 °C, next, passing to a heating rate of 10 °C min
  <span class="sup">−1</span> until 300 °C, remaining on this temperature for 10 min; drag gas nitrogen (1.18 mL min
  <span class="sup">−1</span>); split rate 1:50; column pressure of 115 KPa, and injected volume of 1 μL in hexane.
 </p>
</sec>
