<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>Temperature fluctuations may induce metabolic and physiological imbalances over marine organisms, involving reproduction, growth, immune response, osmoregulatory capacity, and antioxidant defenses. It is of great importance to find tools, including nutritional interventions on farms, able to reduce such imbalances and the consequent stress for animals. In light of this perspective, we investigated the correlations between temperature and metabolic performance in sea bass fed on diet containing oregano essential oil. Under the condition of our study, thermal changes affected the levels of several biomarkers (e.g., triglycerides and cholesterol) highlighting an attempt to provide for additional energy, to counterbalance the oxidative damage, and to maintain cell homeostasis. On the other side, the activity of antioxidant enzymes, TBARS levels, and the energetic balance seemed to benefit from the intake of oregano essential oil under exposure to thermal changes.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>A feeding trial for 150 days was carried out to evaluate the cross-effects between oregano essential oil (EO) dietary supplementation and dynamic temperature change in sea bass. Under exposure to rising temperature (13–25 °C), fish were fed with a control diet (CD) and two experimental diets supplemented with 100 (D100) and 200 ppm (D200) of EO. Feed inclusion of EO promoted the activity of antioxidant enzymes in sea bass exposed to increasing temperature. Consistently with the temperature rise, TBARS concentrations increased in CD and D200 groups, whereas were almost stable in D100. Trend of blood glucose in fish fed on CD was likely affected by glycogenolysis and gluconeogenesis. Similarly, the depletion of triglycerides and cholesterol in fish fed on CD likely supported the energy cost of gluconeogenesis. On the other hand, the reduction of glucose, triglycerides, and cholesterol in D100 and D200 was mainly attributable to the hypoglycemic and hypolipidemic effects of EO. The higher levels of serum protein observed in D100 and D200 groups were also associated to a reduced thermal stress compared to CD. EO dietary supplementation may be a promising strategy to alleviate the negative effects of temperature shift on sea bass physiological and oxidative state.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
