<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As it’s known, the bone broth is a liquid food and occupies large volumes for storing and transportation and also it has limited shelf life due to its chemical composition. Therefore, it is necessary to increase the storage stability of such liquid foods with appropriate preservation methods. Drying is one of the most ideal preservation methods which would practice in liquid foods. With the help of the drying, larger volumes can be substantially decreased and shelf life of final dried products can be extended (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Khawas et al., 2014</xref>). Although there are several types of drying techniques such as drum, freeze and microwave-vacuum drying, spray drying is an efficient drying method used to transform liquids into powdered product by spraying it continuously into a hot drying medium (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kurozawa et al., 2009</xref>). Especially, compared to freeze-drying, the cost of spray-drying method is seen to be more cheaper (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Desobry et al., 1997</xref>). Moreover, due to their high protein and fat content the bone broth cannot pulverized in spray-dryer without carrier agents alone, it has necessary been used encapsulating with carrier agents. Carbohydrates such as maltodextrin (MD), gums, pectin, starches and corn syrup are usually used as carrier agents in spray drying method. With the exception of MDs with dextrose equivalence between 10 and 20, carbohydrate based on wall materials showed poor interfacial properties and must be chemically modified in order to improve their surface activity. In contrast, proteins have an amphiphilic character which shows excellent emulsification properties and accordingly allows to encapsulate hydrophobic core materials. Moreover, protein compounds such as sodium caseinate, soy protein isolate, and whey protein concentrates and isolates, could also be expected to have good microencapsulating properties. MDs, whey protein and mixture of them isolates are low cost and very useful for spray drying process on food materials. So, encapsulation is an important step in the production of the bone broth powder. Encapsulation is defined as a process in which tiny particles or droplets are surrounded by coating or embedded in a homogeneous or heterogeneous matrix and give small capsules with many properties (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gharsallaoui et al., 2007</xref>). Carrier agents provided extra protection against oxygen, water and light which leads to oxidation reactions (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Turchiuli et al., 2005</xref>). The whey protein isolate, the MD and mixtures of them have been utilized as carrier agents for a good microencapsulation in food industry. The whey protein isolates are by-product of the dairy industry and have high protein content thus, they show good emulsification, gelation and film formation properties in encapsulation process. The MD is an important product obtained from starches and is mainly used in materials that are difficult to dry (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kurozawa et al., 2009</xref>). It has been reported that the use of the whey protein isolates in combination with the MD during the encapsulation process provides a nearly smooth surface in the final powdered food particles. This smoothness is important for the functionality of the core material (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sanlıdere-Aloglu and Oner, 2010</xref>).
</p>
