<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">The study was conducted in the semi-arid lowlands (Njemps Flats) of Baringo County, located along the Great Rift Valley system in Kenya (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The study area extends from latitude 0° 10′ N to 0° 50′ N and longitude 35° 20′ E to 36° 20′ E, covering an area of approximately 180,000 ha. The Njemps Flats are slightly undulating, with an average altitude of 700 m a.s.l. They are surrounded by Laikipia Escarpment on the east and Tugen Hills and Elgeyo Escarpment on the west, ridges and plateaus of the Lake Baringo catchment with peaks of over 3000 ma.s.l
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup>. The average annual temperature and precipitation are 24.6 °C and 671 mm, respectively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup>. Presently, the vegetation is predominantly a woody mixture of indigenous and exotic species. It ranges from 
 <italic>Vachellia</italic>-dominated deciduous shrubland on the valley floor to the evergreen forests in the highlands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> currently dominates the lowland flats, the shores of Lake Baringo and further southwards to Lake Bogoria`s western shoreline
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup>. Historically, the lowland flats consisted of a mosaic of grasslands and 
 <italic>Vachellia</italic>-dominated savanna
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>
 </sup>. The study area is essentially a rangeland with few isolated pockets of dryland subsistence agriculture and small-scale irrigation in Marigat
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup>. The major social-economic activities are livestock production, and bee-keeping, and more recently charcoal production
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>
 </sup>. A more detailed description of the study area is provided by Mbaabu et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
