<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There were no detrimental AOCED effects on litter size or puppy viability and survival indices (
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>). Moreover, the viability and survival indices were generally higher in the AOCED dietary groups compared to those in the control group, confirming that DHA and EPA are needed for optimal fetal and neonatal development [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Further, puppy body weights, height and head circumference before weaning were generally increased in the low- and mid-dose AOCED groups compared to those in the control (
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217794.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217794.s009" class="xref">S1 Fig</xref>). Interestingly, there were no differences in growth parameters observed in the high-dose AOCED group compared to the control; the increases were limited to the low- and mid-dose groups. The apparent limitations in beneficial effects of AOCED on early dog development by doses up to 1.5% in the diet could be related to modulating effects of DHA and EPA on arachidonic acid levels. Arachidonic acid (ARA) is needed for adequate growth and development during perinatal nutrition along with DHA [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In the human studies with pre-term infants, growth parameters were affected negatively in a group consuming formula supplemented with marine oil [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. This effect was attributed to the decline in ARA blood levels observed in the marine oil group compared to the standard formula control [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. To achieve a balance between omega-3 and omega-6 fatty acids, commercial infant formulae are typically supplemented with both DHA and ARA.
</p>
