<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A competitive relationship between the long chain omega-3 and omega-6 fatty acids has been reported in animal studies as well [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Dietary DHA and EPA compete with ARA for incorporation into cell membrane phospholipids [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Accordingly, supplemented DHA and EPA allow for the partial replacement of ARA in the lipids of blood cells and organ cells thereby reducing the ARA content and the amount of ARA available to form metabolites [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. We observed declines in ARA tissue levels with administration of high doses of algal oils across multiple species including rats, dogs and humans [
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217794.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. The AOCED lot used in the present study contained 2.0% ARA and 56.3% of combined DHA+EPA as area% of total fatty acids (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec002" class="xref">Methods</xref> for details). Plasma ARA reductions were observed in the high-dose AOCED group both in the dams at the end of lactation period and in the puppies at weaning (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec014" class="xref">Results</xref> for details). Noteworthy, no detrimental effects on growth parameters were observed even in the high-dose group compared to the control, indicating that there was sufficient amount of ARA in the diet to sustain an adequate growth. However, the beneficial effects of AOCED diets on growth parameters observed in the low- and mid-dose AOCED groups were absent in the high-dose group, i.e. the growth was similar to the control rather than superior (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217794.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217794.s009" class="xref">S1 Fig</xref>).
</p>
