<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The vetiver essential oils from different extraction techniques were analyzed by GC-MS. The gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analyses were performed using an Agilent GC 7820A (Agilent Technologies, Model 7820A G4350A, Santa Clara, CA, USA) coupled with an Agilent 5975C mass selective detector (Agilent Technologies, Model 5975C VL, USA). The MS detector was operated in the electron ionization (EI) mode (electron energy = 70 eV), scan range = 4–400 mAU, and scan rate = 3.99 scans/s). GC was equipped with a flame ionization detector (FID) and an HP-5ms capillary column (30 m × 0.25 mm, i.d × 0.10 μm, film thickness). Helium was used as a carrier gas with a column head pressure of 48.7 kPa and a flux of 1 mL/min [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Samples of 1 μL were injected using the split mode (split ratio 1:50). The injector and detector temperatures were 250 and 220 °C, respectively. The oven temperature was set as follows: Initial temperature of 50 °C, held for 5 min; increased at 3 °C/min to 240 °C, and maintained at 240 °C for 10 min. The chemical compounds of vetiver essential oil were identified based on the retention indices of the homologous series of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-alkanes, and by comparing their mass spectral with those reported in literature [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-24-01897" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], as well as the NIST11 library, Wiley10 library and FFNSC1.2 library.
</p>
