<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are mixed results with regard to an adverse effect of KDs on growth retardation. Some prospective studies reported constant linear growth during the first six months of treatment with CKD [
 <xref rid="B40-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], while others have observed a deceleration in height after six months of treatment, in children prescribed with CKD [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>] and MCTKD [
 <xref rid="B49-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Nevertheless, from the available research it is difficult to draw firm conclusions on the effect of the ketogenic diet on growth. Very often the results are confused by the ketogenic dietary management, the follow-up protocol, the duration of treatment, and the pre-existing malnutrition due to the diagnosed disease [
 <xref rid="B50-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Furthermore, the same mechanisms underlying the association between KDs and growth are unclear. One hypothesis involves reduced secretion and bioavailability, during treatment with KDs, of insulin-like growth factor I (IGF-1), one of the major growth effectors in children [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Further speculation links the reported growth retardation found in children treated long-term with KDs with reduced levels of serum ghrelin [
 <xref rid="B51-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. However, the results concerning the KDs impact on ghrelin concentration are conflicting. Finally, KDs could act differently on growth across the different developmental ages. In a prospective study of 237 children treated with CKD, it was found that older children grew “almost normally”, whereas younger ones had growth retardation [
 <xref rid="B43-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Other studies, on the contrary, did not find any age difference between children who grew as expected and those who had retarded linear growth [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Prospective studies specifically designed to evaluate the impact of KDs on growth are required before drawing any firm conclusions.
</p>
