<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For the lipid profile, the results are discordant. Several prospective studies reported an increment in serum lipids after initiation with CKD, both in children [
 <xref rid="B42-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] and adults [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. However, in children, these increments are usually transitory, and normalize with diet continuation. Medium-long term studies showed an improvement of the lipid profile after 12 and 24 months [
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>], with a return to pre-treatment values after this period [
 <xref rid="B57-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. No study evaluated the long-term effect of CKD on lipid profile in adults. A return to pre-diet values has instead been shown after diet cessation [
 <xref rid="B55-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. In adults, early increments in serum lipids have been shown with MAD [
 <xref rid="B38-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>] and LGIT [
 <xref rid="B38-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], however, also here, they tend to normalize within a year of treatment [
 <xref rid="B59-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Finally, conflicting results are reported for the impact of MCTKD on blood lipids in children. In a prospective study, an improvement of the lipid profile was observed 4 months after diet initiation [
 <xref rid="B42-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], however, in another, 7% of the children showed a relevant increase in both total cholesterol and LDL cholesterol values during the MCTKD [
 <xref rid="B61-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>].
</p>
