<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To determine the lowest inhibitory concentration of cinnamaldehyde extract on two strains 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Candida glabrata</italic>, we used eight different concentrations. For each microorganism, a plate was used to evaluate the effect of cinnamaldehyde extract, and overall two plates for two types of 
 <italic class="italic">candida</italic> were considered. To prepare the required dilutions for nystatin, according to the protocol of the Sigma factory, 1.024 mg of nystatin powder were added to 1 ml of 5% Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and a concentration of 1.024 mg/ml of nystatin obtained. The culture media were prepared according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Then, the 
 <italic class="italic">candidates</italic> prepared on the culture medium with sterile inoculating loops and the plate was incubated for 24 hours in a 37°C incubator, and then candida colonies appeared on the culture medium. Fungal suspensions were prepared according to the turbidity McFarland criterion 0.5. Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC) of cinnamaldehyde extract were determined by dilution in the tube. To determine the MIC for a series of eight tubes, we tested the dilutions of each extract. Also, a tube as a positive control containing diluted extract and a negative control medium containing microbial suspension and culture medium was considered. A total of eight dilution series of cinnamaldehyde extract was prepared as 187.5, 125, 93.75, 62.5, 46.8, 31.2, 23.4, 15.6 μl/ml. According to the microdilution method contained in CLSI, in each of the eight microplates, these concentrations, plus 10 μl of fungal suspension were placed. They were incubated 24 hours at 37°C and eventually the first transparent well that indicated the lack of microorganism growth was considered as MIC. The contents of wells without growth were cultured in a solid culture medium, and after 24 hours of incubation, the lowest concentration in which growth was not observed was considered as MFC. To control the test, positive control and negative control were considered, so that we used the culture medium and 
 <italic class="italic">candida</italic> for positive control and the culture medium and cinnamaldehyde for negative control. Ethics committee approval was not required for this study.
</p>
