<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Arthropod Borne Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Arthropod Borne Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAD</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">JAD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Arthropod-Borne Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2322-1984</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2322-2271</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5641611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jad-11-226</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of Larvicidal Activity of Essential Oil from Leaves of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> against Three Mosquito Species</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>Shahid Iqbal</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vishwakarma</surname><given-names>Kishor Sukhlal</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>Vijay Laxminarayan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="C1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="AFF1">School of Life Sciences, North Maharashtra University, Jalgaon, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="C1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Prof Vijay Laxminarayan Maheshwari, E-mail: <email>vlmaheshwari@rediffmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright&#x000a9; Iranian Society of Medical Entomology &#x00026; Tehran University of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License which allows users to read, copy, distribute and make derivative works for non-commercial purposes from the material, as long as the author of the original work is cited properly.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>To study the chemical constituents and larvicidal activity of essential oil extracted from the leaves of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> against three mosquito species.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Essential oil was extracted by hydro distillation using clevenger apparatus and was analyzed for chemical constituents by gas chromatography-mass spectrophotometry (GC-MS). Larvicidal activity was recorded after 12 and 24h of post-exposure against three mosquito species, <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic>, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>. Dead larvae were identified when they failed to move after probing with a needle in the siphon or cervical region. The LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values for three mosquito larvae were calculated by Probit analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The GC-MS analysis revealed that essential oil contains 23 different constituents. Out of these 23 constituents, major constituents identified were n-tetracosane (39.18%), n-eicosane (30.04%), tetratriacotane (2.97%), 7-octadecanal (2.81%), and tricosane (2.31%). Essential oil from leaves of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> exhibited significant larvicidal activity against <italic>An. stephensi</italic> with LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values 39.41ppm and 123.24ppm, respectively. This was followed by <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic> with LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values of 48.20ppm, 131.84ppm and 52.80ppm, 135.48ppm, respectively after 24h of exposure.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>The results could be useful in developing a cost effective, ecofriendly, region specific and practical strategy for the control of mosquito vectors.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Coccinia grandis</italic></kwd><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd>Mosquito</kwd><kwd>Larvicidal</kwd><kwd>GC-MS</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Mosquitoes are responsible for a number of human health problems causing illness and death throughout the world in both children and adults. They are vector for many diseases such as malaria, filariasis, dengue, Japanese encephalitis, chikungunya and west Nile virus infection in tropical and subtropical countries (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Anupam et al. 2012</xref>). Malaria is a deadly disease and globally about 3.3 billion peoples are at the risk of it. About 198 million cases of malaria and 0.58 million deaths occurred globally in 2013 (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2014</xref>). Of the six malarial vector species, <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> is the main mosquito vector responsible for malaria in urban areas of India (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar et al. 2009</xref>). Dengue fever is caused by mosquito vector species, <italic>Ades aegypti</italic> in its epidemic areas affecting millions of people and thousands of deaths per year all over the world (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Service 1996</xref>). Similarly, <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> is a vector for lymphatic filariasis, commonly known as elephantiasis, in India. Lymphatic filariasis is caused by the worms <italic>Wuchereria bancrofti</italic>, <italic>Brugia malayi</italic> and <italic>Br. timori</italic> of which, first is found to be more endemic in Indian subcontinent. According to <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">WHO (2009)</xref> more than 1.3 billion people spread over 72 different countries worldwide are threatened by it. Collectively, these mosquito mediated diseases are responsible for long term suffering, morbidity and high socio economic burden on society (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Ramaiah et al. 2000</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Intirach et al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>Efficient control of these diseases would require a two-pronged strategy, (i) prompt treatment with effective medicines and (ii) vector control based prevention strategies. Injudicious use of medicines, particularly antimalarial drugs, has resulted in development of resistance by the malarial parasite and enhanced casualties in endemic areas (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Intirach et al. 2012</xref>). Mosquito management therefore, offers a better and practical alternative for controlling diseases mediated by them. Mosquito adulticides, causing temporary reduction in population are good but do not offer a lasting solution. Mosquito larvae being delicate, less mobile and more concentrated in their natural habitat offer a much simpler and efficient point of intervention and control (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Rutledge et al. 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Dharmagadda et al. 2005</xref>). However, there are reports of development of resistance and behavior changes in adult mosquitoes and larvae towards these chemicals (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Mittal et al. 2004</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2006</xref>). Moreover, they adversely affect the environment, causing soil, air, water pollution and harm the beneficial non target organisms (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Dharmagadda et al. 2005</xref>). Plant extract including essential oils or insecticides from botanical origin are attractive alternatives because they contain high amount of various bioactive compounds, many of which are selective and have little or no harmful effects on non-target organisms and environment (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Rutledge et al. 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Dharmagadda et al. 2005</xref>). Essential oil is natural volatile substances found in many plants. Essential oils isolated from plant are generally a mixture of many constituents, primarily biologically active monoterpenes (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Govindrajan 2010</xref>). Traditionally, they have been used for flavor enhancement in food, odorants in fragrances, pharmaceuticals and confectionary industries (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al. 2001</xref>). Of late, they have received considerable attention as potentially active, human and environment friendly bio insecticides (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. 2003</xref>). There are several reports on larvicidal activity of essential oil from neem, basil, citronella, lemon, eucalyptus, pine etc (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Amer and Mehlhorn 2006</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Dua et al. 2009</xref>). The resistance against plant derived insecticides has not been reported so far (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kannathasan et al. 2011</xref>).</p><p><italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> (family Cucurbitaceae) is a unique tropical plant, commonly known as &#x02018;little gourd&#x02019;, growing abundantly and widely all over the India. It is a fast growing perennial climbing shrub with white flowers. It grows several meters long and forms dense mat that readily cover shrubs and small trees. It is well known for its hypoglycemic activity (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ajay 2009</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Munasinghe et al. 2011</xref>).</p><p>The present study was focused on the chemical constituents and larvicidal activity of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> leaf essential oil against vectors of malaria (<italic>An. stephensi</italic>), dengue (<italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>) and filariasis (<italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>). To the best of our knowledge it is the first report on the larvicidal activity of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> leaf essential oil against the three mosquito species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Collection of Plant material and extraction of essential oil</title><p>Plant material of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> was collected from Eklagna village Jalgaon. [20&#x000b0; 58&#x02032; 54.3&#x02033; N, 075&#x000b0; 27&#x02032; 09.5&#x02032; E (elevation: 199m)] Maharashtra, identified at Botanical Survey of India, Pune and a specimen voucher number MSMI-1 was deposited in the School of Life Sciences, North Maharashtra University Jalgaon. The collected fresh leaves were cut in to small pieces and extraction was done using Clevenger apparatus for 6h (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al. 2008</xref>). The extracted essential oil was subjected to dryness over anhydrous sodium sulfate (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) to remove traces of moisture. The physical characteristics of extracted essential oil were recorded, percentage average yield was calculated and it was stored at 4 &#x000b0;C in amber-colored bottle in refrigerator until further analysis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>GC and GC-MS analysis</title><p>Gas chromatography mass spectroscopy (GC-MS) analysis of essential oil was performed using JEOL GCMS-Mate-II model gas chromatograph-mass spectrometer equipped with an AOC-20i auto injector and HP-5 capillary column (30m &#x000d7; 0.25mm ID &#x000d7; 0.25&#x003bc;m coating thickness) column. The injector temperature was set at 280 &#x000b0;C, and the oven temperature was initially set at 40 &#x000b0;C then programmed to increase up to 300 &#x000b0;C at the rate of 10 &#x000b0;C/min and finally held at 200 &#x000b0;C for 5 min. Helium gas was maintained at a flow rate 1.0ml/min as a carrier gas. One microliter of the sample diluted with acetone in 1:10 ratio was injected in the split mode. The percentage of constituents in essential oil of leaves was calculated by the GC peak areas. Data handling was made through JEOL software and the compounds were identified based on the comparison of their retention time (RT) and mass spectra of WILEY, NIST library data of the GC-MS.</p></sec><sec><title>Mosquito larvicidal assay</title><p>Mosquito larvicidal activity was performed against mosquito larvae of species <italic>An. stephensi</italic>, <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and <italic>Cu. quinquefasciatus.</italic> Larvae of <italic>An.s stephensi</italic> [21<sup>0</sup>00&#x02032;14.3N, 075<sup>0</sup>29&#x02032;39.8E (elevation: 207m)], <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> [2101&#x02032;01.2N, 075<sup>0</sup>29&#x02032;52.3E (elevation: 192m)] and <italic>Cu. quinquefasciatus</italic> [21<sup>0</sup>00&#x02032;53.5N, 075<sup>0</sup> 29&#x02032;39.8E (elevation: 185m] were collected from local breeding areas of Jalgaon, India and identified using the microscopic examination as per Theodore et al. (2005). The collected mosquito larvae were brought to laboratory and maintained at 25&#x02013;30 &#x000b0;C with 80&#x02013;90% relative humidity and 12 h/d/night cycle in plastic trays containing dechlorinated water. Mosquito larvae were fed with 10% sterile sucrose solution and pet biscuits. The mosquito larvicidal activity was performed according to standard procedure recommended by <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">WHO (1981)</xref>. The extracted dried and pre weighed essential oil was dissolved in 1ml of acetone and from this different concentrations were made such as 3.125, 6.25, 12.50, 25, 50 and 100ppm in distilled water. Twenty five early fourth instar stage larvae of each of the three species of mosquito were used for larvicidal assay in 200ml beakers and three replicates were maintained for each concentration used. During the experiment, no food was given to the larvae.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The larval mortality rate was calculated after 12 and 24 h of exposure time. The lethal concentrations, LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> and their 95% confidence limit of the lower and upper levels were calculated by probit analysis using statistical software Stats Direct 2.8.0.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The essential oil yield from fresh and finely cut leaves of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> was 0.14gm% (<italic>w/w</italic>). The yield was calculated after drying (removing the moisture) over anhydrous sodium sulfate (Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>). The essential oil after dryness gave a slightly sticky clump with light yellow color and a characteristic odor. The GC-MS profile of the essential oil from leaves of <italic>Co. grandis</italic> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. The various constituents of essential oil, their retention time and percent composition in order of elution from the column are given in the <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The GC-MS profile shows a total of 23 constituents accounting for 99.60% of total oil. The two major constituents of essential oil from leaves of <italic>Co. grandis</italic> were n-tetracosane (39.18) and n-eicosane (30.04%). Six constituents (peak number 4, 6, 10, 13, 18 and 19) were present between 2&#x02013;3 percent were as the percentage composition of remaining ranged between 0.1&#x02013;2 percent (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry profile of essential oil obtained from leaves of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAD-11-226-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Chemical composition of essential oil of the leaves of <italic>Coccina grandis.</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Peak no.</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Retention time(min)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chemical compounds</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Percentage</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>01.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E,E,Z-1,3, 12-Nanodecatriene-5,14-diol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>02.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.76</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heneicosane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>03.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phytol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>04.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-heptatriacotanol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>05.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17-pentatriacontene</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>06.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tricosane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>07.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1- Dodecanol, 2-Coctyl-</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>08.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.96</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,5-Furandione, 3-dodecyl</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>09.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetrapentacosane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Dodecen-1-yl(-)sucinic anhydride</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.77</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n-Eicosane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octasane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-octadecanal</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>14.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.06</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexatriacontane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>15.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.77</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n-tetracosane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,3 O-triacotanediol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>17.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.41</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z-14-octadecen-1-ol acetate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.96</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pentadeachal</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>19.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetratriacotane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triacotane</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>21.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.62</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meissyl alcohol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>22.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.76</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palmitic acid</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>23.</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myristic acid</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>99.60%</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The essential oil extracted from leaves of <italic>Co. grandis</italic> shows promising larvicidal activity against three mosquito species <italic>An. stephensi</italic>, <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and <italic>Cu. quinquefasciatus</italic>, (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values against early fourth instar larvae of <italic>An. stephensi</italic>, after 12 and 24 h of exposure were calculated to be 72.60 and 169.90 and 39.41 and 123.24ppm, respectively. Similarly, LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values against early fourth instar larvae of <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> after 12 and 24h of exposure were calculated to be 83.25 and 191.60 and 48.20 and 131.84ppm, respectively. The values were marginally higher with early fourth instar larvae of <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic> than the other two species under identical conditions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Larvicidal activity of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> leaf essential oil after 12 and 24 h of exposure period on larvae of <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic>, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mosquito species</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Concentration (ppm)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>% of Mortality&#x000b1;SE</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>LC<sub>50</sub> (LCL&#x02013;UCL)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>LC<sub>90</sub> (LCL&#x02013;UCL)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>X<sup>2</sup> (df=4)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN4"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>An. stephensi</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 12h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.125</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0&#x000b1;6.89</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.60 (43.12&#x02013;106.50)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.90 (90.05&#x02013;265.96)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.60</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="11" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">After 24h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x000b1;5.77</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">39.41 (12.07&#x02013;67.619)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">123.24 (43.276&#x02013;212.45)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">28.581</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x000b1;1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#x000b1;1.52</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42&#x000b1;1.55</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60&#x000b1;0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.125</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x000b1;0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21&#x000b1;0.82</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41&#x000b1;1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#x000b1;1.52</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66&#x000b1;1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75&#x000b1;1.85</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ae. aegypti</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 12h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.125</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0&#x000b1;0.33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.35 (25.73&#x02013;145.96)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191.60 (35.89&#x02013;370.94)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.077</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="11" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">After 24h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#x000b1;0.87</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">48.20 (19.25&#x02013;78.66)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">131.84 (49.23&#x02013;223.96)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">27.862</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26&#x000b1;0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38&#x000b1;1.52</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43&#x000b1;0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51&#x000b1;0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.125</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#x000b1;1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x000b1;0.88</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33&#x000b1;0.86</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51&#x000b1;0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61&#x000b1;1.15</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71&#x000b1;0.26</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 12h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.125</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0&#x000b1;0.28</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.40 (36.18&#x02013;175.94)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">217.39 (54.32&#x02013;413.03)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.41</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="11" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">After 24h</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x000b1;0.39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">52.805 (23.92&#x02013;83.50)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">135.48 (55.54&#x02013;224.83)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="11" colspan="1">25.756</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x000b1;0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31&#x000b1;1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#x000b1;0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41&#x000b1;0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.125</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#x000b1;0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#x000b1;0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#x000b1;0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47&#x000b1;1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59&#x000b1;0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69&#x000b1;0.96</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p><sup>a</sup>Degree of freedom</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><p>LCL lower confidence level,</p></fn><fn id="TFN3"><p>UCL upper confidence level</p></fn><fn id="TFN4"><p><sup>a</sup>95% confidence level</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Several authors have reported different compositions of essential oils obtained from different plant species (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Govindrajan 2010</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar and Venkatesalu, 2010</xref>, Zhu et al. 2011, 2012, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Rajkumar et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Intirach et al. 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. 2012</xref> and <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar et al. 2013</xref>). The plants show significant variations, both in terms of number and percentage composition, of different constituents in essential oil and it appears to be the characteristics of a particular plant.</p><p>The excellent larvicidal activity of the essential oil of <italic>Co. grandis</italic> against three species of mosquitoes could be either due to the major components, i.e. n-tetracosane and eicosane or synergistic action of the major and minor components present in it and is difficult to pin point at this stage. Tetracosane is an alkane hydrocarbon and use of hydrocarbons as pesticidal agents is reported (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Siddique et al. 2004</xref>). Similarly, there are evidences indicating larvicidal and antimicrobial activities of the other major component, eicosane (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Akpuaka et al. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Manas et al. 2014</xref>). The results show significantly improved bioefficacy against one of the mosquito species, <italic>An. stephensi</italic> compared to earlier report which showed LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values of 93.3 and 192.6ppm, respectively (as against the 39.41 and 123.24ppm in present study) (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Rajkumar et al. 2011</xref>). Similarly, the LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values against <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> have been found to be 47.54 and 86.54ppm for <italic>Mentha piperita</italic>, 40.50 and 85.33ppm for <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>, 115.60 and 193.30ppm for <italic>Cu. longa</italic> and, 148.50 and 325.70ppm for <italic>Oc. basilicum</italic>, respectively (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Kalaivani et al. 2012</xref>) compared to 48.20 and 131.84ppm for <italic>Co. grandis</italic> in the present study. The LC<sub>50</sub> and LC<sub>90</sub> values of the <italic>Co. grandis</italic> leaf essential oils against larvae of <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic> were marginally better than essential oils of <italic>Acorus calamus</italic> reported by <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar and Venkatesalu (2012)</xref>.</p><p>The results are also in agreement with several other previous reports where the major components of essential oils have shown excellent larvicidal or insecticidal activities, eg <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> leaf essential oil (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar and Venkatesalu 2010</xref>), <italic>Clausena anisata</italic> leaf essential oil (Govindrajan 2011), <italic>Feronia limonia</italic> leaf essential oil (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar et al. 2013</xref>). Similarly, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Intirach et al. (2012)</xref> studied essential oils of six different plant families and demonstrated their larvicidal activity against laboratory colonized <italic>An. cracens</italic> mosquito. A careful observation of these representative studies indicated that there was no common thread in terms of chemical constituents, in these essential oils. The composition and major and minor components of essential oil are characteristics of particular plant and, at the best may be represented in the other members of same family. The composition and larvicidal activity of essential oil of a plant may vary as a function of age of plant, geographical location and season. The observed variations in the efficacy of essential oils from various plants against different vectors could be due to different chemical compositions and/or synergistic action of major and minor components in them (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Senthilkumar and Venkatesalu 2012</xref>). The natural diversity of essential oils in the indigenous plants thus offer good opportunity of developing a cost effective, ecofriendly, region specific and practical strategy for the control of mosquito vectors either independently or as a part of integrated vector management strategy. Though there are no reports of insecticide/larvicide resistance in the study area, the same is well documented in African countries for <italic>Anopheles</italic> species against all the approved four classes (organochlorines, pyrethroids, carbamates and organophosphates) of insecticides (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Kristan et al. 2003</xref>). Of the four classes, resistance to pyrethroids and its mechanisms in <italic>An. gambiae</italic>: the most important malarial vector in Africa has been extensively studied. It was found out that the insect develops resistance to insecticide either by altering its binding site, by point mutations, or by detoxifying it enzymatically before it reaches the target site (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Tielong et al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>Pyrethroids are the insecticides of choice for mosquito control primarily because of their superior human and environment safety records (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adedayo et al. 2012</xref>). Besides, the use of insecticide mixtures and their periodic rotation, integrated vector management, involving biopesticides/essential oils of plant origins could be the answer for preventing/ delaying development of resistance in mosquitoes (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Brogdon and Allister 1998</xref>).</p><p>The present study is a step forward in the direction, demonstrating the larvicidal potential of essential oil of a locally available plant against three most common mosquito species. The chemical analysis shows a different set of major and minor components in the essential oil than the earlier reported studies which can be gainfully utilized further.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Results of this study will be helpful in developing cost effective, ecofriendly, region specific and practical strategy for the control of mosquito-borne diseases.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>One of the authors (SIM) acknowledges the fellowship from UGC, New Delhi under its MANF (Maulana Azad National Fellowship for Minorities) scheme. Financial support from UGC, New Delhi and DST, New Delhi for strengthening the research facilities in the School under the SAP-DRS and FIST programmes, respectively are gratefully acknowledged. The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adedayo</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmanuel</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><name><surname>Muyiwa</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name><surname>Adedapo</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Judith</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Olubunmi</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Taiwo</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Evidence of carbamate resistance in urban populations of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> s.s</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22686575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ajay</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Hypoglycemic activity of <italic>Coccinia indica</italic> (Cucurbitaceae) leaves</article-title>. <source>Int J Pharm Tech Res</source>. <volume>1</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>892</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>893</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akpuaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekwenchi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dashak</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dildar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Biological Activities of Characterized Isolates of n-Hexane Extract of <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> A. Juss (Neem) Leaves</article-title>. <source>New York Sci J</source>. <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehlhorn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#x0201c;Larvicidal effects of various essential oils against <italic>Aedes</italic>, <italic>Anopheles</italic>, and <italic>Culex</italic> larvae (Diptera: Culicidae)&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>466</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>472</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16642386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anupam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandita</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Goutam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Plant extracts as potential mosquito larvicides</article-title>
<source>Indian J Med Res</source>. <volume>135</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>581</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>598</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22771587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brogdon</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Allister</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Insecticide resistance and vector control</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <volume>4</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>613</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9866736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>&#x0201c;Bioactivity of selected plant essential oils against the yellow fever mosquito <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> larvae&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol</source>. <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dharmagadda</surname><given-names>VSS</given-names></name><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasudevan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Larvicidal activity of <italic>Tagetes patula</italic> essential oil against three mosquito species</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol</source>. <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>1235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1240</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15734310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dua</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Raghavendra</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>&#x0201c;Larvicidal activity of neem oil (<italic>Azadirachtaindica</italic>) formulation against mosquitoes&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Malar J</source>. <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>124</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19500429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chemical composition and larvicidal activity of leaf essential oil from <italic>Clausena anisata</italic> (Willd.) Hook. f. ex Benth (Rutaceae) against three mosquito species</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Trop Med</source>. <volume>3</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>874</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>877</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajeswari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yogalakshmi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chemical composition and larvicidal activity of essential oil from <italic>Mentha spicata</italic> (Linn.) against three mosquito species</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>2023</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2032</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Intirach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Choochote</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Junkum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaithong</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Champakaew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuetun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jitpakdi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitasawat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Chemical constituents and combined larvicidal effects of selected essential oils against <italic>Anopheles cracens</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>
<source>Psyche</source>. <volume>2012</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalaivani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthil-Nathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murugesan</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Biological activity of selected <italic>Lamiaceae</italic> and <italic>Zingiberaceae</italic> plant essential oils against the dengue vector <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> L. (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>110</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>1261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21881945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kannathasan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesalu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Mosquito larvicidal activity of methyl-p-hydroxybenzoate isolated from the leaves of <italic>Vitex trifolia</italic> Linn</article-title>. <source>Acta Trop</source>. <volume>120</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21763671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kristan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Della</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Pyrethroid resistance/ susceptibility and differential urban/ rural distribution of <italic>Anopheles arabiensis</italic> and <italic>A. gambiae</italic> s.s malaria vectors in Nigeria and Ghana</article-title>. <source>Med Vet Entomol</source>. <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>326</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>332</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12941018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pawan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Raka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>In vitro propagation and biosynthesis of steroidal sapogenins from various morphogenetic stages of <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> Lam, and their antioxidant potential</article-title>. <source>Acta Physiol Plant</source>. <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1749</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1762</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijeyaratne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Status of insecticide resistance of malaria, kala-azar and Japanese encephalitis vectors in Bangladesh, Bhutan, India and Nepal (BBIN)</source>, <publisher-name>Environmental Health Project</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washigton, DC, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munasinghe</surname><given-names>MAAK</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeysena</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaddehige</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidanapathirana</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Piyumal</surname><given-names>KPB</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Blood Sugar Lowering Effect of <italic>Coccinia grandis</italic> (L.) J. Voigt: Path for a new drug for Diabetes Mellitus</article-title>. <source>Exp Diabetes Res</source>. <volume>2011</volume>: <fpage>978762</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21822423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin-Chao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui-Wen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhi-Long</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu-Shan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhi-Wei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Chemical composition and insecticidal activity of the essential oil of <italic>Illicium pachyphyllum</italic> fruits against two grain storage Insects</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>. <volume>17</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>14870</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14881</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23519259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajkumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jebanesan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effect of leaf essential oil of <italic>Coccinia indica</italic> on egg hatchability and different larval instars of malarial mosquito <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic></article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Trop Med</source>. <volume>4</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>948</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>951</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22118029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramaiah</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The economic burden of lymphatic filariasis in India</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Today</source>. <volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10827432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutledge</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Larval mosquito control</article-title>, <source>Technical bulletin of the Florida mosquito control association</source>. <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesalu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Chemical constituents and larvicidal potential of <italic>Feronia limonia</italic> leaf essential oil against <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic>, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></article-title>
<source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23160893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesalu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chemical composition and larvicidal activity of the essential oil of <italic>Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> (Lour.) Spreng against <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic>: a malarial vector mosquito</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>1275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1278</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20668876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesalu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Larvicidal potential of <italic>Acorus calamus</italic> L. essential oil against filarial vector mosquito <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Trop Med</source>. <volume>107</volume>: <fpage>1275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1278</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurusubamanian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Larvicidal and adulticidal activities of some medicinal plants against the malarial vector <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> (Liston)</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18787842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Service</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1996</year>) <source>Medical Entomology for Students</source>. <publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilyas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulzar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Naqvi</surname><given-names>SNH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Analysis of Insecticidal <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic></article-title>. <source>Z Naturforsch C</source>. <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15018062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>IPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heluani</surname><given-names>GSD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampasona</surname><given-names>MPD</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Chemistry, antioxidant and antimicrobial investigations on essential oil and oleoresins of <italic>Zingiber Officinale</italic></article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>3295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18706468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andreadis</surname><given-names>Theodore G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>Michael C</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Identification guide to the mosquito of Connecticut</article-title>. Shepard Illustrations by Gale Ridge The Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tielong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Daibin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Linhua</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xuelian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fengyang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiyun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title><italic>Anopheles sinensis</italic> mosquito insecticide resistance: comparison of three mosquito sample collection and preparation methods and mosquito age in resistance measurements</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24472598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Instruction for determining the susceptibility or resistance of mosquito larvae to insecticideas</article-title>. <source>WHO-VBC 81</source>. <volume>807</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Global programme to eliminate lymphatic filariasis</article-title>. <source>Wkly Epidemiol Rec</source>. <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>444</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19860021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <source>World Malaria Report</source>. <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Guidelines for the Treatment of Malaria</article-title>. <source>WHO-WC</source>. <volume>770</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>BCR</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of vetiver oil and seven insect-active essential oils against the Formosan subterranean termite</article-title>. <source>J Chem Ecol</source>. <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1625</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11521400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>