<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hepato steatosis or fatty liver disease (FLD) is mainly caused by an imbalance in production and metabolization of fat in the body. Higher consumption of fat also negatively affects oxidation of fatty acid in the liver and enhanced deposition in the chief functional cells of the liver (hepatocytes), which causes oxidative stress and hepatic steatosis. A very high fat cell deposition alters the signaling pathways. The peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR) and nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kB) pathways are involved in the obesity inflammation process. The progression of liver damage may result in subclinical icteric hepatitis to necro-inflammatory hepatitis, cirrhosis, and carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B71-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Therefore, the compounds having a role as an antioxidant and inhibitor of lipid peroxidation and their free radical scavenging capacity may show the hepatoprotective properties. MLs tea was prepared using Ubá variety leaves [
 <xref rid="B72-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. This MLs tea contains about 0.72 mg/mL mangiferin, 1.59 mg GAE/mL total phenolic content, 80% of radical scavenging activity, and 0.007 µg/µL EC
 <sub>50</sub> value. The 25 mL/day dose of MLs tea was given to fat obese rats and the effects were evaluated. The rats consuming a high-fat diet activated hepatic steatosis and increased accumulation of cell fat by 46% compared to control. Treatment of rats consuming a high fat diet with MLs tea increases the nucleus, cytoplasm blood vessels percentages, and reduced accumulation of fat droplets, consequently reducing the incidence of FLD. These hepatoprotective activities of MLs tea were mainly due to gene expression. It is reported that increased expression of PPAR-α enhances oxidative stress, inflammation, and lipid metabolism in obese mice, whereas negative modulation of PPAR-α and adiponectin receptor II (AdipoR2) results in FLD [
 <xref rid="B73-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. High fat diet decreases the expression of mRNA of PPAR-α and AdipoR2, while MLs tea up-regulates the gene expression of PPAR-α and AdipoR2, attenuating FLD. At the same time, the expressions of NF-κB p65 and sterol regulatory element-binding proteins (SREBP1c) genes were reduced in cells of liver. It was also concluded that MLs tea improves the situation of FLD by acting as an anti-inflammatory agent via PPAR-α activation and NF-κB modulation [
 <xref rid="B74-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Therefore, MLs products can be used as hepatoprotective and alternative for the treatment of fatty diet induced FLD or hepatic steatosis.
</p>
