<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effect of the 
 <italic>C. alnifolia</italic> extracts was evaluated on cell viability. One nontumour cell line was used: NIH/3T3 (ATCC CRL-1658—a murine fibroblast) as well as five tumour cell lines: HeLa (ATCC CCL-2—an adenocarcinoma cell of human uterus), SiHa (ATCC HTB-35—a human squamous cellular carcinoma cell), PC-3 (ATCC CRL-1435—a human prostate adenocarcinoma cell), B16-F10 (ATCC CRL-6475—a mouse skin melanoma cell), and PANC-1 (ATCC CRL-1469—a pancreatic adenocarcinoma cells). First, cell lines were grown in culture flasks using the Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) supplemented with FBS (10% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) and antibiotics (100 U/mL penicillin and 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL streptomycin). These culture flask were maintained in a humidified 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> atmosphere at 37°C. To evaluate the extract effect on cell viability, the cells were transferred into 96-well plates at 5 × 10
 <sup>3</sup> cell per well until they reach the confluence. The extracts (HE, CE, EE, ME, WEE, and AE) were added at 0, 100, 250, or 500 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL for 24 h at 37°C in a 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> atmosphere. After the incubation period, the medium was changed to 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>L of MTT (1 mg/mL dissolved in DMEM). Then, cells were incubated for 4 h in a 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> atmosphere at 37°C. Next, the wells were aspirated, and formazan crystals were solubilized by the addition of 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>L/well ethanol [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Plate was read at 570 nm absorbance using an Epoch microplate spectrophotometer (BioTek Instruments Inc., Winooski, VT, USA). Cell viability was determined and compared to the negative control (only DMEM) using the following formula: %viability = (
 <italic>A</italic>
 <sub>test</sub>/
 <italic>A</italic>
 <sub>control</sub>) × 100, in which 
 <italic>A</italic>
 <sub>test</sub> corresponded to the absorbance of the experimental group, and 
 <italic>A</italic>
 <sub>control</sub> was the absorbance of the negative control.
</p>
