<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum micranthum</span> Willd was taxonomically classified and identified by the biologist José L. Tapia of the Herbarium at Natural Resources Unit of the Center for Scientific Research of Yucatan, Merida, Yucatan, Mexico. A specimen was deposited in this same Herbarium with reference number 68785. Leaves of this plant were used to obtain the extracts evaluated in the present study. Leaves were collected during the winter season between December 2013 and February 2014 at 100 m around the point 21°9'10.91" North latitude and 89°5'4.58" West longitude in the town of Cansahcab, Yucatan, Mexico. Harvested leaves were washed and then dried in a convection oven at 50 °C for 16 h. Finally, the leaves were ground in a mill Ika (model A11).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation of essential oil and aqueous extract</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil was obtained by hydro-distillation of ground leaves of 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum micranthum</span> Willd, using a Clevenger trap [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. The fraction of essential oil was separated by density and then stored under refrigeration (4 °C) in glass vials sealed with Teflon tape, and covered with foil until its characterization.
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aqueous phase was collected in plastic containers, then filtered using a membrane of 0.22 μm and finally stored under refrigeration (4 °C). This phase was called the aqueous extract.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preparation of the ethanolic extract</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ethanolic extract was obtained by Soxhlet extraction of ground leaves of 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum micranthum</span> Willd, using reagent-grade ethanol (JT Baker) as the solvent. The ethanol was recovered through Büchi rotary evaporator (model R-215) with a vacuum controller (V-850) coupled to a cooling unit. The extract was stored in glass bottles and then filtered through a filtration system comprising a stainless-steel base and a Millipore filter (0.22 μm). Finally, the ethanolic extract was labeled and refrigerated at 4 °C until its analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microbial strains</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antimicrobial activity of the essential oil and extracts of 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum micranthum</span> Willd leaves was evaluated through the determination of minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) using the microdilution technique on a 96 well plate and by staining with a solution of iodonitrotetrazolium chloride (INT). The microorganisms used in this study consisted of two Gram-positive strains (
   <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> ATCC® 25973TM and 
   <span class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</span> ATCC® 465 TM); one Gram-negative strain (
   <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> ATCC ® 27,853 TM) and one yeast-fungus strain (
   <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> ATCC® 14,053 TM).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Growth kinetics</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the McFarland turbidimetric analysis [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], a wavelength of 590 nm was used. The absorbance values of this test were correlated with the absorbance values from the growth kinetics of each microorganism tested. This correlation was used to calculate the time taken by each microorganism to reach the exponential phase and the concentration of microorganism necessary to carry out the microdilution test. The value recorded in the present study was 0.50 on the McFarland scale which is equivalent to 1.5 × 10
   <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/mL. In the growth kinetics, a pre-inoculum of each microorganism was incubated for 20–21 h at 35 °C in agitation. The culture medium used for this purpose were brain heart infusion (BHI) broth for 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span>, nutritive broth (
   <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span>) and sabouraud broth (
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span>). The absorbance was measured every 2 h during a period of 16 h using a spectrophotometer model GENESYS 20 (®Thermo Scientific) at a wavelength of 590 nm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimal inhibitory concentration</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the MIC test, five concentrations of the fluid extracts (ethanolic, aqueous and essential oil) of 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum micranthum</span> Willd leaves were analyzed. These concentrations were chosen through the evaluation of the results of osmolality and pH assays that were performed to avoid interferences in the tests with mammalian cells. The dilutions of the extracts were prepared with 5% dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) solution (D8418-500 mL ® Sigma Aldrich). This concentration of reagent was selected based on the results of a preliminary test where different concentrations of DMSO were evaluated to measure its toxicity on the microorganisms utilized in the present study and to eliminate the possibility of interference by the concentration of DMSO. Positive controls such as amikacin (4 mg/L) and nystatin (2 mg/mL), control of culture medium, color control of each extract concentration and positive control of growth of each microorganism were used. In the test, 100 μL of each microorganism suspension at a concentration of 1.5 × 10
   <span class="sup">8</span> CFU/mL (0.5 of the McFarland scale) was inoculated in the 96 well microplates, and then 100 μL of each extract solution were added. The microplates were incubated at 35 °C for 20–21 h in the case of 
   <span class="italic">S. aureus, B. subtilis</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span>; in the case of 
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span>, the incubation time was 40–42 h. Once the incubation period had lapsed, 20 μL of a solution of iodonitrotetrazolium chloride 0.25 mg/mL (58030-1 g-F ®Sigma Aldrich) was added to the 96 well microplates, which were incubated at 35 °C for 1 h [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Subsequently, the MIC was determined visually, and of the wells that did not present a color change, an aliquot of 50 μL was taken to inoculate a Petri dish with a media corresponding to the evaluated microorganism. On the Petri dish, an extension technique using a digralsky spreader was carried out, after the Petri dishes were incubated at 35 °C for 24 h (
   <span class="italic">S. aureus, B. subtilis</span>, 
   <span class="italic">and P. aeruginosa</span>) and 48 h (
   <span class="italic">C. albicans</span>). Finally, the microplates were read in a microplate reader (model Stat Fax 4200 (® Awareness Technology) at a wavelength of 492 nm.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MIC was reported for each microorganism in every extract. The MIC was defined as the lowest concentration that led to growth inhibition, which was visually observed as no color change in the colorimetric test. The growth of some microorganisms in the Petri dishes indicated a bacteriostatic effect, while no growth of the microorganism indicated a bactericide effect of the extracts. Concerning 
   <span class="italic">Candida albicans,</span> the terms that were applied were either a fungistatic or fungicide effect respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of pH and osmolality</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before performing the MTT test, the pH and osmolality of the culture media, which was supplemented with the extracts, were evaluated with the purpose of verifying that the values were in the optimum range and to avoid cytotoxic effects by osmotic shock or pH and, in this way, assess only the effect of the extracts on the cell lines. All osmolality measurements were performed with an osmometer (Advanced Instrument Inc. model 3320) using the freezing point depression method. The pH measurements were carried out with a VWR® SB90M5 pH meter.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell lines and cell culture</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two cell lines were used in this study, healthy human breast-derived fibroblasts (hFB) and adherent Chinese hamster ovary cells (CHO-K1, Gibco, USA), this last cell line is a classic model of cytotoxic tests and proliferative assays due to its capacity of adaptation in adherent mode or suspension [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Both cell lines were routinely grown in DMEM F12 medium (Gibco, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, USA) at 37 °C in a humidified atmosphere of 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MTT assay</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of the essential oil and the aqueous and ethanolic extracts of 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum micranthum</span> leaves on CHO-K1 and hFB cell lines was assessed using the tetrazolium colorimetric MTT assay [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. The cells were seeded at a density 2 × 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> cells/well in 96-well microtiter plates and incubated at 37 °C and 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub> in a humidified environment for 24 h. Subsequently, 100 μL of six different concentrations of each extract was added to the wells, and the plates were incubated for 48 h. The final concentrations of the extracts in the wells were 0.0075%, 0.015%, 0.03%, 0.06%, 0.125% and 0.25% for essential oil; 0.25%, 0.5%, 1%, 2%, 4%,8% for aqueous extract and 0.0075%, 0.015%, 0.03%, 0.06%, 0.125% and 0.25% for ethanolic extract. After that, 10 μl of MTT solution (5 mg/ml in RPMI-1640 without phenol red, Sigma Aldrich®) was added to each well, and the plates were incubated at 37 °C for 2 h. Following the incubation period, 100 μL of MTT solvent (0.1 N HCl in anhydrous isopropanol) was added to the wells to solubilize the formazan crystals. Multiskan FC (®Thermo Scientific) microplate reader at 570 nm was used for the measurement of the absorbance. The measurement of the color control of all concentrations of each extract was carried out to ensure that no interference occurred in the measurement of each well. The percentage of relative cell proliferation was calculated based on a comparison with untreated cells (control) as [extract absorbance/control absorbance] × 100. Microscopic viewing of the cell cultures was performed before and after the assay using an inverted microscope Axio Vert 200 (Carl Zeiss) coupled to a video camera.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trypan blue exclusion assay</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trypan blue exclusion assay is a visual method used for the direct counting of viable cells. Therefore, it was chosen to evaluate the proliferative activity of the essential oil and extracts (aqueous and ethanolic) of 
   <span class="italic">Ocimum micranthum</span> leaves on hFB cell line and for comparison with a colorimetric method such as MTT. The cells were seeded in a 24 well plate (cell density of 2 × 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> cells/well) and incubated at 37 °C in an atmosphere of 5% CO
   <sub>2</sub> and a humidified environment for 24 h. The next day, cells were treated with six different concentrations of each extract for 48 h. The morphological changes of treated and untreated cell line (control) were compared by monitoring, using an inverted microscope Axio Vert 200 (Carl Zeiss). After the morphological assessment, the cell viability was evaluated by Trypan blue dye exclusion assay. For this, the cells were rinsed with 1 mL of phosphate buffered saline (PBS 1X, Gibco) and trypsinized with 0.50 mL of 0.025% trypsin-EDTA (Gibco). Then, trypsin was neutralized by the addition of 0.50 mL of growth medium. Samples were taken and stained with 0.04% Trypan blue dye solution (Sigma Aldrich). Within two minutes, the cells were loaded in a Neubauer chamber, and the number of viable and non-viable cells in squares with a 1 mm
   <span class="sup">2</span> area, was counted under a phase contrast microscope. The relative cell proliferation was determined as [no. of viable cells in the cells treated/ no. of viable cells in the cells no treated (control)] × 100.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results of MTT and Trypan Blue test were presented as the Mean ± Standard deviation (SD). The data were subjected to one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) using STATGRAPHICS PLUS 5.1 statistical program. Duncan’s Method was used in the multiple comparisons in the cases where the ANOVA detected a significant difference (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
