<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">Cinnamon oil is an aromatic liquid obtained from the twigs, bark and leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. Extracts of cinnamon bark (CNB) and leaves (CNL) have been used extensively as therapeutics in many cultures since antiquity. The anti-candida activity of CNB oil against planktonic and biofilm culture of 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">non</italic>-
 <italic class="italic">albicans</italic> spp. has been documented [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>]. The main constituents of CNB oil include trans-cinnamaldehyde, and minor components such as eugenyl acetate, linalool, and benzyl benzoate, each having antifungal activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>]. CNB oil has been shown to alter cell membrane permeability and fluidity, and inhibit biofilm formation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>], but the mechanisms of toxicity remain unknown. On the other hand, each component has been extensively studied, showing effects at various cellular sites, including the cell membrane and cytosol. For example, cinnamaldehyde, the major constituent of CNB oil, targets the membrane and causes increased cell wall thickness in 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>], attributed to β-1-3-glucan synthase inhibition as observed in 
 <italic class="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>]. The increase in bud scar formation upon cinnamaldehyde exposure also suggests an impact on cell division, resulting in decreased viability [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. Benzyl benzoate and linalool affect membrane fluidity and induce cell cycle arrest at the G2-M and G1 phases, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>] at concentrations greater than the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. We hypothesized that the cell wall and membrane are primary targets of CNB oil, which in turn disrupt intracellular processes vital to 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> survival.
</p>
