<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To understand the effect of suboptimal actin fixation protocols on CD4 membrane organization we correlated live-cell and fixed-cell actin and CD4 organization using NanoJ-Fluidics (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2A</xref>) and Structured Illumination Microscopy (SIM) (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>).We imaged actin in live COS7 cells with an utrophin domain (UtrCH-GFP) (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>) probe and CD4 tagged with TagRFP-T. We performed chemical fixation using three different chemical fixation protocols, 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in PBS at 23°C, 4% PFA in PEM (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>) at 4°C or at 37°C (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figures 2B</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">D</xref>). Subsequently, using NanoJ-SQUIRREL (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>), to compare the live-cell vs. fixed-cell organization of actin and CD4, we were able to identify the effects of the suboptimal (4% PFA in PBS at 23°C and 4% PFA in PEM at 4°C) fixation protocols on these targets and compare with the optimal protocol (37°C 4% PFA in PEM) (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>). As expected (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>), using PBS we observed a loss of protrusive actin-based structures and actin stress fibers appear to be disassembled or disrupted (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2B</xref>). The fixation resulted in an almost indiscernible actin cytoskeleton, which translates to a NanoJ-SQUIRREL error map exhibiting strong artifacts (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2B</xref>). Using PEM buffer, more suited for actin preservation (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>), but at a suboptimal temperature (4°C), we see less of the aforementioned defects on the actin organization (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2C</xref>). Pre-warming the PFA-containing PEM buffer to 37°C yielded a similar difference between live and fixed sample as measured by NanoJ-SQUIRREL (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2D</xref>). Regardless of the fixation approach we did not see an effect on CD4 membrane organization, quantified on the error maps where most of the differences are due to vesicle motion during fixation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figures 2B</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">D</xref>).
</p>
