<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One limitation of the present work is that cases involving hornets, wasps, or bees could not be separately identified, with data provided by death certificates. Statistics extracted from hospitals and poison centers are difficult to obtain, so it is very important to facilitate the sharing of this information [
 <xref rid="B38-biology-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In this context, the different news that appeared in the media should not be ignored, since they allow us to know insect-related incidents with precise details about the fatality. Between 2014 and 2018, I recorded eight fatalities in Galicia involving wasps and/or hornets, which appeared in the media. Most of them showed enough evidence to point to the Asian hornet as the cause of death. So far this year (2020), the national press, radio, and television have reported three deaths from insect stings in Galicia and one death in Asturias, pointing to the Asian hornet as the culprit. In Galicia: (i) in September, a 69-year-old man, working in the forest, was found lying on the ground two hours after leaving his house; the first hypothesis suggests that the death occurred as a consequence of an attack by an Asian hornet nest; (ii) in May, a 73-year-old man suffered a strong allergic reaction that ended his life, when he was harvesting seeds in the garden and received the attack of 
 <italic>Vespa velutina</italic> nest embedded in a close-by fencing wall; and (iii) also in May, a 54-year-old man passed away after receiving a 
 <italic>Vespa velutina</italic> sting while checking on an apiary near his house. An Asian hornet nest was settled inside one of the beehives. The deceased was accompanied at the time by another beekeeper. Emergency health services rushed to the scene, but there was nothing to be done to save his life. The victim was not allergic to honeybee venom. On previous occasions, he had suffered stings from common bees/wasps without significant effects; however, this time a single sting on the face was fatal in a few minutes. In Asturias, in July, a 40-year-old man died in Asturias, due to 
 <italic>Vespa velutina</italic> stings. The tragic event occurred when he was mowing grass on his property, where a nest was found.
</p>
