<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SWEET proteins are encoded by a large and ancient gene family in divergent plant species, and associated with diverse plant physiological and developmental processes such as disease infection, pollen growth and seed development [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Patil et. al [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] showed that soybean contains 52 
 <italic>GmSWEET</italic> genes that have been clustered into distinct subfamilies. Diverse expression patterns have been observed for those soybean genes, suggesting that 
 <italic>GmSWEET</italic> gene family have been sub-functionalized with distinct expression patterns to meet diverse needs of sugar transporting for plant growth and response to environmental signals [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Interestingly, 
 <italic>GmSWEET39</italic> and its orthologue 
 <italic>AtSWEET15</italic> were both predominantly expressed in seed coat tissues and functioned in regulating oil content [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Arabidopsis and soybean have been diverged from each other for 90 million years [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The conservation of their gene expression pattern and function suggested that both 
 <italic>SWEET</italic> genes preserved an ancient and important function in specifically transporting sugar from seed coat to filial embryo and cotyledon to support seed development and storage reserve production. Interestingly, 
 <italic>GmSWEET15</italic> was identified by its specific expression in the seed endosperm, and silencing of it decreased 60–70% sucrose and resulted in severe seed abortion [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The orthologous pair, GmSWEET39 and AtSWEET15, were clustered with 
 <italic>GmSWEET15</italic> and 
 <italic>AtSWEET11</italic> and 
 <italic>12</italic> in the same subfamily [
 <xref rid="pgen.1009114.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This observation raises a possibility that plants have evolved an ancient 
 <italic>SWEET</italic> subfamily to specifically express in those interface tissues to facilitate transporting sugar from maternal tissues to filial cotyledon to support seed development and seed filling. It will be interesting to examine expression patterns and functions of the other 
 <italic>SWEET</italic> genes in the subfamily to validate the hypothesis.
</p>
