<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">Repellency was determined by a one-choice landing assay that uses the amount of mosquito landings to calculate the overall effectiveness of a candidate repellent when compared to a control. Twenty, adult female 
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes were aspirated into a rearing cage and starved for 1 day. Testing was performed between 10:00 am and 4:00 pm PST during 
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti’s</italic> active hours. A 37 °C heat pack was used to as the heat source to attract the mosquitoes in the upper region of the back panel of the rearing cage. The different treatments were extracted in acetone and 500 µL applied to the filter paper (6 × 9 cm) used to wrap the heat source. A control of acetone was applied to filter paper before and after each treatment to ensure reproducibility in mosquito behavior where percent repellencies for each treatment represented the percent reduction in mosquito landings from the prior control. The controls showed no significant repellency at all and thus data is not presented. Six repetitions we performed with twenty mosquitoes for each treatment and at each concentration along with an acetone control. The dose response curve was generated from identifying a concentration of the treatments that exhibited complete repellency and then working in reverse logarithmically with respect to the concentration of the treatment. Initial tests showed that few enough landings were observed at 1.0% generating a 95% reduction in mosquito landings and was defined as complete repellency. Time-lapse photography recorded one image every five seconds for five minutes where a custom macro named “Final Mosquito Counter” generated a Z stack of the images and counted the number of mosquitoes on the filter paper wrapped heat pack automatically through the open source image processing software ImageJ
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
