<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Olive oil is a mixture of fatty acids (saponifiable fraction), such as unsaturated fatty acids, saturated fatty acids (SFA) and other minor compounds (unsaponifiable fraction), such as polyphenols, hydrocarbons, phytosterols, and triterpenes (Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>). According to the International Olive Council and the United States Department of Agriculture, the nutritional significance, physiological characteristics, and the main types of components are generally equal amongst varying grades of olive oil. Based on the free acidity or degree of processing of the oil, extra virgin olive oil, virgin olive oil, refined olive oil, and pomace oil are the standard grades of olive oil that currently available on the market. The degree of unsaturation of fatty acids is one of the most important properties of olive oil that influences lipid oxidation. Olive oil is the most abundant in monounsaturated fatty acid (MUFA) content, which is the highest compared to the other edible oils such as corn, soybean and sunflower oils, and the SFA content of olive oil is lower than in these edible oils (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>). Also, olive oil is low in polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA). The major MUFA, SFA, and PUFA in olive oil are oleic acid, palmitic acid, and linoleic acid, respectively (Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). Olive oils rich in MUFAs are considered to be one of the best sources of fatty acids that effectively contribute to the low incidence of CVDs (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>). It is worth mentioning that linoleic acid, the essential fatty acid, is an important component for cell structure, development, and function. It cannot be synthesized by the human body and must be provided in the diet. The unique fatty acid ratio of olive oil governs its specific benefits for endothelial function. Moreover, olive oil contains a heterogeneous fraction of phenols of over 30 compounds with a distinct chemical structure. The major phenolic compounds are oleuropein, hydroxytyrosol, and tyrosol (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>), representing ~90% of the total phenol fraction in virgin olive oil (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>). Phenolic compounds are vital for the quality of olive oil because they provide remarkable stability against oxidation, despite the great variation in their antioxidant potency. In addition, among the variety of tocopherols present in olive oils, α-tocopherol is the main tocopherol (≥90% of tocopherols) (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>). Tocopherol (vitamin E) is the powerful inhibitor of lipid peroxidation of cellular membranes and lipoproteins. The presence of other minor compounds is also associated with the antioxidant properties of olive oils (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>).
</p>
