<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effects of olive oil interventions were investigated in numerous randomized controlled clinical trials. A recent systematic review and meta-analysis reported that a daily intake of olive oil ranging between 1 and 50 mg for a minimum of 4 weeks favorably affected inflammatory status and endothelial function (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>). Additionally, the results of another systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized intervention trials provided evidence suggesting that a Mediterranean dietary pattern reduced inflammation and improved endothelial function (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>). The quantities of olive oil within the range of doses tested in these clinical trials were recommended for the general population, as daily intake amounts. In 2004, the USA Food and Drug Administration suggested eating about two tablespoons (23 g) of olive oil daily. However, the standardization of real-life daily doses of olive oil poses some difficulties due to the influence of multiple interactions between endogenous and exogenous factors affecting its composition and bioactivity. The study showed that the biological properties of phenolic compounds depend on the extent of their absorption and metabolism 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>). Some bioavailability studies demonstrated that polyphenols were absorbed in a dose-dependent manner, and, additionally, high olive oil phenol intake increased their concentrations in blood plasma and excretion (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>). Different environmental conditions and agronomics are factors of great importance that affect olive oil chemical composition and quality. It was confirmed that the geographic area of cultivation is responsible for the differences observed in olive oil compound content (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>). Olive oils produced in various countries can differ from sample to sample since their fatty acid content depends on the following factors: the variety, production zone, the latitude, the climate, the stage of fruit maturity, and olive oil maturity (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>). The most studied olive oils, such as Greek, Italian, and Spanish were found to be high in oleic acid and low in linoleic and palmitic acid content, whereas, Tunisian olive oils are high in linoleic and palmitic acids and low in oleic acid content (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>). Moreover, the processing systems make a significant impact on the composition of olive oil, especially regarding its minor components. Large quantities of phenols can be lost in the refining process (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>). The influence of the extraction, storage and packaging conditions of virgin olive oils was also reported (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>). In addition, with regards to estimating olive oil bioactivity, the lack of robust and reliable methods for quantifying phenolic compounds plays an important role. Thus, it was established that the final composition of virgin olive oils is the result of a numerous variables, such as cultivar, the agriculture, time of harvesting, the refining process, the extraction, storage and packaging conditions, which take effect from the oil formation in the olive tree to the state of the oil at consumption. These factors have important effects on the compound concentrations modifying the oxidative stability of olive oil and, therefore, on its bioactivity. Taking into account all the factors influencing olive oil composition, based on the known chemical composition, further olive oil intervention studies are required that would help to establish direct dose/effect relationships.
</p>
