<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MLs are the potential source of minerals, viz. potassium (K), phosphorus (P), nitrogen (N), calcium (Ca), iron (Fe), sodium (Na), magnesium (Mg), boron (B), zinc (Zn) manganese (Mn), and vitamins, viz. A, B, E, and C. Ali et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] reported concentrations of various minerals in MLs as 589 (K), 480 (P), 343 (Fe), 98 (Mg), 368 (Ca), 28 (Na), 14 (Zn), 3 (Mn), and 2 (N) mg/100 g dry weight (DW). Another study also found Ca (4.41%), Mg (1.58%), K (0.55%), Na (0.23%), N (2.60%), and P (0.40%) in MLs [
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Various studies reported the concentration of minerals present in MLs as N (0.003–2.6%), P (0.007–0.48), Ca (0.003–4.41%), Mg (0.009–1.58), S (0.37–0.88), Zn (0.0024–0.014%), Na (0.003–0.23%), B (0.0016–0.0042%), copper (0.0021–0.0029%), Fe (0.0062–0.034%), Mn (0.0028–0.003%), and cadmium (0.015%) [
 <xref rid="B13-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. These minerals are important for human nutrition, as they play a major role in various activities such as maintenance of healthy bones and teeth, nerve functioning, muscles contraction and relaxation, immune system health, blood pressure regulation, blood clotting, energy metabolism, and part of many enzymes [
 <xref rid="B25-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The concentrations of vitamin A, B, E, and C reported as 121, 189, 10, and 30 mg/100 mL in ML [
 <xref rid="B20-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In another study, Princwill-Ogbonna et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] found vitamin composition in ML as vitamin A (22.60 mg), B1 (0.48 mg), B2 (0.21 mg), B3 (0.38 mg), and C (13.20 mg). The reported range of various vitamins in MLs was vitamin B1 (0.04–0.48 mg/100 g), B2 (0.06–0.21 mg/100 g), B3 (0.38–2.20 mg/100 g), C (13.20–53 mg/100 g), and A (22.60 mg/100 g) [
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. These vitamins have numerous health promoting activities in human body viz. development of epithelial tissue, maintaining skin health, visual sharpness, bone development, wounds healing, immune response, and providing strength to the connective tissues. Vitamins B1, B2, and B3 act as a cofactor for various enzymes involved in carbohydrate metabolism and oxidation–reduction reactions [
 <xref rid="B25-antioxidants-10-00299" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Mineral and vitamin composition of MLs reported by various researchers is presented in 
 <xref rid="antioxidants-10-00299-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.
</p>
