<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Serverogenin acetate is a bioactive compound known for its application in pharmacology, this bioactive compound isolated from methanol leaf extracts of 
 <italic>Trichilia connaroides</italic> demonstrated broad spectrum of biological properties such as antioxidant, anti-insect, antimicrobial, anticancer and antiulcerogenic activities
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. The trimethylsilyl derivative compound trimethyl-[4-(2,4,4-trimethylpentan-2-yl)phenoxy]silane identified from n-hexane seed extract of 
 <italic>G. kola</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, chloroform and ethanol leaf extracts of 
 <italic>Acacia karroo</italic> and 
 <italic>Ziziphus mauritiana</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> produced significant antibacterial activity against clinical bacteria and also recorded anti-inflammatory, anticancer, analgesic and diuretic activities. Ethyl 2-oxopropanoate is an androstane natured compound reported from methanol leaves extract of 
 <italic>A. nilotica</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup> and 
 <italic>Kamettia caryophyllata</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup> showed potent bioactivities of acidifier, acidulant and inhibits production of uric acid
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. (1,3-
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>2</sub>)propanedioic acid has been isolated from methanol extract of 
 <italic>Alysicarpus monilifer</italic> whole plant
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup> however its biological activity is yet to confirm. The flavonoid compound 2,4-dimethyl-1,3-dioxane known to possess anti-inflammatory, analgesic, antibacterial and antifungal activities was isolated from Arjunarishta, a modified ayurvedic medicine
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. 5-amino-6-nitroso-1
 <italic>H</italic>-pyrimidine-2,4-dione from methanol leaf extract of 
 <italic>Stachytarpheta jamaicensis</italic> capable of producing high multi therapeutic properties such as antioxidant, anti-arthritic, anti-inflammatory and bactericidal potentials
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. (2
 <italic>S</italic>,4
 <italic>S</italic>,5
 <italic>R</italic>,6
 <italic>R</italic>)-3,8,9-trioxatricyclo[4.2.1.0
 <sup>2,4</sup>]nonan-5-ol is a sugar moiety natured compound identified from ethanol extract of aerial parts of 
 <italic>Crotalaria longipes</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup> and ethanol extracts of whole plant of 
 <italic>Sarcostemma secamone</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup> reported to be used as a preservative. In this study, the leaf and rhizome extracts of 
 <italic>A. nilgiricum</italic> showed remarkable in vitro antibacterial and antifungal activities by suppressing their colony and growth rate. In support of this study, earlier our group reported the potential antimicrobial activities of rhizome extracts of 
 <italic>A. niligiricum</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. In addition we have also noticed remarkable antioxidant and antidiabetic activities from the leaf and rhizome extracts of 
 <italic>A. nilgiricum</italic> which is the first kind of report from this study. Previously, the antibacterial and antioxidant activities using the essential oil extracted from 
 <italic>A. subulatum</italic> was documented Shrestha
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, Sharma et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> reported the antioxidant activity by seed extract of 
 <italic>A. subulatum</italic>.
</p>
