<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CR is a common TCM being used in treating varieties of pain. Except the usage in relieving pain, the herbal extracts of CR, or its alkaloids, are commonly used in treatment of myocardial ischemia, rheumatism, and dysmenorrhea, and most of these medical problems are involving different types of inflammation [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Alkaloids are commonly found in herbal medicines that are used for anti-inflammation. For example, berberine, originated from 
 <italic>Coptis chinensis</italic> Franch. and 
 <italic>Phellodendron chinense</italic> Schneid., inhibited expression of proinflammatory cytokine by modulating Sirt1/NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B signaling [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Palmatine and columbamine, originated from 
 <italic>Tinospora sagittata</italic> (Oliv.) Gagnep, inhibited production of nitric oxide and activation of NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Glaucine, isolated from 
 <italic>Glaucium flavum</italic> Crantz. (Papaveraceae), reduced proinflammatory cytokine, and increased anti-inflammatory cytokine (IL-10) by Toll-like receptor-mediated signaling [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Stylopine, isolated from 
 <italic>Corydalis impatiens</italic>, reduced the production of proinflammatory cytokine by inhibiting NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B and MAPK signaling [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In line with other alkaloid-containing herbs, CR has been shown to reduce the acetic acid-induced mice writhing and relieve ear swelling and neuropathic pain [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], while rotundinum, the quality chemical marker of CR (described in &lt;&lt;Pharmacopoeia of P.R. China&gt;&gt;, 2020), is able to inhibit the secretion of proinflammatory cytokine by blocking MAPK phosphorylation [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Dehydrocorydaline, corydaline, corydalmine, and isocorypalmine are the representing alkaloids in analgesic effect of CR usage [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]; however, due to different mechanism of pain and inflammation, the signaling of anti-inflammatory property of these alkaloids has not been fully revealed.
</p>
