<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>AChE is an enzyme to hydrolyze acetylcholine in cholinergic synapses, and 
 <italic>α</italic>7nAChR is an important inflammation-related receptor in many kinds of immune cells [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. These two cholinergic molecules have been known to play important role in “cholinergic anti-inflammatory pathway (CAP)” by regulating cholinergic anti-inflammatory response [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], which includes the release of proinflammatory cytokines (TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>, IL-6, and IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>) in macrophage by controlling the level of acetylcholine and activation of 
 <italic>α</italic>7nAChR. In addition, recent studies have shown that the inflammation, induced by LPS, could upregulate expression of AChE in macrophage [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In parallel, AChE-targeting microRNA-132 could attenuate inflammation by reducing AChE level in immune cells [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In addition, the regulation of AChE expression could be triggered by cyclic AMP responding element acting on the AChE gene promoter, and this regulation could be induced by phytochemicals [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Many alkaloids, for example, huperzine A from 
 <italic>Huperzia serrata</italic>, fangchinoline from 
 <italic>Stephania tetrandra,</italic> and coptisine from 
 <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, showed good inhibitory activity on AChE [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Here, most of the CR alkaloids showed AChE inhibitory activity at different magnitudes [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Moreover, there is a positive correlation between AChE and inflammation inhibition, that is, quaternary ammonium alkaloids (e.g., berberine, palmatine, dehydrocorydaline, and columbamine), having strong AChE inhibitory and anti-inflammatory effects compared to their hydrogenated tertiary amine alkaloids (e.g., canadine, rotundinum, corydaline, and isocorypalmine). Thus, the anti-inflammatory function of CR alkaloids could be, at least partly, contributed by its AChE inhibition, which needs to be studied further.
</p>
