<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We implemented multiple model algorithms for each species since statistical model choice is the greatest source of quantifiable uncertainty in species distribution modeling [
 <xref rid="pone.0229253.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0229253.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], allowing us to evaluate and reduce the potential biasing effects of algorithm choice on our results. These included Maxent (v 3.4.1), Boosted Regression Trees (BRT), Random Forest (RF), Generalized Linear Model (GLM) and Multivariate Adaptive Regression Splines (MARS). We used SAHM [
 <xref rid="pone.0229253.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] within the VisTrails software framework [
 <xref rid="pone.0229253.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] to fit models to each combination of algorithm and background method (‘SAHM Model Fitting’, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0229253.g001">Fig 1</xref>). SAHM provides an established, streamlined and replicable approach to preprocess model inputs, run multiple algorithms and compare results. Three of the five models have an internal variable selection process; BRT used bag fraction = 0.5; GLM used a bidirectional stepwise procedure using Akaike’s Information Criterion (AIC), considering all interactions and squared terms; and MARS used Mars Degree (Friedman’s μ) = 1 and GVL penalty = 2.0. Both Maxent and RF retain all variables provided to them. We used a default set of parameters for each model algorithm, and subsequently evaluated model-specific parameter settings for any resulting model where the training and test area under the receiver operating characteristics (AUC-ROC) values based on 10 fold cross-validation had a difference &gt; 0.05, which we defined 
 <italic>a priori</italic> as a threshold to indicate overfitting along with visual inspection of response curve complexity (e.g.,[
 <xref rid="pone.0229253.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], ‘Model Overfitting Assessment’, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0229253.g001">Fig 1</xref>). We developed 10 models for each species (five modeling algorithms each with two background sampling approaches) to estimate suitable habitat. Any model that was either still overfit or had poor assessment metrics (i.e., test AUC-ROC &lt; 0.7 [
 <xref rid="pone.0229253.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]) was dropped from further analysis. We produced a multivariate environmental similarity surface (MESS) for each model [
 <xref rid="pone.0229253.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and overlaid this surface on maps to highlight areas of extrapolation beyond the environments captured by the training data. All models were developed using the training data described above and applied to predictors for the contiguous U.S. at a spatial resolution of 90 m.
</p>
