<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, we have particularly focussed on the presence of volatile compounds in the peel of the 10 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> species most commonly analyzed, for which a significant amount of information is available in the scientific literature. Depending on each particular study, compounds have been identified with a different degree of confidence. We have systematically classified the reliability of identification for each compound in each of the revised articles in a scale from A+++ (highest confidence) to H (lowest confidence), as detailed in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2" class="xref">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. We considered it a key feature in this review, as our own experience in 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> juice volatile profiling is that misidentification of volatile compounds is far to be rare in the scientific literature, particularly for those tentatively identified based on retention indices (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">González-Mas et al., 2011</xref>). Therefore, we have used a conservative approach all along this review for the description of the volatile profiles, as well as for the generation of figures and statistical analyses. We have selected only the 763 volatile and semi-volatile compounds which have been identified by, at least, both retention index and mass spectrum (reliability classified from A+++ to B in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2" class="xref">Supplementary Table S2</xref>), while discarding those identified with a lower degree of confidence. We used this approach to perform a qualitative description (described/never described) of the volatile profiles of these species, summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">2</xref>, and to elaborate the HCA shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>. Applying this criterion, we observed that slightly more than half of these 763 reliably identified compounds are terpenoids, whilst the other half corresponds to a wide range of non-terpenoid compounds. Oxygenated monoterpenes is the most numerous group, comprising almost a quarter of all the compounds identified. Forty-nine of these volatile compounds have been described in all 10 species (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6" class="xref">Supplementary Figures S1B–H</xref>), almost 90% of which are terpenoid. Therefore, in some way they could be considered as those defining the characteristic 
 <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> volatile profile. Interestingly, most of these shared compounds are monoterpenoids (15 monoterpene hydrocarbons; 17 oxygenated monoterpenes) or sesquiterpenoids (9 sesquiterpene hydrocarbons; 2 oxygenated sesquiterpenes). The only non-terpenoid common volatiles are 1-octanol and the five C
 <sub class="sub">8</sub> to C
 <sub class="sub">12</sub> linear aliphatic aldehydes from octanal to dodecanal. On the other hand, 410 compounds of ample chemical diversity have been described up to date in only one of these species, most often in only one study (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2" class="xref">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). It cannot be discarded that in some cases this might be due to misidentification, particularly when compound identification was not confirmed with a pure standard. Nevertheless, when unambiguously identified, they could be considered as biomarkers for each particular species.
</p>
