<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As previously described, several different -and somewhat complementary- analytical techniques have been used for the identification of the VOCs in the EOs along the scientific literature. In the case of these 10 species we considered that the number of studies already published is sufficient to rely on the total list of compounds identified as quite representative of their actual volatile profile. Therefore, we addressed the classification of these species by HCA based on their respective volatile profiles as described in the literature. This approach allowed us to classify these species into three clusters based on their volatile profile as described in the literature (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rambla et al., 2015</xref>). The first cluster is comprised by 
 <italic class="italic">C. reticulata, C. grandis, C. sinensis, C. paradisi</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic>, and is mainly characterized by the presence of a larger abundance of aliphatic and olefinic non-terpene compounds, principally esters and aldehydes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). The second cluster is comprised by 
 <italic class="italic">C. junos</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. medica</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantifolia</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">C. bergamia</italic>, and is characterized by the prevalence of mono- and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons. Finally, 
 <italic class="italic">C. limon</italic> shows a particular volatile profile with some sulfur monoterpenoids and non-terpenoid esters and aldehydes as part of its main differential peculiarities (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2" class="xref">Supplementary Table S2</xref>).
</p>
