<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we compared the selective antibacterial (diarrheagenic/probiotic strains) and cytotoxic (cancer/normal intestinal cells) activities of phytochemicals (alkaloids and phenolics) and their synthetic analogs with those of antibiotics in vitro. For each test compound, values of minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs), half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>), and 80% inhibitory concentration of proliferation (IC
 <sub>80</sub>) were assessed. The means of these values (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mover accent="true">
     <mi>x</mi>
     <mo>¯</mo>
    </mover>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>
 <italic>-</italic>MIC, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm2">
   <mrow>
    <mover accent="true">
     <mi>x</mi>
     <mo>¯</mo>
    </mover>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>
 <italic>-</italic>IC
 <sub>50</sub>, and 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm3">
   <mrow>
    <mover accent="true">
     <mi>x</mi>
     <mo>¯</mo>
    </mover>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>-IC
 <sub>80</sub>), each defined for a particular type of strain/cell line, were used for calculation of selectivity index (SI) between activities against normal intestinal cells and diarrheagenic strains (SIa), probiotic and diarrheagenic strains (SIb), and normal and cancer intestinal cells (SIc). The aim was to obtain some of the missing data on particular in vitro activities of the test compound, to assist in identifying phytochemicals with scaffolds that possess a potent combination of bioactivities. They could subsequently be utilized in future chemotaxonomic investigation of antidiarrheal medicinal plants with their bioactive components considered for new chemotherapeutic agents against diarrheal infections and associated intestinal cancer diseases. Our results show that 8-hydroxyquinoline alkaloids and zinc pyrithione possess in vitro selective antibacterial properties against diarrheagenic bacteria comparable to ciprofloxacin and tetracycline, with additional in vitro antiproliferative activity against cancer intestinal cell lines. However, in contrary to antibiotics, these compounds generally possess increased cytotoxicity to normal intestinal cells.
</p>
