<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides 
 <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> from Greece (var. 
 <italic>chia</italic>), there are other reports on 
 <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> species grown in other parts of the world. In Tunisian 
 <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic>, the most prevalent constituents identified at the whole-plant level were 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene, 
 <italic>β</italic>-myrcene, 
 <italic>α</italic>-limonene, and germacrene-D. Differences were also observed in the essential oil and phenol contents extracted from the plant, which were reported to be season- and gender-related, as well as plant-part-related within the same gender. Remarkable antioxidant activity monitored by DPPH and ferric-reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assays was demonstrated for the acetonic extracts from both plant genders in the Tunisian species [
 <xref rid="B40-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In another study, Bouyahya et al. reported that the volatile compounds of 
 <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> L. (Morocco) essential oil extracted from the fruits of the plant had better free radical scavenging and ferric-reducing properties compared to the essential oil extracted from the plant leaves [
 <xref rid="B41-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The GC-MS analysis identified 22 compounds, with the main components being myrcene (33.5%) and 
 <italic>α</italic>-pinene (19.2%) in the essential oil extracted from the plant leaves, while limonene (18.3%) and α-pinene (20.5%) were the main components in the essential oil extracted from the plant fruits. Although there are differences in the chemical composition between the mastic preparations used across the studies, a recent study characterized and compared the volatile oils of the mastic gum and mastic oil and revealed that α-pinene and myrcene are the two major components found in the two mastic preparations [
 <xref rid="B42-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. From the above information, it becomes apparent that the antioxidant activity reported for 
 <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> is variable to many factors, such as the chemical composition of the extracts prepared, the kind of the plant parts used, the plant gender, as well as the species variance, collecting season, and geographic origin. 
</p>
