<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cytoprotective potential of mastic oil, myrcene, and α-pinene was studied against the oxidative agents UVB and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, which induce cellular oxidative stress via different mechanisms. UVB is a potent oxidative agent and exposure to UVB radiation leads to the generation of ROS from the excitation of O
 <sub>2</sub> to form singlet oxygen, along with the transfer of 1, 2, or 3 electrons to oxygen to form superoxide, hydrogen peroxide, and hydroxy radical, respectively [
 <xref rid="B50-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], resulting in oxidative damage to membrane lipids, nucleic acids, and proteins, causing cellular destruction [
 <xref rid="B51-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The oxidative stress achieved by H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> treatment utilizes H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> as a precursor to hydroxyl radical, which is less reactive but more readily diffusible, and thus more likely to be involved in the formation of oxidized bases [
 <xref rid="B52-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Our results showed that pre-treatment with mastic oil or post-treatment with myrcene prior to or following UVB irradiation, respectively, resulted in increased viability of HaCaT cells. On the contrary, α-pinene could not protect HaCaT cells from the cytotoxic effects of UVB radiation. Although the differential cyto-protection observed is quite interesting, it cannot be explained in detail yet, but may provide the basis for further testing of mastic oil and myrcene in applications such as skin protective agents against UV radiation. The specificity of the chemical composition of the oil (the potential synergistic effect of the mixture), differences in the UV-absorbing spectra (acting as UV blockers), or possible differential effects on the efficiency of DNA repair mechanisms caused by the compounds may explain the differences observed, and further research is required towards this direction. On the other hand, all tested compounds managed to efficiently protect HaCaT cells from the cytotoxic effects of H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, which may be explained by the different mechanisms of action that the two oxidants exert. To the extent of our knowledge, this is the first time that the cytoprotective properties of mastic oil under oxidative stress conditions are being reported. We hypothesize that mastic oil and its constituents could exert their cytoprotective effect through inducing NRF2 and other genes associated with antioxidant response, thus enhancing the cellular defense under oxidative conditions. Similarly, the monoterpenes α-pinene and 1,8-cineol were reported to exert neuroprotective potential against H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative stress in PC12 cells by eliciting an antioxidant response through induction of the nuclear NRF2 factor and upregulation of the antioxidant enzymes CAT, SOD, GPX1, GSR, and HMOX1 [
 <xref rid="B53-antioxidants-10-00127" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. 
</p>
