<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bacterial pathogens are major causes of diarrhoea, and several studies have already screened Australian medicinal plants for antidiarrheal properties. Palombo and Semple investigated the growth inhibitory properties of extracts prepared from 39 Australian plant species against a panel of bacterial pathogens, including several diarrhoea-causing species [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. That study reported that several species had noteworthy inhibitory activity and highlighted 
 <italic>Eremophila duttonii</italic> F. Muell. as having the greatest activity of the species tested. However, that study screened the plant extracts at a single dose (concentration not specified), and MIC values were not reported, making a comparison with other studies impossible. Furthermore, the Palombo and Semple study tested ethanolic extracts instead of the decoctions that were used by the First Australians. Therefore, whilst that study was interesting and highlighted several plants worthy of further evaluation, it did not validate the traditional use of those species to treat diarrhoea. Another study screened extracts prepared from 109 Australian plants for the ability to inhibit the growth of 
 <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>, which is one of the most common causes of acute enteritis in humans, and reported potent activity for many species [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. That study reported MIC values below 1000 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL for all species against two 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic> strains and similar potency against several other diarrhoea-causing bacteria. Several 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> spp. were amongst the most potent species tested in that study. Several recent studies have also reported good inhibitory activity for several high-antioxidant Australian plant species against multiple bacterial species, including diarrhoea-causing pathogens [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A recent study also tested 
 <italic>Terminalia ferdinandiana</italic> Excell. extracts against multiresistant ESBL 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) and reported MIC values as low as 200 
 <italic>μ</italic>g/mL [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Several studies have also reported good inhibitory activity for Australian plants against the gastrointestinal protozoal parasite 
 <italic>Giardia duodenalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Furthermore, a recent study from our group reported notable antimicrobial activity for one of the species examined herein (
 <italic>B. obovata</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, all those studies examined extracts prepared under laboratory conditions using organic solvents and did not consider the traditional preparation methods.
</p>
