<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The improvement of life expectancy over the 21st century has led to demographic aging with a steady increase of age-related neurodegenerative pathologies [
 <xref rid="B1-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is the most widespread form of dementia estimated to affect some 75 million people by 2030 and to double by 2050 [
 <xref rid="B2-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Chronic pain is often experienced by the elderly, ranging from 50% of community-dwelling older adults to 80% of care facilities residents, of whom 25% do not receive pain-relief [
 <xref rid="B4-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The problem of pain can be even more burdensome when it coincides with severe dementia. In the real-world community setting, the access of these patients to pain treatment, particularly neuropathic, is very limited [
 <xref rid="B7-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and associated with the increased use of antipsychotics and antidepressants [
 <xref rid="B9-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In fact, the inadequate pain treatment received by cognitively impaired patients is often due to their reduced or absent communication skills that prevent self-reporting: unrelieved pain is involved in the development of agitation [
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], one of the most challenging behavioral and psychological symptoms of dementia (BPSD), also known as neuropsychiatric symptoms (NPS). This leads to the off-label use of antidepressants and atypical antipsychotics that double the risk of death for cardiocerebrovascular accidents in these patients [
 <xref rid="B11-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Additionally, in the frame of the current novel severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) pandemic, it is the elderly who paid the highest price [
 <xref rid="B12-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and COVID-19 (COrona VIrus Disease 2019) and dementia, the pandemic of global aging [
 <xref rid="B13-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], are overlapping. Pain assessment in severe dementia can be performed only through specific observational pain scales, but the risk of contagion often impedes these non-urgent practices [
 <xref rid="B14-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This paints a picture of the worrying implications concerning the management of chronic pain in severe dementia and of its global social burden. A fundamental aspect to consider is that agitation can be remarkably minimized through adequate pain treatment and the regular review of therapy [
 <xref rid="B15-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The epidemiology of pain in dementia highlights that its severity correlates significantly with dementia severity, NPS, and antipsychotic prescriptions [
 <xref rid="B17-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Incidentally, pain and BPSD share some pathways in aged animals [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Thus, effective pain treatment is a priority and can avoid the unnecessary and harmful use of atypical antipsychotics, endowed with serious side effects, and often used off-label and without evidence of the benefits such as quetiapine. Only risperidone is licensed in Europe for demented patients suffering from resistant aggression and it can be used for a short period of up to six weeks, a maximum of twelve [
 <xref rid="B19-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Aromatherapy with melissa and lavender has proven efficacy in the management of agitation in dementia [
 <xref rid="B20-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], but clinical trials in aromatherapy are too few and small and most of them lack methodological consistency [
 <xref rid="B22-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. One of the points of weaknesses in the quality of the outcome assessment is due to the strong smell of essential oils that do not allow adequate allocation masking and double-blinding. Moreover, due to the tight link existing between pain and agitation, the essential oil to be used needs to be endowed with analgesic activity. Most preclinical studies on essential oils do not justify their clinical use, with the exception of the essential oil of bergamot (BEO, Citrus bergamia Risso et Poiteau) that has provided strong preclinical evidence of its antinociceptive and anti-allodynic effect [
 <xref rid="B23-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. BEO contains furocoumarins, e.g., bergapten, that can induce phototoxicity [
 <xref rid="B24-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]; interestingly, BEO deprived of bergapten (BEO-bergapten free, BEO-BF) [
 <xref rid="B25-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] keeps all its pharmacological properties and it is devoid of toxicity (European Medicine Agency (EMA), 13 September 2011 EMA/HMPC/56155/2011 Committee on Herbal Medicinal Products (HMPC)). Another issue with aromatherapy concerns the delivery system that does not allow the exposure of individuals to the known amount of phytocomplex, which hampers dose-effect relations in clinical settings for biological, therapeutic, or side effects and reproducibility. In addition, some volatile components of essential oils are relatively unstable to heat and light. Therefore, it is necessary to provide a delivery system of BEO able to overcome all these limitations. Here we present a nanotechnology BEO-BF delivery system, i.e., NanoBEO, obtained with the use of solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN) [
 <xref rid="B26-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], in the pharmaceutical form of a cream for transdermic application, which is able to: deliver known amounts of the phytocomplex; to protect its ingredients from chemical instability; encapsulate the smell providing an odourless formulation. According to the present invention currently under patent consideration, it is now possible to effectively use aromatherapy with BEO-BF in complementary medicine for the therapy of acute and chronic pain and prevention or treatment of BPSD and any other stress, including itch-related behaviors and mood disorders in normal or demented people. The clinical trial NCT04321889 has been registered for the study of the effectiveness of NanoBEO on agitation and pain in severely demented patients. Therefore, the aim of this study was to engineer a nanotechnology delivery system based on solid lipid nanoparticles loaded with bergamot essential oil (BEO) and devised in the pharmaceutical form as an odorless cream (NanoBEO) to confirm its analgesic efficacy for further development and application to control agitation in dementia.
</p>
