<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the last decade, special attention has been paid to the search for natural compounds for preserving foods from spoilage microorganisms and oxidation [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This has become especially urgent due to the progressive withdrawal of commonly used synthetic antioxidants such as, e.g.: butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT), butylated hydroxyanisole (BAH) or propyl galate (PG) [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and as a result of European Union (EU) law, prohibiting the application of antibiotic growth promoters in food production. The common use of in-feed antibiotics in large-scale livestock rearing has contributed to the increase in the resistance among human pathogens. Thus, since 2006 in the EU such practices are no longer acceptable in animal production [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This situation has caused the need to screen natural substances able to control growth of pathogens and prevent undesirable oxidation reactions in food products. Among foodborne bacteria, several species have gained a particular attention due to their high pathogenicity. Microorganisms such as 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> can infect and intoxicate humans, leading to serious diseases manifested as abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting and diarrhea [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Among these, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> seems to be the most dangerous since it causes high mortality, especially in the case of pregnant women, newborns, and the elderly [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Thus, the search for a new, natural substances being able to control foodborne pathogens is focused on the abovementioned group.
</p>
