<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Up to now, several plant-derived secondary metabolites, mainly phenolics, have been described to reveal activities against these pathogens. Among them the most interesting are phenolic acids (e.g., caffeic acids derivatives), flavonoids (e.g., (−)-epicatechin, quercetin), and volatiles, including essential oils and their components, e.g.: thymol, carvacrol or eugenol [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The antibacterial activity of phenolic acids is well-documented, especially when regards to rosmarinic acid. This compound shows potential in the control of 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli, S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Shigella</italic> spp., and 
 <italic>Enterobacter</italic> [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. It has an inhibitory impact on the proteins of the microbial surface recognizing adhesive matrix molecules, what leads to damage to the bacteria cell wall [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Moreover, the presence of a carboxylic acidic group enables ionisability and/or the formation of salts with mineral cations, what was also observed in the case of antibiotics such as, e.g. daptomycin [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The activity of other phenolic acids, including chlorogenic acid, is based on a similar mechanism of action [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In the group of phenolic compounds, flavonoids exhibit a strong antibacterial activity expressed in an inhibition of nucleic acid synthesis, inhibition of cytoplasmic membrane function and by disorders in the energy metabolism of bacterial cells [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Volatiles show well-known antibacterial potential, especially essential oils and their components, e.g. carvacrol and thymol. Due to their hydrophobic nature, they are able to cross the lipid bilayer of cell membrane causing a loss of its integrity and leakage of cellular material. Unlike many antibiotics, these compounds gain access to the periplasm of Gram-negative bacteria such as 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> through the porin proteins of the outer membrane, and finally damage it irreversibly [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. It is worth noting that the precursor of carvacrol, 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, is not an effective antibacterial agent when used alone. However, when combined with carvacrol, synergism has been observed. When 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene is incorporated into the lipid bilayer, the transport of carvacrol is visibly facilitated [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00988" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Thus, the works on antibacterial and antioxidant activity should focus not only on single compounds but especially on complex extracts or their fractions. 
</p>
