<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The development of preservation methods in order to delay such degenerative phenomena would be desirable. Several studies have investigated the preservation technologies to maintain fish flesh elasticity and firmness. High-pressure treatment has been reported to be a useful way to improve fish flash quality by decreasing the initial activity of calpain in sea bass (
 <italic class="italic">Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B14-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Cold storage and freezing are classic methods for fish preservation, but they do not fully inhibit the spoilage of the quality inasmuch that they cannot prevent oxidative degradation. Therefore, as a supplement to ice or refrigeration to inhibit the normal spoilage flora, vacuum packaging (VP) and modified atmosphere packaging (MAP) are used. However, such technologies increase the costs of packaging and require specially trained workers [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Edible films and coatings are appealing opportunities to increase the shelf-life of perishable food products [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Both films and coatings can be made of polysaccharides, proteins, and lipids alone, or in combination, and their relevance is due to the fact that they can be safely consumed [
 <xref rid="B20-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Furthermore, ingredient additives, such as antioxidant substances and antimicrobial agents can be included in the formulations for edible films and coatings in order to increase the shelf-life of foods. In their review, Socaciu et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] reported ~10 different biopolymers, proteins, and polysaccharides, used alone or in combination to develop coatings and films to extend the fish fillet shelf life up to 13 days. The presence of active ingredients, mainly essential oils and polyphenols, improved the coating and film performances, especially regarding the antimicrobial properties, in both marine and freshwater fish.
</p>
