<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The application of lignocellulosic fibers in bioplastics has been investigated in several studies which mainly focus on cellulose fiber. Several reviews published recently can provide the readers with more detailed information [
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">136</xref>]. Unmodified fibers can serve as a cheaper material compared to cellulose modification, therefore, the application of raw lignocellulosic fibers in bioplastics has attained more attentions in recent years [
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Although the studies on the application of lignocellulosic fibers in bioplastics have been conducted for decades, the interfacial compatibility between matrix and fiber is still not addressed [
 <xref rid="B38-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>]. First, either inter- or intra-molecular hydrogen bonding has been developed in most functional groups of LCC. These strong interactions in LCC render lignocellulosic fibers recalcitrance for interaction with other biopolymers. As a consequence, additional hydrogen bonding between these biopolymers is difficult to create via blending, which results in low interfacial miscibility, and further deteriorates the mechanical properties of the biocomposites. Second, due to the intense interaction among lignocellulosic fiber molecules, agglomeration is possible to exist in the biocomposite, resulting in low performance of bioplastics. As free movement of fibers will be severely restricted by the high viscosity of biopolymers, the case in the melt process is much more serious. Therefore, concentrated areas would be generated due to the agglomerated fibers in the biocomposites and they lower the performance of bioplastics further [
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Third, due to the presence of hydroxyl and other chemical groups of LCC, lignocellulosic fibers exhibit high polar and hydrophilic characters. In addition, the amorphous components in the lignocellulosic fibers such as pectin, lignin, hemicellulose, and other waxy materials also allow absorption of moisture [
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Swelling and holes in the LCC are likely to develop due to the water uptake of LCC, which induces limited dimensional stability and poor mechanical properties of the bioplastics [
 <xref rid="B24-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>].
</p>
