<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, efforts have been undertaken to fully integrate spectral and LiDAR instrument systems and analytical techniques in order to improve the analysis of vegetation functional and structural properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b72-sensors-09-04869">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b73-sensors-09-04869">73</xref>]. When instruments are flown on separate aircraft, post-processing steps are required to co-align the data for fusion-based analysis; however, post-flight integration usually results in data misalignments of up to 4 pixels between sensors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74-sensors-09-04869">74</xref>]. While this may be acceptable for some applications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75-sensors-09-04869">75</xref>], a fully-integrated set of measurements, with co-alignment errors ≪ 1 pixel allows for the development and use of fully-automated approaches to measuring canopy chemistry, structure and invasive species occurrence (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3-sensors-09-04869">Figure 3</xref>). To our knowledge, one of the only systems in the world with this capability is the Carnegie Airborne Observatory (CAO) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74-sensors-09-04869">74</xref>]. Precisely aligned hyperspectral and LiDAR data afford an opportunity to automatically select and compare vegetation canopy properties: LiDAR can provide a high-resolution canopy surface model, with which spectral data can be selected based on precise calculations of solar position, canopy shape, and viewing geometry [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b76-sensors-09-04869">76</xref>]. Using this “laser-guided spectroscopy” CAO approach, Asner 
 <italic>et al.</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62-sensors-09-04869">62</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b77-sensors-09-04869">77</xref>] were able to map individual crowns of five highly invasive tree species throughout Hawaii Island (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4-sensors-09-04869">Figure 4</xref>). Detection errors for most species were only a few percent over more than 221,000 ha of dense rain forest. Once detected with the spectral data, the LiDAR was again used to measure the effects of invasion on the 3-D structure of the canopy. It was shown that different invasive tree species alter the fundamental structure of the forests they invade, but in different ways, either from the ground-up or from the top-down [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62-sensors-09-04869">62</xref>].
</p>
