<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Pest control could be achieved through the integration of multiple tactics; among the possible alternatives to synthetic pesticides, the use of chemical stimuli to manipulate insect behavior is considered a suitable biotechnical control tool in the management of several insect pests
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. Some insecticides, beside lethal toxicity, affect insect behavior preventing settling on the host plant, probing and feeding, oviposition, and virus transmission
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, behavioral effects caused by an insecticide that is apparently non-toxic for the insect in conventional tests, could in fact permit to contain the insect populations and associated yield losses. As remarked in the introduction to this paper, massive untimed and mainly unjustified use of synthetic pesticides following the introduction of OSW in Italy was ineffective, beside possibly causing the emergence of resistant whitefly populations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. The current relentless spread of OSW over the Mediterranean together with the threat posed to 
 <italic>Citrus</italic> spp., grapevine and ornamental plants, call for the urgent search of alternatives to conventional control strategies. In this perspective, botanicals and in general organic-certified insecticides could represent a sustainable tool. However, recent works highlighting previously overlooked biopesticides’ lethal and sub-lethal effects on natural enemies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>, warn for a reconsideration of the general concept of their safety for non-target organisms, and for more accurate risk-assessments
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Organic-certified pesticides could be even integrated with synthetic insecticides in alternate treatment regimes, preventing or at least delaying the development of resistance, and reducing the environmental impact of pest control practices
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. However, as stated by Copping and Menn
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> referring to botanicals, there is a general low level of acceptance of organic-certified pesticides given their limited shelf-life, and inconsistent results. Nonetheless, considering inconsistent results, most of the trials performed with organic pesticides (and pesticides in general) focus on lethal toxicity rather than considering also the sub-lethal effects, i.e. physiological and behavioral effects caused by the insecticide on the pest survived to exposure
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, in contrast with previous technical reports
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>, the pesticides tested in our experiments caused no significant mortality in any of the OSW instars, although interesting sub-lethal effects that could be exploited in an environmentally sustainable IPM strategy were observed. In this study, to have a complete picture of the effects of the organic insecticides under screening on OSW, we used a complex approach integrating classical field mortality trial, laboratory free-choice and oviposition experiments, and EPG. Several authors have used EPG to assess the effect of insecticides on insect probing and feeding behavior
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. In our case, EPG furnished important indications on OSW reaction to the different compounds. However, lack of phloem activities in our recordings might suggest OSW females were strongly affected by the tethering technique, different from the one indicated by Chesnais and Mauck
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup> as the most suitable for the whiteflies. An alternative and intriguing explanation to the observed phenomenon, that deserves to be investigated in the future using different host plants and comparing nymphs and adults, is that adults’ feeding activity at least on sweet orange is limited, thus this plant is used by adults as mating and oviposition site rather than food source. Still, we consider EPG data collected in this experiment as reliable and useful for our evaluation, since our purpose was limited to a treatments comparison.
</p>
