<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">The main advantage of the organic compounds we tested, at least theoretically (as discussed above), is their relative safety for non-target-organisms compared to conventional pesticides, thus the possibility of using them in combination with biological control, the latter proven to be effective against OSW
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup>. Regarding biological control, following OSW first detection in Europe, efforts were put in place to find suitable candidates for the whitefly biological control
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. In parallel to our experiments, during August 2019, 80 OSW-infested leaves of 
 <italic>Citrus</italic> spp. (lemon, orange, tangerine) surrounding the CIHEAM Bari experimental field were randomly collected, isolated singly in Petri dishes covered with aphid net and sealed with rubber band, and stored in a growth chamber (24 ± 2 °C, 60%RH, 14:8 L:D) for two weeks. Two parasitoid wasp species emerged from the samples, 
 <italic>Eretmocerus mundus</italic> Mercet (Hymenoptera: Aphelinidae) (a total 62 individuals emerged from 13 leaves) and 
 <italic>Telenomus</italic> sp. (Hymenoptera: Scelionidae) (a total of 24 individuals emerged from 19 leaves), together with OSW adults. It was not possible to associate the parasitoids with specific whitefly instars. 
 <italic>Eretmocerus</italic> spp. were reported as parasitoids of 
 <italic>A. spiniferus</italic> in the South-East Asia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, 
 <italic>E. mundus</italic> is an effective parasitoid of the whitefly 
 <italic>Bemisia tabaci</italic>, with a preference for second and third instar nymphs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. The association of 
 <italic>Telenomus</italic> with Aleyrodidae has never been recorded, and the present work cannot confirm any possible association. 
 <italic>Telenomus</italic> host range include a large amount of genera of different Orders; another genera of the superfamily Platygastroidea, 
 <italic>Amitus</italic> Haldeman (Hymenoptera: Platygastridae), was recorded as parasitoids of 
 <italic>Aleurocanthus</italic> spp.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>, Further studies on these two parasitoids exploring their possible relationship with OSW are urgently needed.
</p>
