<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0255">This paper highlights the importance of phytotherapeutic agents as candidates in search for drugs against COVID-19. Based on the novelty of the virus and the disease caused, safety concerns still loom over the use of phytomedicine. Therefore, safety aspects must be taken into consideration. Insufficient data exist for most of the plants to guarantee their quality, efficacy and safety. Untested use of pure compounds is not recommended, and these compounds should first go through the proper efficacy and safety testing. The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for example provides guidelines for safe use of natural products as drugs (
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">FDA 2006</xref>). Similarly, the European Medicines Agency (EMA), asserts that herbal medicinal products should only be used traditionally if they have been used for at least 30 years, including at least 15 years within the European Union and are not administered by injection. Furthermore, marketing and well established use should only be authorized after scientific literature is available that confirms that the pure constituent/active ingredient of the herbal product has a recognized efficacy (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Calapai 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">EMA 2001</xref>). However, there is a wrong perception, that herbal drugs are fully safe and free from any side effects. There are hundreds of toxic constituents in different plants. Compared to synthetic compounds, natural products and plant-based compounds have shown lesser toxicity and thus requires less stringent evaluation. However, to avoid the side effects of the unregulated use of these plant-based compounds, safety regulation on the use of the products is important (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Calixto 2000</xref>). It is, suggested that while bringing harmony with other agencies, regulatory authorities should work for regulating herbal products and using them as drug candidates for treating COVID-19.
</p>
