<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Comparisons between rhizosphere and endosphere microbial communities have revealed that as the interactions between plants and microbes intensifies, i.e., when microbes can actively colonize the inner part of the plants as endophytes, the plant imposes a strong selection pressure that limits microbiome composition [
 <xref rid="B69-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Our results corroborate these findings given the reduction in richness and diversity in the bacterial communities colonizing the root endosphere in relation to corresponding rhizosphere community, likely due to the selection for bacterial traits that allow them to enter and persist inside the roots [
 <xref rid="B69-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Our data also revealed that a large percentage of the endophytes were likely transmitted horizontally, i.e., they have been acquired from the surrounding soil, as the majority of the root endosphere (60% of the ASVs) was shared with either rhizosphere or bulk soil communities [
 <xref rid="B71-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The majority of the reminder endosphere ASVs were specific to each ecotype, indicating the indirect effect of elevation on plant physiology influencing the endosphere composition. Although we cannot pinpoint the exact plant mechanisms leading to the differentiation in endosphere composition observed among plant ecotypes, several aspects might be at play. For instance, the difference in composition may be explained by differences in the endosymbiotic bacteria associated to the mycorrhiza fungus [
 <xref rid="B62-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], which are lacking or not detected in the LE ecotype. Furthermore, this indicates the strong effect of elevation on plant local adaptation since plant genetic or phenotypic relatedness is positive correlated to root bacteria similarity [
 <xref rid="B66-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Although ecotype-specific bacteria could contribute to the better performance of seedlings in the elevation that resembled their parental origin [
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], this hypothesis needs to be specifically tested in further studies.
</p>
