<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is a rising global interest in ethno-pharmacological studies on plants that have been traditionally used to alleviate a myriad of diseases (
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2018</xref>). Due to the increasing number of people with non-communicable diseases, which represent about 70% of deaths in the world, the search for new pharmacological agents started to evaluate the medicinal plants mentioned in the pharmacopeias of different countries (
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2018</xref>). In this sense, 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> sp. has been the center of attention of many studies, which aim to evaluate and validate the therapeutic potential based on its ethnobotanical use. As 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> species can be found in many countries, the ethnobotanical information on their medicinal use is diverse; for example fruits, leaves, and stem bark of different 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> sp. has been reported to be used as a remedy to treat geriatric diseases, memory improvement, abdominal and back pain, cough, and colds, conjunctivitis, diarrhea, fever, headache, heart disorders, inflammation, leprosy, pneumonia, sexually transmitted diseases, urinary disorders, among others (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">Maulik and Katiyar, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Maulik and Talwar, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Cock, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Afshari et al., 2016</xref>). Medicinal plants have long been known to be rich sources of bioactive compounds. 
 <italic>Terminalia</italic> sp. belongs to the family 
 <italic>Combretaceae</italic>, has several biological activities, including antibacterial, antifungal, as well as antiparasitic. In addition, the extracts from the plant species showed antidiabetic, anticancer, and antioxidant activity.
</p>
