<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">
 <italic>Satureja</italic>
 <italic>hortensis</italic> is one of the typical plants of the 
 <italic>Lamiaceae</italic> family, and its essential oil has a wide variation of composition depending on the growing area and climate conditions. As found in literature
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> the main components of 
 <italic>S.hortensis</italic> essential oil are carvacrol, 
 <italic>γ</italic>-terpinene, 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, thymol, caryophyllene, 
 <italic>⍺</italic>-terpinolene, 
 <italic>β</italic>-pinene, 
 <italic>⍺</italic>-thujene and 
 <italic>⍺</italic>-pinene, which have antibacterial, antiviral, antifungal activities
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Due to its well-known properties, 
 <italic>S.</italic>
 <italic>hortensis</italic> essential oil has been imposed in various applicative fields, from the food industry to aromatherapy, which involves several treatments and heating processes that can affect its composition and thermal properties. The data obtained in this paper are meant to complete the previously reported results by other authors related to thermal analysis and kinetics of volatilization for different other essential oils types
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. The importance of the carvacrol, which was determined to be the major constituent of the essential oil of summer savory in the heated samples of essential oil of 
 <italic>S.</italic>
 <italic>hortensis</italic> (more than 91%), was earlier established and its applications were recently reviewed by Fierascu et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Carvacrol is also the major compound of the essential oils obtained from thyme, oregano, pepperwort, wild bergamot. Carvacrol presents antioxidant, antimicrobial, and antiparasitic properties, as well as anti-inflammatory, antinociceptive, hepatoprotective, anticancer, pain management activity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Due to these properties, carvacrol is used in the food industry, the beverage industry, and perfumery
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. Mohtashami et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> demonstrated that the quality of 
 <italic>S.</italic>
 <italic>hortensis</italic> essential oil is increasing during storage, for example, the carvacrol content of the sample increased from 50.69% to 57.66% when the sample was kept for six months in the freezer (at -20 ºC).
</p>
