<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Propionate formation, also considered as H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-utilisation pathway, consumes reducing equivalents, pyruvate which is reduced to propionate [
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>]. Though these H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> are the key precursor for the production of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, the increase in propionate formation is proportionally linked with decrease CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production. The succinate pathway is the major pathway of propionate production in the rumen where malate, fumarate, and succinate are formed as intermediate products. In this pathway, a mixture of bacteria such as fumarate reducers (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Wolinella succinogenes</italic>), succinate producers (
 <italic class="italic">Fibrobacter succinogenes</italic>), and succinate utilizers (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Selenomonas ruminantium</italic>) also involve. The acrylate pathway is an another important propionate producing pathway in the rumen by lactate-utilizing bacteria (
 <italic class="italic">Megasphaera elsdenii</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. The lactate is required in this pathway, therefore lactate-producing bacteria such as 
 <italic class="italic">Streptococcus bovis</italic> play a regulatory role. There are several studies have been conducted to enhance propionate production in the rumen targeting increase animal productivity through dietary probiotics [
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>–
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>] which are indirectly linked with methane mitigation approaches. The decrease in CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production was recorded in lactating dairy cows consumed a mixed 
 <italic class="italic">Propionibacterium jensenii</italic> – 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. direct feed microbials [
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>]. Mamuad et al. [
 <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>] reported that fumarate reducing bacteria alters the rumen microbiome and helping ruminal fermentation, and reducing CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production 
 <italic class="italic">in-vitro.</italic> Recently, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> production was also reduced through supplementation of fumarate reductase-producing enterococci (
 <italic class="italic">Enterococcus faecium</italic> SROD) with the increasing of total VFAs in an 
 <italic class="italic">in-vitro</italic> experiment [
 <xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>].
</p>
