<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <p id="Par1" class="p">
  <italic class="italic">Podisus nigrispinus</italic> Dallas (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae), released in biological control programs, is a predator of Lepidopteran and Coleopteran species. Lemongrass essential oil and its constituents can be toxic to this natural enemy. The major constituents of lemongrass essential oil are neral (31.5%), citral (26.1%), and geranyl acetate (2.27%). Six concentrations of lemongrass essential oil and of its citral and geranyl acetate constituents were applied to the thorax of 
  <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> nymphs and adults. The walking and respiratory behavior of the 
  <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> third-instar nymphs, treated with citral and geranyl acetate at the LD
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> and LD
  <sub class="sub">90</sub> doses, were analyzed with video and respirometer. The lemongrass essential oil toxicity increased from first- to fifth-instar 
  <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> nymphs. The 
  <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
  <italic class="italic">nigrispinus</italic> respiration rates (μL de CO
  <sub class="sub">2</sub> h
  <sup class="sup">−1</sup>/insect) with citral and geranyl acetate in the LD
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> and LD
  <sub class="sub">90</sub> differed. Nymphs exposed to the lemongrass essential oil and its constituents on treated surfaces presented irritability or were repelled. 
  <italic class="italic">Podisus nigrispinus</italic> adults were tolerant to the lemongrass essential oil and its constituents, geranyl acetate and citral. The altered respiratory activity with geranyl acetate and the fact that they were irritated and repelled by citral suggest caution with regard to the use of the lemongrass essential oil and its constituents in integrated pest management incorporating this predator, in order to avoid diminishing its efficiency against the pests.
 </p>
</abstract>
