<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The larvicidal activity of essential oils cinnamon (
  <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum verum</italic> J. Presl), Mexican lime (
  <italic class="italic">Citrus aurantifolia</italic> Swingle) cumin (
  <italic class="italic">Cuminum cyminum</italic> Linnaeus), clove (
  <italic class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</italic> (L.) Merr. &amp; L.M.Perry), laurel (
  <italic class="italic">Laurus nobilis</italic> Linnaeus), Mexican oregano (
  <italic class="italic">Lippia berlandieri</italic> Schauer) and anise (
  <italic class="italic">Pimpinella anisum</italic> Linnaeus)) and their major components are tested against larvae and pupae of 
  <italic class="italic">Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> Say. Third instar larvae and pupae are used for determination of lethality and mortality. Essential oils with more than 90% mortality after a 30-min treatment are evaluated at different time intervals. Of the essential oils tested, anise and Mexican oregano are effective against larvae, with a median lethal concentration (LC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub>) of 4.7 and 6.5 µg/mL, respectively. Anise essential oil and 
  <italic class="italic">t</italic>-anethole are effective against pupae, with LC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> values of 102 and 48.7 µg/mL, respectively. Oregano essential oil and carvacrol also have relevant activities. A kinetic analysis of the larvicidal activity, the oviposition deterrent effect and assays of the effects of the binary mixtures of chemical components are undertaken. Results show that anethole has synergistic effects with other constituents. This same effect is observed for carvacrol and thymol. Limonene shows antagonistic effect with 
  <italic class="italic">β</italic>-pinene. The high larvicidal and pupaecidal activities of essential oils and its components demonstrate that they can be potential substitutes for chemical compounds used in mosquitoes control programs.
 </p>
</abstract>
