<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Thus far several studies have found that inoculation of seeds with biofertilizers like 
 <italic>Azospirillum</italic>, 
 <italic>Azotobacter</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> or the combined application of bio-chemical fertilizers increases the number of branches and capsules (follicles) per plant in 
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. and plays an effective role in increasing seed yield of sesame or canola by various mechanisms such as N fixation, the synthesis of phytohormones, and different enzymes like phosphatase and biologically active compounds
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. The application of biosulfurs, which contains 
 <italic>Thiobacillus</italic> species, increased the seed yield of canola and sesame significantly. 
 <italic>Thiobacillus</italic> as sulfur-oxidizing bacteria improved the uptake of nutrients like P
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Inoculation with biological fertilizers, in combined treatments, seemingly enhances the efficiency of nutrient translocation to the seed. This can be ascribed to higher photosynthetic potential and the resulting filling of the plant reproductive sinks (seeds), which in turn improves 1000-seed weight. These effects of biofertilizers or their combination with chemical fertilizers can be observed in various plants such as dill, pinto beans, and psyllium
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Also, biofertilizers have been able to provide more nutrients to the plants through bacterial secretions and pH modulation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> and have been effective in increasing production with the production of more assimilates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
