<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the most extensively studied compounds isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> plants is piperlongumine, also known as piplartine. Piplartine is an amide alkaloid found in several 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> species (Piperaceae). It has been shown that piplartine has potential anticancer properties [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Piplartine also shows benefits in the treatment of the parasitic infection schistosomiasis, caused by helminth flatworms of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Schistosoma</italic> [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Compounds from 
 <italic class="italic">Piper tuberculatum</italic> fruits show antiplasmodial and antileishmanial activities [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. All these activities of 
 <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> plants on neglected tropical diseases are very important for pantropical regions, which are the natural habitats of these plants. Piperlongumine shows anti-inflammatory effects in the central nervous system (CNS). In relation with inflammation-related brain diseases, such as Alzheimer’s disease (AD), Parkinson’s disease (PD) and Huntington’s disease, one of the potential approaches in prevention and treatment of these diseases is normalization of microglia activity. The anti-neuroinflammatory effects of piperlongumine are characterized as inhibition of the production of nitric oxide (NO) and prostaglandin E
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (PGE
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) induced by lipopolysaccharide (LPS), also reducing the expression of inducible nitric oxide synthase and cyclooxygenase-2 as well as proinflammatory cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α and interleukin-6 (IL-6), and also by suppressing the nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κB) signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>].
</p>
