<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">Pyrochar improved soil characteristics not only under control conditions (without any contamination) but also under oil contamination. Thermal desorption had little effect on soil properties. The most promising results were shown by the combined application treatment. Soil amendments with combined application treatment (pyrochar and thermal desorption) improved the properties of soil. In thermal desorption, the soil contaminants are desorbed, mobilized, and evaporated by the rise in temperature (from 100 to 600 °C). Besides, thermal desorption also promotes biodegradation but decreases soil fertility
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. Relatively limited studies are available on the application of pyrochar on the remediation of soil contaminated with organic pollutants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. However, little is currently known about the effects of pyrochar combined application with thermal desorption technique on the remediation of petroleum-contaminated soil. However, it has been observed in the present study that this combined application treatment effectively improved soil characteristics both at 10% and 20% crude oil contamination. This may be possibly due to the synergistic action of pyrochar and thermal desorption under their combined application in pyrochar. This is mainly due to the greater absorptive capacity of pyrocahr’s greater surface area and microporous structure. Pyrochar enhances the nutrient content of soil for microbial populations and absorbed hydrophobic compounds more strongly. Improved microbial population stimulates the breakdown of absorbed hydrocarbons and used it as a source of carbon and energy. While thermal desorption accelerates the degradation of hydrocarbons. In thermal desorption, soil properties get changed and this type of soil is not supportive for the growth of plants. So in a combined application with pyrochar and thermal desorption, pyrochar improves the status of nutrients and holds hydrocarbons on its surface for degradation by microbes and thermal desorption and so this not only helps in degradation also enhances the nutrient status of the soil.
</p>
