<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>People have long histories in the uses of traditional medicinal and aromatic plants for medical purposes in the world, and currently, this use is often actively promoted. The medicinal significance of these plants can be authenticated through ethnomedicinal research, and a variety of studies have confirmed the use of medicinal species. 
 <italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> leaf extract is used for injuries and in joint pain [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]
 <italic>. Artemisia vulgaris</italic> is used against intestinal worms and for cardiac problems [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Leaves, roots and bark of 
 <italic>Berberis lycium</italic> are used for diabetes, muscle growth, broken bones, and diarrhea [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Traditionally, 
 <italic>Aconitum violaceum</italic> helps to remedy cough, asthma, neural disorders and heart disorders, as well as for treatment of joint pain and sciatica [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. 
 <italic>Cichorium intybus</italic> is used against gastro-intestinal problems, asthma, and gall stones [
 <xref rid="B64-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Ethnobotanical research in neighboring countries also supported our research findings. 
 <italic>Tribulus terrestris</italic> is used as a blood purifier, 
 <italic>Nerium oleander</italic> for toothache, and scorpion stings [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The above ethnomedicinal information and similarities with other regions confirm the importance of the described plants. 
 <italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic> has long been used for the treatment of inflammation in Chinese medicine, particularly to treat respiratory inflammation [
 <xref rid="B66-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The extract of 
 <italic>Mentha longifolia</italic> is used against infertility, Dyspepsia and Diarrhea because of the existence of Alkaloids, Tannins and Flavonoids [
 <xref rid="B67-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Mentha piperata</italic> is used to treat nausea, indigestion and anorexia [
 <xref rid="B68-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]
 <italic>. Tribulus terrestris</italic> extracts are commercially marketed and use for the development of muscles, sore throat, mental stimulation, relaxing the period of uncontrolled climacteric in women, and digestion disorders [
 <xref rid="B69-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. 
 <italic>Withania somnifera</italic> contains Withanolide A and Withaferin A and appears to possess various therapeutic activities against diseases like Alzheimer’s, cancer, fluid retention, Parkinson’s disease and diabetes [
 <xref rid="B70-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> contains Cannabidiol, which is used as an antipsychotic, schizophrenic agent and anxiolytic [
 <xref rid="B71-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The pure leaf extract of 
 <italic>Olea ferruginea</italic> has special inhibitory effects on fungal and bacterial pathogens [
 <xref rid="B72-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Ethanolic leaves extract of 
 <italic>Acacia modesta</italic> showed significant activity against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Proteus mirabilis, S. aureus, K. pneumonia, P. aeruginosa, S. typhi, B. cereus and B. subtilis and Streptococcus pneumonia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B73-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. This shows that further research on the reported ethnomedicinal plant species can lead to the recognition of novel agents with useful properties.
</p>
