<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results suggest that a context-dependent pre-adaptation of the tetraploid 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> rather than post-introduction evolution in North American tetraploids contributes to the high impact of North American tetraploid 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> in North America (cf. our hypotheses 2 &amp; 3 of the Introduction). Tetraploids reduced the biomass of the resident community more significantly than diploids, but this difference was only observed when competing with NA natives. Since the growth rate of the EU vs. NA neighbouring community in the non-competition containers did not differ consistently, our results indicate that tetraploid 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> inflict an over-proportional impact on NA neighbouring community compared to EU neighbouring community (hypotheses 1 &amp; 2). The fact that the biomass of all three 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> geo-cytotypes was correlated with the biomass of the EU neighbouring community, but not with that of the NA neighbouring community (hypotheses 4 &amp; 5), suggests an inherently different mechanism underlying the competitive interactions between 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> and its old neighbouring community in Europe vs. 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>stoebe</italic> and its new neighbouring community in North America. This pattern is unlikely to be influenced by individual neighbouring species. While a marginally significant variation in impact was found among the NA species used in this study (see the REI results in the 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec002">M&amp;M</xref>), no significant variation in impact was found among sixteen NA species (including the species used in this study) in a previously conducted pairwise competition experiment ([
 <xref rid="pone.0155712.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]); also, EU species did not differ in impact neither in this study nor in the previously conducted experiment ([
 <xref rid="pone.0155712.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]).
</p>
