<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Quantitative analysis of leaves revealed that withaferin A is 1.6% of total dry weight (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Leaves of the plant were extracted with ethanol and investigated to contain (5R,6S,7S,8S,9S,10R,13S,14S,17S,20R,22R)-6,7α-epoxy-5,17-α,27-trihydroxy-1-oxo-22R-witha-2,24-dienolide (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Several dragendorff positive alkaloids isolated from crude methanolic extract of roots were recognized as pseudotropine, cuscohygrine, isopelletierine, 
 <italic>dl</italic>-isopelletierine-3-tropyltigloate, anaferine, hygrine, anahygrine, somniferine, meso-anaferine, 3α-tigloyloxtropine, choline, withanine, visamine, withananine, hentriacontane, and withasomnine along with pyrazole derivatives, pseudowithanine, and ashwagandhine. It was concluded, using spectral studies, that methanolic extract of shade-dried aerial parts possessed chlorinated withanolide (27-acetoxy-4
 <italic>β</italic>,6
 <italic>α</italic>-dihydroxy-5
 <italic>β</italic>-chloro-1-oxowitha-2,24-dienolide) along with diepoxy withanolide, and withaferin A, which displayed anti-cancerous potential against human lung cancer (NCI-H460 cell line) (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Steroidal lactones, withanolide G and Δ16-withanolide (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>-
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>) were isolated from chemotype III. Whole plant extracted with equimolar ratios of water and methanol was characterized using spectroscopic techniques and X-ray crystallographic analysis and explored and found to contain new chlorinated withanolide, 6α-chloro-5β,17α-dihydroxywithaferin A along with nine known withanolides such as (22R)-5β-formyl-6β,27-dihydroxy-1-oxo-4-norwith-24-enolide, 6α-chloro-5β-hydroxywithaferin A, 2,3-dihydrowithaferin A, withaferin A, withanone, 3-methoxy-2,3-dihydrowithaferin A, withanoside IV, 2,3-didehydrosomnifericin, and withanoside X. Ethanol extract of the plant was examined and shown to have withasomniferin A, iso-sominolide and sominone (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>)
 <italic>.</italic>  Leaves of crossbreed of 
 <italic>W. somnifera</italic> from Israel and new Dehli (India) regions were extracted with ethanol and showed the presence of withanolide T and U (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>).
</p>
