<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The plants are rich in phytochemicals such as alkaloids, steroids, terpenoids, etc., which are important parts of food and folk medicine in the history of mankind (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>-
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Power and Salway initiated phytochemical studies of 
 <italic>W. somnifera</italic> in 1911 with the isolation of withaniol, somnirol, somnitol, withanic acid, phytosterol, ipuranol, and alkaloids from alcoholic extracts of leaves and roots (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Alkaloids isolated in the study mentioned above were named as somniferine, somnine, somniferinine, withamine, withanmine, pseudowithamine, and withanaminine (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). It was investigated that alcoholic extract of the plant contains various phytochemicals such as tropine, choline, pseudotropine, 
 <italic>dl</italic>-isopelletierine, cuscohygrine, anahygrine, and anaferine (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Furthermore, a pyrazole alkaloid, withasomnine, was separated from the alcoholic root extract of 
 <italic>W. somnifera</italic> (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In 1980 the presence of tisopelletierine, 3α-tigloyloxtropine, cuscohygrine, 3-tropyltigloate, hygrine, 
 <italic>dl</italic>-isopelletierine, withasomnine, mesoanaferine, withanine, somniferine, hentriacontane, withananine, visamine, ashwagandhine, and pseudowithanine in methanolic extract of the plant leaves was reported (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Besides, the methanolic extract of the plant was shown to have withaniol, reducing sugars, acylsteryl glucosides, ducitol, starch, hantreacotane, iron, and amino acids such as aspartic acid, proline, tyrosine, alanine, glycine, glutamic acid, cysteine, and tryptophan (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Seven new withanosides I-VII were obtained from methanolic extract of the plant root, and structures were confirmed using Fast Atom Bombardment-Mass Spectrometry, 
 <sup>13</sup>C and 
 <sup>1</sup>H nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR), and UV-Visible spectroscopic techniques (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).
</p>
