<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">Gallic acid, ethyl gallate, scopoletin and maniladiol were isolated from the 
 <italic>Canarium schweinfurthii</italic> stem bark extract, these compounds were reported for the first time in this medicinal plant species and belong to the classes of polyphenols, triperpenes and coumarins. From the previous reports [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], only gallic acid and scopoletin have been isolated from other plants belonging to the same genus as 
 <italic>Canarium schweinfurthii</italic> and these compounds were reported to have antibacterial and antioxidant properties. The isolated compounds have variable activities (16 ≤ MIC≤1024 μg/mL) against the tested 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> serotypes. Among the pure isolated compounds, scopoletin showed the highest inhibitory activity with a MIC of 16 μg/mL against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium and 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Enteritidis. The activity of most of the isolated compounds was less than those of oxyphylline B (10 μg/mL) isolated from 
 <italic>Zizyphus oxyphylla</italic> Edgew against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] and lespedin 
 <bold>(</bold>12.25 μg/ml) isolated from 
 <italic>Brillanta isialamium</italic> against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However the anti-salmonellal activity of gallic acid and scopoletin against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi (32 μg/mL) was better than those of Bafoudiosbulbins A and Bafoudiosbulbins B isolated from 
 <italic>Dioscorea bulbifera</italic> L. var. sativa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. These results corroborate the finding of Lunga et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] who showed that the anti-salmonellal activity of isolated compounds from 
 <italic>Paullinia pinnata</italic> Linn ranged from 0.781 to 100 μg/mL. According to the Kuete’s classification scale [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], the antibacterial activity of a compound is significant when the MIC&lt; 10 μg/mL; moderate when 10 &lt; MIC≤100 μg/mL and low when MIC&gt; 100 μg/ml. With regard to this scale, the anti-salmonellal activities of the isolated compound from 
 <italic>Canarium schweinfurthii</italic> are moderate (10 &lt; MIC≤100 μg/mL). Scopoletin and gallic acid are significantly active against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi, 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi ATCC6539 and 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium. These results corroborate those of Okoli et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] who showed that 3β-hydroxylolean-12,18-diene isolated from 
 <italic>Canarium schweinfurthii</italic> was active on 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> with a MIC of 12.5 μg/ml against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi. It has been shown that in addition to its immunomodulatory effect [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], scopoletin reduces the intracellular survival of 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhi within U937 human macrophage cell line [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Gallic acid has in addition to its in vitro and in vivo antibacterial effect against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>], an antioxidant activity. These compounds related properties corroborate the findings of Sokoudjou et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] who reported that the ability of the extract of 
 <italic>Canarium schweinfurthii</italic> to cure salmonellosis in broilers could be explained by its ability to directly kill 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> and/or boost the immune system of the host. The dosage of the compounds isolated from this plant can be used to normalize the extract during the phytomedicine evaluation and preparation.
</p>
