<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Furthermore, in order to elucidate the physiological role of EgFAD8, we also detected whether the 
 <italic>EgFAD8</italic> promoter could be affected by the environmental stress including low-temperature and darkness treatments. In our previous study, the activity of 
 <italic>EgFAD8</italic> promoter in transgenic Arabidopsis has been characterized (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196693.s001">S1 Fig</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0196693.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The GUS staining results indicated that the 
 <italic>EgFAD8</italic> promoter has the expected capability to drive transgene expression in all tissues tested, except with very weak expression in roots (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196693.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). Thus, we used the 
 <italic>ProEgFAD8</italic>::
 <italic>GUS</italic> transgenic plants for the stress treatment analysis, since the EgFAD8 promoter is constitutively active in transgenic Arabidopsis. The results revealed that the GUS activity of the transgenic plants under the darkness and low temperature treatment was increased by 26% and 14-folds after 48-hour treatment when compared with that of the control, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196693.g004">Fig 4</xref>). So the 
 <italic>EgFAD8</italic> gene from oil palm could be significantly induced by low temperature and slightly induced by darkness. This is consistent with the induction expression of 
 <italic>AtFAD8</italic> from Arabidopsis when treated at 4 °C [
 <xref rid="pone.0196693.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0196693.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Similarly, the 
 <italic>PoleFAD8</italic> transcript level of 
 <italic>Portulaca oleracea</italic> L. also increased significantly after treatment at 5 °C [
 <xref rid="pone.0196693.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. As expected, this result also evidenced that the chloroplastic 
 <italic>EgFAD8</italic> from oil palm is cold-inducible. On the other hand, lots of light regulatory elements were predicted in the promoter of 
 <italic>EgFAD8</italic> by PlantCARE [
 <xref rid="pone.0196693.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The result of the darkness treatment on transgenic plants is also consistent with the bioinformatic prediction. The darkness could slightly induce the expression of 
 <italic>EgFAD8</italic>. While, the mechanism that the light regulates the expression of 
 <italic>FAD8</italic> still remains obscure. Our hypothesis is that more chloroplasts are needed for fatty acid synthesis in the dark than in the light, since the rate of fatty acid synthesis in leaves is six-fold higher in the light than in the dark [
 <xref rid="pone.0196693.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Thus, to maintain the constitutive function, more chloroplasts are synthesized in the leave cells, and the expression level of genes encoding the corresponding enzymes involved in the synthesis of chloroplast might be up-regulated. FAD8 is responsible for the polyunsaturated components of chloroplast membranes [
 <xref rid="pone.0196693.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, the related mechanism needs to be elucidated.
</p>
