<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to some authors, proteins and cytoplasmic enzymes would also suffer damage during plasma treatments. Indeed, reactive species are able to (i) break peptide bonds, (ii) oxidize amino acid side chains, especially of sulfur amino acids, such as methionine and cysteine, and amino acids harboring aromatic rings (tryptophan, phenylalanine and tyrosine), (iii) produce crosslinks within proteins, and (iv) give rise to aggregation phenomena, which are favored by the formation of intra- and inter-molecular disulfide bonds. All these effects result in modifications in the conformation and three-dimensional structure of proteins and enzymes (Surowsky et al., 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). In addition, in the case of enzymes, their activity could also be compromised by the oxidation of their cofactors (Colagar et al., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Actually, the oxidation of just one amino acid in a protein can affect its function (Lackmann et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). These latter authors showed that the loss of 3-phosphate glyceraldehyde activity after NTAP treatment was due to the oxidation of a cysteine residue (cys150) of its active site, which is known to be irreversible (Brandes et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). However, it is still unknown which enzymes and proteins are specific targets for the action of NTAP. In the particular case of vegetative cells, Hosseinzadeh Colagar et al. (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) analyzed 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> proteins after exposure to plasma using sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) techniques and found that high molecular weight proteins, of between 50 and 90 KDa, were especially sensitive to NTAP, observing a decrease in their content as treatment time increased. In addition, these authors also observed that the concentration of free amino acids linearly increased with exposure time, which suggested that NTAP is not only able to break peptide bonds, but also to fragment proteins liberating free amino acids. Concerning bacterial spores, several authors (Klämpfl et al., 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Tseng et al., 
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) have pointed out that the effectiveness of NTAP against these resistant forms is due to the inactivation of various enzymes responsible for spore germination, such as GerA and GerB, as well as to the inactivation of channel proteins involved in the transport of ions and dipicolinic acid, which also results in the inability to initiate germination processes.
</p>
