<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Production of sandy everlasting for therapeutic use could be carried out by small farms as a niche product and since the sandy soil is needed, sandy terrains could be utilized for the production of this medicinal plant (Olsson et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). Although the sandy everlasting is very interesting for the pharmaceutical industry, and also classified as endangered species in a number of European countries, very few data about its cultivation are available in the literature. First attempts of growing 
 <italic class="italic">H. arenarium</italic> date back to the mid of the 1970s (Fijalkowski and Seroczynska, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1974</xref>; Moroz et al., 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1976</xref>; Pacholak and Zalecki, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1979</xref>; Sawilska et al., 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>), but none of them was completely successful in terms of surviving ratio and growth (Buchwald, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1992</xref>). Most of the authors concluded that this plant is inconvenient for cultivation since experimental trials yielded only slightly higher amounts of inflorescence biomass than those from natural stands. Tyszynska-Kownacka (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1972</xref>) even suspected that this species might not be suitable for growing. Later cultivation trials have only explained the reason why those attempts failed (Sawilska, 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). The main flaws of the attempts at growing sandy everlasting in the previous century were neglecting the clonal character of its growth and ignoring its mycorrhizal associations. Sawilska et al. (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) took step forward in the further explanation on the necessity of mycorrhizal associations of arbuscular fungus 
 <italic class="italic">Glomus intraradices</italic> with plant roots, but, although feasible, soil vaccination with mycorrhizal inoculum did not much influence the growth and flowering of single shoots. Sawilska and Jendrzejczak (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) suggested 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> method of propagation, which seems to be more profitable as it allows the acquisition of a potentially unlimited number of shapely plants that flower at the same time. Each method of cultivation proved to be feasible, as each yielded a particular amount of valuable, raw herbal material.
</p>
