<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">If in a layer 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>, in the section of the abscissa 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic>, its breaking load reaches 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm14" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <msubsup class="msubsup">
      <mi class="mi">σ</mi>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">r</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mfenced open="(" close=")" class="mfenced">
       <mi class="mi">k</mi>
      </mfenced>
     </msubsup>
     <mfenced open="(" close=")" class="mfenced">
      <mi class="mi">x</mi>
     </mfenced>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, then it breaks and a first bar damage occurs. After the break of the first layer, the efforts are taken over by the other layers, causing a tension change in the layers. Thus, there are two scenarios for the break mechanism. The first presupposes that the breaking load is reached in other layers too, hence their concatenation and the bar break without any increase in the stress force. The second presupposes that after the redistribution of the tensions in the layers the breaking load is not reached in any of the remaining layers. In this case, the stress force may increase, leading to tension increase until the tensile strength is reached in one of the remaining layers, repeating the break phenomenon. The breaking load of the bar, marked by 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm15" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi class="mi">σ</mi>
     <mi class="mi">r</mi>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, is considered to be the average tension in the bar section at the moment when the concatenated break and the bar destruction occur. Since Hooke’s law stipulates proportionality between tensions and characteristic deformations, the highest tensions appear in the sections where the characteristic deformations are maximal. These arise in the points where the bar section rigidity is minimal. In practice, the break can be considered to occur at the strands in the area where the bar section rigidity is minimal.
</p>
