<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2662-7671</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7541265</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3095</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-020-03095-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Isolation of endophytic bacteria from the leaves of <italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> CIX1 for metabolites and their biological activities</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nxumalo</surname><given-names>Celiwe Innocentia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0894-0219</contrib-id><name><surname>Ngidi</surname><given-names>Londeka Sibusisiwe</given-names></name><address><email>londekangidi@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shandu</surname><given-names>Jabulani Siyabonga Emmanuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maliehe</surname><given-names>Tsolanku Sidney</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442325.6</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Science and Agriculture, Department of Biochemistry and Microbiology, </institution><institution>University of Zululand, </institution></institution-wrap>Private Bag X1001, KwaDlangezwa, KwaZulu Natal Province 3886 South Africa </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>300</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Endophytes, especially those that are found from ethnopharmacologically noteworthy medicinal plants have attracted attention due to their diverse bioactive metabolites of pharmacological importance.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This study aimed at isolating endophytic bacterium from the leaves of <italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> CIX1 for its bioactive metabolites. The endophytic isolates were identified by 16S rRNA sequence and investigated for antibiotic sensitivity using different antibiotics. The secondary metabolites were evaluated for antibacterial activity against four bacterial strains. The 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and 2, 2&#x02032;-azinobis (3- ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) (ABTS) methods were used to assess their scavenging activities. The chemical components were analysed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Out of 13 isolates, Isolate 1 was identified as <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> CP043328.1. It was resistant to clindamycin, ertapenem, penicillin G, amoxicillin, cephalothin and kanamycin but sensitive to imipenem, meropenem, and gentamycin. Its extract demonstrated antibacterial activity with minimum inhibitory concentration value of 0.098 against <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102) and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925) and 0.391&#x02009;mg/ml against <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) and <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic> (ATCC 25933). The extract revealed DPPH and ABTS scavenging activities with half maximal inhibitory concentration value of 0.650&#x02009;mg/ml and 0.15&#x02009;mg/ml, respectively. The GC-MS revealed a total of 15 compounds with diisooctyl phthalate (50.51%) and [1, 2, 4] oxadiazole, 5-benzyl-3 (10.44%) as major components.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4"><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP043328.1 produced secondary metabolites with antibacterial and antioxidant activities.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> CP043328.1</kwd><kwd>Antibacterial activity</kwd><kwd>Antioxidant activity</kwd><kwd>Volatile compounds</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100011512</institution-id><institution>National Research Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>HBG181011371909</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ngidi</surname><given-names>Londeka Sibusisiwe</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par26">South Africa has remarkable successes in treatment of infectious diseases that include HIV and TB, malaria and others. This is evidenced by the increase in life expectancy over the years. The increase stems from the implementation of some health initiatives that include the use of antiretroviral agents for people living with HIV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Although an outstanding progress has been made in reducing morbidity and mortality rates due to infectious diseases, new microbial resistance mechanisms threaten prevention and treatment procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This is due mainly to inadequate dosing, poor quality drugs, and genetic plasticity of the microorganisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Without effective antimicrobial agents, the success of even minor surgeries can be of a great challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Therefore, joint efforts to discover and develop new drugs is imperial.</p><p id="Par27">Medicinal plants are the predominant sources for bioactive compounds used in modern-day drug discoveries and developments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Over 80% of drugs on the market shelves currently have their origin in medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Although plant metabolites exhibit strong physiological activities, their production are not of convenience in terms of quality and productivity due to hysterical environmental conditions and rapid climatic changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Thus, bioprospecting of bioactive metabolites from microorganisms have become a promising alternative route for drug discovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">Microorganisms such as bacteria and fungi can produce high quality metabolites on a large scale under optimized culture conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. This is because their metabolite production is reproducible, weather and season independent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Microorganisms often produce metabolites that display distinctive molecular skeletons which are not even available in the chemical libraries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Endophytes are microorganisms which inhabit within plant tissues and often occur as symbionts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Endophytes, especially those that are found from ethnopharmacologically noteworthy medicinal plants have attracted attention due to their diverse bioactive metabolites against pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. They produce a plethora of metabolites with unique structures and profound biological activities. These include essential enzymes, alkaloids, flavonoids, phenolic acids, quinines, steroids and terpenoids. Although these metabolites were primarily beneficially to the host plant, they have found a wide-ranging application industrially. They are harvested and used as agrochemicals, antibiotics, immunosuppressants and antioxidants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Nevertheless, most of research focuses on fungal-based bioactive products and a limited number has been isolated from bacterial endophyte [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par29"><italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> is a well-recognized medicinal plant that belong to Basellaceae family. <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> possesses pharmacological activities such as antibacterial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], gastroprotective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], antivirus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], antidiabetic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], anti-inflammatory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], wound healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and antioxidant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Phytochemical screening has revealed the presence of flavanols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], glycosides, alkaloids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], flavonoids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], saponin and steroid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] in different parts. Although there are many studies documenting its medicinal properties and usage, to the best of our knowledge, there are no studies reporting on its bacterial endophytes.</p><p id="Par30">The study was designed to isolate and identify endophytic bacteria from <italic>A. cordifolia</italic>. The bacteria were screened for extracellular enzyme and antimicrobial agent production. Moreover, its biological activities such as antibacterial and antioxidant activities were evaluated from the extracted secondary metabolites of one of the isolates. Lastly, metabolites composition was analysed. The other isolated bacteria will be investigated in future studies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Chemicals and media</title><p id="Par31">All chemicals and media used were procured from Sigma-Aldrich and Merck (Pty) Ltd. The water used was distilled and autoclaved.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Sample collection and treatment</title><p id="Par32">Healthy fresh leaves of <italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> were collected on the 2nd of July 2019 from KwaDlangezwa area in the city of Umhlathuze, KwaZulu-Natal Province, South Africa (28 &#x000b0;45 &#x02032;S31 &#x000b0;54 &#x02032;E). The voucher specimen for <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> species, voucher number CIX1, was prepared and deposited in the University of Zululand Herbarium [ZULU], which is available mainly to researchers. The leaves were washed thoroughly under running tap water and air dried. The surfaces of the leaves were disinfected by dipping them in 75% ethanol for 5&#x02009;min, followed by dipping in sodium hypochlorite (2% w/v NaOCl) for 4&#x02009;min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. They were further dipped in sodium bicarbonate (10% NaHCO3) for 2&#x02009;min and subsequently rinsed in sterile distilled water six times. The excess water was dried under laminar airflow chamber. To confirm the disinfection process, aliquots of the sterile water used in the final rinse were plated onto nutrient agar (NA). The plates were then incubated at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;days and observed for any microbial growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Isolation of endophytic bacteria</title><p id="Par33">NA was used for the isolation of the endophytic bacteria. The disinfected leaves, without midribs, were ground in sterile 6&#x02009;ml of aqueous saline solution (0.9% NaCl) using a sterile mortar, under aseptic conditions. The tissue extract was serially diluted in sterile aqueous solution. About 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of each dilute (10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> and 10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;2</sup>) and undiluted sample were pipetted on NA plates and spread evenly using a sterilized glass spreader. Plates were sealed and incubated at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;days. The colonies were counted as colony forming units (CFU) per gram and expressed as population density. The colonies were selected based on divergence in morphology, size and colour. They were then sub-cultured twice on NA and stored at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Screening for enzyme production</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Amylase production</title><p id="Par34">The amylase production was investigated by starch agar plate method. Briefly, NA medium was supplemented with 1&#x02009;g/L of starch. One microliter of the isolates was inoculated onto the medium and incubated at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;days. The positive controls were <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) and <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102) while autoclaved distilled water served as a negative control. The plates were then flooded with Gram&#x02019;s dye solution. The presence of halos around the colonies were indicative amylase production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Proteinase production</title><p id="Par35">Proteolytic production of the bacterial strains was assessed on protease casein medium that contained NA supplemented with 1% casein. One microliter of each isolate was pipetted on the plate and incubated at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;days. The positive control was <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102) while autoclaved distilled water served as a negative control. After incubation time, the clear zones due to casein hydrolysis were considered as an indication of protease production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Cellulase production</title><p id="Par36">Carboxy methyl cellulase production was evaluated using the method by Zamani et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The NA supplemented with 1% of carboxy methyl cellulose was inoculated with the isolates and incubated for 5&#x02009;days at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The negative control was <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) while <italic>Cellulomonas humilata</italic> ATCC 2517 served as the positive control. The plates were then flooded with a solution of 0.5% Congo red. Isolates forming yellow coloured zones were considered positive for cellulase activity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Esterase production</title><p id="Par37">The medium containing peptone 10.0&#x02009;g/L, NaCl 5.0&#x02009;g/L, CaCl2.2H2O 0.1&#x02009;g/L, agar 18.0&#x02009;g/L, pH&#x02009;7.0 was prepared for determining esterase activity. To the sterilized culture medium, previously sterilized Tween 80 (1% (v/v) was added. Endophytic bacterial isolates, <italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) (negative control) and <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102) (positive control) were separately pipetted onto the medium and incubated at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5 days. After incubation period, the appearance of a well visible halo around the colonies was indicative of the esterase production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Screening for antimicrobial agents production</title><p id="Par38">Pure endophytic bacterial isolates were pre-cultured overnight on NA at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. A loopful of fresh endophytic bacterial species were inoculated into 100&#x02009;ml Erlenmeyer flask containing 50&#x02009;ml of sterilised nutrient broth (NB). They were incubated at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 130&#x02009;rpm for 72&#x02009;h. Two millilitres of the fermented broth were centrifuged at 13000&#x02009;rpm for 15&#x02009;min. The culture supernatant was used for screening of antibacterial activity. An agar well diffusion method was employed to screen antibacterial activity of the isolates in accordance to [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Briefly, test bacterial inoculums <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102), <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925), <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic> (ATCC 25933) and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) were adjusted to 106&#x02009;CFU/ml. The test bacterial strains were streaked on Mueller Hinton (MH) agar with sterile swabs over the agar surface. About 6&#x02009;mm diameter wells were made on the bacterial lawn using sterile cork borer. A total of 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the centrifuged endophyte broths-supernatants was pipetted into the wells. MH broth was set as negative control and ciprofloxacin (20&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml) as a positive control. The plates were left at room temperature for 10&#x02009;min to allow the diffusion of the supernatants into the agar. They were then sealed and incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. After 24&#x02009;h, the plates were observed for the inhibition of the selected bacteria. The zone of inhibition was measured and expressed in millimetres as an indication of antibacterial activity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Morphological identification of endophytic bacteria</title><p id="Par39">Pure bacterial colonies were subjected to Gram staining to investigate their morphological physiognomies such as shape and Gram stain reaction. Briefly, the bacterial isolates were spread on the glass slides and heat fixed using Bunsen burner. The crystal violet was used as a primary stain, followed by iodine solution. It was decolorized by ethanol after washing with tap water. The slides were flooded with safranin and rinsed with tap water. Lastly, the slides were viewed at 1000X magnification using a compound bright- field microscope [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Molecular identification of endophytic bacteria</title><p id="Par40">Five isolates (Isolate 1&#x02013;5) were further identified using 16S rRNA sequence analysis by Inqaba Biotechnical Industries (Pty) Ltd. Briefly, DNA extraction was done using a ZR Fungal/Bacterial Kit&#x02122; according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was run to amplify the 16S rDNA gene of the endophyte with the primers 16S- 27F: 5&#x02032;AGAGTTTGATCMTGGCTCAG- 3&#x02032; and 16S- 1492R: 5&#x02032;- CGGTTACCTTGTTACGACTT-3&#x02032;, using DreamTaq&#x02122; DNA polymerase. PCR products were gel extracted and sequenced in the forward and reverse directions on the ABI PRISM&#x02122; 3500xl Genetic Analyser. The PCR products were cleaned with ExoSAP-it&#x02122; following the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations. Purified sequencing products were analysed using CLC Bio Main Workbench v7.6, followed by a BLAST search using the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) database to identify the closest bacterial species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Sensitivity assay</title><p id="Par41">Antimicrobial susceptibility assay was performed using the Kirby&#x02013;Bauer disk diffusion method. Different antimicrobial agent that include; clindamycin 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g, ertapenem 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g, imipenem 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g, kanamycin 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g, gentamicin 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g, cephalothin 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g, amoxicillin 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g and meropenem 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g were used. <italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC 27853) served as the reference strains alongside the test strain. The zones of inhibition were interpreted in accordance to the Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Metabolites extraction</title><p id="Par42">The secondary metabolites from Isolate 1 were obtained by inoculating 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of bacterial suspension into 500&#x02009;ml of NB. The culture was incubated at 28&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;days on a rotating shaker at 130&#x02009;rpm. The broth culture was centrifuged at 5000&#x02009;rpm for 30&#x02009;min. The supernatant was collected and the pellet discarded. The supernatant was extracted with an equal volume of ethyl acetate (500&#x02009;ml) and then left overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The solvent phase containing the extracted secondary metabolites was separated using separating funnel. The extract was evaporated using a rotary evaporator at 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with 90&#x02009;rpm to yield the crude metabolites. The residue was re-dissolved in methanol. The concentrated crude extract was then stored at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for further studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Determination of antibacterial activity using crude extract</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Agar well diffusion</title><p id="Par43">Preliminary antibacterial activity of the crude extract was determined by agar diffusion method as described previously. Ten percent of DMSO was used as a negative control while ciprofloxacin (20&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml) served as a positive control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Serial microdilution method</title><p id="Par44">The extract was submitted to further analysis to detect its minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) using microdilution method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The stock solution of 100&#x02009;mg/ml of the extract was prepared in 10% dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO). Micro-serial dilution was carried out using MH broth in a range of 50&#x02013;0.313&#x02009;mg/ml. About 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of the fresh selected bacterial suspension at a density of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup>&#x02009;CFU/min<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>, was pipetted into the wells. Ten percent of DMSO was used as a negative control while ciprofloxacin (20&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml) served as a positive control. The plates were sealed and incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C overnight. Afterwards, 40&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 0.2&#x02009;mg/ml of piodonitrotetrazodium violet (INT) solution was added to each well and incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min. The MIC was perceived as the lowest concentration of the extract that inhibited the bacterial growth.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Evaluation of minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC)</title><p id="Par45">MBC was assessed by removing a loopful of each culture from the wells that had no bacterial growth. They were then streaked on different sterile MH agar plates. The agar plates were incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;h. The lowest concentration of the extract that exhibited the complete killing of the selected bacterial test species was considered as the MBC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>2, 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical scavenging assay</title><p id="Par46">The DPPH free radical scavenging activity of the extract was investigated in a sterile 96-well plate. The DPPH (0.02&#x02009;mg/mL) was mixed (1:1&#x02009;v/v) with the extract at different concentrations. The mixtures were made to stand at room temperature (25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) for 30&#x02009;min in darkness and the absorbance was read at 517&#x02009;nm by using microplate reader. The extract without DPPH was used as the blank while ascorbic acid (AA) and butylated hydroxyl anisole (BHA) served as the positive controls. The percent inhibition of DPPH radical was measured by the using the formula: %DPPH scavenging activity&#x02009;=&#x02009;[Ao &#x02013; A1 / Ao]&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100 where, A1 and Ao equal the absorbance at 517&#x02009;nm of the control and the test, respectively. The median inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) of the extract against DPPH was calculated graphically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>2, 2&#x02032;-azino-bis-3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (ABTS) radical scavenging assay</title><p id="Par47">The ABTS free radical scavenging activity of the extract was evaluated by using serial dilution method. ABTS solution (0.003&#x02009;g/mL) was mixed (1:1&#x02009;v/v) with the extract at different concentrations. Each mixture was made to stand for 15&#x02009;min at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and the absorbance was read at 734&#x02009;nm by using microplate reader. The extract without ABTS solution served as blank. Ascorbic acid (AA) and butylated hydroxyl anisole (BHA) were used as the positive controls. The percent inhibition of ABTS radical was calculated by the following formula: %ABTS scavenging activity&#x02009;=&#x02009;[Ao &#x02013; A1 / Ao]&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100 where, A1 and Ao equal the absorbance recorded at 734&#x02009;nm of the control and the test, respectively. The IC<sub>50</sub> of the extract against ABTS was calculated graphically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Analysis of volatile compounds</title><p id="Par48">The components of the extract were analysed by using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS). The temperature of the GC oven was initially set at 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min and subsequently increased by 5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C per minute to 220&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The temperature of the injector was programmed to 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and the flow rate of the helium gas was 1.0&#x02009;ml per minute, with a 10:1 split ratio. The ion source temperature of the MS system was put at 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with the voltage of 70&#x02009;eV. The evaluation was performed two times [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Software and statistical analysis</title><p id="Par49">All the experimentations were done in triplicates and the data were subjected to one-way analysis of variance using Graph Pad Prism TM 6.1. Arrow bars represented the standard deviation and values with different alphabets represent the significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec25"><title>Isolation and surface sterilization</title><p id="Par50">The surface of the leaves was sterilised by sequentially immersing them in 70% ethanol, 2% sodium hypochlorite and 10% sodium bicarbonate. This protocol was effective as the control plates did not reveal any bacterial growth after 5&#x02009;days. Nutrient agar plates inoculated with <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> leaf samples showed morphologically different colonies. The number of CFU per gram fresh weight of the isolates was investigated. The results showed that the leaves had 9.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;103&#x02009;CFU/g<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Endophytic bacterial population from the fresh leaves of <italic>A. cordifolia</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sample</th><th>Un-diluted<break/>(CFU/g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</th><th>10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup><break/>(CFU/g<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>)</th><th>10<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;2</sup><break/>(CFU/g<sup>&#x02212;&#x02009;1</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Leaves</td><td>TN</td><td>TN</td><td>9.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>TN denotes too numerous to count</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Enzyme and antimicrobial agent production</title><p id="Par51">The isolates were all screened qualitatively on solid casein, cellulose, tween 80 and starch media for the four industrially important enzymes namely; proteases, cellulase, esterase and amylases. All isolates showed the ability to produce two or more of the tested enzymes. About 38, 62, 38 and 77% of the isolates produced proteinase, amylase, esterase and cellulase, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Isolate 1&#x02013;5 showed the ability to produce all the tested enzymes. The isolates were further screened for antimicrobial agent production using broth fermentation cultures. Isolate 1 did also show broad spectrum against all tested clinical human pathogens (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Enzyme and antimicrobial agent production</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Isolates</th><th colspan="3">Enzyme production</th><th colspan="3">Zone of inhibition</th><th colspan="2"/></tr><tr><th>Proteinase</th><th>Amylase</th><th>Esterase</th><th>Cellulase</th><th><bold><italic>E. coli</italic></bold> (ATCC 25922)</th><th><bold><italic>P. mirabilis</italic></bold> (ATCC 25933)</th><th><bold><italic>B. cereus</italic></bold> (ATCC 10102)</th><th><bold><italic>S. aureus</italic></bold> (ATCC 25925)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>++</td><td>++</td><td>+++</td><td>+++</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>++</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>++</td><td>++</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>++</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>++</td><td>++</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>++</td><td>+</td><td>+++</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+++</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>++</td><td>++</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>++</td><td>+++</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>+ denotes enzyme production and - denotes no enzyme production. Inhibition zone diameter index: + (&#x02264; 9&#x02009;mm) weak activity, ++ (10&#x02013;20&#x02009;mm) moderate activity, +++ (&#x02265;21&#x02009;mm) strong activity and -denotes no activity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Identification of the endophytes</title><p id="Par52">The isolates were selected for morphological characterization using Gram staining. Twelve isolates were Gram negative rods while one isolate was a Gram positive rod (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Molecular characterization of the endophytic bacteria indicate that they are different bacterial species. The final taxonomic status of 5 selected endophytic bacteria isolates was determined by 16S rRNA gene sequencing. The sequence alignment showed the similarity in a range of 97&#x02013;99% in BLAST with different strains of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> namely; <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP43328.1, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP033432.1, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> LR657304.1, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP044006.1 and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP032126.1 (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Identities and morphological characteristics of the endophytic bacterial isolates</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Isolates</th><th>Assigned bacterial<break/>Names</th><th>GenBank accession number</th><th>Similarities (%)</th><th>Colony morphology</th><th>Gram reaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td><bold><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></bold></td><td><bold>CP043328.1</bold></td><td><bold>99</bold></td><td><bold>Rod</bold></td><td><bold>Negative</bold></td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></td><td>CP033432.1</td><td>97</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></td><td>LR657304.1</td><td>97</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td><p><italic>Pseudomonas</italic></p><p><italic>Aeruginosa</italic></p></td><td>CP044006.1</td><td>98</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td><p><italic>Pseudomonas</italic></p><p><italic>aeruginosa</italic></p></td><td>CP032126.1</td><td>98</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Positive</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td><italic>&#x02013;</italic></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>Rod</td><td>Negative</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Susceptibility pattern of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP43328.1</title><p id="Par53">Based on the outstanding results showed by Isolate 1 (<italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP43328.1) during screening methods, Kirby-Bauer method was used to evaluate its susceptibility patterns using different antibiotics. The isolate was resistant to clindamycin, ertapenem, cephalothin, penicillin G, kanamycin and amoxicillin but sensitive to imipenem, meropenem and gentamycin (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Antibiotic susceptibility pattern of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> CP43328.1; inhibition zones</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Isolate</th><th>MEM</th><th>IML</th><th>KF</th><th>ETP</th><th>DA</th><th>K</th><th>A</th><th>GM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.0</td><td>0</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Key: <italic>MEM</italic> meropenem, <italic>IML</italic> imipenem, <italic>KF</italic> cephalothin, <italic>ETP</italic> ertapenem, <italic>DA</italic> clindamycin, <italic>K</italic> kanamycin, <italic>A</italic> amoxicillin and <italic>GM</italic> gentamicin</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Extraction of secondary metabolites</title><p id="Par54">Based on the outstanding results obtained during screening of enzymes and antibiotic production, secondary metabolites from Isolate 1 (<italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP043328.1) were extracted. The isolate yielded 0.6&#x02009;g/500&#x02009;ml of the extract.</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Antibacterial activity of the extract</title><p id="Par55">The tests for the antibacterial potency of the extract was evaluated against the selected bacterial pathogens using the agar diffusion method and results are demonstrated in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. The extract demonstrated significant inhibitory ability against all selected bacterial strains. It was mostly effective against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925), with the maximum inhibition zone of 31&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.25&#x02009;mm.
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Antibacterial activity of the extract evaluated by agar diffusion method</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">concentration</th><th colspan="4">Zone of inhibition (mm)</th></tr><tr><th><bold><italic>E. coli</italic></bold><break/>(ATCC 25922)</th><th><bold><italic>P. mirabilis</italic></bold><break/>(ATCC 25933)</th><th><bold><italic>B. cereus</italic></bold><break/>(ATCC 10102)</th><th><bold><italic>S. aureus</italic></bold><break/>(ATCC 25925)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>4&#x02009;mg/ml</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.25</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.00</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.41</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">31&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.25</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par56">Microdilution method was used to investigate the minimum inhibition concentration (MIC) of the extract. MIC of the secondary metabolites ranged from 0.098&#x02009;mg/ml to 0.39&#x02009;mg/ml. The profound antibacterial activity of the extract was against the Gram-positive bacteria <italic>B. cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102) and <italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925) with MIC value of 0.098&#x02009;mg/ml (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). Although the extract was more pronounced against Gram positive bacterial strains, it also did demonstrate remarkable antibacterial activity against Gram negative bacteria <italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922) and <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> (ATCC 25933) with the MIC of 0.39&#x02009;mg/ml. Moreover, ciprofloxacin showed higher MIC value (25&#x02009;mg/ml) against the tested strains when compared to the extract. Minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) of the extract was evaluated against the selected bacterial strains. The extract showed only bactericidal effect against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925) with the MBC of 25&#x02009;mg/ml (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>MIC and MBC values of the extract against the selected bacterial strains</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Bacteria</th><th colspan="2">Extract</th><th colspan="2">Ciprofloxacin</th></tr><tr><th>MIC (mg/ml)</th><th>MBC (mg/ml)</th><th>MIC (mg/ml)</th><th>MBC (mg/ml)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>B. cereus</italic> (ATCC 10102)</td><td>0.098&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>&#x0003e; 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>&#x0003e; 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925)</td><td>0.098&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>&#x0003e; 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC 25922)</td><td>0.391&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>&#x0003e; 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>&#x0003e; 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>P. mirabilis</italic> (ATCC 25933)</td><td>0.391&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>&#x0003e; 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td><td>25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0</td><td>&#x0003e; 50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>2, 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical scavenging assay</title><p id="Par57">The scavenging activity of the extract against DPPH is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The extract exhibited maximum DPPH scavenging activity of 63% at 1.0&#x02009;mg/ml. It also demonstrated the IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.650&#x02009;mg/ml, which was higher than that of ascorbic acid (0.200&#x02009;mg/ml) and BHA (0.188&#x02009;mg/ml).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>DPPH scavenging activity of the extract, ascorbic acid and BHA</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3095_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>2, 2&#x02032;-azino-bis-3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (ABTS) radical scavenging assay</title><p id="Par58">The ABTS radical scavenging activity of the extract is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. The scavenging activity of the extract increased up to 91% at 0.5&#x02009;mg/ml. The extract had potent antioxidant activity with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.150&#x02009;mg/ml. Ascorbic acid and BHA had IC<sub>50</sub> of 0,258&#x02009;mg/ml and 0,300&#x02009;mg/ml, respectively.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>ABTS scavenging activity of the extract, ascorbic acid and BHA</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3095_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Analysis of bioactive compounds</title><p id="Par59">GC-MC chromatogram displayed a total of 15 compounds (Table <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>). They are diisooctyl phthalate (50.51%), 9-octadecenamide (10.44%), [1, 2, 4] oxadiazole, 5-benzyl-3- (thiophen-2-yl) (5.70%), 2-dodecenoic acid (5.51%), trans-2-decenoic acid (4.57%), xanthoxylin (3.74%), L-proline, N-valeryl-, undecyl ester (2.86%), L-proline, N-valeryl-, tetradecyl ester (2.61%), pyrrolo [1,2-a]pyrazine-1,4-dione, hexahydro-3-(2-methylpropyl) (2.37%), pentadecanoic acid (2.13%), cis-9-octadecenoic acid (2.13%), cyclohexanone, 4-methyl, O-methyloxime (2.04%), 3-nonynoic acid (1.88%), benzonitrile, 2-(2-pyridinyl) (1.88%) and ergotaman-3&#x02032;,6&#x02032;,18-trione,9,10-dihydro-12&#x02032;-hydroxy-2&#x02032;-methyl-5&#x02032;-(phenylmethyl) (1.68%). (TLC) was carried out to investigate chemical compounds in the extract.
<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Chemical constituents of the extract</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Number of compounds</th><th>Compounds</th><th>Area (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>Ergotaman-3&#x02032;,6&#x02032;,18-trione,9,10-dihydro-12&#x02032;-hydroxy-2&#x02032;-methyl-5&#x02032;-(phenylmethyl)</td><td>1.68</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>3-Nonynoic acid</td><td>1.88</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Benzonitrile, 2-(2-pyridinyl)</td><td>1.88</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Cyclohexanone, 4-methyl-, O-methyloxime</td><td>2.04</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Pentadecanoic acid</td><td>2.13</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>cis-9-Octadecenoic acid</td><td>2.13</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Pyrrolo[1,2-a]pyrazine-1,4-dione, hexahydro-3-(2-methylpropyl</td><td>2.37</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>L-Proline, N-valeryl-, tetradecyl ester</td><td>2.61</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>L-Proline, N-valeryl-, undecyl ester</td><td>2.82</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Xanthoxylin</td><td>3.74</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>trans-2-Decenoic acid</td><td>4.57</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>2-Dodecenoic acid</td><td>5.51</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>[1, 2, 4] Oxadiazole, 5-benzyl-3-(thiophen-2-yl)</td><td>5.70</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>9-Octadecenamide</td><td>10.44</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>Diisooctyl phthalate</td><td>50.51</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par60">The multi-drug resistance of pathogenic microorganisms is getting more and more severe yearly due to misuse of drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Endophytes, especially those from medicinal plants are reported to be prolific producers of variety of metabolites with profound bioactivities. Moreover, their metabolites are biodegradable and easy to be produced on a large scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Thus, bacterial endophytes from <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> CIX1 were isolated for production of bioactive compounds.</p><p id="Par61">A variety of chemical disinfectants have been employed for surface sterilization of excised plant tissues to remove epiphytes. However, immersion of tissue in ethanol, sodium hypochloride and bicarbonate have shown significant success in different studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The effectiveness of surface sterilization of the leaves from <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> CIX1 was confirmed as there was no microbial growth observed after 5&#x02009;days. This indicate that the surface sterility method was effective at inhibiting growth of epiphytic bacteria and fungi. Thus, the subsequence isolates can be considered as true endophytic bacteria. The leaves had CFU value of 9.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;103 (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The diversity of isolated endophytic bacteria dependent on the media used during isolation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Our results demonstrated that NA did support the growth of endophytic bacteria. Thirteen endophytic strains were isolated from the fresh leaves of <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> CIX1. It can therefore be assumed that the ecological success of <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> CIX1 in the north part of Kwazulu-Natal could not only be associated to the conducive climate and fertile soil but also to its association with active endophytes as they are known to have symbiotic relationship.</p><p id="Par62">Currently, microorganisms are attracting an increasing attention as source of for new enzymes because enzymes derived from microbes are relatively stable and active than corresponding enzymes derived from plants or animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. In the study, the qualitative analysis of enzyme production namely; protease, cellulase, esterase and amylase was done. Most of the isolate tested positive for enzyme production. Our observations are in agreement with previous reports that illustrated endophytes such as <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. as producers of extracellular amylase, esterase, cellulose and proteinase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The hydrolytic enzymes are perceived to play an important role for the colonization of <italic>A. cordifolia</italic> CIX1 by the isolated endophytes.</p><p id="Par63">All the morphologically identified bacterial endophytes were of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. The isolate of interest (Isolate 1) exhibited 99% similarity with <italic>Pseudomonas aureuginosa</italic> CP043328.1. Most studies have reported that <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. are one of the main endophytic bacteria often found associated with most of the medicinal plants. Thus, our study affirmed these reports. Endophytic <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. have been used as biocontrols against phytopathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">Antimicrobial resistant genes, in addition to clinical pathogens, are also present in environmental isolates. Isolate-<italic>P. aureuginosa</italic> CP043328.1 was sensitive to meropenem, imipenem and gentamycin (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This suggest that these compounds (antibiotics) are not present as secondary metabolites in <italic>P. aureuginosa</italic> CP043328.1. Moreover, these antibiotics can be used if there is an outbreak due to <italic>P. aureuginosa</italic> CP043328.1. Ethyl acetate solvent was used for extraction of the secondary metabolites and the yield was 0.6&#x02009;g/500&#x02009;ml. Ethyl acetate is the good solvent for extraction of active metabolites from bacterial endophytes as it has medium polarity (dissolve both polar and non- polar active compounds) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. In addition to medium polarity, the solvent extract low and high molecular weight polyphenols.</p><p id="Par65">In therapeutic applications, secondary metabolites are significant as they often demonstrate among others, efficacy against multidrug-resistant bacteria. Thus, secondary metabolites from Isolate 1-<italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP043328.1 were extracted and antibacterial potency of the extract was evaluated against the selected bacteria. The extract showed a broad-spectrum activity against all tested bacterial strains (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). It was more pronounced against Gram positive bacterial strains. Gram-negative bacteria, in addition to a thin peptidoglycan layer (2 to 7&#x02009;nm), do possess approximately 7 to 8&#x02009;nm of the outer membrane. This outer membrane consists of an additional protective lipopolysaccharide layer that exhibits toxicity and antigenicity against antibacterial agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. It was therefore concluded that the resistance shown by the Gram-negative bacteria as compared to Gram-positive bacteria to the extract was as the result of the mechanism of action of this layer. Gram positive bacteria do not possess this layer and therefore they were highly sensitive to the extract. Gram positive bacteria allowed the direct contact of the extract constituents with the phospholipid bilayer of the cell membrane, enabling the extract to inhibit bacterial growth easily. Microbial and plant extracts that have noteworthy antibacterial activities are those with MIC values less than 1&#x02009;mg/ml [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Thus, the profound activity of the extract suggests the potential use as a therapeutic agent since it demonstrated MIC values in a range of 0.098&#x02013;0.391&#x02009;mg/ml against the selected pathogens. Moreover, it is interesting to note that ciprofloxacin had higher MIC value (25&#x02009;mg/ml) against the tested strains when compared to the extract. This implied that that the bacterial strains had developed ciprofloxacin resistance and affirms the need for novel antibacterial agents. Furthermore, the extract exhibited bactericidal effect against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925) with the MBC of 25&#x02009;mg/ml.</p><p id="Par66">Compounds with scavenging activities against free radicals have gained constant attention in recent years. These compounds have potential to nullify disease progression caused by excess free radicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Since there are few studies investigating the antioxidant activity of extracts from endophytic microorganisms, the evaluation of antioxidant activity of the extract was imperial. The extract showed poor activity against DPPH radical (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and moderate activity against ABTS radical (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Molyneux, 2004 classified the antioxidant activity where the highly active compounds have IC<sub>50</sub> values &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05&#x02009;mg/ml, the active category have IC<sub>50</sub> values of 0.05&#x02013;0.1&#x02009;mg/ml, medium category have IC<sub>50</sub> values of 0.1&#x02013;0.15&#x02009;mg/ml, and weak categories have IC<sub>50</sub> values of 0.151&#x02013;0.2&#x02009;mg/ml. Thus, the results clearly show that the extract has promising ABTS scavenging activity and could be a potential source of natural antioxidant.</p><p id="Par67"><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> is known for producing a wide variety of metabolites with antimicrobial and antioxidant effects. The identified volatile compounds, xanthoxylin, trans-2-decenoic acid, [1, 2, 4] oxadiazole, 5-benzyl-(thiophen-2-yl), dodecenoic acid, 3-nonynoic, pyrrolo [1,2-a]pyrazine-1,4-dione, hexahydro-3-(2-methylpropyl), pentadecanoic acid and diisooctyl phthalate are recognised for possession of antimicrobial activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. cis-9-Octadecenoic acid, 2-dodecenoic acid and 9-octadecenamide are reported to possess antioxidant property [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. It was therefore assumed that the profound antibacterial and antioxidant activity of extract was due to synergistical activities of the identified bioactive compounds.</p></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par68">Out of 13 isolates, Isolate 1 (<italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP43328.1) produced all the tested enzymes and showed the ability to produce antimicrobials that were effective against all the tested pathogens. Its secondary metabolites demonstrated antibacterial activity with MIC values ranging from 0.098&#x02013;0.391&#x02009;mg/ml. It had bactericidal effect against <italic>S. aureus</italic> (ATCC 25925) at 25&#x02009;mg/ml. It also illustrated potent ABTS scavenging activity with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.051&#x02009;mg/ml. The extract showed a total of 15 volatile compounds with diisooctyl phthalate (50.51%) and [1, 2, 4] oxadiazole, 5-benzyl-3 (10.44%) being the major compounds. <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> CP43328.1 has a potential to serve as a source of pharmacologically important compounds. Further studies, quantitative analysis of the detected enzymes and evaluation of the mechanisms involved in antibacterial activity are imperial.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>NA</term><def><p id="Par5">nutrient agar</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MH</term><def><p id="Par6">Mueller Hinton</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFU</term><def><p id="Par7">colony forming units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TLC</term><def><p id="Par8">thin layer chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NCBI</term><def><p id="Par9">National Center for Biotechnology Information</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIC</term><def><p id="Par10">minimum inhibitory concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MBC</term><def><p id="Par11">minimum bactericidal concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATCC</term><def><p id="Par12">American Type Culture Collection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMSO</term><def><p id="Par13">dimethyl sulfoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INT</term><def><p id="Par14">piodonitrotetrazodium violet</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IC<sub>50</sub></term><def><p id="Par15">half maximal inhibitory concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ABTS</term><def><p id="Par16">2, 2&#x02032;-azinobis (3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BHA</term><def><p id="Par17">butylated hydroxyl anisole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEM</term><def><p id="Par18">meropenem</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IML</term><def><p id="Par19">imipenem</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OB</term><def><p id="Par20">cloxacillin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KF</term><def><p id="Par21">cephalothin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ETP</term><def><p id="Par22">ertapenem</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DA</term><def><p id="Par23">clindamycin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CLSI</term><def><p id="Par24">Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BLAST</term><def><p id="Par25">basic local alignment search tool</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>I would like to acknowledge our laboratory mates- Medical Microbiology Group for outstanding support throughout the course.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>The study was conceived and designed by TSM and JSES. The experiments were conducted by CIN and LSN. TSM analysed the data. TSM and JSS contributed to study design, data analysis, and revising the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the University of Zululand, and Future Planning (MSIP) National Research Foundation of South Africa (NRF) (Grant reference: HBG 181011371909). The funding bodies have no role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data in writing the manuscript, which are fully the responsibilities of the authors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par69">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par70">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par71">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Organization WH: WHO Country Cooperation Strategy 2016-2020: South Africa 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Organization WH: Antimicrobial resistance and primary health care: brief. In: World Health Organization; 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisi-Johnson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Obi</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Okoh</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity of crude extracts of some south African medicinal plants against multidrug resistant etiological agents of diarrhoea</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>321</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-017-1802-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28629407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28629407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Holmes KK, Bertozzi S, Bloom BR, Jha P, Gelband H, DeMaria LM, Horton S: Major infectious diseases: key messages from Disease Control Priorities, vol. 9: World Bank Washington, DC; 2017.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newman DJ. Are microbial endophytes the actual producers of bioactive antitumor agents. Trends Cancer. 4(10):662&#x02013;70.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophytes: a treasure house of bioactive compounds of medicinal importance</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1538</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01538</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 5041141?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27746767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophytic bacteria: A new source of bioactive compounds</article-title><source>3 Biotech</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>315</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13205-017-0942-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28955612?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28955612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buatong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Phongpaichit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rukachaisirikul</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakayaroj</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of crude extracts from mangrove fungal endophytes</article-title><source>World J Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3005</fpage><lpage>3008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-011-0765-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bundale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Begde</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nashikkar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of culture conditions for production of bioactive metabolites by Streptomyces spp. isolated from soil</article-title><source>Advances Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>06</issue><fpage>441</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/aim.2015.56045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gangwar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Narang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of endophytic actinomycetes from Syzygium cumini and their antimicrobial activity against human pathogens</article-title><source>J Applied Natural Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31018/jans.v8i1.809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Property distributions: differences between drugs, natural products, and molecules from combinatorial chemistry</article-title><source>J Chem Inf Comput Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci0200467</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12546556?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12546556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Asaf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endophytic fungus <italic>Paecilomyces formosus</italic> LHL10 produces sester-terpenoid YW3548 and cyclicpeptide that inhibit urease and &#x003b1;-glucosidase enzyme activities</article-title><source>Arch Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>200</volume><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-018-1562-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30167726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30167726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyoma</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Toghueo</surname><given-names>RMK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabalgogeazcoa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez de Aldanab</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymatic activity of endophytic fungi from the medicinal plants <italic>Terminalia catappa, Terminalia mantaly</italic> and <italic>Cananga odorata</italic></article-title><source>South Afr J Botany</source><year>2017</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2016.12.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhoonobtong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawadsitang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sodngam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongkolthanaruk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of endophytic bacteria, <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> for antimicrobial agents production</article-title><source>International Conference on Biological and Life Sciences</source><year>2012</year><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Germaine</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial endophytes: recent developments and applications</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2008</year><volume>278</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2007.00918.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18034833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garmana</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukandar</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fidrianny</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity of several plant extracts against drug- sensitive and drug-resistant microbes</article-title><source>Procedia Chemistry</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.proche.2014.12.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horng</surname><given-names>C-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>H-R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>C-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F-A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastro protective effect of madeira vine against ethanol-induced gastric mucosal lesion in rat</article-title><source>Asian J Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>765</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Qiong G, Yun-Bao M, Xue-Mei M, Rui-Rui W, Jun Z, Yong-Tang M, Ji-Jun C. One new flavanoid and anti-HIV active constituents from <italic>Boussingaultia gracilis</italic> miers var. Pseudobaselloides bailey. 2007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Astuti</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakinah</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Andayani</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Risch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of saponin compound from <italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> (ten) Steenis plant (binahong) to potential treatment for several diseases</article-title><source>J Agric Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>224</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laksmitawati</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Widyastuti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Afifah</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rihibiha</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nufus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Widowati</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory effects of <italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> and <italic>Piper crocatum</italic> extracts on lipopolysaccharide-stimulated macrophage cell line</article-title><source>Bangladesh J Pharmacol</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3329/bjp.v12i1.28714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Istyastono EP, Yuliani SH: Scarless wound healing gel with Binahong (<italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> (Ten) Steenis) leaves extract and celecoxib as the active ingredients. In: AIP Conference Proceedings: 2016: AIP Publishing; 2016: 160001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djamil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahyudi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanafi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of flavonoid from <italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> (ten) Steenis leaves</article-title><source>Int Res J Pharmacy</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>243</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lestari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukandar</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><name><surname>Fidrianny</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic> leaves extract as antihyperlipidemia and endothelial fat content reducer in male Wistar rat</article-title><source>Internation J Pharmaceutical Clin Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>439</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djamil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Winarti</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaidan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdillah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidiabetic activity of flavonoid from Binahong leaves (<italic>Anredera cordifolia</italic>) extract in alloxan induced mice</article-title><source>J Pharmacognosy Natural Products</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4172/2472-0992.1000139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanvir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajid</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasnain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of endophytic <italic>Streptomycetes</italic> isolated from <italic>Parthenium hysterophorus</italic> L. against nosocomial pathogens</article-title><source>Pakistan J Pharmaceutical Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>283</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vaidya S, Rathore P: Isolation, screening and characterization of amylase producing bacteria from soil of potato dump sites from different regions of madhya pradesh. In Conference Paper 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijayaraghavan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>GPV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for the detection of protease activity on agar plates using bromocresolgreen dye</article-title><source>J Biochem Technol</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>630</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zamani H, Salehzadeh A, Abdolhosseini M: Isolation and molecular identification of a cellulotic bacterium from muncipal waste and investigation of its cellulose production. Bioscience J 2018, 34(3). 10.14393/BJv34n3a2018-40007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for the detection of lipolytic activity of micro-organisms and some observations on the influence of the contact between cells and fatty substrates</article-title><source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source><year>1957</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02545855</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 13425509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13425509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muzzamal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarwar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajid</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasnain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation, identification and screening of endophytic bacteria antagonistic to biofilm formers</article-title><source>Pakistan J Zool</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2012</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bergey&#x02019;s of determinative bacteriology</source><year>1974</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>United States of America</publisher-name><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>563</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;ffer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.17.3389</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 146917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papich</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Performance standards for antimicrobial disk and dilution susceptibility tests for bacteria isolated from animals: clinical and laboratory standards institute</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Son</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some fungal endophytes from vegetable crops and their anti-oomycete activities against tomato late blight</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2006.02093.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17309513?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17309513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maliehe</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shandu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Basson</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Simelane</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacodynamic and cytotoxicity effects of <italic>Syzygium cordatum</italic> {S Ncik, 48 (UZ)} fruit-pulp extract in gastrointestinal tract infections</article-title><source>Trop J Pharm Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/tjpr.v16i6.19</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sensitive and quick microplate method to determine the minimal inhibitory concentration of plant extracts for bacteria</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>64</volume><issue>08</issue><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2006-957563</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9933989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9933989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand-Williams</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuvelier</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Berset</surname><given-names>CLWT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of a free radical method to evaluate antioxidant activity</article-title><source>LWT-Food Sci Technol</source><year>1995</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0023-6438(95)80008-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Re</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Proteggente</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice-Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity applying an improved ABTS radical cation decolorization assay</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9&#x02013;10</issue><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(98)00315-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10381194?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10381194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsilo</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Maliehe</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shandu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and some biological activities of the methanolic <italic>Encephalartos ferox</italic> fruit extract</article-title><source>Pharmacognosy J</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2020</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Golinska P, Wypij M, Agarkar G, Rathod D, Dahm H, Rai M. Endophytic actinobacteria of medicinal plants: diversity and bioactivity. Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek. 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangwan</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytotoxic and antimicrobial activities of endophytic fungi isolated from <italic>Bacopa monnieri</italic> (L.) Pennell (Scrophulariaceae)</article-title><source>BMC Complementary Alternative Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>52</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-14-52</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of culture independent bacteria and antimicrobial activity of culturable endophytic bacteria isolated from different Dendrobium stems</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-37186-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Quecine</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacava</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Luvizotto</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and enzyme bioprospection of endophytic bacteria associated with plants of Brazilian mangrove ecosystem</article-title><source>SpringerPlus</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>382</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2193-1801-3-382</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25110630?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25110630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Deeb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazaid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gherbawy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhariry</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of endophytic bacteria associated with rose plant (Rosa damascena trigintipeta) during flowering stage and their plant growth promoting traits</article-title><source>J Plant Interact</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17429145.2011.637161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mercado-Blanco J, JJ Lugtenberg B: Biotechnological applications of bacterial endophytes. Current Biotechnol 2014, 3(1):60&#x02013;75.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramachandran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruthupandy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manoharan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extraction and partial purification of secondary metabolites from endophytic actinomycetes of marine green algae <italic>Caulerpa racemosa</italic> against multi drug resistant uropathogens</article-title><source>Biocatalysis Agricultural Biotechnol</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcab.2019.01.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uche-Okereafor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebola</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapfuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekuto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavumengwana</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activities of crude secondary metabolite extracts from <italic>Pantoea</italic> species obtained from the stem of <italic>Solanum mauritianum</italic> and their effects on two Cancer cell lines</article-title><source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>602</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph16040602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wilson R. Free radicals and tissue damage, mechanistic evidence from radiation studies. Biochem Mechanisms Liver Injury. 1998; pp. 123&#x02013;25.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Polidori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mecocci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress in brain aging, neurodegenerative and vascular diseases: an overview</article-title><source>J Chromatogr B</source><year>2005</year><volume>827</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchromb.2005.04.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>dos Reis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>da Rosa</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>da Rosa</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>do Carmo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>LMB</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugalde</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal and antibacterial activity of extract produced from <italic>Diaporthe schini</italic></article-title><source>J Biotechnol</source><year>2019</year><volume>294</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Royal jelly acid, 10-hydroxy-trans-2-decenoic acid, as a modulator of the innate immune responses</article-title><source>Endocrine Metabolic Immune Disorders</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/187153012803832530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadi</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hameed</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical screening of methanolic dried pgalls extract of Quercus infectoria using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) and Fourier transform-infrared (FT-IR)</article-title><source>J Pharmacognosy Phototherapy</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/JPP2015.0368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antilarval-settlement potential and metabolite profiles of novel sponge-associated marine bacteria</article-title><source>J Ind Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2009</year><volume>36</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10295-009-0588-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19471982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19471982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belakhdar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjouad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdennebi</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of some bioactive chemical constituents from <italic>Thesium humile</italic> Vahl</article-title><source>J Materials Environmental Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>2778</fpage><lpage>2783</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altaee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadhim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hameed</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of volatile compounds produced by Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated from UTI patients by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Int J Toxicological Pharmacy Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leemans</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahasenan</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumarasiri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Spink</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Daniel</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional QSAR analysis and design of new 1, 2, 4-oxadiazole antibacterials</article-title><source>Bioorganic Med Chem Letters</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bmcl.2015.12.041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moniot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Forgione</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailu</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nebbioso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carafa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellicciari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of 1, 2, 4-oxadiazoles as potent and selective inhibitors of the human deacetylase sirtuin 2: structure&#x02013;activity relationship, X-ray crystal structure, and anticancer activity</article-title><source>J Medical Chemistry</source><year>2017</year><volume>60</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2344</fpage><lpage>2360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.6b01609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abou-Elela</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd-Elnaby</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Okbah</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marine natural products and their potential applications as anti-infective agents</article-title><source>World Appl Sci J</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>880</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;z&#x000e7;elik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aslan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Orhan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Karaoglu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial, antifungal, and antiviral activities of the lipophylic extracts of Pistacia vera</article-title><source>Microbiol Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>160</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2004.11.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15881833?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15881833</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>