<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Amphipterygium adstringens</italic> belongs to the Anacardaceae family, which is widely known due to its beneficial effects on circulatory problems, ulcers and gastric infections including 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>. Tea made from the tree bark is the most common form of consumption of this plant, commercialized as “Cuachalalate”. This plant contains anacardic acids, triterpenoids and sterols as major components. In a study, eight compounds were isolated from this folk plant: anacardic acid, 6-[16′Z-nonadecenyl]-salicylic acid, 6-[8′Z-pentadecenyl]-salicylic acid 6-nonadecenyl-salicylic acid, 6-pentadecyl-salicylic acid, masticadienonic acid, 3α-hydroxymasticadienonic acid, 3-epi-oleanolic acid and β-sitosterol [
 <xref rid="B183-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>]. Some of these compounds exhibited antibacterial activity, whereas the alcoholic extract of 
 <italic>A. adstringens</italic> was able to reduce colitis ulcerative in a preclinical mouse model [
 <xref rid="B184-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>] and the alcoholic extract produced gastroprotection in rats [
 <xref rid="B185-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>]. Moreover, antinociceptive properties of 
 <italic>A. adstringens</italic> have been studied in acetic acid-induced writhing; however, the extract of the plant did not reduce the nociception [
 <xref rid="B79-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Furthermore, aqueous and hexane extracts from 
 <italic>A. adstringens</italic> reduced ear and paw edemas in mice, suggesting that masticadienonic and 3
 <italic>α</italic>-hydroxymasticadienonic compounds (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00865-f001">Figure 1</xref>) produce the inhibition of nitrites as a possible mechanism of action [
 <xref rid="B186-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>]. Likewise, the anti-inflammatory potential of this plant was addressed by Arrieta et al. [
 <xref rid="B187-plants-10-00865" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>], highlighting nitric oxide inhibition, which has a fundamental role in inflammatory pain treatment. In summary, preclinical assays have demonstrated the anti-inflammatory but not the antinociceptive effect of 
 <italic>A. adstringens</italic>.
</p>
