<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At the end of the experiment, microbial profiles were examined is separate intestines, as bacteria of different genera unevenly prevail in different parts of the gut [
 <xref rid="B56-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Significant changes were detected regarding bacterial composition in the ileum. Although taxonomical composition was similar in both groups, the amounts of separate genera were unequally distributed in the intestines of experimental group. The main changes were associated with an increase of 
 <italic>Escherichia</italic> (almost three times) and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> (five times) and a decrease of 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> (59 times) in the experimental group, compared with control pigs. Both 
 <italic>Escherichia</italic> and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> are considered as probiotic bacteria [
 <xref rid="B57-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]; therefore, EOs obviously had a positive effect on the numbers of those genera; however, 
 <italic>Escherichia</italic> is also a possible pathogen and can be unwanted microorganism, depending on its pathogenicity. While virulence factors of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> were not investigated in this study, it should be taken into account that it could be investigated in forthcoming trials. Although 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> is usually found in pig GI tract in large amounts [
 <xref rid="B58-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], there is a lack of information about the importance of this genus in pigs. There are suggestions that 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> may play important roles to combat post-weaning diarrhoea and that it may contribute to nutrient transport and uptake in the pig gut ecosystem [
 <xref rid="B59-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. It is unclear, however, in which part of the GI tract 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> has the most important role, but according to the study performed previously, this bacterium is mostly distributed in the colon [
 <xref rid="B56-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. In our study, we found the highest amount of 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> present in the caecum, where it was the most predominant genus in both groups of pigs. Moreover, the amount of 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> in the caecum of experimental animals was significantly higher than in the control group; therefore, the total number of this genus in GI did not decrease in pigs fed with EEOs supplement. The species whose prevalence increased in the ileum of control animals were 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Lactobacillus amylovorus</italic>. The number of 
 <italic>L. amylovorus</italic> increased 12 times and made 17% of total bacterial count from the jejuni. This species has adhesive and significant pathogen inhibitory efficacy and is recognized as potential candidate to be used as probiotic feed supplement [
 <xref rid="B60-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Changes in the caecum content were mostly associated with an increase of 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> and 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic> and a decrease of 
 <italic>Barnesiella</italic> and 
 <italic>Denitrobacterium,</italic> compared with the control group. The amount of 
 <italic>Barnesiella,</italic> however, was more than eight times less in the experimental group and was probably replaced by 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic> and 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>. Although 
 <italic>Barnesiella</italic> has been found in many other studies investigating pig microbiome, there is still no clear information regarding its functions and significance. 
 <italic>Denitrobacterium</italic> has a single species—
 <italic>D. detoxificans,</italic> which is better known as ruminant species and its significance in porcine GI is also still under-investigated. The increased genera in the caeca of experimental pigs therefore are considered as positive or even probiotic (
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>) microbiota. The most prevalent species in the caeca of the experimental group of pigs was 
 <italic>Prevotella copri,</italic> whose prevalence was 24.3%, and that is 3.5 times higher than in the control group. The role of this species in pigs is not known yet, but 
 <italic>P. copri</italic> is a common human gut microorganism that is both positively and negatively associated with host health [
 <xref rid="B61-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The role of 
 <italic>P. copri</italic> in human health is debatable [
 <xref rid="B62-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In a recent study, De Filippis et al. have detected distinct strains of 
 <italic>P. copri</italic> by metagenome studies and showed that the diet might select distinctive 
 <italic>P. copri</italic> populations [
 <xref rid="B62-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], but there is still no data about this in pigs. The most prevalent bacterial species in the caeca in the control group was 
 <italic>Barnesiella intestinihominis,</italic> followed by 
 <italic>P. copri</italic>. 
 <italic>B. intestinihominis</italic> was also more prevalent in the colon content of experimental animals; therefore, there were no big differences in this species between the groups. 
 <italic>B. intestinihominis</italic> has been better described in humans than in pigs and has also been mentioned in a study were this species together with 
 <italic>Enterococcus hirae</italic> had a positive effect on the efficacy of cyclophosphamide used for cancer treatment in mice. The prevalence in healthy pigs of species that were previously associated with human microbiota, demonstrates the similarity between human and porcine microbiota. This fact is important as pig model can gain more knowledge about the pathogenesis of different human diseases. Variety of the rest of the species in the caecum content was similar in both groups demonstrating that EEOs did not have a selective inhibitory effect on the main species normally inhabiting the GI of pigs. Such variety similarities were also observed in other large intestines. The amount of some genera and species, however, differed significantly. In the colon, these differences were also noticeable: while in the control group the most prevalent genus was 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, in the experimental group predominated 
 <italic>Prevotella</italic>. Among streptococci the most prevalent species were 
 <italic>S. lutetiensis</italic> and 
 <italic>S. gallolyticus,</italic> whose prevalence reached almost 30%. Those species were also detected in the experimental group but only in a small amount (1.7%). It is not clear yet if these species of streptococci are widely distributed in pigs, but they are frequently encountered in blood cultures of humans with bacteremia, sepsis, and endocarditis [
 <xref rid="B63-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Recently, Piva et al. described the first case of isolation of 
 <italic>S. lutetiensis</italic> from a diseased cat [
 <xref rid="B64-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. 
 <italic>S. lutetiensis</italic> and 
 <italic>S. gallolyticus</italic> belong to the group of 
 <italic>S. bovis</italic> from which they were separated into separate species [
 <xref rid="B63-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. While 
 <italic>S. lutetiensis</italic> is well known as pathogenic species in humans, particularly in patients with reduced immunity, 
 <italic>S. gallolyticus</italic> is recognized as an inhabitant of the alimentary tract of cattle, sheep, and other ruminants [
 <xref rid="B65-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. This study revealed that both 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic> species can be abundant in the intestinal tract of pigs and proves that pigs are carriers of streptococcal species pathogenic to humans. For this reason, 
 <italic>S. gallolyticus</italic> and, particularly, 
 <italic>S. lutetiensis</italic> can be considered as zoonotic bacteria. On the other hand, this is not certain for types or strains that might differ between the hosts, thus more studies in this direction should be performed. 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>gallolyticus</italic> is known to be transmitted either directly or indirectly between animals and humans [
 <xref rid="B66-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. It is also important to note that 
 <italic>S. gallolyticus</italic> is genetically close to the other species—
 <italic>S. suis</italic>—which is known as a normal inhabitant of the oral cavity of pigs [
 <xref rid="B67-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. There are data that it is sometimes difficult to correctly identify 
 <italic>S. suis,</italic> and even molecular methods, including PCR, have a risk of misidentifying 
 <italic>S. gallolyticus</italic> as 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B68-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. As in this study 
 <italic>S. suis</italic> was detected in very low amounts, taxonomic distribution of 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic> species should be further studied for more accurate identification. The rest of the species in the colon were more equally distributed by their variety and numbers in both groups of pigs, although big differences were also observed regarding 
 <italic>Clostridium cellulovorans,</italic> which had a higher prevalence in the control group, and different species of 
 <italic>Prevotella,</italic> which were more prevalent in the experimental group. 
 <italic>C. cellulovorans</italic> is known as widely distributed bacteria, which is also found in porcine respiratory tract; however, there is no clear information about its role in pigs.
</p>
