<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par60">Ulcers are detected primarily in the stomach and the proximal duodenum [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]; these lesions are the result of a multifactorial gastrointestinal disorder that has been associated with substantial morbidity and mortality, and affects many people worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Both endogenous and exogenous stimulation can contribute to the pathogenesis of this disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], most notably the chronic use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Moreover, pro-inflammatory cytokines, including tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), interleukin-6 (IL-6), and interleukin-1 beta (IL-1β), as well as pro-apoptotic factors, are among the critical endogenous mediators that induce or aggravate GUs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Pogostone, a characterized component of patchouli oil (PO), has been confirmed as effective against the oxidative stress associated with GUs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Recent results have shown that pogostone can protect the gastrointestinal mucosa from indomethacin-associated GUs by its capacity to activate superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione (GSH), and catalase (CAT), and reduce the concentration of malondialdehyde (MDA) in rat models of disease. Levels of prostaglandin E
 <sub>2</sub> (PGE
 <sub>2</sub>) and the protein and relative mRNA expression of cyclooxygenase 1 (COX-1) and cyclooxygenase 2 (COX-2) were all remarkably elevated in pogostone pretreated rats. The administration of pogostone also resulted in increased levels of heat-shock protein 70 and Bcl-2 protein, together with the diminished expression of Bax protein in ulcerated tissue [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]; these results indicated that pogostone was capable of suppressing cellular apoptosis as part of its gastroprotective mechanism. PAO, another component that has been isolated from PO, exhibits similar pharmacological effects; pretreatment with PAO significantly limited the extent of ethanol-induced GUs in rats. The administration of PAO resulted in increased levels of GSH, SOD, and CAT activities, together with the suppression of MDA in gastric tissues. Furthermore, PAO exhibited anti-inflammatory activity as it coordinated the production of both pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokines by its capacity to regulate the expression of several NF-κB pathway-related proteins. Moreover, immunohistochemistry revealed that the mechanism underlying PAO-mediated anti-apoptosis was largely related to its capacity to inhibit the expression of caspase-3, Fas, and FasL in the stomach tissue [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. In addition to PAO, β-PAE mediates a prominent gastroprotective effect. A prominent metabolite of PA, β-PAE was significantly better than its parent compound at reducing the size of GUs in rats. Additionally, the administration of β-PAE resulted in dramatic reductions in the levels of MDA, TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6 in the serum, as well as the local expression of Fas, FasL, and caspase-3; the activities of SOD, GSH, and CAT were all increased concomitantly. The impact of β-PAE on GUs involved its interactions with both the NF-κB and ERK1/2 signaling pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].
</p>
