<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020" class="p">Various poplar (
 <italic class="italic">Populus tremula x alba</italic>) trees which are genetically modified for lignin amount and composition have been made [
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Lignin from 
 <italic class="italic">CCoAOMT</italic> downregulated trees showed an increase of 11% in the S/G ratio [
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. On the other hand, 
 <italic class="italic">COMT</italic> downregulation lead to a reduction in the S/G ratio by approximately 50% accompanied by the appearance of 5-hydroxyguaiacyl units [
 <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">CAD</italic> suppressed transgenic lines showed an increased production of benzaldehydes, vanillin, syringaldehyde and extractable lignin content due to the incorporation of cinnamaldehydes into the lignin structure [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[24]</xref>]. However, no significant change was observed in the S/G [
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Pyrolysis of wood derived from 
 <italic class="italic">COMT</italic> downregulated greenhouse-grown 
 <italic class="italic">Populus tremula x alba</italic> revealed a three-fold decrease in the pyrolysis products corresponding to syringyl (S) units while 
 <italic class="italic">CCoAOMT</italic> down-regulation lead to a decline in G-derived products by 1.6 times, as reported by Toraman et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. There have been very few studies on fast pyrolysis of using genetically engineered biomass. All the trees analyzed so far were grown either in greenhouse or in controlled environments [
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Rencoret et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] utilized fast pyrolysis as a quick technique to determine the effect of gene modification in greenhouse grown poplar [
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. They reported that overexpression of 
 <italic class="italic">F5H</italic> in poplar lead to a substantial increase in S units. Pilate et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] reported that the structural changes in lignin in field grown transgenic poplars were similar to those in greenhouse grown plants. However, in the case of 
 <italic class="italic">COMT</italic> downregulated lines, the lignin structural changes were milder due to less suppressed enzymatic activity compared to that of greenhouse grown trees [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>].
</p>
