<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Milk thistle (
 <italic class="italic">Silybum marianum</italic> (L.) Gaertn. (Asteraceae)) extract (MTE) is an important source of silymarin. It is a well-known complex of flavonolignans (silybin A and B, isosilybin A and B, silydianin, and silychristin) and flavonoids (taxifolin and quercetin) used to reduce inflammation, also having membrane-stabilizing, hepatoprotective, anticarcinogenic, and antiviral activities [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. MTE extract is noted to be able to decrease cellular peroxidation and protect skin from photo aging, as well as ultraviolet rays UVB-induced damages and carcinogenesis [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Further studies have already shown that topical application of silymarin suppresses intracellular production of hydrogen peroxide, and nitric oxide and reduces depletion of catalase in UVB-irradiated mouse skin [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Unfortunately, MTE clinical use is negatively influenced by low aqueous solubility, which limits oral and topical administration [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Moreover, the silymarin complex and its main component, silybin, which is well known for its broad spectrum of biological properties, [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], react readily with various environmental factors and undergo to oxidation/degradation process with consequent functionality decrease. The recommendations of the manufacturer to store silybin standards are to keep them at 4 °C and away from light, to avoid degradation. To overcome these limitations, we recently produced a new stable water-soluble microparticulate powder system using spray drying technology containing a silymarin-rich extract (MTE-mp) [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. MTE-loaded microparticles by spray drying were produced with high and reproducible yields and encapsulation efficiency. NaCMC, used as a coating/swelling polymer in a proper solvent system, was able to protect the functionality of the extract over time. The in vitro dissolution and permeation rates of silymarin were dramatically improved suggesting a higher bioavailability after the administration [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-01547" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Silymarin anti-inflammatory abilities were preserved by the encapsulation process, as demonstrated by immune cell exposure to MTE-mp and inflammatory cytokine suppression, which suggest that the microencapsulation process didn’t affect silymarin efficiency.
</p>
