<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The use of chemically synthetic preservative in controlling food spoilage and pathogenic fungus has been a controversial topic (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tian et al., 2014</xref>). The artificially chemical compounds are considered as chronic and reproductive toxicants causing respiratory diseases or other health risks (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fleming-Jones and Smith, 2003</xref>). In this case, natural preservatives such as essential oil (EO) have been extensively used due to its biodegradable and antimicrobial properties. EO contains a variety of substances called ‘phytochemicals’, which belong to natural components in plants (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pratt, 1992</xref>). The phytochemical preparations with dual functionalities in preventing lipid oxidation and antimicrobial properties have tremendous potential for extending shelf life of food products (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fadli et al., 2012</xref>). Generally, EO possesses high volatility. When EO is applied as a vapor, less oil is used. Further, the residues of EO on the product are minimized, and there will be less of a problem with tainting (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Szczerbanik et al., 2007</xref>). It may be more appropriate to use EO in their vapor phase for postharvest applications (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Concha et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zollo et al., 1998</xref>). Cinnamon (
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum verum</italic>), rich in EO, belongs to Lauraceae family comprising about 250 species and usually distributes in India, China, Sri Lanka, and Australia (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prasad et al., 2009</xref>). Cinnamon essential oil (CEO) is a promising food preservative for the inhibition of foodborne pathogens and spoilage microorganisms (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tian et al., 2012</xref>). Our previous studies have shown that CEO have good efficacy on preservation of ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit. Moreover, ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit fumigated with 0.4 μL/mL of CEO could be stored at (4 ± 1) °C with relative humidity of 90–95% for 120 days (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">He et al., 2015</xref>). CEO has been demonstrated as a strong and broad range of inhibition for bacteria, fungi and yeast (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chao et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manso et al., 2015</xref>). Our previous studies have demonstrated that CEO have good inhibitory effects against 
 <italic class="italic">Botryosphaeria parva in vitro</italic>, and can reduce soft rot on ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">He et al., 2015</xref>). Antifungal activity of CEO against 
 <italic class="italic">C. acutatum</italic> isolated from strawberry anthracnose was investigated (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Duduk et al., 2015</xref>). Cell plasma membrane (PM) is the action site invaded by antifungal substances, such as silicon and chlorine dioxide (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wei et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2010</xref>). For fungi, the integrity of PM plays a crucial role in maintaining cell constituents being important to viability, such as sugar, protein and nucleic acid. The soluble sugar, soluble protein and nucleic acid are the basic and functional components in the cell. The PM is damaged, and the intracellular components can be leaked (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wei et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2010</xref>). The antifungal activity of EO was strongly associated with its compositions, such as monoterpenic phenoles, especially thymol, carvacrol, and eugenol (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Barrera-Necha et al., 2008</xref>). The antifungal mechanism of EO is speculated to induce membrane disruption by their lipophilic compounds (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan, 1999</xref>). The low-molecular-weight and highly lipophilic components of EO pass easily through cell membranes and cause disruption to the fungal cell organization (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chao et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shukla et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, in this study, the dominant pathogens, which caused postharvest diseases such as anthracnose in ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit, was firstly isolated and identified. Further, the antifungal activity and the possible antifungal mechanism of CEO against 
 <italic class="italic">C. acutatum</italic> isolated from decayed ‘Hongyang’ kiwifruit were investigated.
</p>
