<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> species have been cultivated in tropical and subtropical regions in Asia, Australia, and South America for culinary as well as medicinal applications. The biological activities of 
  <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> have been attributed to the non-volatile curcuminoids as well as to volatile terpenoids. 
  <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> essential oils have demonstrated a wide variety of pharmacological properties. The objective of this work was to examine the variation in the compositions of 
  <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> rhizome essential oils. In this work, the volatile oils from 
  <italic class="italic">C. longa</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">C. zedoaria</italic> were obtained and analyzed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry. The chemical compositions of 
  <italic class="italic">C. longa</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">C. zedoaria</italic> essential oils, including those reported in the literature, were analyzed by hierarchical cluster analysis. In addition, cluster analyses of the chemical compositions of 
  <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">C. aeruginosa</italic> from the literature were also carried out. 
  <italic class="italic">Curcuma longa</italic> volatiles were dominated by α-turmerone, curlone, 
  <italic class="italic">ar</italic>-turmerone, β-sesquiphellandrene, α-zingiberene, germacrone, terpinolene, 
  <italic class="italic">ar</italic>-curcumene, and α-phellandrene and showed four distinct chemical clusters. 
  <italic class="italic">C. zedoaria</italic> rhizome oil contained 1,8-cineole, curzerenone/
  <italic class="italic">epi</italic>-curzerenone, α-copaene, camphor, β-caryophyllene, elemol, germacrone, curzerene, and β-elemene and showed two different chemical types. 
  <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> had three clearly defined clusters, and 
  <italic class="italic">C. aeruginosa</italic> had three types.
 </p>
</abstract>
