<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cultural practices that enhance crop health include the selection of plant species and varieties that are resistant to prevalent pests, weeds, and diseases. Plant resistance has been an effective insect pest management tool since its inception in the early part of the last century, but only against a limited number of pests in any given system [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The problem for organic growers is that the development of new insect pest resistant plant varieties will lag behind those used in non-organic systems. Organic production explicitly forbids the use of transgenic crops, which are developed more rapidly than resistant varieties from traditional breeding programs [
 <xref rid="B18-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and this is viewed as one of the constraints contributing to a limited organic grower pest management toolbox. In some cases, growers do have the opportunity to conduct their own self selection of land races for crops that show promise in resisting pests [
 <xref rid="B20-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The benefit to this approach is that it meets the NOP mandate of selecting varieties with suitability to site-specific conditions. The downside is not all crops or varieties lend themselves to being propagated so easily or growers do not have the facilities to conduct such an activity. Such tactics do not take into account the diversity of cropping systems that are organically certified or the size of such operations [
 <xref rid="B23-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Large-scale growers depend on nurseries or seed companies for source material and are often mono-cropped due to economy of scale [
 <xref rid="B24-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-insects-12-00140" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]—thus, landrace selection is impractical, if not impossible. However, for some growers, educational programs can provide a better understanding of the concept of landraces and how to select and propagate resistant crop plants.
</p>
