<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study is one of the few that have characterized the plant community that recolonized sites following 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> eradication [
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Consistent with those studies, we found that, rather than recovering to a similar native plant community found elsewhere in the marsh, the sites shifted to a completely different suite of species. The results of our vegetation surveys were consistent with surveys of 1.0 m
 <sup>2</sup> plots conducted by the Nature Conservancy at the same marsh locations [
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In this case, the new community was characterized primarily by the presence of 
 <italic>Leersia oryzoides</italic> and 
 <italic>Polygonum arifolium</italic>, rather than 
 <italic>Typha</italic>-dominated marshes that are typical of emergent wetlands in the Hudson River (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Notably, many of these species are commonly found in the understory of 
 <italic>Typha</italic>-dominated marshes in the Hudson River, and may represent an early stage in the succession of a disturbed tidal marsh community in this system [
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. This new community attained only 1/4 of the peak biomass of a 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic>-dominated plant community and contained less than half the nitrogen content of a mature 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> leaf (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g004">Fig 4A and 4B</xref>). Overall, the capacity of this community to store nitrogen in aboveground tissue is severely reduced relative to both 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic>- and 
 <italic>Typha</italic>-dominated communities (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g004">Fig 4</xref>). The net effect of species succession in this case could serve to increase the amount of time needed for a site to recover nitrogen-removal capacity following invasive species removal. Though we did not measure belowground traits of the plant communities, the lag in recovery of denitrification potential (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g007">Fig 7</xref>) suggests that plant communities may also differ in their belowground effects on microbial processes. In order to fully understand impacts of plant-community alterations on ecosystem processes, belowground measurements should be given greater attention in future studies.
</p>
