<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Overall, 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic>-dominated plant communities assimilate more nitrogen in aboveground biomass (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g003">Fig 3</xref>) and store more nitrogen in organic form in sediments (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g004">Fig 4</xref>) than native plant communities. Further, the removal of 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> resulted in significant increases in dissolved inorganic nitrogen pools (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g006">Fig 6</xref>) and significant decreases in the potential of the microbial community to permanently remove nitrogen to the atmosphere via denitrification (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0149813.g007">Fig 7</xref>). Together, these results suggest a management trade-off between eradicating 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> to restore a diverse native plant community and promoting nitrogen-removal ecosystem services in the wetland. Certainly, management actions such as seasonal timing of treatment or immediate replanting of native plants could help ameliorate these impacts, but follow-up herbicide treatments are always required, and some degree of disturbance is likely to be inevitable [
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In light of this trade-off in management priorities, the question then becomes: When and where is 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> eradication likely to significantly impact local water quality? For small, isolated patches of 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> in a system like the Hudson, which is relatively hydrologically open and well flushed by periodic tidal inundation, the impact on water quality is likely to be quite small relative to the benefit of restoring native diversity and improving habitat conditions for wildlife. However, for systems in which 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> has become the major plant community in the landscape, complete eradication is not only unlikely [
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] but may result in water quality problems that outweigh the benefits of biodiversity restoration, particularly for aquatic systems where water sources are smaller or hydrologically isolated. Invasive-species management highlights the need to develop specific management priorities for ecosystems. Frameworks are continually being developed that seek to simultaneously optimize multiple ecosystem services, with the understanding that management priorities may in some cases conflict [
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0149813.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
