<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mixed litter resulted in fewer emerged seedlings than in grass litter, but more emerged seedlings compared to ragwort litter, which suggests that the effects of grass and ragwort litter simply added up to a neutral effect. This supports the mass-ratio hypothesis by Grime [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] for the factors seedling number, biomass per plant and mean leaf number, i.e. mixed litter effects did not deviate positively nor negatively from the expected combined effects. However, for biomass per pot and plant height, effects in mixed litter were higher than could be assumed from the simple addition of grass and ragwort. Thus, ragwort growth profited in single aspects from mixed litter layers. Thus, from a management point of view, leaving litter on ragwort infested sites does slightly facilitate ragwort growth when biomass of ragwort and grass is balanced. However, if ragwort is dominating the standing biomass, germination of its seedlings might indeed be limited. When litter cover is too high, the soil is shaded and seedling emergence gets lower. Accordingly, compared to the control treatment, seedling emergence was lowest from beneath 400 g of litter and not reduced from beneath 200 g of litter cover. The reduced seedling emergence of ragwort from beneath 400 g of litter is very likely linked to the relatively small seed mass of ragwort (0.22 mg; [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]). The smaller the seeds are, the less resources a seed can spend to successfully penetrate through a litter cover [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In addition, small seeded species, like ragwort, tend to depend on higher light levels for germination than large seeded species [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Since photosynthetic active radiation (PAR) decreases with increasing litter cover [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] not only will germination be lower, but germinated seedlings will also lack light resources for successful penetration of the litter cover. This is also in accordance with van der Meijden and van der Waals-Kooi [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], who found that emergence in ragwort significantly decreased when seeds were placed beneath a sand cover of more than 4 mm. Furthermore, Facelli et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] showed that ruderal species, such as ragwort, tend to be more sensitive and thus more likely to be negatively affected by high amounts of litter. Therefore, ragwort seedlings might be reduced by a mulching regime on productive sites where litter amounts are medium to high.
</p>
