<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to the findings for seedling emergence, seedlings in ragwort litter built up more biomass, grew higher and tended to have more leaves than seedlings in grass litter. Biomass and height are the two variables where we found a significant interaction between litter type and litter amount. This could be explained by a reduction in competition for the few seedlings that emerged in ragwort litter. The interaction was quantitative and weak compared with the effects of litter type and amount alone (
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Seedlings emerging from beneath high amounts of litter and/or ragwort litter built up the highest biomass and got tallest. This is also diametrical to the findings of van de Voorde et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], who reported lower biomass for seedlings in ragwort influenced environments. These conflicting results could be due to different methodology. While van de Voorde et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] harvested seedling biomass after 19 days, seedlings in our study were harvested about 50 days later. While van de Voorde’s results were supported by our early observations (seedlings looked smaller and thinner early during early development in ragwort litter), seedlings started to grow bigger after ragwort litter had decomposed. Thus, the longer duration of our experiment compared to the experiment by van de Voorde et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] allowed us to observe a change in the importance of litter effects in relation to intraspecific density dependent competitive effects [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], which is further supported by the fact that lower seedling numbers from beneath grass litter resulted in seedlings of higher biomass and height. Loydi et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] already identified, that while litter plays a major role for seedling emergence, for instance, via phytotoxins, competition is more important for seedling development later during seedling growth. Significantly increased mean leaf numbers in seedlings in high litter amounts and in ragwort litter compared to plants in grass or mixed litter might be linked to lower intraspecific competition as there were fewer seedling numbers in the ragwort pots or by less physical hampering compared to grass litter [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. However, indirect positive effects of reduced seedling emergence in boosting seedling biomass could be especially pronounced in situations where, as in the present experiment, intraspecific competition prevails and may overlay different environmental constrains under field conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].
</p>
