<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ultrasound-assisted extraction (UAE) is a widely used method that serves as an excellent physicochemical condition for the treatment of raw materials [
 <xref rid="B142-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. By means of ultrasound, the extraction procedure can be boosted by intensifying the transfer of heat mass between the solvent and plant matrix [
 <xref rid="B143-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Such a technique is being advanced due to its ability to enhance the quality and environmental health of the extraction procedure [
 <xref rid="B134-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. UAE is an alternative method that has the potential to reinforce industries such as wood processing [
 <xref rid="B144-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>] and natural product extraction [
 <xref rid="B145-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Furthermore, UAE shows many advantages including selectivity, low energy consumption, high yield quality, lessened hazardous compounds, and high automation level [
 <xref rid="B146-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. The application of UAE has been discussed by many studies. For instance, Rodrigues and Pinto [
 <xref rid="B147-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>] employed UAE to extract phenolic compounds from coconut. Goula [
 <xref rid="B148-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>] extracted seed oil of pomegranate. Alissandrakis et al. [
 <xref rid="B149-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>] extracted volatile compounds from the flowers and honey of citrus. Gullon et al. [
 <xref rid="B63-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] proved that UAE is an ecofriendly and inexpensive method for the extraction of antioxidant phenols from 
 <italic>E. globulus</italic> leaves. Meanwhile, Xu et al. [
 <xref rid="B150-plants-10-00929" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>] found that there is a great potential to use UAE in the process of hemicellulose separation from 
 <italic>E. grandis</italic>.
</p>
