<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-medicines-04-00031" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Chemical Composition of the Essential Oil from Z. monogynum Leaves </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hydrodistillation of the 185.0 g of leaves resulted in 1.1 g of essential oil. Analysis by gas chromatography with flame ionization detector (GC/FID) and chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry (GC/MS) and calculation of Kovats indexes and comparison with the literature data [
  <a rid="B18-medicines-04-00031" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-medicines-04-00031">18</a>] allowed for the identification of 18 compounds (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00031-t002" href="#medicines-04-00031-t002">Table 2</a>), which represents 99.06% of the oil. The major compound is citronellol (43.03%), a monoterpenoid that is followed by the sesquiterpenoid farnesol (31.96%). Another monoterpenoid, citronellal (9.57%), was identified followed by D-germacrene (4.52%), β-pinene (2.02%), δ-elemene (1.38%), and (Z)-β-farnesene (1.20%). Together, these seven compounds correspond to 93.68% of the oil composition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the study performed by Maia and Andrade in 2007 [
  <a rid="B17-medicines-04-00031" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-medicines-04-00031">17</a>] with the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Z. monogynum,</span> from different regions, the composition of each of them is described: In one of the major compounds was the oils citronellal (57.1%), limonene (13.8%), citronellyl acetate (13.1%), and citronellol (6.2%). In the other, the main compounds were 2-undecanone (70.2%) and citronellal (22.5%). It is believed that this difference in composition might be related to the use of leaves from two chemotypes of 
  <span class="italic">Zanthoxylum monogynum</span>. Additionally, some factors can affect this difference in composition such as geographical locations, environment, and stage of maturity [
  <a rid="B21-medicines-04-00031" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-medicines-04-00031">21</a>]. 
 </p>
</sec>
