<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fresh leaves of 
 <italic>A. ursinum</italic> were quickly homogenized in liquid nitrogen using mortar and pestle. (Oxoid, Hampshire, United Kingdom) medium, were harvested by centrifugation (4500 × 
 <italic>g</italic>, 10 min) and washed in 0.85% saline. Aliquots of 
 <italic>A. ursinum</italic> powder (2 g) or bacterial pellets, obtained from 10 ml of overnight 
 <italic>L. fermentum</italic> BGSR163 and 
 <italic>L. fermentum</italic> BGSR227 cultures in MRS were placed in 50 ml conical tubes and mixed with 3 g of infant formula (Juvitana, Swisslion Product d.o.o. Indjija, Serbia) which contained 3% of protein, 10% of carbohydrate and 1% of fat according to manufacturer’s specifications. The formula was prepared from boiled turkey meat, boiled potato and corn paste, rice flour, and water. Control was prepared by mixing 2 ml of distilled water with 3 g of infant formula. Obtained mixtures were subjected to standardized static 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> digestion according to the method of 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Minekus et al. (2014)</xref>. Oral phase of simulated digestion was started by addition of 5 g of previously obtained mixture to 3.5 ml of simulated salivary fluid (SSF), 0.5 ml of salivary α-amylase solution (1500 U/ml), 25 μl of 0.3 M CaCl
 <sub>2</sub> and 975 μl of water, shaken vigorously and incubated 2 min at 37°C. In the following gastric phase, 10 ml of previously treated oral bolus was mixed with 7.5 ml of simulated gastric fluid (SGF), 1.6 ml of pepsin solution (25000 U/ml), prepared in SGF, 5 μl of 0.3 M CaCl
 <sub>2</sub> and pH was adjusted to 3.0 using 1M HCl. The mixture was supplemented with distilled water to achieve volume of 20 ml. Obtained mixture was incubated at 37°C for 2 h, using orbital shaker at 300 rpm. For the final intestinal phase 20 mL of obtained gastric chyme was mixed with 11 ml of simulated intestinal fluid (SIF), 5 ml of pancreatin solution 800 U/ml (trypsin activity) prepared in SIF, 2,5 ml of 160 mM bile salt solution and 40 μl of 0.3 M CaCl
 <sub>2</sub>. The pH value of 7.0 was adjusted using 1M NaOH and the mixture was supplemented with distilled water to reach final volume of 40 ml. Additional incubation was performed with constant shaking at 300 rpm during 2h at 37°C. After completed digestion samples were centrifuged at 4500 × 
 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min at 4°C, supernatants were kept and their volume was accurately measured, then immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and kept for further experiments at −80°C. Composition of SSF, SGF and SIF electrolyte solutions was presented in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The results of 
 <italic>L. fermentum</italic> BGSR163 and 
 <italic>L. fermentum</italic> BGSR227 survival after 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> digestion were expressed as Log CFU (Colony forming units)/ml and the survival rate was calculated from the viable cell count with respect to initial cell counts. The aliquots were taken at 0, 10, 120, and 220 min of the simulated digestion. The 10 times serial dilutions were prepared in 0.85% saline and plated on MRS agar plates and incubated anaerobically at 37°C for 48 h. The experiments were performed in triplicates.
</p>
