<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Illicium verum</italic> Hook. f. (
 <italic>I. verum</italic>) is a famous medicinal plant since the ancient times and known as “drug homologous food” in China. 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> possesses abundant active ingredients, including flavonoids, organic acids, and terpenoids, which endow 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> with numerous biological activities, including anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, antiviral, and anticancer effects; these activities are usually associated with low toxicity, making 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> a promising medicinal plant source of therapeutic drugs (
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Ebani et al., 2018</xref>). For example, essential oils isolated from 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> could fight against herpes simplex virus (HSV) type 2 with inhibitory concentrations (IC50) at 0.016% (
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Koch et al., 2008</xref>). 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> sesquiterpenes showed antiviral effects against hepatitis B virus (
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2015</xref>) and HIV (
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Song et al., 2007</xref>). In a previous study, some 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> extracts were isolated and used to treat SGIV infection 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. The 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> active ingredients quercetin, shikimic acid, trans-anethole, and 3,4-dihydroxybenzoic acid have dose-dependent antiviral activities against SGIV infection. Furthermore, quercetin (50 μg/ml) has the greatest antiviral activity, with percent inhibition of 99.83%, making it a potential candidate for developing effective drugs for controlling SGIV infection (
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020a</xref>). In this study, to address the urgent need for therapeutic agents against SGIV in aquaculture, the effects of 
 <italic>I. verum</italic> ingredient quercetin against SGIV infection were assessed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. The possible antiviral mechanisms of quercetin were analyzed.
</p>
