<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main goal of modern dentistry is to maintain the function of the masticatory system throughout one's life. This goal is hard to achieve without endodontic therapy in most patients.[
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>] 
  <span class="italic">Enterococci</span> are responsible for most of the primary infections of the root canal system. They have been isolated from many treated root canals with chronic apical periodontitis and failed root canal treatment.[
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">2</a>] These bacteria are capable of invading the dentinal tubules. They can tolerate different ecological conditions, well adapt to unfavorable intracanal environment, and are multidrug resistant. 
  <span class="italic">Enterococci</span> are highly sensitive to sodium hypochlorite and also chlorhexidine (CHX). However, their sensitivity decreases with a reduction in the concentration of these antimicrobial agents.[
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">3</a>] Since inadequate cleaning and shaping as well as debris pushed into the root canal are among the factors responsible for root canal treatment failure, different irrigating solutions are used for cleaning and disinfection of the root canal system.[
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>] Irrigating solutions must have low cytotoxicity and surface tension, adequate flow, and sustained antimicrobial activity. Moreover, they must be easily accessible and affordable and have a pleasant odor. An irrigating solution with high antimicrobial activity and insignificant adverse effects is obviously preferred.[
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to extensive antimicrobial activity, CHX has several applications in dentistry, and due to strong antimicrobial activity, relatively long substantivity, and lack of toxicity, CHX is considered a favorable irrigating solution for root canals. However, its frequent use results in dental stains, burning sensation of the mucosa, xerostomia, gingival desquamation, impaired taste, and adverse systemic complications if swallowed accidentally.[
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>] Since there are numerous side effects of chemical agents and emerging resistance of bacteria to these agents, researchers have been in search of herbal products with antimicrobial, antifungal, and anticancer properties since herbal medications often have minimal side effects and are affordable. However, studies on the properties of organic compounds for dental applications are not many. Four medicinal plants harvested in Iran with significant antibacterial properties, which have been traditionally used for the treatment of oral and dental conditions, are evaluated in this study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Prangos ferulacea</span> (PF) is native to Iran and possesses significant pharmaceutical, nutritional, and antioxidant properties. Strong antibacterial properties of this plant against several Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria have been previously confirmed.[
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>] 
  <span class="italic">Ziziphora tenuior</span> (ZT) grows on mountain slopes.[
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>] The extract of some species of this plant such as 
  <span class="italic">Ziziphora clinopodioides</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Ziziphora persica</span> is capable of preventing the growth of a wide range of Gram-positive and Gram-negative pathogenic microorganisms.[
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>] 
  <span class="italic">Ferula gummosa</span> (FG) has extensive antibacterial properties as well.[
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>] Essential oil of the seeds of this plant has strong antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive bacteria such as 
  <span class="italic">Enterococcus faecalis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>.[
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>] 
  <span class="italic">Dracocephalum moldavica</span> (DM) has a wide spectrum of antimicrobial activity against pathogens such as 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus mutans, Micrococcus luteus, S. aureus, Candida albicans, Escherichia coli</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</span>.[
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">16</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To the best of authors' knowledge, no previous study has evaluated the antibacterial activity of the aforementioned four medicinal plants against oral and dental pathogens. Thus, this study aimed to compare the antibacterial effects of PF, ZT, FG, and DM essential oils in comparison with CHX on 
  <span class="italic">E. faecalis</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
