<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">The artificial aging test optimized contributes to the understanding of invasive seed thermosensitivity that may be used to design soil seed bank eradication treatments. In this way, soil solarization is a non-chemical environmentally-friendly agricultural method for soil disinfestation. Using transparent polyethylene sheets, the temperature of the soil at a depth of 0–20 cm usually reaches 40–60 °C, leading to the eradication of pathogens, arthropod pests, and weeds. This soil treatment has been already tested to manage invasive seed banks and lead to significantly reduced viability of buried 
 <italic>Acacia</italic> seeds, including the invasive species 
 <italic>A. saligna</italic>, 
 <italic>A. murrayana</italic> and 
 <italic>A. sclerosperma</italic>, by exposing seeds to lethal hydrothermal conditions, constituting an effective method to reduce the persistent invasive seed bank of those species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Considering the 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> seeds’ thermic sensitivity described here and the fact that a 77.6% of this species’ soil seed bank is mainly found in the species’ litter and the first 0-5 soil cm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], soil solarization may constitute a promising tool for invaded soil seed bank eradication. Just 24 h at 60 °C and 87% RH may be enough to obtain a complete viability loss in 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> seeds. Midday soil surface temperatures in the range 50–80 °C have been reported in environments ranging from tropical forests to deserts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], and 60 °C may be easily obtained under polyethylene sheets with air temperature reaches 30 °C [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However, further research is needed to determine the effectivity of a soil solarization treatment under natural soil moisture conditions and the effect of thermal cycles versus the sustained temperatures explored here.
</p>
