<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Later, with the help of affinity magnetic bead technique and recognized a protein of mitochondrial outer membrane, Furukawa et al. [
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] explored the molecular progression by which precocene II tended to inhibit trichothecene fabrication in 
 <italic>F. graminearum</italic>, with the voltage-dependent anion channel (VDAC) as the precocene II-interacting protein. Precocene II escalated the mitochondrial proteins (oxidized) concentration and superoxide level in mitochondria, which led to the discontinuation of trichothecene production in the key causal agent of 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> head blight and trichothecene contamination in grains. Subsequently, several other researchers also buoyed the influence of precocene II in disturbing the cell structure and mitochondria of fungi, proving it to be a progressive antifungal agent. Thati et al. [
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>] studied the mechanism by which some silver-coumarin complexes exhibited their antifungal potential against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, a pathogenic strain. Results demonstrated a disruption of respiratory function and depletion of the ergosterol content of the fungal cell, which resulted in a deformed plasma membrane because membrane integrity and membrane fluidity are regulated by ergosterol in fungal cells. This sequence of processes enhanced the trans-membrane seepage of the amino acids, leading finally to apoptosis. These upshots were further supported by the findings of Widodo et al. [
 <xref rid="B102-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>], who performed scanning electron microscope (SEM) and transmission electron microscope (TEM) analysis to study the influence of coumarin on 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> that was isolated from 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic>. This exploration confirmed that the compound damaged fungal cells by pores development in the cell wall, allowing the escape and necrosis of cytoplasmic content, leading to death. Remarkably, the anti-candida mechanism reported for coumarin was different from other antifungal extracts obtained from medicinal plants such as 
 <italic>Swietenia mahogany</italic> and 
 <italic>Barleria grandiflora</italic> [
 <xref rid="B117-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>].
</p>
