<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The relative importance of medicinal ginger taxa were calculated using the modified Cultural Importance Index (CI), the original version [
 <xref rid="B51-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] of which is calculated as:
 <disp-formula id="FD1-plants-09-00906">
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>CI</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mi>UR</mi>
     <mo>/</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="normal">N</mi>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where UR is the total number of use reports for a species, and N is the total number of informants in the interview. As all the references used in this analysis used ethnobotanical methods in their studies, they specified the methods for collecting data very well, including locations, seasons, samplings and interviewing methods. Most of the studies used semi-structured interviews to collect data, while some of them used opened or structured interviews. As all these kinds of interviewing methods yield similar data for the uses of a single plant species, each use of a species from a reference refers to a single use report (UR) in this study. When using meta-data for analysis, it is difficult to connect a single use report to a single informant possessing the knowledge. We combined knowledge from all informants living in the same villages into one dataset. We use the term “pseudoinformant” to replace an individual person, “informant”, with a village from which the information is derived. This term is the same as the one we use in our previous study [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Hence, the CI values shown in this study were calculated from the following equation: 
 <disp-formula id="FD2-plants-09-00906">
  <math id="mm2">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>CI</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mi>UR</mi>
     <mo>/</mo>
     <msub>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">N</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mi>ps</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where N
 <sub>ps</sub> is the number of pseudoinformants or the number of studied villages. A high CI value indicates that the plant is commonly known among pseudoinformants, i.e., among the study villages. On the other hand, CI values close to zero (0) show that the plant is rarely used.
</p>
