<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Heteronuclear Ru(II)(
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene) complexes, containing ferrocenyl (
 <bold>40a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>) and 3,4-dichlorophenyl (
 <bold>41a</bold>–
 <bold>c</bold>) bioisosteric units, based on an 
 <italic>N</italic>-terminated organosilane TSC backbone, have also been reported (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f010">Figure 10</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The appeal of ruthenium-based TSC complexes (
 <bold>42</bold>–
 <bold>43</bold>), as promising antiplasmodial agents, has been previously established by Adams et al. against CQS NF54 and CQR Dd2 strains of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Within this study, the chloro-aryl thiosemicarbazones (
 <bold>42a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>) emerged as the most potent in the series [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In other studies, an organosilane moiety was incorporated into the lateral alkyl side chain of chloroquine- and ferroquine-derived ruthenium complexes, leading to the attainment of highly potent antimalarial agents (
 <bold>44</bold>–
 <bold>45</bold>), active in the low nanomolar range, targeting the malarial hemozoin pathway [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Organosilane moieties are famous for their exceptional lipophilic properties and have been incorporated into privileged drug scaffolds, to augment their biological activities and impart new therapeutic benefits [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. This has been successfully applied in drug discovery to increase the cell permeability of drug molecules and, consequently, their tissue penetrating ability and thus bioavailability [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. It should also be noted that all the silicon-containing aminoquinoline complexes (
 <bold>44</bold>) displayed lower resistance indices than CQ, with complexes 
 <bold>44d</bold> and 
 <bold>44e</bold> showing activity greater than CQ against the Dd2 strain of the parasite 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Furthermore, all of the ferroquine-derived counterparts (
 <bold>45a</bold>–
 <bold>c</bold>) were shown to be approximately 2.5-fold more potent than CQ against the Dd2 strain, and up to 8.5-fold more potent than ferroquine against the NF54 strain [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. These observations were an unequivocal indication that the presence of the terminally appended organosilane motif had a significant impact on the antiplasmodial activity.
</p>
