<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Dendrobium</italic> is the second largest genus of the family Orchidaceae in Nepal. Thirty 
 <italic>Dendrobium</italic> species are found in Nepal, distributed across the tropical, subtropical, and temperate climatic regions [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. 
 <italic>Dendrobium chryseum</italic> is an epiphytic herb found throughout the western and eastern Himalayas at elevations from 1000 to 2150 m. It is popularly used in traditional and folk Chinese medicine for its antipyretic, eye benefiting, and immunomodulatory effects. Yang et al. reported the presence of particular compounds such as bibenzyl-phenanthrene and coumarin derivatives in 
 <italic>D. chryseum</italic>. While the chemical compound isolated from the stem of 
 <italic>D. chryseum</italic> exhibited antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], polysaccharides from the 
 <italic>D. aurantiacum</italic> var denneanum (
 <italic>D. chryseum</italic> non Rolfe.) possess tumor-inhibitory and blood glucose-reducing effects 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
 <italic>D. chryseum</italic> Rolfe demonstrated antioxidant properties and an antidiabetic indication in various studies [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Its wild resource has been depleted by overexploitation to meet the demand in traditional medicine and the floriculture industry due to its beautiful flowers. Germination of its seeds in nature is very low since seed germination depends on a symbiotic relationship between the seeds and a special mycorrhizal fungus [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Recent decades have seen a sharp increase in the role of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> techniques in plant conservation efforts designed to counter the rapid decline in the world's biodiversity [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Indeed, 
 <italic>ex situ</italic> cultivation is one of the key elements in modern conservation strategies adopted to address the threats of increasing urbanization, population growth, and industrialization [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> techniques are highly useful for providing sustainable sources of optimal plant-derived natural products [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
