<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because the reported differences in the antimicrobial activity of TTO could relate to the specific composition of the volatile compounds in the TTO, one of the strengths of this report was the combination of the chemical analysis of TTO components together with the evaluation of its antimicrobial activity both in liquid and VP. In particular, it has been reported that the antimicrobial activity of TTO is attributed mainly to terpinen-4-ol, which is the major component of the oil [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-23-02584" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] and exhibits a favorable hydrophobic/hydrophilic profile [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-23-02584" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Several studies on terpinen-4-ol have shown it to be a bactericidal agent. Ferrini et al. [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-23-02584" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>] reported its activity against strains resistant to mupirocin, fusidic acid, vancomycin, methicillin, and linezolid. In their article the terpinen-4-ol antistaphylococcal potency was found even higher than that of some antibiotics. In a different report the antimicrobial potency of some TTO chemical components was performed, including the terpinen-4-ol, by using disc diffusion and broth microdilution methods [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-02584" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Terpinen-4-ol compared to the other components was found active against all tested microorganisms including 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. In the present study, the direct comparison of the two analyses (liquid and VP) indicated a marked increase in the percentage of α-pinene and a marked reduction in terpinen-4-ol percentage in the VP compared to that observed in the liquid phase. This difference could be responsible for the higher biological effects of liquid TTO, especially against Gram-positive bacteria. In addition, it is of note that the greatest effects were observed with eucalyptol, a component often considered to have marginal antimicrobial activity. Even in the present study, we confirmed that eucalyptol was highly represented in liquid as well as in VP, raising the possibility that even if eucalyptol may not be one of the primary antimicrobial components, it might contribute to the permeabilization of bacterial membranes and thus facilitate the entry of other and more active components [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-23-02584" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. 
</p>
