<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All referral procedures updated the SmPC with the latest scientific knowledge available at the time of referral on the use of antibiotics for specific population such as children. Not only is it important to select the appropriate antibiotic when treating children, but also to administer the correct dose, taking into account potential differences in pharmacokinetics [
 <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Adjustment of dosage for paediatric patients was found in the majority of referral procedures. The European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (EUCAST) recommends updates on dosing recommendations every year, often increasing the doses [
 <xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Our current study shows that the vast majority of antibiotics had divergent SmPC at the national level. The overall outcome of regulatory actions ensures that these antibiotics which have been on the market for several decades, continue to be relevant antimicrobial medicines. The harmonisation of information available to EU healthcare professionals and citizens is an important step in ensuring an appropriate use of antibiotics and at the same time addressing AMR. The SmPCs provide up-to-date scientific knowledge that should encourage rational and sustainable use of antibiotics. Whether clinical practice will adopt and implement the new updated evidence-based product information and enforce these recommendations in daily clinical practice remains to be evaluated. Restriction of use or posology adjustment may also have yet unforeseen consequences to clinical practice. The impact of post-referral prescribing trends for various medicines has been assessed in a study on the impact of the EU label changes for systemic diclofenac after referral procedure [
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. We acknowledge that the impact of referral procedures is likely to differ between primary and secondary care. Our future research will aim to look closer at the impact of the regulatory changes described here on antimicrobial clinical practice.
</p>
