<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As previously reported, the conformations of C6a and C6b were studied in mixed zwitterionic DPC/SDS (90:10 M/M) micelles. Consistent with the observation of a high number of NOE effects in 2D NOESY spectra, the two peptides assume non-
 <italic class="italic">random coil</italic> but well-structured conformation in the micelle solution. This may be explained considering that they are confined to the surface of micelles and have limited conformational freedom. Analysis of the backbone dihedral angles reveals that C6a adopts regular 
 <italic class="italic">β-turn</italic> structures involving the residues 
 <sup class="sup">773</sup>WVGW
 <sup class="sup">776</sup> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0204042.s004" class="xref">S4 Table</xref>), while C6b assumes folded, but non-canonical, secondary structures. According to the amino acid sequences, we can infer that in C6a, the 
 <sup class="sup">774</sup>VG
 <sup class="sup">775</sup> residues act as a flexible linker between 
 <sup class="sup">773</sup>W and 
 <sup class="sup">776</sup>W, favouring a regular 
 <italic class="italic">β-turn</italic> conformation. In C6b, 
 <sup class="sup">771</sup>ED
 <sup class="sup">772</sup> forms a more rigid linker between 
 <sup class="sup">770</sup>W and 
 <sup class="sup">773</sup>W, preventing the formation of regular secondary structures. Analysis of the most representative C6a and C6b NMR structures evidence that C6a is characterised by an elongated molecular shape, with the indolyl rings of 
 <sup class="sup">773</sup>W and 
 <sup class="sup">776</sup>W in a nearly parallel orientation (the planes that run through the 
 <sup class="sup">773</sup>W and 
 <sup class="sup">776</sup>W are at an angle of angle of 13.64°). These generate a hydrophobic molecular surface (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0204042.g006" class="xref">Fig 6</xref>), calculated for 220.5 Å
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. The negatively charged 
 <sup class="sup">772</sup>D side chain flanks the 
 <sup class="sup">773</sup>W indolyl ring directly in this molecular area. Contrarily to C6a, C6b has a globular shape, and the planes that run through the 
 <sup class="sup">770</sup>W and 
 <sup class="sup">773</sup>W indolyl rings are at an angle of 62°. The 220.5 Å
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> molecular surface generated by these residues is smaller as compared to C6a. The negatively charged side chains of 
 <sup class="sup">771</sup>E and 
 <sup class="sup">772</sup>D are on the opposite side with respect to the tryptophan indolyl rings (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0204042.g006" class="xref">Fig 6</xref>).
</p>
