<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As a consequence of these changes, problems of nutritional insufficiencies are not restricted to the developing world. Currently, just 17 plant species are consumed as 90 % of the global human diet, meaning that many diets, in both developing and developed countries, lack adequate vitamins, micro-nutrients and health-promoting phytonutrients. The strength and pervasiveness of fast-food industries in developed countries, the relative weakness of their horticultural sectors, the increasing cost of fruit and vegetables relative to convenience foods and the addictive nature of soft, palatable diets (
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gearhardt 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2009
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) have all contributed to a general decline in the nutritional value of diets worldwide, and a paucity of fruit and vegetables in modern, Western diets. Following the financial crisis, there has been rising food insecurity in European and North American countries which has brought with it additional nutritional insecurity (
 <xref rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Seligman and Schillinger, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Loopstra 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2015
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>) People without enough money to buy food reduce the variety of foods in their diet and concentrate on a few low-cost, energy-dense, but nutritionally poor foods including those with added refined carbohydrates, sugars and fats which are cheaper than nutritionally rich fruits, vegetables and dairy products. These dietary shifts have had profound effects on the incidence and management of obesity, hypertension, diabetes, and other diet-sensitive chronic diseases (
 <xref rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Seligman and Schillinger, 2010</xref>). Nutritional insecurity is now a global problem, and underpins much of the increase in chronic disease, world-wide. Yet measures to address these issues are based, almost exclusively, on expensive public information campaigns that recognize the importance of fruit and vegetables in the diet, but which ultimately have little impact on dietary patterns or behaviours (
 <xref rid="CIT0076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rekhy and McConchie, 2014</xref>). Towards this end, nutrition security has been linked to food security in the UN’s Sustainable Development Goals – Goal 2: end hunger, achieve food security and improved nutrition, and promote sustainable agriculture (
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Griggs 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> 2013
 </xref>).
</p>
