<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Essential oils (EOs) have gained increasing interest as a low-toxic, eco-friendly alternative to synthetic repellents and insecticides against insect pests. However, they have scarce practical application in the protection of stored grain because of their limited efficacy and their interference with the organoleptic properties of the grain. In this study, we evaluated the olfactory profile of the EOs of 
  <italic class="italic">Foeniculum vulgare</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Pistacia lentiscus</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Ocimum basilicum,</italic> and their toxicity against the main stored grain pest 
  <italic class="italic">Sitophilus granarius</italic>. Trained assessors identified 
  <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">F. vulgare</italic>, as more suitable than the 
  <italic class="italic">P. lentiscus</italic> EO for the wheat treatment. In laboratory tests, the most toxic EO was the 
  <italic class="italic">P. lentiscus</italic> (LC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 36.36 μL∙kg
  <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) while, the least toxic, was the 
  <italic class="italic">F. vulgare</italic> one (LC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 77.59 μL∙kg
  <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). The EOs were also tested combined with diatomaceous earths (DEs) showing synergistic effects (co-toxicity coefficient values ranging from 1.36 to 3.35 for 
  <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">F. vulgare</italic> EOs, respectively). Overall, 
  <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> resulted as the best EO for the wheat treatment, considering its insect toxicity and olfactory profile. In real storage conditions, the wheat co-treated with 
  <italic class="italic">O. basilicum</italic> EO and DEs showed a significantly lower mean infestation (1.5 insect kg
  <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) than the non-treated wheat (7.0 insect kg
  <sup class="sup">−1</sup>).
 </p>
</abstract>
