<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">RES encapsulated in zein/pectin core-shell NPs with mean diameter approx. 235 nm and polydispersity index 0.24 showed improved in vitro antioxidant activity as well as lower IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values (by 32%) related to antiproliferative activity tested using human hepatocarcinoma Bel-7402 cells compared to free RES, suggesting that such nanoformulation of RES could be used in functional foods and beverages as well as in DISs and pharmaceutical products [
 <xref rid="B157-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">157</xref>]. The aqueous solubility of RES from α-lactalbumin (α-Lalb)-RES nanocomplexes was 32-fold higher than that of free RES, and the nanocomplexes considerably improved the antioxidant chemical stability under storage, especially at pH 8.0 and high temperature, and showed superb in vitro antioxidant activity compared to free RES, suggesting that α-Lalb as a nanoscale carrier could effectively deliver lipophilic nutraceuticals in the functional food, biomedical, and pharmaceutical products [
 <xref rid="B158-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">158</xref>]. The protection of light-sensitive AST, a carotenoid with the most potent antioxidant activity, from photodegradation achieved by its inclusion in different hierarchically assembled nano- and microstructures in order to produce model foods for humans and fishes decreased as follows: NEs &gt; carrageenan-coated NEs &gt; CS coated NEs, and CS beads provided higher protection to AST than alginate beads. These hierarchically assembled materials represent ideal platforms to create foods for humans and animal species, because their flexibility enables also the incorporation of other active molecules such as proteins, PUFAs, antibiotics, antiparasitics, etc. [
 <xref rid="B159-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>]. The average size (94 nm) of AST-loaded NLCs containing α-tocopherol and ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid as antioxidants and stabilized with Tween 80 and lecithin increased at pH ≤ 5, high NaCl concentrations (≥50 mM), and slightly at simulated gastric juice, which was connected mainly with decreasing zeta-potential, while increasing at treatment at 80/90 °C. On the other hand, cryoprotectant glycerol prevented the aggregation of AST-NLCs during freeze-thawing. Therefore, this nanoformulation could be used as a DIS [
 <xref rid="B160-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">160</xref>].
</p>
