<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antiglycation assay was carried out using a fructose-mediated BSA glycation model as reported previously [
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-26-00224" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] with minor modifications. In brief, 50 mg/mL of BSA was prepared using 0.033% sodium azide-containing 0.1 M PBS (pH 7.4), and 286 mM of fructose was prepared using 0.1 M PBS (pH 7.4). Then, 600 µL of BSA solution (50 mg/mL) was incubated with 350 µL of fructose solution (286 mM) and 50 µL of sample solution (dissolved in 50% methanol aqueous solution, extract 0.25–2 mg/mL; compounds 0.5–2 mM) in the dark at 37 °C for 14 days. Then, 200 µL of the reaction solution from each sample was pipetted to black 96-well plates to determine the fluorescent AGEs using a microplate fluorescence reader (BIOTEK-FLx800, Winooski, VT, USA) at excitation and emission wavelengths of 360 ± 20 nm and 460 ± 20 nm, respectively. Aminoguanidine [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-00224" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], a synthetic antiglycation agent, was used as a positive control with final concentrations of 200 µg/mL to 800 µg/mL or 1 mM to 4 mM. The antiglycative activity (%) was calculated using Equation (3):
 <disp-formula id="FD3-molecules-26-00224">
  <label>(3)</label>
  <math id="mm3">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mo>%</mo>
     <mi>i</mi>
     <mi>n</mi>
     <mi>h</mi>
     <mi>i</mi>
     <mi>b</mi>
     <mi>i</mi>
     <mi>t</mi>
     <mi>i</mi>
     <mi>o</mi>
     <mi>n</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mfenced>
      <mrow>
       <mn>1</mn>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <mfrac>
        <mrow>
         <msub>
          <mi>f</mi>
          <mrow>
           <mi>s</mi>
           <mi>a</mi>
           <mi>m</mi>
           <mi>p</mi>
           <mi>l</mi>
           <mi>e</mi>
          </mrow>
         </msub>
         <mo>−</mo>
         <msub>
          <mi>f</mi>
          <mrow>
           <mi>b</mi>
           <mi>l</mi>
           <mi>a</mi>
           <mi>n</mi>
           <mi>k</mi>
           <mn>1</mn>
          </mrow>
         </msub>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <msub>
          <mi>f</mi>
          <mrow>
           <mi>c</mi>
           <mi>o</mi>
           <mi>n</mi>
           <mi>t</mi>
           <mi>r</mi>
           <mi>o</mi>
           <mi>l</mi>
          </mrow>
         </msub>
         <mo>−</mo>
         <msub>
          <mi>f</mi>
          <mrow>
           <mi>b</mi>
           <mi>l</mi>
           <mi>a</mi>
           <mi>n</mi>
           <mi>k</mi>
           <mn>2</mn>
          </mrow>
         </msub>
        </mrow>
       </mfrac>
      </mrow>
     </mfenced>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
     <mo>%</mo>
     <mo>,</mo>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>f
  <sub>sample</sub>
 </italic> is the fluorescence of fructose-mediated AGEs in the presence of a sample; 
 <italic>f
  <sub>blank</sub>
 </italic>
 <sub>1</sub> is the fluorescence of the mixture solution of BSA and a sample in the absence of fructose; 
 <italic>f
  <sub>control</sub>
 </italic> is the fluorescence of fructose-mediated AGEs in the absence of a sample; 
 <italic>f
  <sub>blank</sub>
 </italic>
 <sub>2</sub> is the fluorescence of BSA without fructose or samples.
</p>
