<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0255">Moreover, comet assay, a widely accepted standard method for assessing DNA lesions in eukaryotic cells on one hand, and DNA repair activity on the other hand (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Azqueta et al., 2014</xref>), was used to establish additional effects of the extracts of six Lamiaceae species in an eukaryotic model system. The results showed that since treatment with hydrogen-peroxide induced single-strand DNA breaks (SSB), MRC-5 cells, also treated with Lamiaceae extracts, activated SSB rejoining pathways concentration dependently. Since 
 <italic>Ov</italic> and 
 <italic>Tc</italic> extracts, especially aqueous ones, were the most successful in protecting the eukaryotic DNA from the hydrogen-peroxide inflicted damage, it might be hypothesized that chlorogenic acid might have had an influence in regard to this activity since in these extracts its quantity was rather high in comparison with the others. Moreover, flavonols like quercetin might have also influenced the displayed antigenotoxic activity, however the rather high amounts of rutin found in 
 <italic>Tc</italic> extracts is not to be ignored since it has been previously shown that rutin prevents UV-induced changes in fibroblasts’ cell membrane function and it also has a cytoprotective effects on cells which are exposed to different physical factor (
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Gęgotek et al., 2020</xref>). Hence, this metabolite might have provided these extracts with the ability to prevent genotoxic damages of the DNA molecule. According to a review paper (
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Sabahi et al., 2018</xref>) and a comprehensive literature survey, only a handful of plants from the Lamiaceae family were studied for their antigenotoxic effect on normal cell lines. Previous research suggests that the antigenotoxic potential of these plants might be attributed to the presence of phenolic groups (
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Kapiszewska et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Sghaier et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Sabahi et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <italic>Thymus piperella</italic> showed better antigenotoxic ability (around 40% of DNA was protected) in comparison to 
 <italic>Origanum heracleoticum</italic> (around 5%) (
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Kapiszewska et al., 2005</xref>), while according to our results no significant difference between 
 <italic>Thymus</italic> and 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> plant extracts was observed.
</p>
