<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, it appears that microbial cell envelopes are not the only damaged cell structure. Indeed, reactive species, such as singlet oxygen, hydrogen peroxide, nitric oxide and excited atoms and molecules, can rapidly and easily diffuse into the cells, even when the membrane is intact, and oxidize many macromolecules (Dobrynin et al., 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Joshi et al., 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Yost and Joshi, 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Recently, Ziuzina et al. (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015b</xref>) detected and quantified, in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, the intracellular pool of reactive oxygen species after exposure to NTAP, using fluorescence techniques. They observed an increase in their concentration after NTAP treatment, which was more pronounced in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic>. Similarly, Joshi et al. (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>), using highly selective fluorescent compounds for singlet oxygen and hydrogen peroxide quantification, found that the singlet oxygen concentration inside 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> cells increased steadily within a 60 second NTAP treatment, whereas hydrogen peroxide content reached a maximum value after 12 s of treatment. In 
 <italic class="italic">S. cerevisiae</italic>, an increase in the intracellular concentration of reactive species of oxygen and, especially, of nitric oxide has also been reported (Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Once inside the cell, reactive substances provoke damage not only on lipids, but also on proteins, nucleic acids and carbohydrates. In order to neutralize the deleterious effects of such oxidant species or to repair the damage they cause, microorganisms have a number of mechanisms of elimination and transformation of these compounds, such as catalases, superoxide dismutases and glutathione and thioredoxin systems, among others. Nevertheless, when the accumulation of reactive oxygen species exceeds the cellular detoxifying capacity, and their concentration surpasses a critical level, the microbial cell suffers from oxidative stress, which induces the expression of certain genes and the activation of different defense responses (Pomposiello and Demple, 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>). For instance, in 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, the regulators 
 <italic class="italic">oxyRS</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">soxRS</italic> are involved in the cellular response to oxidative stress induced by NTAP. Indeed, the exposure of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> to NTAP results in the overexpression of the 
 <italic class="italic">oxyS, soxS</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">soxR</italic> genes, as well as of those genes encoding for the catalase (KatG) and superoxide dismutase (SodA) enzymes (Sharma et al., 
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Yost and Joshi, 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). In addition, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> mutants lacking the 
 <italic class="italic">oxyR</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">soxS</italic> genes have been shown to be more susceptible than wild-type strains to a plasma treatment using as working gases helium or a mixture of helium and oxygen (Perni et al., 
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Similarly, Yost and Joshi (
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) reported that strains deficient in superoxide dismutase (SodA) were more rapidly inactivated by a NTAP treatment than wild-type strains. Overall, these results demonstrate the occurrence of reactive oxygen species within the cells during plasma treatments and suggest that the membrane is not the unique cellular component targeted by NTAP.
</p>
