<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par82" class="p">When working with an inherently sensitive molecule, development and manufacturing of a drug substance may be of particular concern, as during the drug substance manufacturing process for many molecules, no surfactant is present until the final step. Until the risk of exposure to interfacial stress has been evaluated, a conservative operating space should be employed and exposure to excessive interfacial stress should be avoided. Experience is gained as each molecule moves through the development process, but risk assessment tools should be applied to better understand the effect of interfacial stress on a given protein. In particular, agitation studies and freeze/thaw studies are often performed early in the development process. In these studies, the product is exposed to agitation stress or to multiple freezing and thawing cycles, respectively, then characterized 
 <italic class="italic">via</italic> size exclusion chromatography and particulate analysis, as well as any specific stability indicating assays important for the molecule of interest. For example, an agitation study may include agitation of the molecule on an orbital shaker at moderate rate for 1 to 7 days, or a shorter period of agitation 
 <italic class="italic">via</italic> a wrist action shaker. During the early development process, an average of five freezing and thawing cycles is often performed, where the molecule is cycled between − 70°C and room temperature, and then analyzed for HMWS and particle formation after each cycle to look for any upward trends. While each company has their own operating space and product specifications, any significant increase in either soluble aggregates or particle counts with exposure to interfacial stress should be examined further and potential root causes should be evaluated. These early screening tools can provide insight into the stability of the product under stress conditions and can allow the development team a design space in which to operate while designing the manufacturing process.
</p>
