<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> has been known as the largest genus of the 
 <italic class="italic">Lamiaceae</italic> family. This large genus comprises a wide variety of species through the whole flora. Previous reports showed that approximately 900 species have been known as 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> all across the world. Eighty-six species of 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">Lamiaceae</italic>) have been known in Turkey [
 <xref rid="B1-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] and many species are medicinal and aromatic plants. 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> species (
 <italic class="italic">Lamiaceae</italic>) could be defined to be quite endemic with a high endemism percentage of 45% in the flora of Turkey [
 <xref rid="B2-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The origin of the word 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> dates back to the Latin word “
 <italic class="italic">salvare</italic>” which means “to heal” [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Previous scientific reports presented that 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> has health-healing properties such as antiseptic, antipyretic, analgesic, antimicrobial, antioxidant, anticancer, anticholinesterase and anti-inflammatory characteristics, and it is used for herbal teas [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Different parts of the 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> plant such as leaves, flowers, roots and seeds may be used for their health benefits. The seeds of 
 <italic class="italic">S. hispanica</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. sclarea</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. umbratica</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. viridis</italic> are used for medicinal purposes [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Results from previous studies demonstrated a strong and consistent relationship between the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> and antimicrobial, antiviral and cytotoxic effects [
 <xref rid="B4-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. In Turkey, 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> species are mainly consumed in the form of herbal teas with the aim of curing the common cold, and 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> has applications in treating some diseases which cause pain in different parts of the body such as the stomach and liver [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> seeds have been known to have an important nutritional composition. Seeds contain fat, protein, fibers, minerals and phenolic compounds. Thus, they are indicated as sources of fats, proteins, antioxidants and dietary fibers [
 <xref rid="B6-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. For instance, 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia hispanica</italic> L. has 17–20% protein content and 25–38% fat content with approximately 60% linoleic acid content [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Additionally, previous studies reported that it is possible to isolate important new and previously known compounds such as abietane, clerodane, pimarane diterpenoids, sesterterpenoids, triterpenoids and flavonoids. As clearly seen, 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> seeds may qualify for development of new functional foods, innovative food products and dietary supplements [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Along with this growth in the food applications of 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia,</italic> there is increasing interest in the economic and nutritional value of 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> species. In recent years, there has been an increasing interest in fingerprinting (characterization of) 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Previous studies showed the chemical properties and compositional and physical characteristics of this valuable seed. However, very few studies have focused on the evaluation of the seeds of 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> species. For instance, Porras-Loaiza et al. (2014) performed a study with the aim of comparing the physical and chemical properties of chia (
 <italic class="italic">Salvia hispanica</italic>) seeds from different Mexican regions [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. In another study, the main objective was to chemically and nutritionally characterize commercial chia seeds [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Similarly, Capitani et al. (2012) characterized the physicochemical and functional properties of meals and fibrous fractions of chia seeds [
 <xref rid="B10-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. In another study, Yilmaz et al. (2016) evaluated the rheological characteristics of 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia sclarea</italic> seed gum [
 <xref rid="B11-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. It is now well established by a variety of studies that 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic> seeds have high saturated, monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fatty acids in their composition [
 <xref rid="B3-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. It was reported that fingerprinting herbs may be accomplished using chromatographic techniques. Findings suggested that the application of chromatographic techniques for characterization and identification of herbs has gained recognition from foremost organizations such as the World Health Organization and Food and Drug Administration [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Gas chromatography is effectively and preferably used in various sections of the food industry such as process control and quality control with the aim of tracking the composition of volatile compounds [
 <xref rid="B12-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The gas chromatography mass spectroscopy (GC-MS) technique especially could be regarded as the gold standard since the combination of gas chromatography with mass spectroscopy provides opportunities for the identification of unknown components with high accuracy [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Another popular and strong fingerprinting technique is known as Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR spectroscopy). FTIR spectroscopy is non-destructive and can rapidly obtain biochemical fingerprints that provide reliable information on molecular structure and composition [
 <xref rid="B14-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Because of these advantages, FTIR spectroscopy has been used effectively and successfully with the aim of identification and evaluation of a wide variety of food products. Nowadays, many laboratories have the capability to produce comprehensive data sets by using this instrumental analysis equipment. Chemometrics in statistics is used to evaluate the outcomes obtained by laboratory equipment [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Chemometrics may be used effectively and efficiently to determine the hidden relationships between variables, thus providing an opportunity for evaluation of the samples in compliance with their similarities or differences. The most popular and widely used techniques are known as hierarchical cluster analysis (HCA), principal component analysis (PCA) and partial least squares (PLS) [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-08-00118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>].
</p>
