<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Ascorbic acid is a vital, strong, and least toxic natural antioxidant, it is the main water-soluble antioxidant present in milk, and the free radical scavenging activity of ascorbic acid is due to low oxidation-reduction potential (330 mV). Ascorbic acid can scavenge superoxide anion radicals, alkoxyl radicals, and singlet oxygen [
 <xref rid="ref114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. Ascorbic acid significantly inhibited the degradation of riboflavin in cream in the presence of 1000 Lux light for 4 days [
 <xref rid="ref137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>]. Ascorbic acid and tocopherol were added in milk to enhance the flavor and photo-oxidative stability. It was done on fresh raw milk collected from Virginia Tech Dairy Farm through gas chromatography. Ascorbic acid and tocopherol (100 mg/kg of milk fat) supplemented samples revealed better flavor and photo-oxidative stability as compared to non-supplemented samples [
 <xref rid="ref116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. Ascorbic acid significantly inhibited the degradation of riboflavin in light-exposed milk, and antioxidant activities were mainly attributed to the scavenging effect on singlet oxygen [
 <xref rid="ref138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">138</xref>]. A research was conducted to assess the impact of tocopherol and Vitamin C against atopy development in infants. Increased concentration of Vitamin C in breast milk which is water soluble decreases the risk of atopy in infants [
 <xref rid="ref139" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>]. Ascorbic acid is extremely helpful for the infants, also plays a significant role during developmental stage in the production of neurotransmitters and synthesis of carnitine, and improves the absorption of iron, while in human and cow milk, its concentration is approximately 40 and 20 mg/l, respectively [
 <xref rid="ref141" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">141</xref>]. Oxidation of ascorbic acid depends on temperature, light, oxygen, and amount of catalysts. Vitamin is regarded as primary lipid-soluble antioxidant; main job of this vitamin is to protect the PUFAs and associated biochemical compounds from peroxidation. Among the tocopherols, α-tocopherol is regarded as more powerful antioxidant; antioxidant activity of β-, γ-, and δ-tocopherol is about 80-90% less than α-tocopherol [
 <xref rid="ref142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">142</xref>]. γ-Tocopherol is of high functional value; it can trap the nitrogen oxide species. It helps the body to prevent cardiovascular diseases and cancers; concentration of Vitamin E in cow milk is about 0.9 mg/ml (
 <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table-5</xref>) [
 <xref rid="ref143" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">143</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">145</xref>], and summer milk has higher concentration than winter milk. The concentration of vitamin in human milk ranges from 3 to 13 mg/ml [
 <xref rid="ref146" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">146</xref>]. Batool 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref147" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">147</xref>] studied the impact of supplemented Vitamin E and selenium on oxidative stability of cheddar cheese which efficiently inhibited the LPO and raised the shelf stability.
</p>
