<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Family Cupressaceae is the largest coniferous plant family. Essential oils of many species belonging to family Cupressaceae are known to have several biological activities specially antimicrobial activity. The essential oils from aerial parts of 
  <italic class="italic">Calocedrus decurrens </italic>Torr.,
  <italic class="italic"> Cupressus sempervirens stricta </italic>L. and
  <italic class="italic"> Tetraclinis articulata</italic> (Vahl) Mast. were prepared by hydrodistillation. The chemical composition of the essential oils has been elucidated by gas chromatography-mass spectroscopy analysis. The prepared essential oils were examined against selected species of Gram-positive, Gram-negative bacteria and 
  <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> species. Broth dilution methods were used to detect minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) and minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC). Sixteen compounds were identified in the essential oils of both 
  <italic class="italic">Calocedrus decurrens </italic>and 
  <italic class="italic">Cupressus sempervirens </italic>L. and fifteen compounds were identified in the essential oil of 
  <italic class="italic">Tetraclinis articulata</italic>. δ-3-Carene (43.10%), (+)-Cedrol (74.03%) and Camphor (21.23%) were the major constituents in the essential oils of 
  <italic class="italic">Calocedrus decurrens</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Cupressus sempervirens </italic>L. and 
  <italic class="italic">Tetraclinis articulata</italic>, respectively. The essential oils showed strong antimicrobial activities against the selected microorganisms in concentration range 0.02 3- 3.03 µL/mL. This study could contribute to the chemotaxonomic characterization of family Cupressaceae. In addition, it proved that the essential oils under investigation possess potential antimicrobial properties.
 </p>
</abstract>
