<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="plants-09-01214-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="pii">plants-09-01214-t002_Table 2</object-id>
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Morphological characteristics of 
   <italic>P. protopunica</italic> Balf.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <italic>Punica protopunica</italic> Balf.
    </th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Morphological Characteristics</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>General habit</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The tree can reach a height of 2.5 to 4.5 m. It is considered a small tree or shrub, but if it reaches more than 9.14 m it can be classified as a tree, that is, it can be considered as both main forms. There are trees that are wider than they are tall (for example, trees that grow on the slopes rocks of Socotra) and trees taller than they are wide (typical of trees growing on the Socotra limestone plateau.) Generally, the tree is equal in width to height, with an upright shrub appearance.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Bark, branches and trunk</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The bark is reddish-brown when the tree is young, but changes to a grayish hue as it grows older. The branches have thorns.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Leaves</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The leaves grow to a length of 3 cm, in pairs on the opposite sides of the stalk, they are perennial, their most common shape is elliptical or oblong, although there are also circular or oval and obovate leaves (a single branch can have leaves of all the shapes described). Its color is dark green, with a bright tone.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Flowers</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The flowers have obovate or oval petals, although they are sometimes heart-shaped. Its color is light pink with glitter and its shape is “trumpet”. Flowering occurs from December until the summer of the following year. Their physiology allows them to produce fertilization and pollination. It is a self-crossing species.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Fruits</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The shape of the fruits is almost identical to that of modified tangelos (Citrus x tangelo). They retain their floral chalice tube. The peel is hard and its color when ripe is light green to greenish yellow and may or may not contain pink reflections. Inside they present a spongy pericarp with membranes (endocarp) that separate the arils into compartments. In turn, each aril contains a membrane, pulp juice and a seed.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Seeds</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The seeds are inside the arils and there are hundreds of them, they are relatively light. </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>Adapted from [
    <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
    <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
    <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
    <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
    <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01214" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
