<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As was mentioned before, interest in a circular economy and food or agricultural waste valorization is increasing. Therefore, biorefinery approaches for recovering bioactive molecules with target biological properties are consequently growing to face the current challenge: moving towards a circular system production model [
 <xref rid="B24-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. The use of by-products from the agri-food industry for the recovery of tannins was proposed decades ago. In 1990, it had been already suggested that pods, seeds, cake or kernel residues of some products, such as mango or cocoa, could serve as potential sources of tannins [
 <xref rid="B106-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Their presence has been assessed in different by-products of the agri-food industry, such as green tea processing residues and acorn, chestnut and persimmon hulls and starch, showing antioxidant or antimicrobial properties, among others [
 <xref rid="B107-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. More recently, other studies have also addressed the possibility of recovering tannins from a secondary residue, such as distilled waste by-products remaining after the steam distillation of the underutilized biomass of specific trees [
 <xref rid="B108-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Additionally, other experiments have been focused on assessing the bioavailability of tannins and the cellular level where they are located, i.e., they were found inside the cell lumen of parenchymatic cells and the vessels of chestnut wood [
 <xref rid="B109-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Further applications are focused on obtaining other products from tannin-based sources. For instance, coffee pulp (rich in tannins) was submitted to solid state fermentation by 
 <italic>Penicillium verrucosum</italic> to produce tannase [
 <xref rid="B110-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. However, to date, one of the biggest concerns regarding obtaining tannins is their high diversity, since this is related to their origin, extraction and purification procedures [
 <xref rid="B111-foods-10-00137" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Hence, conventional and novel extraction techniques have been investigated to optimize the extraction parameters of tannin recovery from different by-products (
 <xref rid="foods-10-00137-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).
</p>
