<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Electrospinning is an innovative technology to generate ultrathin fibrous mats made of a wide range of polymer and biopolymer materials with fiber diameters ranging from several nanometers to a few microns [
 <xref rid="B15-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Electrospun ultrathin fibers have prompted their use in a wide range of industrial sectors, including packaging applications [
 <xref rid="B16-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. This technique is highly suitable for the encapsulation and/or sustained delivery of active and bioactive substances at the nanoscale level due to both the high surface-to-volume ratios of the electrospun fibers and the high porosity of their mats [
 <xref rid="B18-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. In particular, electrospinning is interesting for the development of antimicrobial materials by either the use of inherently antimicrobial polymers or the nanoencapsulation of biocide substances [
 <xref rid="B20-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. As a result, within the frame of active packaging, different recent studies have reported the encapsulation of metal nanoparticles (MNPs) in electrospun matrices. For instance, poly(vinyl alcohol) (PVOH) and poly(N-isopropylacrylamide) (PNIPAAm) membranes containing silver nanoparticles (AgNPs) immobilized onto cellulose nanowhiskers (CNWs) presented antimicrobial activity against several Gram-negative (G-) and Gram-positive (G+) bacteria [
 <xref rid="B21-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. In another study, polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP)/poly(ε-caprolactone) (PCL) nanofibers functionalized with zinc oxide nanoparticles (ZnONPs) and AgNPs, also prepared by electrospinning, showed a high antibacterial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B22-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Similarly, electrospun chitosan/poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO) membranes containing AgNPs presented antimicrobial effect against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B23-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Recently developed electrospun PHA materials containing AgNPs [
 <xref rid="B24-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] and copper oxide nanoparticles (CuONPs) [
 <xref rid="B25-nanomaterials-09-00227" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] have been also able to considerably reduce bacterial growth at very low contents. These novel NPs-containing electrospun materials offer significant potential as new antimicrobial coatings or interlayers, that is, internal layers in a multilayer system, for application in the design of active food packaging structures.
</p>
