<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently, three possible terpenoid production strategies have been applied, including plant extraction, chemical synthesis, and microbial biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>). Extraction from biomass of herb plants is the traditional terpenoid production method. The monoterpenoids of menthone and pulegone are the effective medicinal ingredients of 
 <italic>Nepeta cataria</italic> (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). The volatile components of 
 <italic>N. cataria</italic> are mainly extracted by the physical methods of distillation and extraction, including reflux method, and temperature-programmed microwave extraction method (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2012</xref>). However, the volatile oil contents in 
 <italic>Nepeta</italic> are low, and extraction of monoterpenoids from 
 <italic>Nepeta</italic> biomass is difficult (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Wen et al., 2019</xref>). The chemical structures of terpenoids are relatively complex. Chemical synthesis of terpenoids needs many steps, and the purity and yield of the products are not high enough, making chemical synthesis of terpenoids is difficult and high-cost. With the development of synthetic biology and metabolic engineering, many terpenoids have been successfully synthesized by engineered microorganisms (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2020</xref>). The most successful example is the synthesis of artemisinic acid using metabolically engineered yeasts (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Paddon et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Kai et al., 2018</xref>). In China, the most successful large-scale production of terpenoids is the synthesis of rare ginsenosides with engineered 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Yan et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Wang P. et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2015</xref>). Due to the complex structures of monoterpenoids, microbial production of monoterpenoids is of great interest.
</p>
