<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many studies have been reported on the biological activities of 
 <italic>Ocotea</italic> metabolites: the alkaloid reticuline isolated from extract of 
 <italic>O. duckei</italic> showed potent central nervous system depressant action [
 <xref rid="B13-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. (−)-Caaverine, a noraporphine alkaloid isolated from 
 <italic>O. lancifolia</italic>, has shown high antiprotozoal activity against 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> and 
 <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> parasites [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The chloroform fraction obtained from an extract of fruits of 
 <italic>O. puberula</italic> and the alkaloid dicentrine displayed antinociceptive effects [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The butanolides isolated from roots of 
 <italic>O. macrocarpa</italic> showed good cytotoxic activities against the A2780 ovarian cell line [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The flavonoids of 
 <italic>O. notata</italic> showed antimycobacterial activity and ability to inhibit NO production by macrophages [
 <xref rid="B17-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The essential oil of 
 <italic>O. quixos</italic>, rich in 
 <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamaldehyde and methyl cinnamate, showed anti-inflammatory properties in vitro and in vivo models [
 <xref rid="B18-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Studies on the chemical characteristics of the species 
 <italic>O. caudata</italic>, 
 <italic>O. cujumary</italic>, and 
 <italic>O. caniculata</italic> are rare and important because 
 <italic>Ocotea</italic> species are classified as threatened to extinction by the Brazilian List and the risk of extinction is increased due the reduction of genetic variability [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] so knowledge of the genetic diversity is necessary for our understanding of the factors that determine essential oil quantity and quality in these economically important species [
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-18-01081" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].
</p>
