<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, flavonoids have been reported with good anti-HBV effect. Luteolin (
 <bold>15</bold>), isolated from 
 <italic>Swertia macrosperma</italic> C. B. Clark, could significantly inhibit the secretion of HBsAg and HBeAg with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.02 mM on HepG 2.2.15 cells 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Isovitexin (
 <bold>16</bold>) isolated from 
 <italic>S. yunnanensis</italic> had good anti-HBV effect, which could not only inhibit the secretion of HBsAg and HBeAg, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.04 mM, &lt;0.03 mM, and 0.23 mM, but also significantly inhibit the replication of HBV-DNA, with the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.09 mM, &lt;0.01 mM, and 0.05 mM [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Huang et al. [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] isolated LPRP-Et-97543 (
 <bold>17</bold>) from 
 <italic>Liriopemuscari</italic> (Decne.) L.H.Bailey, which had significant anti-HBV activity and could significantly reduce the activity of Core, S, and preS promoters. Moreover, the mechanism may be that it inhibited the replication of viral DNA by regulating viral proteins. In recent years, molecular docking technology was used to screen the active ingredients against HBV, a 3D structure of HBV polymerase (Pol/RT) was modeled and docked with the active compounds, and quercetin (
 <bold>18</bold>) was proved that could enhance its anti-HBV activity up to 10% [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In addition, some researchers found that glabaarachalcone (
 <bold>19</bold>) and isopongachromene (
 <bold>20</bold>), isolated from 
 <italic>P. pinnata</italic>, could bound with HBV-DNA polymerase protein target [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Isooriention (
 <bold>21</bold>), isolated from 
 <italic>S. mussotii</italic>, displayed significant anti-HBV activities against the secretions of HBsAg and HBeAg with IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 0.79 and 1.12 mM, as well as HBV-DNA replication with IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 0.02 mM [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Epimedium Hyde II (
 <bold>22</bold>), a potential Chinese herbal active ingredient against HBV, could inhibit the replication of HBV-DNA and the expression of HBsAg and HBeAg in the serum of HBV-replicated C57BL/6 mice [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The chemical structures of compounds 
 <bold>15</bold>~22 showed in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>.
</p>
