<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">
 <italic>Rhus vulgaris</italic> Meikle (Anacardiaceae) is found in tropical and temperate regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In Kenya, the stem bark of this plant is used in the treatment of malaria [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In Uganda, this plant is used for the treatment of toothaches [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and it is one of the most commonly used chewing sticks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In Tanzania, 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> leaves are traditionally used for the treatment of dental problems and as a refreshment in herbal teas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In regions surrounding Lake Victoria in East Africa, 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> fruits are used for the treatment of tooth ache, coughing, syphilis, gastrointestinal disorders and for the prevention of infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Rhus</italic> genus has demonstrated significant antimicrobial, antifungal, antiviral, antioxidant, antimalarial and cytotoxic properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> have been reported to possess good antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The dichloromethane, ethyl acetate and aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> stem bark, root and leaf have shown antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Klebsiella oxytoca, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Salmonella typhi, Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>Salmonella kisarawe</italic> with MIC values ranging from 0.39 mg/ml to 25 mg/ml while gentamycin, positive control, exhibited MIC values ranging from 0.003 mg/ml to 0.25 mg/ml [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The dichloromethane, ethyl acetate and aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> stem bark, root and leaf have also demonstrated antifungal activity against 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> and 
 <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> with MIC values ranging from 1.56 mg/ml to 25 mg/ml while fluconazole, positive control, demonstrated an MIC value of 0.19 mg/ml [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> (500 mg/ml) stem bark, root and leaf have demonstrated good antioxidant activity of 80.11, 80.25 and 80.62% respectively at 30 min [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> methanolic extract (1000 mg/kg) showed greater anti-inflammatory activity compared to indomethacin (10 mg/kg), the standard anti-inflammatory drug, with a decrease in inflammation for up to 90 min [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The dichloromethane, ethyl acetate and aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>R. vulgaris</italic> stem bark, root and leaf have exhibited moderate to toxic toxicity against brine shrimp with LC
 <sub>50</sub> values ranging from 3.55 μg/ml to 734.06 μg/ml while cyclophosphamide, the positive control, demonstrated an LC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 15.28 μg/ml [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].
</p>
