<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant species belonging to the family Euphorbiaceae contain a high diversity of phytochemicals, including terpenoids, phenolic compounds, alkaloids, and fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This variability of plant chemicals may account for the varied uses of the plants from this family as among others, anti-infective agents [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The studied plant—
 <italic>Plukenetia huayllabambana</italic> (R. W. Bussmann, C. Téllez &amp; A. Glenn) (Euphorbiaceae), also known as ‘Giant Sacha Inchi’ or ‘Giant Inca Peanut’, is a native plant to the tropical rain forest of the Amazon region of South America [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. 
 <italic>P. huayllabambana</italic> is closely related to another species of the same genus, namely 
 <italic>Plukenetia volubilis</italic>, commonly known as ‘Sacha Inchi’ or ‘Inca Peanut’. The two species differ in morphological and physicochemical properties. The morphological dissimilarity between 
 <italic>P. volubilis</italic> and 
 <italic>P. huayllabambana</italic> might also involve variance in the phytochemical composition. Indeed, Chirinos and collaborators [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] revealed pretty similarly fatty acid profiles for both species but 
 <italic>P. huayllabambana</italic> presented a significantly higher content of alpha-linolenic acid than 
 <italic>P. volubilis</italic>, while important contents of γ- and δ-tocopherol were evidenced in both oils. β-Sitosterol was the most important and representative phytosterol. In Cameroon, 
 <italic>P. huayllabambana</italic> is used for alimentation and therapeutics. Seeds are edible (in a cooked or roasted form), while other parts of the plant are used traditionally to cure wounds and various infections. Most of the reported biological effects are related to seed-derived oils, while there are almost no studies on organic extracts. Sacha inchi oil-related products have been reported to exhibit anti-adherent activity against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, skin tightening, anti-aging effects [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. 
 <italic>P. huayllabambana</italic> has been characterized as a rich source of fatty acids (saturated, mono- and polyunsaturated) comprising linolenic and linoleic acids as major ones. It also contains varied pharmacologically active compounds such as γ- and δ-tocopherol, phytosterol (high content of sitosterol), phenyl alcohols, and phenolic compounds including flavonoids, secoiridoids, and lignans [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01111" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In the present work, we evaluated the antibacterial efficacy of the crude methanolic extract and solvent fractions from 
 <italic>P. huayllabambana</italic> fruits against five drug-resistant Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria, and the evaluation of the antibacterial modes of action. The gas chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry (GC–MS) analysis for bioactive components identification was performed on the n-hexane fraction.
</p>
