<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Essential oils (EOs) are a mixture of volatile constituents produced by aromatic plant/herbs. There are about 3,000 well-recognized EOs, of which 300 are generally recognized as safe (GRAS) to humans by the United States Food and Drug Administration (U.S. FDA) and have broad applications in food preservation, additives, and favors, perfume, cosmetic industries, antiseptic oral solutions, toothpastes, cleaner, and air fresheners for centuries (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pandey et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sakkas and Papadopoulou, 2017</xref>). These natural products are of particular interest as “green” antimicrobial agents because of their low-cost, biocompatibility, potential antibiofilm properties, and friendly to eukaryote cells and environment (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burt, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nostro et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kavanaugh and Ribbeck, 2012</xref>). Among these safe EOs, oregano oil has been shown to have a variety of activities such as antioxidant (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yan et al., 2016</xref>), anti-inflammatory (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ocana-Fuentes et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shen et al., 2010</xref>), anti-fungal (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akgul and Kivanc, 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soylu et al., 2007</xref>), and anti-allergic (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Benito et al., 1996</xref>). Its antimicrobial effect has been demonstrated 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> cell culture, food systems studies (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lopez-Reyes et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soylu et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Munhuweyi et al., 2017</xref>), and 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> systemic infections (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manohar et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Preuss et al., 2005</xref>). In the present study, we investigate effectiveness of oregano oil in inactivation of MDR bacteria isolated from combat casualties 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> and bioluminescent strains of 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic> (PA01) and MRSA (USA300) in mouse burn wounds. Our study showed that oregano oil effectively inactivated various pathogenic bacteria and their biofilms irrespective of their antibiotic susceptibility. The study is the first 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> attempt on the use of oregano oil for the treatment of burn wounds infected with clinically important MDR bacteria.
</p>
