<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> is a saprophytic species that exhibits a high survival rate in food ecosystems, including fruits and vegetables (raw, cooked, and processed) (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hadjilouka et al., 2015</xref>), meat (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gouveia et al., 2016</xref>), milk (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sadeghi et al., 2016</xref>), and fish (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rocourt et al., 2003</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> is able to grow in different niches and has a strong ability to resist environmental and technological stresses, such as high/low temperatures and modified atmospheres. In addition, 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> is able to adapt and survive to different stress conditions within the food chain (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gandhi and Chikindas, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chan and Wiedmann, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cacace et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dutta et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">NicAogáin and O’Byrne, 2016</xref>), including those used for food processing and storage (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gomes Neto et al., 2015</xref>). Consequently, 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> constitutes a major risk to consumers and causes high economic losses (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cabrita et al., 2015</xref>). The European Commission (No 2073/2005) requires that the levels of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> in foods not intended for infants and hospitalized individuals and not representing an optimal medium for its growth must not exceed 100 CFU/g. In minimally processed fruits and vegetables, the use of chemicals (e.g., ozone, H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, organic acids, calcium-based solutions and peroxiacetic acids) as disinfectants is not sufficient to statistically decrease the survival of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> strains (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soliva-Fortuny and Martìn-Belloso, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Patrignani et al., 2015</xref>). However, based on consumer concerns regarding chemical synthetic additives (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sivakumar and Bautista-Baños, 2014</xref>), one of the emerging strategies used to decrease the survival of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> in food products is the use of natural antimicrobial compounds alone or in combination with other mild chemicals (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kamdem et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ngang et al., 2014</xref>). Antimicrobial products produced by plants, such as essential oils (EOs) and six carbon atom aldehydes generated in the lipoxygenase pathway, play key roles in plant defense against microbial proliferation, with many of these products being generally recognized as safe (GRAS) and used to improve the sensory quality and shelf-life of fruits, vegetables, meat and dairy foods (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burt, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Belletti et al., 2010</xref>). The antimicrobial properties of EOs are primarily related to presence of C10- and C15-terpenes with aromatic rings and phenolic-hydroxylic groups that can form hydrogen bonds with active sites of target enzymes (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Picone et al., 2013</xref>). In addition, other compounds in EOs, such as alcohols, aldehydes and esters have antimicrobial effects. EOs affect bacterial and fungal viability differently depending on their composition and structural configuration as well as to the possible synergistic interactions among the components (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Picone et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Patrignani et al., 2015</xref>). Interestingly, some EOs have a wide spectrum of activity against pathogens, including 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oliveira et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Patrignani et al., 2015</xref>). Some EOs from rosemary, thyme and oregano, such as citral (a mixture of monoterpene aldehydes present in geranial and neral), carvacrol, thymol, hexanal and trans-2-hexenal appear to be good natural antimicrobial candidates due to their inhibitory effects against bacteria and fungi in foods (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hao et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lanciotti et al., 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burt, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cava-Roda et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ivanovic et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Siroli et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Patrignani et al., 2015</xref>). Compared to other common antimicrobial compounds and human pathogens, there is little information available regarding the use of natural antimicrobial products to decrease the biofilm formation, cell survival, and environmental adaptation of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Helke et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tracanna et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Vuuren and Holl, 2017</xref>). Despite recent progress in elucidating the details of the 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> genome, the mechanisms this bacterium adapts to natural antimicrobial compounds remains largely unclear (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">NicAogáin and O’Byrne, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Braschi et al., 2018a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>). Studies on the adaptation of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> to natural antimicrobial compounds are crucial to highlight the relationship between stress and virulence and to optimize the protocols used for food production (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chaturongakul et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bowman et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">He et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
