<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Behavioral study</div>
 <sec id="sec3-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acute treatment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the acute dose study, groups were as follows:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Group I: Vehicle control group (normal saline plus Tween 80 (1%); Group II-IV: cinnamon essential oil (0.5, 1, and 2 mg/kg); Group V: Desipramine 10 mg/kg; Group VI: Fluoxetine 10 mg/kg.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All drugs were given intraperitoneally, 1, 8, and 24 hr before the test. In the acute study, antidepressant-like effects were assessed using the forced swim test (FST). Locomotor activity and anxiety-like behaviors were measured by the open field test and elevated plus maze, respectively.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sub-acute treatment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the sub-acute study, groups were as follows:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Group I: Vehicle control group (Tween 80+normal saline); Group II-IV: cinnamon essential oil (0.5, 1, and 2 mg/kg) for antidepressant activity; Group V-VII: cinnamon essential oil 0.5, 1, and 2 mg/kg for antianxiety activity; Group VIII: Desipramine 10 mg/kg; Group IX: Fluoxetine 10 mg/kg; Group X: Diazepam 2 mg/kg.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this regimen, drugs were given once daily during a period of 14-day, through the same route as in the previous regimen. Antidepressant-like effects were evaluated in FST and tail suspension test (TST). Locomotor activity and anxiety-like behavior were measured using the open field test and elevated plus-maze, respectively.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forced swim test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TFST is one of the most widely acceptable rodent behavioral models used for assessing depression and antidepressant-like efficacy of new drugs. One hour after the last treatment of acute study or 24 hr after tTST of sub-acute study, mice were individually placed in an inescapable transparent cylinder (15 cm in diameter), filled with 35 cm of room temperature water, such that the animals could not touch the bottom of the container with their hind paws or their tails. Immobility of animals was recorded during 6 min and the first 2 min was considered as trial (pre-test) (
   <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tail suspension test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TST was performed one day before FST in the sub-acute study. In this test, the mice were suspended by their tails, using tape, from a wire at the height of 33 cm. In such a position the animal was not able to escape or hold onto nearby surfaces. The absence of initiated movements was defined as immobility and recorded during a short-time period of 6 min and the first 2 min was considered as trial (pre-test). Mice were returned to the box after each animal was tested (
   <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Open field test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A wooden (30⊆30 cm) box with sidewalls of 40 cm was used to measure locomotor/exploratory activity of animals in a quiet environment. After passing 45 min of the last treatment of the acute study or after the 14th day of sub-acute study, animals were placed in the center of box and number of squares crossed with four paws of the animal was recorded. Each trial lasted 5 min (
   <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Elevated plus maze</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For conducting this test, different groups of animals received normal saline or essential oil for 14 days, and were individually placed in the center of a wooden cross elevated 40 cm above the floor. This apparatus consisted of two open (30⊆5 ⊆0.25 cm) and two closed arms (30⊆5⊆40 cm) as described previously (
   <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>). At the time of the experiment, each animal was placed in the center of apparatus, facing one of the open arms. Anxiety was evaluated during 5 min by recording the entries to open arms/total entries and the time spent in the open arms/time spent in all arms of the apparatus.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all three tests, after ending each trial session, fecal boli and urine were removed and surfaces were cleaned with 70% ethanol to start the next session.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
