<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We determined the complete cp genomes of three 
 <italic>Arnebia</italic> and one 
 <italic>Lithospermum</italic> accessions. The organization of these four cp genomes follows that of other Boraginaceae (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Zhang, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2020</xref>), and includes a typical quadripartite structure with LSC and SSC regions separated by two IRs. Genomes in the tested 
 <italic>Arnebia</italic> and 
 <italic>Lithospermum</italic> species possess 112 unique genes. Their gene order, GC content, genomic structure, and overall length (149,316–150,465 bp) conform to previously described angiosperm cp genomes (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Millen et al., 2001</xref>). Codon usage is a key factor for correct expression of genetic information, and plays an important role in shaping cp genome evolution (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Yi et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <italic>Arnebia</italic> and 
 <italic>Lithospermum</italic> accessions possess nearly identical codons, which are similar to those of other cp genomes (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Raman et al., 2019</xref>). RSCU values indicated synonymous codon usage bias, with a disproportionate number of codons having an A or T in the third position. This phenomenon has been described in many angiosperm cp genomes and is consistent with the pattern in seed plants. Indeed, high RSCU values correspond to more highly conserved cp genes (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Ivanova et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">Zuo et al., 2017</xref>). We surveyed the RSCU values for six Boraginaceae cp genomes downloaded from NCBI. Half of the codons had a weak codon bias (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>), denoted in green in the figure (RSCU &gt; 1). This result is similar to other cp genomes, and most codons with high RSCU values had an A or T in the third position. The cp genome of 
 <italic>B. officinalis</italic> displayed slightly different codon bias than other Boraginaceae species. In particular, GGT (Guanine), AGG (Arginine), and GGG (Guanine) codons had relatively low RSCU values; whereas TGT (Cysteine) and CGA (Arginine) had somewhat higher RSCU values.
</p>
