<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on the previous results about the inhibitory effect of EOCs in vitro, we decided to choose the best antifungal EOCs for in situ experiments. The pH value, fatty acid content, MDA content, and colony number parameters of the grain were tested to make a comprehensive and systematic evaluation of grain quality after EOC treatment. The pH declined as storage time increased, which was accounted for by the reason that the two EOCs were slightly acidic. A recent study declared that the decreasing pH was mainly caused by the degradation of proteins and metabolism of pathogens in rice, and the pH balance in cells would improve the nitrogen use efficiency of rice to extend storage life [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. EOCs with low pH values in foodstuffs were more hydrophobic and had more affinity to the target hydrophobic areas of proteins in the bacterial cell membrane [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Therefore, the lower pH of grain may help the EOCs play a better inhibitory effect against pathogens. With respect to fatty acid content, the increase of lipid acidity level being an early indicator of mold spoilage, some toxigenic fungus produced lipase in suitable conditions, which accelerated the hydrolysis of rice fats and caused an increase the fatty acid content of grain [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Our results demonstrated that citral significantly postponed the ascent of fatty acid content. MDA is the ultimate product of membrane lipid peroxidation in rice plants, and the cell undergoes oxidative stress with the increase of lipid peroxidation level and the accumulation of MDA [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In this study, the EOCs could maintain the lower level of MDA to protect the rice from oxidative damage. Concerning the microbial numbers, these parasitic microbes competed with the grains for oxygen and derive nutrients from grain tissues for their growth to deter grain respiration [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Besides, there are many factors, such as temperature, humidity, pH, and microorganisms, which consistently impact the efficacy of the combined biofungicides in the field experiments. Thus, the major compounds of EOs at the MIC in vitro used in grain could not realize the complete inactivation of fungi in situ. SEM analysis signified that both geraniol and citral effectively protected starch granules from the challenge of 
 <italic class="italic">A. flavus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. ochraceus</italic>. It was previously found that carvacrol was very effective when used against the foodborne pathogen 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus cereus</italic> at 0.15–0.75 μL/g on boiled rice [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], which indicated that EOCs could be used in food or agricultural products to achieve potential antibacterial activity.
</p>
