<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mode of action of EOCs for microbes could be attributed to the changing permeability of cell membranes and walls, as well as to the DNA, to alter gene expression, cellular respiration, and energy metabolism and eventually kill the cells [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. In our current study, we explored citral and geraniol as bioactive agents against 
 <italic class="italic">A. flavus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. ochraceus</italic> for grains and the underlying antifungal mechanisms. 
 <italic class="italic">A. flavus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. ochraceus</italic> were completely inhibited at the MIC of citral and geraniol in vitro, at which growth and metabolism of 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> spp. could not be detected; therefore, we adopted lower concentrations of citral and geraniol for use with the two pathogens to better expound the antifungal action of the EOs’ major components. The modes of antifungal action of citral and geraniol on the common 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> spp. of grain were investigated by evaluating cell membrane permeability, cellular ROS change, and growth and secondary metabolite gene expression. According to the results for relative conductivity, both EOCs showed a better capability of increasing cell membrane permeability in 
 <italic class="italic">A. ochraceus</italic> compared to 
 <italic class="italic">A. flavus</italic>, which led to the leakage of intracellular constituents. It was likely that the leakage was caused by the interaction between antimicrobial ingredients and the cytoplasmic membrane [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The different relative conductivity changes of 
 <italic class="italic">A. ochraceus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. flavus</italic> might be due to the involvement of different components and binding sites of the cell membrane when treated with the same EOC. Meanwhile, the electrical conductivity of 
 <italic class="italic">A. ochraceus</italic> increased by 28.3% and 28.8% after exposure to citral and geraniol, respectively, indicating that the integrity of the cell membrane was partially disrupted. When damage to the cell membrane occurred, more small molecules such as electrolytes were released, causing the higher electrical conductivity to accelerate cell death [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-23-02108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>].
</p>
