<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The bacosides are part of the class of saponin triterpenes which are found predominantly in the extract of 
 <italic>Bacopa monnieri</italic>, from the Scrophulariaceae family [
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. They are known for their therapeutic effects demonstrated in numerous studies, such as: the antioxidant effect and the potential to inhibit the production of superoxides [
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>], the anti-metastatic potential in hepatocellular carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B110-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>], as well as the cicatrizing effect on skin lesions and the potential to accelerate wound closure [
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. In an in vivo study by Sharath et al., the repair effect of bacosides vs. total methanolic extract of 
 <italic>Bacopa monnieri</italic> was evaluated on incision wound models; results showed that bacosides and methanolic extract exhibit a repairing effect similar to the synthetic drug nitrofurosone used as control. The effect on wound healing is presumably due to the astringent and antibacterial effect exerted by bacosides; it has also been noticed that by oral administration of bacosides, collagen deposition in the affected tissue is increased, thus increasing tissue resistance and healing [
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Another in vivo study was performed in order to evaluate the effect of bacosides on the wound healing caused by burns in rabbits; after 28 days of topical application of a bacoside A extract, the levels of collagen, hydroxyproline and hexosamine decreased, as did the size of the wound. Authors hypothesized that the healing effect of bacoside A is due to a complex mechanism of action that involves: (i) changing the structure of collagen fibers; (ii) upregulation or downregulation of beta-1 growth factor and metalloproteinase-1 matrix transformation [
 <xref rid="B112-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>].
</p>
