<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Exp Pharmacol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jexpharm</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Pharmacology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1454</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7815069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">285079</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JEP.S285079</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>In vitro Antileishmanial Activity of Some Ethiopian Medicinal Plants</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Nigatu et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Nigatu et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nigatu</surname><given-names>Hulubanchi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Belay</surname><given-names>Alemnesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ayalew</surname><given-names>Hiwot</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>Besufekad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>Alemu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tewabe</surname><given-names>Yitagesu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4020-9813</contrib-id><name><surname>Degu</surname><given-names>Abel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry and Pharmacognosy, <institution>School of Pharmacy, College of Health Sciences, Addis Ababa University</institution>, <addr-line>Addis Ababa</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmacology and Clinical Pharmacy, <institution>School of Pharmacy, College of Health Sciences, Addis Ababa University</institution>, <addr-line>Addis Ababa</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Hiwot Ayalew <institution>Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry and Pharmacognosy, School of Pharmacy, Addis Ababa University</institution>, <addr-line>P.O. Box 1176</addr-line>, <addr-line>Addis Ababa</addr-line><country>Ethiopia</country> Email hiwia444@gmail.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 Nigatu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Nigatu et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#x02013; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="s2001" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Leishmaniasis is a group of diseases caused by protozoan parasites, which remains a burden for developing countries. The lack of a vaccine as well as the emergence of resistance toward the recommended drugs pose a challenge for the control of the disease. This urges the demand for new antileishmanial agents to prevent and treat this disease. Consequently, four Ethiopian plants were selected and tested for their antileishmanial activity against two Leishmanial parasites.</p></sec><sec id="s2002"><title>Methods</title><p>Methanol (80%) was used to macerate the plant materials. In vitro antipromastigote activity of the crude extracts was then tested against promastigotes and axenically cultured amastigotes of <italic>Leishmania aethiopica</italic> and <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic> clinical isolates using Alamar Blue assay, and cell viability was measured fluorometrically. 1% DMSO and the media were used as a negative control while amphotericin B was used as a positive control. Furthermore, preliminary phytochemical analysis of the extracts was performed.</p></sec><sec id="s2003"><title>Results</title><p>From the four plants&#x02019; extracts, <italic>Ferula communis</italic> and <italic>Otostegia integrifolia</italic> showed better activity with IC<sub>50</sub> value of 11.38&#x000b1;0.55 and 13.03&#x000b1;0.87 &#x000b5;g/mL against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic>, respectively. However, the same plant extracts exhibited lower activity against <italic>L. donovani</italic> with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 23.41&#x000b1;2.32 and 17.24&#x000b1;1.29 &#x000b5;g/mL, respectively. <italic>O. integrifolia</italic> exhibited highest effect against amastigotes of <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>: 16.84&#x000b1;0.65) and <italic>L. donovani</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>:14.55&#x000b1;0.38). <italic>F. communis</italic> resulted second highest in growth inhibition against amastigotes of <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic> with IC<sub>50</sub> value of 14.32&#x000b1;0.54 and 31.12&#x000b1;0.19, respectively. The phytochemical analysis of the extracts indicated the presence of phenol, flavonoids, tannins, saponins, terpenoids, and alkaloids.</p></sec><sec id="s2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The findings from this study demonstrate that crude extracts of <italic>F. communis</italic> and <italic>O. integrifolia</italic> showed promising antileishmanial activity against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic> that may be attributed to the presence of different secondary metabolites.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>antileishmanial activity</kwd><kwd>in vitro</kwd><kwd><italic>Leishmania aethiopica</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Leishmania donovani</italic></kwd><kwd>medicinal plants</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>funding</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>No specific funding was granted for this project.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="10"/><ref-count count="31"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Leishmaniasis is a protozoan parasitic disease caused by the genus <italic>Leishmania</italic>. There are more than 20 <italic>Leishmania</italic> species<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> which are mainly transmitted to humans via the vector of infected female <italic>Phlebotomus</italic> and <italic>Lutzomyia</italic> sand-flies.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> More than 70 animal species including mammals serve as a host or reservoir, including humans, in the transmission of the parasite.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></p><p>The disease is endemic in 98 countries, most of which are developing countries.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> According to World Health Organization&#x02019;s fact sheet on leishmaniasis, approximately 20,000&#x02013;30,000 deaths and 0.7&#x02013;1 million new cases of leishmaniasis occur per annum.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> From the three main forms of the disease, an estimated 50, 000 to 90, 000 new cases of visceral leishmaniasis (VL) and 600, 000 to 1 million new cases of cutaneous leishmaniasis (CL) occur worldwide annually. Furthermore, more than 90% of mucocutaneous leishmaniasis (MCL) cases occur in Bolivia, Brazil, Ethiopia and Peru. In Ethiopia, the disease burden is huge, where the country is highly affected by both VL and MCL, with an estimated 4500 to 5000 new cases of VL per year.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Besides, the four <italic>Leishmania</italic> species <italic>L. aethiopica, L. donovani, L. major</italic>, and <italic>L. tropica</italic> are common in the country.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></p><p>Given that there is still no vaccine available for use in humans, the treatment of leishmaniasis mainly depends on chemotherapy. However, there has been development of resistance toward first line drugs. In addition, the second line drugs have severe adverse effects and are costly in resource-limited areas.<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> This urges the demand for new antileishmanial agents to prevent and treat this disease. Moreover, researchers&#x02019; attention is being drawn toward naturally derived compounds used to treat parasitic diseases including leishmaniasis for identification of new lead compounds and/or new drugs against the disease which warrant investigation.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p><p>The use of plants as alternative medicine in Ethiopia has been a long-standing practice for centuries. In fact in Ethiopia, for 70%-80% of its people and around 90% of domestic animals, traditional medicines are used as a primary source of treatment.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Consequently, the following plants of interest were selected; <italic>Discopodium peninervium</italic> Hochst (Solanaceae) also called &#x0201c;Ameraro&#x0201d; in Amharic,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
<italic>Ferula communis</italic> L. (Apiaceae) identified colloquially as &#x0201c;Doge&#x0201d;,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
<italic>Otostegia integrifolia</italic> Benth (Lamiaceae) locally recognized as &#x0201c;Tinjuit&#x0201d;,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and <italic>Urtica simensis</italic> Hochst. ex. A. Rich. (Urticaceae) also called &#x0201c;Samma&#x0201d; in Amharic.<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></p><p>The aforementioned herbs were selected for their traditional use as treatment for skin and wound infection which is ostensibly similar to the manifestations of leishmaniasis.<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Besides, similar antileishmanial activities were reported within the genus of these plants.<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14&#x02013;16</xref> Therefore, in this study, in vitro antileishmanial activity and phytochemical analysis of 80% methanolic extracts of each plant were investigated.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001"><title>Collection and Authentication of Plant Materials</title><p>Fresh leaves of <italic>D. peninervium, O. integrifolia, U. simensis</italic> and roots of <italic>F. communis</italic> were collected from Semien Shewa Ensaro woreda (Latitude: 9&#x000b0; 49&#x002b9; 59.99&#x0201d; N Longitude: 39&#x000b0; 00&#x002b9; 0.00&#x0201d; E) 139 km away from Addis Ababa, in September, 2019. The identification and authenticity of the plant materials was confirmed at the National Herbarium, Department of Biology, Addis Ababa University. The voucher specimen; <italic>D. peninervium</italic> (HA001), <italic>O. integrifolia</italic> (AD001), <italic>U. simensis</italic> (HA003) and <italic>F. communis</italic> (HA002) was deposited for future reference. The collected parts of plants were separated, washed with tap water, and left to dry in shade. Dried parts of plants were grounded to a coarse powder and stored in a desiccator at room temperature until further use.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002"><title>Preparation of Plant Extracts</title><p>The powdered plant materials (250 g) were macerated using 80% methanol (3 &#x000d7; 2 L, 72 h each). Then the plant extracts were filtered and the methanol in the filtrate was removed using a rotary evaporator (Buchi, Switzerland). The concentrated extract was dried with a lyophilizer (Wagtech, Denmark). Finally, the crude extracts of <italic>D. peninervium, O. integrifolia, U. simensis</italic> and <italic>F. communis</italic> yielded 12.5%, 16.6%, 24.4%, and 10.15% respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003"><title>In vitro Antileishmanial Activity Test</title><sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001"><title>Cell Culture</title><p>In vitro antipromastigote activity test was carried out against the promastigote stage of clinical isolates of L. aethiopica and L. donovani. The two clinical isolates were grown in tissue culture flasks containing RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal calf serum, 100 IU penicillin/mL (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany) and 100 &#x003bc;g/mL streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany) solution at 22&#x000b0;C for L. aethiopica and 24&#x000b0;C for L. donovani.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> A cell-free medium was used to grow parasites in vitro and to set up the test system for determination of the IC<sub>50</sub> values.</p><p>From late stationary phase promastigotes (3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL) axenically cultured amastigotes were acquired. Using medium 199 with Hank&#x02019;s salts supplemented with 20% FBS, 2 mM L-glutamine, 50 IU/mL penicillin, and 50 &#x003bc;g/mL streptomycin, the cells were centrifuged and then resuspended. After that, by using 1 N HCl, the pH was made to 5.5. Following incubation of cells at 31<sup>&#x000b0;</sup>C for <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and 37<sup>&#x000b0;</sup>C for <italic>L. donovani</italic> at 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, amastigote-like rounded morphology together with loss of flagella and cell clumping started appearing within 24 h. The parasites were kept for a week as some motile parasites with intermediate forms and short flagella were detected. The human monocytic leukemia cell line THP-1 cells were incubated in RPMI 1640 medium plus 10% hi-FCS and 20 ng/mL phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA; Sigma) at 37<sup>&#x000b0;</sup>C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 72 h. A cell-free medium was used to grow parasites in vitro and to set up the test system for determination of the IC<sub>50</sub> values of the extracts.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0002-s2004"><title>In vitro Antileishmanial Assay</title><p>Each of the plant extracts was added to a separate 96-well microtiter plate containing 100 &#x000b5;Lcomplete culture medium to achieve a final concentration of 100 &#x000b5;g/mL. Then, a suspension of 100 &#x000b5;L of the parasites (3.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> promastigotes of <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> or <italic>L. donovani</italic>) obtained from the previous culture was added to each well. After that, parasites were incubated for 72 hrs at room temperature for promastigotes of both strains, at 31&#x000b0;C and 37&#x000b0;C for axenically cultured amastigotes of <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> or <italic>L. donovani</italic> respectively, in the presence of various concentrations of extract. Next, resazurin (0.125 mg/mL) was added to 20 &#x000b5;L suspension (10% of the total volume of each well). The mixture was covered with aluminum foil, and left at the previously stated temperature. Fluorescence intensity was measured using Victor 3 Multilabel Counter (PerkinElmer, MA, USA) at excitation wavelength of 544 nm and emission wavelength of 590 nm. The assay was conducted in triplicate and compared to negative controls (1% DMSO and Media alone) and reference drug (Amphotericin B, Sigma-Aldrich, Germany). During the assay, cell viability was monitored by measuring fluorescent signal. The fluorescence intensities produced are proportional to the number of viable cells.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2005"><title>Cytotoxicity Study in THP-1 Monocyte</title><p>Onto 96-well plates, THP-1 monocytes were plated at a density of 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cells per well (in 200 volume) in the presence or absence of plant extracts, and plates were incubated at 37<sup>&#x000b0;</sup>C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 72 h. Then Alamar Blue was added, during the last 3 h of incubation, cell viability was measured fluorometrically as described previously.<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2006"><title>Phytochemical Screening</title><p>The 80% methanol extracts of each plant were investigated for the presence or absence of secondary metabolites such as alkaloids, flavonoids, phenols, saponins, tannins, and terpenoids following standard procedures.<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2007"><title>Determination of Total Phenols</title><p>Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu&#x02019;s method was used to determine the total phenolic content of the extracts. Serial dilutions of the standard (gallic acid) were prepared in distilled water with concentrations 100, 50, 25, 12.5, 6.75 and 3.375 &#x000b5;g/mL, to establish calibration curve. 1 mL of the standard was then transferred into test tubes. After that, 5 mL of distilled water and 0.5 mL of Folin&#x02013;Ciocalteu&#x02019;s reagent were added into the test tubes. 5 minutes later, 1.5 mL of Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> (20%) was added and the volume made up to 10 mL with distilled water. It was allowed to stand for 90 minutes at ambient temperature. The absorbance of the solution was measured at 760 nm using a UV spectrophotometer (Jenway Model 6500, England). Every experiment was conducted in triplicate. Similar procedure was also followed for the extracts (100 &#x000b5;g/mL) and the blank solutions. The total phenolic content was determined using a standard curve of gallic acid (y = 0.0075x - 0.0862, R2 = 0.9665). The calculated total phenolic results were expressed as mg of gallic acid equivalent per 100 g of extracts.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2008"><title>Determination of Total Flavonoid Content (TFC)</title><p>Aluminum chloride complex forming assay was employed to determine the total flavonoid content of the extracts. Serial dilutions of the standard (Quercetin) were prepared in methanol with concentrations 1, 0.50, 0.25, 0.125 and 0.065 mg/mL, to establish calibration curve. 1 mL of the standard was then transferred into test tubes. 0.3 mL 5% NaNO<sub>2</sub> was added and left for 5 minutes. Another 0.3 mL of 10% AlCl<sub>3</sub> was mixed with the solution and allowed to stand for 5 minutes. After that, 2 mL solution of 1M NaOH was added into the solution followed by quantity sufficient distilled water to make up the volume to 10 mL. Finally the solution was incubated for 30 minutes at ambient temperature. The absorbance of the solution was recorded at 510 nm on UV spectrophotometer (Jenway Model 6500, England). The same procedure was repeated with the extract (1 mg/mL) and the blank solutions. The total flavonoid content was determined using a standard curve of quercetin (y=0.5957x - 0.0055, R2 = 0.9982). The calculated total flavonoid results were expressed as mg of quercetin equivalent per 100 g of extracts. All the procedures were performed in triplicate.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2009"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Antileishmanial activity (IC<sub>50</sub>) values were calculated from sigmoidal dose-response curves of percent inhibition using the computer software GraphPad Prism 8.4.3 (GraphPad Sofware, Inc., CA, USA), and Microsoft excel; values were expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD of triplicate experiments.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0003-s2001"><title>Antileishmanial Assay</title><p>The methanolic extracts of all the plants showed activity against promastigotes and axenically cultured amastigotes of <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic> with varying IC<sub>50</sub> values (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Antipromastigote Activity IC<sub>50</sub> Values and Percent Inhibition of the Plant Extracts Against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant Extracts</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Inhibition (100 &#x000b5;g/mL) Against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Inhibition (100 &#x000b5;g/mL) Against <italic>L. donovani</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;(&#x000b5;g/mL)<sup>a</sup> Against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;(&#x000b5;g/mL)<sup>a</sup> Against <italic>L. donovani</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D. peninervium</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.88&#x000b1;0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.27&#x000b1;0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.38&#x000b1;1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.62&#x000b1;1.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F. communis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.47&#x000b1;1.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.57&#x000b1;1.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.38&#x000b1;0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.41&#x000b1;2.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>O. integrifolia</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.78&#x000b1;0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.40&#x000b1;1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.03&#x000b1;1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.24&#x000b1;0.87</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>U. simensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.91&#x000b1;0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.99&#x000b1;0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.78&#x000b1;0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.37&#x000b1;1.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amphotericin B (Reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21&#x000b1;0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31&#x000b1;0.065</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Media alone (NC)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1% DMSO (NC)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Values are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD; n = 3. <sup>a</sup>Effective concentration required to achieve 50% growth inhibition in &#x000b5;g/mL; <sup>b</sup>no effect.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NC, negative control; DMSO, dimethyl sulphoxide.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>IC<sub>50</sub> Values and Percent Inhibition of the Plant Extracts Against Axenically Cultured Amastigotes of <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant Extracts</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Inhibition (100 &#x000b5;g/mL) Against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Inhibition (100 &#x000b5;g/mL) Against <italic>L. donovani</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;(&#x000b5;g/mL)<sup>a</sup> Against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;(&#x000b5;g/mL)<sup>a</sup> Against <italic>L. donovani</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytotoxic Effect in THP-1 LC<sub>50</sub> (&#x000b5;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D. peninervium</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.98&#x000b1;0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.6&#x000b1;0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.13&#x000b1;2.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.52&#x000b1;0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>186.01&#x000b1; 0.08</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F. communis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.64&#x000b1;0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.39&#x000b1;1.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.32&#x000b1;0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.12&#x000b1;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.22&#x000b1; 0.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>O. integrifolia</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.31&#x000b1;0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.58&#x000b1;0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.84&#x000b1;0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.55&#x000b1;0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.55&#x000b1; 0.49</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>U. simensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.35&#x000b1;0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.39&#x000b1;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.37&#x000b1;1.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.30&#x000b1;1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.11&#x000b1; 0.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amphotericin B (Reference)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22&#x000b1;0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.461&#x000b1;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.32&#x000b1; 0.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Media alone (NC)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1% DMSO (NC)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: Values are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD; n = 3. <sup>a</sup>Effective concentration required to achieve 50% growth inhibition in &#x000b5;g/mL; <sup>b</sup>no effect.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: NC, negative control; DMSO, dimethyl sulphoxide.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Antipromastigote activity of the plant extracts against <italic>Leishmania aethiopica</italic> (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic> (<bold>B</bold>).</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="JEP-13-15-g0001"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: DP, <italic>Discopodium peninervium</italic>; FC, <italic>Ferula communis</italic>; OI, <italic>Otostegia integrifolia</italic>; US, <italic>Urtica simensis</italic>.</attrib></fig><fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effects of plant extracts on axenically cultured amastigotes against <italic>Leishmania aethiopica</italic> (<bold>A</bold>) and <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic> (<bold>B</bold>).</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="JEP-13-15-g0002"/><attrib><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: DP, <italic>Discopodium peninervium</italic>; FC, <italic>Ferula communis</italic>; OI, <italic>Otostegia integrifolia</italic>; US, <italic>Urtica simensis</italic>.</attrib></fig></p><p>Of all the extracts, <italic>O. integrifolia</italic> exhibited highest antipromastigote activity with percentage inhibition of 71.78% and 71.40% (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) with maximum tested concentration (ie, 100 &#x000b5;g/mL) against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic> respectively. At this concentration, <italic>O. integrifolia</italic> exerted similar effect against the amastigotes of <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic> with percentage inhibition of 67.31% and 70.58% respectively (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). <italic>F. communis</italic> also exerted comparable antipromastigote activity with percentage inhibition of 68.47% and 63.57% against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic> respectively. While the same plant exerted slightly lower activity against the amastigotes of both Leishmanial species (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>However, all the extracts showed lower activity as compared to amphotericin B which exhibited IC<sub>50</sub> of 1.21&#x000b1;0.11&#x000b5;g/mL and 1.31&#x000b1;0.065 &#x000b5;g/mL (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic> correspondingly.</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2002"><title>Preliminary Phytochemical Analysis</title><p>The result found from the investigations revealed the presence of different secondary metabolites such as alkaloids, flavonoids, phenols, saponins, tannins and terpenoids in the plant extracts as summarized in <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Phytochemical Screening of 80% Methanol Extracts of Tested Plants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phytochemicals</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D. peninervium</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F. communis</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>O. integrifolia</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>U. simensis</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkaloids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saponins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tannins</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Note</bold>: (+) present, (&#x02212;) not present.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="s0003-s2003"><title>Determination of Total Phenols and Flavonoid Content</title><p>The highest total phenol content was found from <italic>D. peninervium</italic> (0.43 mg of GAE/g extract) followed by <italic>O. integrifolia</italic> (0.39 mg of GAE/g extract) as indicated in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3 A</xref>. Similarly, the highest amount of flavonoids was measured with <italic>D. peninervium</italic> (0.38 mg of QE/g extract) while <italic>F. communis and O. integrifolia</italic> contained comparable amounts of flavonoids, 0.2 and 0.18 mg of QE/g extract respectively as depicted in <xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3B</xref>.<table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Total Phenolic and Flavonoid Content of 80% Methanol Extracts of Tested Plants</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plant</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenol (mg of GAE/g)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoid (mg of QE/g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D. peninervium</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43&#x000b1;0.0031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#x000b1;0.0059</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F. communis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#x000b1;0.0032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2&#x000b1;0.0012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>O. integrifolia</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39&#x000b1;0.0025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#x000b1;0.0032</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>U. simensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2&#x000b1;0.0021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078&#x000b1;0.0003</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0006"><p><bold>Note</bold>: Values are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD; n = 3.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Total phenol (<bold>A</bold>) and flavonoid (<bold>B</bold>) contents of 80% methanol plant extracts.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="JEP-13-15-g0003"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Leishmaniasis is a widespread health burden in developing countries like Ethiopia. This is partly attributed to undernourishment as a result of poverty, compromised immunity, as well as unresponsiveness of the disease to recommended drugs.<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> Therefore, it is vital to search for alternative drugs from medicinal plants. Accordingly, the present study was carried out to search for the antipromastigote potential of some Ethiopian medicinal plants that are used in folk medicine.</p><p>The four crude extracts showed antipromastigote activity against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and <italic>L. donovani</italic>. However, all the plant extracts exerted lower activity than the reference drug; amphotericin B (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">B</xref>).</p><p>The highest antipromastigote activity was recorded for <italic>F. communis</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>=11.38&#x000b1;0.55 &#x000b5;g/mL). The extract also halted the growth of <italic>L. donovani</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>=23.41&#x000b1;2.32 &#x000b5;g/mL) (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). There are studies that stated similar activities of members of the genus <italic>Ferula</italic>. The hydroalcoholic extract of <italic>F. asafetida</italic> and essential oil from <italic>F. galbaniflua</italic> arrested the growth of <italic>L. major</italic> (I<italic>C<sub>50</sub></italic>=11.8 &#x000b5;g/mL)<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> and <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>/24hr=95.70 &#x000b5;g/mL) respectively.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></p><p><italic>O. integrifolia</italic> exhibited highest effect against <italic>L. donovani</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>=17.24&#x000b1;0.87 &#x000b5;g/mL) as compared to other extracts. In addition, the extract displayed activity against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>=13.03&#x000b1;1.29 &#x000b5;g/mL) (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Mothana et al reported growth inhibition of hydroalcoholic extract of <italic>O. fruticosa</italic> against <italic>L. infantum</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub> &#x0003e;64.0 &#x000b5;g/mL).<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></p><p><italic>D. peninervium</italic> showed comparable activity against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub><italic>=13.38&#x000b1;1.20</italic> &#x000b5;g/mL) as that of <italic>O. integrifolia,</italic> while it exhibited lower activity against <italic>L. donovani</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub><italic>=63.62&#x000b1;1.84</italic> &#x000b5;g/mL) (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In another study, the essential oil from the same plant exhibited better activity against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>=12.62 &#x003bc;g/mL) and <italic>L. donovani</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub>=19.93 &#x003bc;g/mL).<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></p><p>On the other hand, <italic>U. simensis</italic> showed lowest result with IC<sub>50</sub> value of 63.78&#x000b1;0.89 &#x003bc;g/mL against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and 44.37&#x000b1;1.61 &#x003bc;g/mL against <italic>L. donovani</italic> (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The aqueous extract of <italic>U. dioica</italic> halted the growth of <italic>L. major</italic> promastigotes with IC<sub>50</sub> of 4500 &#x003bc;g/mL.<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p><p>However, no study has reported on the effect of the studied plant extracts against <italic>L. aethiopica</italic> and L. <italic>donovani</italic> axenic amastigotes.</p><p>The phytochemical screening of the four extracts revealed the presence of various phytochemical constituents, ie, phenols, flavonoids and terpenoids (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Phenols were reported to possess antipromastigote activity. For instance, rosmarinic acid tested against <italic>L. donovani</italic> promastigotes and intracellular amastigotes resulted in altered membrane integrity of the mitochondria and the cells.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Flavonoids were also found to exert significant antileishmanial activity against <italic>L. donovani</italic>.<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> In an attempt to decipher the mechanism of antileishmanial activity of flavonoids, catechins; type of flavonoid were found to form complexes with the parasite cell wall to influence processes requiring cell linking, and hence inhibit the parasite growth.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Meanwhile, intracellular activities were reported for quercetin that inhibited enzyme topoisomerase II and chelated iron which is used in the replication of the parasite within the macrophage phagolysosomes.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p><p>Nerolidol, a terpenoid commonly found in many plants exerts antileishmanial activity against <italic>L. amazonensis</italic> via inhibition of various biochemical pathways such as biosynthesis of dolichol, ergosterol, and ubiquinones.<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> In addition, a triterpenoid dihydrobetulinic acid inhibited the growth of <italic>L. donovani</italic> amastigotes by targeting DNA topoisomerase I and II preventing DNA cleavage via forming enzyme&#x02013;DNA complex, leading to apoptosis. Thus, the antileishmanial activity of the plant extracts, which are rich in phenols, flavonoids and terpenoids, may possibly be due to the specific components and/or synergistic interaction among various principles.<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study showed 80% methanol extracts from <italic>O. integrifolia</italic> and <italic>F. communis</italic> exhibited promising in vitro antileishmanial activity. This not only corroborates the traditional claim of the plants, it also provides clues for further examination of active principles of these plants for the development of effective and safe antileishmanial drugs.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors are thankful to Mr. Melaku Wondafrash, Addis Ababa University, for identification of the plant material. The authors are thankful to department of microbiology, immunology and parasitology, faculty of medicine, college of health sciences for providing the laboratory setting.</p></ack><sec id="s0006"><title>Abbreviations</title><p>CL, cutaneous leishmaniasis; DMSO, dimethyl sulfoxide; IC<sub>50</sub>, the half maximal inhibitory concentration; MCL, mucocutaneous leishmaniasis; VL, visceral leishmaniasis.</p></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Data Sharing Statement</title><p>The data used to support the findings of this study will be available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="s0008"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to data analysis, drafting, or revising the article, have agreed on the journal to which the article will be submitted, gave final approval of the version to be published, and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="s0009" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest for this work and declare that there is no conflict of interest regarding the publication of this article.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>WHO</collab> (<year>2020</year>) <source><italic toggle="yes">Leishmaniasis</italic></source>, <comment>Available at</comment>: <italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/factsheets/detail/leishmaniasis">https://www.who.int/news-room/factsheets/detail/leishmaniasis</ext-link></italic>
<date-in-citation>Accessed <day>12</day><month>4</month> 2020</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alemayehu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alemayehu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Leishmaniasis: a review on parasite, vector and reservoir host</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Health Science Journal</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21767/1791-809X.1000519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McGwire</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Satoskar</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Leishmaniasis: clinical syndromes and treatment. QJM</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Didwania</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shadab</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sabur</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ali</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Shadab, M., Sabur, A. and Ali, N. Alternative to Chemotherapy&#x02014;The Unmet Demand against Leishmaniasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Immunol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1779</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2017.01779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29312309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Leta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dao</surname>
<given-names>THT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mesele</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alemayehu</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghedin</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Visceral Leishmaniasis in Ethiopia: an Evolving Disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e3131</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25188253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Assefa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Leishmaniasis in Ethiopia: A systematic review and meta-analysis of prevalence in animals and humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Heliyon</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e00723</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2018.e00723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30101202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ghorbani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farhoudi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Leishmaniasis in humans: drug or vaccine therapy?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">Drug Des Devel Ther</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/DDDT.S146521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ayalew</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solomon Tadesse</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindemann</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tewabe</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hailu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chemical Composition</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>In Vitro Antipromastigotes Activity of Essential Oil of the Leaves of <italic>Discopodium pennnervium</italic> Hochst</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EPJ</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chekole</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used against human ailments in Gubalafto District, Northern Ethiopia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-017-0182-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28978342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Geyid</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abebe</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Debella</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Screening of some medicinal plants of Ethiopia for their anti-microbial properties and chemical profiles</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Ethnopharmacol</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>427</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2004.08.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15740876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Getahun</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Some Common Medicinal and Poisonous Plants Used in Ethiopian Folk Medicine</italic></source>. <publisher-loc>Addis Ababa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Faculty of Science, Addis Ababa University</publisher-name>; <year>1976</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Enyew</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asfaw</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelbessa</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagappan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ethnobotanical study of traditional medicinal plants in and around Fiche District, Central Ethiopia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Res J Pharm Biol Chem Sci</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yineger</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelbessa</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bekele</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lulekal</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Plants used in traditional management of human ailments at Bale Mountains National Park, Southeastern Ethiopia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Plants Res</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ramzi</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nawal</surname>
<given-names>A-M-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohamed</surname>
<given-names>A-AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Louis</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of the <italic>in vitro</italic> antiplasmodial, antipromastigotes, and antitrypanosomal activity of medicinal plants used in saudi and yemeni traditional medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<fpage>905639</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/905639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24963330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Badirzadeh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heidari-Kharaji</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fallah-Omrani</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dabiri</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Araghi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salimi Chirani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antileishmanial activity of <italic>Urtica dioica</italic> extract against zoonotic cutaneous leishmaniasis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e0007843</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31929528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Essid</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rahali</surname>
<given-names>FZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Msaada</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Antileishmanial and cytotoxic potential of essential oils from medicinal plants in Northern Tunisia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ind Crop Prod</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>795</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2015.09.049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tewabe</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kefarge</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Belay</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bisrat</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hailu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asres</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antipromastigotes Evaluation of the Leaf Latex of Aloe macrocarpa, Aloin A/B, and Its Semisynthetic Derivatives against Two Leishmania Species</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<fpage>2019</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>WC</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pharmacopoeial and Related Drugs of Biological Origin. Text Book of Pharmacognosy</italic></source>. <edition>13th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Bailiere-Tindall Ltd</publisher-name>; <year>1989</year>:<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>383</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Teng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Total phenolic, flavonoid content, and antioxidant activity of bulbs, leaves, and flowers made from Eleutherine bulbosa (Mill.) Urb</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Food Sci Nutr</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>154</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estimation of flavonoid, polyphenolic content and in vitro antioxidant capacity of leaves of Tephrosia purpurea Linn. (Leguminosae)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pharma Sci and Res</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>66</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Van Griensven</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gadisa</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aseffa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hailu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beshah</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diro</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Treatment of cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by Leishmania aethiopica: a systematic review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iranshahi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arfa</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramezani</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Sesquiterpene coumarins from Ferula szowitsiana and in vitro antileishmanial activity of 7-prenyloxycoumarins against promastigotes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Phytochemistry</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>554</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>561</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2006.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17196626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Andrade</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Azevedo</surname>
<given-names>CDS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Motta</surname>
<given-names>FN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Essential oils: in vitro activity against Leishmania amazonensis, cytotoxicity and chemical composition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Complement Altern Med</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>444</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1401-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27825341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mothana</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Musayeib</surname>
<given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Ajmi</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cos</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maes</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of the in vitro antiplasmodial, antileishmanial, and antitrypanosomal activity of medicinal plants used in Saudi and Yemeni traditional medicine</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<fpage>2014</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ayalew</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solomon Tadesse</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindemann</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Chemical composition and in vitro antileishmanial activity of essential oil of the leaves of Discopodium pennnervium Hochst</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EPJ</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Antwi</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amisigo</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adjimani</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gwira</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rafati</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>In vitro activity and mode of action of phenolic compounds on <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e0007206</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30802252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tasdemir</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kaiser</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brun</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yardley</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tosun</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antitrypanosomal and Antileishmanial Activities of Flavonoids and Their Analogues: in Vitro, In Vivo, Structure-Activity Relationship, and Quantitative Structure-Activity Relationship Studies</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1364</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.50.4.1352-1364.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16569852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ogeto</surname>
<given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Odhiambo</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shivairo</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Antipromastigotes activity of Aloe secundiflora plant extracts against Leishmania major</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adv Life Sci Tech</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>De Arias</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pandolfi</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Celeste Vega</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rol&#x000f3;n</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Selected natural and synthetic phenolic compounds with antileishmanial activity: a five-year review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Curr Bioact Compd</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>333</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1573407211208040002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Arruda</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D&#x02019;Alexandri</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katzin</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uliana</surname>
<given-names>SRB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antileishmanial activity of the terpene nerolidol</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1687</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.49.5.1679-1687.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chowdhury</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mandal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goswami</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Dihydrobetulinic acid induces apoptosis in Leishmania donovani by targeting DNA topoisomerase I and II: implications in antileishmanial therapy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Molecular Medicine</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>):<fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03402104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12765337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>