<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Domesticated apple (
 <italic class="italic">Malus</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">domestica</italic> Borkh.) is one of the most important fruit crops worldwide. According to FAOSTAT (2018) [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-07-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>], the world production of apple in the last five decades has increased by 424% from 17.0 million tons in 1961 to 89.3 million tons in 2016. Leading production nations include (in descending order) China, USA, Poland, Turkey, Iran, Italy, Russia, Uzbekistan, and Ukraine. There are hundreds of apple cultivars, but only five currently dominate world production: Fuji, Golden Delicious, Delicious, Granny Smith, and Gala. Currently, dessert apples are processed into many food products including juice (2.1 million liters among the 28 European Union member states (EU-28)) [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-07-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>], apple sauce, slices (dried, frozen and canned) and cider (sweet and hard) (1.4 million liters in the EU-28) [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-07-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. The increased production of apples as well as burgeoning demand for plant-derived food products have resulted in dramatic increase of waste. The food processing sector contributes the most to food waste—in 2012, this was estimated to be 17 million tons or 19% of a total amount of 87.6 million tons of food waste generated in the EU-28, based on data provided by Fusions EU Project [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-07-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. In large-scale apple juice production, 75% of the apple are utilized for juice, while the remaining 25% are discarded as waste or utilized rather inefficiently [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-07-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. These by-products may be processed and further incorporated as ingredients in making high-value functional food products (cereal bars, cookies, muffins, bread and fermented milk products) with many physiological and biochemical effects [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-07-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>].
</p>
