<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The studies were conducted in laboratory conditions at 29° ± 1 °C with 60 ± 5% relative humidity (RH). Ten-day-old, adult beetles of 
 <italic>S. oryzae</italic> used in the tests were obtained from breeding colonies kept under the same conditions as experimental colonies. The methodology of emigration (repellence) developed by Kłyś [
 <xref rid="B41-insects-11-00836" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] was used in the emigration tests. Sets containing two plastic breeding containers were used: an inside container with a 28 cm
 <sup>2</sup> of floor area, and an outside container with a 50 cm
 <sup>2</sup> floor area. Forty grams of wheat grain were placed in each container. Wheat grain was the food and place for egg laying for 
 <italic>S. oryzae</italic>. The containers were tightly sealed with perforated lids. The inside container had 30 holes of 1.5 mm in diameter separated by 1.5-cm spaces in the floor and sidewalls up to the level of the grain. Four 4-cm-high “screw inserts” were mounted onto the bottom of the inside container, allowing for the placement of the container above the wheat grain in the outside container, which prevented migrating beetles from returning to the inside container. The insects were placed in the inside container together with a circular ring of filter paper soaked with the caraway essential oil in the subsequent series of mass concentrations of 0.1, 0.5 and 1%, and with L-carvone in 0.05, 0.1, 0.5 and 1% concentrations. The insects were put into the inside container, numbering 40 pieces in each variant of the experiment and in each of its replications. The soaked filter paper disc had no contact with the wheat and was placed over the wheat. The circular ring of filter paper soaked in the substance remained effective throughout our study period. The emigration of insects from the internal to the external container was considered as the repellency. The caraway essential oil and L-carvone (liquid substances) were bought from Sigma–Aldrich and were applied without dilution. Their respective weight concentrations were calculated and weighed. The repellent effect, mortality and the numbers of emigrating insects were recorded after 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 24 and 48 h of exposure. Each variant of the experiment was conducted in nine repetitions.
</p>
