<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alzheimer’s disease (AD) is the most common neurodegenerative disorder associated with aging that causes memory, thinking and behavior disorders. Currently, FDA-approved anti-AD drugs (rivastigmine, galantamine, donepezil, memantine) are potential effective in the short term but are unable to halt or reverse disease progression (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2019</xref>). In November 2019, Sodium oligomannate received its first approval in China for the treatment of mild to moderate AD to improve cognitive function (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Syed Yahiya, 2020</xref>), therapeutically remodels gut microbiota and suppresses gut bacterial amino acids-shaped neuroinflammation to inhibit AD progression (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2019</xref>), but there is some controversy in China (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Rao, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). In this Research Topic, there are three research articles and two review articles describing the potential efficacy and related mechanisms of medicinal plants for AD or brain aging. An research article by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2019.01041" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Yang et al.</ext-link> evaluated the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> effects of a traditional Chinese medicinal formula named 
 <italic>Yizhiqingxin formula</italic> (YQF) on autophagy, the authors found that YQF could improve spatial learning in APP/PS1 mice and ameliorate the accumulation of Aβ while promoting autophagy 
 <italic>via</italic> mTOR pathway modulation. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2019.01391" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Peng et al.</ext-link>’s article studied the molecular mechanisms of another traditional Chinese medicinal formula, 
 <italic>Baizhu decoction</italic> (BZD) for AD, they found that middle- and high-doses of BZD ameliorated the behavioral aspects of 5xFAD transgenic mice in elevated plus maze, Y maze and Morris water maze tests with reduced BACE1 and PS1, resulting in a reduction of Aβ plaques and oxidative damage. Study by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2019.01529" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Wang et al.</ext-link> showed that β-Asarone, the main constituent of 
 <italic>Acorus tatarinowii Schott</italic>, significantly dose-dependently increased cell proliferation and decreased cytotoxicity, inhibited SA-bGal and improved cell senescence in PC12 cell AD model. In a literature review, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2020.00171" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Balkrishna et al.</ext-link> reviewed the phytochemical profile, pharmacological attributes and medicinal information of 
 <italic>Convolvulus prostratus</italic> (a nootropic herb used in traditional medicinal systems) with comprehensive research gap analysis, 
 <italic>Convolvulus prostratus</italic> is mainly endowed with neuroprotective, nootropic and neuro-modulatory activities without any signs of toxicity and neurodegeneration up to a dose of 2000 mg/kg in mice. Another review article by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphar.2019.01334" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Martínez-Coria et al.</ext-link> analyzed the most important pharmacological actions of 
 <italic>dihydromyricetin</italic> (one of the main flavonoids of some Asian medicinal plants), including its antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and neuroprotective actions, as well as its ability to restore GABA neurotransmission, improve motor and cognitive behavior.
</p>
