<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="fsn3557-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fungi are significant spoilage microorganism of foodstuffs during the storage, rendering them unfit for human consumption by retarding the quality of food. These fungi may produce as secondary metabolites a diverse group of chemical substances known as mycotoxins. Aflatoxins are the most hazardous mycotoxins that contaminate foods. They are produced by fungi such as 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus flavus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus parasiticus</span> (
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> belonged to 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus</span> family). The favorable humidity and temperature for its activity are 80–90% and 36–38°C, respectively (Benavides, Villalobos‐Carvajal, &amp; Reyes, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0005">2012</a>; Kamkar, Karim, Aliabadi, &amp; Khaksar, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0008">2008</a>; Nazzaro, Fratianni, De Martino, Coppola, &amp; De Feo, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0016">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wheat (
  <span class="italic">Tricitum aestivum</span>), one of the most important staple foods used in Iran, is susceptible to fungal attack either in the field or during storage, and adversely affect quality of it that destined for human and livestock. Moreover, mold growth on cheese is a common problem for the cheese manufacturer during ripening and curing as well as for the retailer and consumer during refrigerated storage (Balaguer, Lopez‐Carballo, Catala, Gavara, &amp; Hernandez‐Munoz, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0004">2013</a>; de Elguea‐Culebras et al., 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0006">2016</a>; Reis et al., 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0022">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various chemical and physical methods have been studied for inhibiting the growth of fungi; among them, plant essential oils are known as one of the most effective and natural methods. Plant‐derived spices have been used in foods as flavoring agents. Nevertheless, there are a number of studies that demonstrated these compounds also exhibit antimicrobial activity by interfering and destabilizing the operation of the phospholipids bilayer of the cell membrane, enzyme systems, and genetic material of bacteria (Azizkhani, Misaghi, Basti, Gandomi, &amp; Hosseini, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0002">2013</a>; Kim, Marshall, &amp; Wei, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0009">1995</a>; Zhang &amp; Lokeshwar, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0027">2012</a>). Examples of these antimicrobial spices are garlic, onion, cinnamon, mustard, black pepper, oregano, rosemary, Jamaican pepper, cardamom, and clove (Aguilar‐González, Palou, &amp; López‐Malo, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0001">2015</a>; Li, Shi, Liang, Huang, &amp; Chen, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0010">2014</a>; Manso, Cacho‐Nerin, Becerril, &amp; Nerín, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0013">2013</a>; Ye, Dai, &amp; Hu, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0026">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thyme is a spice plant belonging to the Lamiacea family that geographically grows only in Iran, Pakistan, and Afghanistan. It is known as “Avishan‐e‐Shirazi” in Iran. Carvacrol and thymol are known as main phenolic compounds in its essential oil (EO) composition (Azizkhani et al., 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0002">2013</a>). Clove is small shrub with evergreen and sharp leaves belonging to Myrtaceae family that is native to Indonesia and East Pacific. Eugenol is known as the main phenolic compound in its EO composition which contains 70–90% EO (Nikolić et al., 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0018">2015</a>; Oussalah, Caillet, Saucier, &amp; Lacroix, 
  <a rid="fsn3557-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3557-bib-0019">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study the inhibitory potential of clove and thyme EOs on growth and aflatoxin B
  <sub>1</sub> formation by 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> ATCC 15546 was evaluated in culture media (potato dextrose agar [PDA] and potato dextrose broth [PDB]) and in Iranian ultrafiltered cheese.
 </p>
</sec>
