<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylligenin is produced from pinoresinol via epipinoresinol in 
 <italic>F. intermedia</italic> and 
 <italic>S. alatum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B256-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">256</xref>], whereas 2-episesalatin is produced in 
 <italic>S. alatum</italic> via pluviatilol through consecutive steps of hydroxylation and 
 <italic>O</italic>-methylation [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00883-f010">Figure 10</xref>). Arctigenin is produced from the 
 <italic>O</italic>-methylation of matairesinol in 
 <italic>F. intermedia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B256-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">256</xref>,
 <xref rid="B263-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">263</xref>]. Podophyllotoxin, an aryltetralin lignan with anticancer properties, is produced from matairesinol via pluviatolide in 
 <italic>Linum</italic> and 
 <italic>Podophyllum</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B264-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">264</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00883-f010">Figure 10</xref>). The cytochrome P450 enzyme responsible for matairesinol to pluviatolide via methylenedioxy bridge formation were identified in 
 <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> (CYP719A23) and 
 <italic>P. peltatum</italic> (CYP719A24) by Marques and collaborators [
 <xref rid="B249-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">249</xref>]. The next steps from pluviatolide were published for 
 <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> in 2015 by Lau and Sattely [
 <xref rid="B265-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">265</xref>]. The enzyme 
 <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase (OMT3) catalyzes the methylation of pluviatolide to form 5′-desmethoxy-yatein, which is then hydroxylated by CYP71CU1 to 5′-desmethyl-yatein. The methylation of this intermediate by enzyme OMT1 produces yatein (a native substrate for ring closure) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00883-f010">Figure 10</xref>). The biosynthesis of deoxypodophyllotoxin is catalyzed by the enzyme deoxypodophyllotoxin synthase (2-ODD) from yatein forming the core of the aryltetralin scaffold by oxidative ring closure [
 <xref rid="B265-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">265</xref>]. The next steps to form podophyllotoxin in 
 <italic>P. hexandrum</italic> have not been identified yet. However, Lau and Sattely [
 <xref rid="B265-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">265</xref>] demonstrated that two different P450 enzymes (CYP71BE54 and CYP82D61) produce 4-desmethyl-deoxypodophyllotoxin and 4-desmethyl-epipodophyllotoxin (an etoposide lignan) from deoxypodophyllotoxin, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00883-f010">Figure 10</xref>). In 
 <italic>L. flavum</italic>, the biosynthesis of 6-methoxypodophyllotoxin (a cytotoxic lignan) occurs through deoxypodophyllotoxin via three steps, including a 6-hydroxylase (DOP6H) enzyme, which is a cytochrome P450-dependent monooxygenase, followed by 
 <italic>O</italic>-methylation by β-peltatin 6-
 <italic>O</italic>-methyltransferase (βP6OMT) enzyme and 7-hydroxylation with a yet unknown enzyme [
 <xref rid="B262-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">262</xref>,
 <xref rid="B266-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">266</xref>]. On the other hand, although the enzyme has not been characterized, hydroxylation of carbon 7 of deoxypodophyllotoxin is the putative step that produces podophyllotoxin in various 
 <italic>Linum</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B261-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00883-f010">Figure 10</xref>).
</p>
