<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The biofilm formation is relatively similar from one bacteria species to another, a sequence summarized in four major steps: adhesion, microcolonies development, biofilm maturation, and dispersion [
 <xref rid="B26-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The extracellular matrix production, initiated at microcolonies development and continued all along the maturation of biofilm, has an adhesin function, allowing bacterial communities to form a rigid and stable structure (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antibiotics-09-00830-f001">Figure 1</xref>). These extracellular matrixes are complex environments, essentially composed of water (97%), proteins, nucleic acids, lipids/phospholipids, and exopolysaccharide polymers (EPS), differing according to bacterial species/phenotypes. For instance, (i) 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> produces an EPS mainly represented by cellulose, colanic acid (polymer of glucose, galactose, fucose, and glucuronic acid) and β-1,6-
 <italic>N</italic>-acetyl-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucosamine polymers (PGA) [
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]; (ii) 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> produces at least three types of EPS, mainly alginate (
 <sc>l</sc>-guluronic and 
 <sc>d</sc>-mannuronic acids), Pel (glucose-rich matrix material), and Psl (repeating pentasaccharide units, consisting of 
 <sc>d</sc>-mannose, 
 <sc>l</sc>-rhamnose, and 
 <sc>d</sc>-glucose) that are required for biofilm formation and architecture [
 <xref rid="B29-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]; and (iii) 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> mainly produces a glycocalyx primarily composed of teichoic acids and PGA-based exopolysaccharides called “Polysaccharide Intercellular Antigen” (PIA) composed of β-1,6-linked 
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylglucosamine residues and a lower content of non-
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylated 
 <sc>d</sc>-glucosaminyl residues that contain phosphate and ester-linked succinate [
 <xref rid="B26-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
