<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is widely demonstrated that the change in people’s behavior or lifestyles, oriented towards a healthy and diversified diet associated with moderate physical activity and by breaking down unhealthy habits, significantly reduces the risk of numerous diseases such as cardiovascular disease, diabetes, cancer, etc. Obviously, all diseases, including the so-called lifestyle diseases, have multiple causes and it would be simplistic to charge the entire prevention strategy to the correct lifestyle alone; however, there is no doubt that a diet based on a diversified source of vegetables reduces the incidence of numerous human disorders and diseases. From immemorial times, many vegetables are known to have been used to exert healing properties against human ailments due to their content of secondary active metabolites. In recent years, biological activities, nutritional values, and potential health and therapeutic benefits of several medicinal and edible plants have been intensively explored and investigated and their role in the prevention and mitigation of lifestyle-related disorders has been widely confirmed. In particular, many foods of plant origin and herbal remedies, typical of the tradition of many cultures around the world, possess innumerable beneficial effects. In this Special Issue, the diverse health functions and the various mechanisms of actions of the major bioactive components of tea (
 <italic>Camelia sinensis</italic>), one of the most popular beverages all over the world, have been widely demonstrated by several in vitro, in vivo, and human studies [
 <xref rid="B1-ijms-22-02991" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Seaweed polysaccharides, often recommended as food and food additives, have also been reviewed for their multiple health functions and effectiveness as antioxidants, immune-modulatory, anti-inflammatory, anti-coagulant, and anticancer agents [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-22-02991" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Besides their well-known antioxidant and pro-oxidant activities, natural compounds have been also reported to be involved in anti-mutagenic and/or anti-carcinogenic pathways and to possess several other biological activities. In particular, Costantini et al. showed that the hydroxytyrosol contained in olive oil (
 <italic>Olea europea</italic>) induces the apoptotic death of melanoma cells by increasing ROS levels, p53 and γH2AX expression and by the decrease in AKT expression [
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-22-02991" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. A Thai herbal preparation known as Benja Amarit is capable of inducing apoptotic death in cholangiocarcinoma cells, through the regulation of the nuclear factor-KB (NF-KB) signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-22-02991" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Both hydroxytyrosol and Benja Amarit preparation result in safe and promising therapeutic tools for the treatment of these highly invasive tumors.
</p>
