<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Obesity as a common precursor of many chronic diseases is associated with low-grade chronic inflammation and intestinal dysbiosis [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. It can lead to various metabolism-related problems including cardio- and cerebrovascular diseases, type 2 diabetes, chronic kidney disease, musculoskeletal disorders, and digestive diseases [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], therefore represents a major health problem. Studies have revealed that the gut microbiota plays a crucial role in diet-related obesity and glucose and/or lipid metabolism disorders [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. For example, “obesity-related” and “normal-weight-related” microbiotas exhibit significant differences in their composition and profile and in their ability to utilize glucose and/or lipids in humans and other animals [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Moreover, germ-free animals show a significant increase in body weight and metabolic dysfunctions after receiving gut microbiota isolated from donors with high-fat diet (HFD) induced obesity [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], suggesting a causal relation between gut dysbiosis and obesity. The gut microbiota as one of the predisposing factors of metabolic disorders affects the expression of host genes that regulate energy expenditure and storage especially in livers as the intestinal microbiota determines the development of non-alcoholic fatty liver disease in mice [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], whereas, steatosis is among the most common phenotype of HFD mice [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. More recently, studies revealed that the specific bacterial species 
 <italic class="italic">Akkermansia muciniphila</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">muciniphila</italic>) inversely correlates with obesity and diabetes in both mice and humans [
 <xref rid="pone.0218490.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Thus, the gut microbiota may be crucial for metabolic disease etiology.
</p>
