<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped, positive-sense, single-stranded RNA virus of 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> family. This virus was categorized as a member of 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> genus alongside severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV). Usually, most human cases of coronavirus infection are mild or asymptomatic. However, the outbreak of SARS-CoV in 2003
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. MERS-CoV in 2014
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>, and SARS-CoV-2 rang the alarm bell of the global public health crisis. Currently, there are no specific drugs for the treatment of COVID-19. All drug options are based on the treatment of the related viruses, such as SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, influenza virus, Ebola virus, and HIV-1. Accordingly, several FDA-approved drugs with a broad therapeutic window serve as potential candidates for COVID-19 treatment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. The most promising repurposed drugs included chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>, favipiravir
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>, lopinavir/ritonavir
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>, and remdesivir
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. However, the degree of efficacy and the severe side effects of these drugs were still under controversy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Apart from FDA-approved drugs, natural product-based medicines are gained much attention. The use of Thai traditional herbs, particularly their phytochemicals, has been reported to exert broad-spectrum activities as the anticancer, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant therapeutics, and antivirals
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. This suggests their potential as the anti-SARS-CoV-2 candidates.
</p>
