<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Herbal therapies are proven safe and effective for healing diseases and have been the potential source for the development of new drugs [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A majority of people in the world rely on herbal therapy [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Phytotherapy is the antecedent of modern drugs, and one-third of the top-selling drugs in the world are plant origins [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. More than 800 plants have been used as remedies for diabetes healing, and the most successful story in drug discovery is isolation of guanidines (analogue of metformin) from 
 <italic>Galega officinalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. A variety of phytochemicals such as flavonoids, phenols, triterpenoids, and alkaloids have shown prominent antidiabetic activity [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The leaf of 
 <italic>Capparis spinosa</italic> L. and 
 <italic>Juglans regia</italic> L. contained phenols and flavonoids (rutin) that showed prominent antidiabetic and antidyslipidemic activity [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Rutin showed strong free radical scavenging and cholinesterase inhibitory activity and reverse kidney and liver injuries [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The leaf gel of 
 <italic>Aloe vera</italic> offers promising results for the development of novel antidiabetic drugs. The leaf gel of this plant has been under clinical trial in prediabetic and type 2 diabetic patients [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Combination of deleterious effects, limited efficacy, and contraindication of current antidiabetic drugs initiate noble antidiabetic drug development to minimize DM progression and deleterious effects [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
