<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Silk fibroin (SF) nanofibers were largely employed in the biomedical field due to their valuable properties, such as biocompatibility, electrospinnability, low inflammatory response, and therapeutic features [
 <xref rid="B176-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>]. SF/PEO nanofibers, incorporating Manuka honey [
 <xref rid="B177-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>], have been successfully fabricated by electrospinning and evaluated as a potential antimicrobial tissue engineering scaffold [
 <xref rid="B138-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Manuka honey/SF nanofibers exhibited antibacterial properties against methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli,</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Similarly, SF/PVP nanofibers loaded with baicalein, a Chinese herbal extract, were prepared by electrospinning technique and proposed as wound healing devices [
 <xref rid="B139-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. Experimental release displayed that almost 65% of baicalein was delivered within 24 h, reaching the lag phase after 48 h. In addition, in vitro antibacterial test against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> displayed complete inhibition of the pathogen, while in vivo experiments in mice treated with SFP/PVP/baicalein exhibited a significant acceleration of the wound closure process. SF was employed with hyaluronic acid to fabricate nanofibers by coaxial electrospinning [
 <xref rid="B140-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>], an innovative synthetic methodology able to produce nanofibers with sheath/core morphology, utilizing two needles that, coaxially placed, allowed to feed core and shell solutions throughout two different channels. Specifically, the device was structured by a shell of SF, while hyaluronic acid and olive leaf extract, a source of bioactives, formed the core. The analysis of the release profiles showed an almost complete delivery (&gt;90%) in nine days, reaching the lag time after two weeks. Olive leaf extract-loaded nanofibers also revealed remarkable antibacterial features against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> bacteria. The same synthetic methodology was proposed to fabricate core-shell nanofibers from zein (core) and tragacanth gum (shell) [
 <xref rid="B141-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>] for the encapsulation of saffron extract [
 <xref rid="B175-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. Release values in the range 16.1–43.9% after 2 h were recorded in saliva, water, and in media, simulating gastric and intestinal fluids. Zein nanofiber mats loaded with ethanol propolis extracts were also effectively fabricated by the classic electrospinning method, and their antimicrobial activities were investigated against various microorganisms, highlighting that the nanofibers were able to mainly inhibit the growth of the Gram-positive species [
 <xref rid="B142-pharmaceutics-13-00230" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>].
</p>
