<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25" class="p">In this study, we could show that newly emerged workers and foragers might discriminate between the different characteristic 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">vulgaris</italic> terpenes, despite some of them being structurally similar (like carvacrol and thymol). This might also mean that bees (forager) can discriminate between chemotypes and stored nectar/honey types (nurses). The overall EAG responses were much lower for the newly emerged workers than for the forager bees, but response patterns for the different substances were similar for both. This result is consistent with previous studies showing that age and rearing conditions significantly influence antennal response. Right after hatching bees need about 4 days for maturation of EAG responses and show a plastic response to pure and complex odours from the 15
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> day
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, we could show that the antennal response of both revealed three distinct response clusters from low to high, with very low response for the phenolic substances (carvacrol and thymol). Geraniol and geranyl acetate elicited the highest response, which is not surprising as geraniol is a major compound of the Nasanov/aggregation pheromone of honey bees
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>
 </sup> and should therefore be detected with highest sensitivity. Over all substances tested, we measured no difference between the major thyme terpenes (like geraniol) and their acetylated forms (e.g. geranyl acetate). The different response groups and low variance for the different substances might be explained by several mutually non-exclusive theories, based on the interaction of honey bees’ odorant-binding proteins (n = 177), odorant receptors (n = 21) and odorant-degrading enzymes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" class="xref">82</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">83</xref>
 </sup>:
 <list list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par26" class="p">Odorant-binding proteins and/or odorant receptors of the bees’ antennae may primarily discriminate between phenolic and non-phenolic substances, as they bind a wide range of odorant molecules.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par27" class="p">Receptor density and/or saturation for phenolic substances is much lower than for non-phenolic substances, leading to lower antennal response.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par28" class="p">Odorant-binding proteins do not discriminate between acetylated and non-acetylated substances as they mainly recognize specific motifs of certain molecules.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
