<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17" class="p">In comparison to honey, nectar terpene concentrations are usually measured from fresh material and give a more precise picture of nectar quality. For the six different chemotypes analysed in this study, terpene concentrations do not differ much for each substance and are potentially characteristic for each chemotype. The thymol concentration (7.67 ppm), at least, is well in the range of a previous study (2.22–8.2 ppm)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>, even though a different extraction method and plant material (cultivars) were used. For pollen, more data are needed to conclude if the detected values are representative for the distinct chemotypes. The thymol content of pollen could not be determined in this study since no male flowers were available. Nevertheless, data from hive pollen samples for the U.S.A. National Survey showed that thymol concentrations can vary from 0.0263 to 55.8 ppm
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>, which is in the range of the other pollen terpenes analysed in the current study. Apart from that, the higher values may have resulted from sampling pollen from 
 <italic class="italic">Varroa</italic>-treated hives (by fumigation, see introduction). Altogether we assume that 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">vulgaris</italic> nectar and especially its pollen contain terpene concentration with a potential of activity against parasites and pathogens if stored or directly distributed and consumed in the hive. The concentration of leaf volatiles are orders of magnitude higher than for nectar and honey, and may not contribute directly to the health status of honey bee colonies. However, leaf-cutter bees (
 <italic class="italic">Megachile rotundata</italic>) harvesting plant leaves to coat their brood chambers may benefit from the amount of leaf terpenes protecting their brood against, for instance, chalkbrood
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. Whether and how thyme leaves are used by bees is not completely understood, but the high terpene concentrations may contribute to orientation and decision making during foraging flights
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
