<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">For estimating the antibiotic potential of the selected plant terpenes, bacterial growth inhibition was measured for several bee-associated bacteria. For some of these bacteria species (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">faecalis</italic>) it is known that herb essential oil mixes are biologically much more effective than single compounds (e.g. carvacrol, thymol, geraniol, linalool, α-terpineol, geranyl acetate)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. Here, we have shown that carvacrol and thymol performed best in inhibiting bacterial growth in comparison to the other plant terpenes tested. For both substances low concentrations were sufficient to inhibit bacterial growth by 50%. In some cases (MIC - minimum inhibitory concentration, showing the first sign of growth inhibition
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>: 100–300 ppm for 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alvei</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">dendritiformis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">coli</italic>, this study) they showed comparable activity to the complete essential oil bouquet (MIC: 100–200 ppm
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>). This might be due to their phenolic structure, as all other thyme terpenes tested in this study are non-phenolic (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>). Chemical modifications of terpenes strongly affect their antibiotic activities. For example, acetylation led to the complete inactivation of geraniol, linalool and α-terpineol in the current study (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>), except for their activity against 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">plutonius</italic>. This inactivation not only causes reduced or even absent antibiotic activity against bacteria but also towards fungi
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup>. Hence, thyme nectar terpenes vary strongly in their antibiotic activity and this variance is defined in part by their modifications. Such a relationship between chemical structure (acyl group size) and antibiotic activity against bacteria (
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">larvae</italic>) and fungi (
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">apis</italic>) was recently discovered for propolis dihydroflavonols
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>
 </sup>. Among the foraged and self-produced bee products with high effectivity on bee pathogens
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>, propolis is the hive product for which the raw material and its compounds were studied in most detail, for instance regarding its effect on 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alvei</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>. Future studies have to determine the effectivity of 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">vulgaris</italic> plant nectar and pollen terpenes in larval food to cure larval infectious diseases like American or European foulbrood. However, first it is mandatory to estimate how much terpenes can be detected in larval food under normal hive conditions, as variance between IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values and concentration in nectar and pollen is quite high. The high amounts needed to inhibit bacteria 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> may only be reached by feeding pollen (to drone and worker brood) or by accumulating terpenes while producing honey. On the other hand 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values are not necessarily the same for 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> studies. Lower concentrations might be sufficient as synergistic effects or additional antibiotic activity by other substances of the larval food cannot be excluded
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup>. This means for some terpene concentrations of nectar and mainly pollen a sufficient amount is present to reduce pathogen growth 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic>, for most of the bacteria. A total inhibition, in particular 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic>, may only be reached by combinations of terpenes, other plant metabolites and hosts’ own proteins and enzymes. By measuring nectar and pollen terpene concentrations, and the antibiotic activity of single plant terpenes, the direct significance for self-mediation has not been tested here and has to be evaluated in future studies.
</p>
