<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to Bentes et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], the antioxidant activities of 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil were screened by five different methods: DPPH free radical scavenging, modified TBARS (using egg yolk as a lipid-rich medium) for measuring the inhibition of lipid peroxidation, FRAP assay based on the reduction of ferric iron (Fe
 <sup>3+</sup>) to ferrous iron (Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>) by antioxidants present in the samples, chelating activity on ferrous ions (Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>), and superoxide anion radical scavenging. With the DPPH free radical scavenging assay, 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil was almost totally ineffective as an antioxidant, in contrast to the remaining water-soluble hydrodistillation-aqueous phase extract that showed similar activity to that of α-tocopherol, particularly at higher concentrations (75 and 100 mg/L). This result suggests that a considerable portion of the antioxidant compounds were retained in the remaining hydrodistillation-aqueous water. In this study, the FRAP assay of 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil was also compared. However, the correlation between DPPH and the FRAP assay activities was not as clear in the evaluation of different extracts. Whereas the hydrodistillation-aqueous phase extracts were the best antioxidants when evaluated by DPPH, the 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> methanolic extract had a greater capacity for reducing Fe
 <sup>3+</sup> than the hydrodistillation-aqueous phase extract. In addition, in the superoxide anion assay, only the hydrodistillation-aqueous phase and methanolic extracts were able to scavenge superoxide radicals, but the first ones were the most effective. The superoxide radical scavenging capacity of these extracts was even higher than that of the positive control (ascorbic acid, particularly at 500 mg/L). 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> methanol extracts were powerful superoxide radical scavengers with 40–60% activity.
</p>
