<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The strong origin effects with native 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> populations displaying better performance than plants from the exotic range supported the hypothesis of genetic divergence between native and exotic population: The direction of the differences, however, contradicted our expectation of increased performance in exotic plant material. Plants of native German origin produced higher below‐ and aboveground biomass and invested in a faster development of a large rosette. Although experimental studies on a multiple species basis have often indicated higher performance of exotic origins (Beckmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Blumenthal &amp; Hufbauer, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Colautti et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), there are nevertheless contradictory findings showing that increased growth of exotic plant origins as, for example, predicted by the EICA hypothesis (Blossey &amp; Notzold, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>), is not universal (Parker et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). More specifically, for 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic>, plant performance has been studied along environmental gradients in native and non‐native ranges and was found not to consistently differ between ranges (Seipel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). In contrast, field studies and experimental common garden studies revealed better performance of introduced populations in the United States when compared to native European populations (Alba et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Alba &amp; Hufbauer, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Endriss et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). In the present study, the pattern was completely reversed and there are several scenarios that might explain this outcome. First, it is possible that the differences encountered may be partially due to covarying effects of different abiotic conditions in native and exotic ranges. Site conditions of populations investigated in this study did not only differ in annual average temperature and precipitation (Table 
 <xref rid="ece36894-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>) but also varied significantly in soil pH with much lower values for populations from New Zealand (between 4.68 and 5.75) compared with those from Germany (between 6.94 and 7.67; Table 
 <xref rid="ece36894-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>), therefore presumably also varying in resource supply. Alba and Hufbauer (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>) was able to identify reduced performance of exotic 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> populations compared with native ones, when accounting for additional abiotic differences among ranges. In contrast to our results, a common garden experiment in the United States revealed exotic 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> populations from the United States to have significantly larger shoot biomass than native European ones (Alba et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). However, our study system involved exotic NZ–native EU comparisons where levels of abiotic resources displayed in the introduced and native range may be different from exotic US–native EU comparisons. These contradictory results point to the importance of the exact range identity and associated environmental conditions when comparing native and exotic ranges studied (Endriss et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). This highlights the need to expand biogeographic comparisons of exotic species to multiple region studies involving exotic ranges with different levels of resource supply to quantify the impact of qualitative and quantitative abiotic changes and their contribution to evolutionary divergence (Erfmeier, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Second, apart from effects of abiotic differences among regions, experienced differences in biotic conditions, such as in competition, may have evoked divergence in plant origin responses. Increased size as indicated by rosette growth superiority of native German plants has the potential to limit the growth of competitors and is thus often advantageous in highly competitive environments. This matches with our field observations of higher productivity of co‐occurring species in German populations when compared to neighboring plant species in New Zealand populations. Alba and Hufbauer (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>) precisely elaborated that density of 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> was negatively related to vegetation cover. In addition, there is experimental evidence that increased growth and performance in exotic origins if compared to native ones may only become evident under situations of competition, as was shown specifically for 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> (Kumschick et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) and in a meta‐analysis including 27 studies (Felker‐Quinn et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Increased performance in exotic origins may only pay off when there is competition with neighboring (native) plants and thus not be evidenced in isolated settings as done in the present study. A third explanation for contradictory outcomes in different exotic ranges is that patterns of genetic diversity and associated effects might depend on particular histories of introductions into regions. 
 <italic>Verbascum thapsus</italic> was most probably introduced to New Zealand in the mid‐nineteenth century with the second immigration wave (Esler, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>). It is conceivable that a limited number of founder populations functioned as a source for its spread throughout the island resulting in a reduced genetic diversity (Austerlitz et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Dlugosch &amp; Parker, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Schrieber &amp; Lachmuth, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) and, as a consequence, reduced plant performance in the new distribution area (Ellstrand &amp; Elam, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>; Keller &amp; Waller, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). As founder effects are governed by chance events, the extent of genetic bottlenecks might strongly differ among different regions of introduction (Lachmuth et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).
</p>
