<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The bacteriostatic activity of the essential oils was tested by measuring bacteriostatic circles using the filter paper method. Qualitative filter paper was cut into small round pieces (diameter, 1.5 cm) using a puncher, and autoclaved before use. 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">B. subtilis</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> were cultured in nutrient agar medium at 37 °C for 24 h. Under sterile conditions, the corresponding culture medium (20–25 mL) was poured into the sterilized culture dish and the solid plate was prepared after cooling and solidifying. The prepared bacterial suspension (200 μL) was added to the corresponding solid plate medium and uniformly coated. The filter paper sheet was attached to the bacteria-bearing plate. Essential oil (5 μL) was added to each piece of filter paper. The essential oil diffused from the center to the periphery of the bacteria-bearing tablet, gradually forming a concentration gradient that inhibited the growth of the tested strains and formed a transparent bacteriostatic circle. The bacteriostatic activity of the essential oils can be preliminarily determined according to the OD of the bacteriostatic ring [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-23-02168" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. The inhibition ratios were calculated as follows:
 <disp-formula id="FD2-molecules-23-02168" class="disp-formula">
  <label class="label">(2)</label>
  <math id="mm2" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">Inhibition</mi>
     <mo class="mo"> </mo>
     <mi class="mi">ratio</mi>
     <mo class="mo"> </mo>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mo class="mo">(</mo>
      <mo class="mo">%</mo>
      <mo class="mo">)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">R</mi>
        <mi class="mi">t</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <mi class="mi">R</mi>
       <mi class="mi">o</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">R</mi>
        <mi class="mi">t</mi>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo class="mo">×</mo>
     <mn class="mn">100</mn>
     <mo class="mo">%</mo>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic class="italic">R
  <sub class="sub">t</sub>
 </italic> is the average OD of the inhibition zone, and 
 <italic class="italic">Ro</italic> is the average OD of the blank sample. Experiments were performed in triplicate.
</p>
