<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results on the FA profile of both the breast and leg chicken meat in the present experiment highlighted that 27 days duration of dietary treatment was enough to generate relevant effects on the FA profile of the meat. In the present trial, the addition of HI larvae fat into chickens’ diets increased the SFA content of the breast meat to a higher extent than was observed in the work by Schiavone et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] (17.4% and 35.1% increase in HI50 and HI100 diets, respectively, compared to the control group). Moreover, the decreasing pattern in the breast MUFA proportion, from the control to the HI100 groups, was not observed in the study of Schiavone et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], where the breast MUFA content remained unaffected by increasing the dietary incorporation of HI larvae fat. Fatty acid deposition is the result of absorption, de novo synthesis, and β-oxidation of FA [
 <xref rid="B33-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]: elongase and Δ-9 desaturase (stearoyl-CoA desaturase) enzyme activities from C12:0, C14:0 and C16:0 FA, whose dietary content augmented with increasing incorporation level of HI larvae fat, might have compensated for the lower dietary intake of MUFA [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. However, as the addition of a double bond is a rate-limiting step in MUFA biosynthesis rather than the simple chain elongation, it was observed that elongation activity (insertion of two carbon units at the carboxyl terminal of FAs) tends to be higher than desaturation (addition of a double bond). Furthermore, on the one hand, surplus amounts of SFA were shown to block the biosynthesis of some MUFA, especially 18:1 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-9, by suppressing elongase activity [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. On the other hand, dietary PUFA was shown to reduce Δ-9 desaturase enzymatic activity, thus lowering the conversion of SFA into MUFA [
 <xref rid="B33-animals-09-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Therefore, the delicate equilibrium between dietary FA absorption and the contribution of dietary FA to modulate enzymatic activity could explain the results of the present research.
</p>
