<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot3-medicines-04-00030" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Antibacterial Activity of EO</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antibacterial effect of EO was evaluated in vitro against nine pathogenic bacteria species (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00030-t003" href="#medicines-04-00030-t003">Table 3</a>). Gram-positive bacteria were more delicate to the EO than Gram-negative bacteria. 
  <span class="italic">B. cereus</span> was the most susceptible bacteria to 
  <span class="italic">A. millefolium</span> oil at the applied concentrations (5 and 10 µg/mL). The smallest inhibition zones were obtained in 
  <span class="italic">S. typhimurium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. agona</span> cultures while 
  <span class="italic">St. epidermidis, S. enteritidis</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> were resistant against all concentrations of 
  <span class="italic">A. millefolium</span> oil. MIC for 
  <span class="italic">B. cereus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">St. aureus</span> were 100 and 120 µg/mL, respectively; while the MIC for 
  <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span> was 310 µg/mL. Among the Gram-negative tested bacteria, a remarkable antibacterial effect was observed only for 
  <span class="italic">S. typhimurium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. agona</span> with their respective MIC values 2000 and 1000 µg/mL. The effect of 
  <span class="italic">A. millefolium</span> oil from Turkey [
  <a rid="B3-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-medicines-04-00030">3</a>] was also tested against 
  <span class="italic">St. aureus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">B. cereus</span>; it was found that the MIC was 72 mg/mL, which is remarkably higher than the MIC of 
  <span class="italic">A. millefolium</span> oil measured in our study. As was shown, the composition of 
  <span class="italic">A. millefolium</span> oils from various locations may be rather different. The properties and the content of individual constituents may have an important power on the antibacterial effect of oil against different bacteria species. For instance, sabinene, 1,8-cineole, and camphor, which were abundant in 
  <span class="italic">A. millefolium</span> oil studied in this work, are well-known natural chemicals with antibacterial potentials [
  <a rid="B21-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-medicines-04-00030">21</a>]. The EO also studied in our work also contained 12% of germacrene-D and 7.3% of (
  <span class="italic">E</span>)-nerolidol, which were absent in the Turkish oil. The antibacterial activities of germacrene-D and (
  <span class="italic">E</span>)-nerolidol were previously reported as well [
  <a rid="B22-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-medicines-04-00030">22</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
