<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="med21743-fig-0013" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 13</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Schematic representation of the potential molecular mechanism by which generation of nitric oxide (NO) strongly inhibits the production of cellular energy through two mechanisms: inhibition of mitochondrial respiration by reversible (from constitutive isoforms of nitric oxide synthase [NOS]) and irreversible (from inducible NOS [iNOS]) inhibition of cytochrome P450
   <xref rid="med21743-bib-0578" ref-type="ref">
    <sup>578</sup>
   </xref>; and glycolysis inhibition through modification of the SH‐groups of glyceraldehyde 3‐phosphate dehydrogenase.
   <xref rid="med21743-bib-0579" ref-type="ref">
    <sup>579</sup>
   </xref> In anaerobic glycolysis, muscle glycogen is converted to lactic acid via glucose‐6‐phosphate, yielding three ATP molecules for each glucose residue. Aerobic oxidation of glucose is required for the sustained exercise and provides 34 ATP molecules per glucose residue via the Krebs cycle and the respiratory chain, a process that occurs 1 min after anaerobic ATP generation. If a sufficient supply of ATP is not generated, anaerobic glycolysis is continued. NO levels increase during stress, consequently decreasing performance by inhibiting ATP production. Adaptogens prevent stress‐induced increases in NO,
   <xref rid="med21743-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
    <sup>18</sup>
   </xref> and as such, ATP production remains efficient and performance and endurance are increased.
   <xref rid="med21743-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">
    <sup>26</sup>
   </xref> Updated from authors’ drawings
   <xref rid="med21743-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">
    <sup>26</sup>
   </xref> [Color figure can be viewed at 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wileyonlinelibrary.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">wileyonlinelibrary.com</ext-link>]
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-25" xlink:href="MED-41-630-g013" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
