<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To maximize light use for photosynthesis, plants possess fully developed strategies based on short‐ and long‐term responses to adapt to low light intensities (Mathur, Jain, &amp; Jajoo, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Photosynthesis is the key function for plant growth and is highly sensitive to light conditions. In photosynthetic systems, the pigment protein complexes photosystem I and photosystem II are interconnected through the cytochrome (Cyt) 
 <italic>b
  <sub>6</sub>f
 </italic> complex and electron transfer chain (Mamedov, Govindjee, Nadtochenko, &amp; Semenov, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Photosystem II is a protein complex embedded in thylakoid membranes of higher plants and able to absorb light and split water. The core complex subunits, such as PsbB, PsbC, PsbR, PsbO, PsbP, and PsbQ proteins, are also called oxygen‐evolving enhancer (OEE) proteins, with main functions of enhancing the efficiency of the oxygen‐evolving complex (Bricker, Roose, Fagerlund, Frankel, &amp; Eaton‐Rye, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Silveira &amp; Carvalho, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Similar to photosystem II, the photosystem I core complex contains reaction center subunits (PsaA and PsaB), binding subunits (PsaG, PsaK, PsaH, PsaL, PsaO, and PsaP), ferredoxin docking subunits (PsaD and PsaE), plastocyanin docking subunits (PsaF and PsaN), and FeS apoprotein (PsaC; Kouril et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Furthermore, ATP synthase subunits (α, β, γ, and δ), cytochrome 
 <italic>b
  <sub>6</sub>f
 </italic> (PetB, PetD, PetA, and PetC), ferredoxin (Fdx) complex, and ribulose‐bisphosphate carboxylase large chain (RbcL) involved in the Calvin cycle can play important roles in the photosynthesis process (Silveira &amp; Carvalho, 
 <xref rid="ece36206-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The results for the three comparison groups revealed significant differences in photosynthesis‐related GO terms and KEGG pathways. In the present study, most of the photosynthesis‐related DEGs were enriched in the “photosynthesis,” “photosynthesis‐antenna proteins,” and “carbon fixation in photosynthetic organisms” pathways. Moreover, the “photosynthesis” pathway contains photosystem II, photosystem I, cytochrome b6/f complex, electron transport, and ATP synthase‐related genes. Our result showed that most DEGs were upregulated and enriched in photosynthesis II, such as 
 <italic>PsbO</italic>, 
 <italic>PsbP</italic>, 
 <italic>PsbQ</italic>, 
 <italic>PsbR,</italic> and 
 <italic>PsbW</italic>, and photosynthesis I such as 
 <italic>PsaD</italic>, 
 <italic>PsaE</italic>, 
 <italic>PsaF</italic>, 
 <italic>PsaH</italic>, and 
 <italic>PsaK</italic>. These upregulated DEGs indicated that 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>canadensis</italic> could enhance the expression of photosynthesis II‐ and photosynthesis I‐related genes to adapt to low‐light conditions. Cytochrome 
 <italic>b
  <sub>6</sub>f
 </italic>, Fdx complex, ATP synthase, and RbcL‐related DEGs, such as 
 <italic>PetC</italic>, 
 <italic>PetF</italic>, 
 <italic>PetH</italic>, ATP synthase γ, δ, and b, were also related upregulated DEGs that were enriched in the “photosynthesis” pathway. These results indicated that enriched DEGs might be vital for 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>canadensis</italic> to resist shade stress conditions.
</p>
