<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0255" class="p">In most cases oviposition deterrence was higher during early exposure and although the treated substrate was less favorable to females this trend diminished progressively. Therefore, it is possible that the essential oils drops readily impinge on host surface, short time after their application, but the activity weakens as the essential oils concentrations evaporate. This suggestion is supported by the recovery of relatively small number of eggs that were deposited on the oviposition substrate 10 and 15 days after treatment. Nevertheless, other factors may also affect female oviposition preference and may diminish the effectiveness of essential oils, especially under laboratory and field conditions. Fruit varieties for example with rough surfaces [
 <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>] or color (Sidney et al.) [
 <xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>], may also affect oviposition preference. Thomson [
 <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] and Javed et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>], stated that the females of 
 <italic class="italic">H. armigera</italic> prefer to lay eggs on plant parts with high trichome density and high concentration of stimulatory chemicals. Trichome is a factor which positively affects oviposition preference also in 
 <italic class="italic">Anarsia linetaella</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Moreover, fruit damage due to other causes, for example damage by other insect species, is likely to affect fruit protection by essential oils, unless they contain strong deterrent compounds [
 <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. Nevertheless, since I used the same oviposition substrate in choice experiments, the failure to lay eggs on fruits treated with essential oils was likely due to the high volatile properties and strong essence of the oils, though the presence of non volatile deterrents cannot be eliminated.
</p>
