<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Microbial contamination can affect any step of the food chain, from seed germination to food processing and storage [
 <xref rid="B177-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>,
 <xref rid="B179-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. Initially, the seed-borne pathogens endanger the correct development of grains, affecting both yield and quality [
 <xref rid="B179-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]. Besides, bacteria and fungi are the principal causative agents of many postharvest diseases. 
 <italic>Erwinia</italic>, 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>, 
 <italic>Corynebacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> are some of the most common food spoiler species, seriously compromising the quality of food products. Moreover, human health may be disturbed by the contact with these contaminated products [
 <xref rid="B181-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>], along with a deleterious impact in the reliability and economics of the agri-food industry [
 <xref rid="B177-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>]. Synthetic pesticides and preservatives, some of them with detrimental effects, have been the most commonly used formulations to prevent and stop the growth of these microorganisms. Therefore, natural, safer and eco-friendly antimicrobials are demanded by the consumers [
 <xref rid="B178-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>,
 <xref rid="B186-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>]. Essential oils constitute a potential alternative, because they possess antimicrobial activity, individually or in combinations between them and with antibiotics. They prevent food deterioration, maintain their appearance and quality and are able to be used in biopreservation and biocontrol in the agri-food industry [
 <xref rid="B187-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>,
 <xref rid="B188-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>,
 <xref rid="B189-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>,
 <xref rid="B190-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>,
 <xref rid="B191-plants-10-00044" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>].
</p>
