<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Whole genome data in its turn led to insights into biosynthesis pathways (
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Denoeud et al., 2014</xref>). The list of species with sequenced genomes is growing, collaborations are emerging to join efforts and collect more data. The Medicinal Plant Genomic Resource (MPRG)
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn0001">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> is a domain-specific database created by consortium efforts to collect deep DNA sequencing, RNA sequencing, and metabolomics data. In general, genome sequencing is used to discover new candidates and to elucidate biosynthesis pathways to prepare data sets of new molecules for further analysis. One can predict the presence of a compound among plant metabolites if gene involved in the biosynthesis of the compound in question was discovered in the plant genome. For example, cardenolides discovered in the 
 <italic>Calotropis gigantea</italic> genome were historically used to cure pneumonia and as an anti-inflammatory, anticancer, and antimalaria (
 <xref rid="ref500" ref-type="bibr">Hoopes et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Boone et al., 2020</xref>), and they also can be easily converted to mappicine ketone, an antiviral led compound (
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Das et al., 1998</xref>). Genes to biosynthesize curcumin were found in 
 <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> genome (
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Katsuyama et al., 2007</xref>). Recently conducted chromosome-scale genome assembly of 
 <italic>I. indigotica</italic> assisted to reveal new candidate genes for the biosynthesis of several groups of active compounds in this medicinal plant (
 <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Kang et al., 2020</xref>). Phenolic compounds of 
 <italic>I. indigotica</italic> have already shown activity against the M
 <sup>pro</sup> (
 <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2005</xref>), and indole alkaloids in this plant demonstrated inhibition of HSV-2 reproduction (
 <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2010</xref>). Besides, cultivars of the same species can differ in the amount of the medicinal compounds (
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Hisashi and Saito, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Kajikawa et al., 2017</xref>). Complete genome data allow to identify gene clusters for secondary metabolism, which opens the way to metabolic engineering. For example, whole-genome sequencing can reveal huge number of “silent” gene clusters which can be learned to activate to run currently non-working biosynthetic pathways (
 <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Osbourn, 2010</xref>).
</p>
