<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Polymeric films attract a significant degree of interest because of their widespread use in several industrial applications, with particular reference to packaging. Over the last decades, the large use of oil-derived polymers, due to their good mechanical, thermal and barrier properties, as well as their low cost, has led to significant problems in term of production and accumulation of wastes [
 <xref rid="B1-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Rising concern about the reduction of waste coming from plastic packaging has encouraged both academia and industry to engage in research focused on polymers coming from natural resources, biodegradable or compostable [
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Bio-based polymers are those obtained from natural resources, while biodegradable polymers are those which can degrade into water and carbon dioxide under normal environmental conditions through microbial action, providing compost as a simple and sustainable disposal option [
 <xref rid="B7-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], and all of these can be regarded to as bioplastics. For instance, in the case of food packaging, polymers combining renewable sources and biodegradable nature are preferred [
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-polymers-11-00651" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
