<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In comparison, ‘isolation by environmental distance’ is a relatively recent approach used to explore the effects of environmental heterogeneity on genetic divergence. For instance, various bioclimatic (e.g. temperature, precipitation, etc.) and environmental variables (e.g. altitude, soil, etc.) tend to have a correlation with genetic divergence (
 <xref rid="PLU052C60" ref-type="bibr">Temunovic 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>) that is suggestive of selection. However, in order to know a specie's diverse environmental requirements, one has to understand the complex association between species presence and environmental factors. Species distribution modelling or ecological niche modelling (ENM) explores this relationship through various algorithms and identifies suitable areas where potential populations could survive (
 <xref rid="PLU052C41" ref-type="bibr">Pearson 2010</xref>). While the application of niche modelling (species distribution modelling, SDM) to understand species ecology and distributions, and to design conservation planning is well established (
 <xref rid="PLU052C52" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2007
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C63" ref-type="bibr">Urbina-cardona and Loyola 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C16" ref-type="bibr">Groot 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2009
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C35" ref-type="bibr">Mateo 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2013
 </xref>), its implementation to uncover the role of physical and climatic factors in genetic differentiation has been realized very recently (
 <xref rid="PLU052C38" ref-type="bibr">Parisod and Christin 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C42" ref-type="bibr">Pease 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2009
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C37" ref-type="bibr">Ortego 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C60" ref-type="bibr">Temunovic 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>). In order to understand invasion, niche modelling has been widely applied to delineate the future distribution potential (
 <xref rid="PLU052C68" ref-type="bibr">Zalba 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2000
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C67" ref-type="bibr">Welk 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2002
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C43" ref-type="bibr">Peterson 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C69" ref-type="bibr">Zhu 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2007
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C44" ref-type="bibr">Petitpierre 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C64" ref-type="bibr">Vaclavik and Meentemeyer 2012</xref>); however, studies integrating niche modelling with genetics to shed light on invasion dynamics are rare.
</p>
