<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec id="st1" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Plectranthus amboinicus</span> Lour is a species which is widespread throughout tropical countries where it is widely used against respiratory tract disorders such as bronchodilator, antitussive, and expectorant conditions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st2" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Objective:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study aims to characterize the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> (PaEO) and produce and evaluate emulsions containing PaEO.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st3" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil was characterized by physical-chemical analyses for density, refractive index, 90% ethanol solubility, color, appearance, and identification by gas chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry detection. The emulsions were prepared following a hydrophile-lipophile balance [HLB] spreadsheet design from two nonionic surfactants (Span 80
   <span class="sup">®</span> and Tween 20
   <span class="sup">®</span>) producing HLB values ranging from 4.3 to 16.7. The products were stored at room temperature at 5°C. The emulsion stabilities were tested both in the long and short-term.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st4" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PaEO was obtained by steam distillation and the total extraction was reached after 3 hours yielding of 0.2% (w/w). This essential oil was characterized by physicochemical analyses for density [1.5 g.ml
   <span class="sup">-1</span>], refraction index [0.9167], ethanol 90% solubility [1:2], color, and appearance (yellow/clear). Nineteen components were identified in the oil, among them the sesquiterpenes: carvacrol [33.50%], p-cymene [28.20%] and γ-terpinene [14.77%]. The emulsions obtained successfully showed, for the first time, HLB values for essential oils from 
   <span class="italic">Plectranthus amboinicus</span> [15.7].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st5" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion:</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experimental data shows a relationship between HLB values of the surfactant mixtures contributing to the emulsified systems production containing phytopharmaceuticals. Such an approach is of great importance to the development of lipid carriers for therapeutic drugs.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st6" class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SUMMARY</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>The essential oil from leaves of 
      <span class="italic">Plectranthus amboinicus</span> was extracted by steam distillation and characterized.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>The emulsions containing essential oil were produced and the stability was performed in the short and long term.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>The critical hydrophilic-lipophilic balance (HLB) of the essential oil was 15.7 and was achieved by the combination of surfactants (Tween 80
      <span class="sup">®</span> and Span 20
      <span class="sup">®</span>).
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div xlink:href="PM-13-159-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="bold">Abbreviations used:</span> PaEO: essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span>, HLB: hydrophilic-lipophilic balance, CI: Creaming Index, MET: micro-emultocrit technique
  </p>
 </sec>
</div>
