<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Food safety inspection and quality control is important for ensuring the high quality of agriculture products. To meet this criterion, photonics techniques have been extensively implemented into numerous applications. For instance, clean drinking water is undeniably one of the most important elements to sustain the organisms’ life. Contamination may happen when treated drinking water is travelling in the distribution system to the consumer, whilst the sensitivity to the inhibitor of contamination can be measured by the elevated dissolved organic matter (DOM) at the tap relative to the water leaving the treatment plant [
 <xref rid="B216-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">216</xref>]. Across a biologically stable drinking water system, humic-like fluorescence (HLF) intensities of less than 2.2% relative standard deviation are measured after accounting for quenching by copper. In addition, a minor infiltration of a contaminant is detectable by sewage with a strong tryptophan-like fluorescence (TLF) signal thus validating the potential of DOM fluorescence in detecting the water quality changes in drinking water system. Moreover, fluorescence spectroscopy was demonstrated in evaluating the microbial quality of untreated drinking water through online monitoring [
 <xref rid="B217-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">217</xref>]. The DOM peaks are targeted at excitation and emission wavelengths of 280 and 365 nm for TLF, as well as 280 and 450 nm for HLF. Both TLF and HLF are strongly correlated to micro-bacterial cells such as 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> with a correlation coefficient of 0.71 to 0.77. In comparison to turbidity for 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> with correlation coefficient of only 0.4 to 0.48, the DOM sensor appears to be a better indicator for micro-bacterial cells in untreated drinking water. Apart from the DOM sensor, an optical sensor was proposed to differentiate the particles in drinking water as either bacteria or abiotic particles with an accuracy of 90 ± 7% and 78 ± 14% for monotype and fix-type suspensions, respectively, based on a 3D image recognition and classification algorithm [
 <xref rid="B218-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">218</xref>]. In addition, this optical sensor can detect micro-particles with minimum size of 0.77 μm. Significantly, the aforementioned optical sensors incorporating photonic techniques serve as an early warning for drinking water pollution. 
</p>
