<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2-6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Biofilm removal</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Biofilm removal potential of both agents alone and in combination was assessed using 24-well flat-bottomed polystyrene microtiter plates according to the method explained previously with some modifications.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">17</a>
  </span> An aliquot of 200 μL of bacterial suspension with OD
  <sub>600</sub> = 0.1 was dispensed into each well which was filled previously with 1800 μL of LB broth, using four repetitions per treatment to reach a suspension with 10
  <span class="sup">7</span> CFU/ mL per well. After incubation for 24 h at 37 ±1 °C, the planktonic cells in wells were then removed and the plates were washed three times with PBS and air-dried for 20 min at 23 ±2 °C. Then, 2000 μL of MIC, 2MIC and 4MIC concentrations of ZEO and SNP and their combinations (1/4 OIC, 1/2OIC, and OIC concentrations) were gently poured into the wells and incubated for 15 min at ambient temperature. The solutions were then removed and plates were washed three times with PBS and air-dried for 20 min at 23 ±2 °C. Following staining with 2 mL of 1% crystal violet (CV) (w/v) for 30 min, the contents of the wells were decanted and washed twice with tap water to remove the color excess and then allowed to air-dry for 30 min. The biomass of biofilms was quantified by solubilizing CV with 2 mL of acetic acid 33% and subsequent measuring optical absorbance (OD) at 540 nm. Wells containing LB broth and LB with bacteria without antibacterial were considered as negative and positive controls, respectively. Biofilm removal percentage was calculated as follow:
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="uneq3" class="disp-formula">
   <div id="m3" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">R</span>
     <span class="mi">e</span>
     <span class="mi">d</span>
     <span class="mi">u</span>
     <span class="mi">c</span>
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mi">i</span>
     <span class="mi">o</span>
     <span class="mi">n</span>
     <span class="mo"> </span>
     <span class="mi">p</span>
     <span class="mi">e</span>
     <span class="mi">r</span>
     <span class="mi">c</span>
     <span class="mi">e</span>
     <span class="mi">n</span>
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mi">a</span>
     <span class="mi">g</span>
     <span class="mi">e</span>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">C</span>
         <span class="mo">−</span>
         <span class="mi">B</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">T</span>
         <span class="mo">−</span>
         <span class="mi">B</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">C</span>
         <span class="mo">−</span>
         <span class="mi">B</span>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">×</span>
     <span class="mn">100</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> where C is OD
  <sub>540nm</sub> of control wells, B is OD
  <sub>540nm</sub> of negative controls and T is OD
  <sub>540nm</sub> of treated wells.
 </p>
</sec>
