<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another medicinal plant growing in the reserve is the species 
 <italic>Croton linearis</italic>. This aromatic shrub widely distributed in the Caribbean region, is empirically used by the Cuban population as an analgesic to reduce fever and to treat infections [
 <xref rid="B154-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. In the 
 <italic>Croton</italic> genus, the therapeutic effects have been mainly attributed to LMW compounds such as alkaloids, terpenoids and flavonoids [
 <xref rid="B155-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. However, little information is available about the 
 <italic>C. linearis</italic> species, its phytochemical composition and pharmacological potential. In this sense, García et al., (2018, 2019) reported that the antimicrobial potential of this plant may be associated with the presence of alkaloids, flavonoids and essential oils [
 <xref rid="B155-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>,
 <xref rid="B156-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Following a bioassay-guided fractionation, the studies identified seven compounds, which were for the first time isolated and characterized in this species, with alkaloids and flavonoid-derived substances among them. In summary, some of the active constituents from 
 <italic>C. linearis</italic> showed in vitro activity against 
 <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic> (alkaloid reticuline) and 
 <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> (flavonoid glycoside isorhamnetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-(6″-
 <italic>O</italic>-
 <italic>p</italic>-
 <italic>trans</italic>-coumaroyl)-β-glucopyranoside). Until now, no study exploring the antioxidant potential has been performed yet. However, the anti-protozoal action observed, could be closely correlated with the antioxidant capacity of the isolated isoquinoline alkaloids (benzylisoquinoline and aporphine) [
 <xref rid="B157-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Indeed, the free radical scavenging capacity of this group of compounds is related to its structural characteristics, which has been well described in the literature. Most aporphine and benzyl-tetrahydroisoquinoline alkaloids have multiple phenolic hydroxyls on the benzene ring and are expected to scavenge reactive free radicals at least by generating thermodynamically and kinetically stable phenoxy radicals [
 <xref rid="B158-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. However, generally, aporphine alkaloids exhibit higher antioxidant activity than the latter even without hydroxyl groups. The reason may be dual: (1) increased spin delocalization of phenoxy radicals in the plane biphenyl configuration in aporphine leads to a more stable structure after accepting a radical and (2) the nonphenolic analogues presumably act through the delocalization of the neighboring nitrogen lone electron pair.
</p>
