<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For centuries, medicinal plant extracts have been utilized extensively by mankind in treating several diseases [
 <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. These herbal extracts possess a wide variety of bioactive compounds such as tannin, flavonoids, alkaloids, and phenolic substances, which may serve as potential alternatives to many synthetic drugs [
 <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Previously, several identified compounds for curing parasitic diseases such as malaria have been isolated from plants, for example, quinine and artemisinin [
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In Egypt, the utilization of medicinal plants rose since Pharaonic times, and nowadays, many Egyptians still rely on medicinal plants for the treatment of several diseases [
 <xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Considering the aforementioned drawbacks of the current anti-
 <italic>Toxoplasma</italic> remedies, it is imperative to search for novel and highly effective compounds for the treatment of toxoplasmosis with minimal side effects. Therefore, in an attempt to develop a new therapy from Egyptian herbal extracts for 
 <italic>T. gondii</italic>, this study aimed to investigate the effect of methanol and oil extracts of some plants against 
 <italic>T. gondii</italic>. The selected plants for this research are frequently used for treating many diseases in herbal therapy and are known to have diverse bioactive constituents. In addition, most of these plants have been previously reported to exhibit antiprotozoal and anthelmintic activity against organisms such as 
 <italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic> [
 <xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]; 
 <italic>Laurus nobilis</italic> [
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]; 
 <italic>Citrullus colocynthis</italic> [
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]; 
 <italic>Cinnamum camphor</italic> [
 <xref rid="r76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]; 
 <italic>Boswellia scara</italic> [
 <xref rid="r64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]; 
 <italic>Melissa officionalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="r52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]; 
 <italic>Cymbopogon citratus</italic> [
 <xref rid="r70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]; 
 <italic>Origanum majorana</italic> [
 <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]; 
 <italic>Salvia rosmarinus</italic> [
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]; 
 <italic>Syzygum aromaticum</italic> [
 <xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]; and 
 <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> [
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, to the best of our knowledge, no literature on their potential anti-
 <italic>Toxoplasma</italic> activities is available.
</p>
