<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">To sample genetic variation as broadly as possible, seeds were collected from 18 native populations in Europe and 18 invasive populations in Australia, Western and Eastern North America (for detailed population information see Supporting Information Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> and Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Native seeds from the potential source populations along the western coast of Europe were selected to compare them with invasive populations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. For each population, seeds from three different plants (hereafter referred to as “mother plants”) were germinated in petri dishes with moistened filter paper. After 5 weeks, 4 well-grown seedlings from each mother plant were selected and randomly assigned to the control and defoliation treatments and plants were harvested at control T0 (seedling harvested at T0 before potting), control T1 (plants harvested at T1), control T2 (plants harvested at T2) and defoliation T2 (Plants defoliated at T1 and harvested at T2 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Therefore each of the 4 treatments contained 108 plants (1 seedling * 3 mother plants * 36 populations). Seedlings from control T0 were harvested and oven-dried for 3 days at 50 °C and then weighed. Plants from control T1, T2 and defoliation T2 were potted into 1 L pots with 20% potting soil (Slingerland potting soil, Zoeterwoude, The Netherlands), 80% dune sand (collected from Meijendel, The Netherlands, 52°13′N, 4°34′E) and 2.5 g Osmocote slow-release fertilizer (Scott®, Scotts Miracle-Gro, Marysville, Ohio, USA; N:P:K:MgO 15:9:11:2.5). Plants were grown in a climate room at 20 °C, 70% humidity, 16 hours daylight with a light intensity of 113 umol PAR m
 <sup>−2</sup> s
 <sup>−1</sup>. Eight weeks after potting, plants from control T1 were harvested and plants from the defoliation T1 were defoliated by removing the shoot (1 cm above the root crown) with a pair of scissors. The plants used were rosettes so the defoliation treatment removes only leaves as the flowering stem is not yet present and the growing point was left intact. The removed shoot materials were dried in an oven at 50 °C for three days and weighed to determine their dry mass.
</p>
