<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">While long-term variation in organic carbon accumulation in soils largely result from factors affecting climate, geology and soil formation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>, changes in land use / land cover are at play over shorter periods
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. For example, plant functional groups with different allocation of photosynthates to above- and belowground plant parts and with different root architecture are known to affect the total amount and the vertical distribution of SOC profiles
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. Our findings provide evidence that degradation of natural vegetation in the semi-arid parts of Baringo County and re-establishment of vegetation have led to major changes in total SOC stocks and SOC profiles to 1 m depth. First, total SOC stock in degraded grasslands was 37% lower than that in pristine grasslands. This value is considerably higher than that reported in a worldwide review by Dlamini et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> for degraded grasslands in arid and semi-arid regions (-16%), but studies in South Africa revealed losses of SOC stocks which were comparable or even higher than those reported in our study. For example, Dlamini et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> found a 79% SOC loss in grasslands in KwaZulu-Natal Province with &lt; 5% vegetation cover and a 42% SOC loss in grasslands with &lt; 50% cover, while Baer et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> reported a 56% loss in total SOC due to cultivation of grasslands in the South African Highveld. Based on field data collected in Serengeti National Park, Tanzania, Ritchie
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup> modelled the effect of grazing intensity on SOC and predicted that SOC increases at intermediate grazing intensity but then declines rapidly at the highest grazing intensities. We attribute our lower SOC levels in degraded grasslands largely to the grazing pressure by livestock, because in our study area, grazing pressure is above the threshold where SOC is expected to decline rapidly (see below).
</p>
