<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Microbial pathogens are a major cause of a significant number of various illnesses around the world. Therefore, to overcome their virulence, essential oils derived from plants have been proposed and tested as powerful strategies in alternative medicine generally accompanied by reduced side effects. In a previous study, the inhibitory effects of essential oils are enhanced by the effect of monoterpene and sesquiterpenes constituents (representing 22.72% in our study) on the cell membrane [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In this study, the higher inhibitory action of the tested PCEO might be due to the presence of eugenol and methyleugenol in high quantity. In fact, phenolic -OH groups can easily bind the active site of enzymes and alter their metabolism via the presence of a double bond in the α,β positions of the side chain and to a methyl group located in the γ position [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. We note that methyleugenol is the most sensitive against bacteria than eugenol because of its higher hydrophobicity. The lowest effect of eugenol is probably due the presence of hydroxyl group that is not involved for hydrogen bonding and to the presence of methoxy group in the 
 <italic>ortho</italic> position (of eugenol) that produced steric hindrance. Hyldgaard et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] reported that methyleugenol and eugenol show higher activity against Gram-negative bacteria than Gram-positive bacteria. Caryophyllene, as monoterpene exerted antimicrobial properties against some strains [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and its mode suggest that diffuse into and damage the cell membrane structures by altering the membrane, affecting the transport of ions and ATP and therefore, changing the fatty acid profile of different bacteria and affects various bacterial enzymes, including ATPase, histidine, carboxylase, amylase and protease [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Lopez et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] reported that natural methyl eugenol lacking of free hydroxyl groups attached to the benzene ring proved ineffective against the oral bacteria 
 <italic>Streptococcus sobrinus.</italic> Recently, Nazzaro et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] confirmed that the antimicrobial activity of eugenol could be ascribed to the presence of a free hydroxyl group in the molecule. Studying the mechanism action of eugenol against several 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolates. Devi et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-00205" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] demonstrate that eugenol first alters the 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> membrane permeability followed by the leakage of ions and extensive loss of other cellular contents, and ultimately results in cell death.
</p>
