<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Further in this study, the biofilm formation inhibitory effect of selected medicinal plants against biofilm-producing 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> was investigated. 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> biofilms are known to typically colonize both artificial and tissue surfaces in humans and cause serious infections including implant-associated infections, cystic fibrosis, lung infections, and chronic wounds [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Among the tested plants, 
 <italic>Holarrhena floribunda</italic> stem bark exhibited the highest biofilm formation inhibitory activity against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Three extracts, pet-ether (PHE), ethyl acetate (EHE), and methanol (MHE) fractions, were prepared from the crude extract and tested for biofilm inhibitory activity. The methanol fraction exhibited the highest antibiofilm activity among the fractions, extracts, and the reference control. Crude alkaloids (AKL) precipitated from this methanol fraction also showed considerable activity although twofold less active than the methanol fraction (
 <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Bioassay-guided fractionation of the bioactive alkaloidal fraction revealed the presence of the steroidal alkaloids, holonamine (
 <bold>HF1A</bold>), holadienine (
 <bold>HF1B</bold>), and conessine (
 <bold>HF1C</bold>), which also showed considerable antibiofilm forming activity. These compounds have been previously reported from 
 <italic>H. floribunda</italic> and other 
 <italic>Holarrhena</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This is however the first report of the biofilm formation inhibitory effect of 
 <italic>H. floribunda</italic> and the isolated plant constituents. Thus, fractionation of the stem bark extract of 
 <italic>H. floribunda</italic>, to some extent, afforded much potent antibiofilm methanol fraction, which owed its activity, in part, to its constituent alkaloids.
</p>
