<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Holarrhena floribunda</italic> is well known in African traditional medicine for the treatment of malaria, diarrhea, dysentery, diabetes, skin diseases, swellings, and urinary and sexually transmitted infections [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The antibacterial activity demonstrated by the crude extract and the solvent fractions of the 
 <italic>H. floribunda</italic> stem bark in the current work is consistent with previous reports on the same plant [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Steroidal alkaloids are the major types of phytoconstituents identified in 
 <italic>H. floribunda</italic> [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Flavonoids, fatty acid esters, and trichothecenes have also been reported [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The antibacterial activity of 
 <italic>Holarrhena</italic> species has been attributed to the presence of steroidal alkaloids [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Conessine (HF1C) is a well-established constituent of 
 <italic>H. floribunda</italic> [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Although the antibiofilm inhibitory property of 
 <italic>H. floribunda</italic> and its constituents was not previously investigated, a recent study demonstrated the resistance-modifying ability of conessine through the inhibition of multidrug efflux pumps [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Another study has shown that compounds with efflux pump inhibition may also cause biofilm disruption [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. This assertion makes the current results of the antibiofilm formation effect of conessine very plausible. The activity of the individual isolated compounds was lower than the crude alkaloid fraction, suggesting the possible role of synergism in the activity of the steroidal alkaloids. This is consistent with a previous study by Li-Na et al. [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], which reported synergistic antibacterial activity of steroidal alkaloids isolated from 
 <italic>Holarrhena antidysenterica</italic> against methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. In a previous study, the hydroalcoholic extract 
 <italic>H. antidysenterica</italic> inhibited the formation of biofilm in opportunistic pathogenic 
 <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. This puts 
 <italic>Holarrhena</italic> species in the spotlight as potential prospects of antibacterial agents with biofilm inhibitory activity.
</p>
