<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Carboxymethyl cellulose (CMC) is derived from cellulose and contains carboxymethyl groups (–CH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>–COOH) bound to the hydroxyl groups of the cellulose backbone [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f006" class="xref">Figure 6</xref>C). Carboxymethyl cellulose sodium salt (NaCMC) begins to form a rigid gel at 2.5%, and its viscosity is increased by increasing the NaCMC concentration; however, its solubility limit is slight above 10% [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. A 7% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) stock gel of NaCMC in water was heated at 60–70 °C and trapping of bubbles was minimized by homogenization with spatula [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Homogeneous thick gels were formed within 2 days at room temperature and stored at 4 °C to prevent contamination by microorganisms. A NaCMC delivery medium was obtained quickly by adding NaCMC slowly to vigorously stirred water in a beaker. Once all the powder was incorporated, the stirring speed was lowered and the mixture was heated under vacuum for 1 h at 60–70 °C. The NaCMC gel was then left under vacuum conditions overnight to fully hydrate and to remove any residual bubbles. This gel was mixed with crystal suspension using the mechanical mixing method with a syringe setup (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f004" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>). The NaCMC delivery medium was then loaded with a 150-μm ID capillary at a flow rate of 0.3–5.9 μL/ min. The crystal structures of lysozyme and thermolysin derived from NaCMC were determined at resolutions of 1.9 Å and 2.3 Å, respectively, using &lt;0.5 mg protein. This delivery medium has a very low background scattering with a weak diffuse ring at 2.6–4 Å. In terms of the chemical compatibility of NaCMC with crystallization precipitants, NaCMC provided a stable injection stream in high salt or PEGs crystallization solutions such as 1.25 M LiSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, 1.25 M MgSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, 1.8 M ammonium sulfate, 2 M sodium chloride, 35% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) PEG 400, 30% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) PEG 2000, 25% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) PEG 4000, 25% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) polypropylene glycol 400, and 35% (
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) 2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol (MPD). As a result, NaCMC forms stable streams with a wide range of precipitants. However, medium preparation is time consuming compared with other delivery media. In addition, NaCMC is sensitive to crystal size, where the stability of the stream is disturbed when large crystals are embedded in NaCMC [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>].
</p>
