<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">BACKGROUND</title>
  <p class="p"> This work describes a chemical study of the essential oil from leaves of 
   <italic class="italic">Xylopia ochrantha</italic>, an endemic Annonaceae species from Brazil, and its activity against 
   <italic class="italic">Biomphalaria</italic> species. Considering its poor solubility in aqueous medium, the essential oil was nanoemulsified to evaluate its action on controlling some mollusc species of genus 
   <italic class="italic">Biomphalaria</italic>, snail hosts of 
   <italic class="italic">Schistosoma mansoni</italic> that causes schistosomiasis, which mainly affects tropical and subtropical countries.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">OBJECTIVES</title>
  <p class="p"> The main aims of this work were to analyse the chemical composition of essential oil from 
   <italic class="italic">X. ochrantha</italic>, and to evaluate the effect of its nanoemulsion on molluscs of genus 
   <italic class="italic">Biomphalaria</italic> and their oviposition.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">METHODS</title>
  <p class="p"> Chemical analysis was performed by gas chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry. Nanoemulsions were prepared by a low energy method and characterised by particle size and polydispersity index. Biological assays evaluating the mortality of adult species of 
   <italic class="italic">B. glabrata</italic>, 
   <italic class="italic">B. straminea</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">B. tenagophila</italic> and their ovipositions upon contact with the most stable nanoemulsion during 24 and 48 h were performed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">FINDINGS</title>
  <p class="p"> Chemical analysis by mass spectrometry revealed the majority presence of bicyclogermacrene and germacrene D in the essential oil. The formulation with a hydrophilic-lipophilic balance (HLB) of 9.26 was the most suitable for the oil delivery system. This nanoemulsion caused the mortality in 
   <italic class="italic">B. tenagophila</italic>, 
   <italic class="italic">B. straminea</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">B. glabarata</italic> of different sizes at levels ranging from 50 to 100% in 48 h. Additionally, the formulation could inhibit the development of deposited eggs.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">CONCLUSION </title>
  <p class="p">Thus, these results suggest the use of nanoemulsified essential oil from 
   <italic class="italic">X. ochrantha</italic> as a possible alternative in controlling some 
   <italic class="italic">Biomphalaria</italic> species involved in the schistosomiasis cycle.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
