<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study was conducted June-August 2011 on three pairs of sites in two coastal dune habitats on the North Spit of Humboldt Bay in northwestern California. The specific locations of the studies avoided protected species (40°51’18.0”N, 124°09’53.1”W; 40°51’33.3”N, 124°09’51.3”W; 40°51’38.2”N, 124°09’58.2”W). One habitat was dominated by 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>, whereas the other habitat was restored and free of 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic> (
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Our 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>-dominated sites were located on a private 46-ha reserve owned and managed by a nongovernmental organization, Friends of the Dunes. On these sites, the plant community was comprised almost entirely of 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>. These 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic> stands are notoriously dense, and canopy cover ranged from 70–100% (see 
 <xref rid="sec003" ref-type="sec">Results</xref> for more details of plant community). Our restored sites were located on adjacent land on the southern portion of Ma-le’l Dunes Cooperative Management Area, a 62-ha parcel owned and managed by the Bureau of Land Management (BLM), who granted permission for the field research. The BLM partnered with the California Conservation Corps (CCC) for 14 years to achieve complete removal of 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic> in the foredunes, thus making way for ongoing native American dunegrass (Leymus mollis ssp. mollis) recovery efforts [
 <xref rid="pone.0117903.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Thus, this habitat is a restored coastal dune site dominated by native plant species that are maintained naturally at much lower levels of cover than in the 
 <italic>Ammophila</italic>-dominated habitat. Canopy cover ranged from 10–80% (see 
 <xref rid="sec003" ref-type="sec">Results</xref> for more details of the plant community). Permission for our field studies was obtained directly from Friends of the Dunes and the Bureau of Land Management (Arcata office), who should be contacted for future research permissions.
</p>
