<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0210">Nuclear factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2), often expressed in the liver, lung, heart, and brain is known as the most significant endogenous factor related with cellular response to oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Nrf2 translocates into the nucleus and binds with an antioxidant response element (ARE) to upregulate a battery of antioxidative gene expressions, including SOD, catalase, and Peroxidases in response to antioxidants and oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Although results of this study showed that Nrf2 expression was downregulated in serum and brain tissue of untreated envenomed group and but upregulated catalase and SOD activities as observed in results of antioxidant profiles. The ability of the venom to downregulate the expression of Nrf2 confirms that 
 <italic>N. haje</italic> venom is capable of inducing a dysfunction of the antioxidant system at a molecular level which may leads to substantial enrichment of ROS resulting in oxidative stress. Cells are capable of regulating the enzymatic system by a ‘‘coarse’’ mechanism whereby the rate of transcription of the enzyme is altered or by ‘‘fine’’ method whereby the activity of the available enzyme is regulated [
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The increased activity of SOD and catalase may then be due to the anti- ROS mechanism by the cell (via regulation of the available enzymes). Nevertheless, antivenom and extract partitions of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> upregulated Nrf2 expression mostly in group treated with ethanol partition of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic>. Monte et al. [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] reported that elevated Nrf2 expression is part of protective mechanism against induced toxicity. This result may indicate that 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> can protect against 
 <italic>N. haje</italic>-induced damage through the activation of the Nrf2 antioxidative pathways. The consequent decrease in antioxidant enzymes activities is the testament to the ability of treatment to mitigate the generated ROS.
</p>
