<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0220">Snake envenoming are most times resulted into inflammation and tissue damage [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. It was observed in this study that 
 <italic>N haje</italic> venom causes pathological changes on vital organs of untreated rats as tissue degeneration were noticed on the brain, liver and kidney which supports earlier observations that 
 <italic>N. haje</italic> venom is capable of affecting histology of vital organs after envenomation in rats [
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, antivenom and various extract partitions of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> showed ameliorative effects as no remarkable lesion was observed in groups treated with high dose (600 mg/kg) of the extract partitions. Studies have reported the ameliorative effects of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> extract on histological defects noticed on vital organs following envenoming by cobra and viper venom in rats [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>]. The anti-venom ability of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> and ability to neutralize various toxicities induced by 
 <italic>N. haje</italic> venom could be due to various compounds present in extract partitions. Although this study did not focus on profiling of the phytochemicals in 
 <italic>M. oleifera,</italic> the presence of flavonoids, tannins and alkaloids has been confirmed by Fahal et al. [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Studies have suggested that compounds present in plant extracts could bind to divalent metal ions in the venom which are required for the hydrolytic activities of PLA2 thereby rendering it inactive, as metal ions are co-factors which are very crucial for enzymes stability and functionality [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> has been shown to possess immunomodulatory, antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects due to the aforementioned phytochemicals [
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Thus, we pose that; the ameliorative effects of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> on the various pathologies induced by the venom may also be due to its ability to inhibit the activity of PLA2 which in turn renders the venom inactive.
</p>
