<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Myanmar, which lies between China and India, is well known for its rich biodiversity and cultural diversity. As one of the key regions designated as global hotspots for biodiversity protection, Myanmar has an abundance of plant resources [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The U.S. National Herbarium, the Forest Department of Myanmar and the University of Yangon provided a Myanmar plant checklist containing over 3000 species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. KM Lwin and MKT Lwin catalogued a list of medicinal plants in Myanmar that contained 1500 species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], and Defilipps et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] recently reviewed the main information of 472 Myanmar medicinal plant species. For thousands of years, Buddhism has been widely distributed in Myanmar and has impacted almost every aspect of life there, including medicine. Vinaya, one of the Tripitaka philosophies of Buddhism about the regulation of life, is the theoretical basis of Myanmar traditional medicine. In Buddhist Vinaya practices, a qualified Buddhist follows strict dietary rules to maintain the health of both the body and spirit. Unhealthy dietary habits and bad foods can cause serious digestive problems, which are detrimental to Buddhist practice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Therefore, in addition to medicine, Myanmar people use food to maintain health and treat ailments by following Vinaya in the traditional lifestyle; a well-known Myanmar proverb states that “medicine is food, food is medicine”. However, there are still few studies on this subject in international journals and books. The only related studies published in English have shown rich local medicinal knowledge among ethnic minority communities in Chin State [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], Shan State [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], Kachin State [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and Mon State [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Nevertheless, the core region of Myanmar, central Myanmar and its main ethnic population, the Bamar people, have been ignored in previous ethnobotanical studies.
</p>
