<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par68" class="p">The oil extraction was performed by microwave-assisted hydrodistillation (MWHD), as described elsewhere [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. Briefly, a domestic microwave oven (Kendo, 2.45 GHz, 800 W) was modified with a side orifice through which an external Dean-Stark trap joined a round flask that contained the plant material (100 g) and water (0.5 L), inside the oven. Three 15 min heating periods at full power were used to perform the hydrodistillation. The Dean-Stark trap permitted to decant the essential oil from the condensate. A gas chromatograph GC 7890 (Agilent Technologies, AT, Palo Alto, CA, U.S.A.) coupled to a mass selective detector MSD 5975C (AT, Palo Alto, CA, U.S.A.), using electron impact ionization (EI, 70 eV) was used for essential oil characterization. This system included a split/splitless injector (1:30 split ratio), and a MS-ChemStation G1701-DA data system, with the WILEY, NIST and QUADLIB 2007 spectral libraries. For their GC-MS assays, individual essential oil samples (50 μL) were mixed with 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-tetradecane (2 μL, internal standard) and diluted with dichloromethane to a final volume of 1.0 mL. Helium (99.9995%) was used as the carrier gas, with 155 kPa column head pressure and 27 cm s
 <sup class="sup">− 1</sup> linear velocity (1 mL minute-1, at constant flow), in two columns of different polarities (DB-5MS and DB-WAX from J&amp;W Scientific, USA). The GC oven temperature was programmed from 50 °C (5 min) to 150 °C (2 min) at 5 °C min
 <sup class="sup">− 1</sup>, then to 230 °C (10 min) at 5 °C min
 <sup class="sup">− 1</sup>. When the DB-5MS column was used, a final heating to 275 °C (15 min) at 10 °C min
 <sup class="sup">− 1</sup> was added. The temperatures of the injection port, ionization chamber and of the transfer line were set at 250, 230 and 285 °C, respectively. For the polar DB-WAX column, the transfer line temperature was set at 230 °C. Mass spectra and reconstructed (total) ion chromatograms were obtained by automatic scanning in the mass range 
 <italic class="italic">m/z</italic> 30–400 at 4.5 scan s
 <sup class="sup">− 1</sup>. Compound relative abundances were calculated from the chromatographic area of profiles obtained with an AT 7890 gas chromatograph provided with flame ionization detection (FID, 250 °C). The chromatographic columns, carrier gas and oven temperature programs employed in GC-FID analysis were the same as described previously for the GC-MS system. The EO compounds were identified using mass spectra and linear retention indices relative to C
 <sub class="sub">8</sub>-C
 <sub class="sub">32</sub> n-alkanes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>]. Several terpenoid standard compounds, such as limonene, carvone, geranial, geraniol, β-caryophyllene, and β-caryophyllene oxide, obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, U.S.A., with purities above 98%) were used. The extracted EOs were preserved at 4 °C and protected from light before GC-MS and cellular analysis. Finally, the 76 EOs were arranged into 12 groups, according to the significant differences in the percentages of their major terpenes and one oil of each group was arbitrarily selected for further biological analysis, comprising six EOs from Citral chemotype (A13, A20, A23, A24, A25, and A28), and six from the Carvone chemotype (B7, B16, B37, 2B8, 2B18, and 2B19).
</p>
