<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Free radicals are those compounds that contain unpaired electrons, are extremely reactive species such as many reactive oxygen species (ROS) usually are the outcomes of routine cellular biotransformation in the biological systems (Qadir et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR275">2014</xref>; Zhang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR380">2018</xref>). ROS is a complete range of large riposte molecules that are produced from oxygen metabolism (Dhanapal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2016</xref>). Antioxidants maintain the equilibrium of radicals in cells, which prohibit oxidative stress against different ailments (Szerlauth et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR334">2019</xref>). However, the excess formation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) is due to severance of the exquisite balance in the middle of the antioxidant system, its production is accountable for the oxidative damage which results in the deterioration of cellular macromolecules like enzymes, lipids, deoxyribose nucleic acids (DNA), and proteins (Halliwell and Gutteridges 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131">1984</xref>; Msaada et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR225">2015</xref>). This imbalance can be used for the diagnosis of numerous disorders like necrosis, swelling, Parkinson’s disease, Alzheimer’s sickness, high blood pressure, hyperglycemia, atherosclerosis, heart-related problems, and immunological perturbation (Morris et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR224">2013</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR353">2019</xref>). ROS can cause necrosis due to their strength to enlarge cell growth, endurance molecular wandering. Moreover, it can also responsible for DNA impairment, which evinces in the form of genetic complications that prompt tumorigenicity and ensuing tumor development (Storz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR327">2005</xref>). Malignancy is one of the fatal diseases predominantly in public health aspects in both progressing as well as the progressed world (Prakash et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR274">2013</xref>). In conjunction with this, current perspectives of cancer therapy, for example, immunosuppression, radiotherapy, chemotherapy and surgery, are integrated with a vast mortality rate despite substantial development in cancer therapy of cytostatic compounds (Sidaoui et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR310">2016</xref>). Furthermore, the results of the presently available procedure for the diagnosis of several cancers are clear, mainly when cancer has attained the metastatic phase and cellular progression of cancer has been done (Seo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR302">2003</xref>; Mojarab et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR220">2009</xref>).
</p>
