<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Z. multiflora</italic> contains various compounds including terpens, luteolin, 6- hydroxyluteolin glycosides, di-, tri, and tetra-ethoxylated which could be responsible for the therapeutic effects of it
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">88</sup>
 </xref>
 <italic class="italic">Z. multiflora</italic> Boiss essential oil (ZEO) possesses preservative effects whereas vigorous taste and aroma have limited its usage as food preservative in high amounts.
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">89</sup>
 </xref> In Iranian traditional medicine, the plant is used for its analgesic, antiseptic and carminative effects.
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">88</sup>
 </xref> It has also been documented that the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. multiflora</italic> has antioxidant, antibacterial and antifungal properties in 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic>.
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">89</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">90</sup>
 </xref> The results of studies have indicated that the ZEO exhibited more potent antioxidative effect than pomegranate juice.
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">89</sup>
 </xref> Antibacterial,
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">90</sup>
 </xref> immunoregulatory
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">91</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">117</sup>
 </xref> and anti-inflammatory
 <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">92</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">118</sup>
 </xref> effects of this plant have also been reported. In addition, it has been reported that the Aβ-caused learning and memory impairments could be restored by i.p. administration of 
 <italic class="italic">Z. multiflora</italic> essential oil in rats. Therefore zataria multiflora essential oil was considered to be as a worth source of natural therapeutic agent for attenuating cognitive symptoms of Alzheimer's disease (AD) by researchers.
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">93</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
