<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33" class="p">The pH of Biochar was determined at a solid-to-liquid ratio of 1:20 (w/v) after 18 h. A CHN/O elemental analyzer (PerkinElmer 2400 Series II, USA) was used to determine after C, H, and N contents of biochar. The total N contents of the samples were measured using H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>SO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>–H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> digestion via the Kjeldahl procedure
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. XRD was conducted using a Bruker D8 X-ray diffractometer (Cu Kα, 40 kV, 20 mA, λ = 1.54056 Å) to characterize any crystallographic structure in biochar. Surface functional groups and bonding modes of organic molecules were determined by FTIR spectroscopy (Thermo-Nicolet Nexus 670, USA). XPS was carried out to analyze surface composition in ~10 nm depth of biochar using an ESCALAB 250Xi spectrometer (THERMO FISHER, USA) with a focused monochromatized Al Kα radiation (hν = 1486.6 eV). Biochar surface morphology was observed by SEM (Zeiss Sigma) with EDS (Bruker) at a working distance of 8–9 mm and an acceleration voltage of 10–15 kV. N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> adsorption was conducted on a 3H-2000PS2 Analyzer to identify the SSA and pore volume (PV) of samples. Before measuring the SSA, the samples were pretreated to eliminate other adsorbed substances from the surface (degassing) by heating them in vacuum at 105 °C for 12 h. The total internal SSA of the samples was calculated from the nitrogen adsorption isotherm through Brunauer−Emmett−Teller analysis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. The density functional theory method was used to characterized the pore size distribution from the adsorption isotherm, particularly, the method of quenched solid-state functional theory was employed to consider slit/cylindrical pores
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
