<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Shell eggs are stored at room temperature or preferably in the fridge prior to be used by consumers (eggs are considered as “fresh” up to 28 days after laying). The conditions of egg storage can induce deep internal changes including physicochemical modifications that may increase some technological properties that are useful for the food industry, and alteration of antibacterial properties of the egg white [
 <xref rid="B173-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">173</xref>,
 <xref rid="B174-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">174</xref>,
 <xref rid="B175-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B176-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-00684-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>). These alterations result from water exchange between yolk and the egg white and from water and carbon dioxide loss through the eggshell pores, which elicited an increase in the air cell that develops between the two eggshell membranes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="nutrients-11-00684-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>a). Albumen height decreases with time of storage while albumen pH and whipping volume increase [
 <xref rid="B136-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">136</xref>]. In parallel, the strength of vitelline membrane decreases upon egg storage due to loosening thereby impacting yolk shape/index (the yolk becomes flat and its diameter is higher) [
 <xref rid="B173-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">173</xref>]. These latter modifications favor egg white/egg yolk exchanges of components such as carbohydrates and glucose [
 <xref rid="B177-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">177</xref>], proteins [
 <xref rid="B178-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">178</xref>,
 <xref rid="B179-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>], vitamins, and trace elements [
 <xref rid="B181-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">181</xref>]. In addition, storage duration and conditions are associated with protein degradation [
 <xref rid="B175-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">175</xref>,
 <xref rid="B179-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>] and a decrease in its antibacterial potential [
 <xref rid="B175-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">175</xref>]. However, except for proteins, there is only little information available that describes the changes/denaturation in lipids, vitamins, and minerals composing both egg white and egg yolk during storage. It will be interesting to further investigate how these modifications impact the respective functional, nutritional, and technological properties of egg yolk and egg white (foaming, emulsifying properties, etc.). Recent data has demonstrated that the antioxidant activity of egg yolk was globally unchanged during six weeks of retail storage [
 <xref rid="B182-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. All these alterations of freshness criteria are accelerated at room temperature when compared to refrigerated conditions.
</p>
