<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The increasing number of bacteria that are resistant to antibiotics has contributed to the failure of the treatment of infections caused by them and is a serious health problem in medicine worldwide. Therefore, it is reasonable to conduct research on the effect of plant extracts and essential oils to enhance the antimicrobial activity of antibiotics. Some researchers combine antibiotics with plant compounds, e.g., EOs, to determine transcriptional changes in the bacterial genome, receiving information on key genes that underlie the synergism between essential oils and antibiotics. Lai et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] conducted transcriptomic analysis of multidrug-resistant 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> to identify any presence of transcriptional changes in the genome upon the use of a combination of lavender essential oil (
 <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic>) (LEO) and piperacillin. Analysis of the results revealed that the use of LEO-piperacillin caused the upregulation of certain genes which affected fructose and mannose metabolism, the metabolism of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> in diverse environments and nitrotoluene degradation, as well as the phosphotransferase system. The combinatory treatment also caused the downregulation of the 
 <italic>aldA</italic> gene, for example, which is crucial for the survival and replication of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> strains under harsh conditions. The above results show that the presence of LEO can increase the potential of piperacillin for cellular destruction. Some research has shown that the presence of plant components enhances the potency of antibiotics by weakening bacteria’s ability to develop resistance. Scazzocchio et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] showed that the presence of coriander essential oil (
 <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic>) reduced the MIC of gentamicin against multidrug-resistant UPECs. A strong synergy was reported for two Moroccan thyme (
 <italic>Thymus maroccanus</italic> and 
 <italic>T. broussonetii</italic>) EOs in combination with chloramphenicol against two strains: wild-type 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> K-12 (AG100) and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> K-12 mutant (AG102) overexpressing the AcrAB pump, responsible for resistance to tetracycline, chloramphenicol, ampicillin, nalidixic acid and rifampicin. Both EOs decreased the MIC values of chloramphenicol against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> AG100 and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> AG102 strains by 4- and 32-fold, respectively [
 <xref rid="B43-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Similar results were obtained for another Moroccan thyme (
 <italic>Thymus riatarum</italic>) EO in combination with chloramphenicol against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> K-12 (AG100) and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> K-12 mutant (AG100A) with the AcrAB pump deleted. 
 <italic>T. riatarum</italic> EO decreased the MIC values of chloramphenicol against AG100 and AG100A by 4- and 2-fold, respectively [
 <xref rid="B26-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The results suggest that the synergy could be attributed to efflux pump activity changes by thyme EOs, thus increasing the activity of chloramphenicol. Duran et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] examined the effects of 
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> EOs against drug-resistant 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> strains. Following treatment with essential oils, resistance rates of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> strains against ampicillin, levofloxacin and cefuroxime decreased—the growth inhibition zone diameters of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> strains were higher and the MIC values of the antibiotics were lower when compared to bacteria not treated with the EOs. In the research conducted by Miladinovic et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-pharmaceutics-13-00573" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] lemon thyme (
 <italic>Thymus pulegioides</italic>) EO showed synergistic effects with tetracycline and chloramphenicol against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922. It is worth noting that the combination of lemon thyme EO and streptomycin displayed an antagonistic effect against 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922. This phenomenon is probably caused by competition for the same target, with the bacterial 30S ribosomal subunit being crucial in protein synthesis.
</p>
