<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An alternative approach was reported in 1977 by Laws and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Extraction of hops with supercritical CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> was performed at temperatures between 40 and 50 °C and pressures between 150 and 400 bar. A high-quality hop extract was also obtained by using LCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> at relatively low temperatures. A patent of Muller [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] described the extraction at a temperature below the critical temperature (approximately 31 °C) but at a pressure higher than the critical one (73.25 bar). Next variation included the addition of a small amount of ethanol as a solvent to the liquid carbon dioxide [
 <xref rid="B17-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The choice of an appropriate solvent represents the key factor for isolation of the compound of interest and depends on a number of factors, including dissolving power, selectivity, inflammability, volatility, and cost. Selectivity of LCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is for example used to provide hop extracts free of hard resins and polyphenolic materials which is not the primary focus of this review article that mainly covers extraction and separation methods for isolation of acidic compounds contained in hop flowers and their antitumor, antimicrobial, and antioxidative effects. CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is thus a substitute for organic solvents of a highly nonpolar character, such as hexane and pentane. The range of organic species which dissolve in LCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> includes hop resins and aroma components, paraffins, naphthenes, olefins, alcohols, aldehydes, phenols, esters, carboxylic acids, amines and nitrogen heterocycles, aromates, ketones, ethers, amides, and nitrites [
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], but not polyphenols.
</p>
