<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Supercritical fluid extraction, routinely used for the production of bitter acid extracts for the beer brewing industry, represents an effective method for the isolation of both volatile and nonvolatile compounds of hops including essential oils. Operating conditions, temperature, and pressure used for the extraction markedly affect the composition of the obtained extract. Relatively high recovery of volatile compounds is obtained at lower temperatures, whilst elevated pressures and temperatures favor high recovery of bitter acids and resinous compounds. Unfortunately, under the conditions used in the extraction with supercritical carbon dioxide for the preparation of hop extracts for the brewing industry, a large group of biologically active prenylflavonoids (prenylchalcones and prenylflavanones) remains in the plant material. Besides CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, water is also relatively often used as an extraction medium, mainly due to the ability to become an excellent solvent for organic compounds and a very poor solvent for inorganic salts above its critical point (374 °C, 218 atm). This means that the same solvent can be used to extract the inorganic and the organic components, respectively. Products obtained in this way are solvent-free, without the presence of coproducts and the operational temperature is in the case of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> low [
 <xref rid="B24-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The application of supercritical fluids (SCF) for extraction of natural substances at even higher pressures (over 70 MPa) than in conventional SCF extractions gives rise to new products from known plant materials such as the isolation of less soluble substances. A method for extraction and dissolution of hop acids, including α-acids, iso-α-acids, β-acids, and their derivatives in aqueous media, also comprising of the formation of quaternary ammonium salts of hop acids with quaternary ammonium compounds or mixtures thereof has been recently developed by Mertens and Pascal [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Hop acids containing matter is mixed with one or more quaternary ammonium compounds. Quaternary ammonium salts of hop acids are thereby formed. Their specific advantage is a high solubility in (acidic) aqueous medium compared to the corresponding hop acids in the free acid form. This invention further relates to the use of quaternary ammonium salts of hop acids in the beer brewing process and represents an effective concept of improving the utilization of hop acids, including α-acids and bitter taste contributing iso-α-acids, in this process. 
</p>
