<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It has also been recognized that diuretics are the backbone of treatment for hypertension and edematous states characterized by surplus extracellular fluid [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Usually, diuretics enhance the excretion of large amounts of water and salts from the body in order to decrease blood volume and blood pressure and therefore reduce blood flow resistance. Despite the abundant availability of diuretics for use in humans, such medicines are related to different side effects majorly including various metabolic complaints, strengthening the significance of rummage around for new diuretic agents with more efficacy and fewer side effects. Therefore, in the current situation, new diuretic medicines are planned primarily from natural sources [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In fact, several medicinal plants display a number of pharmacological properties on the renal system, acting on different well-established targets such as nitric oxide-cGMP, renal carriers, carbonic anhydrase, prostaglandin-cAMP, and renin-angiotensin systems [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In the current study, crude extracts and fractions from 
 <italic>A. tenuifolius</italic> induced significant diuretic and natriuretic effects in normotensive rats, with maximum diuretic response produced by AS-AT. Similar to hypotensive effects, AS-AT was subjected to further studies to evaluate the possible involvement of nitric oxide, acetylcholine, and prostaglandins in the renal action. In our study, we found that diuretic activity of AS-AT was reduced in the presence of muscarinic receptor blocker (atropine) whereas prostaglandin inhibitor (indomethacin) and NO synthesis inhibitor (L-NAME) did not alter the diuretic action. Thus, our findings suggest a muscarinic AChR-induced endothelium-independent vasodilation, which increases capillary blood flow leading to diuresis [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
