<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Mixed-species forest plantation is a sound option to facilitate ecological restoration, plant diversity and ecosystem functions. Compatible species combinations are conducive to reconstruct plant communities that can persist at a low cost without further management and even develop into natural forest communities. However, our understanding of how the compatibility of mycorrhizal types mediates species coexistence is still limited, especially in a novel agroforestry system. Here, we assessed the effects of mycorrhizal association type on the survival and growth of native woody species in mixed-species 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plantations. To uncover how mycorrhizal type regulates plant-soil feedbacks, we first conducted a pot experiments by treating distinct mycorrhizal plants with soil microbes from their own or other mycorrhizal types. We then compared the growth response of arbuscular mycorrhizal plants and ectomycorrhizal plants to different soil microbial compositions associated with 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plants. We found that the type of mycorrhizal association had a significant impact on the survival and growth of native tree species in the 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plantations. The strength and direction of the plant-soil feedbacks of focal tree species depended on mycorrhizal type. Non-mycorrhizal plants had consistent negative feedbacks with the highest survival in the 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plantations, whereas nitrogen-fixing plants had consistent positive feedbacks and the lowest survival. Arbuscular mycorrhizal and ectomycorrhizal plants performed varied feedback responses to soil microbes from distinct mycorrhizal plant species. Non-mycorrhizal plants grew better with 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> soil microbes while nitrogen-fixing plants grew worse with their own conspecific soil microbes. Different soil microbial compositions of 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> consistently increased the aboveground growth of arbuscular mycorrhizal plants, but the non-mycorrhizal microbial composition of the 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> soil resulted in greater belowground growth of ectomycorrhizal plants. Overall, 
  <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> plants induced an unfavorable soil community, impeding coexistence with other mycorrhizal plants. Our study provides consistent observational and experimental evidence that mycorrhizal-mediated plant-microbial feedback on species coexistence among woody species. These findings are with important implications to optimize the species combinations for better design of mixed forest plantations.
 </p>
</abstract>
