<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The genus 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> L. (Zingiberaceae) represents a group of perennial rhizomatous herbs native to tropical and subtropical regions. 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> is extensively cultivated in tropical and subtropical regions of Asia, Australia, and South America [
 <xref rid="B1-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. There are approximately 93–100 accepted 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> species, however the exact number of species is still controversial [
 <xref rid="B2-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The genus is best known for being an essential source of coloring and flavoring agents in the Asian cuisines, traditional medicines, spices, dyes, perfumes, cosmetics, and ornamental plants [
 <xref rid="B3-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Several 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> species are used medicinally in Bangladesh, Malaysia, India, Nepal, and Thailand [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] for treating pneumonia, bronchial complaints, leucorrhea, diarrhea, dysentery, infectious wounds or abscesses, and insect bites [
 <xref rid="B2-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The rhizome is the most commonly used part of the plant. The main active components of the rhizome are the nonvolatile curcuminoids and the volatile oil [
 <xref rid="B6-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Curcuminoids (curcumin, demethoxycurcumin, and bisdemethoxycurcumin) are nontoxic polyphenolic derivatives of curcumin that exert a wide range of biological activities [
 <xref rid="B9-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Several phytochemical studies on 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> oils led to the identification of sesquiterpenoids and monoterpenoids as the major components [
 <xref rid="B9-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The essential oil (EO) of 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> species possesses a wide variety of pharmacological properties, including anti-inflammatory, anticancerous, antiproliferative, hypocholesterolemic, antidiabetic, antihepatotoxic, antidiarrheal, carminative, diuretic, antirheumatic, hypotensive, antioxidant, antimicrobial, antiviral, insecticidal, larvicidal, antivenomous, antithrombotic, antityrosinase, and cyclooxygenase-1 (COX-1) inhibitory activities, among others [
 <xref rid="B7-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> oils are also known to enhance immune function, promote blood circulation, accelerate toxin elimination, and stimulate digestion [
 <xref rid="B18-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">C. longa</italic> (turmeric) and 
 <italic class="italic">C. zedoaria</italic> (zedoary) are the most extensively studied species of 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> due to their high commercial value. Other 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic> species have been studied to a lesser degree. This review provides an update on recent studies performed on the chemical composition and biological studies on genus 
 <italic class="italic">Curcuma</italic>. The search engines Google Scholar, PubMed, ScienceDirect, and ResearchGate were used to access the literature.
</p>
