<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The gramineous plant 
 <italic>Deyeuxia angustifolia</italic> (Komarov) Y. L. Chang (
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic>), originally distributed on the low altitude birch forest belt of the Changbai Mountains, is one of the dominant herbs under birch forest. However, field observations in the past 30 years have shown that after growth and reproduction, 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> at lower elevations of the tundra have been connected into patches. The increasing biomass of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> has been able to exclude native plants such as 
 <italic>Rhododendron chrysanthum Pall.</italic> and 
 <italic>Vaccinium uliginosum Linn.</italic> and became the only dominant species [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The main reason for the upward expansion of the tundra belt on 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> was that a large number of forest gaps were formed due to the typhoon that occurred in 1986, which created a natural expansion opportunity for low altitude plants [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. In the subsequent warming and nitrogen deposition experiments, the researchers compared the effects of warming and nitrogen deposition on the expansion of the 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> plant and the native 
 <italic>Rhododendron chrysanthum Pall.</italic> plant in the tundra of the Changbai Mountains. The results showed that nitrogen deposition significantly promoted the growth of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic>. Nutrient disturbance may be the main reason for the expansion of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> into tundra ecosystem of the Changbai Mountains [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The previous studies of our research group showed that the expansion of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> significantly reduced the species diversity and aboveground biomass of the native plant community, and changed the soil microbial community structure of native plants in the tundra belt [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-10-00291" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Consequently, previous studies mainly explored the reasons for the expansion of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> into the tundra zone and its impact on native plants in the tundra. However, the adaptation mechanism of 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic> invading the tundra is still unclear. In the end, we will gain better knowledge on how 
 <italic>D. angustifolia</italic>, and probably other invasive species, adapt to stressful environments.
</p>
