<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">The net reproductive rate (R
 <sub>0</sub>) represents the potential of the female offspring to replace the mother throughout her life. This parameter is a good predictor of population growth and is strongly influenced by immature survival rates and female fecundity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. The high values of R
 <sub>0</sub> calculated for 
 <italic>S. americanum</italic>, 
 <italic>S. gilo</italic>, 
 <italic>S. habrochaites</italic>, 
 <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, 
 <italic>S. melongena</italic> and 
 <italic>S. tuberosum</italic> indicated that 
 <italic>T. absoluta</italic> populations would be predicated to increase when larvae developed on these plants. These experiments were performed under controlled conditions, with 
 <italic>T. absoluta</italic> larvae isolated from natural environmental factors (natural enemies and climatic elements). Under field conditions, the natural mortality of 
 <italic>T. absoluta</italic> is around of 92–99%, as verified in ecological life tables by Bacci et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> and Miranda et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. The colonization of plants with low nutritional quality may jeopardize the persistence of non-indigenous insects in the environment due the high mortality, decreased fecundity and extended life cycle, increasing exposure to natural mortality factors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. However, environment conditions suitable for survival and the absence of natural enemies may reduce the impact of food quality on the establishment and spread of invasive species into new regions. Cherif et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup> demonstrated that temperature and relative humidity can impact the biological performance of 
 <italic>T. absoluta</italic> on host plants such as tomato, potato and eggplant. On average, 81 females replace the mother when insects were reared on potato, and this number was similar to that on tomato (72.72). A possible explanation for this result could be the low mortality of the immature stages (larvae and pupae) (24%) and high female fecundity (211.88 eggs) following development on tomato and potato plants (13% and 188 eggs). These results are different to those obtained by Pereyra and Sanchez
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup> and Kanle Satishchandra et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>, who documented a higher R
 <sub>0</sub> on tomato (49 and 52.15) in relation to potato (14 and 27.60). We attribute these differences to the plant varieties and genetic differences between 
 <italic>T. absoluta</italic> populations used by each research group.
</p>
