<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="app1-molecules-25-04818">
  <title>Supplementary Materials</title>
  <p>The following are available online at, Figure S1: Sage 1H NMR spectrum (600 MHz, 0.5 mL CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>; 5 mm sample tube; 25 °C; 32 
   <italic>K</italic> data points; 256 scans; 0.37 Hz/point; 1 s delay), Figure S2: Sage 1H-1H COSY NMR spectrum (600 MHz, CDCl3-d, 25 °C), Figure S3: Sage 1H-1H TOCSY NMR spectrum (600 MHz, CDCl3-d, 25 °C), Figure S4: Sage 1H-13C HMQC NMR spectrum (CDCl3-d, 25 °C). The 600 MHz 1H NMR spectrum is shown at the top edge and a 150 MHz 13C NMR spectrum at the left-hand edge, Figure S5: Sage 1H-13C HMBC NMR spectrum (CDCl3-d, 25 °C). The 600 MHz 1H NMR spectrum is shown at the top edge and a 150 MHz 13C NMR spectrum at the left-hand edge, Figure S6: Sage 13C APT NMR spectrum (150 MHz, 0.5 mL CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>; 5 mm sample tube; 25 °C; 64 
   <italic>K</italic> data points; 44506 scans; 0.60 Hz/point; 1 s delay), Figure S7: Bay laurel 1H NMR spectrum (600 MHz, 0.5 mL CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>; 5 mm sample tube; 25 °C; 32 
   <italic>K</italic> data points; 256 scans; 0.37 Hz/point; 1 s delay), Figure S8: Bay laurel 1H-1H COSY NMR spectrum (600 MHz, CDCl3-d, 25 °C), Figure S9: Bay laurel 1H-1H TOCSY NMR spectrum (600 MHz, CDCl3-d, 25 °C), Figure S10: Bay laurel 1H-13C HMQC NMR spectrum (CDCl3-d, 25 °C). The 600 MHz 1H NMR spectrum is shown at the top edge and a 150 MHz 13C NMR spectrum at the left-hand edge, Figure S11: Bay laurel 1H-13C HMBC NMR spectrum (CDCl3-d, 25 °C). The 600 MHz 1H NMR spectrum is shown at the top edge and a 150 MHz 13C NMR spectrum at the left-hand edge, Figure S12: Bay laurel 13C APT NMR spectrum (150 MHz, 0.5 mL CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>; 5 mm sample tube; 25 °C; 64 
   <italic>K</italic> data points; ca. 30000 scans; 0.60 Hz/point; 1 s delay), Figure S13: Rosemary 1H NMR spectrum (600 MHz, 0.5 mL CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>; 5 mm sample tube; 25 °C; 32 
   <italic>K</italic> data points; 128 scans; 0.37 Hz/point; 1 s delay), Figure S14: Rosemary 1H-1H COSY spectrum (600 MHz, CDCl3-d, 25 °C), Figure S15: Rosemary 1H-1H TOCSY spectrum (600 MHz, CDCl3-d, 25 °C), Figure S16: Rosemary 1H-13C HMQC spectrum (CDCl3-d, 25 °C). The 600 MHz 1H NMR spectrum is shown at the top edge and a 150 MHz 13C NMR spectrum at the left-hand edge, Figure S17: Rosemary 1H-13C HMBC spectrum (CDCl3-d, 25 °C). The 600 MHz 1H NMR spectrum is shown at the top edge and a 150 MHz 13C NMR spectrum at the left-hand edge, Figure S18: Rosemary 13C APT NMR spectrum (150 MHz, 0.5 mL CDCl
   <sub>3</sub>; 5 mm sample tube; 25 °C; 64 
   <italic>K</italic> data points; ca. 34000 scans; 0.60 Hz/point; 1 s delay), Figure S19: (A) Rosemary, (B) sage and (C) bay laurel essential oils 1H NMR spectra at 600 MHz in CDCl3-d. The enumeration scheme used for the assignment of the NMR spectra is shown for every compound. Figure S20: Scatter plot showing correlations between different pretreatments (on the diagonal) regarding the chemical composition of sage essential oils. Significant 
   <italic>p</italic>-values based on Spearman’s rank test are shown above the diagonal, while bivariate scatter plots are shown below the diagonal, Figure S21: Scatter plot showing correlations between different pretreatments (on the diagonal) regarding the chemical composition of bay laurel essential oils. Significant 
   <italic>p</italic>-values based on Spearman’s rank test are shown above the diagonal, while bivariate scatter plots are shown below the diagonal, Figure S22: Scatter plot showing correlations between different pretreatments (on the diagonal) regarding the chemical composition of rosemary essential oils. Significant 
   <italic>p</italic>-values based on Spearman’s rank test are shown above the diagonal, while bivariate scatter plots are shown below the diagonal. Table S1. Chemical composition of sage essential oils isolated by hydrodistillation with and without different pretreatments, Table S2. Chemical composition of bay laurel essential oils isolated by hydrodistillation with and without different pretreatments, Table S3. Chemical composition of rosemary essential oils isolated by hydrodistillation with and without different pretreatments.
  </p>
 </app>
</app-group>
