<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To protect plants from oxidative stress and maintain normal cell function, antioxidant enzymes including SOD, POD, CAT, and APX, play the role of ROS scavengers in plants. We can further understand the molecular adaptation of plants to HT stress by studying the gene expression underlying the change in antioxidant enzyme activity. The results indicated that the SOD, POD, CAT, and APX genes of 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> showed low expression at the transcription level (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f005">Figure 5</xref>D–G), and the antioxidant enzyme activity was also decreased under HT stress (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f004">Figure 4</xref>A–D). Studies have demonstrated that various environmental stresses lead to H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> production, and its excessive production causes the regulation of POD, CAT, and APX genes expression [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. It has also been found that a decrease in CAT and APX activity will greatly weaken the protective effect of the antioxidant system, resulting in an increase in the active oxygen concentration [
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The decrease in CAT and POD enzyme activities could not timely convert H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> into H
 <sub>2</sub>O and O
 <sub>2</sub> that was harmless to cells. In contrast, under HT treatment, the antioxidant enzyme gene expression and its regulated enzyme activity of 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> remained at a high levels as observed under normal temperature, which was an important reason for its stronger ROS-scavenging ability. In addition, non-enzymatic antioxidants including flavonoids (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f003">Figure 3</xref>E), total phenols content (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f003">Figure 3</xref>F), and TAC (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f003">Figure 3</xref>G) decreased significantly, indicating that scavenging capacity of ROS was much lower than that of 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic>. Moreover, carotenoid content increased in 
 <italic>S. trilobata</italic> but decreased significantly in 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> under HT stress (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00748-f001">Figure 1</xref>E). Studies have found that carotenoids could act as endogenous antioxidants of cells, absorbing residual energy, quenching active oxygen, and preventing membrane peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-00748" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Therefore, the destruction of the antioxidant system, which failed to remove ROS in a timely manner, was the main reason that the degree of oxidative stress in 
 <italic>S. calendulacea</italic> is more serious than that of in 
 <italic>S. trilobata.</italic>
</p>
