<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0155">Regarding the impact of 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> on the diversity indexes of the studied locations, the species richness and evenness were higher outside the canopy, which indicates a negative effect of the invasive shrub 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> on the plant biodiversity in the study area. The invasive species have been reported to decrease the biodiversity in several habitats, worldwide (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Gawad and El-Amier, 2015</xref>). This impact of invasive species is attributed to competition with the native plants for nutrients, water, and space (
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Broadbent et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Schultheis and MacGuigan, 2018</xref>). Moreover, this shrub is characterized by a high growth rate and one shrub can produces 10,000–1,000,000 seeds per year, that are dispersed by hydrochory, the most effective seed dispersal way (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Florentine and Westbrooke, 2005</xref>). Also, many invasive plants are characterized by the production of allelochemicals that inhibit or kill the native species (
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Hierro and Callaway, 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Florentine and Westbrooke, 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Gawad, 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Abd-ElGawad et al., 2020</xref>). The shrub 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> shrub is characterized by its allelopathic effect against native species such as 
 <italic>Juniperus procera</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Alshahrani, 2008</xref>), as well as crops such as 
 <italic>Lactuca sativa</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Florentine and Westbrooke, 2005</xref>), 
 <italic>Medicago sativa</italic> and 
 <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">El-Kenany et al., 2017</xref>). The extract of 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> has been reported to have several allelochemicals such as alkaloids, flavonoids, glycosides, Sterols, phenolics, and coumarins (
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">El-Kenany et al., 2017</xref>). However, further study is recommended for deep characterization of the allelochemical compounds in 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic>, and for determination of their mode of actions and allelopathic activity against a wide range of weeds.
</p>
