<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Rhynchanthus</italic> J. D. Hooker is a small genus of Zingiberaceae, with about four species distributed in Indonesia, Myanmar, and Southern China [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. 
 <italic>Rhynchanthus beesianus</italic> W. W. Smith is a perennial herb, cultivated as a medicinal, edible, and ornamental plant in Myanmar and Southern China [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. 
 <italic>R. beesianus</italic> is a wild edible spice, and its tender leaf and rhizome are used as vegetables in Yunnan Province, China. 
 <italic>R. beesianus</italic> flower with brilliant color and peculiar brush shape is used as a fresh cut flower. Its rhizome has been used as an aromatic stomachic in traditional Chinese medicine to treat stomachache and indigestion [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Additionally, the essential oils from 
 <italic>R. beesianus</italic> have been used as an aromatic stomachic in China [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. According to the previous study, the essential oil of 
 <italic>R. beesianus</italic> rhizome was mainly composed of 1,8-cineole (47.6%), borneol (15.0%), methyleugenol (11.2%), and bornyl formate (7.6%) and was found to possess antibacterial, anti-inflammatory, 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase, and acetylcholinesterase activity inhibitory properties [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
 <italic>R. beesianus</italic> mainly relies on the vegetative propagation of rhizome for population expansion. Only harvesting the aerial parts (flower, leaf, and stem) of 
 <italic>R. beesianus</italic> can reduce its damage, which is conducive to its sustainable use. However, there are no reports on the chemical components and antibacterial and anti-inflammatory properties of essential oils from 
 <italic>R. beesianus</italic> flower, leaf, and stem.
</p>
