<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Regarding the C2 phenyl ring (
 <xref ref-type="scheme" rid="SCH0001" class="xref">Scheme 1</xref>), small electron donor groups (EDGs) such as the amino moiety (compound 
 <bold class="bold">12</bold>, 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>
 <sub class="sub">dOASS-A</sub> = 1.4 μM), when not substituted, allowed to maintain good binding properties, whereas bulkier groups such as the nitro and a substituted alkylamine (compound 
 <bold class="bold">8</bold>, 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>
 <sub class="sub">d</sub>
 <sub class="sub">OASS-A</sub> = 61 μM; compound 
 <bold class="bold">10</bold>, 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>
 <sub class="sub">dOASS-A</sub> = 155 μM) weakened the interaction of the molecule with the active pocket, thus decreasing the affinity. It is possible to conclude that expansion of the series towards the 
 <italic class="italic">para</italic> position of the phenyl ring, unless carried out with small groups, is detrimental for the activity of the compounds. To increase the polarity of the molecule, substitution of the C2 phenyl ring with a pyridine showed to be a more fruitful strategy, with high affinity toward both isoforms (compound 
 <bold class="bold">5</bold>, K
 <sub class="sub">dOASS-A</sub> = 0.4 μM, 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>
 <sub class="sub">dOASS-B</sub> = 6.1 μM). Even though the carboxylic acid group is essential for the binding to OASS
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">27</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">28</sup>
 </xref>, its scarce diffusion across biological membranes is a well-known issue
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">32</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">33</sup>
 </xref>. Therefore, to preserve the key interactions with the target, we carried out the replacement of the carboxylic acid by several isosters (
 <xref ref-type="scheme" rid="SCH0002" class="xref">Scheme 2</xref>). Substitution with a sulphonamide led to molecules unable to elicit significant changes in the fluorescence emission of the cofactor, potentially indicating that the compounds did not bind to the active site of the enzyme. This prompted us to further investigate the mechanism of inhibition of these molecules, since the residual activity at saturating concentrations is significant (about 40 − 50%, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>, panel A). The molecules are poorly soluble in the buffer used for activity assays, compound 24 having a solubility limit of about 250 μM and compound 25 of about 50 μM. This hampers the accurate determination of the inhibition mechanism due to limitations to the range of inhibitor concentration that can be explored. However, since partial inhibition is a typical feature of allosteric inhibitors, we used a method developed by our group
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">24</sup>
 </xref> to assess if compound 
 <bold class="bold">25</bold> is able to displace a low affinity active site binder, 1-ethylcyclopropane-1,2-dicarboxylic acid, that forms a highly fluorescent complex with OASS. Compound 
 <bold class="bold">25</bold> is unable to displace the compound up to an equimolar concentration of about 200 μM. This is a strong indication that compound 
 <bold class="bold">25</bold> is not able to compete for binding to the active site with 1-ethylcyclopropane-1,2-dicarboxylic acid. Therefore, either the dissociation constant of compound 
 <bold class="bold">25</bold> for OASS-B is much higher than 170 μM (the 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>
 <sub class="sub">d</sub> of 1-ethylcyclopropane-1,2-dicarboxylic acid for OASS-B) or compound 
 <bold class="bold">25</bold> does not bind to the active site of the enzyme (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>, panel B). Unfortunately, replacement of the carboxylic acid by a tetrazole resulted in the decrease of the binding affinity (compound 
 <bold class="bold">29</bold>, 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>
 <sub class="sub">dOASS-A</sub> = 90 μM). Additional derivatization of the carboxylic acid group to deliver a small series of amides (compounds 
 <bold class="bold">16</bold>–
 <bold class="bold">22</bold>) was attempted as well in order to gain further insights into the anchoring groups that can be tolerated by StOASS. Either unsubstituted or substituted amides, regardless of the moiety attached to the nitrogen atom, had in general a detrimental effect on the binding constant. Rather surprisingly, the good activity of the tertiary amide 
 <bold class="bold">16</bold> (compound 
 <bold class="bold">16</bold>, IC
 <sub class="sub">50 OASS-A</sub> = 17.2 μM) represents an exception to the SAR information collected. Indeed, from the bulk of experimental data so far described, it can be speculated that carboxylic acid replacement is tolerable if at that position the presence of a sharable hydrogen is granted. By contrast, the lack of a hydrogen for H-bond formation in compound 
 <bold class="bold">16</bold> makes difficult its collocation within the SAR. With the help of computational methods, further efforts on the study of the mechanism of binding for this molecule will help in the explanation of this odd result.
</p>
