<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the study of de Souza Grinevicius et al. [
 <xref rid="B312-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">312</xref>], the ethanolic extract of 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> fruits was evaluated for its antitumor activity in Balb/C mice model of Ehrlich carcinoma and breast (MCF-7) and colon cancer (HT-29) cell lines. The dytotoxicity of the extract was determined in carcinoma cells by 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) assays and effective concentrations (EC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>) of 27.1 ± 2.0 µg/mL in MCF-7 and 80.5 ± 6.6 µg/mL in HT-29 were found. In vivo studies exhibited that extract treatment elicited 60% decrease of tumor growth and 76% increase of survival time together with stimulation of apoptosis which collectively resulted in inhibition of Ehrlich carcinoma in mice. Furthermore, Bax and p53 protein expression levels were increased, whereas Bcl-xL and cyclin A expressions were inhibited with the treatment of extract; so, cell cycle arrest at G1/S and increased rate of apoptosis were observed. The following year, a more effective extraction method—Supercritical Fluid Extraction (SFE)—was introduced; briefly a high-pressure unit was used to obtain extract from the 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> fruits, specifically Bragantina cultivar [
 <xref rid="B313-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">313</xref>]. SFE produced an extraction product, namely SFE200, having a minimum ratio of monoterpenes/ sesquiterpenes and a relatively higher concentration of piperine. SFE200 showed higher cytotoxic effects on MCF-7 cells than conventional extracts. In vivo studies validated the effect of this special extract for which Ehrlich tumor-bearing mice were selected as model organism. Treatment by SFE200 at a dose of 10 mg/kg/day presented more significant tumor growth inhibition and increased the time for survival comparing with conventional extract treatment group. It was also noticed that SFE200 decreased cell number founding at S phase, probably due its apoptotic effect by arresting G2/M phase of cell cycle.
</p>
