<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In contrast to the above study where the piperine content was increased, the biological effects of piperine-free 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigrum</italic> (PFPE) extract were investigated in the study of [
 <xref rid="B314-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">314</xref>]. Several cancer cell lines and two normal cell lines were subjected to different doses of PFPE to determine its cytotoxicity and selectivitiy index. Among cell lines, PFPE showed higher cytotoxic effect on MCF-7 breast carcinoma cells (IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>: 7.45 µg/mL) together with better selectivity. Flow cytometry analysis demonstrated that PFPE induced apoptosis on MCF-7 carcinoma cells in a dose-dependent manner. The expressions of apoptosis-associated proteins were also examined by western blot, and treatment by PFPE with IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> concentration upregulated p53 and cyt C and downregulated topoisomerase II. Similar results were also obtained for in vivo studies. When rats with mammary tumorigenesis were administered with 100 mg/kg PFPE, tumor grew much smaller as compared to non-treated control group. The same research group published one more article in the following year that clarifies the action mechanisms of PFPE on breast cancer [
 <xref rid="B315-molecules-24-01364" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">315</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-nitroso-
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>-methylurea-stimulated mammary carcinoma rat models were administred with different concentrations of PFPE (100, 200 and 400 mg/kg). The most significant tumor suppression activity was obtained in 400 mg/kg treated groups and suppression scores were 2.18-fold and 1.75-fold for 100 and 200 mg/kg treatment groups, respectively. Moreover, PFPE decreased the expression level of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), E-cad and c-Myc proteins as compared to control groups, while protein level of p53 was significantly increased. Western-blot analyzes over breast cancer cell line MCF-7 exhibited similar results for those proteins but expressions of proteins were not changed significantly in PFPE-treated ZR-75-1 cell line. In conclusion, PFPE was found to be a promising extract for the suppression of uncontrolled proliferation of cancer cells through increasing the expression level of p53 and by decreasing the level of c-Myc.
</p>
