<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The synthesis of volatile compounds in olives arises during the oil accumulation phase because the main compounds (hexanal, hexyl acetate, (
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>)-hex-3-en-1-al, (
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>)-hex-3-en-1-ol, (
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-hex-2-en-1-al, (
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-hex-2-en-1-ol, (
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>)-hex-3-enyl acetate, and (
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>)-hex-2-enyl acetate) are formed through the lipoxygenase (LPO) pathway from linoleic and linolenic acids. Alcohols, esters, and ketones are also formed by fatty acid metabolism [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. In this study, it was noticed that the alcohol concentration of all deficit irrigation oils was higher than that of the control oil. This fact may be related to an increase of LPO pathway as a result of water stress [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. García et al. [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] found similar results to those shown in the current study; alcohols increased when water stress was applied to “Arbequina” cultivar. Other studies with different olive varieties also reported an increase of volatiles after applying water stress. It was found that 6C “green volatile” compounds, 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-3-hexen-1-ol, and hexyl acetate augmented when stress was applied on “Koroneiki” cultivar [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Similar changes on aldehydes and alcohols were reported by Servili et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] on “Leccino” cultivar under water stress, as well as an increase in 2-hexen-1-ol on “Frantoio” olive oil [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Changes in polyphenols, volatiles, and fatty acids are directly correlated with changes in sensory descriptors of olive oil [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. With respect to other cultivars under water stress, it was found that for “Leccino” and “Koroneiki” olive oils, under water stress had an increase in the pungent and bitter descriptors on oils with higher phenolic concentrations [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], but, with respect to “Arbequina” olive oil, it was found that deficit irrigation did not affect sensory quality [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], although Gomez Del Campo et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] reported that bitterness could change when the irrigation is applied in July or August and also with the intensity of the stress. In the current study, bitterness and astringency scores only decreased in the T1 oil, where the lower concentration of polyphenols, aldehydes, and ketones was found.
</p>
