<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Cannabis is potent in its gynecological actions, and cannabinoids might potentially influence the dysregulation of the endocannabinoid system whereby as specific agonists or antagonists (Luschnig and Schicho 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2019</xref>, Russo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">2002</xref>). FMPs of Bangladesh have used 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> for gynecological problems like excessive menstrual and its pain, erectile dysfunctions (Hasan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2015a</xref>, Rahmatullah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2010g</xref>, Siddique et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">2006</xref>, Walid et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">2013</xref>). Similarly, herbal practitioners of Western Uganda and tribal communities near the Pak-Afghan border area also reported treating gynecological problems (abdominal pain, gonorrhea, sexual impotence, erectile dysfunctions) with the plant Cannabis (Aziz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2018</xref>, Kamatenesi-Mugisha and Oryem-Origa 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2005</xref>). The traditional usage of Cannabis was mentioned as an abortifacient in Bangladesh (Kona and Rahman 2006) together with Afghanistan, India, sand South Africa (Ross 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2007</xref>). In animal studies, THC was found to impair women’s fertility (Misner and Favetta 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2020</xref>, Wang et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136">2006</xref>), as well as Cannabis was reported to inhibit the capacity for male fertility (Payne et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2019</xref>). Despite this, Cannabis has been reported to be used as traditional aphrodisiac in Bangladesh (Nawaz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2009</xref>, Rahmatullah et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">2010g</xref>), India, and the USA (Ross 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2007</xref>).
</p>
