<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effective potentiality of studied plant EOs due to the presence of the most toxic components for insects such as linalool and linalyl acetate for 
 <italic>O. basilicum</italic>, linalool, methyl ether, linoleic acid ethyl ester for 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> and lavandulyl acetate for 
 <italic>L. angustifolia</italic> similar to previous studies proved major constituents in essential oils with toxic activity and insecticidal potentialities such as limonene, camphor, 1, 8-cineole, and g-terpinene [
 <xref rid="B78-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Studied EOS resulted in death for 
 <italic>S. oryzae</italic> adult pest, and this may be because of neurotoxic effect for these plants Eos, as revealed previously, which medicinal volatile and aromatic wild plants contain essential chemical constituents acting as inhibitors for 
 <italic>S. oryzae</italic> and other insects [
 <xref rid="B80-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. In this study, toxicity against 
 <italic>S. oryzae</italic> through detecting the mortality percentage was highest using 
 <italic>L. angustifolia</italic> EO with the value of 100% at 48 and 24 h, this result agrees with the result of [
 <xref rid="B82-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], who reported the highest mortality against 
 <italic>Sitophilus oryzae</italic> and 
 <italic>Callosobruchus chinensis</italic> with the value of 100% after two days using 
 <italic>Cinnamomum sieboldii</italic> bark extract. The highest Inhibition activity and toxicity were recorded using EOs of 
 <italic>L. angustifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>O. basilicum</italic> due to their plants are aromatic and contain volatile oils. In the same context, [
 <xref rid="B83-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>] ensured that oils with high volatility led to the decay of insects through their fumigant and gaseous actions. Our results are in harmony with [
 <xref rid="B84-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>], who reported that cinnamon EO had the most toxic effect at 1 h against 
 <italic>S. zeamais</italic>. Gene CYPs is a metabolic component in microorganisms and insects and plants; which released against any stresses as insecticides, pesticides, fungicides, and herbicides through increasing the activity of flavonoids compounds and increasing the antioxidant activity. Mode of action of CYPs occurs through increasing the content of CBT-ol which induces and exhibits resistance [
 <xref rid="B85-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Results of qRT-PCR revealed the expression of selected genes CL8, CYP 4Q4, and CL1294 demonstrated the expression of these genes up and down in each treatment. Mode of action for detoxification genes inside insects has three pathways [
 <xref rid="B86-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. For pathway 1 functional group as nucleophilic was infused to the xenobiotic compound which active and considered as a water-soluble compound, the gene of cytochrome CYP 4Q4 is important in phase I. These genes have the main role in the detoxification and metabolization of insecticides leading to reduce toxic effect [
 <xref rid="B87-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. For phase II, enzymes increase solubility for water for the metabolite of Phase I through union with endogenous compound, which prevents tissue damage through combination with molecules of insecticides and CL1294 important in this phase [
 <xref rid="B88-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Finally, in phase III, ABC enzyme transport xenobiotic compound out of the cell [
 <xref rid="B89-plants-10-00829" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>].
</p>
