<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">
   <italic>Nymphaea lotus</italic> L. 
   <italic>(N. lotus)</italic> is an aquatic plant with anecdotal reports suggesting its use in the traditional management of cancer. However, there is a paucity of data on the antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and cytotoxic properties of 
   <italic>N. lotus</italic> in relation to its phytochemical and elemental contents. This study aimed at determining the antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and cytotoxic properties of the hydro-ethanolic extract of 
   <italic>N. lotus</italic> leaves (NLE), and its phenolic, flavonoid and elemental constituents.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">The antioxidant property of NLE was determined using total phenolic and flavonoid, DPPH radical scavenging, lipid peroxidation and reducing power assays. The anti-inflammatory activity of NLE (100–250-500 mg/kg), diclofenac and hydrocortisone (positive controls) were determined by paw oedema and skin prick tests in 
   <italic>Sprague Dawley</italic> rats. Also, the erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) was determined by Westergren method. The macro/micro-elements content was determined by the XRF method. The cytotoxic property of NLE was determined by the MTT assay, on two cancer cell lines (MCF-7 and Jurkat) and compared to a normal cell line (Chang liver). Inhibitory concentrations were determined as IC
   <sub>50</sub> values (±SEM).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">The extract had appreciable levels of phenolic and flavonoids compounds and was two-fold more potent in scavenging DPPH radicals than Butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT). However, NLE was three- and six-fold less potent than ascorbic acid and BHT, respectively, in reducing Fe
   <sup>3+</sup> to Fe
   <sup>2+</sup>. The extract was six-fold more potent than gallic acid in inhibiting lipid peroxidation. The extract caused a dose-dependent decrease in rat paw oedema sizes, comparable to diclofenac, and a significant decrease in wheel diameters and ESR. The elemental analysis revealed relevant concentrations of Mg
   <sup>2+</sup>, P
   <sup>2+</sup>, S
   <sup>2+</sup>, K
   <sup>2+</sup>, Mn
   <sup>+</sup>, Fe
   <sup>+</sup>, Cu
   <sup>+</sup>, Zn
   <sup>+</sup> and Cd
   <sup>+</sup>. The extract exhibited cytotoxic activity on both MCF-7 (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 155.00 μg/ml) and Jurkat (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 87.29 μg/ml), with higher selectivity for Jurkat cell line. Interestingly, the extract showed low cytotoxicity to the normal Chang liver cell line (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 204.20 μg/ml).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4">
   <italic>N. lotus</italic> leaves extract exhibited high antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and cancer-cell-specific cytotoxic properties. These aforementioned activities could be attributed to its phenolic, flavonoid and elemental constituents.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Graphical abstract</title>
  <p id="Par5">
   <graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="12906_2020_3195_Figa_HTML" id="MO1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
