<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig-group id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Effect of Sb-EE on inflammatory gene expression and transcriptional factors. (A) To verify the effect of Sb-EE on inflammatory biomarker expression, RAW264.7 cells were pre-treated with Sb-EE, then stimulated with LPS (1 µg/mL) for 6 h. mRNA expression of 
   <italic>iNOS</italic>, 
   <italic>COX-2</italic> and 
   <italic>TNF-α</italic> was analysed by semi-quantitative RT-PCR. (B, C) To validate the effect of Sb-EE on the transcriptional activity of NF-κB and AP-1, a luciferase assay was performed. HEK 293 cells were transfected with NF-κB-Luc (B) or AP-1-Luc (C) genes, and Flag-MyD88 or CFP-TRIF were additionally overexpressed to activate transcription of NF-κB-Luc and AP-1-Luc genes. Then, HEK 293 cells were treated with Sb-EE (0–200 μg/mL) for 24 h. Luciferase activity was measured using a luminometer. (D) To analyse nuclear translocation of transcription factor subunits, Sb-EE (200 μg/mL) pre-treated RAW264.7 cells were stimulated with LPS for the indicated times. Then, the levels of AP-1 (c-Fos and c-Jun) and NF-κB subunits (p65 and p50) in nuclear lysate were determined by immunoblotting. Lamin A/C was utilized as a loading control. All data are presented as the mean ± SD of experiments. 
   <sup>##</sup>
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 compared to the normal group, and *
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and **
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 compared to the control group (LPS-alone group in (A, D), and MyD88/TRIF-alone group in (B, C)).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <fig id="F0002a" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
  <graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1866024_F0002a_B" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </fig>
 <fig id="F0002b" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
  <graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1866024_F0002b_B" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </fig>
</fig-group>
