<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prunella is a genus of perennial herbaceous plants in the Labiatae family. Approximately 15 species have been identified worldwide, most of which are distributed in the temperate regions of Europe and Asia. From this genus, the most extensively studied is 
 <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> (PV) (selfheal) due to its several thousand-year histories as an antipyretic and antidotal herb used in traditional Chinese medicine [
 <xref rid="B24-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The Prunella genus is known to contain triterpenoids and their saponins, phenolic acids, sterols and associated glycosides, flavonoids, organic acids, volatile oil and saccharides. Various pharmacological studies investigating Prunella have demonstrated the enhanced antiviral, antibacterial, anti-inflammatory, immunoregulatory, anti-oxidative and anti-tumour properties it possesses [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. PV is a herbaceous plant that is commonly known as self-heal and heal all [
 <xref rid="B27-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. PV has been reported to exhibit various biological properties including anti-inflammation, antimicrobial and even anticancer. PV has been widely studied via the use of in vitro studies; as a result, approximately 200 compounds have reported to be isolated from PV, many of which have been characterised as triterpenoids, sterols and flavonoids, followed by coumarins, phenylpropanoids, polysaccharides and volatile oils [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In order to investigate the antiviral mechanism of action of PV against Ebola virus (EBOV) infection, Zhang et al. developed a sensitive EBOV- glycoprotein (EBOV-GP) pseudo-typed HIV-1-based vector system. Based on this system, scientists showed that an aqueous extract from PV called CHPV exhibited potent inhibitory effects on EBOV-GP pseudo-typed virus in various cell lines including human umbilical vein endothelial cells and human macrophages. Moreover, the results concluded that in VeroE6 cells, CHPV was able to efficiently block eGFP-expressing Zaire Ebola virus (eGFP-ZEBOV) infection. The inhibition rate almost reached 99.5% when the concentration of CHPV was 20 μg/mL and when it was consistently present in the culture medium. This inhibitory effect of CHPV was observed in a dose exhibited in a dose-dependent manner. Additionally, at a concentration level of 12.5 μg/mL, CHPV showed more than 80% inhibition of EBOV-GP-V and eGFP-EBOV infections. In the same study, a “time-of-addition” study was performed in order to investigate the CHPV anti-EBOV mechanism of action. The results obtained concluded that the inhibitory effect of CHPV occurred via binding directly to EBOV-GP-Vs and possibly suppressing virus attachment through targeting the viral GP protein, thus blocking the early viral events [
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Previous studies investigating PV found that aqueous extracts from this herb had the potential to decrease the replication of herpes simplex virus (HSV) by directly preventing the virus to bind to cells as well as having the capability to inhibit HIV-1 infection by preventing viral attachment to CD4+ T cell receptor [
 <xref rid="B29-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. It has been previously suggested that the antiviral abilities of CHPV may be due to an anionic polysaccharide. Polysaccharides have the ability to bind to and from complexes with viral proteins, which can ultimately block virus entry into cells and thus prevent early infection. However, this polyanionic property of CHPV is yet to be determined [
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Interestingly, the results from this study also confirmed that CHPV has the ability to enhance anti-EBOV activity of the anti-EBOV antibody (2G4) against EBOV-GP. This antibody is an important component of the two-antibody cocktail, ZMAb and ZMapp. Previous investigations have shown that 2G4 has enhanced efficacy in blocking EBOV infection both in in vitro and in vivo animal models [
 <xref rid="B31-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The results from this study showed that combined use of 2G4 and CHPV at low concentrations achieved the same anti-EBOV-GP efficacy as a high concentration of 2G4 alone. Overall, from this study, it can be concluded that that CHPV has great anti-EBOV activity and has the potential to be developed as a novel antiviral approach against EBOV infection [
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This natural Chinese herb merits further investigations as an antiviral due to the promising results observed in its antiviral properties. Upon further research, these antiviral properties may also show efficacy against SARS-COV-2. 
</p>
