<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among the galling insects, Thysanoptera, commonly known as thrips, are suckers and induce their galls (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meyer, 1987</xref>) by means of chemical and/or mechanical stimuli, and alter the development of their host plant tissues (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mani, 1964</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hori, 1992</xref>). Galls result from the interaction between a galling organism and its host plant, and demand a high complex and intimate interaction between the associated species (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shorthouse et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raman, 2007</xref>). The galling organism manipulates the cellular communication system of the host plant by suppressing its defenses (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oates et al., 2016</xref>), and induces anatomical and biochemical changes in the host plant (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raman et al., 2005</xref>). Previous studies show that galling insects manipulate plant cells and tissues by the interaction between secondary metabolism and phytohormones (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bedetti et al., 2014</xref>). Also, gall induction impairs redox homeostasis, and the accumulation of reactive oxygen species in cell walls is responsible for cell wall loosening and consequent cell redifferentiation and hypertrophy (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Isaias et al., 2015</xref>). Both of these processes are commonly observed during gall growth and development. Nevertheless, how the insect is able to achieve such an extraordinary level of control over its host plant is perhaps the most intriguing question surrounding plant-galling insect interaction (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oates et al., 2016</xref>), and has not been fully described yet.
</p>
