<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antiproliferative effect of rosemary extract and its active ingradients carnosol, carnosic acid and rosmarinic acid on human ovarian cancer cells was investigated by Tai et al. Rosmary extract was shown to have significant antiproliferative effect in human ovarian cancer cells (A2780) and cisplatin resistance daughter cell line A2780CP70 with effective IC
 <sub>50</sub> at 1/1000 and 1/400 dilutions, respectively. Moreover, the extract and its active ingradients enhanced the antiproliferative effect (synergistic effect) of cisplatin in both A2780 and A2780CP70 cells. The effect of rosemary extract was due to the suppression of the expression of Bcl-2, Bcl-x, cIAP-1, HIF-, and HO-1 (anti-apoptosis proteins) and Bax, Fas and FADD (pro-apoptosis molecules). Furthermore, A2780 cells were more sensitive to carnosol, carnosic acid and rosmarinic acid than A2780CP70 cells. Interestingly, rosmary extract upregulated a heme-containing protein, cytochrome C, that was emitted from the mitochondria in response to pro-apoptotic stimuli [
 <xref rid="B196-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. Alternatively, rosemary extract inhibited cell proliferation and enhanced apoptosis of human NSCLC adenocarcinoma A549 cells in a dose-dependent manner. This effect was associated with the reduction in phosphorylated/activated Akt, mTOR and p70S6K levels [
 <xref rid="B197-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. Additionally, aqueous extract of the fruits of rosemary showed anti-cancer and cytotoxic effect against gastrointestinal cell lines, KYSE30 (human esophageal squamous cell carcinoma) and AGS (human gastric carcinoma). Using MTT assay, IC
 <sub>50</sub> value was 150 mg/mL after 72 h of exposure in KYSE30 cell lines, however, in AGS cell lines, IC
 <sub>50</sub> value was 1.3 mg/mL after 72 h of exposure [
 <xref rid="B198-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. In prostate cancer, rosmarinic acid minimized cell proliferation through the downregulation of p53 expression [
 <xref rid="B199-molecules-25-04207" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>].
</p>
