<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>This study deals with the green synthesis of chromium oxide (Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub>) nanoparticles using a leaf extract of 
  <italic>Abutilon indicum</italic> (L.) Sweet as a reducing and capping agent. Different characterization techniques were used to characterize the synthesized nanoparticles such as X-ray diffraction (XRD), Scanning electron microscope (SEM), Transmission electron microscope (TEM), Energy-dispersive X-ray (EDX), Fourier transform infrared (FTIR), X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS), and ultraviolet-visible (UV-VIS) spectroscopy. The X-ray diffraction technique confirmed the purity and crystallinity of the Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles. The average size of the nanoparticles ranged from 17 to 42 nm. The antibacterial activity of the green synthesized nanoparticles was evaluated against four different bacterial strains, 
  <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
  <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
  <italic>B. bronchiseptica</italic>, and 
  <italic>B. subtilis</italic> using agar well diffusion and a live/dead staining assay. The anticancer activities were determined against Michigan Cancer Foundation-7 (MCF-7) cancer cells using MTT and a live/dead staining assay. Antioxidant activity was investigated in the linoleic acid system. Moreover, the cytobiocompatibility was analyzed against the Vero cell lines using MTT and a live/dead staining assay. The results demonstrated that the green synthesized Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles exhibited superior antibacterial activity in terms of zones of inhibition (ZOIs) against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria compared to plant extracts and chemically synthesized Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles (commercial), but comparable to the standard drug (Leflox). The green synthesized Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles exhibited significant anticancer and antioxidant activities against MCF-7 cancerous cells and the linoleic acid system, respectively, compared to chemically synthesized Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles. Moreover, cytobiocompatibility analysis displayed that they presented excellent biocompatibility with Vero cell lines than that of chemically synthesized Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles. These results suggest that the green synthesized Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles’ enhanced biological activities might be attributed to a synergetic effect. Hence, green synthesized Cr
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>3</sub> nanoparticles could prove to be promising candidates for future biomedical applications.
 </p>
</abstract>
