<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The significance of bioactive components present in foods has been gaining interest recently due to public health concerns. Moreover, with rising consumer awareness regarding promotion, prevention as well as maintenance of health, bioactive components present in food could play a very important role [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Bioactive compounds can be described as molecules present in food derived of plant or animal sources consumed to have a regular energy intake along with various therapeutic activities such as against metabolic disorders, anti-inflammatory, chronic diseases and many more [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The presence of these bioactive components, even in minute quantities, not only meets the basic nutritional needs, but also confers numerous health benefits. Epidemiological studies indicate that high consumption of foods rich in bioactive compounds with different phytochemicals such as antioxidants, vitamins, flavonoids and carotenoids has a positive effect on human health [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Mushrooms have been known and used for centuries for food and medicinal use. Among various mushrooms, very well-known medicinal mushrooms like 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> producing bioactive metabolites are used or studied for the possible treatment of several diseases [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The presence of antioxidants acquired by modifying our diet with mushrooms could play an important role in the prevention of diseases. 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> have a history of medicinal use spanning millennia in parts of Asia, but they can also be potentially used for their nutraceutical values [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> have been reported to contain various bioactive components such as proteins, fat, carbohydrates, exopolysaccharides, cordycepin, phenolic compounds, polysaccharides, cordycepic acid, adenosine, proteoglucans, terpenoids, amphinol, steroids, ergosterol, lectins, etc. A detailed list of bioactive components present in 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> is presented in 
 <xref rid="molecules-25-02735-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> along with the chemical structures of some potent identified bioactive molecules (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-02735-f001">Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-02735-f002">Figure 2</xref>). Out of these, cordycepin is the main active constituent which is most widely studied for its medicinal value along with its nutraceutical potential [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Moreover, various mechanisms have been reported for the pharmacological actions of cordycepin such as inhibition of DNA and RNA synthesis, post-transcriptional processing of hnRNA and activation of adenylate cyclase, inhibition of chemotaxis and particular protein synthesis of macrophage cell lines, anti-tumorigenic activity on some cell lines, enhancement of cell differentiation etc. [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].
</p>
