<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the number of ethnomedicinal species and the number of use reports, we found that these 62 references documented 76 ginger species, that together had 771 use reports. As the treatment of the ginger family for the Flora of Thailand remains to be finished, we compared species in our list to the listing found in the book 
 <italic>Gingers of Thailand</italic> [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Plant names in that book were mostly the same as the plant names on the WCVP website [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and only 13 names from the book needed to be updated (2 
 <italic>Alpinia</italic> spp., 2 
 <italic>Amomum</italic> spp., 5 
 <italic>Globba</italic> spp., 
 <italic>Hedyhium</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Hornstedtia</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Kaempferia</italic> sp. and 2 
 <italic>Zingiber</italic> spp.). It is interesting that the data gathered for this study include many species that were not listed in the book (1 
 <italic>Alpinia</italic> sp., 2 
 <italic>Amomum</italic> spp., 1 
 <italic>Boesenbergia</italic> sp., 4 
 <italic>Curcuma</italic> spp., 1 
 <italic>Etlingera</italic> sp., 1 
 <italic>Gagnepainia</italic> sp., 1 
 <italic>Globba</italic> sp., 1 
 <italic>Rhyncanthus</italic> sp., 1 
 <italic>Stahlianthus</italic> sp. and 1 
 <italic>Zingiber</italic> sp.) [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-plants-09-00906">Tables S1 and S2</xref>). This suggests that some knowledge has been exchanged between areas, or adopted from other countries. Some gingers in our list, which are not listed in 
 <italic>Gingers of Thailand,</italic> were also used as medicine in China (Hong et al., 2015) [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Further, some species in our list may not have been taxonomically recorded in Thailand at the time the book was published in 2006. Likewise, the synopsis of the genus 
 <italic>Zingiber</italic> in Thailand, published in 1999 and based on herbarium specimens, includes fewer 
 <italic>Zingiber</italic> spp. than the book does [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
