<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>S. fruticosa</italic> is the fourth 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> species found to have protective properties against A
 <italic>β</italic> neurotoxicity [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], and this potential has been attributed to 
 <italic>Salvia</italic> adequacy in active constituents such as flavonoids, terpenoids, and phenolic acids [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In essential oils and extracts obtained from SF grown in various areas of Greece, Italy, Jordan, and Lebanon, many substances of these categories were identified [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>–
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Methanolic extracts obtained from SF grown at the experimental field of IPB&amp;GR, from which our study material was collected, were rich in phenolic acids such as rosmarinic acid and benzoic acid derivatives, in the terpenoids 1,8-cineole, carnosic acid, and carnosol, and in the flavonoids apigenin and luteolin, all of which are known neuroprotective substances [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>–
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The above active compounds are most likely present in the SF extracts of this study, and their presence in the three different extracts (SFD, SFM, and SFP) in different proportions can explain the differences in neuroprotective capacity between the extracts. However, the fact that SFD and SFP exhibit important neuroprotectivity, but have a lower TPC and TFC comparatively to the nonneuroprotective SFM, hints that the substances responsible for the neuroprotectivity in SF are not restricted to the polyphenols or the flavonoids categories, and those additional active substances may be present. Further phytochemical analysis, with the isolation and the structure elucidation of such compounds in every extract, may clarify the above points.
</p>
