<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <italic>Background</italic>. 
  <italic>Asphodelus tenuifolius</italic> Cav. (Asphodelaceae) is widely used in Pakistan traditional medicine as a hypotensive and diuretic agent. Despite the cardioprotective effects described for 
  <italic>A. tenuifolius</italic>, the mechanisms involved in its probable hypotensive and diuretic effects have never been evaluated. Firstly, different extracts from 
  <italic>A. tenuifolius</italic> seeds were obtained, and their antioxidant profiles and chemical constituents by LC-DAD-were determined, including molecular networking by the GNPS platform. Then, to evaluate changes in blood pressure, different groups of anesthetized normotensive rats were intravenously treated with the crude extract (AT-Cr, 1–50 mg/kg), aqueous (AS-AT, 1–25 mg/kg), n-butanol (BS-AT, 1–50 mg/kg), and dichloromethane fraction (DS-AT, 1–80 mg/kg). The diuretic effects of AT-Cr, AS-AT, BS-AT, and DS-AT at 100, 200, and 300 mg/kg, p.o. doses, were also evaluated in comparison with hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ, 10 mg/kg, p.o). The urinary volume, sodium, potassium, and pH were estimated in the sample collected for 6 h from saline-loaded rats. Using pharmacological antagonists or inhibitors, we determine the involvement of acetylcholine, prostaglandins, and nitric oxide in 
  <italic>A. tenuifolius</italic>-induced hypotensive and diuresis action. In addition, the activities of angiotensin-converting enzyme, erythrocyte carbonic anhydrase, and renal Na+/K+/ATPase were evaluated 
  <italic>in vitro</italic>. Acute treatment with crude extract and fractions of 
  <italic>A. tenuifolius</italic> exhibited significant hypotensive and diuretic potential in normotensive rats. However, AS-AT produced the most potent and significant dose-dependent hypotension and diuretic effects in normotensive rats. Previous treatment with atropine significantly reduced the hypotensive and diuretic action of AS-AT, but pretreatment with indomethacin or L-NAME did not affect these effects. Moreover, the 7-day treatment with AS-AT did not reduce activities of serum angiotensin-converting enzyme, erythrocyte carbonic anhydrase, and renal Na+/K+/ATPase. AS-AT showed four major compound node clusters, which included sugars, alkaloids, nucleoside, amino acid, and glycosylated flavonoids. This research supports and extends the traditional use of 
  <italic>A. tenuifolius</italic> as a hypotensive and diuretic agent. The results showed that AS-AT from 
  <italic>A. tenuifolius</italic> could present compounds responsible for hypotensive and diuretic activities through the activation of muscarinic receptors.
 </p>
</abstract>
