<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The presence of diosgenin, an aglycon of dioscin has also been reported in several species of yams, making yam one of the leading sources of steroidal sapogenin diosgenin, a precursor used for the synthesis of the steroidal drugs estrogen and progesterone in the pharmaceutical industry [
 <xref rid="B140-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. The synthesis of cortisone and hormonal drugs such as sex hormone, progestational hormone and other steroids with diosgenin extracted from 
 <italic>D. zingiberensis</italic>, 
 <italic>D. villosa</italic> and 
 <italic>D. composite</italic> have been reported [
 <xref rid="B141-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>,
 <xref rid="B142-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. The utilization of diosgenin is linked to its pharmacological activities and medicinal properties including decreasing oxidative stress, inducing apoptosis, suppressing malignant transformation, preventing inflammatory events, promoting cellular differentiation/proliferation and regulating the T-cell immune response, thus, resulting in antidiabetes, anticancer, neuro- and cardiovascular protective, immunomodulatory, estrogenic and skin protective effects [
 <xref rid="B134-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B143-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>,
 <xref rid="B144-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. A study by Tada et al. [
 <xref rid="B145-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>] examined the efficacy of diosgenin extracted from 
 <italic>D. composita</italic> or 
 <italic>D. villosa</italic> against skin aging. Their findings revealed potential of diosgenin to enhance DNA synthesis of skin using a human 3D skin equivalent model anda restoration of keratinocyte proliferation in aged skin. In addition, spirostanes possess better antimicrobial activity when compared to other steroid glycosides; however, the activity is dependent on the type and sequence of the sugars [
 <xref rid="B135-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>].
</p>
