<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Iwu et al. (1999) by GC/MS analysis reported 32 terpenoid compounds including 16 monoterpenes and 13 sesquiterpenes from the essential oil content of 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>suaveolens</italic> having antifungal and broad spectral antibacterial activity against both Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The diterpenoids comprise structurally diverse compounds that may be acyclic or having 1–5 ring system synthesized by mevalonate pathway and they constitute the integrated potential components of large number of medicinal plants of present and future drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Suaveolic acid (14α-hydroxy-13β-abiet-8en-18oic acid) and suaveolol are two diterpenoid compound present abundantly in 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>suaveolens</italic>, having high cytotoxic activity inhibiting growth of other plants adjacent to their clumps [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]
 <italic>.</italic> Plants specimens of 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>suaveolens</italic> also contain three triterpene lactones and triterpenoid compounds like betulinic acid, ursolic acid, Beta sitosterol, oleanic acid, and acetyloleanic acid [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. A new pharmacologically active pentacyclic triterpene Urs-12-en-3beta-29-oic acid have also been recorded from the 
 <italic>H. suaveolens</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Diterpenoid endoperoxide, 13alpha-epi-dioxiabiet-8(14)-en-ol, present in petroleum ether extract of leaves of 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>suaveolens</italic> have high antiplasmodic activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Ursolic acid (3-β hydroxy-urs-12-ene-28oic acid) is a natural pentacyclic triterpenoid (C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>48</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>) which is an important terpenoids reported in 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>suaveolens</italic> and other members of family Lamiaceae. It is synthesized from dammarenyl cation by cyclization of squalene in plants cells having diverse therapeutic potential and pharmacological effect [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The natural ursolic acid that occur in many plant species under family Lamiaceae need more analytical evidence to develop it into future drug to treat chronic diseases like cancer, diabetes, and viral infections like AIDS, COVID-19, etc. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].
</p>
