<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In human metabolism, it is well known that the human body needs certain essential minerals for its growth; in general, they are indispensable for a healthy human nutrition, with important physiological roles [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-10-01066" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].The result of mineral content analysis of 
 <italic>M. officinalis</italic> leaves presented in 
 <xref rid="plants-10-01066-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows that 
 <italic>M. officinalis</italic> leaf contains macro and microminerals, and that the most common element was K (16,412), followed by iron (282), Rb (75), Ba (58), Na (51), Zn (28). Shekarchi et al. stated that potassium was more common (17.275 ppm), followed by Ca (5698 ppm), Mg (5550 ppm), Fe (119.4 ppm), Na (83.34 ppm), and Zn (29.163 ppm). Lower values were recorded for Mn 16.41 ppm, Cu 6.559 and Ni 1.067 [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-10-01066" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-10-01066" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The difference in the concentration of these minerals among various studies is due to the plant’s ability to absorb nutrients from the soil, the soil’s mineral content, sample preparation, irradiation and the counting system [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-10-01066" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].By comparison between 
 <italic>M. officinalis</italic> leaves and the tomato leaves, it was found that there were some elements in abundance while some were absent. Tomato leaves contain Br, Fe, Na, and Zn, while 
 <italic>M. officinalis</italic> leaves contains K, Rb, Co, La, and Sm. On the other hand, compared with tea leaves, we found they contain Br, Co, K, and La, while 
 <italic>M. officinalis</italic> leaves contain Ba, Fe, Na, Rb, Sc, and Zn. When z-score was measured, it was found to be less than 2, which means that the estimation of these elements in all plants used was correct. Hence, it might be concluded and confirmed from this study, that this plant is not only a flavoring agent but also a good source of several essential nutrient elements.
</p>
