<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">Different carbon sources in the growth medium influence the composition of BS production. Carbon sources studied for BS production include crude oil, diesel, glucose, sucrose and glycerol. Several studies show that marine bacteria can utilize hydrocarbons as substrate and produce BS, therefore the ability of hydrocarbon degrading marine bacteria to produce BS could be utilized in the bioremediation of hydrocarbon-contaminated environments. 
 <italic class="italic">Halomonas</italic> sp. strain C2SS100 degraded hydrocarbons and produced BS at high salinity (Mnif et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">2009</xref>), while 
 <italic class="italic">Brevibacterium luteolum</italic> synthesized BS using mineral oil as a carbon source (Vilela et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" class="xref">2014</xref>). A 
 <italic class="italic">Brevibacillus</italic> strain degraded phenanthrene to produce BS (Reddy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">2010</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Alteromonas</italic> sp. 17 degraded hydrocarbons and produced BS using long chain alkane eicosane (Al-Mallah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">1990</xref>). Glycolipopeptide BS was also produced by 
 <italic class="italic">Corynebacterium kutscheri</italic> using cheaper carbon sources like waste motor lubricant oil and peanut oil cake (Thavasi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" class="xref">2007</xref>). It is important to bear in mind that for large-scale commercial production of BS the cost of the growth medium may only constitute a smaller contribution to the total production costs when the energy required to run the fermentation for a prolonged period is taken into account and since many renewable plant oils are relatively cheap, readily available and of consistent composition. Therefore, the obsessive search for ‘waste’ materials as substrates towards achieving cost effective processes may be unjustified.
</p>
