<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Differences between individuals from different locations are also confirmed by the higher content of SWM and GP in belowground parts obtained from Vlasina individuals and the higher content of MGF and ISOOR in aboveground parts of Golija individuals. Besides specific local climatic and topoedaphic conditions at two localities, sampled populations were members of different forest stands (beech-dominated in Vlasina and spruce-dominated in Golija), and differences in local flora and the composition of plant communities may also affect the production of secondary metabolites. Comparative analyses related to phytochemical profiling of geographically distinct populations of numerous species revealed the need for more research regarding the impact of both genetic origin and a specific set of environmental conditions on the composition and content of secondary metabolites [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Several studies documented the chemical variability among natural populations in 
 <italic>Gentiana</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The study of high-altitude 
 <italic>G. straminea</italic> showed significant interpopulation variability for several secondary metabolites, providing the basis for a geo-authentic production area for this traditional medicinal plant [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and our results show that particular metabolites can even be absent in the chemical profile of some populations. Sweroside, a secoiridoid with anti-inflammatory and analgesic properties, has been used in the treatment against osteoporosis in traditional Chinese medicine and can be a promising therapeutic product for this medical issue [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Information regarding its abundance in certain geolocations can be valuable for further investigation regarding the plant–environment biochemical response and indicative of exploitation and production.
</p>
