<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0185">In this study, we first revealed the effects of growth years and post-harvest processing on the contents of medicinal active ingredients of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. By estimating the contents of eight active ingredients (baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, wogonin, scutellarin, scutellarein, apigenin, and chrysin) in roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> of different growth years (ranging from 1 year to 15 years) using HPLC, we conducted a systematic analysis to determine the optimal harvest period of this important medicinal crop. Our results showed that the best harvest period for 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> should be determined as 2–3 years based on comprehensive evaluation of active ingredient content, annual yield increment, and land use efficiency. Meanwhile, we compared the contents of six active ingredients in different parts (cortex and stele) of roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, and monitored the dynamic changes of the contents of active ingredients in fresh-crush and fresh-cut roots of 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> at room temperature. In addition, we observed the effects of six different post-harvest treatments on the contents of active ingredients to determine the best primary processing technology. We concluded that the contents of baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, and wogonin in cortex were significantly higher than those in stele (
 <italic>P</italic> ≤  0.05). The contents of four main active ingredients (baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, and wogonin) under drying (
 <italic>D</italic>) and cutting-drying (
 <italic>C-D</italic>) treatments were significantly higher than those of the other four treatments (
 <italic>P</italic> ≤  0.05). Collectively, these results will provide valuable references for determining the optimal harvesting and processing technology that will obtain the maximum products of active ingredients for 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. Furthermore, the processing methods of softening, cutting, and drying proposed in this study will help improving the product yield for pharmaceutical industry of other medicinal crops.
</p>
