<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Effect of cultivar and NPK fertilization on the status of individual fatty acid may not lead to definite conclusion about the overall fatty acid composition in oil globule. Hence, we estimated various fatty acid ratios to draw logical conclusions. We observed that the year-effect was significant for different ratios. Significantly higher uptake of P and K in maize grain might be the key factor in determining significant variation in fatty acid ratios over the years. The higher ODR and LDR with concurrent lowering of MUFA: PUFA, saturated: unsaturated and linoleic: linolenic acid was observed in cultivar P 3396. Reverse trend was recorded in P 3522. The higher ODR advocates better and longer shelf-life of oil; however, reduced ODR inhibits the next desaturation steps, which finally leads to reduced linolenic acid contents [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Such results indicate better quality of oil, as we observed for extracted-oil from the tested cultivar P 3396. The average ODR and LDR were increased with increasing NPK levels up to 100 and 125% RDF, respectively. However, average MUFA: PUFA, saturated: unsaturated and linoleic: linolenic acid ratios were increased on receiving 75% RDF, and beyond that it showed decreasing trend. Omission of P recorded the highest ODR and LDR, and lowest MUFA: PUFA and linoleic: linolenic acid ratios. In case of K omission, the trend was just opposite to that of P omission. Dag et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>] also recorded significant reduction of MUFA: PUFA ratio with raising P and N-rates. The application of N promotes elongation of the carbon chain of linoleic acid and oleic acid, and encourages the ODR, LDR [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] and saturated: unsaturated fatty acid ratio [
 <xref rid="pone.0216939.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>].
</p>
