<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par56">Considering chalcones as an important subgroup of flavonoids and particularly one of the desirable scaffolds displaying unique anticancer activities, in a study by Ayati et al. a number of 4-amino-5-cinnamoylthiazoles derivatives were synthesized and investigated as chalcone- like anticancer agents. Synthesized derivatives were classified to three groups; pyrrolidine, piperidine, morpholine, and tested for their antiproliferative activities on MCF-7, HepG2 and SW480. In SAR studies, presence of various cyclic amine stocks to the thiazole core and substituent on the phenyl were assessed for antiproliferative profile. As a result, more favorable ring for antiproliferative activity was pyrrolidine ring. Pyrrolidine derivative namely (
 <italic>E</italic>)-1-(4-amino-2(pyrrolidin-1-yl)thiazol-5-yl)-3-(2,4-dichlorophenyl)prop-2-en-1-one (
 <bold>62)</bold> could significantly prevent proliferation of MCF-7 and especially HepG2 cell lines with IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 12.6 and 10.6 µg/mL, respectively. This compound was twofold more potent than its corresponding piperidine analog and was found to be significantly more active than its morpholine congener. While the unsubstituted cinnamoyl compounds in all series were active against all tested cell lines, introduction of 2,4-dichloro substituent on phenyl ring in pyrrolidine series increased the cytotoxicity. For comparison of 2,4-dichloro derivatives, 
 <bold>62</bold> with the corresponding 4-chloro analog, incorporation of second chlorine on phenyl ring increased cytotoxic effect on cell lines in pyrrolidine and morpholine series. Compound 
 <bold>62</bold> blocked G2 phase of cell cycle and induced apoptosis pathway that led to inhibit proliferation of HepG2 cells. Percentage of apoptotic cells for compound 
 <bold>62</bold> was obtained 44.3% that was higher than etoposide (18.1%). These results indicated that thiazole-based chalcones could be considered as effective cytotoxic leads (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>].
</p>
