<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dairy animals are often exposed to stressful agents due to environmental conditions (e.g., very high or very low temperatures), management (high yield, weaning, transportation, feedlot entry) or nutrition (e.g., a high-grain diet). Stressful events have been implicated in promoting oxidative stress through the excessive production of reactive oxygen species or decreased antioxidant defenses [
 <xref rid="B73-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Excessive reactive oxygen species production overwhelms antioxidant defenses, leading to the oxidative damage of biological molecules, disrupting normal metabolism and physiology. However, a reverse relationship between antioxidant intake and stress-related diseases is supported by numerous studies [
 <xref rid="B74-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Hence, improving antioxidant capacity through feeding of cornus extract alone or in combination with oregano and thyme is expected to enhance the overall health of sheep and, thus, to improve milk performance. In support of this, a recent study, carried out using 95 control heifers and 95 heifers fed with 0.9 kg/d of cornus extract, showed that the average daily gain increased from 0.89 to 1.12 kg/d [
 <xref rid="B67-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Therefore, it is hypothesized that feeding with red osier dogwood may influence the rumen microflora, immunity (intestine and body) and antioxidant status, and consequently impact feed digestion and immune response. Heat stress is one of the limiting factors affecting the production performance of Mediterranean dairy ruminants, since it evokes a series of drastic changes in animal biological functions, which include a decrease in feed intake efficiency and utilization; disturbances in the metabolism of water, protein, energy and mineral balances; enzymatic reactions; hormonal secretions and blood metabolites [
 <xref rid="B74-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. To avoid such situations, proper management approaches are needed. Thus, nutritional techniques can be a part of the solution; in this line, several studies have revealed that supplementing ruminants’ rations with various essential oils has shown promising results, such as a decrease in SCC in generally healthy dairy cows or goats under mild heat stress conditions [
 <xref rid="B75-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>].
</p>
