<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">The chemical composition and structure of lignocellulose has evolved to provide a barrier against microbial infection of the plant (Gupta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2016</xref>; Tavares and Buckeridge 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">2015</xref>). Straw, like all lignocellulose, is a heterogenous, multicomponent material mainly built by the three major plant polymers cellulose, hemicellulose and lignin. Cellulose is a polysaccharide consisting of cellobiose subunits. Due to the β-1,4 glycosidic bounds between the glucose units building up the cellulose chain, the glucose fibrils can be very tightly packed and form crystalline structures. Hemicellulose of monocotyledons, which are the sources of straw, are branched polysaccharides built of a xylan backbone with side chains of arabinose and glucuronic acid, the latter frequently methylated. Hemicelluloses have a random and amorphous structure; they form a network in the plant cell wall, crosslinking the cellulose fibrils and lignin. Their fine structure can vary from plant to plant, tissue to tissue and even within the same molecule (Girio et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2010</xref>; Holtzapple 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2003</xref>; Isikgor and Becer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2015</xref>; Biely et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2016</xref>). Lignin, in contrast to cellulose and hemicellulose, is not a polysaccharide but consists of phenylpropanoid units, which form a three-dimensional network. Lignin is hydrophobic, provides stiffness to the cell wall and resistance against insects and plant pathogens (Isikgor and Becer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2015</xref>). Some typical compositions of straw are provided in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>. There are, however, large variation in the proportions of the three major polymers in straw. In some studies, cellulose contents of wheat straw were found to reach almost 50% (Brandenburg et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2018</xref>; Saha et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2005</xref>). This composition variation is apparently due to differing proportions of tissues in different cultivars, i.e. the proportion of internode-, node-, leaf- and ear tissue (Collins et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
