<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0160">In order to determine the effect of microbial inoculation, it is very evident to know the feasibility of those microbes, particularly their combine outcome as different microbes have a different degree of colonization (
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Ambrosini et al. 2016</xref>). The present investigation showed that microbial inoculated sesame plants grew well with the different combinations used compared to control plants. It is apparent from the results that consortium treatment having AMF and 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>fluorescens</italic> was proved to be the best treatment. AM fungi are involved in stimulating strigolactones responsible for improving root and shoot growth, which might be why our study sesame plant height and root-shoot dry weight ratio increased compared to control (
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). The hyphopodia of AMF enter the plant root cortex to obtain lipid plus carbohydrate from the host plant (Sesame) and help the roots with increase uptake of nutrients, significantly P, which is compulsory for nucleic acids, enhancing the vegetative growth (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Bona et al. 2017</xref>). This might be the reason for the higher plant height and plant weight of sesame with PSB and AMF inoculation. Treatment/s comprises of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>laevis</italic> and 
 <italic>G</italic>. 
 <italic>mosseae</italic> showed diverse results in all parameters studied because the extent of sap (water + minerals) absorption might differ due to different colonization (
 <xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Jiang, 2015</xref>). Similarly, these AM fungi, when combining with 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>fluorescens,</italic> possess a different absorption rate (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Rashid et al. 2016</xref>). AMF produce organo-polysaccharides exudates that are decisive for soil porosity and quality, additionally when AMF inoculants mixed with 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>fluorescens</italic> activity of theses exudates become more commendable (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Rashid et al. 2016</xref>).
</p>
