<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0175">Additionally, it is reported that there is up-regulation of some aquaporin genes, nitrate transporters and plant glutathione-S-transferases by applying AMF and PSB, which facilitate and maintain ionic/water balance in the plants even under drought stress (
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Jia-Dong et al. 2019</xref>). The increment of 
 <italic>G. mosseae</italic> and 
 <italic>A. laevis</italic> in sesame plants positively correlated to AM colonization (
 <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Chitarra et al. 2016</xref>). This might be the reason for increased AM colonization and AM spore in the experiment. 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Gholinezhad and Darvishzadeh (2019)</xref> also reported an increase in sesame protein and oil content when inoculated by 
 <italic>Funneliformis mosseae</italic> and 
 <italic>Glomus intraradices</italic>. 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Harikumar (2017)</xref> also confirmed an increased in yield and oil content, up to 50% in Sesame when inoculated by AMF. Work done by these researchers and many others corresponds to our findings. Moreover, under stress conditions, the symbiotic fungi like AMF thrive and provide extra nutrients to the roots, producing effects such as development and higher yields. AMP can protect plants from rapidly changing climates. As a result, more studies are required to understand the AMF role in increasing crop quality and crop plants' productivity (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Ahanger et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Hameed et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Latef et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Malhi et al., 2021</xref>). The present assessment gives a current impression of the numerous nutrient requirements of AMF and their effects on different plant growth stages, including their crucial importance to oilseed crops like sesame, thereby demonstrating the significance of these dependencies on AMF.
</p>
