<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objective</title>
  <p class="p"> The aim of this review is to analyze preclinical and clinical studies investigating the anxiety effects of
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> or
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> essential oils (EOs).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title"> Design</title>
  <p class="p"> The bibliographic research was made on the major scientific databases. Analysis included only articles written in English and published on peer-reviewed scientific journals describing preclinical experiments and clinical trials carried out to investigate the antianxiety effects of
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium or Citrus sinensis</italic> EOs on anxiety disorders. Clinical studies reporting the antianxiety effects of products containing
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium </italic>or
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis </italic>EOs in combination with other active substances, including medicinal plants, were excluded. Nine clinical studies fulfilled the criteria adopted for analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title"> Results</title>
  <p class="p"> Data show that
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> or
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis </italic>EOs produce anxiolytic effects both in preclinical experiments and in different clinical conditions.
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> EO aromatherapy reduced anxiety level in the great part of stress conditions studied (subjects affected by chronic myeloid leukemia and preoperative patients) except for a sample of patients subjected to colonoscopy. Exposition to
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> EO in clinical studies shows to be positive in reducing anxiety level in patients waiting for dental treatment as well as in healthy volunteers submitted to an anxiogenic situation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title"> Conclusions</title>
  <p class="p"> Overview of clinical trials conducted with
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> or
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> on people with anxiety showed that inhalation or oral administration of
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus aurantium</italic> and inhalation of
   <italic class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</italic> can exert beneficial effects on anxiety; however, because of incomplete accuracy in the reporting of methodology, further more complete clinical studies are warranted.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
