<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned before, EOs can be extracted and obtained from various parts of plants. Clove’s EO derived from the 
 <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> tree’s aromatic flower buds with origin from Maluku, Indonesia contains the powerful scent used in spiced foods [
 <xref rid="B154-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. 
 <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic> oil is mint-like, with properties such as a decongestant, pain relievers, antimicrobial agent, immunostimulant, flu and cold/cough treatment, as well as for mental clarity in aromatherapy [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. One of the most influential EO is from 
 <italic>Lavandula angustifolia,</italic> which is also known as English lavender. Lavender oil possesses strong antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, and antimicrobial properties, and can be used to treat various skin diseases (e.g., eczema, ringworm, acne), improve digestive system, minimise sore muscle swelling, and additionally, alleviate pain [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. 
 <italic>Citrus limon</italic> EOs are used as antimicrobial and antifungal agents, pain relievers, aids in weight loss, and to reduce extreme nausea as well as for usage as soaps, hair shampoo, furniture polishes, and fresheners [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. Oregano (
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic>) EOs are often used for skin care, menstrual problems, stomach problems, and to control flu and cold infections [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. Rosemary’s EO originates from the 
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> evergreen shrub with characteristics of a crisp woody, herbal and balsamic odour, similar to camphor. The usage of rosemary oil ranges from various treatments of skin care, dandruff, and scalp health, as well as to cold prevention and boosting the immune system [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. EO from 
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> is called peppermint oil, which is mainly used in the prevention of flu and colds, reduces headache symptoms, and also in relieving muscle and joint pains [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-26-01107" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>].
</p>
