<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">Plants could serve as a reservoir of potential drugs and therapeutic molecules, and an integrated approach is required to identify and characterize those molecules. Proteomic and metabolomic profiling using high-throughput platforms are a boon for large-scale analysis of plant extracts to identify the biomolecular composition of those extracts. A comprehensive review of literature that exists in use within the community or population can help to identify the potential plants that can be targeted for metabolic screening. Predominantly, metabolites possess therapeutic properties than the simple protein molecules which are reported to be involved in cellular and biological processes of plants. Sampling of plants at different stages of development, preparation of tissue-specific extracts (using different solvents), and analysis of those extracts using Gas and/or Liquid Chromatography-Mass spectrometry can identify metabolites and other volatile compounds present in the extract. High-Performance Thin-Layer Chromatography can assist in fingerprinting of secondary metabolites and separating those metabolites at high-resolution. Computational tools coupled with these platforms, aid in the identification of the metabolites, whose chemical structure can be resolved at high-resolution using several available 
 <italic>in silico</italic> approaches. For screening the efficacy of these biomolecules and studying the potent inhibitors against coronavirus, computer-aided drug design (CADD) serves as a reliable approach [
 <xref rid="bb0480" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0535" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>] as it facilitates a multidimensional study of molecular interactions between putative anti-COVID-19 compounds and target proteins. This approach has suggested the interaction of SARS-CoV-2 encoded proteins with different phytochemicals. 3C-like protease (3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>), also known as Main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>) is an attractive target for anti-CoV drug design. It is a cysteine protease and is responsible for cleaving the replicase polypeptide into various functional proteins and essential for virus multiplication. Phenolic compounds such as coumarin, flavones [
 <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], baicalin, cyanidin 3-glucoside, and α-ketoamide-11r [
 <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] have structural similarity with the protease and might be the potential and safer inhibitors against the SARS-CoV-2. Apart from this, the Moroccan Medicinal plants containing Crocin, Digitoxigenin, and β-Eudesmol were projected as COVID-19 inhibitors based on the computational investigation with a benefit of oral intake [
 <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Phytochemicals such as Belachinal, Macaflavanone E, and Vibsanol B have been found to restrict the formation of ion channels by oligomerization of ‘SARS-CoV2 E', thus inhibiting the virus pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].
</p>
