<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17" class="p">Methane (biogas) production is another option when producing biofuels from straw. Biogas production by anaerobic digestion has better energy efficiency, greenhouse gas emissions and biomass conversion than ethanol production (Börjesson and Mattiasson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2008</xref>). Anaerobic digestion includes four process steps: hydrolysis of biopolymers, acidogenesis, acetogenesis and methanogenesis. During hydrolysis, carbohydrates (including celluloses and hemicelluloses from lignocellulose material), lipids and proteins are degraded into their monomers, for instance monosaccharides, amino acids and short-chain fatty acids. In acidogenesis, these compounds are further converted to organic acids (volatile fatty acids, VFAs). As side products, ammonia, carbon dioxide and other compounds are produced. In acetogenesis, VFAs are converted to acetic acid, CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and hydrogen. In methanogenesis, acetate and hydrogen are converted to methane and CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. While bacterial consortia drive the first three steps, methanogenesis is performed by archea (Schnürer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">2016</xref>). Since hydrolytic bacteria form part of the microbial consortium during anaerobic digestion, a pretreatment of lignocellulosic biomass is not essential for biogas production. However, due to the complexity and recalcitrance of lignocellulose, the hydrolysis step is frequently the limiting factor for methane production from lignocellulose. Therefore, a variety of physical, thermochemical or biotreatments of lignocellulose has been investigated. In principle, the same pretreatments can be used as for bioethanol production. However, losses of hemicellulose should be avoided and fermentation inhibitors may also negatively affect biogas processes. The use of sulphuric acid during pretreatment should be kept to a minimum, since sulphate-reducing bacteria may outcompete methanogens. Biopretreatments by white-rot fungi have frequently been tested, to decrease lignin content and increase availability of polysaccharides for the hydrolysis steps. Biotreatment generates less inhibitors and requires less energy than thermochemical methods; however, it is time consuming and the fungi may degrade some organic material resulting in lowered methane yields. In general, pretreatment can have positive or negative impacts on the final biogas production, and optimisation for the specific material and biogas process is required (Carrere et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2016</xref>; Rouches et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">2016</xref>). There have also been attempts to combine storage of corn stover and pretreatment (Cui et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2012</xref>), similar to experiments with bioethanol production from wheat straw (Passoth et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2013</xref>). When ethanol was produced from oat straw and biogas from the residue of ethanol production, biogas production rate was considerably enhanced and the total energy output was higher than in either bioethanol or biogas production alone. This indicated that ethanol production from the initial material can serve as a pretreatment for enhanced conversion of the remainder to biogas (Dererie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2011</xref>). In general, ethanol production should be connected with valorisation of residues, for instance biogas production, to obtain an energy output similar to biogas production (Lantz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">2018</xref>).
</p>
