<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="section12-2515690X17751314" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study showed that prevalence of 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> in shrimp and fresh fish samples taken in the Kashan region, was low (0.94%). Previous studies in other areas in Iran have been demonstrated as follows; 7.8% of open-air fish market samples in Mazandaran,
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr8-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr8-2515690X17751314">8</a>
  </span> 0% and 1.9% of fresh fish, frozen fish, and shrimp samples in Isfahan and Shahrekord, respectively.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr10-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr10-2515690X17751314">10</a>,
   <a rid="bibr20-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr20-2515690X17751314">20</a>
  </span> Also, our findings are similar to Momtaz and Yadollahi
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr27-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr27-2515690X17751314">27</a>
  </span> who revealed 2.5% (1 sample) 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> contamination in fresh shrimp in Iran. Zarei et al
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr28-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr28-2515690X17751314">28</a>
  </span> reported the low prevalence of 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> in Iranian seafood samples (1.4%). Latorre et al
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr29-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr29-2515690X17751314">29</a>
  </span> reported that 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> was not found in 154 samples of fresh seafood products in Italy.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this work indicate resistance of 
  <span class="italic">Listeria</span> spp to antibiotics (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="table1-2515690X17751314" href="#table1-2515690X17751314">Table 1</a>). 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> was resistant to ampicillin and penicillin as the first-choice antibiotics used for treatment of human listeriosis. Erythromycin and trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole are generally used for treatment of listeriosis in pregnant women and patients having allergy to penicillin, respectively. In this study, 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> was susceptible to trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole that is in agreement with the previous reports.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr30-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr30-2515690X17751314">30</a>,
   <a rid="bibr31-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr31-2515690X17751314">31</a>
  </span> In addition, 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> was resistant to vancomycin as one of the last therapeutic options for the treatment of human listeriosis.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr32-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr32-2515690X17751314">32</a>
  </span> Lakhanpal et al
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr33-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr33-2515690X17751314">33</a>
  </span> showed that 3 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> isolated from milk products were sensitive to ampicillin, gentamicin, vancomycin, and erythromycin. However, the isolates were resistant to nalidixic acid and ciprofloxacin. Rahimi et al
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr34-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr34-2515690X17751314">34</a>
  </span> showed that 3 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> isolated from smoked and salted fish samples were resistant to nalidixic acid, penicillin, and tetracycline. Also, the isolates were sensitive to ciprofloxacin, vancomycin, gentamycin, and chloramphenicol.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently, due to the increasing problem of bacterial resistance, extracts and essential oils are regarded as good candidates for replacing chemical antimicrobial agents. Previous works have demonstrated the antioxidant activity and antibacterial properties of essential oils and extracts.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr2-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr2-2515690X17751314">2</a>,
   <a rid="bibr23-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr23-2515690X17751314">23</a>,
   <a rid="bibr25-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr25-2515690X17751314">25</a>,
   <a rid="bibr26-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr26-2515690X17751314">26</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results showed that 
  <span class="italic">B persicum</span>, 
  <span class="italic">E globulus</span>, and rose water had antioxidant activities (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-2515690X17751314" href="#fig1-2515690X17751314">Figure 1</a>), which was supported by previous studies.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr35-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr35-2515690X17751314">35</a>
   <a href="#bibr36-2515690X17751314">*</a>–
   <a rid="bibr37-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr37-2515690X17751314">37</a>
  </span> Rose water is called “Golab” in Iran. It has been used to prepare drinks and as a traditional medicine for several centuries in Iran.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr35-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr35-2515690X17751314">35</a>
  </span> Ganesan et al
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr38-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr38-2515690X17751314">38</a>
  </span> reported that the phenolic compounds isolated from 
  <span class="italic">E globulus</span> demonstrated antioxidant activity and antioxidative property against glucose- and oxalate-induced oxidative stress in NRK-49F cells. El-Sayed et al
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr39-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr39-2515690X17751314">39</a>
  </span> demonstrated that the Taif rose water byproduct had free radical scavenging activity toward artificial 1,1-diphenyl picrylhydrazyl radical with SC
  <sub>50</sub> = 23.72 ± 0.36 µg/mL. The results in this work indicate that these plants could be a potential sources of natural antioxidant foods.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 4 essential oils and extracts inhibited the growth of 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L grayi</span>. In the present work, 2 essential oils studied had a lower MIC and MBC when used against the Gram-positive 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L grayi</span>. Our results are in agreement with the previous studies.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr40-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr40-2515690X17751314">40</a>,
   <a rid="bibr41-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr41-2515690X17751314">41</a>
  </span> Patra and Beak
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr41-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr41-2515690X17751314">41</a>
  </span> have reported the 
  <span class="italic">Enteromorpha linza</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Undaria pinnatifida</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Laminaria japonica</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Porphyra tenera</span> essential oils exhibited strong antilisterial activity against multiple strains of 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span>. A previous study has demonstrated antibacterial activity of cumin and eucalyptus essential oils against 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Salmonella typhi</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus pyogenes</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Shigella dysenteriae</span>. 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> has the same sensitivity to cumin and eucalyptus essential oils. The MIC and MBC values were 5.625 and 11.25 mg/mL, respectively.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr42-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr42-2515690X17751314">42</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The difference antimicrobial properties of extracts and essential oils against 
  <span class="italic">Listeria</span> spp may be linked to inoculation amount of bacteria, incubation time as experimental conditions, and the sources of extracts and essential oils and their chemical composition.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr40-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr40-2515690X17751314">40</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this study showed, increase in the optical density values at 260 nm of 
  <span class="italic">L monocytogenes</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L grayi</span> treated with 
  <span class="italic">B persicum</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E globulus</span> essential oils over time, which can result in changes of cell membrane structure. Also, the cellular leakage can result from the effect of penetration of the hydrophobic essential oils. Therefore, some reducing sugars, K
  <span class="sup">+</span>, Ca
  <span class="sup">2+</span>, and Na
  <span class="sup">+</span> as small molecules or macromolecules, including proteins and nucleic acids released from the bacteria to the outside. Thus, we concluded that one of the modes of antibacterial action on 
  <span class="italic">Listeria</span> spp was that the essential oils from 
  <span class="italic">B persicum</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E globulus</span> first destroyed the cell membranes, next causing the leakage of cytosolic materials, which finally resulted in the cell death.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar observations regarding the release of cytosolic materials outside of bacterial cells treated with essential oils from 
  <span class="italic">Enteromorpha linza</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Undaria pinnatifida</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Laminaria japonica</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Porphyra tenera</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Laurus nobilis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Mentha pulegium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Satureja calamintha</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula stoechas</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Myrtus communis</span> and other essential oils have been reported.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="bibr26-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr26-2515690X17751314">26</a>,
   <a rid="bibr40-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr40-2515690X17751314">40</a>,
   <a rid="bibr41-2515690X17751314" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr41-2515690X17751314">41</a>
  </span>
 </p>
</sec>
