<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0070">Phenolic compounds and tannins are known to possess anti-inflammatory, anti-oxidant, anti-microbial, insecticidal, anti-diabetic [
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], wound healing, anti-diuretic, anti-parasitic, cytotoxic and anti-neoplastic activities [
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Flavonoids show anti-allergic, anti-inflammatory, anti-microbial and anticancer activity [
 <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Steroids and saponins are the sub- groups of triterpenoids. Saponins possess antimicrobial and anti- inflammatory activity [
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The results of the present study also confirm the presence of phenolics, tannin, flavonoids, sterols and triterpenoids with varied amount in the studied extracts of 
 <italic>T. paradoxa</italic>. The existence of these metabolites may be responsible for the observed biological activities. 
 <italic>T. paradoxa</italic> extracts showed anti-diabetic, anti-inflammatory and cytotoxic activities with varied frequencies. The varied frequency activities may be due to the variation in metabolites contents. The concentrations and frequency of activities are directly correlated. Brine Shrimp Lethality Bioassay (BSLB) has been successfully employed as a simple biological tool to identify the antitumour compounds / fractions / crude extracts of plants [
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The BSL bioassay has good correlation with the human solid tumour cell lines [
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The studied extracts of 
 <italic>T. paradoxa</italic> can be considered as a promising candidate for a plant-derived anti-tumour compound. LC
 <sub>50</sub> values &lt; 1000 ppm are considered significant for crude extracts [
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The cytotoxicity of the 
 <italic>T. paradoxa</italic> were displayed less than LC
 <sub>50</sub> values &lt; 1000 ppm viz., chloroform (LC
 <sub>50</sub> = 25.52 μg/mL) &gt; petroleum ether (LC
 <sub>50</sub> = 36.99 μg/mL) &gt; methanol (LC
 <sub>50</sub> = 44.26 μg/mL) &gt; acetone (LC
 <sub>50</sub> = 55.9 μg/mL). The crude extracts of plants with LC50 values &lt;1000 μg/ml using BSLB are recognized to hold various physiologically active principles [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The existence of phytoconstitutents viz., alkaloids, phenolics and terpenoids in plant extracts has been associated with anticancer and cytotoxic activity [
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>]. The results of the present study suggested that 
 <italic>T. paradaxa</italic> extracts treatment against 
 <italic>Artemia salina</italic> induced a dose dependent lethal effect. The 
 <italic>T. paradaxa</italic> extracts treated 
 <italic>Artemia salina</italic> showed the morphological changes, which disrupted and affected the swimming ability, feeding, intestinal enlargement, deformation and loss of antennae in 
 <italic>A. salina.</italic> The 
 <italic>A. salina</italic> cultured in the control failed to show the morphological change. The exposure of 
 <italic>T. paradaxa</italic> extracts may generate the reactive oxygen species (ROS) that may cause cytotoxicity. Similar kind of observations was observed in the aqueous and silver nanoparticles of 
 <italic>O. chinensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Johnson et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and Nirmali et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] employed 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> alpha amylase inhibitory activity to predict the antidiabetic potential of 
 <italic>Sphaerostephanos unitus</italic>, 
 <italic>Odontosoria chinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>Adenanthera pavonina</italic> extracts respectively. In the present study also 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> alpha amylase inhibitory activity was adopted and identified the antidiabetic potetnials of 
 <italic>T. paradoxa.</italic> The anti-inflammatory activity of 
 <italic>Sphaerostephanos unitus</italic>, 
 <italic>Odontosoria chinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>Gardenia coronaria</italic> leaves extracts was assessed by 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> HRBC membrane stabilization method [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Johnson et al. [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] employed the 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> alpha-amylase inhibitory assay and Brine Shrimp lethality bioassay to determine the toxicity and anti-diabetic properties of 
 <italic>Sphaerostephanos unitus</italic> and 
 <italic>Odontosoria chinensis</italic>. In the present study also 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> HRBC membrane stabilization against heat induced haemolysis method and 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> alpha-amylase inhibitory assay and Brine Shrimp lethality bioassay are employed and determined the toxicity, anti-diabetic and anti-inflammatory properties of 
 <italic>T. paradoxa.</italic> The results of the present study identified the pool of medicinal properties existence in 
 <italic>T. paradoxa</italic>. Further studies on the isolation of active principles may bring out an alternative source for anti-inflammatory and anti-cancer drugs from 
 <italic>Tectaria paradoxa</italic>.
</p>
