<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="app1-insects-12-00404">
  <title>Appendix A</title>
 </app>
 <app id="app2-insects-12-00404">
  <title>Appendix B</title>
 </app>
 <app id="app3-insects-12-00404">
  <title>Appendix C</title>
 </app>
 <app id="app4-insects-12-00404">
  <title>Appendix D. Path-Analysis Setting Details and Discussion</title>
  <p>In the literature, as a rule of thumb, if the delta between two values of AIC values is greater than 2, the model with the lower AIC shows a significant improvement in parsimony [
   <xref rid="B77-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Here, for our path analyses, when several models were discriminated with a delta AICc &lt; 2, we systematically chose the models with the lowest AICc. 
  </p>
  <sec id="secDdot1-insects-12-00404">
   <title>Appendix D.1. Impact of Landscape Composition and Configuration on Flower-Visiting Insects </title>
   <p>Preliminary model selection led to three equivalent models to explain the abundance of flying insects (
    <xref rid="insects-12-00404-t0A3" ref-type="table">Table A3</xref>). According to these models, the insect abundance is positively influenced by the landscape configuration (higher IJI index), and the percentage of SNH (
    <xref rid="insects-12-00404-t0A3" ref-type="table">Table A3</xref>). The abundance is, however, negatively influenced by the increased distance to SNH. 
   </p>
   <p>We selected the model with the lowest AIC to set the path-analysis, i.e., the model which explained abundance according to the IJI index. We added the missing path explaining the insect abundance by the insect family richness to the selected model.</p>
   <p>Preliminary model selection also led to three equivalent models to explain the family richness of flying insects (
    <xref rid="insects-12-00404-t0A4" ref-type="table">Table A4</xref>). According to these models, the family richness was positively influenced by an increase in the IJI index and the percentage of SNH (
    <xref rid="insects-12-00404-t0A4" ref-type="table">Table A4</xref>). The family richness was, however, negatively affected by the distance to the closest woody SNH (
    <xref rid="insects-12-00404-t0A4" ref-type="table">Table A4</xref>). We selected the model with the lowest AIC to set the path-analysis, i.e., the model which explained richness according to the IJI index, and the distance from each sample site to the closest SNH. There was no missing path to add to this selected model.
   </p>
   <p>In models 2 and 3 (higher AICc but without a delta AICc &gt; 2), parcel size and pesticide use seemed to have no effect on insect abundance and a positive effect on insect family richness. Sihag ([
    <xref rid="B66-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]) already showed the positive synergistic effect of insect pollination and use of pesticides on seed yield. It has been shown that different pesticides could have different effects on different organisms [
    <xref rid="B78-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. The increase in parcel size could also have a positive effect on insect abundance [
    <xref rid="B79-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] and richness as it increases the floral display of mass-flowering crops and, thus, floral resource availability [
    <xref rid="B80-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], leading to an increase in foraging efficiency [
    <xref rid="B81-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] and decrease in foraging energetic cost [
    <xref rid="B82-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. As our studied crops were managed with sustainable managing practices (sustainable agriculture), we cannot exclude that the amount of pesticide used might be below a threshold that affects insect communities.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="secDdot2-insects-12-00404">
   <title>Appendix D.2. Insect Impact on Fennel Yield</title>
   <p>Only one model was selected to explain the fennel essential oil yield quantity (
    <xref rid="insects-12-00404-t0A5" ref-type="table">Table A5</xref>). According to this selected model, richness but not abundance positively influences fennel essential oil yield (
    <xref rid="insects-12-00404-t0A5" ref-type="table">Table A5</xref>). 
   </p>
  </sec>
 </app>
</app-group>
