<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Feng et al. used castor oil as basis to synthesize another novel flame-retardant plasticizer based on castor oil (FRC), as shown in 
 <xref rid="polymers-10-01303-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>a. They prepared FRC by a three-step procedure of alcoholysis, epoxidation and ring opening reaction and used molding machine to obtain the blends of PVC and FRC [
 <xref rid="B70-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. The addition of FRC reduces torque by 33.6% and enhances the flame-retardant properties. LOI js enhanced by 31.9%. The addition of FRC causes a significant decrease of 61.94% in tensile strength and approximately 60% in elongation at break for PVC materials, which indicates that FRC has plasticizing effect on PVC. Our group synthesized a series of flame-retardant plasticizers based on vegetable oil [
 <xref rid="B71-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. A flame-retardant plasticizer based on castor oil (PPC) is synthesized by castor oil, H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, phosphate and diethyl phosphate [
 <xref rid="B71-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-10-01303-f012" class="xref">Figure 12</xref> and 
 <xref rid="polymers-10-01303-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>b show its chemical structure and synthesis route. The results show that the glass transition temperature increases from 26.5 to 52.6 °C with the content of PPC in 0 to 20 g in 100 g of PVC while the thermal stability is maintained by PPC until 350 °C. In addition, the leaching test indicates that solvent extraction resistance of PPC is better than DOP.
</p>
