<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The aqueous ethanolic extract from the fresh stems of 
 <italic class="italic">OD</italic> has potent radical scavenging activity. In this study, three new compounds isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">OD</italic> called 
 <italic class="italic">opuntioside</italic> I, 4-ethoxyl-6-hydroxymethyl-alpha-pyrone and kaempferol 7-O-beta-D-glucopyranosyl-(1→4)-beta-D-glucopyranoside, were evaluated based on the chemical and physicochemical evidence. The radical scavenging effects of principal compounds were examined too [
 <xref rid="b56-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Li H 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., evaluated the antioxidant effect of polysaccharides isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">OD</italic> using DPPH test, hydroxyl radicals and superoxide radical in vitro. Their study showed these acidic polysaccharides demonstrated good antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="b57-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. A purification and fractionation of OD extract isolated several 
 <italic class="italic">betalains</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">polyphenol</italic>. This process followed by betalainic and phenolic characterization revealed that this plant was a valuable source of bioactive compounds, with a high amount of total betacyanins (16.63 mg beta-nin/100 g fresh fruit) and betaxanthins (7.55 mg indicaxanthin/100 g fresh fruit) with elevated antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="b31-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. The antioxidant activities in extracts obtained from four cacti (
 <italic class="italic">Opuntia</italic> species) fruit varieties were investigated. Quercetin, kaempferol, isorhamnetin, ascorbic acid and carotenoids were achieved from these extracts. The varieties with red-skin fruits contained the most ascorbic acid (815 μg/g fruits weight) and the yellow-skinned fruits (
 <italic class="italic">Opuntia stricta var. stricta</italic>) had the most carotenoids (23.7 μg/g fw). This study also reported the fact that, the antioxidant capacity of cactus fruits can be related to their flavonoid, ascorbic acid and carotenoid contents. The data exhibited that cactus fruits are a precious source of natural antioxidants [
 <xref rid="b58-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Chang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. evaluated the methanolic extract from betacyanin-free seeds of 
 <italic class="italic">OD</italic> for antioxidant activity. The results showed in three assay systems a higher antioxidant capacity for betacyanin-free seeds of 
 <italic class="italic">OD</italic> than extracts from peel and pulp with betacyanins. The pulp contains more ascorbic acids than peel and seeds did not contain this valuable vitamin. The extracts obtained from the former have the greater antioxidant capacity than the latter because of a higher amount of total phenolic compounds (133.4 versus 91.5 mg/100 g fresh weight) [
 <xref rid="b43-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Antioxidant activity of this plant in aqueous extractions against lipid peroxidation is also reported [
 <xref rid="b59-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Betanin and isobetanin are two compounds with high amounts of 
 <italic class="italic">OD</italic> fruit. It was indicated that these two compounds were considered great free radical scavengers and valuable antioxidant constituted in certain pH levels [
 <xref rid="b60-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. It is also suggested that these compounds may be considered as potentially effective bio-molecules for improving human health and preventing disease states [
 <xref rid="b61-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b62-2093-6966-v22-n03-016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>].
</p>
