<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par79">The reception of western medicine was different in Japan, where through Dutch medicinal knowledge a separate medicinal school evolved, “Rangaku” 蘭學 (Dutch medicinal learning). Generally speaking, we can observe that Japanese scholars were more open towards new knowledge and practices from Europeans. The world map of Matteo Ricci, 
 <italic>Kunyu Wanguo quantu</italic> 坤輿萬國全, had a great impact on local scholars, after it became known in Japan. In 1708, Arai Hakuseki 新井白石 (1657–1725), a well-known Neo-Confucian scholar, official and writer in the Japan of that time, produced a painted, coloured version of the map 
 <italic>Kunyu Wanguo quantu</italic>. He also copied Ricci’s entry on balsam 巴尔娑摩, in his map written as 巴尔婆摩. In 1713, he wrote a three-volume treatise on the Occident entitled 
 <italic>Keiyō kibun</italic> 西洋紀聞 (Chronicle of the West), a work that was mainly based on his conversations with the Italian missionary Giovanni Battista Sidotti (1668–1714). The second volume is a description of the five continents, that is, Africa, Asia, Australia, Europe and the Americas. There, Hakuseki translates the information from Ricci’s map into Japanese, and explains that in Spanish America there is a country called Perukoku 孛露國, where a fragrance is produced called 巴尔娑摩. The tree, when cut with a knife, produces an oil which is used to embalm dead corpses so that they do not decompose. The balsam (バルサモ) that comes from the western countries (i.e. that is traded by the Europeans) is exactly the oil of this tree. I asked some Dutch people about the location of this product and they replied it was Peru. In Chinese, this is translated into Polu 孛露. 
 <italic>Ba’ershamo</italic> 巴尔娑摩, this is balsam (バルサモ) (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]. In his 
 <italic>Sairan igen</italic> 采覽異言 (Strange Stories Acquired), he almost literally copies from Ricci, because, in contrast to his explanations in 
 <italic>Keiyō kibun</italic>, he uses mainly Kanji 漢字. Interestingly, he also adds geographical information, stating that Peru lies in the north of Chile, lying adjacent to a large ocean in the west. And he introduces emus, large birds that cannot fly and have feet resembling horses (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a, b</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. 
</p>
