<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, remote sensing techniques have been used in various natural environments with the goal of reducing the need for in situ measurements [
 <xref rid="B23-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Low-cost data gathering, time saving, and larger study areas are the benefits. Furthermore, data can be directly used and processed within Geographical Information Systems (GIS) [
 <xref rid="B23-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. This has been done successfully, for environmental studies [
 <xref rid="B24-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Closely related to the current work, Reference [
 <xref rid="B27-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] proposed using GIS as a synthesising tool in invasive species management approaches. Reference [
 <xref rid="B28-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] used satellite images of 1992 and 2002 in order to identify stress indicators and change detection in a wetland in Sri Lanka to quantify the conditions of the complex. The authors state that the inventory, mapping, and monitoring are needed to understand interactions in the ecosystem. Classification with the Maximum Likelihood Algorithm were performed, mapping and spatial analysis were used, and finally refined and verified with ground data. Their approach ([
 <xref rid="B28-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]) reached 86% accuracy and provided detailed analysis. GIS in combination with remote sensing data was found to be an effective methodology for investigating wetlands. Reference [
 <xref rid="B29-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] evaluated vegetation change detection while using the NDVI of remote sensing data and applied GIS in order to visualise the results. Landsat and Shuttle Radar Topography Missions were used to capture the Vellore District. Image interpretations were carried out using ERGDAS IMAGINE software in order to classify and detect changes in the vegetation. The differences in the NDVI values were used to analyse data sets of the years 2001 to 2006. The study provided information about the lowest decrease in the forest area by 6%, while agriculture land increased the most by 19%.
</p>
