<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It has been reported that Rac1 and Rac2 are critical GTPases for osteoclast formation and maturation. In fact, Rac1 and Rac2, are intimately associated with the organization of the different types of cellular cytoskeleton, such as: osteoclasts, DCs and macrophages. Notably, these two isoforms are also involved in the osteoclastic adhesive function formation and subsequent bone resorption [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, the specific role of Rac1 and Rac2 in osteoclastogenesis is still unknown. For example, osteoclasts contain NADPH diaphorase activity [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and free radicals which both could influence bone resorption, however, Rac1 and Rac2 are also essential components of NADPH oxidase [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15–18</xref>], the enzyme responsible for generating free radicals. Besides that, a study has also demonstrated that Rac1 and Rac2 could regulate the generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and actin remodeling participating in the osteoclastogenesis regulation. Recent study has found that both Rac1 and Rac2 are required for normal RANKL-induced osteoclast differentiation, but Rac1 deletion results in a more profound reduction in osteoclast formation 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> because of its regulatory role in pre‐osteoclast M‐CSF mediated chemotaxis and actin assembly and RANKL‐mediated ROS generation [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. These results speculated that Rac1 and Rac2 might function in osteoclastic organelle actin dynamics regulating, such as: actin filament ends and podosomes. In fact, Rac1 and Rac2 proteins have overlapping roles in podosome assembly and SZL formation by localizing Arp2/3 at podosome sites during osteoclastogenesis [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21–27</xref>]. Osteoclasts generated from the Rac1 and Rac2 double knockout mouse are devoid of podosomes and SZ, which finally showed impaired bone resorption capacities [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28–32</xref>]. Notably, however, these defects are observed only if Rac1 and Rac2 deletion occurs at the early osteoclast precursor stage, which means the Rac1- and Rac2-deficient osteoclasts lack the capabilities of actin cytoskeletal formation.
</p>
