<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">Comprehensive research on the relationship between different ecological environment factors and the quality of CMMs has also been recorded. For example, in 
 <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> Georgi, most of the chemical constituents were negatively correlated with latitude and positively correlated with temperature. Generally, the contents of 21 chemical constituents were higher at low latitudes than at high latitudes. By gradual regression analysis, it was found that the content of baicalin in 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> was negatively correlated with latitude. Similarly, the content of inorganic elements in soil was excessively high (magnesium (Mg) and calcium (Ca) excluded), which had a negative effect on the accumulation of chemical constituents in 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Taking the well-known antioxidant herb 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> C. A. Mey. as another example, low temperature was a favorable factor for the accumulation of ginsenosides, as a negative correlation was found between temperature and ginsenoside contents within a certain temperature range, while the levels of soil available B, effective Fe and available N were positively correlated to ginsenoside contents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In recent years, due to overexploitation, the destruction of the ecological environment and the lack of proper cultivation practices, the geographical distributions of most DMMs may undergo large changes. For example, although the Changzhi region of Shanxi province and provinces of north-east China was 
 <italic>P. ginseng</italic>’s original production center, the present production center of it is in Xiaoxinganling region (in Heilongjiang province) and Changbaishan region (in Jilin province) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Similarly, 
 <italic>Panax notoginseng</italic> (Burk.) F. H. Chen historically came from the Tianzhou region (in Guangxi province), but now the dominant medicinal material comes from Wenshan region (in Yunnan province) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. In these cases, predicting the geographical distribution of CMMs is important for resource conservation and regional management. Therefore, a geographic information system based on a computer program (TCMGIS) was developed to predict the distribution of CMMs. By integrating geographic location, climate and soil type databases, TCMGIS was able to determine the impacts of environmental components and predict the large-scale distribution of target medicinal herbs such as 
 <italic>P. cablin</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], 
 <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> L. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], 
 <italic>Polygonum multiflorum</italic> Thunb. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], 
 <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic> How [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], 
 <italic>Aquilaria sinensis</italic> (Lour.) Gilg [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], 
 <italic>Rheum tanguticum</italic> Maxim. ex Balf. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], 
 <italic>Amomum villosum</italic> Lour. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], etc.
</p>
