<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diarrhea is a common gastrointestinal disorder characterized by an increase in the frequency, volume, and fluidity of bowel movement or a decrease in the form of stool (greater looseness of stool) for at least three times a day.
 <xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Diarrhea is the second cause of death next to respiratory infections among under-five years of age children throughout the world.
 <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Diarrhea alone as a gastrointestinal disease causes 5–8 million deaths annually
 <xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> and kills 2195 children every 24 hours more than malaria, measles, and AIDS combined.
 <xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Africa and South East Asia regions account for 78% of all diarrheal deaths occurring among under-five children in the developing world.
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Furthermore, in Ethiopia, diarrhea kills half a million under-five children annually next to pneumonia.
 <xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Even though the availability of many drugs for treating diarrhea, the majority of them suffer from adverse effects like intestinal obstruction, the induction of bronchospasm, vomiting, constipation, and unwanted central effects by long-term use of opioids.
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> Additionally, there is a growing warning of drug resistance and superinfection causing a global warning to the currently available anti-infective agents including antidiarrheal.
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Although globally herbal medicines account for 80%
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> of the healthcare needs of the majority of developing countries including Ethiopia due to accessibility, affordability, and strong cultural belief,
 <xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> traditional medications are passed orally through generations, and the effective doses suggested by the traditional practitioner are not fully known nor is the effectiveness and safety profile also not described.
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Due to the above-mentioned features, WHO inspire studies for the treatment and prevention of diarrheal diseases depending on traditional medical practices.
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> A range of medicinal plants such as the bark extract of 
 <italic>Albizia gummifera</italic>, leaf extract of 
 <italic>Calpurnia aurea</italic>, seed extract of 
 <italic>Coffea Arabica</italic>, root extract of 
 <italic>Ensete ventricosum, leaves of V. amygydalina</italic> and 
 <italic>Caylusea abyssinica</italic> have been widely used for the management of diarrhea by traditional healers in Ethiopia.
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 <italic>V. amygydalina</italic> is native, to Congo, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Kenya, Nigeria, Sudan, Tanzania, Uganda, Yemen is used for the treatment of several human health problems. Leaf decoctions and bark infusions are used to treat fever, cough, malaria, diarrhea, hepatitis, sexually transmitted diseases and as a fertility inducer. Furthermore, leaves are pounded and mixed with warm water for bathing to treat spots on the skin and nausea.
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> In Nigeria, alcoholic extracts of 
 <italic>V. amygdalina</italic> were evaluated stem bark was effective against diarrhea in rat model.
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> In Ethiopia, traditionally, the study revealed that orally administered 
 <italic>V. amygdalina</italic> leaves powder mixed with water has been used for diarrhea treatment in Wonago Woreda and Halaba people, Southern Nations, Nationalities and people of Ethiopia and in Nekemte town, in East Wellega orally.
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16–18</xref> Hence, the aim of this study was therefore to further confirm the antidiarrheal activities of 80% methanol extract of the leaves of 
 <italic>Vernonia amygdalina</italic> using mice models of diarrhea.
</p>
