<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Marineli et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] aimed to assess the effect of consumed chia seeds on selected carbohydrate metabolism indexes. They showed that rats consuming high-fat and high-fructose diet, in which soybean oil was replaced with a 13.3% addition of chia seeds (w/w), were characterised by greater tolerance of both glucose and insulin in comparison to the control. This effect was observed during both short-term (six-week) and long-term (12-week) dietary interventions. In that study, a reduced blood concentration of non-esterified fatty acids (NEFA) is reported for the group of animals consuming chia seeds. Moreover, they recorded a decrease in the levels of hepatocellular damage markers, i.e., alanine transaminase (ALT) and aspartate transaminase (AST), the high concentrations of which were caused by the high-fat and high-fructose diet [
 <xref rid="B44-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. The effect of chia seeds consumption on carbohydrate and lipid metabolism was also investigated by Silva et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. In their experiment Wistar rats were divided into six groups: (1) fed casein as a source of protein; (2) fed a protein-free diet; and (3–6) receiving chia seeds or chia seed flour, with or without thermal processing. They found that the groups of animals receiving chia seeds and flour had lower blood concentrations of triglycerides (TG), total cholesterol (TC), low density lipoproteins (LDL) and very low density lipoproteins (VLDL) in comparison to the control, consuming casein. Furthermore, an increased concentration of high density lipoproteins (HDL) was recorded. They also confirmed the hypoglycaemic effect of chia. It was found that administration of chia seeds and flour reduced blood glucose level in comparison to the control [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Ho et al. [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] observed that individuals consuming bread fortified with chia seeds had lower postprandial glycemia in comparison to individuals, who consumed bread free from that additive. This effect was dose-dependent. The lowest level of glycemia was recorded at the addition of 24 g chia seeds, while it was highest at the addition of 7 g. Those authors suggested that the hypoglycaemic effect of chia seeds results from their high content of dietary fibre [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Studies conducted with type 2 diabetes patients showed that the daily supply of 15 g/1000 kcal chia seeds for 12 weeks caused a statistically significant reduction in the concentration of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein (hs-CRP) (by 40%) and von Willebrand factor (by 21%). Systolic blood pressure (SBP) was reduced by 6.3 mm Hg. No statistically significant differences were observed in blood glucose levels or parameters of the blood lipid profile (TC, LDL, HDL, and TG) [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-01242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. 
</p>
