<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent studies showed that the majority of plasma antioxidants are depleted in diabetic state [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Therefore, future treatment of type 2 diabetes and its complications may include hypoglycemic, anti-inflammatory, and antioxidant drugs [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Traditional medicine systems generally assume that synergy effects of all ingredients of the plants will bring about maximum therapeutic [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In Cameroon, particularly in the centre region (Mbalmayo), 
 <italic>Bridelia atroviridis Müll. Arg.</italic> (Euphorbiaceae) is used by local population to manage various ailments including diabetes, malaria, and venereal diseases. 
 <italic>B. atroviridis</italic> methanolic leaves and stem bark extracts possess antifungal activity, and the decoction from its bark is used as purgative, diuretic, and aphrodisiac remedy [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Although ethnobotanical surveys of certain medicinal plants used in Cameroon do not indicate the traditional use of 
 <italic>B. atroviridis</italic> on diabetes [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], some plants of the genus Bridelia have been cited as antidiabetic [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Meanwhile, the antidiabetic activity of 
 <italic>Bridellia ferruginea</italic> [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], 
 <italic>Bridelia micrantha</italic> [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], 
 <italic>Bridelia ndellensis</italic> Beille [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], 
 <italic>Bridellia grandis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], and 
 <italic>Bridellia retusa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] has been proven. It was also reported that barks of all 
 <italic>Bridellia</italic> Spp have similar medicinal uses in West Africa [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] motivating the investigation of the antidiabetic activity of 
 <italic>Bridelia</italic> hydroethanolic extract. Hereby, we investigated the possible bioactivities of 
 <italic>B. atroviridis</italic> hydroethanolic extract against some pathophysiological effects on nicotinamide-/streptozotocin-induced diabetes in rats.
</p>
