<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p> Infections by microbes (viruses, bacteria, and fungi) and parasites can cause serious diseases in both humans and animals. Heavy use of antimicrobials has created selective pressure and caused resistance to currently available antibiotics, hence the need for finding new and better antibiotics. Natural products, especially from plants, are known for their medicinal properties, including antimicrobial and anthelmintic activities. Geoclimatic variation, together with diversity in ethnomedicinal traditions, has made the Himalayas of Nepal an invaluable repository of traditional medicinal plants. We studied antiviral, antibacterial, antifungal, and anthelmintic activities of medicinal plants, selected based upon ethnobotanical evidence. </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p> Ethanolic and methanolic extracts were tested (1) on a panel of microbes: two Gram-positive bacteria (
   <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and 
   <italic>Listeria innocua</italic>), four Gram-negative bacteria (
   <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
   <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic>, and 
   <italic>Shigella sonnei</italic>), and one fungal species: 
   <italic>Candida albicans</italic>; (2) against three different viruses: yellow fever, chikungunya, and enterovirus; and (3) on the nematode 
   <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>. Also, cytotoxicity was assessed on human hepatoma (Huh), rhabdosarcoma (RD), and Vero (VC) cell lines. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p> Of 18 plants studied, 
   <italic>Ampelocissus tomentosa</italic> and 
   <italic>Aleuritopteris anceps</italic> inhibited 
   <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MIC 35 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL and 649 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL, respectively) and 
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (MIC 15 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL and 38 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL, respectively). 
   <italic>Rhododendron arboreum</italic> and 
   <italic>Adhatoda vasica</italic> inhibited 
   <italic>S. enterica</italic> (MIC 285 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL and 326 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL, respectively). 
   <italic>Kalanchoe pinnata, Ampelocissus tomentosa</italic>, and 
   <italic>Paris polyphylla</italic> were active against chikungunya virus, and 
   <italic>Clerodendrum serratum</italic> was active against yellow fever virus (EC
   <sub>50</sub> 15.9 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL); 
   <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> was active against enterovirus (EC
   <sub>50</sub> 10.6 
   <italic>μ</italic>g/mL). 
   <italic>Ampelocissus tomentosa, Boenninghausenia albiflora, Dichrocephala integrifolia</italic>, and 
   <italic>Kalanchoe pinnata</italic> significantly reduced 
   <italic>C. elegans</italic> motility, comparable to levamisole. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p> In countries like Nepal, with a high burden of infectious and parasitic diseases, and a current health system unable to combat the burden of diseases, evaluation of local plants as a treatment or potential source of drugs can help expand treatment options. Screening plants against a broad range of pathogens (bacteria, viruses, fungi, and parasites) will support bioprospecting in Nepal, which may eventually lead to new drug development.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
