<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Isolation and Identification of 
   <span class="italic">Prototheca zopfii</span> Strains
  </div>
  <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Prototheca zopfii</span> isolates were obtained from a range of milk samples taken from cows with mastitis in the Department of Animal and Environmental Hygiene, University of Life Sciences in Lublin. 
   <span class="italic">P. zopfii</span> strains were identified using standard microbiological methods: They were cultured in Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (bioMerieux, Poland), incubated for 48–72 h at 37 °C and then Gram-stained. Identification was performed using routine culture, macro- and microscopic morphological characterization and API 20C AUX (bioMerieux, Poland) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Clotrimazole susceptibility testing using antibiotic disks (clotrimazole 50 μg) (Bio-Rad) allowed rapid differentiation of 
   <span class="italic">P. wickerhamii</span> from 
   <span class="italic">P. zopfii</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Testing the Susceptibility of 
   <span class="italic">Prototheca zopfii</span> Isolates to Antifungal Chemotherapeutic Agents
  </div>
  <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">P. zopfii</span> isolates were cultured in Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (bioMerieux, Poland) and incubated at 37 °C for 48 h under aerobic conditions. Algae suspensions were prepared with an optical density of 0.5 on the McFarland scale using a densitometer (Den-1B McFarland BioSan Densitometer). Antibiotic susceptibility was investigated by the disk diffusion method on Yeast Nitrogen Base Agar (Becton Dickinson and Company, USA) or on Mueller-Hinton II Agar (Graso, Poland). The following antifungal chemotherapeutic agents were used (Graso, Poland): nystatin (100 μg), amphotericin B (20 μg), clotrimazole (10 μg), miconazole (10 μg), ketoconazole (10 μg), fluconazole (25 μg), econazole (10 μg), flucytosine (1 μg). The results were verified after 24 and 48 h of incubation at 37 °C for all antimicrobials. The inhibitory zone diameters were measured and interpreted according to Clinical and Laboratory Standard Institute (CLSI) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>] and EUCAST standards [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential Oils Used in the Experiments</div>
  <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant Material</div>
   <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aboveground parts (stems, leaves and inflorescences) of five herbs species (
    <span class="italic">T. vulgaris</span> L.—thyme, 
    <span class="italic">O. vulgare</span> ssp. 
    <span class="italic">hirtum</span> (Link) letswaart—Greek oregano, 
    <span class="italic">Origanum majorana</span> L.—marjoram, 
    <span class="italic">Mentha</span> × 
    <span class="italic">piperita</span> L.—peppermint, 
    <span class="italic">A. ursinum</span> L.—bear garlic) from experimental cultivation of the Department of Medicinal and Industrial Plants, University of Life Sciences in Lublin, were collected for the study. Voucher specimens (number N-1SKK-01, N-1SKK-02, N-1SKK-03, N-1SKK-04, N-1SKK-05) are deposited at the Department of Medicinal and Industrial Plants, University of Life Sciences in Lublin. Plant material was collected in August 2016, then dried at 40 °C in a drying chamber and powdered.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis of EO</div>
   <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Assay of the EO Content</span> The content of essential oil in herbal raw materials was assayed by indirect distillation with xylene for 3 h. The distillation was conducted in conformance with the Polish Pharmacopoeia VI [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">GC Analysis: Qualitative and Quantitative Analysis</span> A GC/MS. ITMS Varian 4000 GC–MS/MS (Varian, USA) equipped with a CP-8410 auto-injector and a 30 m × 0.25 mm i.d. VF-5 ms column (Varian, USA), film thickness 0.25 µm, was used; carrier gas He at a rate of 0.5 ml/min; injector and detector temperature 250 and 200 °C, respectively; split ratio 1:50; injection volume 5 µl. A temperature gradient was applied (50 °C for 1 min, then incremented by 4 °C/min to 250 °C, then held at 250 °C for 10 min); ionization energy 70 eV; mass range 40–870 Da; scan time 0.80 s. The oil obtained was collected in dark glass vessels, dried using dehydrated sodium sulfate and stored at below − 10 °C until chromatographic determination.
   </p>
   <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC/FID. GC Varian 3800 (Varian, USA) equipped with a CP-8410 auto-injector and a 30 m × 0.25 mm DB-5 column (J&amp;W Scientific, USA), film thickness 0.25 μm, carrier gas helium 0.5 ml/min, injector and detector FID temperatures 260 °C; split ratio 1:100; injection volume 5 μl. A temperature gradient was applied (50 °C for 1 min, then incremented by 4 °C/min to 250 °C, 250 °C for 10 min).</p>
   <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A qualitative analysis was performed on the MS spectra of the samples; the results were compared with those of the NIST library [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>] and with data available in the literature [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. The identity of the compounds was confirmed by their retention indices, taken from the literature [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>] and our own data. The quantity composition of the volatile oil was determined by GC(FID), assuming that a total area percents of all the particular oil constituted 100%. All determinations were performed in triplicate and averaged.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Determination of the Minimal Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of Essential Oils</div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The microbial activity of the studied essential oils was determined by the microdilution method in the broth according to NCCLS guidelines—The National Committee for Clinical Laboratory Standards based on document M27-A2 for yeast [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tested strains of 
   <span class="italic">P. zopfii</span> were cultured in a Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (SDA) bioMerieux and incubated for 48 h under aerobic conditions at 37 °C. From the inoculum, suspensions of algae were prepared in physiological saline (0.85%) with an optical density of 0.5 McFarland, which is approximately equal to 1 × 108 c.f.u./ml. To determine the density of the suspension, a Den-1B McFarland Densitometer (BioSan) was used.
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tests were performed using sterile 96-well microtiter plates (ProfiLab, Poland). The oils were diluted in DMSO. For each oil, concentrations of 32 to 0.0625 μl/ml were prepared in Sabouraud Dextrose Broth (Graso, Poland), with 100 μl of each concentration being mixed with the same volume of algae suspension. Two controls were prepared: a positive control without the essential oil and a negative control without the 
   <span class="italic">Prototheca</span> suspension. Control media, containing only DMSO at the concentration used, did not inhibit the growth of strains. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of the test substance, i.e., its lowest concentration preventing the growth of the microorganism (no turbidity), was determined after 48-h incubation at 37 °C under aerobic conditions. To confirm the visually defined MIC, SDA plates were plated with 100 μl dilution from the last well without turbidity and the results were read after 48 h under aerobic conditions at 37 °C. All tests were performed in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
