<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Large-scale screening of plants for active antiviral compounds dates to 1952, where around 288 plant extracts were tested for their activity against influenza A virus [
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Later, Debiaggi et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] had shown the antiviral effect of 
 <italic>Chamaecyparis lawsoniana</italic> on herpes simplex virus type 2. Similarly, Serkedjieva [
 <xref rid="bb0390" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] identified the antiviral effect of 
 <italic>Geranium sanguineum</italic> extract against influenza A virus, and Asres and Bucar [
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] showed anti-HIV activity of 
 <italic>Combretum mole</italic>. An aqueous extract of 
 <italic>Agrimonia eupatoria</italic> and root extract of 
 <italic>Boehmeria nivea</italic> were reported to inhibit hepatitis B virus [
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Kotwal et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] had demonstrated that an acidic extract of 
 <italic>Trifolium</italic> species could show a broad-spectrum antiviral activity, including anti-SARS activity. Thus, examining natural antiviral compounds from plants gains momentum in the present scenario. These plant-based therapeutic drugs have several advantages as compared to synthetic molecules. Naturally available biomolecules are safe, economical, and have minimal side effects. Further, if a plant-based compound is found to regulate the COVID-19 infection, it can facilitate an immediate use in the treatment regime after obtaining necessary ethical clearances. However, these compounds might not be stable or produced at minimal levels since they might play limited roles 
 <italic>in planta</italic>. A holistic approach is required to identify such potential compounds, study the biosynthesis pathway, analyze the genes underlying those pathways, and finetuning them using genomics and biotechnological interventions could promote the use of plants as a source and bio-manufacturer of antiviral compounds in large-scale. While mainstreaming plant-based research to identify biomolecules having anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity itself is in a nascent stage, exploiting the potential plants as biofactories is a long way to go. However, the advent of tools and techniques in plant molecular biology and biotechnology could expedite this process provided a roadmap need to be established towards achieving these targets. Given this, the present review enumerates the plant-based compounds that have been identified and characterized so far for treating viral infections with emphasis on coronavirus strains. The strategies for the identification of additional compounds, implementing omics tools for the over-production of those compounds, customization of biomolecules, and scaling-up of the process for large-scale production have been elaborated. Altogether, the review provides a roadmap for extrapolating the biomolecule repertoire of plants and use genomics and biotechnological approaches for their production and effective use in SARS-CoV-2 treatments.
</p>
