<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Essential fatty acids can only be found in dietary sources and are required for adequate function of the human body. Essential fatty acids cannot be made by the human body. It is important to note that there are two major sources of essential fatty acids: alpha-linolenic acid (ALA) and linoleic acid (LA). ALA is an 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-3 PUFA found in a variety of food items such as walnuts and flaxseeds. However, it is most prevalent in flaxseed. LA is an 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-6 PUFA enriched in safflower, poppyseed and rapeseed oil [
 <xref rid="B31-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. These two fatty acids serve in a variety of cell maintenance functions. There is evidence, however, suggesting that over-consumption of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-6 PUFAs may lead to increased inflammation within the body. It is important to note that fatty acids (essential or nonessential) can be found in a variety of dietary sources. Depending upon the saturation, different fatty acids are found in different foods. PUFAs are generally found in fish, flaxseed and grape seed oils. Saturated fatty acids (SFAs) are found in palm, coconut and cottonseed oils as well as chocolate products [
 <xref rid="B32-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Further research into some of these fatty acids to better elucidate their effects within the body and more specifically, their mechanism of action, will aid in the ongoing research within the field of nutraceuticals and functional foods [
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-nutrients-11-01179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>].
</p>
