<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Staining and fluorescence-microscopy</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the root-slices were cut, the water was removed and, based on the experiences of Fridvalszky [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>], one to three drops of 1% aqueous solution of Nile Blue A (Carl Roth GmbH und Co. KG, Karlsruhe, Germany) were applied. After incubating the root-slices for one minute at room temperature, the solution was carefully removed. A drop of water was applied and the root-slices were covered with a cover glass. A further incubation period of at least 30 min followed.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fluorescence-microscopy was done with a magnification of 100 (ocular 10×, objective 10×, ZEISS Axiostar plus, Carl Zeiss AG, Oberkochen, Germany). The initial light generated by a HBO50 high pressure mercury arc lamp was filtered for excitation at 430–510 nm and for emission at 475–575 nm. The images were taken with the connected digital camera ZEISS AxioCam ERc 5 s (a hyperspectral camera was not available) and instantly transferred to the connected computer. Due to the limited lens coverage, the final picture of a complete root-slice had to be composed of several partial images.</p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The green fluorescence oil droplets were imaged with a high-contrast against the black background. Despite all precautions taken, the root-slices did not always have exactly the same thickness and the cytoplasm of the cut cells was more or less leaked, so that the light transmittance of the cell layers varied among and within the root-slices. In order to make the oil droplets clearly visible in all areas of the root slice, brightness and contrast were adjusted through the camera software (ZEISS AxioVison, Carl Zeiss AG, Oberkochen, Germany) by one to two units, upwards or downwards, for each image. The depth of focus on the microscope was not changed so that the same cell layer was shown on each image.</p>
</sec>
