<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec24" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The number and density of oil droplets are not negatively related to the root thickness</div>
 <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mapping results showed an expected increase of the number of oil droplets per cross-section from thinner to thicker roots (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). For the fractions with low to high root diameters (RF1-RF3), the number of oil droplets was in accordance with the essential oil content results of Penzkofer et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. The fraction with the largest root diameter (RF4) showed the highest number of oil droplets in our study, but the lowest essential oil content in their study. It has to be noted that the essential oil content was determined by a very small number of data points and comprised only the clone CE4, because the other clones did not develop roots of this diameter. Considering CE4 only, the oil droplet number was the same for thick and very thick roots (RF3 and RF4, respectively).
 </p>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oil droplet density of total root cross-sections was highest in the thin roots (RF1) and lower in medium to thick roots (RF2-4). Thus, no linear relationship between oil drop density and root thickness can be derived. The high oil droplet density in thin roots may partially be an effect of root age, assuming that a higher portion of young roots occurred in this root fraction, and that oil droplets are formed at a very early stage of development, a phenomenon we were able to see with our image of a young lateral root. However, root age may not entirely explain the difference in oil droplet density between RF1 and RF2 as there was no difference between RF2 and RF3.</p>
 <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the breeding target of thicker roots, we found a positive relationship between root thickness and number of oil droplets per root cross-section. We did not find a negative relationship between root thickness and oil droplet density, especially when medium to very thick roots were considered. Consequently, there is a potential for selection of thick roots that have high oil droplet densities and, therefore, also likely high essential oil content. This is supported by the experience that many inbred lines with coarse roots and high essential oil content could be derived from clone CE4.</p>
</sec>
