<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antioxidant activities</div>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As illustrated in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>, the DPPH scavenging activity of all samples increased in a manner dependent on the concentration. At the concentration of 10 mg/mL, 
  <span class="italic">P. tobira</span> seeds essential oil showed the highest radical scavenging activity value (89.24%) but significantly lower than the vitamin C and BHT (95.97% and 93.66%, respectively) (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05). More precisely, the IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of the tested oil (1.5 ± 0.21 mg/mL) was less efficient than that of the standards BHT (0.093 ± 0.004 mg/mL) and vitamin C (0.0105 mg/mL) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Antioxidant activities of essential oil from 
     <span class="italic">Pittosporum tobira</span> seeds at different concentrations. DPPH free radical-scavenging activities (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), hydrogen peroxide (H
     <sub>2</sub>O
     <sub>2</sub>) scavenging activity (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) and reducing power (
     <span class="bold">c</span>). Values are means of three replications ± SD
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12944_2017_596_Fig4_HTML" id="MO5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Antioxidant capacity of essential oil and methanolic extract of 
     <span class="italic">Pittosporum tobira</span> seeds
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th>DPPH scavenging activity (IC
       <sub>50</sub>, mg/mL)
       <span class="sup">*</span>
      </th>
      <th>Reducing power (EC
       <sub>50</sub>, mg/mL)
       <span class="sup">**</span>
      </th>
      <th>(H
       <sub>2</sub>O
       <sub>2</sub>) scavenging activity (IC
       <sub>50</sub>, μg/mL)
       <span class="sup">***</span>
      </th>
      <th>Anti-hemolytic activity (IC
       <sub>50</sub>, μg/mL)
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Essential oil</td>
      <td>1.5 ± 0.21
       <span class="sup">c,d</span>
      </td>
      <td>0.982 ± 0.24
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td>159.43 ± 2.7
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
      <td>116.54 ± 1.8
       <span class="sup">c</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Methanolic extract</td>
      <td>&gt; 10</td>
      <td>&gt; 1</td>
      <td>308.57 ± 8.14
       <span class="sup">f</span>
      </td>
      <td>–</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Synthetic antioxidant</td>
      <td/>
      <td/>
      <td/>
      <td/>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>BHT</td>
      <td>0.093 ± 0.004
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td>0.384 ± 0.102
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td>–</td>
      <td>–</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Vit C</td>
      <td>0.0105 ± 0.001
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </td>
      <td>–</td>
      <td>20.73 ± 0.78
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td>16.75 ± 0.61
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Values are mean ± SD, 
     <span class="italic">n</span> = 3 (three independent experiments)
    </p>
    <p>Different letters for the same column indicate significant differences at 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">*</span> IC50 value was the effective concentrations at which DPPH were scavenged by 50%
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">**</span>EC50 value: the effective concentration at which the antioxidant activity was 50%; the absorbance was 0.5 for reducing power
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">***</span> IC50 value was the effective concentrations at which H
     <sub>2</sub>O
     <sub>2</sub> were scavenged by 50%
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Vit C</span> Vitamin C, 
     <span class="italic">BHT</span> Butylated hydroxytoluene
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As appears from Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>, antioxidant activity determined using the (H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>) scavenging assay showed results comparable to those obtained with DPPH scavenging activity. Once again, the result suggests that 
  <span class="italic">P. tobira</span> seeds essential oil exhibited the strongest antioxidant activity. This inhibition was dose-dependent (H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>) scavenging ability with IC
  <sub>50</sub> values of 159.43 ± 2.7 and 308.57 μg/mL for essential oil and methanolic extract, respectively. Thus, IC
  <sub>50</sub> values of essential oil were 1.93-fold more efficient than the methanolic extract but less efficient than vitamin C (IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 20.73 ± 0.78 μg/mL) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reducing power assay was commonly reported as a simple and robust method for measuring antioxidant power. This test is based on the conversion of Fe
  <span class="sup">3+</span> to Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span> under the effect of essential oils. In agreement with DPPH and (H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>) scavenging assays, reducing power method showed that essential oils exhibited good antioxidant activity. Thereby, the reducing powers of the tested samples increased when their concentrations were increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a>). As shown in Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>, the tested oil had slightly lower antioxidant potential than BHT (EC
  <sub>50</sub> = 0.384 ± 0.102 mg/mL for BHT and EC
  <sub>50</sub> = 0.982 ± 0.24 mg/mL for tested oil), but better than methanolic extract.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the results obtained from the three methods have shown that 
  <span class="italic">P. tobira</span> exhibited an important antioxidant activity. The obtained results are in agreement with several reports. Notably, the recent study of Dong et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>], demonstrated that essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">Chuanminshen violaceum</span> had potent antioxidant activity in vitro when compared to other sub-fraction like ethanol, ethyl acetate, methanol and chloroform fraction. However, findings of Mohamed et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] suggested that methanolic extract of 
  <span class="italic">Commiphora myrrha</span> exhibited higher DPPH scavenging capacity than the essential oil. These results suggested that there is a relationship between the chemical composition of aromatic plants and their antioxidant activity. According to our results, the antioxidant activity of 
  <span class="italic">P. tobira</span> seed essential oil might be attributed to the presence of biologically active component such as spathulenol, λ-gurjunene, camphor and isospathulenol. Spathulenol was found to be the important component in many medicinal plants such as 
  <span class="italic">Stachys inflata</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Kundmannia syriaca</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Additionally, previous studies showed the immunomodulatory effects of spathulenol identified from 
  <span class="italic">Salvia spinosa</span> essential oil [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Moreover, studies of Martins et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>], have demonstrated the anti-tumor potential of spathulenol.
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite all these investigations, it is difficult to attribute the antioxidant activity to the major active compounds of the essential oil. Indeed, it is also important to take into account minor compounds for their antioxidant activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. In this regard, the individual compound should be studied.
 </p>
</sec>
