<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently, the reasons such as increasing interest in the quality of food products by consumers and preferring those that are packed with environmentally friendly material have increased the interest in new packaging materials. As a result, new types of edible films produced by using food-grade compounds can be used as primary packaging material, which is developed to extend the shelf life of food products [
 <xref rid="B230-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">230</xref>,
 <xref rid="B231-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">231</xref>,
 <xref rid="B232-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>]. However, these days, the commercial use of edible films is significantly restricted because of cost disadvantages. In addition to the cost problems, difficulty in the production process and the strictness of the regulation both restrict the use of edible films and coatings [
 <xref rid="B232-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>]. Edible films that are generally made from single or combinations of polysaccharides, lipids, and proteins obtain advantages such as water, oxygen, and aroma barrier properties with improving the food appearance and quality at all stages of the food processing [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B230-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">230</xref>]. The features of the film are actually directly related to the edible compound. In this manner, compared to protein films, while chitosan films showed better oil barrier properties, their water vapor properties were lower [
 <xref rid="B231-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">231</xref>]. As is commonly known, EOs could be used as natural antioxidant and antimicrobial agents instead of synthetic ones in food products. However, their dominant flavor causes limitations on their use. In respect to this, the addition of EOs to edible coating on food packages provides several advantages such as increasing the film performance by eliminating some limitations [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B231-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">231</xref>]. From the antimicrobial perspective, the incorporation of EOs as antimicrobial agents directly into food packaging systems is a form of active packaging [
 <xref rid="B233-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">233</xref>].
</p>
