<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The assessment of the interaction of bioactive compounds as antioxidant properties represents the first step for the evaluation of the health properties of medicinal plants [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Many species belonging to the 
 <italic class="italic">Lamium</italic> genus have been studied to identify their antioxidant properties. Carović-Stanko et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] pointed out that most of the 
 <italic class="italic">Lamiaceae</italic> sources of antioxidants belong to the subfamily Nepetoideae, such as basil, lemon balm, marjoram, mint, oregano, rosemary, sage, etc [
 <xref rid="B104-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Lamium album</italic> L. is absolutely the most studied species. Trouillas et al. [
 <xref rid="B105-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>] have studied and compared the water-soluble fraction of 16 plants, including 
 <italic class="italic">L. album</italic>, typical of Limousin, a central-southern region of France. Presumably, the whole plant was used, whose main constituents are acid phenols, flavonoids, mucilage, iridoids. Water-soluble extracts have been tested for the ability to inhibit the DPPH radical, the superoxide radical generated by the xanthine/xanthine oxidase (X/XO) system, and the inhibition of the hydroxyl radical generated by the Fenton reaction. It is interesting to note that in the first two cases (DPPH and X/XO) the extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">L. album</italic> (non-stinging nettle) showed to be very effective when compared with the other species studied; particularly, it was 12-16 times more effective than extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">Urtica dioica</italic> (stinging nettle). This result diverged, significantly, from that obtained with a methanol extract of 
 <italic class="italic">L. album</italic> that showed the same ability to inhibit the DPPH radical at an extract concentration about 140 times lower [
 <xref rid="B106-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. This discrepancy could be due to the better ability of methanol to extract flavonoids (≈193 mg of gallic acid equivalents per g of extract (mg GAE/g)). This higher extraction capacity was corroborated by the greater amounts of phenolic compounds extracted when compared to extraction in water. The content of phenolic compounds of the methanol extract was almost five times greater than the aqueous extract. This result was in agreement with the content of phenolic compounds found in methanol extracts of specimens of another species of the 
 <italic class="italic">Lamium</italic> genus, 
 <italic class="italic">L. amplexicaule</italic> L. collected during the flowering period in a region of south-eastern Anatolia, Turkey (≈184 mg GAE/g) [
 <xref rid="B107-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. The presence of polyphenols could, moreover, be the determining factor in explaining why the methanol extract and hexane of 
 <italic class="italic">L. amplexicaule</italic> showed a significant reduction in the formation of nicked DNA and increased the native form of plasmid DNA pBR322.
</p>
