<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">From the perspective of bioinspired designs, the relevant superhydrophilic materials for antifouling and oil/water separation are concentrated in 2D films or membranes. One-dimensional superhydrophilic materials seem to have not much room for development. A turning point came in 2010 and 2012; the discovery of the unique liquid transport ability of spider silk
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup> and cactus
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup> opens the new door for the research of 1D superhydrophilic fibers and channels (
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>
 </xref>d). The combination of Laplace pressure and surface energy resulted in controllable transport of liquid by designing 1D superhydrophilic interfaces. It is also the core guiding ideology of bioinspired designs of 1D superhydrophilic materials. Bai et al.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref78" class="xref">78</xref>
 </sup> designed a series of artificial spider silks with spindle-knots to drive tiny water drops (tens of picoliters) with controllable transport by optimizing the cooperation of curvature, chemical composition, and roughness gradients on fiber surfaces. The key for artificial spider silk bioinspired designs for fog or water collection is to construct a spindle-knot structure, while the main aim of artificial cactus bioinspired designs is to obtain microscale cone structures. Ju and co-workers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref79" class="xref">79</xref>
 </sup> bioinspired designed a dual-gradient one-dimensional fog collector, namely, conical copper wire with gradient wettability. With the help of field-emission scanning electron microscopy, scientists detected that water can transport in carbon nanotubes.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup> The WCAs in carbon nanotubes range from 5° to 15°. On the basis of this pioneering research, superhydrophilic nanochannel materials have attracted more and more attention in recent years. These great works have opened up a favorable new situation of bioinspired designs of superhydrophilic materials.
</p>
