<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An unusual extraction procedure has been described in a study of the biological activity of an 
 <italic class="italic">L. album</italic> oil extract [
 <xref rid="B147-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">147</xref>] by using a biphasic solvent system consisting of 70% ethanol and sunflower oil at a ratio of 1:1, after the maceration of above-ground of 
 <italic class="italic">L. album</italic> in water. The oil extract (OE) was then studied in models of hemolytic anemia (HA) induced with intramuscular (IM) administration of phenylhydrazide chloride to white mongrel male rats. Three groups of animals were formed: (i) intact animals, (ii) negative control group (with induced hemolytic anemia but untreated, (iii) OE treated (with induced hemolytic anemia and treated). The results showed that the administration of extract had anti-anemic effects since all blood parameters (e.g., number of erythrocytes, hemoglobin levels, hematocrit, and red blood cell indices) were significantly better throughout the twelve weeks of the experiment. The authors suggested that the anti-anemic effect of OE may be due to the antioxidant action of chlorophyll preparation. This explanation is not fully convincing since the sunflower oil used to obtain OE contains on average 59% of linoleic acid [
 <xref rid="B148-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">148</xref>]. Recently, linoleic acid has been proved to induce red blood cells and hemoglobin damage via an oxidative mechanism, eventually leading to partial acute anemia [
 <xref rid="B149-molecules-24-01913" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">149</xref>]. In other words, if chlorophyll had effectively carried out anti-anemic action, such an action would be even stronger as it would have contrasted not only the anemic effect due to the administration of phenylhydrazide chloride, but also that induced by the linoleic acid contained in OE. It would have been interesting to know the effect of the administration of the extractor oil only in a further control group, but this eventuality has not been taken into consideration by the authors of this study.
</p>
