<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Teklehaymanot and Mirutse [
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] reported that 70% of the wild edible plants were also used as medicine. Some of the plant parts that are used as a food source but are also ingested as a remedy are taken from the following plants: 
 <italic>Saba comorensis</italic> (Boj.) 
 <italic>Pichon</italic>, 
 <italic>Moringa stenopetala</italic> (Bak. f.) Cuf., 
 <italic>Ximenia americana</italic> L., and 
 <italic>Grewia bicolor</italic> Juss. Kebebew and Leta [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] reported that from the recorded wild edible plants in the study area at Nech Sar National Park, Ethiopia, 18 species serve the local community both as sources of food and as traditional medicine. These nutraceutical plants are used to treat 14 human ailments or health problems. The fruit of 
 <italic>Cordia africana</italic> is mentioned as a treatment for diarrhea. The leaves of 
 <italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> are used to treat abdominal pain, and the roots of 
 <italic>Carissa spinarum</italic> is a remedy for tapeworm. These three important nutraceutical plants are also mentioned in other studies undertaken in different parts of the country [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Among the 16 species (32.7%) of WEPs that were grouped as nutraceuticals, the finding indicated that these WEPs were used as food and remedy [
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table"> Table 3</xref> indicates the list of wild edible plants and their medicinal roles. This showed that wild edible plants are also used for their medicinal value besides their food value. The review indicated that 
 <italic>Moringa stenopetala</italic>, 
 <italic>Solanum nigrum</italic>, 
 <italic>Tamarindus indica</italic>, 
 <italic>Carissa spinarum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Ximenia americana</italic> are some of WEPs commonly used in different parts of the country as indicated by different scholars [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
