<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A study of another invasive weed species, perennial pepperweed (
 <italic class="italic">Lepidium latifolium</italic>), found that greater control was achieved when different treatments were combined, rather than single treatments being applied separately [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. While our study was conducted over 18 months, its relevance to longer term control may perhaps be extrapolated from this experience. We assert that such management advice, if followed carefully, will significantly reduce the dominance of 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pubescens</italic> in affected areas. Pine oil application was the novel method used in this experiment, and this is the first time it has been used directly in the field for the control of a weed soil seedbank. The results we obtained show that this treatment is effective as a means to reduce the density of 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pubescens</italic> seedlings. Previous studies in pot trials had indicated that essential oils, such as pine oil, destroy seed viability by ‘exploding’ the outer coat of the seeds, causing cell damage and desiccation [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. In addition, Kremer and Spencer [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] stated that mechanical degradation of seeds, particularly from damage to the seed coat, makes the seeds more susceptible to attack by microorganisms. This suggests that microbial attack may have been partly responsible for the reduction in seedbank germination observed for the pine oil treatment in this trial. The changes in the seedbank composition of 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pubescens</italic> thus demonstrate that pine oil applications may have an important role in the control of weed seedbank for biodiversity conservation. The results indicate that if applications of pine oil are made regularly in areas of heavy weed infestation, a significant shift in seedbank composition will be achieved. Further, if the pine oil treatment is followed by an application of native plant seeds after a suitable withholding period, then the control will be more effective. The increased native plant population acts to reduce the incidence of bare soil, allows them to compete directly with weed re-establishment, and rapidly decreases the possibility of soil erosion. Weeds often spread at the expense of other species because they have ecological characteristics that enable them to reproduce and proliferate quickly. In general, the most aggressive weeds are characterised by their ability to spread rapidly beyond their natural distribution, high growth rates, rapid seedling recruitment, and high seed production, which suggests that management approaches need to be instituted with these attributes in mind.
</p>
