<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The other effective method found in this study to control 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pubescens</italic> was mulch, a mixture of white sugar and sawdust. This treatment had a positive effect in reducing the cover abundance as well as retarding the seedling emergence of 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pubescens</italic>. There are a number of plausible explanations for the observed effects. Mulch forms a layer on the ground and prevents airborne or dropped seeds from reaching the soil surface, whilst also smothering mature plants and reducing their growth. Previous studies have also found that mulches are an effective technique to control weeds [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Another advantage of incorporating sugar into a mulch mixture is promotion of the activity of microorganisms in the soil. Microorganisms, such as soil fungi, absorb soil nutrients as they grow, thereby reducing nutrient availability to weeds [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. This relative lack of nutrients inhibits or reduces weed growth, while simultaneously providing a better soil environment for native plants, which prefer low nutrient conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. In addition, certain organic mulches, such as sawdust or wood chips, may control weeds chemically through the leaching of naturally occurring allelopathic chemicals [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. In a similar study, Greenly and Rakow [
 <xref rid="pone.0203653.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>] stated that organic mulches are most effective in weed control when applied to a sufficient depth, for example, so that they prevent light reaching the soil surface. Mulch treatment reduces light availability, which stresses existing weeds and prevents germination of their seeds, especially those with small seeds, such as 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pubescens</italic>.
</p>
