<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Hydnora</italic> species have been reported in South Africa, Madagascar, Uganda, Mozambique, Swaziland, Botswana, Kenya, Sudan, Ethiopia, Tanzania, Angola, Somalia, Namibia, and the Arabian Peninsula (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00494-f002">Figure 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Host-based speciation appears to be a dynamic aspect in the evolution of 
 <italic>Hydnora</italic> and this is reinforced by vicariance and changes in phenology. The wide distribution range of the Euphorbiaceae and Fabaceae families may also have led to the subsequent increase in the distribution range of the 
 <italic>Hydnora</italic> species. These species are host-specific (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00494-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). 
 <italic>H. africana</italic>, 
 <italic>H. longicollis</italic>, and 
 <italic>H. visseri</italic> showed high host-specificity with 
 <italic>Euphorbia</italic> species. 
 <italic>H. abyssinica, H. arabica,</italic> and 
 <italic>H. esculenta</italic> are host-specific to Fabaceae, while 
 <italic>H. triceps</italic> grow on both Euphorbiaceae and Zygophyllaceae families. The variation of host dependency of these species to their host plants has not been revealed whether they exchange genes that help them to perform other metabolic activities, or they entirely depend on their hosts for nutrients. The distribution range of this genus is increasing due to their apparent host. 
 <italic>H. abyssinica</italic> and 
 <italic>H. africana</italic> have shown a higher distribution range compared to the other species (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-10-00494-f002">Figure 2</xref>). Furthermore, 
 <italic>H. longicollis</italic> is not well-known due to its inaccessibility [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Recently, this species was collected from Namibia growing on 
 <italic>Euphorbia</italic>; however, very little information on this species is available in the Kew herbarium (
 <uri xlink:href="http://specimens.kew.org/herbarium/29047.275" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://specimens.kew.org/herbarium/29047.275</uri> (20 December 2020) [
 <xref rid="B47-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. esculenta</italic> is only endemic in Madagascar and mostly found in association with the invasive tree, 
 <italic>Pithecellobium dulce</italic>. The distribution range of 
 <italic>H. esculenta</italic> is increasing due to the spread of 
 <italic>P. dulce</italic> in riparian areas and disturbed habitats in Southern Madagascar [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. triceps</italic> is only endemic in Northwestern Cape and Southern Namibia because of the restricted distribution of the host. It depends completely on 
 <italic>Euphorbia dregeana</italic>. A few samples have been collected since its discovery, and so it remains poorly studied [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. visseri</italic> is distributed from Namibia to the Northern Cape Province in South Africa. Its distribution is restricted around the Orange River, where its host plants include 
 <italic>Euphorbia gummifera</italic> Boiss. and 
 <italic>E. gregaria</italic> Marloth [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. sinandevu</italic> is native in Kenya and Tanzania [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. arabica</italic> is distributed from Southern Oman (Dhofar region) to Yemen on Acacia species [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. africana</italic> is distributed in Namibia, Swaziland, Nigeria, Kenya, Zimbabwe, Uganda, Madagascar, Saudi Arabia, South Africa, and Ethiopia [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. abyssinica</italic> is the most widely distributed species in Namibia, Northern Botswana, Zimbabwe, Zaire, Tanzania, Kenya, Ethiopia, Somalia, Sudan, and the Arabian Peninsula [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-plants-10-00494" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].
</p>
