<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0035">The naturally occurring products and phytomedicines are coming to the fore all around the world, owing to the orientation of the social fabric to such remedies in different health care centres all across the globe (WHO, 2004). The global outlook for drug formulation is showing a paradigm shift as individuals are facing chronic as well as lifestyle-related disorders, due to which they are turning their stance towards improving life-styles and disease deterrence. However, during ancient period herbal phyto-constituents were the only alternatives for healing the illness as antibiotics were not discovered. Particularly, herbal formulations endow us with toolbox to concoct novel antiviral products. This pragmatically involves the understanding of antiviral mechanisms of natural products and their role in heckling virus life-cycle, replication, assembly and its release. Ever since, the safety and clinical characteristics of traditional medicines have come out, their consumption have been gradually elevating after approval by scientific communities (
 <xref rid="bib0157" ref-type="bibr">Mohammadi and Shaghaghi, 2020</xref>). Attributable to the side-effects of chemical compounds onto human bodies, it has believed to utilize the herbal therapies with much more effectiveness and nil side-effects. Recently, WHO, has estimated that approximately 80% of the world population has been trusting the herbal therapeutics, yet, a quite a few number of plants have been studied for this noble work (
 <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Baell, 2016</xref>). Undeniably, traditional drugs are long in the tooth since primordial times and play a significant role to meet global health needs. Usually, Ayurveda, Naturopathy, Siddha, Homopathy, Yoga, Persian medicines, Unani, Romanian, and Chinese conventional medicines have been known since ancient times (
 <xref rid="bib0063" ref-type="bibr">Gomathi et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0079" ref-type="bibr">Heidary et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0253" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0124" ref-type="bibr">Ling, 2020</xref>). Usage of these systems in medical field is quite lucrative to suppress viral infections in respiratory systems and modulating inflammatory reactions within immune systems. As depicted earlier, AYUSH has initiated a holistic perspective of medicine to cure presently prevailing anti-viral infections via self remedial processes (
 <xref rid="bib0153" ref-type="bibr">AYUSH, 2020</xref>).
</p>
