<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The compelling in vitro activity of TTO against MRSA has gained considerable interest and it seems to have translated well with the positive outcomes observed in MRSA colonised patients in randomised controlled clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B89-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Caelli et al. (2000) evaluated the clinical efficacy of TTO by randomly allocating MRSA infected patients (
 <italic>n</italic> = 30) to either routine care (2% mupirocin nasal ointment and triclosan body wash, no report on dose and frequency of administration) or TTO (a 4% tea tree oil nasal ointment and 5% tea tree oil body wash, no report on dose and frequency of administration) given for a minimum of three days [
 <xref rid="B89-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. The study reported that more participants were cleared of MRSA carriage in the TTO group (33%) compared to the routine care group (13%) (
 <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05), indicating TTO therapy may be effective in decolonising MRSA carriers. Dryden et al. (2004) also compared MRSA clearing efficacy of TTO regimen (tea tree 10% nasal cream given three times daily plus tea tree 5% body wash given once daily) with standard treatment regimen (mupirocin 2% nasal ointment given three times daily plus chlorhexidine gluconate 4% soap given once daily and silver sulfadiazine 1% cream skin treatments given once daily for five days) in MRSA infected hospitalized patients (
 <italic>n</italic> = 224) [
 <xref rid="B90-antibiotics-09-00909" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. The study reported that among the participants, 49% in the standard treatment and 41% in the TTO groups were cleared of MRSA carriage, showing no significant difference between the treatment regimens (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.0286). TTO treatment was also highly effective at clearing superficial skin lesions compared to the standard treatment (47% versus 31%, respectively, no report on 
 <italic>p</italic> values), indicating its potential use for MRSA-implicated skin infections, such as impetigo.
</p>
