<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>D. benthami</italic> is a legume species of the Dalbergia family. Its tree trunk and root heart are usually used in TCM. The main applications of 
 <italic>D. benthami</italic> in TCM are in the therapy of traumatic injuries, as an analgesic and for the regulation of menstrual cycles [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It has been proven by modern pharmacology that 
 <italic>Dalbergia</italic> genus plants have antitumor, antivirus and antioxidation potentials [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Furthermore, it has been shown that crude extracts of 
 <italic>D. benthami</italic> have significant antibacterial and anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Previous studies of our lab showed that the ethyl acetate extract of 
 <italic>D. benthami</italic> had a greater antioxidation than the extracts prepared with other solvents [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. 14 compounds from 
 <italic>D. benthami</italic> were isolated and identified as isoflavone, dalbergiben-thamone robustin acid, pseudobap-tigenin and formononetin, etc. [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Nevertheless, the active constituent of the ethyl acetate extract is unknown. In our previous studies, RA could be considered as one of the principal components in the plants from the 
 <italic>Dalbergia</italic> genus, and it has been reported to be isolated in minute concentrations from other plants such as 
 <italic>Millettia thonningi</italic> [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], 
 <italic>Erythrina indica</italic> [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and 
 <italic>Derris eriocarpa</italic> How [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. RA has also been synthesized in nine steps from methyl 2,4,6-trihydroxyphenyl ketone, with an overall yield of 18% [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The biological activities of RA were studied by the Chemical Genomics Center (NCGC), and it was found that RA was cytotoxic to H1299 lung cancer cells with p53 Mutation (IC50 7.94 µM) and that it also inhibits Cytochrome P450 activity (IC50 6.31 µM) [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. RA also possesses a significant antimalarial activity [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In our previous studies, RA displayed an obvious Topo I inhibition activity and cytotoxicity, which was probably mediated by an arrest of the tumor cells at the G1 phase and a suppressed cell proliferation via the induction of apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-03919" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Nevertheless, the anti-tumor mechanism of RA still remains unclear, so the biological activities of RA need further exploration.
</p>
