<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Determination of the Minimal Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of Essential Oils</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The microbial activity of the studied essential oils was determined by the microdilution method in the broth according to NCCLS guidelines—The National Committee for Clinical Laboratory Standards based on document M27-A2 for yeast [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tested strains of 
  <span class="italic">P. zopfii</span> were cultured in a Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (SDA) bioMerieux and incubated for 48 h under aerobic conditions at 37 °C. From the inoculum, suspensions of algae were prepared in physiological saline (0.85%) with an optical density of 0.5 McFarland, which is approximately equal to 1 × 108 c.f.u./ml. To determine the density of the suspension, a Den-1B McFarland Densitometer (BioSan) was used.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tests were performed using sterile 96-well microtiter plates (ProfiLab, Poland). The oils were diluted in DMSO. For each oil, concentrations of 32 to 0.0625 μl/ml were prepared in Sabouraud Dextrose Broth (Graso, Poland), with 100 μl of each concentration being mixed with the same volume of algae suspension. Two controls were prepared: a positive control without the essential oil and a negative control without the 
  <span class="italic">Prototheca</span> suspension. Control media, containing only DMSO at the concentration used, did not inhibit the growth of strains. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of the test substance, i.e., its lowest concentration preventing the growth of the microorganism (no turbidity), was determined after 48-h incubation at 37 °C under aerobic conditions. To confirm the visually defined MIC, SDA plates were plated with 100 μl dilution from the last well without turbidity and the results were read after 48 h under aerobic conditions at 37 °C. All tests were performed in triplicate.
 </p>
</sec>
