<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The main pattern of population structure we observed in Europe was a west-east gradient. Differentiation between the western and eastern parts of the European invasive range had previously been observed [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and attributed to two main, distinct invasion sources. Here, we also observed that populations from central Europe (Germany to Italy) were genetically distinct from both Western and Eastern European populations. Several genetic clusters predicted by Structure were not observed or were very infrequent in North American populations, suggesting that we may have sampled only a fraction of the native sources. Alternatively, the additional clusters revealed by Structure under the more refined model (
 <italic>K</italic> = 6) could simply reflect the elevated genetic divergence of some populations. Indeed, Structure analyses are known to be biased towards inferring extra genetic clusters when some populations have undergone strong recent genetic drift; in that case, and contrary to the assumptions of the admixture model, not all genetic clusters are ancestral sources for the present populations [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Population-specific genetic divergences as estimated based on the F-model largely varied among populations, a pattern not expected if all populations similarly derived from a number of ancestral sources [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. This, together with the outputs of Structure for increasing genetic partitioning (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0176197.g003">Fig 3</xref>), suggests secondary founding events associated with genetic drift. This hypothesis was not supported by signatures for recent bottlenecks; however, it is well known that bottleneck tests have a very limited power [
 <xref rid="pone.0176197.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Populations from Italy, Germany and one population from Hungary (TAT) likely had their genetic sources in the South-Eastern part of Europe, whereas one population from France (89-P10) likely originated from eastern France. Although this would need to be validated based a more extensive sampling, genetic patterns revealed here are overall consistent with two main distinct colonization events in Europe (in South-Eastern France: the Rhone valley, and South-Eastern Europe: the Pannonian plain), with secondary colonization events arising northwards and towards Central Europe.
</p>
