<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0040">Plants such as 
 <italic>Moringa oleifera Lam, Azadirachta indica A.Juss, Murraya koenigii (L.) Sprengel</italic> and 
 <italic>Psidium guajava L</italic>possess a rich number of phytoconstituents and also possess many potential therapeutic activities. These plants are widely used in the traditional systems of medicine. 
 <italic>Azadirachta indica (A. indica)</italic> leaves contain various phytoconstituents like nimbanene, nimbiol, nimbin, 6-desacetylnimbinene, nimbolide, nimbandiol, n-hexacosanol, ascorbic acid, amino acid, 7-desacetyl-7-benzoylgedunin, 7-desacetyl-7-benzoylazadiradione, 17-hydroxyazadiradione, ß-sitosterol, and Quercetin. Earlier studies have reported that 
 <italic>A. indica</italic> has established noteworthy therapeutic activities like antiarthritic, anti-inflammatory, hypoglycemic, antipyretic, antiulcer, cytotoxicity activities, and antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Salmonella typhi (S.typhi), Escherichia coli (E.coli), Bacillus pumilus (B. pumilus)</italic> and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa (P.aeruginosa)</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>]. 
 <italic>Moringa oleifera (M. oleifera)</italic> leaves contain a wide range of phytoconstituents such as omega-3, omega-6, palmitic acid, linoleic acid, protein, ß-carotene, vitamin C, minerals like potassium and calcium. Various parts of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> showed therapeutic activities like lipid-lowering, antitumor, antiepileptic, antipyretic, antiulcer, diuretic, antispasmodic, anti-inflammatory, antidiabetic, antifungal, hepatoprotective, antioxidant, and antibacterial activities against 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis (B.subtilis), E.coli, S. aureus, P. aeruginosa, Enterobacter aerogenes, Aspergillus niger</italic> and 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>]. Leaves of 
 <italic>Murraya koenigii (M. koenigii)</italic> contain carbohydrates, proteins, minerals, fiber, carotene, vitamin C, glycosides, oxalic acid, secondary metabolites like triterpenoid (tetrahydromahanmbine, cyclomahanimbine), coumarine (murrayone imperatoxin), alkaloids (murrayaline, murrayastine, pypayafolinecarbazole) and other compounds (mahanimbicine, phebalosin, bicyclomahanimbicine). These phytoconstituents showed a variety of pharmacological activities such as anti-inflammatory, analgesic, antioxidant, antitumor, hepatoprotective, antidiarrheal, and antimicrobial activities against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>B.subtilis</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Major phytoconstituents of 
 <italic>Psidium guajava (P. guajava)</italic> leaves are isoflavonoids, phenolic compounds, rutin, catechin, epicatechin, kaempferol, and naringenin. Different parts of the plant have shown various therapeutic activities like antioxidant, anti-spasmodic, antioxidant, anticancer, hepatoprotective, antidiabetic, analgesic, anti-inflammatory, anti-diarrhea, anti-stomachache and antimicrobial activities against 
 <italic>S. aureus, S. Typhi, E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
