<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>G. pentaphyllum</italic> is an important medicinal herb with promising and clinically important biological activities. It also contains a plethora of structurally diverse natural products, any or all of which may be responsible for the activities observed for the extracts. Our study identifies the compounds most likely to be orally available from the complex mixture that is ingested as “the immortal tea”. The Caco-2 cell monolayer permeability assay on the flavonoids and saponins from 
 <italic>G. pentaphyllum</italic> resulted in the identification of strong candidates for potential human oral bioavailability. The study indicated that kaempferol glycosides 
 <bold>2</bold>–
 <bold>5</bold> exhibited moderate to high permeability across Caco-2 cell monolayers. A notable observation was that the 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>app</sub> value was not significantly affected by the presence of different sugar units as galactose-containing compounds 
 <bold>2</bold> and 
 <bold>4</bold> showed similar 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>app</sub> values to the glucose-containing compounds 
 <bold>3</bold> and 
 <bold>5</bold>, respectively. The quercetin glycoside 
 <bold>7</bold> also exhibited moderate permeability across Caco-2 cell monolayers, whereas other quercetin glycosides 
 <bold>8</bold> and 
 <bold>9</bold> with a higher degree of glycosylation exhibited high Caco-2 cell permeability. Quercetin glycosides exhibited higher permeability across Caco-2 monolayers than kaempferol and isorhamnetin glycosides. It was also observed that the permeability of the glycosides was dependent on the number of sugar units attached to the aglycone and the number of glycosylation sites with a higher degree of glycosylation facilitating the permeability across Caco-2 cell monolayers. 
 <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>
 </xref> provides a summary of the key structural features that our data suggest are critical for enhanced permeability across Caco-2 cell monolayers and therefore for potential bioavailability.
</p>
