<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Wild turmeric EO is reported to promote blood circulation, remove blood stasis, and treat cancers [
 <xref rid="B148-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">148</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> EO showed a remarkable anti-inflammatory activity via suppressing the production of proinflammatory cytokines including protein kinase C (PKC), Akt, tumor-necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2), NF-κB, and IκB kinase (IKK) in vivo in 12-
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>-tetradecanoylphorbol-13-acetate (TPA)-induced edema model [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. It is thought that turmerone, 
 <italic class="italic">ar</italic>-turmerone, 8,9-dehydro-9-formyl-cycloisolongifolene, 
 <italic class="italic">ar</italic>-curcumene, α-zingiberene, and germacrone are responsible for the anti-inflammatory activity of 
 <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> EO [
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The oil showed good cytotoxic activities against LNCaP HepG2, and B16 cell lines [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. The oil can also suppress the growth of hepatoma cells in vivo and in vitro [
 <xref rid="B214-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">214</xref>]. The oil was reported to induce apoptosis in NSCLC cells [
 <xref rid="B208-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">208</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">ar</italic>-Tumerone, turmerone, and curdione from 
 <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> EO have in vitro and in vivo antiproliferative effect on laryngeal cancer (Hep-2) cells [
 <xref rid="B210-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">210</xref>]. Wild turmeric oil infused via hepatic artery inhibited hepatic tumors in patients with primary liver cancer [
 <xref rid="B213-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">213</xref>], rats with transplanted hepatoma [
 <xref rid="B211-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">211</xref>], and mice [
 <xref rid="B212-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">212</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> EO showed antiproliferative effects on hepatoma by inhibiting its growth in mice (51–52%) via decreasing the DNA synthesis of hepatocellular carcinoma and shrinking the nucleus area [
 <xref rid="B212-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">212</xref>]. The antitumor activity of wild turmeric EO was attributed to the presence of β-elemene, curcumol, and curdione [
 <xref rid="B237-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">237</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> EO showed hepatic chemopreventive activity against hepatocellular carcinoma both in vivo and in vitro [
 <xref rid="B214-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">214</xref>]. Pretreatment with 
 <italic class="italic">C. aromatica</italic> oil (100 mg/kg for 3 days) protected mice from hepatic injury from inflammation and oxidative damage induced by concanavalin A, which can decrease the incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma.
</p>
