<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Three enzymes catalyze the prenylation of proteins: farnesyltransferase (FTase) and geranylgeranyltransferases type I and II (GGTase I and GGTase II). They are heterodimers recognising C-terminal consensus sequences in the target proteins. FTase and GGTase I transfer a single farnesyl or geranylgeranyl group to a cysteine residue located in the “CaaX box” (C-terminal consensus sequence in which “C” represents a cysteine, “a” is an aliphatic amino acid and “X” determines the attached isoprenoid) [
 <xref rid="B176-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>]. Proteins modified by FTase or GGTase I need two additional processing steps: cleavage of “aaX” tripeptide by an endoprotease and methylation of prenylcysteine [
 <xref rid="B174-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">174</xref>]. The structure and enzymology of FTase and GGTase I are similar, although most studies focus on farnesylation. First, farnesyl residue binds to FTase [
 <xref rid="B181-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>], secondly the protein with a CaaX-box binds and the C-S bond is formed. While the prenylated protein remains bound to the enzyme, another prenyl group binds to the enzyme and, lastly, the product (prenylated protein) is dissociated before or while a new CaaX-box substrate binds [
 <xref rid="B173-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">173</xref>]. As a consequence, stereochemistry at C-1 position of the isoprenoid is inverted [
 <xref rid="B183-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">184</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">185</xref>] but this causes minimal differences in protein conformation [
 <xref rid="B186-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>]. FTase and GGTase I have not mutually exclusive substrate specificity [
 <xref rid="B187-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>], although there are preferences depending on the “X” aminoacid in CaaX box, as said above, so some prediction tools have been developed.
</p>
