<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First, the results of the decision context, encompassing the analysis of the therapeutic context, the available comparators, the horizon and the stakeholder perspectives [
 <xref rid="B124-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>] provide suitable information to properly identify the benefits and risks associated to the specific treatment. Benefits and risks are then weighted and compared in order to evaluate if the benefits outweigh risks. When considering benefit risk analysis, it is important to have consistent definitions of the related terms. Here ‘benefit’ relates to a favourable outcome (e.g., increased efficacy) of a given medical application, while ‘risk’ is used to denote adverse effects defined by severity and probability of occurrence [
 <xref rid="B122-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. In contrast to occupational or environmental risks, which are calculated as absolute quotients that are strictly acceptable or non-acceptable, the risks from MD or ATMP are always relative to the expected therapeutic benefits and to the potential consequences the specific health problem can bring to the patients (e.g., death, impairment). Therefore, for medical applications such as MD and ATMP, the estimation of the dose-response relationship of possible adverse effects needs to be coupled with a benefit risk analysis, which considers additional criteria such as the nature and severity of the disease to be treated, the possible benefits of the treatment to the patient and the levels of risk acceptance on both the community (societal) and patient (personal) levels. For both benefit and risk, it is recommended that uncertainties such as variation, methodological flaws or deficiencies unsettled issues, limitations of the data set be considered during benefit risk analysis [
 <xref rid="B126-materials-13-04532" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. IATA, as already discussed in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot2dot1-materials-13-04532">Section 2.2.1</xref>, can support the analysis of existing information available along the product development phases, with the aim of guiding the selection of the most suitable and effective tests to provide the information needed to perform an effective benefit risk analysis.
</p>
