<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study demonstrated that 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> leaves and soil C, N, and P stoichiometric characteristics were greatly affected by the tidal level and differed greatly between the different distances from the coastline. Such differences reflect the adaptability of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> to different environments. C is an important element in the formation of plant bodies. In this study, the C content, C/N ratio, and C/P ratio were observed to differ significantly among the different tide levels, which reflects the different nutrient utilization efficiency of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> at different distances from the coastline [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The N/P ratio in leaves is an important indicator to reflect if plants are restricted by nutrition during their growth [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The average N/P ratio in this study was 8.17 ± 0.15, which is significantly lower than the average value of other terrestrial and aquatic plants [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Moreover, Jack et al. [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] demonstrated that when the N/P ratio of wetland plant leaves was less than 14, it indicated that the soil N resources were limited. In addition, the N/P ratio in the soil was 0.86 ± 0.04, which is significantly lower than that of leaves. This result indicates that 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic> is able to more easily accumulate N to maintain survival and ensure growth when N resources are limited in the soil [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], thus reflecting the growth strategy of 
 <italic>S. alterniflora</italic>. The soil C/P ratio is an important indicator of soil P availability [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-plants-10-00013" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In the present study, we found that the soil C/P ratio was significantly related to leaf C, N, and P contents. Therefore, the availability of soil P is believed to be closely related to leaf nutrient levels.
</p>
