<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19" class="p">The protective effects of oral caraway oil (10 mg/kg) on gentamicin induced nephrotoxicity has been confirmed in rat animal model. Caraway essential oil reduced the increased plasma malondialdehyde (MDA) in rats exposed to gentamicin. It also increased superoxide dismutase (SOD), catalase (CAT) and glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px) in rats [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>]. The enhancing effects of oral caraway oil (5, 10, 20 mg/kg) on serum level of GSH-Px, CAT and SOD and the decreasing effects on serum level of MDA in streptozotocin induced diabetic rats were confirmed. In other word, caraway oil has reducing effect on the oxidative stress in diabetes mellitus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>]. The preventive effects of 100 mg/kg essential oil against cecal ligation and puncture model, which induced septic related oxidative liver injury in rats showed myeloperoxidase (MPO) activity and TBARS were suppressed by essential oils in cecal ligation and puncture model of rats. Caraway oils significantly reverse the depleted hepatic cellular Glutathione (GSH) comparable with 10 mg/kg indomethacin. Caraway essential oils had significant suppressive effects on aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT). Plasma alkaline phosphatase (ALP), total bilirubin, albumin and total protein were not affected from caraway essential oil. Essential oils reduced infiltration and sequestration of PMN, interstitial edema, congestion, necrosis and the severity of liver injury index in sepsis model of rats, comparable to indomethacin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>]. The reno-protective effects of oral caraway essential oil (10 mg/kg) in streptozotocin induced diabetic rats were shown by increasing in GSH-Px to normal levels of control group and significant improvement in pathology of diabetic nephropathy with minor pathological changes in glomerular lobulation, mild cellular infiltration in interstitial tissue [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>]. Caraway (30, 60 and 90 mg/kg) for 30 weeks reduced the levels of intestinal, colonic and caecal tissue lipid peroxidation products (conjugated dienes, lipid hyperoxides, TBRAS) and increased the antioxidant enzymes such as SOD, CAT, GSH, glutathione reductase of rats with colon carcinogenesis. Caraway seed extract reduced the activity of tissue GSH-Px, glutathione S transferase (GST), ascorbic and α-tocopherol levels. Caraway fruits could decrease the tumor size and tumor incidence. Caraway make resistant the tumor cells to free radical attack, which result in reduction of cell proliferation of cancerous cells. The activation of antioxidant enzymes scavenge the free radicals in colon cancer rats [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>]. The protective effects of 150 mg/kg oral caraway seed aqueous extract on liver, kidney and fertility exposed to cadmium toxicity in rat animal model was confirmed. Caraway Seed extract decreased the AST and ALT enzymes levels. The serum level of creatinine had the same value with control group. A significant increase in total antioxidant capacity and a significant reduction in serum levels of MDA was observed in caraway female rats. The histopathological samples of liver from caraway treated rats showed normal structures with strong fuchsinophilic reaction in hepatocytes. Pretreatment of cadmium treated rats with caraway seed extract improved the histopathological structure of kidney tubules. An improvement in liver functions was observed after treatment of cadmium exposed albino rats with caraway seed extract, which maintain the liver enzymes in normal level. Caraway seed extract had ameliorative effects against hepatic histological changes induced by cadmium [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>].
</p>
