<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par50">
    <italic>α-glucosidase assay buffer I</italic> (for preparing extracts and acarbose) consisted of freshly prepared 100 mM sodium phosphate buffer with 2% DMSO (pH 6.9). All test extracts and acarbose (positive control) were prepared by dissolving in assay buffer I.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par51">Comments: DMSO was used to aid in the solubility of the extracts in the buffer [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Preliminary testing confirmed that 2% DMSO (final concentration of 0.001% DMSO) had no significant effect on rat intestinal α-glucosidase activity. It is also possible to use PBS (pH adjusted to 6.9) as the incubation buffer in this assay without affecting rat intestinal α-glucosidase activity.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par52">
    <italic>α-glucosidase assay buffer II</italic> (for preparing assay reagents) consisted of a freshly prepared 100 mM sodium phosphate buffer without DMSO (pH 6.9). The enzyme and substrate solutions were prepared by dissolution in assay buffer II.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par53">
    <italic>Test samples</italic> were prepared from the concentrated plant extracts by dissolving and diluting the extracts in α-glucosidase assay buffer I to obtain working test sample solutions of 1 mg/mL. These were freshly prepared immediately before experiments and used on the same day.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par54">
    <italic>Positive control, acarbose</italic> powder was dissolved in α-glucosidase assay buffer I to prepare a 100 mg/mL stock solution which was stored short-term at 4 °C. A working solution of 1 mg/mL acarbose was prepared by diluting the stock solution in α-glucosidase assay buffer I immediately before experiments.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par55">
    <italic>Negative control</italic> (vehicle) was α-glucosidase assay buffer I.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par56">
    <italic>Rat intestinal α-glucosidase enzyme solution</italic> was prepared by sonicating 0.625 g of rat intestinal acetone powder in 50 mL of assay buffer II at RT, followed by vigorous mixing at 800 rpm for 20 min at RT. The mixture was centrifuged at 14,000 rpm for 30 min at 4 °C (Beckman Coulter Avanti J-25i high-speed centrifuge), and the supernatant (working enzyme solution) was stored in aliquots in the dark at 4 °C until use. The working α-glucosidase solution can be refrigerated for storage for up to 3 months without any appreciable decline in enzyme activity. The working enzyme solution cannot be frozen as freezing inactivates the enzyme.
   </p>
   <p id="Par57">Comments: Note that the concentration of α-glucosidase in the enzyme solution is unknown. However, different volumes of the enzyme solution (10, 20 and 30 µL/well) were tested as part of the assay optimisation and 30 µL/well was optimal for the assay method described herein.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par58">
    <italic>p-NPG substrate solution</italic> was prepared by dissolving and diluting 
    <italic>p</italic>-NPG powder in assay buffer II to obtain a working substrate solution of 5 mM.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
