<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Work on small molecular inhibitors of plant origin, several molecules showed high to moderate activity toward 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm. These compounds like Cinnamaldehyde
 <bold>123</bold>, Piperidine 
 <bold>124</bold>, Citral 
 <bold>125</bold>, Furfuradehyde 
 <bold>126</bold>, and Indole 
 <bold>127</bold> showed inhibitory activity toward ergosterol biosynthesis at varying concentrations (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Rajput and Karuppayil, 2013</xref>). A recent study revealed that compound 
 <bold>123</bold> and 
 <bold>124</bold> regulated antifungal activity against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> by ROS mediated apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B165" ref-type="bibr">Thakre et al., 2020</xref>). Similarly, another set of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilm inhibitor Shearinines D and E 
 <bold>(128,129)</bold> derived from 
 <italic>Penicillum species</italic> showed yeast to hyphal blockage. However, it was observed that these compounds are more potent against early biofilm formation than the mature biofilm (
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">You et al., 2013</xref>). Gymnemic acid 
 <bold>130,</bold> a small molecular inhibitor obtained from the leaves of the plant 
 <italic>Gymnema sylvestre</italic>, showed its activity against dual-species 
 <italic>S. gordonii</italic> and 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> together, leading to biofilm formation in the mouth. It decreases the amount of e-DNA present in biofilm. It also inhibits the adhesive property of 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> by inhibiting an enzyme glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase, which is thought to be responsible for the display of adhesion property in 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>albicans</italic> (
 <xref rid="B172" ref-type="bibr">Veerapandian and Vediyappan, 2019</xref>). Similarly, Waikiloid A 
 <bold>131</bold>- a prenylated indole alkaloid and polyketide metabolite Waikialide A
 <bold>132</bold> obtained from a Hawaiian 
 <italic>Aspergillus spp.</italic> both acted as a potent biofilm inhibitor against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> with a IC
 <sub>50</sub> - 1.4 μM and 32.4 μM, respectively (
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
