<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Babu 
  <italic>et al.</italic> (2017)
 </xref> reported that RC leaf extracts exhibit hepatoprotective properties in albino rats and indicate that bioactive compounds are their primary source of efficacy. Our results are similar to 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Toghyani 
  <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)
 </xref>, who reported that broilers supplemented with black seeds (
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic>) and peppermint (
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic>) show no significant differences in the concentrations of serum protein, albumin, triglyceride, LDL, HDL and total cholesterol, SGOT or SGPT. In addition, there was no decrease in laying rate or mortality of the hens. Therefore, an appropriate amount of RC powder supplementation did not adversely affect laying hens. Cells develop nonenzymatic and enzymatic antioxidant systems to limit damage from free radicals and ROS. Enzymatic antioxidants are endogenously synthesized and regulated and are important indicators of the oxidation state of animal tissues (
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lin 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). SOD and CAT are two endogenous antioxidant enzymes that constitute the antioxidant cellular enzymatic system, and act as a first line of defense. SOD catalyzes the dismutation of a superoxide anion (O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>) into hydrogen peroxide (H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>) and an oxygen molecule (O
 <sub>2</sub>) to reduce the damage caused by a superoxide anion. SOD also works in conjunction with CAT, which converts H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> to H
 <sub>2</sub>O (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Ighodaro and Akinloye 2018</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Lee 
  <italic>et al.</italic> (2015)
 </xref> reported that dietary supplementation with 
 <italic>Pleurotus eryngii</italic> stalk residue (PESR) improves the serum antioxidant status as measured by CAT and SOD values, which may be an effect of the flavonoid compounds in PESR. The increased SOD activity in the RC-supplemented feed in our study indicated that phenolic compounds in RC played a role in increasing the level of antioxidant enzymes and enhancing the ability of laying hens to scavenge free radicals and ROS.
</p>
