<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Plant materials</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">Calocedrus decurrens</span> Torr. (California Incense-Cedar), 
  <span class="italic">Cupressus sempervirens </span>L. (Mediterranean or Italian Cypress) and 
  <span class="italic">Tetraclinis articulata</span> (Vahl) Mast. (Cartagena Cypress) were collected from El-Orman Garden, Giza, Egypt on April 2012, at the flowering period. The identity of the plants was kindly verified by Terase Labib, General Manager and Specialist of Plant Taxonomy in El-Orman Botanical Garden, Giza, Egypt. Voucher specimens were deposited in the Department of Pharmacognosy, Faculty of Pharmacy, Al -Azhar University, Cairo, Egypt. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Preparation of the essential oil</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils were prepared from the fresh aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">C. decurrens, C. sempervirens </span>and
  <span class="italic"> T. articulata </span>(500 g) by hydro distillation using Clevenger-type apparatus. The oils were dried over anhydrous sodium sulphate and stored in sealed glass vials at 4-6 
  <span class="sup">o</span>C prior to analysis. Percentage yields were determined according to Egyptian Pharmacopoeia 1984 (
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>). Percentage yields and physical properties of the essential oils are illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">GC/ MS analysis of the essential oil</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The prepared essential oils were subjected to GC/MS analysis using Shimadzu GC//MS – QP 5050 A, fitted with a DB-1 fused silica capillary column (30 m, 0.53 mm ID, 1.51 µM film thickness). Software Class 5000. searched library: Wiley 229 LIB. Carrier gas: Helium (flow rate 1 mL/min.). Ionization mode: EL (70 ev). Temperature program: 40 
  <span class="sup">0</span>C (static for 2 min) then gradually increasing at a rate of 2 
  <span class="sup">0</span>C/min up to 250 
  <span class="sup">0</span>C (static for 7.50 min). Detector temperature 250 
  <span class="sup">0</span>C. Injector temperature 250 
  <span class="sup">0</span>C.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Identification of the essential oil</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compounds were identified by comparison of their retention indices (RI), obtained on a non-polar DB-1 column relative to C5- C24 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes, with those provided in the literature, in addition to Library searched data base Willey 229LIB and by comparing mass fragmentation patterns with those of the available references and with published data (
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>-
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>). The percentage composition of the essential oils was determined by computerized peak area measurements. Results were calculated as mean values after two injections for each essential oil. Results are presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">Tables 2</a>,
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">3</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Test organisms</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pure strains of bacteria (
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> ATCC 13709, 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</span> ATCC 35984, 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus pyogenes </span>ATCC 19615
  <span class="italic">,</span>
  <span class="italic">Eschrechia coli</span> ATCC 9637,
  <span class="italic"> Klebsiella pneumoniae</span> ATCC 1705,
  <span class="italic"> Proteus vulgaris </span>ATCC 8427,
  <span class="italic"> Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> ATCC 27853 and
  <span class="italic"> Shigella boydii</span> ATCC 9905) as well as pure strains of
  <span class="italic"> Candida albicans</span> ATCC 10231, 
  <span class="italic">Candida glabrata</span> ATCC 90030, 
  <span class="italic">Candida krusei</span> ATCC 14243 and 
  <span class="italic">Candida parapsilosis </span>ATCC 22019 were used. All micro-organisms were kindly supplied from the Microbiology Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, Al-Azhar University, Nasr City, Cairo, Egypt.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Testing for antimicrobial activities </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (MICs) were determined using the broth microdilution method (
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>, 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>). Determination of antimicrobial activities against yeast was achieved by microdilution method using serial dilutions of the essential oils (0.008–64.00 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL), which were prepared in 96-well microtiter plates by microdilution method using RPMI-1640 media (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) buffered with MOPS (Sigma). The antibacterial activities were determined by serial dilutions of the essential oils (0.03–128.00 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL, DMSO) in Mueller–Hinton broth (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany). Test yeasts or bacteria strains were suspended in media and the cell densities were adjusted to 0.5 McFarland standards at 530 nm wavelength using a spectrophotometeric method. Inoculums (0.1 mL) were added to the microtiter plates, which were incubated in a humid atmosphere at 30 °C for 24–48 h (yeast) or at 37 °C for 24 h (bacteria). In addition, positive (medium with inoculums but without essential oil) and negative (Uninoculated medium, 200 μL) growth controls were prepared. The growth in each well was compared with the growth in the control well. MICs were visually determined and defined as the lowest concentration of the essential oil produced ≥ 50% growth inhibition for fungi and ≥95% growth reduction for bacteria compared with the growth in the control well. Each experiment was performed in triplicate. Gentamycin (Sigma-Aldrich, Steinheim, Germany) and nystatin (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) in concentration range (0.001- 64.00 µg/mL, sterile distilled water) were used as standard antibacterial and antifungal drugs, respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, media from wells with fungi showing no visible growth were further cultured on Sabouraud dextrose agar (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) and from wells with bacteria showing no visible growth on Mueller-Hinton agar (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) to determine the minimum fungicidal concentrations (MFC) and minimum bactericidal concentrations (MBC).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Statistical Analysis </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results were expressed as the mean ± standard deviation; statistical analysis of experimental results were based on the analysis of variance method. Differences were considered statistically significant at the level of P &lt; 0.001.</p>
</sec>
