<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The use of essential oils to control many diseases and their effective usage as antimicrobial agents (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>-
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>) in addition to their use as functional ingredients in foods, drinks, toiletries and cosmetics is gaining momentum, both for the growing interest of consumers in ingredients from natural sources and also because of increasing concern about potentially harmful synthetic additives (
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>). Essential oils are complex mixture of natural compounds, mostly of plant origin, extremely volatile and with an intense odour. Even if they represent only a small fraction of the plant from which they are derived, they give the whole plant the characteristic of aromatic smell for which these plants are employed by drug, food and perfume industries (
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>). The species that show the largest content of essential oils belong to many families as Asteraceae, Lamiaceae, Apiaceae, Rutaceae, Lauraceae, Myrtaceae, Magnoliaceae, Pinaceae and Cupressaceae (
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>-
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Family Cupressaceae is a common ornamental plants, cultivated around the world, and particularly in South America, Mediterranean basin and North Africa, It is the most widely distributed of all gymnosperm families, occurring in diverse habitats on all continents. Cupressaceae is also the most important conifer family in modern horticulture, members of this family are important for their timber, resin, fruit and as ornamentals (
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>-
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several species belonging to family Cupressaceae have been used in folk medicine as astringent, antiseptic, pulmonary antiseptic, antispasmodic, lymphatic tonic, antibacterial, antihemorrhagic, capillary protector, antipyretic and pelvic decongestant (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>). Many biologically active compounds have been reported from Cupressaceae species such as essential oils, diterpenes, flavonoids, and sterols (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>). 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genus 
  <span class="italic">Cupressus</span> comprising about 20 species;
  <span class="italic"> Cupressus sempervirens </span>L. commonly known as Cypress and known in Arabic as Sarȗ, Sarw, Serwal, Sharbin and Shagaret el Hayat (
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>), is native to eastern North America (
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>) and grown in Egypt as ornamental tree. The essential oil of the leaves of the plant cultivated in Alexandria, Egypt was studied; the main oil constituents were cedrol (21.29%), δ-3-carene (17.85%) and α-pinene (6.90%) and proved to have antimicrobial activities (
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>). Essential oil of the aerial parts of
  <span class="italic"> Cupressus sempervirens </span>cultivated in Safx, Tunisia was studied, 24 compounds were identified, where α-pinene (37.14%), δ-3-careen (19.67%) and R (+)-limonene (5.43%) were the main oil constituents, the oil exhibited a significant antimicrobial activities (
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Calocedrus decurrens</span> (Incense Ceder) is a tree native to Oregon and California, known for its aromatic wood and manufacturing of pencils (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>)]. Heartwood essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. decurrens</span> was studied, it was found that 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-cymene and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-menthane derivatives were the main components (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>). Von Rudloff (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>) reported that leaf oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. decurrens</span> from the pacific northwest, USA, was dominated by limonene (31.31%), δ-3-carene (21%) and α-pinene (9.2%) while Robert &amp; Sanko (
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>) proved that the oils of 
  <span class="italic">C. decurrens</span> from two populations in Oregon and one disjunct population in southern California were high in δ-3 carene (15.20%- 20.00%), limonene (18.21-23.62%), α-pinene (8.7-15.8%), terpinolene (5.72- 8.01%), α-fenchyl acetate (3,5- 9.71%) and cedrol (0.8- 1.2%) (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>,
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Tetraclinis articulata</span> (Cartagena Cypress, known in Arabic as Ahrar, Berbouch and Megloub (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>) is an endemic species of North Africa, Malt and Spain (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>). Various parts of this tree are used in folk medicine for its multiple therapeutic effects, it is mainly used against childhood respiratory and intestinal infections (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>)], gastric pains, diabetes, hypertension and used as antidiarrheal, antipyretic, diuretic, antirheumatic and oral hypoglycemic (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>-
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>). Twenty-seven compounds were detected in Algerian 
  <span class="italic">T. articulata</span> leaves, bornyl acetate (52.11%), caryophyllene (7.51%), germacrene D (5.61%) and caryophyllene oxide (5.01%) were the major components, the oil exhibited antifungal (
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>), antibacterial (
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>), antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fifty-Six compounds were detected in Tunisian 
  <span class="italic">T. articulata</span> plant, where α-pinene (31.32%), linalool acetate (18.18%), alloaromadendrene (7.55%) and γ-caryophyllene (4.16%) were the major constituents in the oil prepared by hydrodistillation method, the oil exhibited antioxidant activities (
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>, 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The main objective of this study was to identify the chemical composition of the essential oils from the aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">C. decurrens</span>, 
  <span class="italic">C. sempervirens</span> and 
  <span class="italic">T. articulata</span> cultivated in Egypt, and to determine their antimicrobial activities, in an attempt to contribute to the use of these essential oils as alternative products.
 </p>
</sec>
