<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Skiophytic plants grow in moist and shaded areas and their photosynthesis is adapted to low illumination [
 <xref rid="pone.0237952.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Skyiophytes have shown optimal growth at light intensities between 200–300 μmol photons m
 <sup>-2</sup> s
 <sup>-1</sup> or 10–15% of full sunlight. At light intensities greater than 500 μmol photons m
 <sup>-2</sup> s
 <sup>-1</sup>, photoinhibitory symptoms have been reported, including a decrease in the rate of photosynthesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0237952.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In order to improve the bio-yield and active ingredient content of herbs, economic and effective actions should be carried out during planting according to plant characteristics such as adjusting light intensities [
 <xref rid="pone.0237952.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0237952.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The effects of light irradiation levels on essential oil yield and composition in plants such as sage and basil have been well documented. Shading strongly reduced the total essential oil content of basil and inhibited the accumulation of eugenol, linalool and 1,8-cineole [
 <xref rid="pone.0237952.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, moderate shading (45% full sunlight) promoted sage highest essential oil content while full sunlight benefited the biosynthesis of myrcene [
 <xref rid="pone.0237952.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Some researchers suggested that shading leads to reduced essential oil content [
 <xref rid="pone.0237952.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], but less attention has been paid to the relation of light irradiation and essential oil composition and precursor metabolites. In addition, how skiophyte plants respond to high light levels with regard to the biosynthesis of essential oil has been less explored. This study was conducted to investigate the effects of light irradiation on photosynthesis and essential oil accumulation and composition in the skiophyte plant 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>heterotropoides</italic> var. 
 <italic>mandshuricum</italic>
</p>
