<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The resource value of the grease of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae has been demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. A total of 1200 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae can digest 1248 g of fresh cow dung by bioconversion in 21 days, and 15.8 g of biodiesel can be extracted from the grease of such larvae. When larvae were used to convert 1 kg of chicken manure, 1 kg of pig manure and 1 kg of cow dung, the amount of crude grease extracted by petroleum ether was 95.5 g, 60.4 g, and 38.2 g, respectively, which accounted for 30.1%, 29.1%, and 29.9% of the total biomass of the 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae, respectively. The physicochemical properties of the crude grease of larvae are as follows: lodine value (the amount of unsaturation in fatty acids), 96 ± 2.4 gL/100 g; acid value, 8.7 ± 0.4 mg KOH/g; saponification value, 157.5 ± 6.2 mg KOH/g; melt point, 5 ± 0.3 °C; and peroxide value, 0.03 ± 0.01 meq/kg grease [
 <xref rid="B112-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. The physical and chemical fuel properties of biodiesel largely depend on the fatty acid distribution of the triglycerides used in the production. The fatty acid composition of larvae fed cow dung is enriched in myristic acid, palmitoleic acid, palmitic acid, oleinic acid, linolenic acid, stearic acid, and other acids [
 <xref rid="B112-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. Compared with biodiesel converted from rapeseed oil [
 <xref rid="B112-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>] and with reference to the EU biodiesel standard (EN14214), the parameters of the biodiesel converted from the crude grease of larvae fed on chicken manure, cow dung, pig manure, dairy manure, and restaurant waste met the standard and exhibited higher oxidation resistance [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. Seven days after feeding 1000 larvae 1 kg kitchen waste, 64.9 g of larvae dry matter was obtained. After subsequent refining, 23.6 g of biodiesel with an ester content of 96.9% was obtained, and the fuel performance of this biodiesel almost met the EU biodiesel standard [
 <xref rid="B113-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. Experimental studies have indicated that 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> can effectively convert kitchen waste and rice straw into organic matter containing polypeptides by co-biotransformation and that the resulting crude grease can be refined into biodiesel that meets the EU biodiesel standard [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. The grease from larvae has been used to replace traditional grease sources in feed formulations without adverse effects on animal performance and product quality [
 <xref rid="B94-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>]. When the grease of this insect was used to substitute soybean oil in the diets for broiler chickens, the productive performance, carcass traits, and overall meat quality were found to be satisfactory [
 <xref rid="B116-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>]. Similarly, when grease from 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> was provided as dietary grease to juvenile Jian carp, satisfactory results were obtained except for a decrease in lipid deposition in the intraperitoneal fat tissue of Jian carp [
 <xref rid="B118-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>].
</p>
