<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0015">A study conducted on 1099 patients (926 non-severe and 173 severe) from 30 provinces of China from December 11, 2019, to January 29, 2020, revealed that dominant clinical manifestations of SARS-CoV-2 infection include fever, cough, fatigue and sputum production. While, symptoms such as shortness of breath, myalgia, sore throat, headache, chills, are common, whereas the gastrointestinal symptoms such as vomiting and diarrhea along with anosmia and hypogeusia are rare in pateints (
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2020</xref>). Later, meta-analysis of total 43 studies from the period of January 24, 2020, to February 28, 2020, including 3600 patients conducted by 
 <xref rid="bib0054" ref-type="bibr">Fu and others (2020)</xref>, ascertains that fever, cough, and fatigue are most frequent, while congestion, sore throat, rhinorrhea, and diarrhea are uncommon clinical manifestations of SARS-CoV-2. Moreover, lymphocytopenia, and increased lactate dehydrogenase, C-reactive protein levels and ground-glass opacities are other common abnormalities among patients. Furthermore, the comprehensive study also suggests this novel SARS-CoV-2 affects elderly people with coexisting other medical complications more seriously. These results are consistent with previous studies conducted on severely ill patients which also advocates high mortality rate in elderly people with acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and comorbidities such as hypertension, diabetes, chronic obstructive lung disease and coronary heart disease (
 <xref rid="bib0253" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020a</xref>). The most common complications associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection are sepsis, respiratory and heart failure, ARDS, and septic shock (
 <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020a</xref>). Even though children of all ages face risk of SARS-CoV infection, the serious progression of infection and morbidity is rare in children and adolescents relative to the adults (
 <xref rid="bib0129" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2020a</xref>).
</p>
