<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The following strains of bacteria were used: 
 <italic>Enterobacter agglomerans</italic> ATCC 27155, 
 <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> ATCC 29212, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 25922, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 53218, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> 10, 28, 128, and 1249 MR multi-resistant strains isolated from clinical cases (donated by the clinical analysis laboratory of the CUSI of the FES Iztacala, UNAM). 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 27853, 
 <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic> ATCC 19430, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 12398, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213 (donated by the Microbiology Laboratory of FES-Cuautitlán), 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> 48, 75, and 83 MR multiresistant strains isolated from clinical cases (donated by the clinical analysis laboratory of the CUSI of the FES Iztacala, UNAM). 
 <italic>Bacillus subtillis, Enterobacter aerogenes, S. epidermidis, Yersinia enterocolitica</italic> (donated by the Clinical Analysis Laboratory of FES Iztacala), 
 <italic>Y. enterocolitica</italic> (isolated from a clinical case and donated by Hospital Angeles Metropolitano), 
 <italic>Proteus mirabilis, Serratia marcences, Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, 
 <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> (isolated from a clinical case), 
 <italic>V. cholerae</italic> INDRE 206 (isolated from polluted water), and 
 <italic>V. cholerae</italic> (clinical strain pertaining to 01 group, Inaba serotype, El Tor biotype, and enterotoxin producer). These strains were maintained at 4 °C in Mueller Hinton agar (Bioxon), submitted to sensitivity tests (multidiscs Bigaux) and were subcultured twice prior the bioassays. The yeasts tested were: 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> ATCC 10231, 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> ATCC 14065, 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> isolated from a clinical case (donated by the Clinical Analysis Laboratory of FES Iztacala), 
 <italic>C. albicans, C. glabrata</italic>, and 
 <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> (isolated from a clinical case and donated by Hospital Angeles Metropolitano). The stock culture was maintained on potato dextrose agar (PDA) and subcultured twice prior the bioassays. 
</p>
