<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_TOXREP1047 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEgr6 jpg ?><?FILEgr7 jpg ?><?FILEgr8 jpg ?><?FILEga1 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 jpg ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?FILEsi2 svg ?><?FILEsi3 svg ?><?FILEsi4 svg ?><?FILEsi5 svg ?><?FILEsi6 svg ?><?FILEsi7 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Toxicology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2214-7500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7848610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2214-7500(21)00015-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2021.01.015</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Regular Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Reduction of anoxia-induced bioenergetic disturbance in astrocytes by methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> and <italic>in silico</italic> evaluation of the effect of its antioxidative constituents on excitotoxicity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0005"><name><surname>Saliu</surname><given-names>Ibrahim Olabayode</given-names></name><email>ibrofina@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0010"><name><surname>Bhagat</surname><given-names>Reshma</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0015"><name><surname>Ojo</surname><given-names>Olubukola Benedicta</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0020"><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>Afolabi C.</given-names></name><email>acakinmoladun@futa.edu.ng</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0025"><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>M. Tolulope</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0030"><name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>Pankaj</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0035"><name><surname>Rema</surname><given-names>Velayudhan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Department of Biochemistry, School of Sciences, The Federal University of Technology, Akure, 340001, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Department of System and Cognitive Neuroscience, National Brain Research Center (NBRC), Manesar, Haryana, 122052, India</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Neurovirology Section, Department of Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience, National Brain Research Centre (NBRC), Manesar, Haryana, 122052, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding authors at: Department of Biochemistry, School of Sciences, The Federal University of Technology, Akure, 340001, Nigeria. <email>ibrofina@gmail.com</email><email>acakinmoladun@futa.edu.ng</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0005"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="fig0045" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="ga1"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="lis0005"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0005">Aridanin, scopoletin, naringenin and ferulic acid were identified in methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (TT) by HPLC-DAD.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0010">TT demonstrated high antioxidant activity and radical scavenging ability <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0015">TT maintained cellular redox status, viability and mitochondrial membrane potential.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0020">Aridanin, from TT has a good binding affinity with glutamine synthetase <italic>in silico</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0025">TT optimized glutamine synthetase so as to attenuate the severity of excitotoxicity.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0015"><p>Oxidative stress and excitotoxicity are some of the pathophysiological abnormalities in hypoxia-induced brain injury. This study evaluated the intrinsic antioxidant property of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (TT), traditionally used for managing brain diseases such as cerebral infarction in West Africa, and its ability to protect primary astrocytes from anoxia-induced cell death. The effect of the phytochemicals present in TT on excitotoxicity was assessed <italic>in silico</italic>, through docking with human glutamate synthetase (hGS). Chromatographic and spectrophotometric analyses of TT were performed. Primary astrocytes derived from neural stem cells were treated with TT and its effect on astrocyte viability was assessed. TT-treated astrocytes were then subjected to anoxic insult and, cell viability and mitochondrial membrane potential were evaluated. Molecular docking of hGS with detected phytochemicals in TT (aridanin, naringenin, ferulic acid, and scopoletin) was performed and the number of interactions with the lead compounds, aridanin, analyzed. HPLC-DAD analysis of TT revealed the presence of various bioactive phytochemicals. TT demonstrated notable antioxidant and radical scavenging activities. TT also protected astrocytes from anoxic insult by restoring cell viability and preventing alteration to mitochondrial membrane integrity. Aridanin, naringenin, ferulic acid, and scopoletin demonstrated good binding affinities with hGS indicating that <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> is a potential source of new plant-based bioactives relevant in the therapy of neurodegenerative diseases.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic></kwd><kwd>Astrocyte</kwd><kwd>Hypoxia</kwd><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>Binding affinity</kwd><kwd>Glutamine synthetase</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><p id="misc0005">Edited by DR. A.M Tsatsaka</p></notes></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="par0030">Reactive oxygen species (ROS) are produced within the body due to normal metabolic activities and its harmful effects are counteracted by endogenous antioxidants. The imbalance between free radical production and antioxidant defense results in oxidative stress which causes deregulation of cellular functions and cause the development of various disease conditions. Oxidative stress has been implicated in various neurodegenerative diseases such as ischemic stroke and cerebral hypoxia [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>].</p><p id="par0035">Mitochondria, an important source of ROS in most cells [<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and their integrity is therefore of utmost importance. During oxidative phosphorylation, ATP synthase uses mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP) to produce ATP [<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. MMP provides the driving force for the production of cellular energy in the mitochondria, making ATP a compound buffering MMP. In hypoxic conditions, oxidative phosphorylation is halted, ATP generation is arrested and this leads to mitochondrial dysfunction [<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p id="par0040">Cerebral hypoxia is the reduction of cerebral oxygen and it is a part of physiological events involved in cerebral ischemic stroke [<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Oxidative stress as a result of hypoxia causes mitochondrial dysfunction characterized by reduction in mitochondrial mass, change in membrane potential and change in oxidative proteins activities [<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Cerebral hypoxia leads to various physiological dysfunctions such as oxidative stress and excitotoxicity, which culminate in the death of neuronal and non-neuronal cells [<xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In cerebral ischemia, excitotoxicity which is characterized by an increase in glutamate level accompanied by a decrease in glutamine level is observed. The decrement in the amount of glutamine has been explained to be due to the inhibition of glutamine synthetase [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Excitotoxicity induced marked expression of several pro-oxidant enzymes or mediators and therefore, alter brain synaptic plasticity and causes neurological dysfunction [<xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Glutamine synthetase catalyzes the condensation of glutamate and ammonia to form glutamine in an ATP-dependent mechanism [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] in other to mop up excess glutamate. Glutamine synthetase is highly expressed in astrocytes compared to other cells in the central nervous system [<xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p id="par0045">Astrocytes are vital housekeeping non-neuronal cells of the central nervous system [<xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. They perform a plethora of functions to maintain brain homeostasis. They scavenge the release of neurotransmitters during synaptic action, control the homeostasis of ions and water, release neurotrophic factors, transport metabolite and waste products, and participate in blood-brain barrier formation [<xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Breakdown of one or more of these astrocytes functions will either alone or in combination with other cell dysfunction, constitute a threat to neuronal survival [<xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Therefore, astrocytic cultures can be a useful model in determining whether the detrimental effects of anoxia can be overcome with therapeutic interventions.</p><p id="par0050"><italic>In</italic> vitro models of neurological diseases have been reported to be useful for investigating the effects of preventive or therapeutic treatments on brain cells directly in both animal and human cultured cells [<xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p id="par0055">Natural products such as medicinal plants contain pharmacologically active secondary metabolites [<xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. These secondary metabolites are antioxidats and can safely interact with free radicals to stop the chain reaction that leads to damage of biomolecules through several mechanisms [<xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>].</p><p id="par0060"><italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> fruit is effective for treating cerebral ischemia [<xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. It is found in the lowland forest of tropical Africa such as Nigeria, Ghana, and Uganda, and has been traditionally used for managing brain diseases [<xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Its stem, bark, root, leaves, and fruits have various medicinal and nutritional properties [<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The medicinal effects of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> plants have been ascribed to the presence of polyphenol components such as phenols, flavonoids and saponins [<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>]. The fruit of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> has been shown to have antihypertensive, anticonvulsive, and cognitive enhancing properties [<xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>].</p><p id="par0065">We hypothesized that the methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (TT) could be beneficial in scavenging free radicals and inhibiting lipid peroxidation that are implicated in cerebral ischemia and may probably be mechanisms used in protecting astrocytes from ischemia-induced mitochondrial biogenetic dysfunction.</p><p id="par0070">Anoxic condition (chronic hypoxia) was employed in this study to mimic the oxygen deprivation in the situation of cerebral ischemia. In cerebral ischemia, the infarct zone has an ischemic core where the death of neurons is detected but the penumbra region (surrounding the ischemic core) does not immediately experience cell death and can be salvageable. In this study, we evaluate the antioxidative potential of TT to mitigate anoxia-induced bioenergetic disturbance in primary astrocytes, as well as examine the role of its phytoconstitutents to optimize human glutamate synthetase (hGS) in abating excitotoxicity through molecular docking.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Chemicals</title><p id="par0075">Bovine serum albumin (BSA), 2,3,5-triphenyl-1,3,4-triaza-2-azoniacyclopenta-1,4-diene chloride (TPTZ), thiobarbituric acid (TBA), ammonium molybdate, 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), 2,2&#x02032;-Azino-bis(3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) (ABTS), neocuproine, potassium ferricyanide, Trolox, sodium nitroprusside, 3-(4, 5-dimethylthiazolyl-2)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) and 5,59,6,69-tetrachloro-1,19,3,39-tetraethylbenzimidazolyl-carbocyanine iodide (JC-1) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). All other materials employed in this study were analytical grade and were purchased from standard suppliers within Nigeria.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Plant material and preparation of TT</title><p id="par0080"><italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> fruits were obtained in the afternoon of April 2016 at the Department of Botany and authenticated at the same Department of Botany, Obafemi Awolowo University, Ile-Ife, Nigeria, in a geographical coordinates 07&#x000b0;30&#x02032;59.46&#x02033; North and 04&#x000b0;31&#x02032;42.82&#x02033; East (Voucher number: IFE17720). The fruits were sundried (65 % humidity), powdered and 600 g was soaked for 72 h in 70 % methanol with constant stiring at every 12 h. It was then sieved with a cloth of 100 &#x003bc;m pore size and further filtered with Whatman filter paper no. 1. The filtrate was concentrated in a rotary evaporator and further concentrated to dryness to obtain the extract (TT). The percentage yield of the extract was 11.6 % of dried plant material. It was dissolved in distilled water and DMSO for biological activity and cell culture experiments, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>2.3</label><title>HPLC-DAD quantification of compounds in methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (TT)</title><p id="par0085">Compounds were quantified in TT using High Performance Liquid Chromatography-Diode Array Detector (HPLC-DAD) according to the previous method by Saliu et al. [<xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Evaluation of <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant activity</title><p id="par0090">All experiments were run in triplicate and absorbance of the antioxidant assays were taken on a UV&#x02013;vis spectrophotometer. Half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) of TT from the antioxidant assays was calculated using the inverse logarithmic method.</p><sec id="sec0035"><label>2.4.1</label><title>DPPH radical scavenging assay</title><p id="par0095">The DPPH radical scavenging ability of TT was estimated using the method of Senguttuvan et al. [<xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. This assay is based on the ability of polyphenol compounds to scavenge and neutralize DPPH radicals by donating one electron to the radical molecule [<xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. DPPH radical solution (0.1 mM) was prepared in methanol and 0.5 mL was added to 0.5 mL of different concentrations of TT (10&#x02212;100 &#x003bc;g/mL). The mixture was incubated in the dark at room temperature for 30 min. A control reference contained methanol instead of TT for baseline correction. After incubation, the absorbance (Abs) was taken at 517 nm. Ascorbic acid served as a standard antioxidant.<disp-formula id="eq0005"><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>D</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><label>2.4.2</label><title>ABTS radical cation decolorization assay</title><p id="par0100">The ability of TT to scavenge free radical was also determined by ABTS radical cation decolorization assay according to the method of Re et al. [<xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. It is based on the ability of polyphenol compound to neutralize ABTS cation radicals by donating one electron to the radical molecule [<xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. ABTS radical was produced by reacting 7 mM of ABTS and 2.45 mM potassium persulfate (1:1,v/v) and incubated in the dark at room temperature for 14 h. ABTS<sup>&#x000b7;+</sup> solution was then diluted with 80 % methanol to obtain an absorbance of 0.700 at 734 nm. Then, 100 &#x003bc;l of different concentrations of TT or Trolox (12.5 &#x003bc;g/mL &#x02013; 100 &#x003bc;g/mL) was added to 2 mL of diluted <sup>&#x02022;</sup>ABTS<sup>&#x000b7;+</sup> solution and the resulting mixture was incubated in the dark for 10 min and the absorbance (Abs) was taken at 734 nm. Control reference contained only ABTS<sup>&#x02022;</sup><sup>+</sup> solution without TT for baseline correction. Percentage ABTS cation radical inhibition was calculated from the formula:<disp-formula id="eq0010"><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>2.4.3</label><title>Hydroxyl radical scavenging activity</title><p id="par0105">Hydroxyl (OH) radicals scavenging activity of TT was determined using the method described by Adjimani and Asare [<xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. It is based on the ability of phytocompound to scavenge OH radicals by donating an electron to the radical molecule [<xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The Fenton reaction mixture was prepared by adding 0.2 mL FeSO<sub>4</sub>.7H<sub>2</sub>O (10 mM), 0.2 mL EDTA (10 mM), 0.2 mL 2-deoxyribose (10 mM) and 1.2 mL phosphate buffer (0.1 M, pH 7.4). Then, 0.2 mL of different concentrations of TT or mannitol (12.5 &#x003bc;g/mL &#x02013; 100 &#x003bc;g/mL) were added, followed by the addition of 0.2 mL hydrogen peroxide (10 mM) and incubated for 4 h at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C. To the incubated mixture, TCA (1 mL, 2.8 % w/v) and TBA (1 mL, 1 % w/v) were added and further incubated in boiling water for 10 min. Thereafter, it was allowed to cool at room temperature and then, centrifuged at 4000 rpm for 4 min. A control reference that contained all solution except TT for baseline correction was used. The absorbance (Abs) was measured at 532 nm against a blank solution.<disp-formula id="eq0015"><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>H</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec0050"><label>2.4.4</label><title>Ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) assay</title><p id="par0110">Benzie and Strain [<xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] method was followed for determining FRAP value of TT. This assay is based on the diminution of ferric iron-TPTZ complex (Fe<sup>3+</sup>-TPTZ) by antioxidants to its ferrous form [<xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. This reduction is monitored spectrohotometrically by measuring the change in absorbance at 593 nm. FRAP reagent solution containing 300 mM acetate buffer, 10 mM TPTZ in 40 mMHCl, 20 mM FeCl<sub>3</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O (10:1:1, respectively) was prepared. FRAP reagent (3 mL) was mixed with 100 &#x003bc;L TT (1 mg/mL) and incubated for 30 min incubation at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C. The absorbance was then taken at 593 nm and FRAP value was extrapolated from a linear graph of FeSO<sub>4</sub> and expressed as mmol Fe<sup>2+</sup> equivalents per g dry weight.</p></sec><sec id="sec0055"><label>2.4.5</label><title>Cupric ion reducing antioxidant capacity (CUPRAC) assay</title><p id="par0115">CUPRAC assay was performed according to the method described by Apak et al. [<xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The ability of antioxidants to reduced Cu<sup>2+</sup> to Cu<sup>+</sup> in the presence of neocuproine [<xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The reduction is spectrohotometrically monitored at 593 nm. Copper(II) chloride (1 mL, 0.01 M), neocuproine (1 mL, 0.0075 M), and 1 M NH<sub>4</sub>CH<sub>3</sub>COO solution were added together. Then, 400 &#x003bc;L of TT (1 mg/mL) or freshly prepared Trolox solution of varying concentrations was added and diluted with 700 &#x003bc;L of deionized water. The mixture was incubated at room temperature for 30 min and the absorbance was taken at 450 nm. CUPRAC of TT was calculated with a molar extinction coefficient of 1.67 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> L mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for Trolox using the formula:<disp-formula id="eq0020"><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>U</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>R</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>E</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>V</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>v</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula>Where absorbance of sample is the absorbance of TT.</p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><label>2.4.6</label><title>Albumin anti-denaturation assay</title><p id="par0120">Albumin anti-denaturation assay was carried out according to the method described by Sakat et al. [<xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The ability of polyphenols to hinder heat-induced protein denaturation was examined here. A reaction mixture containing 200 &#x003bc;L of 1 % bovine serum albumin (BSA) and 1 mL of varying concentrations of TT or ascorbic acid (as standard) was prepared, and the pH adjusted using 1 N HCl. The mixture was initially incubated at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C for 20 min, then also at 60<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C for another 20 min, allowed to cool and the turbidity was measured at 660 nm. The control contained distilled water instead of TT or ascorbic acid. The percentage albumin denaturation inhibition was calculated as follows:<disp-formula id="eq0025"><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>P</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec0065"><label>2.4.7</label><title>Lipid peroxidation assay</title><p id="par0125">The assay for lipid peroxidation was carried out according to Ohkawa et al. [<xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. This is a spectrophotometry assay that is based on the ability of polyphenol to inhibit peroxidation of polyunsaturated fatty acids of biological membrane through inhibiting the formation of thiobarbituric acid reactive substances, TBARS [<xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The excised brain of Wistar rat was homogenized in ice-cold 0.1 M phosphate-buffered saline (PBS, 10 %) and centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 10 min to obtain the brain supernatant. To 0.5 mL of the brain supernatant, 0.5 mL of TT or ascorbic acid of different concentrations (12.5&#x02212;200 &#x003bc;l of 1 mg/mL) and 0.05 mL of freshly prepared FeSO<sub>4</sub> (0.071 mM) were added, vortexed, and incubated at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C for 30 min. After incubation, 1.5 mL of 0.8 % TBA in 1.1 % sodium dodecyl sulfate was added followed by another incubation at 95<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C for 1 h. It was allowed to cool and then centrifuged at 3000 rpm and the absorbance was taken at 532 nm. The control contained methanol instead of TT or ascorbic acid.<disp-formula id="eq0030"><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>x</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0070"><label>2.5</label><title>Evaluation of the effect of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> methanol fruit extract on astrocytes derived from Neural Stem Cells subjected to anoxia</title><sec id="sec0075"><label>2.5.1</label><title>Differentiation of primary human astrocytes from Neural Stem Cells</title><p id="par0130">Astrocytes derived from human induced pluripotent stem cell (hiPSC) were used for this experiment. Human fetal brain tissue was procured following the informed consent of the mother. The brain tissues were processed according to approval by the Institutional Human Ethics and Stem Cell and Research Committee of National Brain Research Centre, India, in compliance with the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR). The telencephalon of human aborted fetuses (10&#x02013;15 weeks old) was used to isolate fetal Neural Stem Cells (fNSCs). Isolation and differentiation of fNSCs to astrocytes were done as described by Fatima et al. [<xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and Bhagat et al. [<xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].</p><p id="par0135">Briefly, isolated neural stem cells (NSCs) were cultured in poly-<sc>d</sc>-lysine (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) coated culture dishes in neurobasal media (Invitrogen, San Diego, CA, USA). The media was supplemented with Neural Survival Factor-1, N2 supplement, bovine serum albumin, glutamine, 25 ng/mL basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF), 20 ng/mL epidermal growth factor (EGF), penicillin and streptomycin solutions, and gentamycin. The expression of neural stem cell markers, SRY-Box Transcription factor 2 (SOX2) and Nestin, and lineage-specific markers, Glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) and microtubule-associated protein 2 (MAP2) were assessed for NSCs characterization using western blotting and immunocytochemistry. Almost 99 % of fNSCs showed immunoreactivity towards SOX2 and Nestin, and were negative for both GFAP and MAP2. Differentiation of NSCs into astrocytes was achieved by withdrawing neurobasal media and growing NSCs in miminum essential medium (MEM) supplemented with 10 % fetal bovine serum (FBS). Cells were maintained in MEM with FBS for atleast 21 days before using them for the experiments. Following trypsinization at the confluency of 80&#x02013;90 %, cells were seeded for experiments in 8 well chamber slides or 12 well plates.</p></sec><sec id="sec0080"><label>2.5.2</label><title>Astrocytes counting and seeding</title><p id="par0140">The prepared astrocytes were counted to know the number of cells per volume of the media. Briefly, 10 &#x003bc;L of the cell was added onto a hemocytometer and viewed under the microscope for cell counting. The population of cells was then calculated:</p><p id="par0145"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>m</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>h</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>l</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>g</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>c</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>o</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>e</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula></p><p id="par0150">For the 12 well plates, 100,000 cells were seeded; and for the 8 well chamber slide, 20,000 cells were seeded.</p></sec><sec id="sec0085"><label>2.5.3</label><title>Induction of anoxia in astrocyte culture</title><p id="par0155">Severe hypoxic condition (anoxia) was set by flushing the hypoxia chambers with a gas mixture of &#x0223c;0.2 % oxygen (replaced with 94.9 % nitrogen) and 5.1 % carbon dioxide [<xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], while normoxia chambers were maintained at 18.0 % oxygen and 5.1 % carbon dioxide and 76.9 % nitrogen, with a pressure of 1.75 bar for both conditions.</p><p id="par0160">Viable but activated astrocytes were analyzed morphologically using the live/dead assay.</p><sec id="sec0090"><label>2.5.3.1</label><title>Assessment of astrocyte viability by live/dead assay</title><p id="par0165">The live/dead assay is used for assessing cell viability/death and was carried out using a live/dead viability/cytotoxicity assay kit for mammalian cells (Invitrogen Detection Technologies, Thermofisher, UK) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. This method is used for assessing cell viability/death in live cell culture of cells. It uses two components, namely; Calcein AM (CaAM), which is component A and Ethidium homodimer-1 (EthD-1), which is component B. Dead cells are characterized by intense fluorescence at over 600 nm and little fluorescence around 530 nm.</p><p id="par0170">Astrocytes seeded in an 8-well chamber slide were allowed to adhere and grow to confluence for 14 h at 37 &#x000b0;C in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. Thereafter, cells were placed in a normoxic or severe hypoxic condition for 3 and 6 h. After 3 and 6 h, 100 &#x003bc;L of EthD-1 (1 &#x003bc;L/mL) and CaAM (0.2 &#x003bc;L/mL) were separately prepared in cell media (MEM), added to the cells, and then, incubated at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C for 10 min. Fluorescent images of the cells were taken at excitation/emission(ex/em) wavelength of 495 nm/515 nm for the green filter (live cells) and ex/em wavelength of 495 nm/635 nm for the red filter (dead cells) using an Invitrogen Floid microscope (Fisher Scientific, Sweden). Percentage cell death was calculated to get the number of dead cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0095"><label>2.5.4</label><title>Determination of cytotoxicity of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> on astrocyte cell culture</title><p id="par0175">Astrocytes were seeded onto a 24 well-plate (Corning Flat Bottom Transparent Polystyrol well plate) at a density of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well and were allowed to stay for 14 h at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. The cells (n = 3) were treated for 24 h with 0.5, 1 and 10 &#x003bc;g/mL of TT dissolved in 0.01 % DMSO in the culture medium. Treatment with DMSO (0.01 % v/v culture medium) alone serves as the control. Thereafter, MTT assay was carried out.</p><p id="par0180">MTT is a colorimetry method used for assessing cell viability and cytotoxicity for drug screening [<xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The MTT assay is based on the reduction of MTT (yellow colored) due to the activity of NAD(P)H-dependent oxidoreductase [<xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p><p id="par0185">After 24 h of astrocyte treatment with the extract, 10 &#x003bc;l of MTT working solution (5 mg/mL) was added and then incubated in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator for 3 h at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C. The medium was removed, and the formazan crystals formed were dissolved by adding 200 &#x003bc;l of DMSO and incubated in the dark inside a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator for 1 h at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C. Finally, the purple color of the dissolved formazan crystals was quantified in a plate reader (Infinite 200Pro Tecan, Switzerland) at 650 nm.</p></sec><sec id="sec0100"><label>2.5.5</label><title>Evaluation of the viability of astrocyte treated with methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> after anoxia induction</title><p id="par0190">Cells (astrocytes) were seeded in a 24 well-plate at a density of 5 * 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well (n = 3) and allowed to stay for 14 h at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. Treatment with TT was performed 4 h before exposure to either 3 h normoxic (normoxia) or anoxic (anoxia) conditions. Two concentrations of TT (1 &#x003bc;g/mL and 10 &#x003bc;g/mL) were used and the treatments were as follows: cells treated with 1 &#x003bc;g/mL TT prior to anoxia (anoxia + TT 1 &#x003bc;g/mL); cells treated with 10 &#x003bc;g/mL TT prior to anoxia (anoxia + TT 10 &#x003bc;g/mL); cells treated with 10 &#x003bc;g/mL TT prior to normoxia (normoxia + TT 10 &#x003bc;g/mL). DMSO was used as a vehicle for TT.</p><p id="par0195">After treatment, MTT assay was carried out to determine the percentage cell viability as previously described. Each assay was repeated twice.</p></sec><sec id="sec0105"><label>2.5.6</label><title>Measurement of mitochondrial membrane potential of astrocytes after anoxia induction</title><p id="par0200">The mitochondrial membrane potential (MMP) was measured by staining astrocytes with JC-1 (5,59,6,69-tetrachloro-1,19,3,39-tetraethylbenzimidazolyl-carbocyanine iodide) according to the method of Korenic et al. [<xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].</p><p id="par0205">JC-1 is a ljipophilic and cationic dye that exhibits a fluorescence emission shift upon aggregation from 530 nm (green monomer) to 590 nm (red &#x0201c;J-aggregates&#x02019;&#x02019; monomer). In healthy cells with high MMP, JC-1enters the mitochondrial matrix in a potential-dependent manner and forms aggregates.</p><p id="par0210">Cells were seeded into groups as previously described. After treatment, cells were stained with 2.5 mg/mL JC-1 at 37<sup>&#x000ba;</sup>C for 15 min. Thereafter, cells were rinsed three times with PBS and the dye was allowed to equilibrate at room temperature for another 10 min before imaging using an Invitrogen Floid microscope (Fisher Scientific, Sweden). Stained polarized mitochondria were detected with red fluorescence while the loss of mitochondrial integrity was detected with green fluorescence. The fluorescence was read on a plate reader (Infinite 200Pro Tecan, Switzerland) with an excitation wavelength of 485 nm and the absorbance at 530 nm and 590 nm. The JC-1 fluorescence values were first normalized separately to their respective controls for red and green signals before the relative MMP was calculated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0110"><label>2.6</label><title>Molecular docking</title><p id="par0215">Docking study was carried out in order to examine the activity of some phytcompounds in TT against excitotoxicity. Pathophysiological mechanisms observed in cerebral ischemic stroke are multifactorial and involve both neuronal and non-neuronal cell dysfunction [<xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>]. An important target enzyme in the pathway is glutamine synthetase [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Glutamine synthetase (GS) catalyzes the biosynthesis of glutamine from glutamate and ammonia. In the human brain, GS regulates excitotoxicity by converting neurotoxic glutamate (cause of excitotoxicity) to harmless glutamine with simultaneous hydrolysis of ATP [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><sec id="sec0115"><label>2.6.1</label><title>Selection of protein and ligands</title><p id="par0220">The 3D structure file of the identified target protein, human glutamine synthetase, hGS (<xref rid="fig0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>), was retrieved from RCSB Server in the PDB format (PDB ID: 2ojw; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org" id="intr0005">www.rcsb.org</ext-link>).</p><p id="par0225">Out of the compounds that were quantified from TT by HPLC, the most abundant phytochemical compounds from four different classes of phytoconstituents, namely, aridanin (saponin), ferulic acid (phenolic acid), naringenin (flavonoid), and scopoletin (coumarin) were selected as ligands (except aridanin which was selected based on the premise that it is a marker compound of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic>). Their structures were adapted from PubChem NCBI database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/" id="intr0010">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/</ext-link>), with ID number 73146, 1548883, 932, and 5280460, respectively (<xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). The structures were delineated by ACD/ChemSketch 11.0 software and the MOL format of these ligands were generated. The structure of the ligands were brought to a ground state and PDB format generated by Avogadro 1.2 software.</p></sec><sec id="sec0120"><label>2.6.2</label><title>Optimization and docking of protein and ligand</title><p id="par0230">Human glutamine synthetase was optimized for protein-ligand interaction studies by deleting all hetero atoms, ligands, and water molecules using Chimera software. The protein and ligands were loaded onto PyRx software in preparation for docking. The amino acid residue in the binding pocket, which includes the active site of hGS [<xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] was selected along with the ligands and toggled to set the grid parameters. The three-dimensional affinity grid parameters were set at 19.120, -13.908, -34.861 (x, y, z respectively) on the geometric center of the target protein and 40.177, 35.676, 36.044 (x, y, z respectively) as dimensions (&#x001fa;). Autodock vina from PyRx was used in docking the ligands into the binding pocket of the protein to get the binding energy data. Protein-ligand complex was generated using PyMol software in PDB format, the complex was uploaded on &#x0201c;Protein-Ligand Interaction Profiler (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://projects.biotec.tu-dresden.de/plip-web/plip" id="intr0015">https://projects.biotec.tu-dresden.de/plip-web/plip</ext-link>)&#x0201d; and analyzed for the number of interactions formed [<xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0125"><label>2.7</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="par0235">All data were presented as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD). One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by post hoc Tukey&#x02019;s test was used for data analysis. Statistical significance was considered at values of p &#x0003c; 0.05. The statistical package used was GraphPad Prism 6 software (Graph Pad Software Inc., San Diego, CA, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0130"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec0135"><label>3.1</label><title>Phytoconstituents</title><p id="par0240">The analysis of compounds identified from the HPLC-DAD chromatogram of TT (Supplementary data) is presented in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. It revealed the presence of isoliquiritigenin, naringenin, butein, scopoletin, aridanin, ferulic acid, echinocystic acid, umbelliferone, octodrine, piperazine and hentriacontane in TT. These compounds can be categorized into flavonoids, saponins, coumarins and phenolic acids. The most abundant phytochemical present was scopoletin (11.13 mg/g) and the least abundant were octodrine and isoliquiritigenin (0.17 and 0.12 mg/g, respectively).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>HPLC-DAD quantified phytochemicals.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0045">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Standard compound</th><th align="left">Standard retention time</th><th colspan="2" align="left">Methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (TT)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left">Area (mUA)</th><th align="left">(mg/g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Ferulic acid</td><td align="left">1.27</td><td align="left">1099.6020</td><td align="left">1.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Echinocystic acid</td><td align="left">2.52</td><td align="left">852.1330</td><td align="left">1.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Umbelliferone</td><td align="left">2.75</td><td align="left">1.384.0905</td><td align="left">1.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Piperazine</td><td align="left">4.45</td><td align="left">164.7690</td><td align="left">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Aridanin</td><td align="left">4.70</td><td align="left">285.5670</td><td align="left">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Octodrine</td><td align="left">5.47</td><td align="left">132.5145</td><td align="left">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Scopoletin</td><td align="left">11.05</td><td align="left">8866.8670</td><td align="left">11.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hentriacontane</td><td align="left">12.17</td><td align="left">3123.0645</td><td align="left">3.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Naringenin</td><td align="left">13.70</td><td align="left">1581.5080</td><td align="left">1.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Butein</td><td align="left">17.62</td><td align="left">225.0670</td><td align="left">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isoliquiritigenin</td><td align="left">19.77</td><td align="left">93.3595</td><td align="left">0.12</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0140"><label>3.2</label><title>Antioxidant activity of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic></title><p id="par0245">Antioxidant activity profile of TT shown in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> indicate the robust ability of TT to scavenge DPPH radicals (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a), ABTS radicals (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b), and hydroxyl radicals (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>c), as well as inhibit lipid peroxidation (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>a) and denaturation of albumin by heat (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>b) <italic>in vitro</italic> in a concentration-dependent manner. <xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> showed the antioxidant activity, inhibition of lipid peroxidation, and inhibition of heat-induced denaturation of protein albumin of TT in the tests in terms of its half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) in comparison with reference standards. TT demonstrated appreciable antioxidant activity with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 20.96 &#x000b1; 0.65, 47.03 &#x000b1; 0.97, 20.63 &#x000b1; 0.68 and 47.36 &#x000b1; 0.67 for DPPH radical scavenging activity, ABTS radical scavenging activity, hydroxyl radical, and lipid peroxidation inhibitory activity, respectively, compared with the IC<sub>50</sub> values of reference standards ascorbic acid (15.36 &#x000b1; 0.29), Trolox (39.88 &#x000b1; 0.52), mannitol (11.06 &#x000b1; 0.87) and quercetin (45.61 &#x000b1; 0.56), respectively. The IC<sub>50</sub> of TT in the CUPRAC and anti-denaturation assays were 32.08 &#x000b1; 1.22 and 26.76 &#x000b1; 0.21, respectively, compared with the value of trolox (9.7553 &#x000b1; 0.89) and ascorbic acid (12.15 &#x000b1; 0.21), respectively, which were still appreciable. The FRAP value of the extract was 117.81 &#x000b1; 4.066 mM Fe/mg dry weight while the TEAC value was 2.89 &#x000b1; 0.451 mM Trolox/mg dry weight.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Scavenging activity of TT <italic>in vitro</italic>. (a) Percentage DPPH radical scavenging activity of TT; (b) Percentage ABTS<sup>&#x02022;</sup><sup>+</sup> radical scavenging activity of TT; (c) Percentage hydroxyl radical scavenging ability of TT. Each bar represents the mean &#x000b1; SD of three replicates. TT: Methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic>; DPPH: 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl; ABTS: 2,2&#x02032;-Azino-bis(3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Inhibitory activity of TT against lipid peroxidation and protein denaturation. (a) Percentage lipid peroxidation inhibitory effect of TT in rat brain homogenate; (b) Percentage inhibitory effect of TT on denaturation of albumin. Each bar represents the mean &#x000b1; SD of three replicates. TT: Methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera.</italic></p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>IC<sub>50</sub> values of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> methanol fruit extract in <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant tests.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0050">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2">Antioxidant tests</th><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2">TT IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th><th colspan="2" align="left">Reference standard<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Compound</th><th align="left">IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">DPPH</td><td align="left">20.96 &#x000b1; 0.65<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">Ascorbic acid</td><td align="left">15.36 &#x000b1; 0.29<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">ABTS<sup>&#x02022;</sup><sup>+</sup></td><td align="left">47.03 &#x000b1; 0.97<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">Trolox</td><td align="left">39.88 &#x000b1; 0.52<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hydroxyl radical</td><td align="left">20.63 &#x000b1; 0.68<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">Mannitol</td><td align="left">11.06 &#x000b1; 0.87<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">CUPRAC</td><td align="left">32.08 &#x000b1; 1.22<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">Trolox</td><td align="left">9.76 &#x000b1; 0.89<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">LPO</td><td align="left">47.36 &#x000b1; 0.67<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">Quercetin</td><td align="left">45.61 &#x000b1; 0.56<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Protein anti-denaturation</td><td align="left">26.76 &#x000b1; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">Ascorbic acid</td><td align="left">12.15 &#x000b1; 0.21<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD (n = 3). IC<sub>50</sub> was calculated using the inverse logarithmic method. Values with the same letter across a row are not significantly different (p &#x0003c; 0.05). TT: <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> methanol fruit extract; DPPH: 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl; ABTS: 2,2&#x02032;-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid); CUPRAC: Cupric ion reducing antioxidant capacity; LPO: Lipid peroxidation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0145"><label>3.3</label><title>Cell death after anoxia</title><p id="par0250">The survival rate of astrocytes following anoxic conditions (severe hypoxia) is shown in <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>. When astrocytes were subjected to anoxia for 3 h (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a), the cell death was 15 % compared to normoxia (p &#x0003c; 0.01), and when the severe hypoxic exposure was for 6 h, 55 % of astrocytic cell death occurred (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>b) compared to that in the normoxia condition (p &#x0003c; 0.01). With 3 h anoxia exposure, a larger number of astrocytes with altered star shape were observed suggesting that they were morphologically impaired live cells. Therefore for further experiments, the 3 h anoxia where cells were morphologically impaired with less cell death was used because it was important to have morphologically impaired viable cells to test the neuroprotective property of TT.<fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Measure of astrocyte survival following hypoxic treatment. (a) Effect on survival of astrocytes after 3 h exposure to (i) normoxicor (ii) anoxic conditions. (b) Effect on survival of astrocyte after 6 h of (i) normoxic or (ii) anoxic conditions. Each bar is expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD (n = 3). Significance with student <italic>t</italic>-test indicated **p &#x0003c; 0.01. All the cells that appeared red (bright or dull) are dead cells while most of the green cells are live cells. Some cells which appeared green but had round shape were counted as dead cell because the round shape indicated that cells were dying. Green cells with altered star-shape were the astrocytes that have lost their morphology and were counted as live cells.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="par0255">All the cells that appeared red (bright or dull) are dead cells while most of the green cells are live cells. Some cells which appeared green but had round shape were counted as dead cell because the round shape indicated that cells were dying. Green cells with altered star shape were the astrocytes that have lost their morphology and were counted as live cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec0150"><label>3.4</label><title>Cytotoxicity of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> on astrocyte</title><p id="par0260">Cytotoxicity of TT on astrocytes after 24 h of treatment is shown in <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a. Compared with the control (0.01 % DMSO), the three concentrations of TT (0.5 &#x003bc;g/mL, 1.0 &#x003bc;g/mL and 10.0 &#x003bc;g/mL) showed no cytotoxicity (p &#x0003c; 0.05). This implied that the extract did not have deleterious effects on the viability of astrocytes up to10 &#x003bc;g/mL.<fig id="fig0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Effect of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (TT) on cell viability using the MTT method. <bold>(a)</bold> Effect of TT on cell viability of astrocytes. Astrocytes were treated for 24 h with varying concentrations of TT to assess its cytotoxicity using MTT method. There was no cell death observed at all doses. Bars with the same letters are not significantly different (p &#x0003c; 0.05) compared to control. <bold>(b)</bold> Effect of TT pretreatment on the viability of astrocytes after 3 h normoxia and anoxia. A significant increase in viable cells indicated that astrocytes were protected during an anoxic condition when pretreated with TT. Each bar in (a) and (b) is expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD (n = 3). <sup>#</sup>p &#x0003c; 0.05 <italic>vs</italic> normoxia; * p &#x0003c; 0.05 <italic>vs</italic> anoxia. TT: Methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera.</italic></p></caption><alt-text id="at0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0155"><label>3.5</label><title>Effect of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> on cell viability following 3 h anoxia</title><p id="par0265">There was a significant reduction (p &#x0003c; 0.05) in viable astrocytes after 3 h of anoxia treatment compared to control (<xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b). This showed that anoxia may result in a reduction of metabolic activity which could be a contributory mechanism in causing the death of cells. When cells were treated with TT before subjecting them to 3 h anoxic condition, the total number of viable cells was significantly higher (p &#x0003c; 0.05) than untreated cells. This implied that TT protected cells against anoxic injury and death.</p></sec><sec id="sec0160"><label>3.6</label><title>Effect of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> on mitochondrial membrane potential following 3 h anoxia</title><p id="par0270">There was a significant decrease (p &#x0003c; 0.05) in MMP of cells subjected to 3 h anoxia (severe hypoxia) compared to normoxia. This was characterized by marked staining of the &#x0201c;J-aggregate&#x0201d; form of JC- 1 (red fluorescence) with few monomer forms (green fluorescence) of normoxia-exposed cells compared to anoxia-exposed cells (<xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). The difference in the loss of mitochondrial integrity of cells was visible with the loss of red stain (polarized J-aggregates form, &#x0007e; 590 nm excitation) on exposure to anoxic condition. In <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, astrocytes that were treated with 1 and 10 &#x003bc;g/mL TT before anoxia exposure exhibited a marked restoration of MMP (p &#x0003c; 0.05) in JC-1 staining compared to untreated anoxia-exposed astrocytes.<fig id="fig0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Effect of methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> on mitochondrial membrane potential of astrocytes. Each bar is expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD (n = 3). <sup>#</sup>p &#x0003c; 0.05 <italic>vs</italic> normoxia; * p &#x0003c; 0.05 <italic>vs</italic> anoxia. TT: Methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic>. Red stain (polarized J-aggregates form) indicated high mitochondria membrane potential while green fluorescence (monomer form) indicates depolarized (low) mitochondrial membranes. Few/loss of red stain indicated low mitochondria membrane potential.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0025">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><fig id="fig0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Ribbon structure of Chain B from the homologous pentamer (A-E) of human glutamine synthetase (hGS) from RCSB (2ojw). The coloured part represents the funnel-shaped binding pocket.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0030">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><fig id="fig0035"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>3D structure of phytochemical constituent. (a) Scopoletin (pubchem ID: 5280460) (b) Aridanin (pubchem ID: 73146) (c) Ferulic acid (pubchem ID: 1548883) (d) Naringenin (pubchem ID: 932). Red balls: Oxygen atoms; White balls: Hydrogen atoms; Grey balls: carbon atoms; Blue ball: Nitrogen atom.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0035">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0165"><label>3.7</label><title>Molecular docking</title><p id="par0275"><xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows that the 4 ligands (<xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>) possess good binding potential towards hGS. Aridanin showed the best binding potential with a minimum binding energy of -8.6 Kcal/mol, followed by naringenin (-8.3 kcal/mol), scopoletin (-7.1 kcal/mol), and ferulic acid (-6.4 kcal/mol). The binding affinity of the ligands having the lowest RMSD value (zero for upper bound and lower bound RMSD) with hGS showed a good binding pose and was considered and documented. Docking conformation was only analyzed for aridanin because unlike the other compounds, aridanin, a triterpenoid saponin, is a marker compound of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> and it has the best binding affinity with hGS. The result of docking analysis of aridanin from PLIP (<xref rid="fig0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>) explicated its interactions with hGS through the formation of ten hydrophobic interactions with amino acid residues TRP 130, GLU 134, ALA 191, ASN 194, GLN 205, PRO 208, ASN 255 and TYR 336 (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), two hydrogen bonds (H-bonds) with amino acids GLY 132 and SER 257 (<xref rid="tbl0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) and one salt bridge formation with the amino acid residue ARG 319 (<xref rid="tbl0030" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Binding affinity of some phytochemical compounds identified in <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> methanol fruit extract with human glutamine synthetase.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0055">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Ligand</th><th align="left">Binding Affinity (Kcal/mol)</th><th align="left">RMSD upper bound</th><th align="left">RMSD lower bound</th><th align="left">Molecular weight (g/mol)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Aridanin</td><td align="left">&#x02212;8.6</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">659.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Naringenin</td><td align="left">&#x02212;8.3</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">272.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ferulic acid</td><td align="left">&#x02212;6.4</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">194.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Scopolectin</td><td align="left">&#x02212;7.1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">192.17</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Aridanin, a lead compound that is peculiarly isolated from <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> fruit, has the minimum binding energy compared to other phytocompounds. The low value of RMSD (less than 1.5&#x001fa;, it is zero in this case) indicates the accuracy of docking. RMSD: Root mean square deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig0040"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p><bold>(a)</bold> 3D structure of interaction between protein (hGS) and ligand (aridanin); <bold>(b)</bold> 3D structure of interaction between hGS and aridanin showing the participating amino acid residue in the protein binding pocket. In (a) and (b): structure in gold colour represent the ligand (aridanin); blue (light and deep) represent amino acid residues from the binding pocket of the protein (hGS); blue line and blue number 1 and 2 represent hydrogen bond; dash and full yellow line represents salt bridge; dash grey lines in (a) and full grey lines which are numbered 1 to 10 in (b) represents hydrophobic interactions.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0040">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Hydrophobic interaction between hGS and ligand (aridanin).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0060">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S/N</th><th align="left">Amino acid residue with position</th><th align="left">Distance between interacting C-atom (&#x001fa;)</th><th align="left">ID of ligand carbon atom</th><th align="left">ID of protein carbon atom</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">TRP 130</td><td align="left">3.34</td><td align="left">3548</td><td align="left">1298</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">GLU 134</td><td align="left">3.85</td><td align="left">3536</td><td align="left">1341</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">ALA 191</td><td align="left">3.69</td><td align="left">3535</td><td align="left">1862</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">ASN 194</td><td align="left">3.97</td><td align="left">3529</td><td align="left">1882</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">GLN 205</td><td align="left">3.52</td><td align="left">3535</td><td align="left">1989</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">GLN 205</td><td align="left">3.36</td><td align="left">3536</td><td align="left">1990</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">PRO 208</td><td align="left">3.15</td><td align="left">3540</td><td align="left">2016</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">PRO 208</td><td align="left">3.18</td><td align="left">3548</td><td align="left">2015</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">ASN 255</td><td align="left">3.33</td><td align="left">3534</td><td align="left">2448</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">TYR 336</td><td align="left">3.23</td><td align="left">3534</td><td align="left">3223</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The hydrophobic interaction between the amino acids of protein and ligand with the geometry of interaction (distance of interacting atoms). Hydrophobic interaction stabilizes the protein-ligand (hGS-aridanin) complex. C-atom: carbon atom.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0025"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Hydrogen bond between amino acid residue in the binding pocket of human glutamine synthetase (hGS) and aridanin.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0065">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S/N</th><th align="left">Amino acid residue with position</th><th align="left">Distance H-A (&#x001fa;)</th><th align="left">Distance D-A (&#x001fa;)</th><th align="left">Donor Angle</th><th align="left">Protein donor?</th><th align="left">Side chain?</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">GLY 132</td><td align="left">3.68</td><td align="left">4.10</td><td align="left">107.64</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">SER 257</td><td align="left">2.03</td><td align="left">2.98</td><td align="left">170.68</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">Yes</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Distance H-A: Distance between hydrogen and acceptor atoms; Distance D-A: Distance between donor and acceptor atom. Protein donor? Yes indicates protein is the donor group for the interaction. Sidechain? Yes indicates that the hydrogen bond is formed with the amino acid side chain while No indicates otherwise.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0030"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Salt bridge formation between the amino acid residue in the binding pocket of hGS and aridanin.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0070">Table 6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S/N</th><th align="left">Amino acid residue with position</th><th align="left">Distance (&#x001fa;)</th><th align="left">Protein positive</th><th align="left">Ligand group</th><th align="left">Ligand atom</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">ARG 319</td><td align="left">4.37</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">Carboxylate</td><td align="left">3555, 3556</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The protein provides a positive charge for the interaction with the carboxylate group of the ligand to form the salt bridge.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0170"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="par0280">Medicinal plants are emerging as a promising option in the treatment of neurological diseases due to their pharmacologically active phytoconstituents [<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> has a long history of use for the traditional management of neurological diseases in West Africa. Studies have shown that its biological effects include antioxidative and anti-inflammatory properties [<xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] and also, its anticonvulsive [<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and anti-ischemic [<xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] properties. Polyphenols in <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> may act synergistically against ischemia/reperfusion injury through abatement of oxidative stress, lipid peroxidation, and neurochemical dysfunctions [<xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p id="par0285">HPLC-DAD quantification of TT revealed the presence of compounds that are pertinent in treating neurological disorders. Aridanin demonstrated anticonvulsive property by modulating nuerotransmitter and opioid receptors [<xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Cerebral infarct size in the brain of rats following cerebral ischemia was reduced by treatment with ferulic acid through antioxidative and anti-inflammatory effects [<xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] and naringenin regulated the expression of inflammatory molecules to give neuroprotection in rats after focal ischemia [<xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Isoliquiritigenin and scopoletin treatment protected the brain of rats following transient cerebral ischemiic injury through antioxidative, anti-inflammatory, anti-convulsive and mitochondrial modulatory effect [<xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>].</p><p id="par0290">The <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant and various radical scavenging activity of phytoextracts offer an insight into their potential biological effects <italic>in vivo</italic>. The antioxidant property of medicinal plants has been associated with their therapeutic potentials [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,<xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Multiple <italic>in vitro</italic> antioxidant tests such as carried out in this study are often employed to account for several antioxidant mechanisms exhibited by phytochemicals [<xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].</p><p id="par0295">TT demonstrated appreciable radical scavenging and antioxidant activity notably against the highly damaging hydroxyl radical and against lipid peroxidation which is a major culprit in the etiology of many brain pathologies. The effectiveness of TT could be due to the presence of both hydrophilic and lipophilic antioxidants. The performance of TT in the various antioxidant tests with different underlying antioxidative mechanisms highlights its efficacy. Antioxidants play a vital role in reducing oxidative processes. The brain is susceptible to damage by oxidative injury and is also a target of lipid peroxidation owing to its high metabolic rate and high levels of polyunsaturated lipids [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,<xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. As observed in this study, the lipid peroxidation inhibitory and protein anti-denaturation activities of TT shows the ability of TT to prevent oxidative damage to biomolecules. The significant antioxidant activity of TT could be related to its reduction of anoxia-induced bioenergetic disturbance in astrocytes observed in this study.</p><p id="par0300">In the present study, anoxia was employed to mimic the events that leads to changes in biochemical and morphological properties of cells in the penumbra region of ischemic brain and to determine what happens to cell metabolism and viability after chronic oxygen deprivation. The astrocytes were also cultured and placed in an anoxic chamber without removing dissolved glucose. Glucose and other nutrients of cell culture were retained in the cultured media and there was no flow of new media after anoxia. In the penumbra region of the ischemic zone, cross-talk between the neurons and astrocytes is vital for the survival of neurons, so maintaining astrocyte viability is critical. Viability of astrocytes support synaptic modification and neurite outgrowth to compensate for neuron loss during ischemic insult [<xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p id="par0305">Astrocytes death recorded in this study may be as a result of severe hypoxia and acidosis [<xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. No cytotoxicity was observed after astrocytes were treated with TT suggesting that TT is not toxic to the cells at the employed concentrations. Protection of the viability and metabolic activity of astrocytes after treatment with TT and subjecting them to the anoxic condition may be due to the protective action of its bioactive components. This suggests that TT treatment may restore the function of astrocytes to provide trophic and metabolic support for neurons during metabolic brain injury.</p><p id="par0310">Alteration to mitochondrial membrane integrity could cause bioenergetic disturbances and cascade of events leading to cell death [<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Also, MMP contributes to determining the driving force for calcium entry into the mitochondria and the extent of ROS production [<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Under hypoxic condition, the mitochondria of astrocytes like other cells, are vulnerable to the production of free radicals that leads to the reduction in ATP generation which could result in cellular damage as observed in mitochondrial dysfunction [<xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In this study, pretreatment of astrocytes with TT increased the MMP of astrocytes subjected to anoxia probably by increasing the energy capacity of the inner mitochondrial membrane and attenuating oxidative stress. Zorova et al. [<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] posited that the higher the MMP, the higher the synthesis of ATP, since the energy capacity of the inner mitochondrial membrane becomes high. Therefore, a decrease in MMP will cause a reduction in mitochondrial ROS, however, this decrease must not be sustained inappropriately. Sustained inappropriate low levels of MMP could lead to reductive stress which is as detrimental as oxidative stress to mitochondrial homeostasis [<xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].</p><p id="par0315">Needless accumulation of glutamate in the extracellular space (outside neuron, astrocytes and glia cells) is toxic to both neuronal and non-neuronal cell (excitotoxicity) and it may cause various neurological disorders if left unabated [<xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Park et al. [<xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] demonstrated that excitatory amino acid transporter 1, EAAC1, (not glutamate transporter 1) is the glutamate transporter responsible for transportation of glutamate in C6 cell and extracellular accumulation of &#x003b2;-amyloid may lead to decrease in EAAC1 expression which may result to excessive glutamate accumulation seen in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. GS regulates excitotoxicity by converting neurotoxic glutamate (cause of excitotoxicity) to harmless glutamine with concomitant hydrolysis of ATP [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Molecular docking was carried out to examine the role of some of the phytochemical constituents (aridanin, ferulic acid, naringenin, and scopoletin) of TT to improve the activity of human glutamine synthetase (hGS). The binding energy of the ligands to the protein is an indicator of the stability of the ligand-protein complex [<xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,<xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The results indicate the ability of the ligands to improve the activity of hGS. The effectiveness of the ligands is shown by the minimum binding energy in the following order; aridanin &#x0003e; naringenin &#x0003e; scopolectin &#x0003e; ferulic acid.</p><p id="par0320">The improved activity of the protein by ligands could further be confirmed by the formation of hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic interaction [<xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The interaction of aridanin, the marker compound in TT [<xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], with hGS was confirmed through the formation of hydrogen bonds with the formation of hydrophobic interaction and salt bridge in the neighborhood of the hydrogen bond. In this case, the side chain of the polar amino acid (SER257) participated in the hydrogen bond formation which corroborated the findings of Stojanovic and Zaric [<xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Using the following criteria; &#x0201c;H-A distance &#x0003c;2.7 &#x000c5;, D-A distance &#x0003c;3.3 &#x000c5;, D-H-A angle &#x0003e;90&#x000b0; and carbon atoms separated by &#x0003c;3.9 &#x000c5;&#x0201d; SER257 is the only amino acid that is truly interacting with the ligand through hydrogen bonding, whereas, GLY132 is only interacting through hydrophobic contact [<xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,<xref rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Also, the shorter distance of the side chains to the ligand promote the formation of hydrogen bond and this may be due to the closeness of the rings of the ligand to the side chain residue (SER257) of the protein [<xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,<xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Therefore, the interaction of aridanin with hGS may improve its activity by positioning it to effectively condense ammonia and glutamate to form glutamine.</p></sec><sec id="sec0175"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="par0325">Methanol fruit extract of <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> (TT) demonstrate impressive antioxidant activity through scavenging of free radical, and it is not cytotoxic. This study revealed that TT has the potential to assuage excitotoxicity, restore astrocytic viability, and reduce bioenergetic dysfunction/disturbance <italic>via</italic> its antioxidative properties in treating cerebral hypoxic conditions. This study also demonstrated that aridanin from TT could help in optimization of the activity of glutamine synthetase in order to attenuate the severity of excitotoxicity in neurological diseases. Therefore, <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> could potentially be employed as a plant-based agent for the treatment of cerebral astrocytic hypoxia. The findings from the <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in silico</italic> results in this study could be employed for further experiment in translational research.</p></sec><sec id="sec00005"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="par00005"><bold>Ibrahim Olabayode Saliu:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing - original draft, Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Reshma Bhagat:</bold> Validation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Writing - original draft. <bold>Olubukola Benedicta Ojo:</bold> Validation, Formal analysis, Investigation. <bold>Afolabi C. Akinmoladun:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Resources, Writing - review &#x00026; editing, Supervision, Project administration. <bold>M. Tolulope Olaleye:</bold> Resources, Project administration. <bold>Pankaj Seth:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Resources, Supervision. <bold>Velayudhan Rema:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Resources, Writing - review &#x00026; editing, Supervision, Project administration.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="par0330">The authors report no declarations of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sindhi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhaka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential applications of antioxidants &#x02013; a review</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Res.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jopr.2013.10.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ord</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Work</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress and the use of antioxidants in stroke</article-title><source>Antioxidants</source><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox3030472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26785066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anees</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zargar</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masood</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sofi</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganie</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress, mitochondrial dysfunction and neurodegenerative diseases; a mechanistic insight</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>74</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2015.07.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26349970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pisoschi</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of antioxidants in the chemistry of oxidative stress: a review</article-title><source>Eur. J. Med. Chem.</source><volume>97</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2015.04.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25942353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>G.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial dysfunction and oxidative stress in metabolic disorders &#x02014; A step towards mitochondria based therapeutic strategies</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta (BBA) - Mol. Basis Dis.</source><volume>1863</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbadis.2016.11.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saliu</surname><given-names>I.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olowookere</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojo</surname><given-names>O.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farombi</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akindahunsi</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement of 2-Vessel occlusion cerebral ischaemia/reperfusion-induced corticostriatal electrolyte and redox imbalance, lactic acidosis and modified acetylcholinesterase activity by kolaviron correlates with reduction in neurobehavioural deficits</article-title><source>Ann. Neurosci.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000484517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29887685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ojo</surname><given-names>O.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amoo</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saliu</surname><given-names>I.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farombi</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurotherapeutic potential of kolaviron on neurotransmitter dysregulation, excitotoxicity, mitochondrial electron transport chain dysfunction and redox imbalance in 2-VO brain ischemia/reperfusion injury</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>111</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2018.12.144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30841465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How mitochondria produce reactive oxygen species</article-title><source>Biochem. J.</source><volume>417</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19061483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zorova</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popkov</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotnikov</surname><given-names>E.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silachev</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Irina</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jankauskas</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial membrane potential</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>552</volume><issue>01</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2017.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28711444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Lisa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colonna</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambassi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansford</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial membrane potential in single living adult rat cardiac myocytes exposed to anoxia or metabolic inhibition</article-title><source>J. Physiol.</source><volume>486</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1995.sp020786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7562625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vignini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Stroke and oxidative stress</chapter-title><source>Oxidative Stress and Free Radical Damage in Neurology</source><year>2011</year><publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Totowa, NJ</publisher-loc><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-60327-514-9_9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ischemic stroke: experimental models and reality</article-title><source>Acta Neuropathol.</source><volume>133</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00401-017-1667-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28064357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willcox</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Summerlee</surname><given-names>A.J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relaxin protects astrocytes from hypoxia in vitro</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e90864</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeitner</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Battaile</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>A.J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical evaluation of the changes in glutamine synthetase activity in models of cerebral stroke</article-title><source>Neurochem. Res.</source><volume>40</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>2544</fpage><lpage>2556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11064-015-1667-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26233464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vezzani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viviani</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuromodulatory properties of inflammatory cytokines and their impact on neuronal excitability</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><volume>96</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2014.10.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25445483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>H.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bannier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer-Lotz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keilhoff</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>doborowonly</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogerts</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of immunoreactive glutamine synthetase in the adult human and mouse brain. Qualitative and quantitative observations with special emphasis on extra-astrogial protein localization</article-title><source>J. Chem. Neuroanat.</source><volume>61&#x02013;62C</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchemneu.2014.07.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberheim</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotrina</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedergaard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astrocytes and ischemic injury</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>40</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>S8</fpage><lpage>S12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/strokeaha.108.533166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19064795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0090"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Functional Neuroscience</chapter-title><year>2012</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/018751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0095"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astrocyes and brain injury</article-title><source>J. Cereb. Blood Flow Metab.</source><volume>23</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12571445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0100"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baik</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fane</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang-Wei Fann</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>U.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pin1 promotes neuronal death in stroke by stabilizing Notch intracellular domain</article-title><source>Ann. Neurol.</source><volume>77</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25558977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0105"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barthels</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current advances in ischemic stroke research and therapies</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta (BBA) - Mol. Basis Dis.</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbadis.2018.09.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>L.B.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical screening, total phenolics and antioxidant activities of bark and leaf extracts of Goniothalamus velutinus (Airy Shaw) from Brunei Darussalam</article-title><source>J. King Saud Univ. - Sci.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jksus.2015.02.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Proch&#x000e1;zkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bou&#x00161;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelmov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and prooxidant properties of flavonoids</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><volume>82</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2011.01.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21277359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000fc;l&#x000e7;in</surname><given-names>&#x00130;.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of food constituents: an overview I &#x002d9; lhami G&#x000fc; l&#x000e7;in</article-title><source>Arch. Toxicol.</source><volume>86</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00204-011-0774-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22102161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bristi</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafiquzzaman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review on in vivo and in vitro methods evaluation of antioxidant activity</article-title><source>Saudi Pharm. J.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.JSPS.2012.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24936134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0130"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oroian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escriche</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidants: characterization, natural sources, extraction and analysis</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>74</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2015.04.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28411973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0135"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saliu</surname><given-names>I.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amoo</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rema</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abatement of neurobehavioral and neurochemical dysfunctions in cerebral ischemia/reperfusion injury by Tetrapleura tetraptera fruit extract</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>264</volume><issue>113284</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2020.113284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0140"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kemigisha</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Owusu</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elusiyan</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omujal</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tweheyo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosu</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> in Ghana, Nigeria and Uganda: households uses and local market</article-title><source>For. Trees Livelihoods</source><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14728028.2018.1498027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0145"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adesina</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwalewa</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnny</surname><given-names>I.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetrapleura tetraptera Taub-ethnopharmacology, chemistry, medicinal and nutritional values - a review</article-title><source>Br. J. Pharm. Res.</source><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9734/bjpr/2016/26554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0150"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okwu</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potentials of <italic>Ocimum gratissimum, Penrgularia extensa</italic> and <italic>Tetrapleura tetraptera</italic> as spice and flavouring agents</article-title><source>Nigeria Agric. J.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/naj.v34i1.3184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0155"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orwa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutua</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamnadass</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Tetrapleura Tetraptera (Schum. &#x00026; Thonn.) Taubert. Agroforestree Database:a Tree Reference and Selection Guide Version 4.0</chapter-title><comment>Retrieved from</comment><year>2009</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldagroforestry.org/sites/treedbs/treedatabases.asp" id="intr0025">http://www.worldagroforestry.org/sites/treedbs/treedatabases.asp</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0160"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erukainure</surname><given-names>O.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onifade</surname><given-names>O.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Odjobo</surname><given-names>B.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olasehinde</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adesioye</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tugbobo-Amisu</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okonrokwo</surname><given-names>G.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethanol extract of Tetrapleura tetraptera fruit peels: chemical characterization, and antioxidant potentials against free radicals and lipid peroxidation in hepatic tissues</article-title><source>J. Taibah Univ. Sci.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtusci.2017.03.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0165"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ojewole</surname><given-names>J.A.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analgesic and anticonvulsant properties of Tetrapleura tetraptera (Taub) (Fabaceae) fruit aqueous extract in mice</article-title><source>Phytother. Res.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.1779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16372367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0170"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aderibigbe</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwalewa</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adesina</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adebanjo</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ukponmwan</surname><given-names>O.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anticonvulsant, analgesic and hypothermic effects of aridanin isolated from Tetrapleura tetrapetra fruit in mice</article-title><source>J. Biol. Sci.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>1520</fpage><lpage>1524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/jbs.2007.1520.1524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0175"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woode</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amissah</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duwiejua</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleischer</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawer</surname><given-names>I.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of tetrapleura tetraptera (Taub) fruit extract on some isolated tissues: possible mechanism(s) of antihypertensive action</article-title><source>J. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/just.v28i1.33075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0180"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odubanjo</surname><given-names>V.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibukun</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oboh</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adefegha</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aqueous extracts of two tropical ethnobotanicals (Tetrapleura tetraptera and Quassia undulata) improved spatial and non-spatial working memories in scopolamine-induced amnesic rats: Influence of neuronal cholinergic and antioxidant systems</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>99</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2018.01.043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29334662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0185"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senguttuvan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsamy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karthika</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical analysis and evaluation of leaf and root parts of the medicinal herb, Hypochaeris radicata L. For in vitro antioxidant activities</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Trop. Biomed.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>Suppl. 1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>S359</fpage><lpage>S367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12980/apjtb.4.2014c1030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25183112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0190"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veskoukis</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerasioti</surname><given-names>e.</given-names></name><name><surname>Priftis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouka</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spanidis</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouretas</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A battery of translational biomarkers for the assessment of the <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> antioxidant action of plant polyphenolic compounds: the biomarker issue</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Toxicol.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cotox.2018.10.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0195"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Re</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Proteggente</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice-Evans</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity applying an improved ABTS radical cation decolorization assay</article-title><source>Free Rad. Biol. Med.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>9&#x02013;10</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0891-5849(98)00315-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10381194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0200"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adjimani</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asare</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and free radical sacvenging activity of iron chelators</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2015.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28962407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0205"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzie</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ferric reducing ability of plasma (FRAP) as a measure of &#x0201c;&#x02018;Antioxidant power&#x02019;&#x0201d;: the FRAP assay</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>239</volume><year>1996</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0210"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;&#x000e7;l&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zy&#x000fc;rek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c7;elik</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of antioxidant capacity assays and the CUPRAC (cupric ion reducing antioxidant capacity) assay</article-title><source>Microchim. Acta</source><volume>160</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00604-007-0777-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0215"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakat</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Juvekar</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambhire</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In&#x000ad;vitro</italic> antioxidant and anti&#x000ad;inflammatory activity of methanol extract of oxalis corniculata linn</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm. Pharm. Sci.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>155</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0220"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohishi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assay for lipid peroxides in animal tissues by thiobarbituric acid reaction</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>95</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1979</year><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(79)90738-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0225"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devasagayam</surname><given-names>T.P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boloor</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramasarma</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minireview Methods for estimating lipid peroxidation: an analysis of merits and demerits</article-title><source>Indian J. Biochem. Biophys.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22900323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0230"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singal</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel insight into role of miR-320a-VDAC1 axis in astrocyte-mediated neuronal damage in neuroAIDS</article-title><source>GLIA</source><volume>65</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27761954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0235"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhagat</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Narwal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agnihotri</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adlakha</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>mani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika virus E protein alters properties of human fetal neural stem cells by modulating microRNA circuitry</article-title><source>Cell Death Diff.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1837</fpage><lpage>1854</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0240"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays</article-title><source>J. Immunol. Methods</source><volume>65</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6606682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0245"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berridge</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herst</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetrazolium dyes as tools in cell biology: new insights into their cellular reduction</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Ann. Rev.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16216776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0250"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korenic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boltze</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deten</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andjus</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Radenovic</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astrocytic mitochondrial membrane hyperpolarization following extended oxygen and glucose deprivation</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0255"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>E.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hommel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathophysiologic cascades in ischemic stroke</article-title><source>Int. J. Stroke</source><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1747-4949.2012.00839.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22712739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0260"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inose</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activated microglia in ischemic stroke penumbra upregulate MCP-1 and CCR2 expression in response to lysophosphatidylcholine derived from adjacent neurons and astrocytes</article-title><source>Neuropathology</source><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/neup.12182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0265"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meadows</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental models of focal and multifocal cerebral ischemia: A review</article-title><source>Rev. Neurosci.</source><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/revneuro-2017-0076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29397392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0270"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yiang</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>A.P.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current mechanistic concepts in ischemia and reperfusion injury</article-title><source>Cell. Physiol. Biochem.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1650</fpage><lpage>1667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000489241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29694958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0275"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acidosis causes failure of astrocyte glutamate uptake during hypoxia</article-title><source>J. Cereb. Blood Flow Metab.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jcbfm.1995.52</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7713999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0280"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excitotoxicity and stroke: identifying novel targets for neuroprotection</article-title><source>Progress Neurobiol.</source><volume>115</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2013.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0285"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krajewski</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmberg-Schiavone</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlberg</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mowbray</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structures of mammalian glutamine synthetases illustrate substrate-induced conformational changes and provide opportunities for drug and herbicide design</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>375</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2210/pdb2ojw/pdb</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18005987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0290"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salentine</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adasme</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PLIP: fully automated protein-ligand interation profiler</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>W1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>W443</fpage><lpage>W447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25873628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0295"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nandakumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengarajan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palaniswami</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnanadhas</surname><given-names>E.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakshminarasaiah</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishigaki</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidants and human diseases</article-title><source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source><volume>436</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2014.06.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24933428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0300"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ojewole</surname><given-names>J.A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adewunmi</surname><given-names>C.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory and hypoglycaemic effects of Tetrapleura tetraptera (Taub) [fabaceae] fruit aqueous extract in rats</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>95</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2004.06.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15507333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0305"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moukette</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieme</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Biapa</surname><given-names>P.C.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Njimou</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bravi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonkeu Ngogang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro ion chelating, antioxidative mechanism of extracts from fruits and barks of tetrapleura tetraptera and their protective effects against fenton mediated toxicity of metal ions on liver homogenates</article-title><source>Evid.-Based Complement. Altern. Med.</source><volume>2015</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/423689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0310"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>HO</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferulic acid reduces cerebral infarct through its antioxidative and anti-inflammatory effects following transient focal cerebral ischemia in rats</article-title><source>Am. J. Chin. Med.</source><volume>36</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19051339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0315"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of naringenin in experimental ischemic stroke: down-regulated NOD2, RIP2, NF-kB, MMP-9 and up-regulated claudin-5 expression</article-title><source>Neurochem. Res.</source><volume>39</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24842554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0320"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venugopala</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashmi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Odhav</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review on natural Coumarin lead compounds for their pharmacological activity</article-title><source>BioMed Res. Int.</source><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0325"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopal</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UPEI-400, a conjugate of lipoic acid and scopoletin, mediates neuroprotection in a rat model of ischemia/reperfusion</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><volume>100</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28017701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0330"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramalingam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun-Il</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical and pahrmacological role of Liquiritigenin and Isoliquiritigenin from Radix glycyrrhizae in human health and disease models</article-title><source>Front. Aging Neurosci.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>348</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30443212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0335"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falode</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ameliorative property of Kigelia africana crude and flavonoid leaf extracts on aluminum-induced hepatotoxicity in albino rats</article-title><source>Comp. Clin. Pathol.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1495</fpage><lpage>1506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00580-019-03004-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0340"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olugbodi</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tincho</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oguntibeju</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glyphaea brevis &#x02013; in vitro antioxidant and in silico biological activity of major constituents and molecular docking analyses</article-title><source>Toxicol. Vitro</source><volume>59</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tiv.2019.04.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0345"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity and total phenolic content of medicinal plants associated with prevention and treatment of cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases</article-title><source>J. Med. Plant Res.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>2438</fpage><lpage>2444</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0350"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crown</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojo</surname><given-names>B.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farombi</surname><given-names>O.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidenaturation and antioxidative properties of phytochemical components from Spondias mombin</article-title><source>Afr. J. Biochem. Res.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/ajbr2014.0769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0355"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obade</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilesanmi</surname><given-names>O.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crown</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akinmoladun</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaleye</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akindahunsi</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuromodulatory effect of solvent fractions of Africa eggplant (Solanium dadyphyllum) against KCN-induced mitochondria damage, viz. NADH-succinate dehydrogenase, NADH- cytochrome c reductase, and succinate-cytochrome c reductase</article-title><source>Clin. Phytosci.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40816-018-0068-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0360"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danilov</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiskum</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hyperoxia promotes astrocyte cell death after oxygen and glucose deprivation</article-title><source>GLIA</source><volume>56</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.20655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18338792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0365"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zorov</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinnally</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tedeschi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Voltage activation of heart inner mitochondrial membrane channels</article-title><source>J. Bioenerget. Biomembr.</source><volume>24</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf00769538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0370"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0370"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jhee</surname><given-names>K.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.-A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amyloid-&#x003b2; peptides inhibit the expression of AQP4 and glutamate transporter EAAC1 in insulin-treated C6 glioma cells</article-title><source>Toxicol. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>1089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2020.08.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32953460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0375"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0375"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeem</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, antimicrobial and &#x003b1;-glucosidase inhibitory potential of mannich bases of mercapto oxadiazoles and their molecular docking studies</article-title><source>Farmacia</source><volume>66</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31925/farmacia.2018.4.22</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0380"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0380"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro evaluation of the &#x003b1;-glucosidase inhibitory potential of methanolic extracts of traditionally used antidiabetic plants</article-title><source>BMC Complem. Altern. Med.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-019-2482-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0385"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0385"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stojanovic</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaric</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic interactions of porphyrins in porphyrin-containing proteins</article-title><source>Open Struct. Biol. J.</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874199100903010034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0390"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0390"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tidor</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel method for probing the specificity binding profile of ligands: applications to HIV protease</article-title><source>Chem. Biol. Drug Des.</source><volume>71</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18384529</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec0185" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="par0345">The following is Supplementary data to this article:<fig id="upi0005" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="mmc1"/></fig></p></sec><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="par0335">The award of DBT-TWAS sandwich postgraduate fellowship provided by the <funding-source id="gs0005">Department of Biotechnology, Government of India</funding-source>, and <funding-source id="gs0010">The World Academy of Science</funding-source> to Ibrahim O. Saliu (FR number: 3240293151) is greatly acknowledged. Thanks to Tolulope Saliu for assistance on molecular docking. This research was partly supported by <funding-source id="gs0015">NBRC core fund</funding-source>.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="sec0180" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="par0340">Supplementary material related to this article can be found, in the online version, at doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxrep.2021.01.015" id="intr0020">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.toxrep.2021.01.015</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>