<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The saponins of 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> L. have been an object of study as early as the 1930s, but the first data on their structure were provided by K. Hiller et al. in 1975 [
 <xref rid="B106-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. In the 1980s, G. Bader et al. were among the first to isolate and establish the chemical structures of deacylated saponins found in the aerial parts, named by the authors virgaureasponins 1–3 [
 <xref rid="B37-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Around the same time, in Japan, Y. Inose et al. isolated and elucidated, from samples of Japanese origin, the structures of oleanane-type solidagosaponins I-XX, many of them glycosylated in position 16 of the aglycone alone or besides position 3 [
 <xref rid="B51-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], and later the same group further identified solidagosaponins XXI-XXIX [
 <xref rid="B108-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. The same Japanese researchers reported the presence of bellisaponin BA2 [
 <xref rid="B108-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>], which had been isolated previously from 
 <italic>Bellis perennis</italic> L. [
 <xref rid="B109-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Later, another European group isolated virgaureasaponins 4–6 from 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> ssp. 
 <italic>alpestris</italic> [
 <xref rid="B73-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Quantitatively, the saponin content is similar between 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic>, 
 <italic>S. gigantean</italic>, and 
 <italic>S. canadensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B71-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Unlike 
 <italic>S. canadensis</italic> and 
 <italic>S. gigantea</italic>, which are derived from byogenin and have more complex sugar chains, the saponins isolated from 
 <italic>S. virgaurea</italic> are derived from polygalacic acid and are acylated by carboxylic acids [
 <xref rid="B37-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. As for many phytochemicals, some of the saponins have multiple synonyms, sometimes confusing; for instance, solidagosaponin XVIII is also known as virgaureasaponin C [
 <xref rid="B73-biomolecules-10-01619" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
