<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_TOXREP459 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Toxicol Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Toxicology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2214-7500</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5615139</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2214-7500(17)30044-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2017.07.001</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Neuropharmacological profile and chemical analysis of fresh rhizome essential oil of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> (turmeric) cultivated in Southwest Nigeria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oyemitan</surname><given-names>Idris A.</given-names></name><email>oyemix@yahoo.com</email><email>oyemitan@oauife.edu.ng</email><email>ioyemitan@wsu.ac.za</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elusiyan</surname><given-names>Christianah A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Onifade</surname><given-names>Ayoola O.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akanmu</surname><given-names>Moses A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oyedeji</surname><given-names>Adebola O.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>Armando G.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Pharmacy, Obafemi Awolowo University, Ile-Ife, Osun State 220005, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Drug Research and Production Unit, Faculty of Pharmacy, Obafemi Awolowo University, Ile-Ife, Osun State 220005, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Department of Chemical and Physical Sciences, Faculty of Natural Sciences, Walter Sisulu University, Nelson Mandela Drive Campus, Mthatha 5117, South Africa</aff><aff id="aff0020"><label>d</label>Renewable Materials Program, Department of Forest, Rangeland and Fire Sciences, University of Idaho, Moscow, ID 833844-1133, United States</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Pharmacy, Obafemi Awolowo University, Ile-Ife, Osun State, 220005, Nigeria. <email>oyemix@yahoo.com</email><email>oyemitan@oauife.edu.ng</email><email>ioyemitan@wsu.ac.za</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>6</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2017 Published by Elsevier Ireland Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0005"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="fig0030" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p>Twenty three compounds detected include turmerone and &#x003b1;-phellandrene as most abundant constituents.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p>Curlone is reported in essential oil of fresh rhizome from Nigeria for the first time.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p>LD<sub>50</sub> values of this <italic>C. longa</italic> species were 693&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p. and 2154&#x000a0;mg/kg, p.o.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p>The essential oil of this plant demonstrated CNS depressant activity in mice.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0015"><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Curcuma longa</italic> (turmeric) is commonly used as spice and also used to treat fever, cough and febrile convulsions in Nigeria. This study determined the chemical composition of the essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> and evaluated its neuropharmacological activity in mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> (EOCL) fresh rhizome was obtained by hydrodistillation and its chemical composition determined by GC&#x02013;MS. Acute toxicity (LD<sub>50</sub>) profile of the essential oil was determined orally (p.o.) and intraperitoneally (i.p.); and the EOCL (50&#x02013;200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) was evaluated for its behavioural, anxiolytic, sedative and anticonvulsant activities using appropriate models in Albino mice (Vom Strain, Jos, Nigeria).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Analysis of the oil showed the presence of 23 compounds with turmerone (35.9%) being the major component. The LD<sub>50</sub> values obtained for the mice were 2154&#x000a0;mg/kg, p.o., and 693&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.</p><p>The EOCL (50&#x02013;200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) caused significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) inhibition of rearing {F<sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9} and locomotor {F<sub>(3,16)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;42} activity; decreased head dips in hole board {F <sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4}; increased the time spent in the open arms of the elevated pus maze {F <sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9}; prolonged total sleeping time {F <sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21} induced by ketamine injection, and protected mice against pentylenetetrazol-induced convulsions.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The major component of the essential oil of this <italic>C. longa</italic> species was turmerone; the oil was slightly toxic orally but moderately toxic intraperitoneally in mice; exhibited significant anxiolytic, sedative and anticonvulsant activities in mice.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Turmeric</kwd><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd>Turmerone</kwd><kwd>Behavior</kwd><kwd>Acute toxicity</kwd><kwd>Sedative</kwd><kwd>Anticonvulsant</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>The current trend in natural product research involves identifying and validating plant derived substances used ethno-medicinally in the management of various diseases. Incidentally, essential oils obtained from plant materials have been evaluated extensively for biological activities with promising results. Thus many compounds have been isolated from essential oils with proven potency and providing pharmacological basis for ethno-medicinal uses of several plants. <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>, commonly known as turmeric is a tropical herb, native to southern Asia and some parts of Africa. The aromatic yellow powder from its mature rhizomes is extensively used for imparting colour and flavor to food <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. <italic>Curcuma</italic> spp. is used worldwide for its antioxidant, antispasmodic, anti-inflammatory and antimicrobial properties <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In Southwest Nigeria, the plant especially the rhizome is locally called <italic>Ata il&#x01eb9; pupa</italic>
<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. The rhizome of the plant is normally boiled and sipped but it is also added to other herbal agents to manage several ailments. Its folkloric uses includes the treatment of malaria, jaundice, gastric ulcer, skin diseases, rheumatoid arthritis, diabetes, hypertension, cold and flu symptoms, convulsions and emotional disorders <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p>Several pharmacological properties have been reported for curcumin, a major component of the alcohol extract of <italic>C. longa</italic> and <italic>C. domestica</italic> rhizomes <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. The essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> has been reported to contain monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, alcohols and ketones <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Terpinolene and &#x003b1;-phellandrene have been identified as the predominant constituents of leaf oil of a Nigerian grown <italic>C. longa</italic>
<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, while <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> reported a different chemotype &#x003b1;-tumerone from Southwest Nigeria. The main focus of previous research study was on the anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, anti-diabetic and other nutritional properties of the plant as well as on curcumin, ethanolic extract of the rhizome. However, there has been no report on the central nervous system effects of the plant, this study therefore aimed at evaluating the <italic>in-vivo</italic> neuropharmacological activity, determine the acute toxicity profile and investigate the chemical composition of the essential oil of the studied species since there were different chemotypes of the Nigerian <italic>C longa</italic>. Therefore this study reveals the contribution of the plant&#x02019;s volatile component to its central nervous system activities, toxicological profile and provides rationale for its ethnomedicinal uses.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Plant material: identification and collection</title><p>Fresh rhizomes and leaves of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> were collected at Ondo (Nigeria), identified and authenticated (specimen number Ife-16593) by Mr. G. Ibhanesebhor, a taxonomist, Herbarium Unit, Obafemi Awolowo University (OAU).</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Extraction and analysis of the essential oil</title><p>The fresh rhizomes of <italic>C. longa</italic> (1.5&#x000a0;kg) were hydro-distilled for 4&#x000a0;h using a Clevenger-type apparatus to yield 10.5&#x000a0;g (0.7% w/w) brownish colour essential oil (EOCL) with characteristic pungent smell. The oil was dried over Mg<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and refrigerated until use.</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry analysis of the oils</title><p>EOCL (0.5&#x000a0;mg/mL in CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub>) was analyzed by GC&#x02013;MS (Focus-ISQ, Thermo Scientific). Separation was achieved using a ZB&#x02013;5&#x000a0;ms capillary column (30&#x000a0;m&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;0.25&#x000a0;mm &#x00424;, Phenomenex) and a temperature program of 40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (2&#x000a0;min) ramped to 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (10&#x000a0;m) at 5&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/min. The eluted compounds were identified by determining the Kovat indices, spectral matching with the 2008 National Institute of Standard and Technology (NIST) spectral library and known standard and literatures <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Drugs and reagents</title><p>Diazepam (Valium<sup>(R)</sup> Roche, Switzerland), pentylenetetrazole (Sigma, USA), strychnine (Sigma, Switzerland), ketamine HCL (Alpha Pharm. Nig.), normal saline (Unique Pharm. Nig. Ltd), Tween 80 and other reagents were of analytical grade.</p></sec><sec id="sec0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Laboratory animals</title><p>Swiss-Webster mice (originally sourced from the National Veterinary Research Institute (NVRI, Vom, via Jos, Nigeria) of both sexes (18&#x02013;25&#x000a0;g)) were bred and supplied from the Animal House, Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Pharmacy, OAU. They were acclimatized to the laboratory environment for 1 week, maintained under 12&#x000a0;h light/dark circle at temperature of 25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and housed 5 mice per cage in a Plexiglas cage with wood shavings as beddings. The procedures were carried out between 9.00 and 16.00&#x000a0;h. The animals were fed with standard laboratory food for rodents (Top Feed, Benin-City, Nigeria) and water was made available <italic>ad libitum</italic>, however, feed was withheld overnight prior to the test and during the experiment. For each experiment, a mixture of both sexes was chosen randomly for the treatment groups. The animal experiment was carried out in strict compliance with National Institute of Health NIH, 1985 as being implemented by the OAU Research Committee through the Faculty of Pharmacy Postgraduate Committee.</p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><label>2.6</label><title>Acute toxicity test</title><p>Acute toxicity (LD<sub>50</sub>) of EOCL was determined as described by <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> via both oral and intraperitoneal routes. Three doses (10, 100 and 1000&#x000a0;mg/kg) of emulsified EOCL were administered to three different groups of mice (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3). In the second phase, doses of 1000, 2000, 2900 and 5000&#x000a0;mg/kg (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1) were used for the oral route because there was no mortality at 1000&#x000a0;mg/kg in this route; while 400, 600, 800 and 1000&#x000a0;mg/kg (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1) were used for the intraperitoneal route because there was 100% mortality at 1000&#x000a0;mg/kg in the first phase for this route. The animals were monitored for 2&#x000a0;h and incidence of mortality recorded after 24&#x000a0;h for each group. The LD<sub>50</sub> values were calculated with the following formula:<disp-formula id="eq0005">LD<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x0221a;(A x B),</disp-formula>Where A and B represent maximum non-lethal and minimum lethal doses respectively</p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><label>2.7</label><title>Neuropharmacological studies</title><sec id="sec0050"><label>2.7.1</label><title>General experimental design</title><p>Animals were randomly selected into 5 groups (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5). Group I serve as the negative control and received the vehicle (5% Tween 80, 10&#x000a0;ml/kg) only. Test groups II&#x02013;IV were treated with the EOCL at doses of 50, 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg respectively, while group V (positive control) received diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.). All treatments were by intraperitoneal (i.p.) route and each treatment was administered 30&#x000a0;min prior to test. The oil forms stable emulsion with Tween 80 and was subsequently used in the formulation of the oil while maintaining the concentration of Tween 80 at&#x02009;&#x02264;5% for all the subsequent bioassays.</p></sec><sec id="sec0055"><label>2.7.2</label><title>Open field test (OFT)</title><p>The open field area was constructed of plexiglass box (30&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;30&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;15&#x000a0;cm), with one transparent wall for direct observation, and three opaque walls which prevent distractions and the floor divided into sixteen squares of equal area <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. The OFT was used to evaluate the animal&#x02019;s exploratory activity. The method used was as described by <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> with slight modification. The novelty-induced behavioural effects scored were rearing (number of times the mouse raised its forepaws in the air or against the wall of the cage for 20&#x000a0;min) and locomotion (the number of squares crossed with all the fore and hind limbs within 10&#x000a0;min).</p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><label>2.7.3</label><title>Anxiolytic test</title><sec id="sec0065"><label>2.7.3.1</label><title>Hole board test</title><p>The hole-board is a flat space (field) of 25&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;25&#x000a0;cm<sup>2</sup> with 16 holes (each 3&#x000a0;cm in diameter). Each treated mouse was placed at the center of the hole-board and the number of head dips was recorded for a period of 5&#x000a0;min <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0070"><label>2.7.3.2</label><title>Elevated plus maze</title><p>The elevated plus maze (EPM) used was as described for mice <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> was used to evaluate anxiety in mice. Each mouse was observed after 30&#x000a0;min pre-treatment. Each mouse was placed at the center of the maze facing one of the enclosed arms. Number of entries into and time spent on closed and open arms were recorded for 5&#x000a0;min.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0075"><label>2.7.4</label><title>Hypothermic test</title><p>The rectal temperature of each mouse in all the groups was taken with a digital thermometer (thermoprobe) by inserting the probe 2&#x000a0;cm deep into the anus of the mice shortly before pre-treatment, and after 30 and 60&#x000a0;min post-treatment for all the treatment groups <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0080"><label>2.7.5</label><title>Sedative test</title><p>Animals in each group were pre-treated 30&#x000a0;min prior to ketamine (100&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) injection and immediately dropped inside observation cage <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. The parameters observed were sleep latency (SL), which is the time interval between injection time and loss of righting reflex; the second is the total sleeping time (TST), which is the time interval between loss and recovery of righting reflex <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec0085"><label>2.7.6</label><title>Anticonvulsant test</title><sec id="sec0090"><label>2.7.6.1</label><title>Pentylenetetrazole (PTZ)-induced convulsions</title><p>PTZ was used to induce tonic-clonic convulsions <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. PTZ (85&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) was administered to different groups of mice (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5), which were pretreated with 5% Tween 80, oil (50,100 or 200&#x000a0;mg/kg) or diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg) for 30&#x000a0;min. Each mouse in each group was individually monitored for incidence of convulsions, latency of convulsions, death and mortality. Mice that survived beyond 30&#x000a0;min after PTZ injection were considered protected <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Cut-off time of 1800&#x000a0;s was used for mice that did not convulse or died within 30&#x000a0;min for the purpose of statistical analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec0095"><label>2.7.6.2</label><title>Strychnine induced convulsions</title><p>Strychnine (2&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) was used to induce tonic-clonic convulsions <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Strychnine was administered to different groups of mice (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5) as described in previous section. Each mouse in each group was individually monitored for incidence of convulsions, latency of convulsions, death and mortality. Mice that survived beyond 30&#x000a0;min after strychnine injection were considered protected.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0100"><label>2.7.7</label><title>Statistical analysis of data</title><p>The results were presented in Mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SEM and analyzed using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by post hoc test using Dunnett&#x02019;s test using GraphPad InStat 3 and GraphPad Prism 5. The level of significance was set at 95% confidence interval (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) for all treatment carried out compared to control group. The results of the anticonvulsant tests for percentage mortality or protection were analyzed with Chi square (non-parametric), while the latency to convulsion and time of death after chemo-convulsant treatment were analyzed with ANOVA followed by Dunnett&#x02019;s post hoc test.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec0105"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec0110"><label>3.1</label><title>Chemical composition of the EOCL</title><p>Twenty-three compounds were detected while 21 compounds were fully characterized in the gas chromatogram of EOCL (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The most abundant components were oxygenated sesquiterpenes with tumerone (35.9%), curlone (12.9%), and <italic>ar</italic>-tumerone (10.0%). The monoterpene alcohol 1,8-cineole was found to be 10.3% while the monoterpene hydrocarbon &#x003b1;-phellandrene was 15.5%. The five compounds alone accounted for 84.5% of the oil (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Other minor constituents of EOCL that exceed 1% in composition includes two monoterpenes hydrocarbons; <italic>p</italic>-cymene (2.1%) and terpinolene (3.2%), and two sesquiterpenes hydrocarbons; &#x003b1;-zingiberene (2.0) and &#x003b2;-sesquiphellandrene (1.8%). The relative density of the oil was estimated to be 960&#x000a0;mg/mL.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Chromatogram of essential oil of fresh <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> rhizome.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0210">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl0005" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chemical Composition of essential oil of fresh rhizome of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0235">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Compounds</th><th align="left">MW</th><th align="left">KI</th><th align="left">% Area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-pinene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">933</td><td align="left">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sabinene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">975</td><td align="left">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Myrcene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">992</td><td align="left">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-phellandrene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">1004</td><td align="left">15.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b4;-3-carene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">1010</td><td align="left">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-terpinene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">1016</td><td align="left">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">p-cymene</td><td align="left">134</td><td align="left">1024</td><td align="left">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">D-limonene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">1028</td><td align="left">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1,8-cineole</td><td align="left">154</td><td align="left">1031</td><td align="left">10.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b3;-terpinene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">1060</td><td align="left">0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Terpinolene</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left">1089</td><td align="left">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">terpinen-4-ol</td><td align="left">154</td><td align="left">1179</td><td align="left">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-terpineol</td><td align="left">154</td><td align="left">1192</td><td align="left">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-caryophyllene</td><td align="left">204</td><td align="left">1425</td><td align="left">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unknown</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1450</td><td align="left">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ar</italic>-curcumene</td><td align="left">204</td><td align="left">1487</td><td align="left">0.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b1;-zingiberene</td><td align="left">204</td><td align="left">1498</td><td align="left">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-curcumene</td><td align="left">204</td><td align="left">1512</td><td align="left">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-sesquiphellandrene</td><td align="left">204</td><td align="left">1528</td><td align="left">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unknown</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">1608</td><td align="left">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>ar</italic>-turmerone</td><td align="left">216</td><td align="left">1670</td><td align="left">10.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Turmerone</td><td align="left">218</td><td align="left">1674</td><td align="left">35.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Curlone</td><td align="left">218</td><td align="left">1697</td><td align="left">12.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>KI: kovats index; MW: molecular mass.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0115"><label>3.2</label><title>Acute toxicity effect of EOCL in mice</title><p>The oil caused zero and 100% mortality at 2000 and 2900&#x000a0;mg/kg, p.o., while zero and 100% death was observed at 600 and 800&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p. Hence, the LD<sub>50</sub> values estimated for EOCL were 2154&#x000a0;mg/kg, p.o., and 693&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.</p></sec><sec id="sec0120"><label>3.3</label><title>Effects of EOCL on novelty-induced behaviours in mice</title><p>The EOCL at 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p. significantly (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) decreased rearing {F<sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.4} and at 50&#x02013;200&#x000a0;mg/kg, significantly {p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01; F<sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;24} decreased spontaneous locomotive activity in mice compared to vehicle. Diazepam also caused significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) decrease in rearing and locomotor activity when compared to the negative control (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A&#x02013;B).<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Effects of the EOCL on rearing (Panel A) and locomotor activity (Panel B) in mice.</p><p>Each bar represents mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SEM. VEH, EOCL and DZM represent vehicle (5% Tween 80), essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> and diazepam respectively. N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.</p><p>*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01; compared to control group (ANOVA, Dunnett&#x02019;s test).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0215">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0125"><label>3.4</label><title>Effects of EOCL on anxiety test in mice</title><sec id="sec0130"><label>3.4.1</label><title>Effect of EOCL on head-dipping in mice</title><p>The EOCL (50&#x02013;100&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) dose dependently and significantly (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) increased exploratory head dipping behaviour {F<sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.3} in mice when compared to negative control. However, at 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p., it caused a significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) reduction in the number of head-dips when compared to the vehicle. Diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) used as positive control similarly caused increase in head dipping activity (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).<fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Effect of the EOCl on head-dipping behaviour on the hole board test.</p><p>Each bar represents mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SEM. VEH, EOCL and DZM represent vehicle (5% Tween 80), essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> and diazepam respectively. N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.</p><p>*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, compared to control group, (ANOVA, Dunnett&#x02019;s test).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0220">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0135"><label>3.4.2</label><title>Effects of EOCL on the elevated plus-maze (EPM)</title><p>The time spent in the open arms of the EPM increased significantly (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; F<sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14) with EOCL administration. EOCL at 50, 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p., caused 49, 55 and 56% increase in the time spent in the open arms compared to 33 and 72% for negative and positive controls respectively. The EOLC at 50&#x000a0;mg/kg caused significant (P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) increase in the% number of entries into the open arms compared to negative group (<xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>A&#x02013;B).<fig id="fig0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Effect of the EOCL on percentage number of entries into open arms (Panel A) and percentage time spent on open arms (Panel B) of the epm.</p><p>VEH, EOCL and DZM represent vehicle (5% Tween 80), essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> and diazepam respectively.</p><p>*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01; significant compared to vehicle group (ANOVA, Dunnett&#x02019;s test).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0225">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0140"><label>3.5</label><title>Effect of EOCL on normal rectal temperature of mice</title><p>In the EOCL (100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) treated groups the oil caused significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) decrease in rectal temperature at 30 and 60&#x000a0;min post-treatment. Diazepam, 1&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p., only caused significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) reduction in rectal temperature at 60&#x000a0;min post treatment (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl0010" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The effect of EOCL on rectal temperature variation in mice.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0240">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Treatment (mg/kg, i.p.) (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5)</th><th colspan="3" align="left">Variation in rectal temperature at (&#x000b0;C)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">0&#x000a0;min</th><th align="left">30&#x000a0;min</th><th align="left">60&#x000a0;min</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Control 5%, Tween 80, (10&#x000a0;ml/kg)</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.70</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EOCL 50&#x000a0;mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.48</td><td align="left">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EOCL 100&#x000a0;mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.70<sup>*</sup></td><td align="left">&#x02212;3.12<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">EOCL 200&#x000a0;mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">&#x02212;4.16<sup>**</sup></td><td align="left">&#x02212;2.98<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diazepam 1&#x000a0;mg/kg</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.02</td><td align="left">&#x02212;1.24<sup>*</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spar0085"><p>Each value represents the difference in rectal temperature at different time intervals. EOCL represents essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="spar0090"><p><sup>*</sup>p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, statistically different from vehicle.</p></fn><fn id="spar0095"><p><sup>**</sup>p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, statistically different from other groups (ANOVA, Dunnett&#x02019;s test).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0145"><label>3.6</label><title>Effect of EOCL on ketamine-induced hypnosis</title><p>The EOCL (50&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) caused significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) decrease and at 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p., it caused significant decrease (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) in sleep latency {F<sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;22.89} compared to control; Similarly, at the same dose levels, EOCL induced significant [p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05&#x02013;0.01; F<sub>(4,20)</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21] prolongation of ketamine-induced total sleeping time (<xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A&#x02013;B).<fig id="fig0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Effect of the EOCL on ketamine-induced sleep latency (Panel A) and total sleeping time (Panel B) in mice.</p><p>VEH, EOCL and DZM represent vehicle (control), essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> and diazepam respectively. N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.</p><p>*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 compared to control; **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01compared to other groups (ANOVA, Dunnett&#x02019;s test).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0230">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0150"><label>3.7</label><title>Effect of EOCL chemically-induced convulsions in mice</title><sec id="sec0155"><label>3.7.1</label><title>Effect of EOCL on PTZ-induced convulsions</title><p>EOCL (100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) and diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) completely blocked the PTZ-induced convulsions, prolonged the latency for convulsions and decreased mortality rate (<xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). However, at the lowest dose of 50&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p., there was about 20% protections but there was statistically significant (P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) delay in death time of the mice compared to control (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap id="tbl0015" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effect of the EOCL on pentylene tetrazol-induced convulsions in mice.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0245">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Treatment (mg/kg, i.p., n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5)</th><th align="left">Incidence of convulsions</th><th align="left">% Mortality</th><th align="left">% Protections</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Vehicle (5% Tween 80)</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EOCL 50</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">80</td><td align="left">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EOCL 100</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">100<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">EOCL 200</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">100<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diazepam 1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">100<sup>*</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spar0105"><p>(+) means incidence of convulsions; (&#x02212;) means absence of convulsions.</p></fn><fn id="spar0110"><p><sup>*</sup>p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, statistically different from the control group (Chi square).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl0020" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effect of the EOCL on latency of convulsions and time of death in the pentylene tetrazol&#x02212;induced convulsions.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0250">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Vehicle</th><th colspan="3" align="left">EOCL mg/kg, i.p., n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5,<hr/></th><th align="left">diazepam 1&#x02009;mg/kg,</th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th align="left">50</th><th align="left">100</th><th align="left">200</th><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Onset of Convulsions (s)</td><td align="left">180.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5</td><td align="left">240.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.3</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Death time(s)</td><td align="left">162.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.2</td><td align="left">614.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;26.0<xref rid="tblfn0005" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td align="left">1800.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">#</xref></td><td align="left">1800.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">#</xref></td><td align="left">1800.0<xref rid="tblfn0010" ref-type="table-fn">#</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>(&#x02212;) means absence of convulsions.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0005"><label>*</label><p id="npar0005">p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, statistically different from control.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn0010"><label>#</label><p id="npar0010">p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, statistically different from other groups at the 30&#x000a0;min cut-off time (ANOVA, Dunnett&#x02019;s).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0160"><label>3.7.2</label><title>Effect of EOCL on strychnine-induced convulsions</title><p>In the strychnine-induced convulsions, the test materials including EOCL (50,100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.), 5% Tween 80, and diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) all failed to protect the mice which resulted in mortality.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec0165"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The chemical composition and the chemotype of the essential oil of <italic>C. longa</italic> were established and its neuropharmacological profile assessed for novelty induced behaviour (NIB), anxiolytic, hypothermic, sedative and anticonvulsant activities in mice. The oil was dominated by oxygenated sesquiterpenes, turmerone and manifested remarkable central effects.</p><p>The LD<sub>50</sub> values of the oil were 693&#x000a0;mg/kg (i.p.) and 2154&#x000a0;mg/kg, p.o. The results of the acute toxicity study revealed that the oil is moderately toxic intraperitoneally but slightly toxic orally <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Low oral bioavailability could be responsible for the wide variation in the lethal effect of this oil compare to its effect after intraperitoneal administration as observed in this study and similarly to previous report <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. The implication of this acute toxicity result is that at high doses, the oil could be harmful due to accumulative toxic effect, therefore, its consumption as a spice, condiment, medicinal recipes and flavouring agents should be with caution and closely monitored <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. The intraperitoneal route was used for further tests because the test agent could be subjected to unpredictable metabolism in the gastrointestinal tract <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> and low systemic bioavailability through oral route has been reported for extract of <italic>C. longa</italic>
<xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Furthermore, it has been suggested that the parenteral route is preferable in neuropharmacological tests in order to prevent the biodegradation or inactivation of the test compounds if given through the oral route <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. There is no pharmacokinetic or toxicokinetic data from human studies on the essential oil component of this plant. However, in previous animal study, the essential oil of <italic>L. longa</italic> was found to cause 20% mortality in mice at &#x02265;28&#x000a0;mg/kg/day for 28&#x000a0;days <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Low oral bioavailability could be responsible for the wide variation in the lethal effect of this oil compare to its effect after intraperitoneal administration as observed in this study and similarly to previous report <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. In a clinical trial study, 0.6&#x000a0;ml (&#x02248;0.5&#x000a0;g) of Turmeric oil administered orally thrice daily for 12 weeks produce no clinical, hematological, renal or hepatic-toxicity in the volunteers <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. This report however has the shortcomings of using very few subjects (7) and short duration (12 weeks), which are grossly inadequate statistically and fell short of the minimal standard for chronic studies in humans. Future studies are imperative to evaluate the long term toxicological profile of oral administration of this extract in preclinical and clinical studies.</p><p>Dose-dependent inhibitory effects were observed for all exploratory behaviours. The novelty-induced behaviours including rearing and spontaneous locomotor activity were found to decrease significantly (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) at all the doses used (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A&#x02013;B). It is has been reported in previous studies that CNS depressant suppresses exploration or inquisitiveness of animals and common sedative drugs have inhibitory effects on exploratory behaviours of animals <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Locomotion is believed to be mediated through dopaminergic pathway and other neural mechanisms <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. It can be suggested that the inhibitory effect of the oil of <italic>C. domestica</italic> on novelty-induced behaviour could be mediated through augmentation of GABA neurotransmission in the CNS as reported for some medicinal plants <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Rearing is also associated closely with the excitability of the CNS <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> and since this oil significantly decreased rearing and locomotor activity in this study, central inhibitory activity is suggested.</p><p>It has been reported that anxiolytic drugs increase exploration of the holes <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. It was observed that the EOCL at 50 and 100&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p increased the exploratory head dipping behaviour of the animals, however, at 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p., it decreased head dipping. This observation might likely be due to increased sedative effect of EOCL at higher doses compared to diazepam (standard sedative drug) has been shown to be effective in these models (Rabbani et al., 2003. EOCL also increased% time spent by the animals in the open arms to 49, 55 and 56% as the concentration increases compared to negative control (33%), (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) indicating anxiolytic effect <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>.</p><p>The EOCL at 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p., significantly (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) caused reduction in rectal temperature at 30 and 60&#x000a0;min post treatment compared to negative control or standard agent, diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg) which caused significant effect at 60&#x000a0;min only (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Hypothermia is an effect usually observed with benzodiazepine receptor agonists that produce this effect at relatively low doses hence the use of diazepam <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Hypothermia has been linked with decrease metabolic heat production and/or vasodilation. The hypothalamus has been reported to regulate body temperature, hence it could be suggested that oil may be mediating its hypothermic effect in the hypothalamus through activation of DA-D2 receptor sites <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>.</p><p>Results in <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>(A&#x02013;B) showed that the EOCL (50&#x02013;200&#x000a0;mg/kg) and diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg) caused significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05&#x02013;0.01) reduction in sleep latency (SL), and caused significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05&#x02013;0.01) increase in ketamine-induced total sleeping time (TST), indicating sedative effect <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Ketamine is known to act primarily in the thalamus and limbic systems acting as a non-competitive antagonist of <italic>N</italic>-methyl-<italic>D-</italic>aspartate receptor <italic>(N</italic>M<italic>D</italic>A<italic>)</italic> receptor. Thus the EOCD may be mediating its sedative effect through augmentation of the inhibitory activity on the NMDA receptors in addition to general CNS depression. <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> is a component of herbal preparations used in the treatment of fever and mental disorders in Southwest Nigeria thus giving an insight into the rationale for its use in this region.</p><p>Furthermore, it was observed that EOCL failed to protect against PTZ-induced convulsions at the lowest dose (50&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p), but there was significant (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) delay in time of death compared to negative control (<xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). However, EOCL higher doses (100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.) prevented episodes of convulsions and offered 100% protections comparable to diazepam (1&#x000a0;mg/kg, i.p.). This result indicates that this oil demonstrated significant anticonvulsant effect and may be effective in the management of generalized convulsion such as tonic-clonic and myoclonic convulsions as suggested in other studies <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. The mechanism of action of the anticonvulsant effect of the oil was not evaluated but enhancement or augmentation of GABA<sub>A</sub> neurotransmission in CNS may be involved <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Strychnine-induced convulsions are closely linked with glycine inhibition in the spinal cord and the brain stem. The ability to reduce percentage mortality after seizures is suggestive of some potential usefulness of a drug against neurotoxicity which normally causes death following extensive seizures. However, the oil at all the tested doses failed to protect the mice against the strychnine-induced convulsions indicating that the oil or its constituent(s) may not have significant facilitatory effect on the glycine neural circuit <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. The anticonvulsant result obtained in this study provides additional justification for the use of this plant in treating epilepsy by the traditional medical practitioners. Generally, this study gives further evidence for the contribution of <italic>C. longa</italic> to several CNS activities that have been reported for the plant.</p><p>The chemical analysis of the essential oil by GC&#x02013;MS (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) showed the presence of twenty-three (23) components. Four major classes of compounds were displayed in the chemical profile of the oil which are monoterpenes (24.6%), monoterpenoids (10.9%), oxygenated sesquiterpenes (58.7%) and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (4.8%). The chemical composition of our rhizome oil seems unique when compared to those in literature <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Our results showed marked differences in composition of rhizomes collected from North Central Nigeria in which &#x003b2;-bisabolene (13.9%), <italic>trans</italic>-ocimene (9.8%) and myrcene (7.6%) were identified as the major constituents <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Interestingly, the rhizome oil showed a close similarity with an earlier study conducted on a Southwest, Nigerian grown <italic>C. longa</italic> spp. leaf and rhizome essential oils. However, the lower monoterpenes &#x003b1;-pinene and <italic>p</italic>-cymene and the monoterpene alcohol 1,8-cineol present in our oil were not detected in the previous report <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.</p><p>Although Nigeria has similar climate with India, reports show that the leaf and rhizome oils from India have varying chemical composition <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Studies on <italic>C. longa</italic> from other regions also confirmed substantial variability in their chemical composition which may be associated with climatic and geographical factors <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. There were also global variation in the oil composition of rhizomes from different regions, for instance, &#x003b1;-turmerone (45.3%), linalool (14.9%) and &#x003b2;-turmerone (13.5%) were reported as the main constituent compounds in the oil of the fresh rhizome of Malaysian <italic>C. domestica</italic>
<xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. While &#x003b1;-phellandrene (24.5%), 1,8-cineole (15.9%), <italic>p</italic>-cymene (13.2%) and &#x003b2;-pinene (8.9%) were the major ones in found in the leaf oil of the Vietnam species <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. It is however noteworthy that turmerone or its isomers appears to be present in substantial quantity in most species so far reported but the isomeric curlone is being reported here as a constituent of the essential oil of fresh rhizome from Nigeria for the first time. This report therefore confirms that the Nigerian spp. <italic>C. longa</italic> is unique in its chemical composition compare to either <italic>C. longa</italic> from other regions where &#x003b1;-turmerone (20.1%) and ar-turmerone (68.9%) have been reported to be the major constituents of an Iranian <italic>Curcuma</italic> species <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. The constituent(s) of the oil responsible for the observed neuropharmacological effects could not be ascertained in this study. However, &#x003b1;-phellandrene has been reported to possess both antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effect <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Also, 1,8-cineol which is the major constituent of many essential oils especially, <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic>, has been reported to possess CNS inhibitory activity <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, hypotensive activity in rat <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> and anti-inflammatory activity <xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Moreover, <italic>E. tereticornis</italic> and <italic>E. globulus</italic> essential oils have been reported to contain 60&#x02013;90% of 1,8-cineole <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref> which have also been shown to possess both analgesic and antiinflammatory activities in animals <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Therefore, the prominent components of the oil in the present study, contributed majorly to the central inhibitory activities observed for the oil. In view of the remarkable potentials displayed by the plant, its use in ethnomedicine should further be harnessed. We do not have data concerning the pharmacokinetic of this oil in systemic circulation in humans; hence it is imperative to carry out further studies to unravel this.</p></sec><sec id="sec0170"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>The major constituents of essential oil from the fresh rhizome of <italic>C. longa</italic> in this study included turmerone, &#x003b1;-phellandrene, 1,8-cineole, <italic>ar</italic>-turmerone and curlone. The neuropharmacological studies showed that the essential oil of the plant displayed significant CNS depressant activity, and exhibited hypothermic, sedative, anxiolytic and anticonvulsant properties in mice, thus providing evidence that may support the folkloric application of this extract.</p></sec><sec id="sec0175"><title>Competing interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec0180"><title><bold>Authors</bold>&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Author IAO designed the project in collaboration with authors CAE and MAA; directly carried out all the animal experiments with author AOO; analyzed all the results; prepared the first draft with author AOO and coordinated the editing, revision and processing of the manuscript for publication. Author CAE carried out the oil extraction; analyzed the oil and interpreted the GC/MS results, edited, revised and processed the manuscript for publication. Author AOO carried out all the animal experiments in conjunctions with author IAO; prepared the first draft and analyzed the results together with author IAO. Author MAA participated in the design of the work; crosschecked and proofread the results analyses and the manuscript. Authors AOO edited the manuscript. Author AGM provided both the standard and the facility for the analysis of the oil, and also edited the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec0185"><title>Funding</title><p>This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Turmeric-nature&#x02019;s precious gift</article-title><source>Curr. Sci.</source><volume>76</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1356</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ammon</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacology of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic></article-title><source>Planta Med.</source><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1991</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2062949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>B.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malani</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin: the Indian solid gold</article-title><source>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</source><volume>595</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Turmeric and curcumin: biological actions and medicinal applications</article-title><source>Curr. Sci.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gbile</surname><given-names>Z.O.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Vernacular Names of Nigerian Plants (Yoruba)</chapter-title><year>1984</year><publisher-name>Caxton Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Great Britain</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osawaru</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eholor</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnotaxonomy and traditional use of turmeric (<italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.) among some Nigerian tribes in South Edo State, Nigeria</article-title><source>Plant Arch.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.plantarchives.org/" id="intr0010">http://www.plantarchives.org/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shosan</surname><given-names>L.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fawibe</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajiboye</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeegunrin</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agboola</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical survey of medicinal plants used in curing some diseases in infants in Abeokuta South Local Government Area of Ogun State, Nigeria</article-title><source>Am. J. Plant Sci.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>3258</fpage><lpage>3268</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adel-Lateef</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammam</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Ahwany</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Wakil</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taleb</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Sayed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassenein</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive chemical constituents of Curcuma longa L. rhizomes extract inhibit the growth of human hepatoma cell line (HepG2)</article-title><source>Acta Pharm.</source><volume>66</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27383887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usman</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>O.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ameen</surname><given-names>O.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>N.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zubair</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of rhizome essential oil of Curcuma longa L. growing in North Central Nigeria</article-title><source>World J. Chem.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>181</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordoloi</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclercq</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils of Curcuma longa L. from Bhutan</article-title><source>J. Essent. Oil Res.</source><volume>9</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>592</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oguntimehin</surname><given-names>B.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyerstah</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marschall-Weyerstah</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. leaves</article-title><source>Flavour Frag. J.</source><volume>5</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>90</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ajaiyeoba</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarna</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Essien</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olayemi</surname><given-names>I.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekundayo</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Setzer</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal activity of turmerone-rich essential oils of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> leaf and rhizome from Nigeria on <italic>Anopheles garnbiae</italic></article-title><source>Pharm. Biol.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>282</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Identification of Essential Oil Components by Gas Chromatography/Quardrupole Mass Spectrometry</chapter-title><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Allured Publishing Corporation</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Illinois</publisher-loc><fpage>456</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babushok</surname><given-names>V.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linstrom</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenkevich</surname><given-names>G.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retention Indices for frequently reported compounds of plant essential oils</article-title><source>J. Phys. Chem.</source><volume>40</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0075"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorke</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new approach to practical acute toxicity testing</article-title><source>Arch. Toxicol.</source><volume>54</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6667118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0080"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akanmu</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeosun</surname><given-names>O.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ilesanmi</surname><given-names>O.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuropharmacological effects of Oleamide in male and female mice</article-title><source>Behav. Brain Res.</source><volume>182</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17588682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0085"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noronha</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Melo</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezerra</surname><given-names>J.N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neto</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lino</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Central effects of isolated fractions from the root of <italic>Petiveria alliacea</italic> L (tipi) in mice</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>120</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18778763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0090"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumiya</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in head-dipping behaviour in the hole-boardtest reflect the anxiogenic and/or anxiolytic state in mice</article-title><source>Eur. J. Pharmacol.</source><volume>350</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9683010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0095"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellow</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chopin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>File</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Briley</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of open: closed arm entries in an elevated-plus as a measure of anxiety in the rat</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Methods</source><volume>14</volume><year>1985</year><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2864480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0100"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Naggar</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Serranillos</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carretero</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villar</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuropharmacological activity of <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. extracts</article-title><source>J. Neuropharmacol.</source><volume>88</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0105"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Namiki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic effect of physostigmine on ketamine-induced anaesthesia</article-title><source>Psychopharmacology (Berl.)</source><volume>102</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2251336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabbani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajjad</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zareitt</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiolytic effects of <italic>Stachys lavandufolia</italic> Vahl on the elevated plus-maze model of anxiety in mice</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>89</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14611891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swinyard</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodlead</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Experimental selection, quantification and evaluation of anticonvulsants</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meldrum</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreifuss</surname><given-names>F.E.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Antiepileptic Drugs</source><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Ravens Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pourgholami</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamalinejad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javadi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majzoob</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayyah</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the anticonvulsant activity of the essential oil of <italic>Eugenia caryophyllata</italic>, in male mice</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>64</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10197752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amabeoku</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinyua</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the anticonvulsant activity of <italic>Zanthoxylum capense</italic> (Thunb.) Harv. (Rutaceae) in mice</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharmacol.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>853</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0130"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodricks</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Calculated Risks; Understanding the Toxicity and Human Risks of Chemicals in Our Environment</chapter-title><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press Cambridge</publisher-name><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0135"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyarzo</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmermann</surname><given-names>B.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-arthritic effects and toxicity of the essential oils of Turmeric (<italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.)</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>58</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>849</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0140"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurenka</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory properties of curcumin, a major constituent of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>: a review of preclinical and clinical research</article-title><source>Altern. Med. Rev.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19594223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0145"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>European Medicines Agency</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Report on Curcuma longa L. Rhizoma</chapter-title><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Committee on Herbal Medicinal Products (HMPC) Assessment, European Medicines Agency: Evaluation of Medicines for Human Use 7 Westferry Circus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Canary Wharf, London</publisher-loc><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.emea.europa.eu" id="intr0015">http://www.emea.europa.eu</ext-link>. Doc. Ref.: EMEA/HMPC/456848/2008</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0150"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stine</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Principles of Toxicology</chapter-title><edition>2nd ed.</edition><year>2006</year><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group, CRC Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Boca Taton, USA</publisher-loc><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0155"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>R.S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lima</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of GABAergic non-benzodiazepine sites in the anxiolytic-like and sedative effects of the flavonoid baicalein in mice</article-title><source>Behav. Brain Res.</source><volume>22</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0160"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaisas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamat</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhagwat</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhide</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early human safety study of turmeric oil (Curcuma longa oil) administered orally in healthy volunteers</article-title><source>J. Assoc. Physicians India</source><volume>51</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1055</fpage><lpage>1060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15260388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0165"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hellion-Ibarrola</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibarrola</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montalbetti</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinichen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute toxicity and general pharmacological effect on central nervous system of the crude rhizome extract of <italic>Kyllinga brevifolia</italic> Rottb</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>66</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10473172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0170"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mogenson</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Injections of dopaminergic, cholinergic, serotonergic and GABAergic drugs into the nucleus accumbens: effects on locomotor activity in the rat</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><volume>20</volume><year>1981</year><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6261181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0175"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zapata-Sudo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>T.C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kartnaller</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortes</surname><given-names>T.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>N.F.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>M.A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sedative and anticonvulsant activities of methanol extract of <italic>Dorstenia arifolia</italic> in mice</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>130</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20307639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0180"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labella</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Punsky</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Havlicek</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphine derivatives with diminished opiate receptor potency showed enhanced central activity</article-title><source>Brain Res.</source><volume>174</volume><year>1979</year><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">226219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0185"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elisabetsky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interference of Propylene glycol with the hole board test</article-title><source>Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res.</source><volume>34</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11285468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0190"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walf</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frye</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of the elevated plus maze as an assay of anxiety-related behaviour in rodents</article-title><source>Nat. Protocols</source><volume>2</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0195"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nutt</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Body temperature discriminates full and partial benzodiazepine receptors agonist</article-title><source>Eur. J. Pharmacol.</source><volume>185</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1979276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0200"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zarindast</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabatabai</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of dopamine receptors subtypes in mouse thermoregulation</article-title><source>Psychopharmacology (Berl.)</source><volume>107</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1535446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0205"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastidas-Ramez</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navvaro</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quezada-Arellano</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanueva- Michael</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garzon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-convulsant effects of Magnolia grandifolia L. in the rat</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>61</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9683345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0210"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiepileptic drugs: mechanisms of action</article-title><source>Epilepsia</source><volume>34</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>S1</fpage><lpage>S8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0215"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell-Horner</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dibas</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Covey</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drewe</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>G.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pentylene-tetrazole-induced inhibition of recombinant gamma-aminobutyric acid type A (GABA<sub>A</sub>) receptors: mechanism and site of action</article-title><source>J. Pharmacol. Ther.</source><volume>298</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>986</fpage><lpage>995</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0220"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Syamasundar</surname><given-names>K.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil composition of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. cv. Roma from the plains of northern India</article-title><source>Flavour Fragr. J.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0225"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahlou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods to study the phytochemistry and bioactivity of essential oil</article-title><source>Phytother. Res.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15287066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0230"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jantan</surname><given-names>I.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N.A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of the rhizome oils of four Curcuma species from Malaysia</article-title><source>J. Essent. Oil Res.</source><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>723</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0235"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dung</surname><given-names>N.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuyet</surname><given-names>N.T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclercq</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constituents of the leaf oil of <italic>Curcuma domestica</italic> L. from Vietnam</article-title><source>J. Essent. Oil Res.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>703</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0240"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asghari</surname><given-names>G.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostajeran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shebli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcuminoid and essential oil components of turmeric at different stages of growth cultivated in Iran</article-title><source>Res. Pharm. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0245"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brand&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leit&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>J.M.R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>F.A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi&#x000fa;ra</surname><given-names>L.M.C.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antinociceptive activity of the monoterpene &#x003b1;-phellandrene in rodents: possible mechanisms of action</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Pharmacol.</source><volume>64</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22221105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0250"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>V.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiinflammatory and antinociceptive effects of 1,8-cineole a terpenoid oxide present in many plant essential oils</article-title><source>Phytother. Res.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10861965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0255"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastos</surname><given-names>V.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinho</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhaled 1,8 cineole reduces inflammatory parameters in airways of ovalbumin-challenged Guinea Pigs</article-title><source>Basic Clin. Pharmacol. Toxicol.</source><volume>108</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20722639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0260"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juergens</surname><given-names>U.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stober</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vetter</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of cytokine production and arachidonic acid metabolism by eucalyptol (1,8-cineole) in human blood monocytes in vitro</article-title><source>Eur. Med. Res.</source><volume>3</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>510</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0265"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>M.I.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>F.J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analgesic and anti- inflammatory effects of essential oils of Eucalyptus</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>89</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14611892</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><bio><p><bold>IAO</bold> is a Senior Lecturer, Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Pharmacy, OAU and a Postdoctoral Fellow, Walter Sisulu University.</p></bio><bio><p><bold>AOO</bold> holds a Bachelor of Pharmacy, OAU and presently engaged in private practice.</p></bio><bio><p><bold>CAE</bold> is a Senior Research Fellow, Drug Research and Production Unit, Faculty of Pharmacy, OAU.</p></bio><bio><p><bold>MAA</bold> is a Professor of Pharmacology, Faculty of Pharmacy, OAU.</p></bio><bio><p><bold>AOO</bold> is a Professor of Organic Chemistry, Walter Sisulu University.</p></bio><bio><p><bold>AGM</bold> is a Professor of Renewable Materials Chemistry, University of Idaho.</p></bio><sec id="sec0195" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p>The following is Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="upi0005"><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>IAO is grateful to Obafemi Awolowo University for study leave and Walter Sisulu University for post-doctoral fellowship.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="sec0190" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.toxrep.2017.07.001" id="intr0005">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.toxrep.2017.07.001</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>