<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antioxidant activity assay for any product is based on the capability of the compounds to inhibit oxidation, thus reducing production of free radicals that result in a chain reaction causing harmful cellular alterations [
 <xref rid="B50-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Studies have reported that antioxidant activity is significantly correlated with several healing properties, such as anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, anticancer and anti-obesity activities [
 <xref rid="B30-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. This is not surprising given the role of antioxidants in oxidative stress/damage is well-known and is implicated in a wide range of diseases (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-10-00923-f004">Figure 4</xref>). Furthermore, the role of antioxidants is not limited to scavenging free radicals; it also have good potentials to modulate signal transduction pathways that affected by free radicals during oxidative stress and are responsible to cellular responses (e.g., inflammation, survival, proliferation and death) in various diseases [
 <xref rid="B52-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Reinisalo et al. have shown that both the nuclear factor-erythroid-2-related factor-2 (Nrf2) pathway and intracellular cyclic AMP (cAMP) second messenger system can be modulated by antioxidant compounds [
 <xref rid="B54-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Activation of Nrf2 results in activation of some Nrf2 target gene candidates (e.g., 
 <italic>Nrf2, SLC48A1, SLC7A11, p62, HO-1</italic> and 
 <italic>Bcl-2</italic> genes) that control antioxidant defense and autophagy. While inhibition of phosphodiesterases (PDE) promotes intracellular cAMP levels, and therefore, activation of cAMP response element-binding protein (CREB) target genes and AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) pathway, which is the key regulator of autophagy and also involves in regulation of Nrf2 pathway [
 <xref rid="B54-biomolecules-10-00923" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
