<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par59">Generally, the chemical composition of medicinal materials is influenced by various factors, and geographic location is the most important one. In China, patchouli is mainly cultivated in Guangzhou city, Zhaoqing city, Zhanjiang city in Guangdong province, and some areas in Hainan province. According to its habitats, patchouli can be divided into 
 <italic>P. cablin cv.</italic> Shipaiensis (also known as Paixiang), 
 <italic>P. cablin cv.</italic> Gaoyaoensisensis (also known as Zhaoxiang), 
 <italic>P. cablin cv.</italic> Zhangjiangensis (also known as Zhanxiang) and 
 <italic>P. cablin cv.</italic> Hainanensis (also known as Nanxiang) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], and traditional experience believes that Paixiang has the best quality. Previous studies illustrated that the difference in chemical composition of patchouli from diverse habitats was mainly characterized by the difference in the content of volatile oil. In 2006, 31, 33 and 42 volatile components were detected from Paixiang, Zhaoxiang and Zhanxiang, respectively using GC-MS. The extraction rates of essential oils of them were 0.25%, 0.40% and 0.64% respectively. Remarkably, the content of pogostone seems to be more susceptible to cultivation regions than other volatile components in patchouli, which can be summarized as the highest content of pogostone in Zhaoxiang, and the lowest content of pogostone in Paixiang [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. In addition, the fingerprint of different solvent extraction sites of patchouli from Huangcun (Guangzhou City, Guangdong Province), Gaoyao (Zhaoqing City, Guangdong Province), Wuchuan (Zhanjiang City, Guangdong Province) and Wanning (Hainan Province) were compared and analyzed in 2011. The studies demonstrated that the similarity value of each extraction part of the water extract of Zhaoxiang and Paixiang was higher than 0.9, while the water extract of patchouli from Wuchuan, Wanning and Huangcun showed a large difference, which was consistent with the traditional experience for classifying patchouli by habitats. Moreover, the comparison of the fingerprints showed that the more polar components were less sensitive to cultivation regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In 2014, the content of PA and pogostone in patchouli from Leizhou County (Guangdong Province), Xuwen County (Guangdong Province), Yangchun County (Guangdong Province), Fumian County (Guangxi Province), and Wanning County (Hainan Province ) were determined and compared by GC. Based on the content of PA and pogostone, the results indicated that the quality of patchouli from Fumian was the best, followed by Yangchun, and the worst was Leizhou and Wanning [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. It’s worth noting that the soil composition, climatic conditions and growth management of different cultivation regions may affect the properties and quality of the medicinal materials. Therefore, the quality control of patchouli and the research of medicinal resources are particularly important.
</p>
