<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In general, the growth performance of broiler chickens did not differ among all the treatments in all periods of the present experiment. According to the obtained results, Kierończyk et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] used 
 <italic class="italic">T. molitor</italic> oil and 
 <italic class="italic">Z. morio</italic> oil to totally replace soybean oil and did not observe any adverse effects on the growth performance of broiler chickens until they reached 35 days of age. Furthermore, Schiavone et al. [
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] investigated a total or partial replacement of soybean oil by 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> oil and did not notice any negative effects on growth performance. All the above studies emphasised that insect oils can be an alternative to soybean oil. Therefore, our study, in which a total replacement of palm oil and poultry fat was performed, corresponded with the findings of Kierończyk et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] and Schiavone et al. [
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Fat sources and their FA profiles are key factors in the growth performance of broiler chickens [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. For instance, some of the FAs are classified as essential for poultry, because birds are not able to synthesise or convert compounds from other FAs; therefore, they must be supplemented in their diets [
 <xref rid="B1-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. According to Baião and Lara [
 <xref rid="B32-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] and Ravindran et al. [
 <xref rid="B1-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>], the essential fatty acids are 18:2 n-6 (linoleic, LA) and 18:3 n-3 (α-linolenic acid, LNA), and their deficiency may retard growth performance. Balnave [
 <xref rid="B33-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] also stated that a deficiency in linoleic acid may cause decreased growth and low resistance to diseases. In the current study, TM oil had the highest levels of essential FAs, i.e., linoleic acid (C18:2) and linolenic acid (C18:3), followed by poultry fat and palm oil, respectively. Therefore, TM oil can be a new source of fat in broiler chicken diets to replace palm oil and poultry fat. Tancharoenrat et al. [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] reported that the digestibility and absorption of fats depend on their sources. Moreover, it is well reported that the fat of young birds contains high proportions of unsaturated fatty acids that are highly digested, and such fat contains high amounts of saturated fatty acids [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Regardless of the fat sources, in our study, there were no significant differences among treatments on the apparent ileal digestibility of crude fat, crude protein and AME
 <sub class="sub">N</sub>. These results are in contrast with those of Tancharoenrat et al. [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], who showed that soybean oil and poultry fat were more highly digested then palm oil and tallow, which was explained by the difference in the content of unsaturated fatty acids among fats that are better digested by poultry. Interestingly, in the present study, the fat sources were not comparable in the case of saturated and unsaturated fatty acids; TM oil showed the highest concentration of unsaturated fatty acids. These findings could be explained by the results reported by Sosa and Fogliano [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], who placed insect oils between vegetable oils and animal fats based on the FA profile, with the exception of palm oil, which is comparable to animal fat. According to Józefiak et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], the digesta pH values can be affected by dietary sources in different parts of the gastrointestinal tract (crop, jejunum and ceca). However, in our experiment, the pH value was not affected. Furthermore, no effects on lipase and trypsin activity were noted. However, amylase activity was lower in the case of TM oil supplementation. Changes in amylase activity could be explained by a long-term adaptive response of the pancreas to the increased lipid content in the composition of the diet. Experiments performed on rats showed that higher consumption of lipids decreased the intracellular amylase activity and the activity of the amylase secreted from the pancreas [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Moreover, some studies indicate that fatty acid composition in the diet can affect α amylase activity. Additionally, experiments performed on diabetic rats have shown that unsaturated fatty acids, such as oleic acid, linoleic acid and palmitoleic acid, and saturated fatty acids, such as stearic acid and palmitic acid, reduce amylase activity [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. On the other hand, some research did not show any effect of dietary lipid content on amylase activity [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Based on this knowledge, we suppose that fat addition and the fat composition of the diet could modulate amylase activity. However, knowledge about this phenomenon is limited and requires further research.
</p>
