<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Chicken meat has a high-protein and low-fat content and has been designated as the principal source of PUFAs with a predominant concentration of n-3 PUFAs [
 <xref rid="B52-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Foods with higher PUFA concentrations are considered functional and beneficial for the prevention of coronary heart disease and other chronic diseases [
 <xref rid="B53-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. Furthermore, fatty acids play a significant role in the health status of humans, and long-chain fatty acids (LCFAs) are beneficial for the prevention of metabolic disorders [
 <xref rid="B47-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. The present study shows that the saturated and unsaturated fats in the breast muscle tissue were not affected by the dietary treatments used here. However, PUFA concentrations were higher and MUFA concentrations were lower in the case of TM oil supplementation. These results are considered positive as PUFAs are a favourable component of food for human consumption. As reported by Schiavone et al. [
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> oil supplementation in the broiler chicken diet increased SFAs and lowered PUFAs in the breast muscle, and no effects were observed on MUFAs. Furthermore, Kierończyk et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] showed an increase in MUFAs by using supplements of both insect oils (
 <italic class="italic">T. molitor</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Z. morio</italic>), respectively, but only TM oil supplementation increased the PUFA content in the breast muscle. As mentioned above, the beneficial impact of n-3 and n-3 PUFAs on human health and their added value to food for human consumption were investigated. TM oil supplementation increased the levels of n-3 and n-3 PUFA, as well as n-6 and n-6 PUFA. However, no changes in the n-6/n-3 ratio were observed. These results are not in line with the findings of Kierończyk et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] and Schiavone et al. [
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The disagreement among the findings of other trials using the same species of insect could be related to the variability of the fatty acid composition of the insect fat due to the rearing conditions at the larval stage [
 <xref rid="B55-animals-09-00116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. The PUFA/SFA ratio, n-6/n-3 ratio, atherogenic index and thrombogenic index are nutritional indexes that display favourable human health-promoting values in the meat of chickens. However, in our results, the aforementioned indexes were not affected by the dietary treatments.
</p>
