<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Additionally, plant–bee networks differed between native and non‐native plants. As expected, networks associated with native plants were more specialized than networks associated with non‐native plants. Native plants share a longer evolutionary history of interactions with native bees than non‐native plants, which likely increased the chance of more specialized interactions evolving (Fenster et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). Other studies found that non‐native plants were predominantly visited by more generalized insects (Aizen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Lopezaraiza‐Mikel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Memmott &amp; Waser, 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Olesen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Schweiger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Stout &amp; Morales, 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Non‐native plants therefore appear to favor generalist (or polylectic) over specialist (or oligolectic) bees. This raises concerns about the use of non‐native plants in seed mixes aimed at supporting bees and other organisms (Bartomeus et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Lopezaraiza‐Mikel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Winfree et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). In our study, we recorded only two oligolectic bee species visiting flowers, preventing more robust inferences on disproportional effects on specialists. In the mid‐Atlantic region, oligolectic bee activity peaks in summer (with up to 57 spp. active in June), followed by spring and fall (Fowler, 
 <xref rid="ece36826-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Our survey might have missed some of the early oligolectic bee species due to the late start of flowering of our experimental plants, especially at native plots. Although oligolectic bees clearly depend on their native host plants for pollen collection, they appear to use non‐native plants for nectar collection or as resting areas, as suggested by the occurrence of 
 <italic>M. desponsus</italic> males on non‐native plants.
</p>
