<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The
 <italic class="italic"> p</italic>-nitrophenyl butyrate (PNPB) assay was used as in vitro approach to investigate the inhibition of pancreatic lipase (PL) and to screen the antilipase properties of
 <italic class="italic"> M fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs samples from different regions of Palestine. To the best of our knowledge, there were no previous studies conducted to explore the activity of
 <italic class="italic"> M fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs against PL enzyme. The results of the current study showed that VO sample from Nablus owned the highest potency with IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 39.81 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>g/mL (
 <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). However, through an
 <italic class="italic"> in vitro</italic> screening of the phytochemical properties of 30 plants growing in Mexico, Villa-Ruano
 <italic class="italic"> et al</italic>. (2013) [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] concluded that plants rich with terpenes and other phytochemicals (steroids, tannins, and glycoside) showed very strong antilipase activity. Other studies reported that plant extracts rich in terpenes showed antilipase activity [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Investigating
 <italic class="italic"> Pinus massoniana</italic> L. volatile oil growing in China by Wang M
 <italic class="italic"> et al</italic>. (2017) [
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] indicated that the dominant components were related to monoterpene and sesquiterpene (
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-pinene, 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-pinene, D-limonene, and caryophyllene) and were responsible for antilipase activity of the oil at IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> 25.10 ±0.49 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>M.  The phytochemical screening of the three samples of
 <italic class="italic"> M fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs supports the existence of monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes in all of three samples of VOs. Samples collected from Nablus owned the highest percentages of (
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-pinene, 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-pinene, and D-limonene) which support the highest antilipase potency and efficacy of Nablus samples. The antidiabetic properties of
 <italic class="italic"> M fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs samples from different regions in Palestine were investigated by the inhibition of 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-amylase activity. According to our knowledge, there were no previous studies conducted for the purpose of assessing the activity of
 <italic class="italic"> M fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs against 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-amylase enzyme. The inhibition of 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-amylase activity of
 <italic class="italic"> Sideritis galactica </italic>Bornm VOs sample growing in Turkey studied by Zengin
 <italic class="italic"> et al</italic>. (2016) [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] was related to abundance of monoterpene hydrocarbons ingredients mainly 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-pinene and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-pinene. In screening the 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-amylase inhibitory activity of
 <italic class="italic"> J. phoenicea </italic>volatile oil growing in Tunisia, the results showed powerful 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-amylase inhibition properties due to presence of terpenes like 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-pinene [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. The
 <italic class="italic"> M fruticosa serpyllifolia</italic> VOs sample from Nablus owned the highest amount of 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-pinene and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-pinene components (0.91 and 1.48%, respectively) compared with samples of Ramallah and Hebron which may explain its highest potency against 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-amylase enzyme.
</p>
