<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To evaluate the effects of EOs on population parameters of 
 <italic>M. persicae</italic> and 
 <italic>R. padi</italic>, the concentration of 0.2% was used. The applied concentration was selected based on the results of the contact toxicity bioassays, where it caused 10–35% aphid mortality. The methodology presented here was previously described by Chrzanowski et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. An adult apterous female of 
 <italic>M. persicae</italic> or 
 <italic>R. padi</italic> was placed on seven-day-old seedlings of pea or wheat, respectively. A single aphid was isolated using a transparent plastic cylinder (Ø 10 cm, height 30 cm) covered with muslin to permit ventilation and left to produce nymphs overnight. Five nymphs were then left on each seedling, whereas the other offspring and adults were removed. The two-day-old nymphs were sprayed with a 0.2% aqueous emulsion of the studied EO or with a control solution, prepared as described above. The individuals were observed daily to determine the duration of pre-reproductive period (PRP). When the aphids reached reproductive maturity, spraying was repeated. The surviving adults were monitored daily for a period equal to PRP, on each occasion recording the number of newborn nymphs. During these observations, all nymphs were removed from the seedlings after having been counted. The daily fecundity (DF) was expressed as the number of nymphs per living adult female per day. The intrinsic rate of natural increase (r
 <sub>m</sub>) was calculated using the Wyatt and White equation [
 <xref rid="B28-insects-12-00360" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]:
 <disp-formula>r
  <sub>m</sub> = 0.738 × (ln Md) × d
  <sup>−1</sup>
 </disp-formula> where d is the length of the PRP; Md is the number of nymphs produced in a reproductive period equal to d; 0.783 is the correction factor. This experiment was performed in 15 independent replicates for each aphid species for both the control and treated groups.
</p>
