<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>OEO nanoliposomes were prepared by using a thin-film hydration–sonication method. This method enabled obtaining nano-sized liposomes at five different concentrations (6.2, 4.9, 3.7, 2.5 and 1.2 mM). Size and morphology were analyzed by DLS and SEM imaging to confirm that the diameters of the prepared vesicles were within the nanometric scale (77.46 ± 0.66 nm) after 1 day, 1 week and 1 month of preparation; OEO nanoliposomes also exhibited spherical morphology. Entrapment efficiency was evaluated after 1 day and 30 days of preparation by spectroscopic analysis. EE% was found to be affected by EO concentrations and the highest values were 79.55 ± 6.9% and 78.7 ± 5.4%, respectively, at a concentration of 6.2 mM OEO. Therefore, stability of OEO nanoliposomes under storage was evaluated 1 day, 1 week and 1 month following the synthesis, with zeta potential measurements reaching values around −36.94 ± 0.36 mV throughout. It was clear that EOs influenced the size of the nanoliposome; at higher concentrations, there was an increase in the particle size, an effect which might be due to the interaction between EOs as hydrophobic agents with the acyl chains of lecithin, which is responsible for altering the acyl chain order, and the effect was more pronounced when the EO concentration was increased. Moreover, the surface charge and stability of the vesicles were affected by the phospholipids and excipients utilized for the fabrication process. After one month of storage, a significant degree of instability was observed, as demonstrated by zeta potential values (approximately −6.97 ± 0.61 mV), PdI, and particle size, not only in the OEO-loaded nanoliposomes, but also in the empty vesicles taken as controls. These results suggest that there was no significant contribution of the surfactant utilized during the synthesis process (Tween-80
 <sup>®</sup>) to stabilize the system during long periods. Moreover, the ATR-FTIR studies confirmed the presence of OEO bands in the nanoliposome formulations. Additionally, OEO nanoliposomes’ antifungal activity demonstrated the capability to inhibit mycelial growth at lower concentrations compared to the pure EOs against fungi strains of 
 <italic>T. rubrum.</italic> Finally, it can be concluded that nanoliposomes are suitable for potential applications as antifungal delivery agents. Nevertheless, further stability studies are necessary to analyze the optimal formulation to prevent agglomeration during storage for longer periods.
</p>
