<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32" class="p">This animal study has evaluated the anti-obesity and hypolipidemic effects of onion oil and garlic oil on hyperlipidemia experimentally induced through the feeding of a high-fat diet. The results revealed that the body weight gains of the rats in the HFD groups were significantly higher than that in the NC group, and the weight gains in the garlic oil and onion oil groups were normalized to or lower than that in the NC group (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). In particular, the epididymal fat pad weight, the perirenal fat pad weight, the ratio of adipose tissue weights to body weight, the ratio of liver weight to body weight and the Lee index were higher in the HFD-B group rats than in the NC group (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>). In the present study, the anti-obesity activity of the onion oil and garlic oil was examined in rats fed an HFD by measuring the Lee index and markers of obesity. The epididymal fat pad weight, the perirenal fat pad weight, the ratio of adipose tissue weight to body weight, and the Lee index were found to be significantly lower in the GO and OO group rats than in the HFD-B group. These results suggest that garlic oil and onion oil have anti-obesity abilities. It has previously been suggested that onion or garlic extract may provide beneficial anti-obesity effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. In this study, the ratio of liver weight to body weight and the ratio of kidney weight to body weight in some intervention groups were significantly higher than those in the HFD-B group. These results may suggest that garlic oil and onion oil result in adverse effects on the liver, although the organ coefficient has its limitations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>]. The individual differences between animals and their source, initial weight, gender, batches, feeding season and environmental conditions all affect the normal range of growth and development and organ index [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>].
</p>
