<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33" class="p">Coronary heart disease risk is positively associated with TG, TC and LDL-C and is inversely associated with HDL-C. High levels of TC, TG and LDL-C lead to a high risk for the development of coronary heart disease and atherosclerosis in middle-aged adults [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. Our data demonstrated that garlic oil and onion oil improved the lipid profile by lowering serum TC, TG, and LDL-C concentrations and the atherogenic index compared with the HFD-B group. As shown in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table" class="xref">6</xref>, the serum TC concentration in the rats in the HFD-A (3.11 mmol/L) group increased by 88.9% compared with the NC group (1.65 mmol/L). However, the serum TC concentrations of the rats in the GO-H and OO-H groups decreased by 38.1 and 19.6%, respectively, compared with the HFD-B group. Similar results have been documented in the reports of Bordia and others [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>]. As shown in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table" class="xref">6</xref>, the serum TG concentration (1.71 mmol/L) in the rats in the HFD-A group increased by 76.8% compared with the NC group (0.96 mmol/L). However, the serum TG concentrations of the rats in the GO-H and OO-H groups decreased by 20.6% and 35.1%, respectively, compared with the HFD-B group. The significant reduction in TC and TG with garlic oil and onion oil administration suggests potential health benefits through reductions in obesity, hyperlipidemia and/or similar to those described in the field of malignant cholesterol diseases. Moreover, the HDL-C concentration in the garlic oil and onion oil groups significantly increased compared with the HFD-B group (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table" class="xref">6</xref>). Our findings are in agreement with other studies that have shown that garlic and onion consumption increased HDL-C levels in hyperlipidemic patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>], animals[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>], and patients with coronary artery disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>]. Finally, our results clearly demonstrated that the contributing dosages of garlic oil and onion oil were 46.3 mg/kg•bw/d (GO-M, OO-L) and 92.6 mg/kg•bw/d (GO-H, OO-H), rather than 11.6 mg/kg•bw/d (GO-L) (Tables 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table" class="xref">6</xref>). That is, the lower garlic dose had no obvious anti-obesity or hypolipidemic effects.
</p>
