<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0145">It has been revealed that 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> extracts and essential oils possess strong antioxidant activity (
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">Ashraf et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0705" ref-type="bibr">Sultan et al., 2012</xref>). The antioxidant effect of TQ has been found in different diseases, including diabetes, asthma, carcinogenesis and encephalomyelitis. TQ preserves the activity of a variety of antioxidant enzymes such as glutathione peroxidase, glutathione-S-transferase and catalase and also acts as free radical and superoxide scavenger. It has been reported that TQ acts as a nephroprotective and decreases SSAT and CYP3A1 gene expression via antioxidant mechanisms (
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Awad et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0495" ref-type="bibr">Mansour et al., 2002</xref>). It reacts with GSH, NADH and NADPH and forms glutathionyl-dihydro-thymoquinone, offering evidence for potent free radical scavengers (
 <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">Khalife and Lupidi, 2007</xref>). Influential chemo preventive action of TQ has been shown against MC-induced fibrosarcoma tumours due to the antioxidant activity and its interference with DNA synthesis (
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">Badary and Gamal, 2000</xref>). Treatment with 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> extract prevented liver damage induced by lipid peroxidation (
 <xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Meral et al., 2001</xref>). The favourable safety profile of herbal medicines is one of the reasons people often favour herbal medicines. It has been reported that a mixture of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> with honey exhibits protection against methylnitrosourea-induced oxidative stress and carcinogenesis (
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad, 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2013a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0455" ref-type="bibr">Mabrouk et al., 2002</xref>). Antioxidant properties of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> ethanol extract exhibit protection from diabetes by improving antioxidant enzyme glutathione peroxidase and decreasing blood glucose levels, lipids levels (
 <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">Kaleem et al., 2006</xref>).
</p>
