<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Focusing on the molecular mechanism behind the onset of lipid imbalance-driven obesity and diabetes, both lipid homeostasis and physical principles governing lipid arrangements in the membranes are involved. Two examples illustrate this mechanism in liver disease (reviewed in [
 <xref rid="B17-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]). The liver is a crucial metabolic organ in controlling body energy metabolism. It functions as a metabolic hub linking several tissues, skeletal muscle and adipose tissue included. In fat metabolism, the liver cells break down fats and produce energy (reviewed in [
 <xref rid="B162-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">162</xref>]). 
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">▪</label>
   <p class="p">In the first example, excessive intake of saturated FA is highly toxic for hepatocytes due to its limited capacity to integrate them into TG [
    <xref rid="B163-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>]. In parallel, an elevated degree of membrane saturation disrupts calcium homeostasis and triggers liver ER stress [
    <xref rid="B164-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">164</xref>]. Chronic activation of ER stress dysregulates lipid homeostasis and might lead to dyslipidemia, insulin resistance, type II diabetes, and obesity [
    <xref rid="B163-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">▪</label>
   <p class="p">A second example involves the previously introduced TFEB, transcription factor partially dictating lysosome biogenesis. As above mentioned, TFEB participates in autophagy and in the clearance of lipid droplets. Furthermore, it governs liver lipid catabolism and energy metabolism interfering with peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ (PPAR-γ) signaling [
    <xref rid="B165-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">165</xref>]. In obese animals, TFEB overexpression rescues obesity and associated metabolic syndrome by promoting lipophagy [
    <xref rid="B166-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">166</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
