<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Survival rate of the exposed fishes decreases with increasing concentration of crude extract in both acute and chronic toxicity test (Figures 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>). From this study, it is clearly shown that most of the mortalities were caused by the effect of bioactive constituent present in the crude extract in either high concentrations as in acute toxicity test or cumulative effect as in chronic toxicity test. Although most of the bioactive constituents (polyphenol) present in the plant crude extract mainly have medicinal effect, some researchers also revealed the effect of phenolic compounds such as alkaloid to be detrimental to body cells, tissues, and organs especially if taken in high concentration or used over a long period of time [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Previous studies showed that most of the anti-inflammatory agents (flavonoid) cause gastroduodenal mucosal injury resulting from deleterious effect of gastric acid overwhelming the normal defensive properties of the mucosa when used in high concentration [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The possibility of systemic effects resulting from the inhibition of endogenous prostaglandin synthesis was also reported. Inhibition of prostaglandin may affect the availability of the epithelial mucus, secretion of bicarbonate, mucosal blood flow, epithelial proliferation, and mucosal resistance to injury [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Several works of literature on 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> toxicity study reported the effect of extract with anti-inflammatory effect to affect vital organs such as liver, kidney, heart, spleen, and brain [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Damage to these vital organs due to the high concentration of phenolic compounds or their cumulative effect over time may be the main causes of the death in this experimental study.
</p>
