<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Arthropod Borne Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Arthropod Borne Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JAD</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">JAD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Arthropod-Borne Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2322-1984</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2322-2271</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5629292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jad-11-105</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Repellency Effect of Essential Oils of some Native Plants and Synthetic Repellents against Human Flea, <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> (Siphonaptera: Pulicidae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghavami</surname><given-names>Mohammad Bagher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="C1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poorrastgoo</surname><given-names>Fahimeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taghiloo</surname><given-names>Behrooz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>Jamshid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="AFF1"><label>1</label>Department of Medical Entomology and Vector Control, Faculty of Medicine, Zanjan University of Medical Sciences, Zanjan, Iran</aff><aff id="AFF2"><label>2</label>Zanjan Health Center, Zanjan University of Medical Sciences, Zanjan, Iran</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="C1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Dr Mohammad Bagher Ghavami, Email: <email>Ghavami@zums.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright&#x000a9; Iranian Society of Medical Entomology &#x00026; Tehran University of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Unported License which allows users to read, copy, distribute and make derivative works for non-commercial purposes from the material, as long as the author of the original work is cited properly.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Fleas are important vectors of human and animal disease, and control measures for protection against their bites and flea-borne diseases are necessary.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>The essential oils (EOs) of four native medicinal plants, <italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic>, <italic>Myrtus communis</italic>, <italic>Achillea wilhelmsii</italic> and <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> were isolated by hydrodistillation technique and analyzed by GC-MC. The repellent activity of EOs and synthetic compounds, DEET and permethrin, were assayed on human subjects against field collected fleas. The effective doses of 50% and 90% of EOs and synthetic compounds were estimated by probit analysis of dose and response regression line.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Analysis of EOs revealed about 19 major components. All oils were found to be more repellent (ED<sub>50</sub> range= 208&#x02013;955&#x003bc;g cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) than DEET and permethrin (ED<sub>50</sub> range= 27&#x02013;182 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup>&#x003bc;g cm<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>). Thyme and myrtle oils showed high repellent activities and among the total detected terpenes, thymol (36.26%) and &#x003b1;-pinene (32.5%) were the major components of those oils respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Low repellent potency of DEET and permethrin against fleas might be related to flea olfactory system and further molecular and electrophysiological studies are required to conceive new ideas for the discovery and development of the next generation of repellents. Based on high repellent activity of thyme and myrtle essential oils against <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> further studies should be staged to develop their appropriate effective formulations. Likewise, field trials should be carried out to evaluate the operational feasibility and dermal toxicity over a long period.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Pulex irritans</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Myrtus communis</italic></kwd><kwd>DEET</kwd><kwd>Repellents</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The human flea, <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> Linnaeus, is the most invasive species worldwide with great medical importance and intolerable nuisance. The control of this vector has received considerable attention since ancient times. The most effective measure to control human flea lies in adult stage using adulticides (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Service 2012</xref>). Although application of synthetic insecticides can be effective, their intensive use has caused concerns regarding their impact on human and environmental health leading to development of resistance in the flea populations like other vectors (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Hemingway and Ranson 2000</xref>). In addition to adulticides, personal protection including the use of repellents can decrease contact between human and fleas. N, N-Diethyl-3-methylbenzamide (DEET) has been considered as one of the most effective synthetic repellents against various groups of vectors and still remains as &#x0201c;the gold standard&#x0201d; among currently available insect repellents (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Swal et al. 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Debboun et al. 2014</xref>). However, there has been no report concerning the repellency of DEET on human flea. In addition, there have been case reports of DEET toxicity especially among children and the elderly (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Qui 1998</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Sudakin 2003</xref>). Moreover, genotoxic effects of this compound have been found previously (Manikhan et al. 2012). In addition to DEET, permethrin, a synthetic pyrethroid, is characterized by a high level of potency against a wide range of vectors, rapid reactivity, excellent photostability, resistance to weathering, low mammalian toxicity (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Yu 2014</xref>) and high potency in tick and insect bite prevention (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Faulde et al. 2003</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). However, skin irritation, including itching, swelling, redness, mild burning and stinging may occur after treatment with permethrin. Moreover, arthropods show differential responses to these products, indicating the possibility of adaptation and emerging resistance or insensitivity (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Klun et al. 2004</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Stanczyk et al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Pellegrino et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Sfara et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Del Fabbro and Nazzi 2013</xref>). Thus, there is a growing demand to evaluate natural repellents to develop suitable agents for prophylactic treatment in integrated pest management.</p><p>Plant essential oils (EOs) specially their monoterpen components; exhibit a variety of biological activities against a wide spectrum of insect pests. They can adversely affect the growth and reproduction rate, behavior trait of insect pests and act as contact insecticide, fumigant, repellent and antifeedent agent. These compounds have a low risk profile on the environment, mammals, and humans and might comprise natural alternatives for conventional insecticides (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Bakkali et al. 2008</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Koul et al. 2008</xref>).</p><p>Fresh and dried shoots of myrtle, mint, thyme, yarrow and their EOs and extracts are widely used in cosmetic, food, gum, toothpaste and pharmaceutical industries. These plants have also been commonly used in folk medicine for treatment of colds, pains and as spices and herbal tea as well (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Naghibi et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Bakkali et al. 2008</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Saeidnia et al. 2011</xref>). Moreover, these plants proved to be toxic to different species of insects and ticks (Maia and Moore 2010, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">George et al. 2008</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Pitarokili et al. 2011</xref>, Yahoobi-Ershadi et al. 2011, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Tavassoli et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Koc et al. 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Lupi et al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>For human flea, however, little work has been done on EOs repellent activity. Moreover, despite the great need in human health area for fleas prophylaxes by natural products, the current knowledge concerning repellent action of EOs on human flea is very limited. Therefore, in the present study the chemical properties and components of some EOs were evaluated. Additionally a comparative study was conducted for detection of flea repellent activity of these Eos.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Plant materials</title><p>The shoots of native medicinal plants, thyme (<italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic>), mint (<italic>Mentha piperita</italic>), yarrow (<italic>Achillea wilhelmsii</italic>) and myrtle (<italic>Myrtus communis</italic>) were collected from different areas of Zanjan and Fars Provinces during May&#x02013;Jun 2013 and 2014. Collected herbs were dried in shade for 8 days at room temperature until they became brittle. Air-dried samples were powdered in electric vegetable chopper and subjected to hydro distillation in a Clevenger type apparatus for about 3h. The extracted oils were dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate and refrigerated at 4 &#x000b0;C in dark glass bottles until the experiment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Gas Chromatography and GC mass analysis</title><p>The gas chromatography (GC) analysis was carried out with an HP Series II 7890N instrument equipped with flame ionization detector and HP-5-MS capillary column (30m&#x000d7; 0.25mm, 0.25&#x003bc;m film thickness). Injector and detector temperatures were set at 260 &#x000b0;C and 270 &#x000b0;C respectively. Thermal program of GC oven started with 60 &#x000b0;C for 4min, then rose to 60&#x02013;225 &#x000b0;C at a rate of 3oc/min. Helium was the carrier gas at a flow rate of 1ml/min. Diluted samples (1:50 in diethyl ether) of 1&#x003bc;l were injected manually in the split less mode.</p><p>Quantity analysis of EOs components was performed using the same condition with GC HP Series II equipped with HP GC 5975C mass selective detector in the electron impact mode 70eV. The oil components were identified by comparison of the retention time with those of authentic samples in mass spectra obtained from literature and the library of the GC-MS system.</p></sec><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Human subjects</title><p>The study was conducted on 6 volunteers (four males and two females) who were aged between 28 to 50 years old. They were nonsmokers, non alcoholics and non-allergic to insect bites or herbal oils. They also had no contact with lotions, perfumes, coils or perfumed soaps on the days of assay. All volunteers signed an formal consent form after having received a full explanation of the test objectives, procedures and foreseeable risk to subject. The research protocol was approved by the ethics committee of Zanjan University of Medical Sciences.</p></sec><sec><title>Flea collection</title><p>Alive samples of fleas were collected by human baits from animal shelters of Khodabandeh and Mahneshan districts of Zanjan Province from September 2013 to October 2014. Volunteers in white overalls and white ladies stockings, walked around the houses for 3&#x02013;5 minutes and attracted fleas were suctioned by electrical aspirator and transferred to laboratory in 2 liters Erlenmeyer flasks.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of solutions</title><p>Dilutions of each essential oil and DEET (Aldrich USA, D100951-500G, N, N-Diethyl-3-methylbenzamide, lot# MKBH0428V, P Code: 1001075635, Density: 0.97g/cm<sup>3</sup>) with grade reagent ethanol (ET) were made to stock in <italic>V/V</italic> at 85% concentration. From which five serial dilutions (42.75%, 21.37%, 10.68% and 5.34% concentrations) were prepared. Also a 20% permethrin (United Phosphorus Ltd, Delhi India, with 96% active ingredient, 42:58 cis: trans ratio) solution was prepared by mixing 2.1g of permethrin with 10ml of grade reagent acetone and 5 serial dilutions (in acetone) were created.</p></sec><sec><title>Repellency tests</title><p>The bioassay was performed by the standard protocols for testing mosquito and tick repellents (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Dautel 2004</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Bissinger 2010</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Maia and Moore 2011</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Krober et al. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">WHO 2013</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Debboun 2014</xref>). About 60 unfed fleas were kept in laboratory condition (25&#x000b1;2 &#x000b0;C and 60% RH) and transferred to 20&#x02033;&#x000d7;6&#x02033; clear cylinder glass vase. For testing, volunteers used the left arm for treatment and the right for control. Five hundred &#x003bc;l of test materials were applied to the treated area of left hand (from elbow to wrist, area approximately 500cm<sup>2</sup>) and allowed to dry for 5 minutes. The same area of right arm was applied with five hundred &#x003bc;l of ET. After drying of treated area, both arms were covered with white ladies stockings and volunteers kept their hands (left as treatment and right as control) in glass jars about 3 minutes. The control hand was exposed before the treatment. Samples of fleas from different parts of arms (hand and wrist to elbow) were collected and recorded separately. These samples were preserved in ET and observed under stereomicroscopy at 30&#x000d7;. Samples of <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> were recorded and other species of fleas were excluded from study. The percentage of repellency in each hand was calculated by the following formula: (Tc&#x02013;Tb)/(Tc+Tb)&#x000d7; 100, Where Tc= the number of fleas in hand of arm and Tb is the numbers in the area between elbow to wrist. The percentage of repellency in treatment groups was corrected with control group by Abbot&#x02019;s formula.</p><p>The data were subjected to probit analysis and the median effective dose (ED<sub>50</sub>) and 95 % effective dose (ED<sub>90</sub>) with 95 confidence interval exposed in microgram of repellent per square of centimeter of skin area were estimated. Significant differences between effective dose values were determined by comparing the confidence intervals of the values.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Water distillation of the dried shoots of the examined plants furnished 0.8&#x02013;1.2% (W/W) of white to yellowish essential oils with strong pleasant odors were identified. Forty seven constituents were determined in the thyme essential oil representing 97.98% of total content. The main constituents were found to be thymol (36.26%), geraniol (11.61%), carvacrol (4.96%) and 1,8 cineol (3.26%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Relative percentage of major components of essential oils of each plant extract</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Compound name</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>LRI (Min)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Myrtus communis</italic></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Achillea wilhelmsii</italic></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mentha piperita</italic></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Pinene</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limonene</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,8 Cineol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Tepinene</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Artemisia alcohol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.86</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.39</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalooll</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dimethyhepta</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.67</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphor</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menthen</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.66</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Terpinol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalyl acetate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.14</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geraniol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>14</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>15</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carvacrol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.57</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperiton</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.99</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>17</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperiton oxide</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.11</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.07</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranyl acetate</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.68</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>19</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trans caryophylen</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.83</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.76</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.75</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Total Compound (No)</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1"><bold>Total percentage</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.43</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.26</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.98</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p>LRI*= Linear regression indices on HP-5 MS column relative to C<sub>9</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>23</sub> n alkanes, identification based on comparison of mass spectra obtained from the library of the GC-MS system and from literature.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A total of twenty compounds were identified in the oil of myrtle, representing around 99.15% of the oil totally. Alpha pinene (32.5%), 1,8 cineol (24.15), limonene (15.5%) linalool (10.6%) and linalyl acetate (5.5%) were the major constituents in the essential oil of <italic>Myrtus communis</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>)</p><p>According to total 87.43% of the <italic>Achillea wilhelmsii</italic> oil, eighty constituents were identified in the essential oil of this plant. The main components were camphen (19%), dimethyl heptatriene (10.15%), borneol (7.3%), artemisia alcohol (5.3%), menthen (4.56%) and 1,8 cineol (3.86%).</p><p>There were fifty eight compounds in the oil of <italic>Mentha pipertta</italic>, comprising 98.26% of the total weight. Menthen (26.66%), piperiton (19.18%), piperiton oxide (19.07%), 1,8 cineol (8.5%) and trans caryophylen (3.29%) were the major compounds of essential oil of this plant (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>During the study, 4529 samples of fleas were collected by human-bait catch. Human flea was the commonest species and 94.3% of samples were identified as <italic>Pulex irritans.</italic> The frequencies of other fleas were 3.8% and 1.9 % for <italic>Ctenocephalidescanis</italic> and <italic>C. felis</italic> respectively. The bioassay tests were carried out with 4271 samples of alive human flea.</p><p>All tested essential oils in five concentrations showed differences in repellency with chemical compounds. The thyme essential oil provided highest repellency followed by myrtle, yarrow and mint essential oils (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Repellent activity (in percentage) of some essential oils and synthetic compounds against <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> on human volunteers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><bold>Dosage (&#x003bc; g/cm<sup>2)</sup></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Study groups</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Myrtus communis</italic></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Achillea wilhelmsii</italic></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mentha piperita</italic></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Permethrin</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DEET</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>200</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>400</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>800</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1600</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The EDs<sub>50</sub> (with 95% confidence intervals) of thyme and myrtle essential oils were 229 (208&#x02013;257) and 295 (269&#x02013;338)&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively. In these plants the ED<sub>90</sub> (with 95% confidence intervals) of essential oils were 776 (660&#x02013;933) and 1172 (988&#x02013;1412) &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Parameters of probit analysis on botanical and chemical compounds and their repellency against <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> on human volunteers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Compound</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>a</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>b</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ED<sub>50</sub> (95 % CE) (&#x003bc; g/cm<sup>2</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ED<sub>90</sub> (95 % CE) (&#x003bc; g/cm<sup>2</sup>)</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>n</bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>X</italic><sup>2</sup></bold></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>p</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.78</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (208&#x02013;257)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">776 (660&#x02013;933)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">828</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Myrtus communis</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 (269&#x02013;338)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1172 (988&#x02013; 1412)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">895</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Achillea wilhelmsii</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;5.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">457 (371&#x02013;630)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2217 (1399&#x02013;4673)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>Mentha piperita</italic></bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">776 (660&#x02013;955)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5717 (3890&#x02013;9120)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">822</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Permethrin</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.76 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">362</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>DEET</bold></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182 &#x000d7; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">710</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Yarrow essential oil showed moderate repellency against human flea. In this plant the ED<sub>50</sub> and EDs<sub>90</sub> (with 95% confidence intervals) of essential oil were 457 (371&#x02013;630) and 2217 (1399&#x02013;4673)&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively. Mint essential oil provided slight repellency. The ED<sub>50</sub> and ED<sub>90</sub> (with 95% confidence intervals) of mint essential oil were 776 (660&#x02013;855) and 5717 (3890&#x02013;9120)&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively.</p><p>Permethrin and DEET compounds showed low repellency in comparison with botanical essential oils. The ED<sub>50</sub> of permethrin and DEET were estimated 7760 and 51000&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>The related dose response lines and regression equations for essential oils and synthetic compounds are represented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Dose response lines for botanical and chemical repellent activity against <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> on human subjects.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JAD-11-105-g001"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Evaluation of botanical compounds is essential to identify effective repellents for vector control programming and protection of populations against vector nuisance and vector borne diseases.</p><p>The insecticidal and repellent activities of various herbal derivatives have been demonstrated in many studies (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Neiro et al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Bisinger and Roe 2010</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Lupi et al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>However, only a few reports present the repellency of plant products against other groups of nuisance vectors especially fleas (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">George et al. 2009</xref>). In our investigation among examined plants, the essential oil of three plants, thyme, myrtle and yarrow, showed excellent to good repellency against all tested fleas. The oils of these plants were rich in volatile terpenes, thymol, &#x003b1;&#x02013;pinene, 1, 8 cineol, camphor, limonene, linalool, and geraniol. In spite of effective repellency of these compounds, the major components of <italic>Mentha piperita</italic>, menthen and piperiton, showed low efficacy against fleas.</p><p>Findings of previous studies have proved that, thymol and &#x003b1;&#x02013;pinene are the most toxic compounds (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Trabouli et al. 2002</xref>) and have effective repellent activity against mosquitoes and ticks (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Pandy et al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Jordan et al. 2012</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Meng et al. 2015</xref>). High repellency of thyme and myrtle oils in our study might be associated with these components. Nevertheless, further laboratory and field studies are required to prove repellent efficacy of these compounds.</p><p>Although the amounts of limonene, geraniol, linalool and camphor in above-mentioned essential oils were high in our study, they showed low potency of repellent activity against fleas. Furthermore, 1, 8 cineol which had low repellency against insects, showed different biological activities against mosquitoes and ticks in previous studies (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">El-Seedi et al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to recent studies synthetic compounds, DEET and permethrin, which have shown effective repellency against mosquitoes, could not repel human flea. Low efficacy of these compounds on <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> compared to other vectors might be related to their difference in mode of action (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Dikens and Bohbot 2013</xref>, Daniel et al. 2014), molecular characteristics of odorant binding proteins (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bohbot and Dikens 2012</xref>) and odorant receptors of fleas (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Ditzen et al. 2008</xref>). This study encourages further electrophysiological and molecular studies on human flea to conceive new ideas for the discovery and development of the next generation of repellents.</p><p>Thyme and myrtle oils showed high repellent activity among the tested oils against human flea on human subjects. The repellent effect of <italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic> essential oil showed the highest repellency (lowest ED<sub>50</sub> value, 208&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> and ED<sub>90</sub> 910&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>). According to our literature review, there is no published paper available on the repellent activity of <italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic> essential oil. Majority of published documents were in favor of thyme essential oil repellency against mosquitoes and only a few of them were conducted against ticks (Zhu et al. 2006, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Park et al. 2012</xref>). In previous studies the lowest value of ED<sub>50</sub> seen in laboratory study of <italic>Origanium majorans</italic>, a species of thyme group, against nymphs of <italic>Ixodesricinus</italic> was 15&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> (Zhu et al. 2006). Thyme oil also showed highest repellency against lab-bred <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (ED<sub>50</sub>= 23&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>) and <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> (ED<sub>50</sub>= 468&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>).</p><p>Our ED<sub>50</sub> and ED<sub>90</sub> estimated values for myrtle oil on human subject were 290 and 1172&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively. In the laboratory study of <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Tavassoli et al. (2011)</xref> the ED<sub>50</sub> and ED<sub>90</sub> values for myrtle essential oil against lab-bred <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> were calculated as 110 and 540&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively. Moreover, in a laboratory study on animal model, using K and D apparatus against lab reared <italic>Phlebotomus papatasi</italic>, Yaghoobi-Ershadi et al. (2006) reported the ED<sub>50</sub> and ED<sub>90</sub> values of myrtle oil 114 and 671&#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> respectively. Interestingly, in our study the ED<sub>50</sub> and ED<sub>90</sub> values of myrtle oil are very close to these studies.</p><p>Based on the repellent result against <italic>Pulex irritans</italic> we recommend <italic>Ziziphora tenuiore</italic> and <italic>Myrtus communis</italic> essential oils for further studies to develop appropriate effective formulations. Field trials should be carried out to evaluate the operational feasibility and dermal toxicity over a long period. It is important to determine whether widespread application of these repellents would produce an overall reduction of vector biting.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Based on our findings the two essential oils, thyme and myrtle, are preferable in terms of repellency effect against human flea. Further electrophysiological and molecular studies are recommended to identify the mode of action of these oils and nature of flea olfactory system in order to develop new generation of repellents.</p><p>Measures to determine the appropriate formulation of recommended repellents and comprehensive field studies to evaluate their potency in bite reduction and possible adverse effects are necessary.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>This work was financially supported by ZUMS. The authors would like to express gratitude to Dr Bighlari, chief of ZUMS and Dr Faghihzadeh, deputy of research and information technology of ZUMS for their valuable help. We would like to thank staff of Zanjan, Mahneshan, and Khodabandeh, Health Centers for their kind collaborations. The authors also thank Dr Yazdineghad for confirmation of herbal identification, Mr Zargharan (Behavar Chemical Co) for donating the technical grade permethrin, Mr Salimi and Mr Mehreghan for excellent assistance in laboratory studies and members of animal house for providing laboratory animals. We also express our gratitude to two anonymous reviewers for their critical review of the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakkali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Idaomar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Biological effects of essential oils. A review</article-title>. 
<source>Food and Chemical Toxicology</source>. 
<volume>46</volume>: 
<fpage>446</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>475</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bissinger</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2010</year>) 
<article-title>Tick repellents: Past, present, and future</article-title>. 
<source>Pestic Biochem Physiol</source>. 
<volume>96</volume>: 
<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>79</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bohbot</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Odorant receptor modulation: ternary paradigm for mode of action of insect repellents</article-title>. 
<source>Neuropharmacology</source>. 
<volume>62</volume>: 
<fpage>2086</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>2095</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dautel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2004</year>) 
<article-title>Test systems for tick repellents</article-title>. 
<source>Int J Med Microbiol</source>. 
<volume>293</volume>(
<issue>37</issue>): 
<fpage>182</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>188</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15147006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debboun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>P. F</given-names></name><name><surname>rances</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2014</year>) 
<source>Insect Repellents Handbook</source>, 
<edition>Second Edition</edition>
<publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Fabbro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Correction: From Chemistry to Behavior. Molecular Structure and Bioactivity of Repellents against <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> Ticks</article-title>. 
<source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>(
<issue>7</issue>): 10.1371/annotation/6636cea1-b3f2-4f93-acf7-b34c5aabce07.doi:10.1371/annotation/6636cea1-b3f2-4f93-acf7-b34c5aabce0.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dickens</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohbot</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>Mini review: Mode of action of mosquito repellents</article-title>. 
<source>Pestic Biochem Physiol</source>. 
<volume>106</volume>(
<issue>3</issue>): 
<fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>155</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ditzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Voshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Insect odorant receptors are molecular targets of the insect repellent DEET</article-title>. 
<source>Science</source>. 
<volume>319</volume>: 
<fpage>1838</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>1842</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18339904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mannig</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruffolo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Piesman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Karchesy</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Ability of two natural products, Nootkatone and Carvacrol, to suppress <italic>Ixodesscapularis</italic> and <italic>Amblyomma americanum</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) in a lyme disease endemic area of New Jersey</article-title>. 
<source>J Econ Entomol</source>. 
<volume>102</volume>(
<issue>6</issue>): 
<fpage>2316</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>2324</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20069863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Seedi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalil</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Azeem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Taher</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Chemical composition and repellency of essential oils from four medicinal plants against <italic>Ixodesricinus</italic> nymphs (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title>. 
<source>J Med Entomol</source>. 
<volume>49</volume>(
<issue>5</issue>): 
<fpage>1067</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>1075</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23025188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faulde</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Uedelhoven</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Malerius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2006</year>) 
<article-title>Factory-based permethrin impregnation of uniforms: residual activity against <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ixodesricinus</italic> in bottle dress uniforms worn under field condition and cross-contamination during the laundering and storage process</article-title>. 
<source>Mil Med</source>. 
<volume>171</volume>: 
<fpage>472</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>477</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16808123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faulde</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Uedelhoven</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2003</year>) 
<article-title>Contact toxicity and residual activity of different permethrin-based fabric impregnation methods for <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae), <italic>Ixodesricinus</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) and <italic>Lepisma saccharina</italic> (Thysanura: Lepismatidae)</article-title>. 
<source>J Med Entomol</source>. 
<volume>40</volume>: 
<fpage>935</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>941</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14765673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Okello</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Port</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparagano</surname><given-names>OAE</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Use of plant-derived products to control arthropods of veterinary importance: A review</article-title>. 
<source>Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</source>. 
<volume>1149</volume>: 
<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>26</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19120167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparagano</surname><given-names>OAE</given-names></name><name><surname>Okello</surname><given-names>GPE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Repellence of plant essential oils to <italic>Dermanyssus gallinae</italic> and toxicity to the non-target invertebrate <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic></article-title>. 
<source>Vet Parasitol</source>. 
<volume>162</volume>: 
<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>134</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19264408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparagano</surname><given-names>OAE</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Present and future potential of plant-derived products to control arthropods of veterinary and medical significance</article-title>. 
<source>Parasit Vectors</source>. 
<volume>7</volume>: 
<fpage>28</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24428899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivakumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Laboratory evaluation of Indian medicinal plants as repellents against malaria, dengue and filariasis vector mosquitoes</article-title>. 
<source>Parasitol Res</source>. 
<volume>114</volume>: 
<fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>612</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25399815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemingway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2000</year>) 
<article-title>Insecticide resistance in insect vectors of human disease</article-title>. 
<source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. 
<volume>45</volume>: 
<fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>391</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10761582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Efficacy of plant-derived and synthetic compounds on clothing as repellents against <italic>Ixodes scapularis</italic> and <italic>Amblyomma americanum</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title>. 
<source>J Med Entomol</source>. 
<volume>49</volume>(
<issue>1</issue>): 
<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>106</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22308777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Comparative Repellency of essential oils against <italic>Culexpipiens</italic> Pallen (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. 
<source>J Korean Soc Appl Biol Chem</source>. 
<volume>52</volume>(
<issue>4</issue>): 
<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>359</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klun</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Debboun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2004</year>) 
<article-title>Comparative resistance of <italic>Anopheles albimanus</italic> and <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> to N, N-diethyl-3-methylbenzamide (Deet) and 2-methylpiperidinyl-3-cyclohexen-1carboxamide (AI3-37220) in laboratory human-volunteer repellent assays</article-title>. 
<source>J Med Entomol</source>. 
<volume>41</volume>: 
<fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>422</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15185944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koc</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Repellent activities of some Labiatae plant essential oils against the saltmarsh mosquito <italic>Ochlerotatuscaspius</italic> (Pallas, 1771) (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. 
<source>Parasitol Res</source>. 
<volume>110</volume>: 
<fpage>2205</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>2209</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22179264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koul</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Walla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhaliwal</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2008</year>) 
<article-title>Essential oils as green pesticides: potential and constraints</article-title>. 
<source>Biopestic Int</source>. 
<volume>4</volume>(
<issue>1</issue>): 
<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>84</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krober</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourquin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>A standaised <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> test method for evaluating tick repellents</article-title>. 
<source>Pestic Biochem Physiol</source>. 
<volume>107</volume>: 
<fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>168</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shra</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Satya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Repellent, larvicidal and pupicidal properties of essential oils and their formulations against the housefly, <italic>Musca domestica</italic></article-title>. 
<source>Med Vet Entomol</source>. 
<volume>25</volume>: 
<fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>31</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21338379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>The efficacy of repellents against <italic>Aedes</italic>, <italic>Anopheles</italic>, <italic>Culex</italic> and <italic>Ixodes</italic> spp. A literature review</article-title>. 
<source>Travel Med Infect Dis</source>. 
<volume>11</volume>: 
<fpage>374</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>411</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24201040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maia</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Plant based insect repellents: a review of their efficacy, development and testing</article-title>. 
<source>Malar J</source>. 
<volume>10</volume>(
<issue>1</issue>): 
<fpage>S11</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21411012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manikkam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrero-Bosagna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Trans generational actions of environmental compounds on reproductive disease and identification of epigenetic biomarkers of ancestral exposures</article-title>. 
<source>PLOS ONE</source>. 
<volume>7</volume>(
<issue>2</issue>): 
<fpage>e31901</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22389676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa Junior</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro-Arellano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>Evaluation of DEET and eight essential oils for repellency against nymphs of the lone star tick, <italic>Amblyomma americanum</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title>. 
<source>Exp Appl Acarol</source>. 
<volume>68</volume>(
<issue>2</issue>): 
<fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>249</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26590930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naghibi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosaddegh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Motamed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2005</year>) 
<article-title>Labiatae family in folk medicine in Iran: from ethonobotany to pharmacology</article-title>. 
<source>Iran J Pharm Res</source>. 
<volume>2</volume>: 
<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>79</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neiro</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivero-Velber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stashenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2010</year>) 
<article-title>Repellent activity of essential oils: a review</article-title>. 
<source>Bioresource Technology</source>. 
<volume>101</volume>: 
<fpage>372</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>378</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19729299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odalo</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Omolo</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Malebo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anjira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Njeru</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndiege</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassanali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2005</year>) 
<article-title>Repellency of essential oils of some plants from the Kenyan coast against <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title>. 
<source>Acta Tropica</source>. 
<volume>95</volume>: 
<fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>218</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16018957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Upadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>Insecticidal and repellent activities of thymol from the essential oil of <italic>Trachyspermum ammi</italic> (Linn) Sprague seeds against <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic></article-title>. 
<source>Parasitol Res</source>. 
<volume>105</volume>: 
<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>512</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19343365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YU</given-names></name><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Chemical composition, larvicidal action, and adult repellency of <italic>Thymus magnus</italic> against <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic></article-title>. 
<source>J Am Mosq Control Assoc</source>. 
<volume>28</volume>(
<issue>3</issue>): 
<fpage>192</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>198</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23833899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellegrino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stensmyr</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>A natural polymorphism alters odor and DEET sensitivity in an insect odorant receptor</article-title>. 
<source>Nature</source>. 
<volume>478</volume>: 
<fpage>511</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>514</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21937991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitarokili</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaelakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koliopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Giatropoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzakou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Chemical composition, larvicidal evaluation, and adult repellency of endemic Greek thymus essential oils against the mosquito vector of West Nile virus</article-title>. 
<source>Parasitol Res</source>. 
<volume>109</volume>: 
<fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>430</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21301870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>1998</year>) 
<article-title>Pharmacokinetics, formulation, and safety of insect repellent N,N-diethyl-3-methylbenzamide (DEET): A review</article-title>. 
<source>J Am Mosq Control Assoc</source>. 
<volume>14</volume>: 
<fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>27</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9599319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saeidnia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghohari</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokhber-Dezfuli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiuchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>A review on phytochemistry and medicinal properties of the genus <italic>Achillea</italic></article-title>. 
<source>Daru</source>. 
<volume>19</volume>(
<issue>3</issue>): 
<fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>186</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22615655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Service</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2012</year>) 
<source>Medical Entomology for Students</source>. 
<edition>5th Edition</edition>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sfara</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mougabure-Cueto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerba</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Alzogaray</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Adaptation of the repellency response to DEET in <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic></article-title>. 
<source>J Insect Physiol</source>. 
<volume>57</volume>: 
<fpage>1431</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>1436</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21801727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanczyk</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brookfield</surname><given-names>JFY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2010</year>) 
<article-title>Behavioral insensitivity to DEET in <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> is a genetically determined trait residing in changes in sensillum function</article-title>. 
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci, USA</source>. 
<volume>107</volume>: 
<fpage>8575</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>8580</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20439757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sudakin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Trevathan</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2003</year>) 
<article-title>Deet: a review and update of safety and risk in the general population</article-title>. 
<source>J Toxicol Clin Toxicol</source>. 
<volume>41</volume>: 
<fpage>831</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>839</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14677793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swale</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloomquist</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2014</year>) 
<article-title>Neurotoxicity and mode of action of N,N-diethyl-Meta Tolamide (DEET)</article-title>. 
<source>PLOS ONE</source>. 
<volume>9</volume>(
<issue>8</issue>): 
<fpage>e103713</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25101788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tavassoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shayeghi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abai</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vatandoost</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoobdel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaderi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>Repellency Effects of Essential Oils of Myrtle (<italic>Myrtuscommunis</italic>), Marigold (<italic>Calendula officinalis</italic>) Compared with DEET against <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> on Human Volunteers</article-title>. 
<source>Iran J Arthropod-Borne Dis</source>. 
<volume>5</volume>(
<issue>2</issue>): 
<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>22</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22808414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traboulsi</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Taoubi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Haj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessiere</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rammal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2002</year>) 
<article-title>Insecticidal properties of essential plant oils against the mosquito <italic>Culexpipiensmolestus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. 
<source>Pest Management Science</source>. 
<volume>58</volume>: 
<fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>495</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11997977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group> (
<year>2013</year>) 
<source>Repellent and Toxicants for Personal Protection</source>. WHO/CDS/WHOPES/GCDPP/2000.5.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaghoobi-Ershadi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhavan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahanifard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vatandoost</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>Gh</given-names></name><name><surname>Moosavi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahraei-Ramazani</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdoli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arandian</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2000</year>) 
<article-title>Repellency Effect of Myrtle Essential Oil and DEET against <italic>Phlebotomus papatasi</italic>, under laboratory conditions</article-title>. 
<source>Iranian J Publ Health</source>. 
<volume>35</volume>(
<issue>3</issue>): 
<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;
<lpage>13</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group> (
<year>2014</year>) 
<source>The Toxicology and Biochemistry of Insecticides</source>. 
<edition>Second Edition</edition>
<publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>