<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Antimicrobial activities of the plants' extracts were determined using standard ATCC strain; for Gram-negative bacteria (
 <italic>Shigella sonnnei</italic> ATCC 11060, 
 <italic>Salmonella Typhimurium</italic> ATCC 14025, 
 <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic> ATCC 13311, 
 <italic>Klebsiella pnuemoniae</italic> NCTC 9633, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 13706 and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 27853
 <italic>)</italic>. For Gram-positive bacteria 
 <italic>used Bacillus subtilis</italic> ATCC 11774, 
 <italic>Bacillus crew</italic> ATCC10876, Methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 35501, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 33862 following agar well diffusion method (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Balouiri et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Magaldi et al., 2004</xref>). Bacterial suspensions were prepared in physiological saline solution (0.9%). The suspension turbidity compared with a 0.5 McFarland turbidity standard, number of bacterial cells approximately 1–2 × 10
 <sup>8</sup> CFU/ mL for each of the tested bacteria.1 ml from each organism suspension of was taken and poured onto sterile Petri plates above which 20 ml of Muller and Hinton agar was poured. A sterile Cork borer of 8 mm size was used to create wells in the agar plates. Stock solution for the antimicrobial activity test was prepared using 100% dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) at 100 mg/mL. The resultant solution was subsequently diluted using two-fold dilution method to 50 mg/mL, 25 mg/mL, 12.5 mg/mL, 6.25 mg/mL, 3.125 mg/mL, and 1.56 mg/mL using methanol as solvent. Using a micropipette, 100 μL of each extracts concentrations were poured into each of three wells on all plates. Methanol was run as a negative control in well four. Then in order to dry solution, the plates were left uncovered in a sterile safety cabinet for 20 min (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Dkhil et al., 2020</xref>). After incubation at 35 °C ± 2 °C for 24 h, the zone of inhibition’s size was measured. The test was done in duplicates and performed thrice, and the result presented as mean of inhibition zone. Antibiotics sensitivity profile for commercially a viable drug against tested bacteria were performed to compare their efficacies with the bacterial spectrum and susceptibility profile of tested plants.
</p>
