<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Traditionally, the decoctions of the leaves of 
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> were taken by postnatal mothers to aid in the recovery of the uterus [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The plant has also been used in managing menstrual problems, as an antidiabetic treatment, to treat arthritis and also to boost the immune system. Besides, the leaves have been used to treat headaches, fevers [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and toothaches [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> has been associated with many pharmacological abilities such as antioxidant and antidiabetic properties [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Adam et al. [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] have discovered that aqueous extract of 
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> has an antihyperglycemic property which increases insulin secretion activity. Meanwhile, the methanolic and ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> increased basal and insulin-mediated glucose uptake into adipocytes cells. The leaves of 
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> possess anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and are able to reduce nociception when tested on animal models [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The plant also serves as a wound-healing agent with enhanced fibroblast proliferation in rats [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and has anticancer potential as it caused apoptosis in human ovarian carcinoma cell lines [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Apart from that, Zahra et al. [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] suggested the antiulcerogenic effect of 
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> when tested on gastric walls of rats by inhibiting the submucosal edema and leucocytes infiltration of the submucosal layer. Findings by Amiera et al. [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] proposed the ability of the aqueous var. 
 <italic>deltoidea</italic> and var. 
 <italic>angustifolia</italic> extract as a uterotonic agent to induce the labor process and treat postpartum hemorrhage. Recent animal studies have shown that the leaves of 
 <italic>Ficus deltoidea</italic> var. 
 <italic>trengganuensis</italic>, var. 
 <italic>kunstleri</italic>, var. 
 <italic>intermedia</italic>, var. 
 <italic>deltoidea</italic>, var. 
 <italic>motleyana</italic>, and var. 
 <italic>bilobata</italic> exhibited significant hypoglycemic effects in normal rats [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
</p>
