<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38">Antioxidants are agents that scavenge free radicals, preventing cellular damage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Reductants are involved in donating hydrogen atoms and breaking down free-radical chains [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Phenols and reductants are good electron donors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. An inadequate supply of free radicals may damage DNA, protein, and lipid molecules, and it may disrupt membrane phospholipids, thereby leading to diseases and cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The methanol extract of stems showed prominent DPPH and ABTS free-radical scavenging activity and reducing power. However, the chloroform extract significantly quenched ferrous ions, showing noteworthy chelating activity. Oxidative stress is related to many health issues such as malignancy, diabetes, cardiac and neurodegenerative disorders, amongst others. Synthetic antioxidants can be used to cure the diseases; however, they may damage vital organs. Therefore, natural antioxidants are of prime importance for better health [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The antioxidative response of 
 <italic>M. buxifolia</italic>, such as its free-radical-scavenging activity, reducing power, and metal-chelating ability, was found to be linked to the presence of antioxidants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Furthermore, it was reported that the solvent used, the plant part used, the mode of processing, and the fractionation scheme influence the extraction of antioxidants and their activities. A number of phytochemicals, such as 3-OH benzoic acid and epicatechin, were reported to have antioxidative potential [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Chelation agents that bind to pro-oxidant metals are regarded as active secondary antioxidants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. These results are also in agreement with studies showing that the antioxidant activity is proportional to the phenolic compound content, which is associated with the solvent used [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The extracts in this study also presented antioxidant activity via the iron-chelation and radical-scavenging assays, thereby indicating the presence of both primary and secondary antioxidants. Primary antioxidants neutralize free radicals to prevent the initiation and propagation of oxidative chain reactions, while secondary antioxidants suppress radical formation and protect against oxidative damage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].
</p>
