<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Soil salinity is an abiotic stress that limits crop yield and productivity in an ecosystem. Soil salinity has been shown to affect approximately 800 million hectares of arable land worldwide
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. It is currently receiving considerable attention in global agricultural research because of its significant threat to plant growth and development
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>. Other studies have shown that salt stress can alter a range of physiological and biochemical processes and inhibit enzyme activities of carbon (C) and nitrogen (N) metabolism
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup>. This effect has been demonstrated among crops such as 
 <italic>Zea mays</italic> L.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>, tomato
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>, wheat
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>, chickpea
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup> and Ethiopian mustard
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Research indicates that salt stress affects the content of lipids, proteins and nucleic acids
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup> and changes the morphological, physiological, biochemical, and molecular characteristics of plants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. Studies however, indicate that salt stress significantly affects the fresh and dry weight of plants, which finally results in a decline in crop yield
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. The constituents of medicinal plants can be changed in relation to their physiology and biochemistry prior to the effects of soil salinity which caused enormous yield losses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, the negative effect of salt stress in medicinal plants has gradually been observed in 
 <italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>peppermint</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>geranium</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>sage</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>, and 
 <italic>Mentha pulegium</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
