<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Besides amino acids and fatty acids, hempseed is rich in lignanamides
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> such as cannabisin A, B, C, etc., caffeoyltyramine-like compounds, and other polyphenols.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup> Because the common part of these constituents is the phenylpropionamide moiety, to simplify, we refer to such constituents as phenylpropionamides in the text. In our previous study on hempseed, more than 30 phenylpropionamides were isolated.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup> We further established a lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated BV2 microglia cells model to explore the anti-neuroinflammatory activity of these compounds. The results showed that most lignanamides had good anti-neuroinflammatory activity by inhibiting the NF-κB signaling pathway.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup> Neuroinflammation is a critical pathological hallmark in the development of Alzheimer’s disease and other neurodegenerative diseases, and high expression of inflammatory mediators in the brain is associated with Aβ deposition and neurofibrillary tangles.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> Lipopolysaccharide (LPS), a critical component in the outer membrane of Gram-negative bacteria, has been used as a stimulator of microglial cells and in animal models to trigger systemic and central inflammatory responses.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> Recent studies have shown that the expression of Aβ, progressive neurodegeneration, loss of learning and memory, and the release of neuroinflammatory mediators have been detected in LPS-induced animals.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20" class="xref">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
