<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For real-time [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> measurements, all cell types were grown as monolayers until 70–80% confluency. Cells were incubated at 37 °C for 30 min with 5-µM Fura 2-AM in complete medium, followed by two gentle washes. De-esterification was allowed for a further 30 min, and then, the monolayers were mounted on the stage of an Olympus IX-81 inverted fluorescence microscope (Olympus America, Center Valley, PA, USA). Cells were superfused continuously with HBSS (in mM: 118 NaCl, 4.8 KCl, 1.23 CaCl
 <sub>2</sub>, 0.6 KH
 <sub>2</sub>PO
 <sub>4</sub>, 4.6 NaHCO
 <sub>3</sub>, 0.6 NaH
 <sub>2</sub>PO
 <sub>4</sub>, and 5.5 glucose, pH 7.4) at a flow rate of 2 mL/min. Cells were exposed to compounds under investigation by switching from the control medium (HBSS with Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>) to the compound-containing medium (working concentrations of treatment prepared in HBSS with Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>) for 30s, unless noted otherwise. Control buffer and treatments were always kept in separate chambers to prevent any potential interaction between the compounds. Relative [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> was allowed to return to baseline after a response before exposing the cells to any successive treatment. Cells were pretreated with the TRPA1 antagonist HC-030031 (20 µM) for 20 min to block TRPA1 activation with essential oils. ATP (25 µM) was routinely utilized to confirm receptor-effector coupling in control parental HEK 293 cells. The [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> measurements were recorded in individual cells using a fluorescence imaging system (Easy Ratio Pro software, Horiba Scientific, North Edison, NJ, USA) equipped with a multi-wavelength DeltaRAM monochromator (Photon Technology International, Inc., Edison, NJ, USA) and a QuantEM 512SC electron multiplying charge-coupled device camera (Teledyne Photometrics, Tucson, AZ, USA), as previously described [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Images and real-time [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> data were acquired using an alternating excitation wavelength protocol (340 nm and 380 nm, 20 Hz) and emission wavelength of 510 nm. Background fluorescence was automatically corrected for the experiments using Easy Ratio Pro software. The signals obtained at 340 and 380 nm were calculated as the 340/380 ratio and used as an index to measure relative changes in [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> from the baseline [
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-25-04873" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>] and expressed as mean ± SEM.
</p>
