<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">Agricultural wastes (lignocellulosic biomass) composed of cellulose, hemicelluloses and lignin, which can be enzymatically converted by microbes into various values added biotechnological products (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Baig 2020</xref>). Plant biomass waste is therefore, a desirable alternative raw material to produce functional products since it is readily available and bio-renewable. Fungi such as 
 <italic>Pleurotus</italic> spp.
 <italic>, Polyporus ostriformi</italic>, 
 <italic>Phanerochaete chrysosporium</italic> and many more have colonizing potentials on ligno-cellulosic materials (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Singh et al., 2012</xref>). 
 <italic>P. pulmonarius</italic> is an economically important edible and medicinal macrofungus that traditionally grown on different substrates namely; corn cob, corn straw, peanut straw, soybean straw, rice straw, rape straw, wheat bran and cottonseed hulls (
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2019</xref>). Information gathered by 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Baeva et al. (2019)</xref> revealed that, species of genus 
 <italic>Pleurotus</italic> capable of utilizing different agrowastes to produce polysaccharides. Fungal polysaccharides, especially EPS possess therapeutic properties like antimicrobial, antioxidant, and anticancer (
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Osemwegie et al., 2020</xref>). This has made EPS to receive greater interest for extensive applications in food, pharmaceutical, and cosmeceutical industries (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Ozcan and Oner, 2015</xref>). Considering a great interest and uses of EPS for different biological purposes, submerged culture of fungi with agrowastes will be a new approach and an eco-friendly strategy to produce EPS. This study therefore, produces EPS by 
 <italic>P. pulmonarius</italic> in submerged fermentation with some agro-wastes namely; peels of plantain, pineapple, mango, groundnut shell, coconut coir and walnut husk. The antimicrobial, antioxidant and prebiotic activities of EPS produced by 
 <italic>P. pulmonarius</italic> were also investigated.
</p>
