<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">According to the study of 
 <xref rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr">Qamar et al. (2020)</xref>, performed on 32,297 molecules with potential antiviral activities used in traditional Chinese medicine, two flavonols namely myricitrine and myricetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-D-glucopyranoside have been docked for their potential anti-COVID-19 capacity against SARS-CoV-2 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>. The obtained results were compared with nelfinavir, prulifloxacin and colistin as positive controls. The data showed that these compounds had a strong ability to bind with the receptor-binding site and catalytic dyad (Cys-145 and His-41) of SARS-CoV-2 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> with high docking scores, high binding affinity and close interactions with the conserved catalytic dyad residues. Indeed, these compounds are also non-toxic, biologically active and naturally found in many medicinal species. In addition, the ability of many flavonols namely astragalin, kaempferol, quercetin, quercetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside and quercitrin to interact with SARS-CoV-2 proteins (3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>, PL
 <sup>pro</sup>) was studied. The data indicated that all the tested molecules have consistent interactions and possess very good binding affinities to all the viral proteins compared to remdesivir as positive control. The highest docking score was observed in quercetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, which binds to His74, Arg83, Tyr155, Asn157, His176 amino acid residues of viral protein at the binding pocket of PL
 <sup>pro</sup> with eight hydrogen bonds (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Hiremath et al., 2020</xref>). Also, quercetin derivatives including quercetin-3-vicianoside, quercetin-3-glucuronide-7-glucoside and quercetin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-galactoside gave low binding energy with M
 <sup>pro</sup> target (
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Joshi et al., 2020</xref>). Further, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. (2006)</xref> reported that quercetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-β-galactoside bound to SARS-CoV 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> with the Gln189 residue playing a key role in stabilizing binding. In the paper of (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Bhatia, 2020</xref>) and his collaborators, kaempferol-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucuronide showed a high docking score (−9.8 kcal/mol), which could be explained by the presence of hydroxyl groups, acid and ketone functions, able to promote hydrogen bonds and Van Der Waal interactions. According to the study of 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Da Silva et al. (2020)</xref>, all glucuronide and sulfate derivatives of quercetin and kaempferol interact better than their aglycones (quercetin and kaempferol) to the 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>.
</p>
