<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Natural products continue to make extensive contributions to human health, alongside modern medicine and in drug discovery. According to reports from the World Health Organization (WHO), universally, 80% of people still trust and use natural medicines; at present, several drugs also owe their inception to medicinal plants. The search for new molecules with therapeutic potential among natural resources is ongoing, and has resulted in numerous important findings, that include anti-oxidant, anti-inflammatory, analgesics, antibiotics, and anti-cancer components. The widespread genetic diversity of natural medicinal plants offers several important opportunities for the improvement of humankind like food production containing single ingredients with nutritional value and medicinal properties [
 <xref rid="B1-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Currently, phytotherapies and pharmacologists represent an around $14 billion market per year, or approximately 5% of the current $280 billion per annum world market for traditional medicine. As a thing of noteworthy, there is a huge difference exists between developed and developing countries in making use of herbal products in their medications. Comparatively the developing countries use plant products in their 25% and 80% of medication strategies [
 <xref rid="B6-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Of the 56% of currently recommended, or prescribed synthetic drugs linked to natural sources in some fashion, 24% are derived from plant species, nearly 9% are synthetic drugs developed using natural products as the reference, around 6% are isolated directly from natural plant species, and 5% are of animal source [
 <xref rid="B7-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, still there is a huge amount of drug resources being untapped. In the cradle of nature having around 350,000 to 550,000 plant species, of which less than 20% species have been explored for therapeutic applications [
 <xref rid="B8-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Dendropanax</italic> genus belongs to the family Araliaceae, and is found throughout the south-western region of East Asia, Korea, and Japan; furthermore, it is considered a neotropical genus containing approximately 91 to 95 species distributed from the Malay Peninsula and Central South America [
 <xref rid="B9-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Indeed, all species but 
 <italic>D. morbiferus</italic> are native to the tropics of South Korea, predominantly found on Jeju Island [
 <xref rid="B12-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Most species of the genus 
 <italic>Dendropanax</italic> is historically important trees that are largely evergreen, and numerous parts of these plant species commonly been used by indigenous peoples to recover from various disorders, atopic dermatitis, asthma, sore throat, anemia, anti-oxidative, viral infections and kidney problems [
 <xref rid="B16-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The traditional use of 
 <italic>Dendropanax</italic> species was used for treating inflammatory and arthritis conditions [
 <xref rid="B9-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Elsewhere, the leaves, stems, roots, and seeds of some species have been used as a form of alternative medicine for lung problems, cough, and neurological disorders, including paralysis, stroke, and migraine [
 <xref rid="B19-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-antioxidants-09-00962" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
