<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study is the first one linking fennel essential oil yield variations to insect abundance and family richness. We showed here that family richness of insects trapped along fennel crops was positively linked with essential oil yield. If we keep in mind that, in fennel, the fruits are the part of the plant containing the highest amount of essential oil, this result is in line with the substantial literature showing the importance of a high diversity of flower-visiting-insect for the yield, quantity and quality of seeds and fruits, and their market value [
 <xref rid="B28-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. This has notably been emphasized in other mass-flowering crops (e.g., oilseed rape [
 <xref rid="B11-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], sunflower [
 <xref rid="B10-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]) or orchards (e.g., apples or/and pears [
 <xref rid="B6-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]). From ecological studies, we know that a community with diverse and complementary traits can enhance the ecosystem functions [
 <xref rid="B68-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. This is notably the case, for example, for pumpkin [
 <xref rid="B73-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] or apple orchards [
 <xref rid="B74-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Here, increasing flower-visitor richness involves increased diversity of insect traits (different mouthparts, foraging behavior variation, hour and date of insect activity) and matches the complementary hypothesis of functional diversity [
 <xref rid="B68-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-insects-12-00404" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. 
</p>
