<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Total phenolic compounds and total tannins in feeds were analyzed following the procedure originally described by Makkar et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00283" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], with modifications as follows. In a 50 mL centrifuge tube, 10 mL acetone 70% (
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) was added to 200 mg of finely ground feeds. Samples were vortex-mixed for 1 min and sonicated in a cold-water bath (4 °C) for 15 min. The tubes were centrifuged at 2500× g for 15 min at 4 °C and the supernatant was collected. The residual solid pellet was re-extracted exactly as above using 10 mL methanol 80% (
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>). The supernatants were combined, and organic solvents were evaporated within 6 min, under vacuum, using a rotary evaporator system (Büchi, R-114, Switzerland) set at 45 °C. The remaining (4 mL) water was mixed with 8 mL methanol and samples were stored at −80°C. For analyses, extracts from pomegranate pomace and pomegranate-containing concentrate were diluted 1:3 with methanol/water (2:1, 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>). Total phenolic compounds were quantified by mixing: 100 μL sample extract, 900 μL distilled water, 500 μL Folin-Ciocalteu reagent (1 N), and 2.5 mL sodium carbonate 20% (
 <italic class="italic">w</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>). The mixture was vortex-mixed, incubated in the dark for 40 min, and centrifuged at 2500× g for 10 min at 4 °C. The absorbance was measured at 725 nm using a double beam UV/VIS spectrophotometer model UV-1601 ( Shimadzu Corporation, Milan, Italy). For the analysis of no-tannin phenolics, sample extracts were first treated with insoluble polyvinylpolypyrrolidone (PVPP) in order to remove tannins. Specifically, 2 mL of sample extract (diluted 1:1 with distilled water) was added to 100 mg PVPP, incubated for 20 min at 4 °C and centrifuged at 2500× 
 <italic class="italic">g</italic> for 20 min at 4 °C. The supernatant (200 μL) was mixed with 800 μL of water and the analysis of no-tannin phenols was performed using Folin–Ciocalteu reagent and 20% sodium carbonate, as previously described. Tannins were calculated as the difference between total phenols and total no-tannin phenols. In all the assays, quantification of phenolic compounds was achieved using standard solutions of tannic acid (TA) ranging from 0 to 100 μg/mL. Total phenols and tannins were expressed as g TA equivalents per kg DM.
</p>
