<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hyperuricemia is a long-time purine metabolic disorder recognized as a result of excessive serum uric acid status in blood and associated with gout, renal sicknesses, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, and atherosclerosis [
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B131-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. militaris</italic> has been reported for its anti-hyperuricemic effect in hyperuricemic mice at different doses, reaching the levels of normal mice [
 <xref rid="B132-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. In another study, Yong et al. [
 <xref rid="B133-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>] also reported cordycepin’s potential as an anti-hyperuricemic in hyperuricemic mice. Infertility can be described as a disease condition where females are not able to become pregnant despite having frequent, unprotected sex for at least a year for most couples. According to the reports, cordycepin has been proved potent in increasing both the sperm quality and quantity. 
 <italic>C. militaris</italic> supplementation has been stated to bring about an increase of serum cordycepin concentration, which concurrently enhances testosterone and estradiol-17 levels, ultimately increasing the percentage of motile sperm cells [
 <xref rid="B134-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. In addition to this cordycepin is also reported to increase semen production as well as sperm quality in boars [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The effect of cordycepin on testosterone levels in male rats was reported. It was found that the concentration of testosterone in the serum of the rats was significantly increased by 
 <italic>C. militaris</italic>. Therefore, fruiting bodies of 
 <italic>C. militaris</italic> grown on the drone bee medium could act as an integrative medicine for the treatment of reproductive problems caused by insufficient testosterone levels in human males [
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. On the other hand, chronic kidney disease (CKD) is a disease condition where the condition of the kidneys deteriorates steadily and has been related with both non-communicable diseases, e.g., diabetes and hypertension, and infectious diseases like hepatitis B, malaria, and HIV [
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. Clinical research exploring the possible cordycepin application has confirmed the beneficial effects in decreasing the progression of end-stage kidney disease in CKD patients [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Moreover, other pharmaceutical applications of cordycepin are also recommended, such as increasing creatinine clearance, serum albumin and hemoglobin, lowering serum creatinine levels as well as improving lipid metabolism [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>].
</p>
