<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Lee (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2019</xref>) asserts that lectins have emerged as a new class of antiviral biologic drugs or biologics by taking advantage of a unique glycosylation pattern only found on the surface of viruses. Lectins, a group of proteins with carbohydrate recognition activity, recognize the SARS-CoV spike protein (Liu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">2015</xref>). Keyaerts et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2007</xref>) found prominent anti-SARS-CoV activity among mannose-specific plant lectins. One of the most potent lectins against the SARS-CoV-induced cytopathicity is the mannose-specific plant lectin isolated from leek (
 <italic>Allium porrum</italic> L.) with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.45 μg/ml and a selectivity index of &gt; 222. The 
 <italic>N</italic>-acetyl glucosamine-specific lectins isolated from the stinging nettle (
 <italic>Urtica dioica</italic> L.) and from the tobacco plant (
 <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> L.) were also markedly active against the SARS-CoV with a selectivity index of &gt; 77 and &gt; 59, respectively (Kumaki et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2011</xref>). A mannose-specific lectin (agglutinin) of 
 <italic>Hippeastrum striatum</italic> (Lam.) H.E.Moore prevented the penetration of SARS-CoV into Vero E6 cells (EC
 <sub>50</sub> 2.5 μg/ml at 4 °C) (Keyaerts et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2007</xref>). SARS-CoV spike protein contains 12 
 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation sites and the sugars attached to four of these 
 <italic>N-</italic>glycosylation sites have been identified (Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">2010</xref>). Two of the four sugars were found to be high-mannose-type glycans and the other two showed complex glycan structures (Zhang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2005</xref>). The potent anti-SARS-CoV activity of mannose-specific plant lectins is therefore attributable to the presence of high-mannose-type glycans in the SARS-CoV spike protein (Keyaerts et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2007</xref>; Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">2010</xref>).
</p>
