<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">S. chinensis</italic> contains many bioactive compounds, including lignans, triterpenes, phenolic acids, flavonoids, essential oils, and polysaccharides. Lignans are mainly responsible for the pro-health properties of SCE. These compounds are predominant in SCE fruits, but can also be found in the leaves, shoots, and seeds. They were extracted from the biomass of in vitro cultures [
 <xref rid="B12-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. The most widely represented groups of SCE lignans are dibenzocyclooctadiene lignans, which, due to structural similarity to and occurrence in plants of the 
 <italic class="italic">Schisandra</italic> genus, are often referred to as “schisandra lignans”. Within dibenzocycloactadiene lignans, which occur in the largest amounts in the fruits of 
 <italic class="italic">Schisandra chinensis,</italic> are schisandrin (syn. schisandrol A, wuweizisu A), schisandrin B (syn. gomisin N, wuwezisu B, γ-schisandrin), schisantherin A (syn. gomisin C, schisandrer A), schisantherin B (syn. gomisin B, schisandrer B), schisanhenol (syn. gomisin K3), deoxyschisandrin (syn. schisandrin A), and gomisin A (syn. schisandrol B) [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. A WHO (World Health Organization) monograph [
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] stated that about 30 
 <italic class="italic">Schisandra</italic> lignans were identified, but to ensure the pro-health activity of fruits, their content should not be lower than 0.4%. At present, many more lignans in SCE have been detected. For example, schineolignins A–C, belonging to the butane-type lignans dibenzyl group, were described by Xue et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]; and schilignan F (tetrahydrofuran lignan) was isolated by Yang et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-nutrients-11-00333" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], from rattan stems of SCE. 
</p>
