<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effects of tricin were evaluated in syngeneic orthotopic colon tumor-bearing mouse model, in which the growth of tumor and metastasis of colon cancer cells were monitored using an In Vitro Imaging System (IVIS). The luciferase-tagged mouse cancer cells Colon26-Luc (1 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> cells per 40 μL PBS) were injected into the posterior wall of the rectum of BALB/c mouse under anesthesia. Three days after cell inoculation, live animal whole-body imaging to monitor luciferase-expressing cells in mice was performed to ensure the successful inoculation using IVIS 200 (Xenogen, Alameda, CA, USA). Images were acquired for 1 to 180 s and the photon emission transmitted from each mouse were quantified using Xenogen Living Image (Igor Pro version 3.2 software), and the data were processed to produce graphs according to the average radiance (photons/s/cm
 <sup>2</sup>/sr) [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The tumor-bearing mice were randomized into different groups and received tricin at 19 or 37.5 mg/kg (Tricin-L and Tricin-H, respectively) by oral gavage daily for 18 days (n = 6–13). A group of mice received FOLFOX (7.5 mg/kg fluorouracil and 2.5 mg/kg folinic acid daily for 18 days plus 2.5 mg/kg oxaliplatin once a week) injection intraperitoneally was served as positive control group. The IVIS imaging was performed on Days 1, 9, 15, 18 during treatments so as to monitor the growth of orthotopic tumors. At the end of experiment, mice were undergone IVIS imaging and then sacrificed under anesthesia. Then the lungs were excised for IVIS imaging because the bioluminescence signal of the metastasized Colon26-Luc cells in lungs could not be detected in situ. Meanwhile the spleens, lymph nodes and half of the tumors were collected for isolation of immune cells for further analyses. The lungs were also subjected to histological examination for metastasis level assessment after haematoxylin &amp; eosin (H &amp; E) staining [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Another half of the tumors were subjected to immunohistochemistry staining against CD8 for tumor infiltrating lymphocytes as previously described [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-25-03730" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The animal experiments were approved by the Animal Experimentation Ethics Committee of The Chinese University of Hong Kong (Ref. No. 18/231/MIS). All methods were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations.
</p>
