<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lignocellulosic residues containing a remarkable polysaccharide portion represent a very interesting source of fillers for bioplastics [
 <xref rid="B84-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. The interaction between lignin-containing cellulosic fibers and biopolymers are complex owing to the various composition of cellulosic fibers. The interaction between jute strands and PLA was evaluated. Five different lignin contents of strands were introduced into the PLA with the fiber ratio of 30 wt %. A PLA matrix was prepared in a discontinuous extruder and characterized by tensile tests. Jute strands with a lignin content of 4% were the most suitable to be used as PLA filler as shown by macro and micromechanical analysis. The phenomenon was mainly attributed to their better interaction and dispersion within the PLA matrix and higher intrinsic mechanical properties [
 <xref rid="B138-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">138</xref>]. Lignocellulosic fillers obtained from bioethanol production were blended with PHB. Spectroscopic, thermal and morphological characterization showed there was a high polysaccharide content in the filler. Lignocellulosic filler produced an active effect on the PHB physical aging by acting as a heterogeneous nucleating agent. Infrared spectroscopic data showed that a low interaction between the lignocellulosic filler and PHB was observed. Furthermore, a deterioration of impact and tensile properties in the composites was attributed to this lack of connection. On the other hand, the biocomposites became more resistant to the degradation with concentration of lignocellulosic filler increasing, possibly because of the antibacterial activity of the lignin. Therefore, because lignocellulosic fillers improved the biopolymer properties in a cost-effective and environmentally friendly way, the utilization of these agro-industrial residues held great potential to widen the application of PHB [
 <xref rid="B139-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>].
</p>
