<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-foods-07-00041" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Propolis is a complex material of resinous consistency produced by bees which has a highly variable physical appearance, color, and consistency, depending on many factors such as geographic origin, types of vegetable sources, time of collection, and season of the year [
  <a rid="B1-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-foods-07-00041">1</a>]. Bees use propolis to seal openings in the hive to avoid the entrance of intruders, to maintain a constant inner temperature, to contribute to the attainment of an internal aseptic environment, and overall to protect the hive from widespread bacterial infection [
  <a rid="B1-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-foods-07-00041">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-foods-07-00041">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-foods-07-00041">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-foods-07-00041">4</a>]. Propolis composition is extremely complex and variable, showing the presence of beeswax, resin, essential oils, and pollen. Bees secrete the wax, while resin and oils are obtained from plants, usually taken from secretions or by cutting fragments of vegetative tissues.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The variations in the chemical composition and consequently in the biological activity of propolis, are associated with its type and geographic origin. However, although propolis is a complex mixture, its biological activities are reported due to the presence of the flavonoids, phenolic acids, and ethers mainly obtained from plant-derived substances [
  <a rid="B5-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-foods-07-00041">5</a>]. Hence, although propolis is obviously an animal product, a considerable proportion of its components responsible for biological activities are plant derived. In fact, the resin contains most of the compounds found in extracts consumed by people from many countries as food complements, nutraceuticals, or alternative medicine. In fact, propolis has been extensively used in folk medicine for many years, and there is substantial evidence to indicate that it has antiseptic, antifungal, antibacterical, antiviral, anti-inflammatory, and antioxidant properties [
  <a rid="B4-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-foods-07-00041">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-foods-07-00041">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-foods-07-00041">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-foods-07-00041">7</a>]. Current applications of propolis include over-the-counter preparations for cold syndrome (upper respiratory tract infections, common cold, flu-like infection), as well as dermatological preparations useful in wound healing, treatment of boils, acne, herpes simplex and genitalis, and neurodermatitis, among other ailments [
  <a rid="B4-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-foods-07-00041">4</a>,
  <a rid="B8-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-foods-07-00041">8</a>]. These effects are exerted by the numerous, more than 300, known substances composing propolis [
  <a rid="B9-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-foods-07-00041">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Propolis, which is barely soluble in water, cannot be used as a raw material and it must be purified by extraction with solvents to remove the inert material and preserve the polyphenolic fraction. These last compounds, flavonoids and phenolic acids, are considered to contribute more to the healing effects than the other propolis constituents [
  <a rid="B9-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-foods-07-00041">9</a>]. Propolis extracts are more commonly obtained through conventional techniques, such as ethanolic or aqueous extraction or by Soxhlet [
  <a rid="B10-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-foods-07-00041">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-foods-07-00041">11</a>]. In fact, in commercial and supplemental health care products, propolis is added in the form of extracts which are obtained by soaking crushed propolis in organic solvent or water. Moreover, in the last few years, different studies have shown the extraction with supercritical fluid as a possible alternative method to obtain compounds derived from natural matrices, including propolis [
  <a rid="B10-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-foods-07-00041">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the very high molecular complex composition of propolis, the different extractive processes utilized and the various solvents available to produce the finished products, the evaluation of the total polyphenols extracted, as well as an accurate determination of the single species and of the derived families of compounds with similar chemical properties, are necessary to assure products rich in molecular species and still retaining biological properties. In fact, despite the high number of compounds extracted, the yield of the extraction process is often lower, which could indicate a selectivity depending on the extractive process. Moreover, the different solvents used to solubilize the extracted polyphenols from propolis may have a selective capacity to produce finished products which possess peculiar compositions and biological properties.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we evaluated this aspect by dissolving a unique propolis extract in various solvents obtaining different finished products such as hydroalcoholic, glycolic, glyceric solutions, and oil, as well as a product in the form of powder. The molecular composition of the different preparations was evaluated by high-performance liquid chromatography-UV-electrospray ionization mass (HPLC-UV-ESI-MS) and the antioxidant activity determined by a 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) anti-oxidant assay [
  <a rid="B12-foods-07-00041" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-foods-07-00041">12</a>]. This is more important by considering that the finished products in various forms often require propolis dissolved in specific solvents and supporting matrixes. Finally, up to now, very few data are available on propolis composition in glyceric and glycolic extracts and no information has ever been published on propolis in oil.
 </p>
</sec>
