<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolution of chemical composition of individual macerals</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maturation is the process under which petroleum is generated by thermal cracking of OM at elevated temperature. The combination of organic petrography with AFM-IR allows the maturation process to be followed on a maceral-by-maceral basis, supplementing the traditional analysis of bulk chemical changes in OM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Here the New Albany Shale is artificially matured by hydrous pyrolysis to various stages in the petroleum generation process, and the evolution in the abundance of individual macerals is measured by petrography while the evolution in the composition of individual macerals is measured by AFM-IR.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Initially, immature New Albany Shale holds abundant solid bitumen and 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span>, with a small fraction of intertinite. During maturation, the abundance of inertinite remains qualitatively unchanged. However, the abundance of 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span> and solid bitumen change dramatically during maturation. Similar to petrographic observations in other shale plays
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span> is observed to decrease in abundance throughout the process, finally disappearing at HP temperatures ≥340 °C, while solid bitumen becomes the dominant maceral at high temperatures.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AFM-IR is used to measure to composition of individual macerals, such as solid bitumen, at different maturities (see example of correlative imaging of micron-scale solid bitumen particles in pyrolyzed shale in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). Localized IR spectra averaged over three or more different solid bitumen particles in each of the original New Albany Shale sample and its hydrous pyrolysis derivatives are plotted in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a> (those individual spectra are plotted in Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>–
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>). The A-factor (aliphatic versus aromatic) and C-factor (oxygenated versus aromatic functional groups) are calculated from the average spectra and used as IR proxies for atomic H/C and O/C ratios, respectively
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a> plots these parameters similar to a standard van Krevelen diagram, with green points labeled by maturity as measured by solid bitumen reflectance (BR
  <sub>o</sub>). The plot illustrates the evolution path of solid bitumen during thermal alteration, showing early loss of oxygenated functional groups followed by loss of aliphatic content at higher pyrolysis tempreatures, consistent with trends observed previously in bulk OM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. A similar analysis was perfomed to investigate the chemical evolution of inertinite (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>) and 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a>) with maturity. Direct comparison of the compositional evolution of all macerals is shown in the pseudo van Krevelen diagram (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>). Significant differences between the composition of these macerals are seen at low maturity, but those compositional differences become less significant at higher maturity when the composition of each maceral type tends toward graphite-like (high aromatic content and low aliphatic and oxygenated content). Macerals that are rich in aliphatic/oxygenated content at low maturity (such as 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span>) undergo relatively large compositional changes with maturity, while macerals that are already dominated by aromatic carbon at low maturity (such as inertinite) undergo relatively small compositional changes with maturity. For example, a relatively large difference is found between the composition of 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span> at 0.25% BR
  <sub>o</sub> and at 0.65% BR
  <sub>o</sub> (the highest maturity at which 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span> is detected), consistent with the high petroleum generation potential of 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span>. Inertinite, on the other hand, is mostly unaffected by maturation, with little change in its abundance or composition. Moreover, the range of compositions spanned by a single maceral at different thermal maturities is comparable to the range of compositions spanned by different macerals at a single (low) thermal maturity. This observation suggests that the impact of maturation in OM composition is driven by both an evolution of the abundance of different macerals and a variation in the composition of individual macerals.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Compositional trends in the maturation of individual macerals. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Average localized infrared (IR) spectra from three or more different solid bitumen particles in untreated and artificially matured New Albany Shale samples, with solid bitumen reflectance (BR
     <sub>o</sub>) ranging from 0.25% to 1.17%. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Average localized IR spectra from different locations in 1–2 inertinite particles in samples with BR
     <sub>o</sub> of 0.25 and 0.90%. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Average localized IR spectra from different locations in 1–2 
     <span class="italic">Tasmanites </span>particles in samples with BR
     <sub>o</sub> of 0.25 and 0.65%. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> Pseudo van Krevelen diagram, constructed by plotting the IR proxy for H/C and O/C atomic ratios of 
     <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span>, solid bitumen, and inertinite at different maturities. Solid bitumen reflectance values are indicated adjacent to calculated IR ratios (T, 
     <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span>; B, solid bitumen; and I, inertinite)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2017_2254_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1312" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, here we demonstrate AFM-IR as a powerful new tool to examine organic chemical and mechanical heterogeneity in shale at nanoscale. AFM-IR images can be registered with traditional optical microscopy images, allowing geochemical and geomechanical characterization of individual macerals assigned by organic petrography. The measurement provides chemical and mechanical mapping at a spatial resolution orders of magnitude finer than provided by traditional diffraction-limited IR microscopy, enabling interrogation of chemical and mechanical heterogeneity at the submicron length scales relevant for shale. Using this approach, we examined the evolution of OM composition during petroleum generation at the maceral level. Immature shale contains several different macerals and the average composition of each maceral type differs widely, although the compositional variation between different locations belonging to the same maceral type is limited. The composition of the macerals controls their mechanical properties, with macerals enriched in aromatic carbon (and lean in aliphatic carbon) having relatively high mechanical stiffnesses. During maturation, both the abundance and the composition of the individual macerals evolve. Organic petrology revealed that originally present macerals, such as 
  <span class="italic">Tasmanites</span>, are depleted during petroleum generation, and the OM in shale is dominated by the solid bitumen maceral at maturities above the peak oil level. AFM-IR revealed that the composition of each maceral evolves as well, as each maceral becomes enriched in aromatic carbon and depleted in oxygenated carbon during maturation, similar to the trend commonly observed for bulk analysis of OM. The results suggest the maturation process involves an evolution in both the abundance of individual macerals and in the composition of those macerals.
 </p>
</sec>
