<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mushrooms, which have always been appreciated for their culinary and nutritional value, are now increasingly valued for their many important medicinal properties, so much so that they are used not only as dietary food (functional foods) but also in the form of dietary supplements, nutraceuticals, and mycotherapy products [
 <xref rid="B1-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Their use for promoting and maintaining a good state of health and the treatment of diseases has been around since ancient times in Asian regions, while in the West, this approach is considerably more recent. Medicinal mushrooms (MMs) are reported to have numerous pharmacological actions such as antimicrobial, anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory, antidiabetic, cytotoxic, antioxidant, hepatoprotective, anticancer, antioxidant, antiallergic, antihyperlipidemic, and prebiotic properties, among others [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These activities are attributable to many bioactive metabolites present in the mycelium but above all in the fruiting body, whose biological effect varies according to the chemical nature and whose distribution varies according to the fungal species. A great deal of research has been carried out and is increasingly being undertaken to identify and characterize mycochemicals and to define their actions and mechanisms, due to the growing interest in the use of natural products, including as adjuvants in traditional therapies. The bulk of research carried out has focused on a few genera or species, for example, those of the oldest and most traditional use among Asian populations, while for those remaining, current scientific support is still lacking. Several studies have so far investigated the various activities of MMs, highlighting their enormous potential for use in the medical sector, but a particular effort has been put into studying their antitumor and immunomodulatory properties, as cancer remains one of the most difficult challenges to date.
</p>
