<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">Indole alkaloids, especially bisindole nuclear alkaloids, have been widely concerned in the field of anti-infection due to their special structure, strong analogues, high selectivity and low side effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Indigo naturalis is rich in indole alkaloids, and the anti-virus research of indigo naturalis mainly focuses on indigo and indirubin. Influenza virus is the pathogen of influenza, especially influenza A virus is easy to mutate, causing a worldwide pandemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Indirubin could reduce activation of the chemokine regulated on, the expression of normal T cell and the secretion of influenza virus A/NWS/33- infected H292 human epithelial cell line. And this inhibitory effect was also observed as well as influenza virus B/Lee-infected cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. In 
 <italic>vivo</italic> test, Indirubin can reduce the sensitivity of stress-induced mice to influenza virus (H1N1), thereby reducing lung injury and improving survival rate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Further study showed that indirubin could promote the formation of IFN- glycolic acid and increase the expression of IFN-
 <italic>β</italic> and IFN-induced transmembrane 3 through mitochondrial antiviral signal copper aluminum, thus maintaining the morphology and function of mitochondria after H1N1 infection. Indigo and indirubin have strong killing activity against Japanese encephalitis virus, which may be related to block virus attachment. Especially indirubin has a strong protective effect on lethal Japanese encephalitis virus model [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In addition, indigo can inhibit the 3C-like protease (3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>) of SARS-coronavirus in dose dependence, which can induce the hydrolysis of replication enzyme polypeptides 1a and 1ab into functional proteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The above studies indicate that indigo naturalis and its active ingredients are expected to become potential antiviral drugs, especially drug-resistant viruses. Meanwhile, more in-depth experiments are needed to prove their potential as antiviral drugs.
</p>
