<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tualang honey was found to have intermediary glycemic index values of 65 ± 7 [
 <xref rid="B110-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Hussain et al. (2012) reported that supplementation of 20 g/day Tualang honey for 4 months in healthy postmenopausal women caused a significant increase in fasting blood sugar (FBS) [
 <xref rid="B111-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. However, by prolonging the treatment to 12 months, a decrease in FBS levels was reported in healthy and diabetic postmenopausal women [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Wahab et al. (2018) suggested a differential effect of honey on glucose metabolism for short- and long-term use. [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Recent findings by Rashid et al. (2019) supported a prior claim that the ingestion of Kelulut honey daily for 30 days has no significant effect on fasting glucose and fasting lipid profile in patients with impaired fasting blood glucose [
 <xref rid="B109-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. The authors suggested short-duration ingestion of Kelulut honey as the factor for the insignificant result. By contrast, one in vivo study showed that supplementation of Kelulut honey for the last 35 days in a 16-week high-carbohydrate high-fructose diet fed in rats decreased the fasting blood glucose compared with non-supplemented control [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. However, the effect of Tualang honey as an anti-diabetic is unclear. Future studies should extend knowledge on the anti-diabetic properties of Tualang honey on patients with diabetes to reinforce the anti-diabetic ability of Tualang honey, as the animal studies discussed above [
 <xref rid="B50-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>] have successfully proven that Tualang honey possesses anti-diabetic effect in animals.
</p>
