<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At present, the determination of index components in 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> is still mostly determined by HPLC, but it is not limited to the determination of a single component, and multi-component determination has gradually become a hot spot. 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. (2013)</xref> used HPLC to determine quercetin and kaempferol in 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic>; 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Tong (2011)</xref> used HPLC to determine oleanolic acid and ursolic acid. Huang Jiayu used HPLC to determine ferulic acid and vanillic acid. 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2011)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al. (2009)</xref> determined the content of quercetin in different parts of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> by HPLC. 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al. (2010)</xref> determined the content of chlorogenic acid in 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> by HPLC. 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al. (2014)</xref> established a HPLC for the simultaneous determination of esculetin, quercetin, quercetin-3-O-β-D-glucuronide, and quercetin-3-O-β-D-glucuronide-6″-methyl ester. 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. (2010)</xref> determined the content of quercetin in stems and leaves of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> in different harvest periods by HPLC, it was found that the content of quercetin in leaves was significantly higher than that in stems, and August is the best harvest season. In addition, some advanced analytical techniques and determination methods have been gradually applied to the quality control of 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic>. 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2012)</xref> separated and determined ferulic acid, caffeic acid, and protocatechuic acid in 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> by sweeping-MEKC. 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al. (2009)</xref> simultaneously determined quercetin, vanillic acid, ferulic acid, caffeic acid, and protocatechuic acid in 
 <italic>P. perfoliatum</italic> by Electrophoretic-electrochemical method (CE-ED).
</p>
