<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Earlier studies performed on human dermal fibroblasts suggested that asiatic acid and asiaticoside enhance the synthesis of collagen I in a similar proportion, and that the presence of the glucidic moiety is not mandatory for this effect [
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] More recently a comprehensive study aimed at identifying the active triterpene from 
 <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> in wound healing compared the effects of asiaticoside, asiatic acid, madecassoside, and madecassic acid on fibroblast proliferation, collagen synthesis and degradation, as well as after oral administration to mice with experimental burn injuries [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The stimulation of fibroblast proliferation could not be pointed out for any of the four compounds. The findings regarding the effects on collagen synthesis in skin fibroblasts were unexpected: only the glycosides (asiaticoside and madecassoside) enhanced this process, as demonstrated by the elevation of mRNA levels for collagen I and III and higher procollagen type I and type III content. Madecassoside proved to be more active than asiaticoside in this regard. Moreover, madecassoside was the only compound able to enhance the expression of metallopeptidase inhibitor 1mRNA expression, a protein which inhibits the collagen degradation. Regarding the effects on the TGF-β/Smad pathway, highly relevant to collagen synthesis by fibroblasts, only the triterpene glycosides were able to activate this pathway with madecassoside being more active. The advantages seen in vitro of glycosides over aglycones were supported by in vivo experiments, where oral administration of triterpenes to mice with burn injuries only induced healing activities in case of the glycosides; madecassoside was more efficient than asiaticoside. A possible explanation for these observations, postulated by the authors, is that the glycosides have a particular absorption and distribution rate in the state of burn lesions [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-05557" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>].
</p>
