<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0032" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Possible mechanisms of radioprotection by aromatic plants</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is a well-known fact that radiation is a powerful cytotoxic agent. Reactive oxygen species such as superoxide anion, singlet oxygen, hydroxyl radical, nitric oxide, hydrogen peroxide and peroxyl radicals are generated by ionizing radiation in biologic system through radiolysis of water and are accountable for the cellular injury caused to DNA and proteins [
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31–33</a>]. The detrimental effects of radiation-induced alterations in biologic systems via reactive oxygen species generation play a crucial role as far as maintenance of metabolic homeostasis in the body and therefore, any disparity in homeostasis results in oxidative stress [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>], which could be trounced by additional provision of naturally occurring, plant based antioxidants [
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39–41</a>]. The extracts of aromatic plants contain several chemical constituents such as essential oils, plant phenolics such as phenolic acids, flavonoids, terpenes, tannins, stilbenes, lignans and vitamins. Among these, the essential oils contain constituents such as monoterpenes and diterpenes that possess antioxidant properties. The activity of cyclic monoterpene hydrocarbons with two double bonds has been found to be comparable to the activity of phenols; however, their antioxidant activities differ due to their composition and oxidation of the components. The correlation between antioxidant capacity and phenolics concentration was pragmatic in several research studies on determining antioxidant capacities of plants [
  <a rid="B236" ref-type="bibr" href="#B236">236</a>]. Phenolic compounds are the secondary metabolites of plants and involved in defense against ultraviolet radiation or aggression by pathogens, parasites and predators [
  <a rid="B237" ref-type="bibr" href="#B237">237</a>]. The chemical structure of phenolic compounds also affects their antioxidant effects. Phenolics have usually one or more aromatic rings that act as an extended conjugated aromatic system to delocalize an unpaired electron and one or more hydroxyl groups which donate a hydrogen atom or an electron to a free radical. Therefore, these phytoconstituents have most suitable structure for free radical scavenging activities. The polyphenols also act as reducing agents, hydrogen-donating antioxidants, singlet oxygen quenchers and metal chelators thus imparting their inherent antioxidant activity. On the other hand, flavonoids interfere with the propagation reactions of the free radical and formation of the radicals by chelating the transition metal. The α-Tocopherol, one of the best known vitamins confer protection to intracellular membranes mainly by quenching singlet oxygen and reacting with lipid peroxy radicals which consequently leads to abrogation of lipid peroxidation levels [
  <a rid="B238" ref-type="bibr" href="#B238">238</a>]. Ascorbic acid (Vitamin C) was found to work synergistically with tocopherols and other phenolic antioxidants. Carotenoids, such as β-carotene, lutein and zeaxanthin, are present in certain aromatic plants such as mints, oregano, balm, basil, sage and rosemary which have demonstrated antioxidant activity both in 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> and animal experimental studies. Thus, antioxidant function and radical scavenging mechanism are the most likely mechanism of radioprotection by aromatic plants as suggested by several workers (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
