<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, inclusion of ginger powder in the diet of birds was effective on various productive parameters. In this experiment, production rate and egg mass were not influenced by the treatments, while feed intake and FCR decreased when birds received increasing levels of ginger powder. In agreement to our results, previous findings confirmed that dietary supplementation with ginger root improved FCR in broiler chickens [
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and decreased feed intake in guinea fowl [
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Furthermore, ginger supplements had no adverse effect on the palatability of broiler feeds [
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and improved the digestibility of dry matter in guinea fowl [
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Contrarily, Damaziak et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] did not observe any positive effect of the ginger root on egg production rate in laying hens. However, findings of our study were not in agreement with the handful studies showing the insignificant effect of ginger powder [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] or ginger extract dietary supplementation [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] on the FCR. Akbarian et al. reported that using different levels of ginger (0.25, 0.5 and 0.75 g/100 g of diet) in laying hens during 30 weeks had insignificant effect on FI and FCR [
 <xref rid="B43-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The disparity of this study with previous research results could be due to differences in ginger source, processing methods as well as poultry species [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Ginger contains many active compounds (e.g., brunel, camphon, limonene, humolin, gingerol, gingeron, gingerdiol, shogaols, some phenolic ketone derivatives, volatile oils, alkaloids, saponins, and flavonoids) [
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] that could stimulate feed digestion and the digestive enzymes, thus increasing FI and FCR [
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In the same way Platel and Srinivasan [
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] stated that ginger enhanced the activity of pancreatic lipase, amylase, trypsin chymotrypsin, and bile acid secretion in albino rats. In fact, these enzymes, bile and biliary bile acids significantly affect the digestion and absorption of nutrients. In accord, Habibi et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] indicated the stimulating effect of ginger root powder (7.5 g/kg of diet) on body weight and weight gain in broiler chicks at 22 days of the experiment. In another study, ginger powder increased production, hatchability, reproductive performance, and economic efficiency at a level of 0.05 g/kg diet while increasing egg weight and feed intake in Japanese quail [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In present study, ginger powder supplemented diet had no effect on egg production, egg weight, and total egg mass among the treatments during the experiment period. Our findings were in line with the results of Wen at al. [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and Herve et al. [
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] reporting the insignificant effect of ginger supplemented diet in laying hen and quail. Moreover, Wen et al. concluded that egg weight was improved in ginger powder fed laying hen [
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The results of studies on the effect of ginger at increasing levels of 0, 5, 10, 15, and 20 g/kg of diet on the performance of laying hens at the age of 27 weeks showed that all laying hens were in good health and no mortality was recorded in the whole period of the experiment. Average egg weight and laying rate were similar in treatments containing ginger powder. Egg mass was positively affected by the treatments compared with the control group, which can be related to the positive effect of ginger powder on laying rate as well as egg weight [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In contrast to the current quail study, egg production rate was increased in ginger extract/powder fed laying hen [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] alone or in combination with medicinal herbs [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. This means that the beneficial effect of ginger on performance depends on the bird species, dosage of ginger, and its derivatives and interaction with other dietary components. However, information about mechanism of action of ginger intake are scarce [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
