<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study ginger powder was beneficial on the reducing the blood triacylglyceride levels yet its effects were not significant on serum cholesterol and glucose levels. Other serum parameters including albumin, and protein were not significantly affected by ginger powder (
 <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Consistent with these results, studies have shown that diet supplementation with ginger extract at 0.4 and 0.6 mg/g of diet, significantly decreased glucose, triglyceride, and cholesterol levels [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Akhany et al. [
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] concluded that ginger extract significantly reduced blood glucose levels and increased insulin levels. Some of the essential minerals (calcium, zinc, potassium, manganese, and chromium) are related to the mechanism of insulin release [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In another study, ginger at concentrations up to 2% of the diet reduced cholesterol, triglyceride, and glucose levels in comparison with the control group, while the serum protein was not affected by the experimental treatments [
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Ginger has previously shown strong anti-lipidemic effect on serum cholesterol and triglyceride levels [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]; hence, its mode of action may be related to the inhibition of cholesterol synthesis (e.g., β-hydroxy-β-methylglutaryl coenzyme A (HMG—CoA) [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Correspondingly, ginger is a potent HMGR-inhibiting drug, known to cause liver-specific inhibition of cholesterol synthesis [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In addition, other reports showed that diabetic therapy with insulin helps in reducing the plasma triglycerides by affecting lipoprotein lipase levels [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Ginger has insulin-stimulating effect which could reduce plasma triglycerides [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Previous studies stated that phenols and flavonoids act as potent antioxidants [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Khalifa and Noseer [
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] revealed that eggs produced by quail supplemented with combined ginger powder and probiotics had the lowest total cholesterol content in serum and yolk compared with the control, along with an increase in high-density lipoprotein (HDL) and decrease of low-density lipoprotein (LDL). Herve et al. [
 <xref rid="B59-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] showed that total cholesterol and triglycerides, transaminases, and MDA decreased in quails supplemented with ginger essential oil at 50, 100, and 150 μL/kg body weight.
</p>
