<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It was established that the protective effects of olive oil compounds on endothelial function could be explained mainly by their anti-inflammatory activity (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>). The first anti-inflammatory mechanism attributed to olive oil is the ability of the major phenolic compounds to inhibit the adhesion of immune cells (T-, B-lymphocytes and monocytes) to the endothelium, in response to the inflammatory process. That was achieved by inhibiting the expression of the inflammatory mediators, such as cytokines (interleukin (IL)-1, IL-6, IL-8 signaling pathways and tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-α), chemokines (monocyte chemotactic protein (MCP-1), adhesion molecules (P and E-selectin, intercellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1), and leukocyte adhesion molecules, i.e., vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 (VCAM-1) (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>), which are critical in the regulation of innate and adaptive immuno-inflammatory responses (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>). A recent study demonstrated that hydroxytyrosol and its metabolites were protective against endothelial dysfunction in human aortic endothelial cells co-incubated with TNF-α by considerably reducing the secretion of E-selectin, P-selectin, ICAM-1, and VCAM-1 (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>). Moreover, hydroxytyrosol metabolites further reduced the levels of MCP-1 (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>). Other studies described the inhibition of endothelial activation by oleuropein and hydroxytyrosol, that were able to reduce the lipopolysaccharide (LPS)- or cytokine (TNF-α, IL-1β)- stimulated expression of VCAM-1 in cultured human umbilical vein endothelial cells by inhibiting its mRNA levels, hence decreasing the adhesion of monocytes to endothelial cells (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>). Besides, oleic acid also showed a potent ability to lower the inflammatory effects of long-chain SFAs in human aortic endothelial cells. In this way, oleic acid inhibited the stearic acid-induced increase in ICAM-1 expression as well as stearic acid-induced phosphorylation of nuclear transcription factor kappa B (NF-kB) (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>).
</p>
