<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Furthermore, polyphenols demonstrated the mechanism of action on the inflammatory process similar to that of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs). In this sense, hydroxytyrosol and oleuropein phenols reduced the inflammatory angiogenesis through the inhibition of matrix metalloproteinase-9 (MMP-9) protein expression levels (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>), and also COX-2 enzyme expression levels consequently modulating the arachidonic acid (AA) cascade and eicosanoid synthesis in the endothelial cell culture (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>). AA and its metabolites (prostaglandins, thromboxanes, leukotrienes) are considered as intracellular messengers that play an important role in the regulation of signal transduction that is implicated in inflammatory responses. For example, leukotriene B4 (LTB4) has a chemotactic effect on neutrophils, directing the cells to the atherosclerotic lesion. Likewise, oleocanthal is another phenol that showed anti-inflammatory effects similar to those of NSAIDs. It was revealed that oleocanthal had an inhibitory effect on COX-1 and COX-2 inflammatory enzymes 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> in a dose-dependent manner, and had higher potency at equimolar concentrations in comparison to ibuprofen (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>). Thus, 25 mM of oleocanthal inhibited the activity of COX enzyme by 41–57%, whilst 25 mM of ibuprofen inhibited it by 13–18%. Interestingly, the NSAIDs-like effects of polyphenols were determined in association with a substantial decrease in stimulated intracellular ROS levels and the activation of redox-sensitive transcription NF-kB. However, to accomplish a comparable effect to the ibuprofen recommended daily dose, 500 g of extra virgin olive oil would be necessary to consume, making the dose/effect relationship beyond any inflammatory benefits due to normal daily consumption of olive oil (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>).
</p>
