<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Electrical impedance has been described in [
 <xref rid="B105-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. This technology is often used in the pharmaceutical industry to test respiratory and lung function [
 <xref rid="B107-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. The electrodes are located periphery around the pipe and have electrical contact with the flow inside the pipe but do not cause any obstruction to the flow [
 <xref rid="B80-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. A current is injected through the cross-section of the pipe and the corresponding electrode voltage is measured. To calculate the fraction of each phase an algorithm is used. The input to the algorithm is the applied current pattern and the electrode voltages, which will then reconstruct an image based on the electrical conductivity and permittivity of the flow [
 <xref rid="B108-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. EIT is not widely used in the oil and gas industry, but [
 <xref rid="B105-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>] shows promising results with a recently developed measurement system that can produce real time 3D images. These are to be used together with an algorithm to monitor the multi-phase flow. The system consists of 80 surface electrodes and is capable of producing 15 frames per second in 3D. Another EIT sensor described in [
 <xref rid="B109-sensors-19-02184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>] presents a multi-mode prototype, with a combination of capacitive and resistive/conductive mode. By experiments the relative errors between measured and calculated values are below 1.64% for the capacitance mode and less than 2.68% for the conductive mode. The sensor requires further development before application but indicates promising results for measurements of multi-phase flow.
</p>
