<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among the ecosystem services provided by GI features, these data suggest that Technosol associated bacteria have the potential to utilize or break down urban contaminants in addition to TPH. This ecosystem service is valuable for management strategies of urban ecosystems to remediate chemical and oil spills as well as heavy metals, especially for long-term contaminated sites (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wilson et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ellis et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mishra et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Delgado-Balbuena et al., 2016</xref>). Bacterial Orders in the top 10% of Technosol community that were enriched compared to urban surface soils, were RB41, iii1-15, Saprospirales, Cytophagales, Pirellulales, Opitutales, Anaerolineae__envOPS12. These bacteria are likely the initial description of a potential consortium that characterize the GI Technosol community through contributing to bioremediation or are indicating of contamination. The top two groups are RB41 (Class Chloroacidobacteria, Order Acidobacteria) and iii1-15 (Class Acidobacteria-6, Order Acidobacteria) and they are common in urban soils and are prominent in soils globally; though their enrichment and role in the context of bioremediation in GI Technosols is unclear (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fierer, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Huot et al., 2017</xref>). Natural urban surface soils had a greater abundance in Myxococcales, which contribute to removal of trace organic contaminants, specifically uranium, and may additionally suppress unwanted organisms (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cardenas et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Phan et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Robinson et al., 2016</xref>). The increase in abundance of Cytophagales in GI Technosols may indicate some functional redundancy within the diverse bacterial community. Cytophagales have previously been documented as enriched in urban soils contaminated with crude oil and can metabolize heavy metal (e.g., Selenium) (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">de Souza et al., 2001</xref>), which also reinforces their potential functional role as a bioremediator within GI features (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mukherjee et al., 2017</xref>). Rhodospirillales had decreased abundance in the Technosols, however, their presence may still contribute to pollutant degradation, since soils with phenanthrene,n-octadecane and PAH pollution had thriving populations of Rhodospirillales (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ji et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jiao et al., 2016</xref>). In the GI Technosols studied here, the contaminant concentrations were most likely too low to drive a response. Additional indicators of bacterial community response to TPH contaminants may also be detected through the increased abundance of bacteria typically used to facilitate bioremediation; such as, 
 <italic class="italic">Corynebacterium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Flavobacterium</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus</italic> species, as well as 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Micrococcus</italic> species because of their notable biodegradation of crude oil (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mishra et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rahman et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Paul et al., 2005</xref>). Since overall TPH levels were low GI sites were not considered polluted. The consequence of the low levels of contaminants detected in the GI sites is likely why respective taxa for bioremediation were not abundant. The bacterial communities of Technosols at GI sites have limited evidence of known urban contaminants. Further understanding of the role of GI features for bioremediation in urban areas requires future studies focused on the enrichments of specific bacterial taxa and contaminants. The bacterial community of different GI designs are influenced by a combination of biogeochemical parameters and GI features. Future studies using shotgun metagenome sequencing would corroborate functional capabilities (e.g., nutrient cycling and bioremediation of contaminants) from these unique GI sites and facilitate comparing observations regarding the urban soil microbiomes across analysis platforms.
</p>
