<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cannabis is known as a complex multipurpose plant with a long history of use as a medicine, drug, and source of fiber [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Among a plethora of unique chemical compounds found in cannabis, the most important secondary metabolites are cannabinoids which are the most studied compounds in this plant. There are a growing number of articles that explore the importance of compounds called “cannabinoids’’ exclusively found in 
 <italic>Cannabis</italic> plants. Phytocannabinoids are 21-22-carbon compounds, classified into 10 structural types with over 100 varieties occurring in resin produced by glandular hairs of 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> L. [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Among these cannabinoids, trans-Δ9-tetrahydrocannabinol (Δ9-THC) and cannabidiol (CBD) are the two which have been the subject of more than 90 percent of scientific investigations. Although THC is the first thing that comes to mind when talking about cannabis, there are also nonpsychoactive cannabinoids with several therapeutic properties such as CBD, which has recently become more important due to THC limitations and new discoveries about CBD medicinal properties in parallel. Indeed, the plant’s adverse psychotropic and addictive effects are attributed to tetrahydrocannabinol [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The use of cannabis has always been very controversial because it is classified as an illegal drug due to its psychoactive THC. Female flowers (marijuana) and leaves (grass) of drug-type cannabis are considered as a “soft” drug but not “Hash or Hashish” which contains a high concentration of THC with harmful effects [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Despite this fact, there has been an increased interest in recent years of the potential use of cannabis derivatives in medical applications [
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In this regard, reviewing and rewriting the regulations by governments, introducing novel gene pools of dwarf and low THC/high CBD accessions, and the development of techniques to accurately characterize the chemical phenotypes (drug and nondrug cannabis plants) have made a significant contribution to the acceptance of this issue and the control of legal and illegal cannabis cultivation [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-25-04036" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
