<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The most bioactive constituents of milk are proteins such as immunoglobulins, lactoferrin, and peptides obtained from hydrolysis of proteins, and fatty acid component such as LA, some minerals, different oligosaccharides, and melatonin. Different methods of processing milk to have more desirable components besides a wide variety of on-farm management systems help in the enhancement of bioactive components that are found naturally in milk [
 <xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. An overview on production of designer milk from transgenic offspring is depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure-1</xref>. Like eggs, milk can also be enriched with various nutrients such as vitamins and minerals. Transgenic techniques can be employed for the development of designer milk. Fortification of milk according to the consumer’s expectation can be done to strengthen the global demand of the milk [
 <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Milk allergy is a common problem in children, so the removal of beta-lactoglobulin (β-LG) will eliminate this problem [
 <xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. Genetic engineering can help in production of novel designer milk, thereby new milk products [
 <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Stitched milk is designer milk that is rich in components of consumer choice, improving the consumers’ health by enhancing the immunity [
 <xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. Milk is an ideal but complex food, capable of providing protection against infections, development of intestinal absorption, immune activation, reduce inflammation, anti-tumor, antimicrobial and promote establishment of unique gut micro-organisms [
 <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. Certain milk components provide multidirectional benefits. All oligosaccharides present in milk are able to control the entry of microbes by blocking the adhesion of pathogens on cell surfaces in addition to lactoferrin and lysozyme that can put forth direct antimicrobial effects. The colostrum provides passive immunity, which is capable enough to stimulate an increased host immune response. Understanding the functions of individual component of milk may help in formulation of a need-based fortified designer or transgenic milk.
</p>
