<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Goat milk is similar to human milk in composition. Humanization of milk means designing milk that resembles mother’s milk, which does not provoke allergic response in the infant babies. Manipulation should be aimed to alter protein, fat, and also oligosaccharides in the milk to achieve safe milk for the babies [
 <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. β-LG is present in cow’s milk but absent in human milk, and hence, it can elicit immune reaction when fed to infants [
 <xref rid="ref81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Hence, infant formulation should lack this β-LG [
 <xref rid="ref83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>]. Another target may be incorporation of casein amino acid sequence of human into cow’s milk through gene manipulation. Lactoferrin and lysozyme should be incorporated into cow milk to increase the antibacterial properties of milk [
 <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. A variety of novel dairy fractions that could be included in infant formula has been identified, and the products are now commercially available. α-Lactalbumin is a compound with a very well-balanced amino acid profile useful in milk-based infant formulas. On breakdown into smaller peptides, it may exhibit various functions, such as enhancing mineral absorption, stimulating growth of beneficial microorganisms, modulating the immune system, and inhibiting the growth of pathogens [
 <xref rid="ref84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. Lactoferrin provides an assembly of bioactivities, including acceleration of iron absorption, initiation of intestinal proliferation and variation, regulation of immune function as well as antibacterial and antiviral effects [
 <xref rid="ref85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. The bovine osteopontin has many structural similarities to human lactoferrin, and it can affect bone mineralization and growth, making it a potential candidate protein for inclusion in infant formula [
 <xref rid="ref86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. Milk fat globule membranes have been shown to exhibit antimicrobial activities [
 <xref rid="ref87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>], and the presence of these components into complementary infants’ foods has been shown to lower the diarrhea incidence. Different constituents are fortified to milk and milk products to improve its quality, thereby its health benefits to human. Beverages based on milk enriched with apple and grape seed, prebiotic and probiotic fortified milk, folic acid-fortified milk, lutein-fortified milk, Vitamin D, calcium-fortified milk, and ice cream are already available for human consumption [
 <xref rid="ref88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. The use of natural products such as herbal extracts during processing of milk while preparation of cheese is reported recently [
 <xref rid="ref93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>].
</p>
