<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides the mentioned abiotic factors that can remarkably affect the chemical constituents of an aromatic plant, one of the main limiting factors in peppermint and chamomile commercial cultivation is weed competition [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] as weeds are able to reduce both oil amount and biomass yield. Dhima et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] reported that the largest losses in annual cultivated aromatic plants were caused by weeds. Matković et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] recorded a 88% loss of aerial biomass of peppermint to weeds, compared to non-weeded control in South Banat in Serbia. Darre et al. [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], in two-year trials, revealed a yield loss of the same species of 35.7% and 50.9% in weeded, compared to non-weeded plots at a Cordoba site in Argentina. Similarly, Karkanis et al. [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] reported a significant yield loss in peppermint fields heavily infested with perennial weeds. Autotrophic flowering plants are predominant among weed species, but weeds also include parasitic plants that have developed various ways of attacking their hosts, by using a special adhesion/absorption organ known as the haustorium. The organ serves as a structural and physiological bridge for parasites to draw water, minerals, organic molecules and solutes from the host plant conductive system, leading to severe host growth and yield reductions [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Dodder are parasitic weeds species belonging to the 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> genus. Among them, field dodder (
 <italic>Cuscuta campestris</italic> Yunck.) is one of the most widespread species, which infests a wide range of crop species [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], inducing negative impacts on the growth and yield of infested hosts, and it has significant effects on the structure and functioning of plant communities that are infested by these holoparasites [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Field dodder prefers a variety of forage crops, vegetables, and ornamental and aromatic plants (including peppermint) that are rich in volatile compounds [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
</p>
