<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The consumption of treated larvae, subjected to parasitism by 
 <italic class="italic">C. flavipes</italic>, by the predatory spined soldier bug suggests mortality of the parasitoid by the insecticides, because heteropteran predators avoid preying on parasitized larvae.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr61-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr62-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup> In addition, dead parasitoids in host larvae body are unable to produce chemical signals responsible to prevent predation.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr63-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup> The faster dying of the predatory spined soldier bug with the positive control, 
 <italic class="italic">ar</italic>-turmerone, and black mustard seed essential oil in the current study shows knockdown effect of these products to the predator. However, this mortality could be reduced because host larvae parasitized by 
 <italic class="italic">Cotesia</italic> species increase the CYP activity.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr64-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup> The higher mortality of the confused flour beetle 
 <italic class="italic">Tribolium confusum</italic> Jacquelin du Val (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) adults by ingestion of a mustard synthetic oil compared to a topical application was due to the great percentage (90%) of allyl isothiocyanate in this oil.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr65-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup> Allyl isothiocyanate vapor alone controlled 100% of the book louse 
 <italic class="italic">Liposcelis entomophila</italic> Enderlein (Psocoptera: Liposcelididae), lesser grain borer, maize weevil, and 
 <italic class="italic">Tribolium ferrugineum</italic> F. (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae) adults 72 h after exposure to a three μg/mL atmospheric concentration.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr66-1559325819827454" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
