<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> Kral &amp; McCartney (Etonia rosemary) was discovered in the Etonia Scrub in Putnam County, Florida in September 1990 and described as a new species in 1991 [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> is similar to 
 <italic>C. grandiflora</italic> in general appearance and the flowers are large and quite similar but the leaves of 
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> are broader than 
 <italic>C. grandiflora</italic> and have clearly visible lateral veins on the lower surface [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> is found in very limited areas of deep white sand scrub dominated by sand pines (
 <italic>Pinus clausa</italic>) and scrubby oaks (
 <italic>Quercus</italic> spp.) on dry soils. Its entire known range is within a subdivision of Putnam County containing streets and a few residences, which make it the most narrowly distributed species of 
 <italic>Conradina</italic> [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> was listed as a federally endangered species in July 1993 [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The latest survey of Etonia rosemary counted about eight subpopulations on Etonia Creek State Forest containing fewer than 1000 total individuals [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The major threats facing 
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> include habitat loss due to development projects for residential housing, horticultural collection, hurricane damage and invasive species or lack of natural processes, such as fire [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Because 
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> requires light but can tolerate the light shade of openings the in scrub, fire suppression is one of the major limiting factors as it results in over-shading by overstory scrub vegetation rendering the habitat less favorable for 
 <italic>C. etonia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
