<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to oregano and thyme, few publications have described the effect of dietary cornus supplementation on ruminants. Cornelian cherry (
 <italic>Cornus mas</italic> L.) is a species of dogwood widely grown in central and south-eastern Europe and Asia. It contains phenolics, including anthocyanins, gallic acid, ellagic acid, quercetin, kaempferol and cyanin [
 <xref rid="B62-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. These phenolics have both antioxidant and antimicrobial properties [
 <xref rid="B63-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], whereas ellagic acid also shows immune modulatory activity [
 <xref rid="B64-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Quercetin, another main phenolic compound, was found to reduce inflammation and oxidation damage caused by 
 <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> in the mucosa of guinea pigs [
 <xref rid="B65-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Cornus is also rich in ascorbic acid, sugar, organic acids, flavonoids, tannins and other bioactive compounds, among which polyphenols were found in significant amounts [
 <xref rid="B66-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Studies demonstrate that feeding with cornus may reduce the use of antibiotics in young animals post-weaning and the incidence of both diarrhea and mortality in rabbits [
 <xref rid="B67-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Moreover, cornus in beef cattle rations displayed an improvement in DM digestibility, which primarily resulted from the enhanced digestibility of fiber (associated with increased ruminal protozoa counts by feeding cornus) and protein [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Another study indicated that increasing dietary cornus was beneficial for the NDF digestibility and also decreased protein degradability, providing a higher concentration of bypass protein. Moreover, in the same study, cornus contributed to the mitigation of acidosis, affecting cattle fed high-grain diets, by altering the nutrient degradability of feeds [
 <xref rid="B19-animals-11-01063" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
