<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Mass Profiler Professional B.12.06 (Agilent Technologies) was used for the elaboration of the untargeted UHPLC/QTOF data by unsupervised hierarchical cluster analysis (HCA), based on the fold-change heat map, as previously reported [
 <xref rid="B17-foods-08-00179" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Thereafter, the raw metabolomic dataset was exported and elaborated into SIMCA 13 software (Umetrics, Malmo, Sweden) by supervised orthogonal projections to latent structures discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA) multivariate statistics. For the OPLS model, raw data were Log2 transformed to improve normal distribution, UV scaled to account for the wide range of intensities, and then analyzed. The variation between the groups was separated into predictive and orthogonal (i.e., related to technical and biological variation) components. The presence of outliers into the OPLS model was checked according to Hotelling’s T2 (i.e., the distance from the origin in the model), using 95% and 99% confidence limits for suspect and strong outliers, respectively. The model cross-validation was then carried out using CV-ANOVA (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), whereas permutation testing (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 100) was done to exclude overfitting. Model parameters, i.e., R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>Y (goodness-of-fit) and Q
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>Y (goodness-of-prediction) were also recorded. Afterward, the variable selection method, namely, VIP (i.e., variable importance in projection) was used to evaluate the phenolic compounds most affected by the long-storage period, and to select those with the highest discrimination potential (VIP score &gt; 1). Finally, a Fold-Change (FC) analysis was carried out considering the UHPLC/QTOF data from the UHPLC/QTOF data as compounds abundance ratio versus the control, in order to evaluate in detail, the trend and impact of the long-storage period on the main phenolic subclasses (i.e., tyrosols, phenolic acids, flavones, and lignans).
</p>
