<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of alternative raw materials (e.g., coffeeberry, leaves, fruits, milk, vegetables, by-products, and wastes) for the fermentation process of Kombucha has been proposed by researchers. For example, by using by-products and wastes in the fermentation process, not only can the time and cost of fermentation be reduced, but also more significant antibacterial and antifungal activity of the final product can be achieved. Similarly, tea with some additives as the raw alternative can enhance the antioxidant and anticancer performance of Kombucha [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In the past, a solid-state fermentation method was applied by researchers to produce Kombucha. However, this fermentation method has several limitations like expensive equipment, low yield, and complicated process. Hence, the submerged fermentation method can be a promising candidate to surmount the mentioned limitations. Several factors like duration of fermentation, substrate type, pH, and temperature can influence the final product; however, due to the comprehensive nature of the available data and some limitations on the length of this section, only essential points are explained. The optimum temperature was maintained throughout the fermentation process, which leads to better enzyme activity and microbial growth and improvement of the fermentation benefits. Moreover, temperature variations can influence the antioxidant effect in substances with the plant sources [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], for instance, the production of the compounds that contain phenol. The temperature values of the Kombucha fermentation process can commonly be considered from 20°C to 30°C. Some researchers in their exciting works investigated the microbial loads (log CFU/ml) of acetic acid bacteria (AAB) in Kombucha for two different temperatures (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5(b)</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].
</p>
