<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This technology has improved since the last decade. Although the 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> proteins and polysaccharides are usually extracted with water or polar organic solvents, the presence of complex polymers, accessibility problems and the attack of polysaccharides with hydrolytic enzymes damage the cell wall and release intracellular material. To improve enzyme extraction efficiency, new procedures have been developed, such as acid extraction and combined enzymatic-chemical extraction, providing antioxidant properties to ulvan [
 <xref rid="B104-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>]. Enzyme-assisted extraction was applied for 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> bioconversion to produce antiviral and antioxidant extracts [
 <xref rid="B105-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. Endoproteases, as well as the combined mixture of carbohydrase, increased the extraction yields as well as the sugar and protein contents in the extracts, which showed free radical scavenging properties. The use of an enzyme-assisted extraction using commercial proteases and carbohydrases improves the extraction efficiency compared to water extraction at 50 °C [
 <xref rid="B106-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. This technique is less effective for polyphenol recovery, and increased from 0.41% to 0.99% in the dry weight (dw) hydrolysate, and it is promising for the extraction of Ulvans, which increased from 8.99% to 21.09% the dw hydrolysate. In addition, all hydrolysate fractions tested were non-toxic to human cells but were active against the 
 <italic class="italic">Herpes simplex</italic> virus. Hydrolysis with cell wall enzymatic degradation offered different results depending on 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> phenotypes [
 <xref rid="B107-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. The best results were obtained with the use of a polysaccharidase mixture (β-glucanase, hemicellulase, cellulose).
</p>
