<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coumarins represent a wide group of naturally occurring compounds, mainly found in the families of Apiaceae, Asteraceae, Leguminosae, Moraceae, Oleaceae, Rutaceae, and Thymelaeaceae [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. More than 1300 chemical entities have been characterized to date, but most chemical and pharmacological studies have been accomplished on either coumarin itself or structurally simple natural and semisynthetic derivatives. Coumarins can be divided into four categories: (a) substituted coumarins, (b) ring-fused coumarins, (c) 
 <italic>C-</italic>prenylcoumarins, and (d) 
 <italic>O-</italic>prenylcoumarins. In particular, these two latter groups comprise phytochemicals in which isoprenyl and/or terpenyl side chains are attached to the benzopyrone ring either directly or through one or more phenoxy moieties via an ether bond. However, while 
 <italic>C-</italic>prenylcoumarins have been investigated in detail from chemical, phytochemical, and pharmacological points of view [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], prenyloxycoumarins, considered for many years as mere biosynthetic intermediates of linear, furano- and pyranocoumarins, have only in the last decade been characterized as secondary metabolites exerting valuable biological activities [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Very recently the properties of notable examples in this group of oxyprenylated phenylpropanoids, namely auraptene (7-geranyloxycoumarin) and umbelliprenin (7-farnesyloxycoumarin), outlined in the literature during the last decade have been reviewed [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The aim of this miniature review is to detail from phytochemical and pharmacological points of view, the features of an additional biologically active coumarin derivative, 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05923-f001">Figure 1</xref>)
</p>
