<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1.2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antioxidant activity</div>
 <p id="p0095" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of different roasting conditions on the antioxidant property of cocoa beans is illustrated in 
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>. As previously observed with the total polyphenol, 
  <span class="italic">DTRCB 5 min</span> and 
  <span class="italic">DTRCB 10 min</span> have exhibited the lowest (p &lt; 0.05) antioxidant activities compared to 
  <span class="italic">DCB</span>, 
  <span class="italic">DORCB 5 min</span> and 
  <span class="italic">DORCB 10 min</span>. No significant difference (p &gt; 0.05) was registered between the antioxidant activity of 
  <span class="italic">DCB</span>, 
  <span class="italic">DORCB 5 min</span> and 
  <span class="italic">DORCB 10 min</span>. These results are in accordance with those previously obtained with the total polyphenol, because samples which exhibited low polyphenol content also exhibited lowest antiradical activity. In previous studies, the relation between polyphenol concentration and antioxidant activity has been demonstrated [
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">13</a>, 
  <a rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib15">15</a>, 
  <a rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib16">16</a>, 
  <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">17</a>, 
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19">19</a>, 
  <a rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib20">20</a>, 
  <a rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">22</a>, 
  <a rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib23">23</a>, 
  <a rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib24">24</a>]. From these observations, is appears clear that traditional roasting significantly reduce both polyphenol concentration and antioxidant activity of cocoa beans These observations are in agreement with that reported by Rizki et al
  <span class="italic">.</span>, 
  <a rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib10">[10]</a> who showed that the decrease in antioxidant activity of cocoa beans during roasting was related to the destruction of their polyphenols.
  <div id="fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Changes in antioxidant activity of cocoa beans extracts during processing [DCB = Oven dried cocoa beans; DTRCB 5 min = Dried and traditionally roasted cocoa beans (5 min); DORCB 5 min = Dried and oven roasted cocoa beans (5 min); DTRCB 10 min = Dried and traditionally roasted cocoa beans (10 min); DORCB 10 min = Dried and oven roasted cocoa beans (10 min)].</p>
   </div>
   <span id="alttext0015" class="alt-text">Fig. 2</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
