<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="p0010" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cocoa is the mature fruit of the cocoa tree (
  <span class="italic">Theobroma cacao</span> L.), growing in tropical regions of Africa and South America 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">[1]</a>. Raw cacao beans are one of the most nutritious foods in the world and has been demonstrated to protect the body from the impact of free radicals, reduces stress and depression, protect against heart diseases and many types of cancer 
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">[2]</a>. This health promoting effect of cocoa beans is generally attributed to the presence of polyphenols. The polyphenols in cocoa beans contribute to about 12–18% of the dry weight of the whole bean. Main classes of polyphenolic compounds found in cocoa beans are simple phenols, benzoquinones, phenolic acids, flavonoids etc. 
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">[3]</a>. In addition, cocoa beans are a good source of nutrients (lipids, proteins, carbohydrates, minerals and vitamins) 
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">[4]</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="p0015" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cocoa beans are mostly consumed after several processing techniques. The cocoa pre-processing steps (harvest, breaking, fermentation and drying) are mandatory to ensure good quality of beans, but cocoa flavors develop during fermentation and roasting. The most commercial products of cocoa are made with roasted beans [
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">6</a>]. The main goal of technological treatment is to improve the organoleptic properties of cocoa beans and eliminate its antinutrients (Hydrocyanate, Oxalate and Theobromine).
 </p>
 <p id="p0020" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During roasting, flavor precursors that are developed during fermentation interact to produce the desired chocolate flavor, which are formed between amino acids and sugars through Maillard reaction [
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">6</a>]. Cocoa beans that are not roasted have bitter, acidic, astringent and nutty flavor. By roasting the cocoa beans, acidity is decreased by reducing the concentration of volatile acids 
  <a rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib7">[7]</a>. However, processing may also cause chemical changes that may decrease the nutritional value and the antioxidant property of the beans. This can negatively affect the potential health benefits arising from the consumption of cocoa beans. For example, high processing temperature can promote lipid oxidation and non-enzymatic browning, which have the property to decrease the nutritional value of foods by causing a loss of essential fatty acids, essential aminoacids and digestible carbohydrates. They also lead to the destruction of vitamins and the reduction of protein digestibility 
  <a rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib8">[8]</a>. Besides affecting the nutritional and organoleptic properties of the beans and final products, they may generate toxic compounds which are harmful for the consumers 
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">[9]</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="p0025" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cameroon is the fifth worldwide and the fourth African cocoa producer. In Cameroon, the crop is cultivated in almost all regions. The seeds are used for industrial and local production of chocolate, cocoa butter, cocoa tea, other sweets etc or eaten directly after roasting.</p>
 <p id="p0030" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies have been reported on the effects of processing temperature and time on the nutritional value and phenolic content of edible seeds [
  <a rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib10">10</a>, 
  <a rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib11">11</a>]. In spite of the studies that have already been conducted on cocoa beans, there is almost no report on the effects of processing temperature and time on its phenolic content, antioxidant activity, lipid quality, proximate composition and mineral content. In one study, Rocha et al
  <span class="italic">.</span>
  <a rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib12">[12]</a> have demonstrated the impact of the roasting temperature and time of cocoa beans on the sensory characteristics and acceptability of chocolate. Thus, the objective of this study was to determine the effect of oven and traditional roasting on the polyphenols content, antioxidant activity, lipid quality and nutritional value of fermented cocoa beans.
 </p>
</sec>
