<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rather than targeting important SARS-CoV-2 proteins for viral life cycle, an alternative approach to anti-COVID drugs involves targeting host factors key to SARS-CoV-2 infection [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. For host cell entry, SARS-CoV-2 employs the spike (S) protein whose S1 subunit has a receptor binding domain (RBD) that specifically recognizes the cell surface receptor angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Notably, both SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV employ ACE2 as the cell entry receptor [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. After attachment of S protein to ACE2 receptor, the membrane fusion of virus and host cell depends on proteolytic activation of S protein by host proteases which involves cleavage of S1 subunit at S1/S2 and S2′ sites resulting in dissociation of S1 subunit and structural change in S2 subunit of S protein [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Hoffmann et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] showed that the host cell proteases, Transmembrane Protease Serine 2 (TMPRSS2) and cathepsin L or cathepsin B, can carry out S protein priming required for SARS-CoV-2 entry. Hoffmann et al. [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] also showed that TMPRSS2 is more essential for S protein priming and SARS-CoV-2 entry. In parallel, Ou et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] used specific inhibitors of cathepsin L and cathepsin B to show that cathepsin L rather than cathepsin B is essential for S protein priming of SARS-CoV-2 and membrane fusion in lysosomes. These studies highlight at least two alternate pathways for host cell entry of SARS-CoV-2. On the one hand, after SARS-CoV-2 attachment to ACE2, the membrane fusion and cytoplasmic entry can occur at the plasma membrane provided the cell surface protease TMPRSS2 is available to carry out S protein priming. On the other hand, after SARS-CoV-2 attachment to ACE2, the virus can be internalized as part of endosomes in the endocytic pathway, and later, the membrane fusion and cytoplasmic entry will occur in lysosomes provided the lysosomal protease cathepsin L is available to carry out S protein priming [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Depending on the target cell and associated expression of host cell proteases, SARS-CoV-2 may use one of the alternative pathways for host cell entry. Importantly, the above-mentioned studies also showed that known inhibitors camostat mesylate and nafamostat mesylate of TMPRSS2 and E-64d and PC-0626568 (SID26681509) of cathepsin L can block or significantly reduce the host cell entry of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In conclusion, human proteases TMPRSS2 and cathepsin L are key factors for host cell entry and are important targets for anti-COVID drugs [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-03822" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
