<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Oudemansiella</italic> is widely distributed throughout tropical and temperate regions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jof-07-00051-f003">Figure 3</xref>) and its basidiomata grow on rotting wood [
 <xref rid="B10-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. For instance
 <italic>, Oudemansiella canarii</italic> can be found in Asia, Africa and Central America [
 <xref rid="B14-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. 
 <italic>Oudemansiella platensis</italic> var
 <italic>. orinocensis</italic> can also be found in tropical and subtropical regions [
 <xref rid="B55-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Many species of 
 <italic>Oudemansiella</italic> were first recorded in Asia, as exemplified by 
 <italic>O. alphitophylla</italic> (as 
 <italic>Agaricus alphitophyllus</italic>), 
 <italic>O. latilamellata</italic>, and 
 <italic>O. rhodophylla</italic> [
 <xref rid="B40-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], which were all first recorded in Japan. On the other hand, 
 <italic>Oudemansiella bii</italic>, 
 <italic>O. fanjingshanensis</italic> and 
 <italic>O. yunnanensis</italic> were first recorded in China. Others, like 
 <italic>O. crassifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>O. submucida</italic> were first recorded in Malaysia, and have also been recorded in Thailand [
 <xref rid="B32-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In some cases, it is not possible to say for sure whether they belong to other genera described here because the descriptions did not rely on the concept by Peterson and Hughes [
 <xref rid="B10-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. For instance, 
 <italic>O. submicida</italic> is probably better placed in 
 <italic>Mucidula</italic> as it closely resembles 
 <italic>M. mucida</italic>. This shows that a lot of work remains to be done to harmonize the taxonomy of the OX complex at a global level. Some species of 
 <italic>Oudemansiella</italic> such as 
 <italic>O. exannulata</italic>, 
 <italic>O. gloriosa</italic>, 
 <italic>O. reticulata</italic> and 
 <italic>O. turbinispora</italic> appear to be endemic to Australia [
 <xref rid="B10-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Historically, Europe is the best studied of all the continents in terms of the number of publications of this genus; however, in terms of the number of species, Asia seems to be more diverse [
 <xref rid="B10-jof-07-00051" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and Africa, as well as South and Central America seem to be understudied.
</p>
