<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phenolic compounds are biosynthesized by plants through shikimate, phenylpropanoid, and flavonoid pathways, and have an aromatic ring bearing one or more hydroxyl groups. These compounds have been reported for their antioxidant, antiproliferative, and cytotoxic properties [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-25-04032" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Many phenolic compounds have been identified elsewhere from the same medicinal plants that are traditionally used to manage cancer in Ethiopia. For instance, (−)-epigallocathechin (
 <bold>25</bold>) isolated from 
 <italic>Maytenus senegalensis</italic> has showed potent cytotoxic activity against mouse lymphoma cell line (L5178Y) [
 <xref rid="B79-molecules-25-04032" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Likewise, a series phenanthrenes (5-(1-methoxyethyl)-1-methyl-phenanthren-2,7-diol (
 <bold>26</bold>); effususol A; effusol; dehydroeffusol; dehydroeffusal; 2,7-dihydroxy-1,8-dimethyl-5-vinyl-9,10-dihydrophenanthrene and juncusol; dehydrojuncusol and 1-methylpyrene-2,7-diol) from 
 <italic>Juncus effuses</italic> inhibited the proliferation of five human cancer cell lines (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-04032-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Among these, 5-(1-methoxyethyl)-1-methyl-phenanthren-2,7-diol (
 <bold>26</bold>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-04032-f003">Figure 3</xref>) was tested against MCF-7 cancer cell line and showed better cytotoxic activity [
 <xref rid="B80-molecules-25-04032" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] than all isolated compounds from 
 <italic>J. effuses</italic>. Another group of phenanthrenoids (effususol A, 
 <bold>27</bold>) has also demonstrated potent cytotoxicity against HT-22 cell by inducing caspase-3-mediated apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B81-molecules-25-04032" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Plumbagin (
 <bold>28</bold>), a naphthoquinone isolated from 
 <italic>Plumbago zeylanica</italic> also induced apoptosis in human non-small cell lung (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 6.1–10.3 µM) [
 <xref rid="B82-molecules-25-04032" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] and human pancreatic (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 2.1 µM) [
 <xref rid="B83-molecules-25-04032" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>] cancer cell lines. On the other hand, knipholone (
 <bold>29</bold>) isolated from 
 <italic>Kniphofia foliosa</italic> Hochst collected from Ethiopia, induced necrotic death in mouse melanoma (B16), mouse macrophage tumor (RAW 264.7), human acute monocytic (THP-1), and promonocytic leukaemic (U937) cell lines with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values that range from 0.5 ± 0.05 to 3.3 ± 0.39 µM [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-04032" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
