<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">To our knowledge, the presented herein results comprise the first in depth exploration of the 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> reproductive organs in respect with their alkaloid content, even though the study of 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> alkaloid content goes back almost 75 years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and quite early managed to define anabasine as the prevailing pyridine alkaloid [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The Baldwin and Ohnmeiss [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] study provided a significant conclusion, indicating that foraging may induce alkaloid content of 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], a result soon confirmed by other researchers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In 2004, Tadmor-Melamed et al. presented the alkaloid content of 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> nectar and discussed on the ecological implications regarding plant’s pollinators. Kaczorowski et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] indicated that foraging impacts on 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> are not restricted to morphological aspects but also may regulate the alkaloid content of nectar, promoting the biosynthesis of anabasine against nicotine. Another element of alkaloid content and foraging interaction was reported soon after by Aizenberg-Gershtein et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], which correlated the foragers’ preferences with the differentiated floral microbiome as a result of alterations in alkaloid content. The final conclusion of Kaczorowski and Markman [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] that plant secondary metabolites ingestion may lead to reduced foraging performance, which in turn could significantly affect an organism’s foraging efficiency, drove our consequent experimentation aiming to delineate the alkaloids fate and impacts on honeybees that forage on 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> flowers.
</p>
