<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Y-Maze spontaneous alternation behaviour test was used to evaluate the short-term memory potentials (STM) of mice by recording spontaneous alternation in a single session on day 10 [
 <xref rid="B36-brainsci-11-00259" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The Y-maze apparatus is comprised of three arms of equivalent size, labelled as A, B, and C, respectively. Each arm is 20 cm long, 6 cm wide and 15.5 cm high and is oriented at an angle of 120° from the other two. One hour after the last treatment and 30 min after scopolamine injection (except for the distilled water group), all the mice were allowed to move freely through the maze for 8 min. The numbers of arm entries were recorded for each mouse. An arm entry was considered to be completed when the hind paws of the mouse were completely placed in an arm. Spontaneous alternation was defined as consecutive entries in a specific sequence of arm transitions (ABC, BCA, or CAB but not BAB or CAC or CBC) by a mouse into the three different arms that reflects short-term memory. The total number of arm entries reveals an overall locomotor activity. The arms of the maze were cleaned using 70% 
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic> ethanol between trials to avoid olfactory cues. The number of arm entries, same arm returns (SAR), and alternate arm returns (AAR) were measured. The percentage of spontaneous alternation performance (% SAP) was determined using the following equation. 
 <disp-formula id="FD6-brainsci-11-00259">
  <label>(6)</label>
  <math id="mm7">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mi>SAP</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mrow>
      <mo>[</mo>
      <mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>Number</mi>
          <mo> </mo>
          <mi>of</mi>
          <mo> </mo>
          <mi>alternations</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
       </mrow>
       <mo>/</mo>
       <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>Total</mi>
          <mo> </mo>
          <mi>arm</mi>
          <mo> </mo>
          <mi>entries</mi>
          <mo> </mo>
         </mrow>
         <mo>−</mo>
         <mo> </mo>
         <mn>2</mn>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
      <mo>]</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
