<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sesquiterpene lactones (SLs) are biosynthesized in the medicinal plants by the oxidative transformation and cyclization of three isoprene units [
 <xref rid="B1-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. They constitute the largest and structurally most diverse group of secondary metabolites among several other natural compounds. SLs revealed the potential in nurturing humans as a dietary source and for health, as pharmaceutical agents, because of their efficiency in treating various types of ailments. SLs are formed through the mevalonic acid pathway of the plants. A general characteristic of SLs is the occurrence of the γ-lactone ring, which contains the α-methylene group. The key combinations of the α-methylene-γ-lactone comprise a few ester groups [
 <xref rid="B35-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. SLs are reputable across the plant kingdom that widespread in the families such as Asteraceae, Cactaceae, Euphorbiaceae, Solanaceae, Apiaceae, Acanthaceae, Amaranthaceae, Polygonaceae, Aristolochiaceae, Burseraceae, Illiciaceae, Magnoliaceae, Menispermaceae, Coriariaceae, Chloranthaceae, Lamiaceae, Lauraceae, and Winteraceae [
 <xref rid="B49-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. They are recognized for holding a wide variety of pharmacological and biological activities such as anti-fungal, anti-bacterial, anti-microbial, cytotoxic, antiviral and anti-inflammatory, etc. Moreover, according to folk remedies, SLs are active ingredients to treat influenza, inflammation, diarrhea, burns, and neuron degradation [
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-biomolecules-11-00350" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>].
</p>
