<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the study by 
 <xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al. (2013b)</xref>, an ethanolic root extract of 
 <italic>E. chinense</italic> (EEC) displayed a total antioxidant capacity of 90.2 μg/ml ascorbic acid equivalents. The PFRAP of the extract and the standard ascorbic acid was 0.26 and 0.42 μg/ml, respectively. The IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of the extract for DPPH, hydrogen peroxide, nitric oxide and hydroxyl radical were 146.3, 221.0, 232.9 and 170.2 μg/ml, respectively, whereas those of the standards ascorbic acid (DPPH assay), rutin (H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and nitric oxide) and butylated hydroxyanisole (hydroxyl) were 79.1, 82.9, 76.4 and 71.9 μg/ml, respectively. The antioxidant capacity of fractions (hexane, chloroform, ethyl acetate and aqueous) of EEC was also evaluated. A total antioxidant capacity of 76.0, 97.4, 89.5 and 44.6 μg/ml ascorbic acid equivalents, respectively, was determined. In contrast, very low DPPH (IC
 <sub>50</sub> 163.1–312.1 μg/ml), nitric oxide (IC
 <sub>50</sub> 201.8–372.2 μg/ml) and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> (IC
 <sub>50</sub> ≥ 187.7 μg/ml) radical scavenging activities as well as a low HORAC (IC
 <sub>50</sub> ≥ 154.4 μg/ml) were observed for these fractions (
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al., 2013a</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">Thongnest et al. (2013)</xref> evaluated the antioxidant activity of 11 flavonoids from the roots of 
 <italic>E. chinense</italic> using a DPPH method. The most pronounced effects, close to the standard butylated hydroxytoluene (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 39 µM), were observed with compounds 
 <bold>10</bold> (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 28 µM) and 
 <bold>20</bold> (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 35 µM), while 
 <bold>11</bold>, 
 <bold>12</bold>, 
 <bold>23–25</bold>, 
 <bold>27</bold>, 
 <bold>33</bold>, 
 <bold>40</bold> and 
 <bold>49</bold> with IC
 <sub>50</sub> ≥ 252 μM, were inactive. In rats, a single oral pretreatment (30 min before castor oil challenge) with EEC (at 400 mg/kg), its chloroform fraction (at 100 mg/kg), and compounds 
 <bold>39</bold> (10 mg/kg) and 
 <bold>81</bold> (10 mg/kg) prevented the alterations of nitric oxide, TBARS (lipid peroxidation), superoxide dismutase and catalase activities in the castor oil-mediated diarrhea model (
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al., 2013c</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al., 2017</xref>). Compound 
 <bold>81</bold> (5 and 10 mg/kg) restored the oxidative status (nitric oxide level, SOD and CAT activities) in the enteropathogenic 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>-induced diarrhea rat model.
</p>
