<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antioxidant capacity of 
 <italic>Eriosema</italic> species was evaluated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> by different methods addressing different mechanisms of action. Each of them has its strengths and weaknesses (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Bibi Sadeer et al., 2020</xref>). The plant extracts and products are mixtures of compounds that can display their antioxidant activity through different mechanisms. Therefore, to better estimate the overall antioxidant activity of a sample, at least two (or even all) of these assays must be combined. 
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">Tan and Lim (2015)</xref> recommended a mix of single electron transfer based (DPPH, ABTS, FRAP, TBARS) and hydrogen atom transfer based (ORAC, HORAC, TRAP, crocin and β-carotene bleaching) assays. Among the six 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies recorded in this review, just two (
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al., 2013a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al., 2013b</xref>) met with this requirement, while the other ones only used β-carotene bleaching (
 <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr">Mmbengwa et al., 2009</xref>) or DPPH (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Awouafack et al., 2013b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">Thongnest et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Awouafack et al., 2018</xref>) assays. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> models are known to be not always reproducible in respective 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> assays. Therefore, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies are necessary for the confirmation of such effects. Interestingly, the weakly active ethanol root extract of 
 <italic>E. chinense</italic>, its chloroform fraction and the inactive compound 
 <bold>39</bold> using DPPH method, restored the alterations of nitric oxide, TBARS, superoxide dismutase and catalase activities in the castor oil-mediated diarrhea model in rats (
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">Prasad et al., 2013c</xref>). Although data at this level seems to be naïve and preliminary for any conclusion, they are indicator of the antioxidant potential of members of the 
 <italic>Eriosema</italic> genus. However, more species need to be investigated 
 <italic>in vitro and in vivo</italic>.
</p>
