<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Traditional medicine refers to ways of protecting and restoring health that existed before the arrival of modern medicine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The World Health Organisation (WHO) defines traditional medicine as native health practices, approaches, knowledge and beliefs that maybe applied either singular or in combination to treat, diagnose and maintain wellbeing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It plays an important role in health care provision in the developing world and its use is also now significant in developed countries thus increasing commercial value. Traditional herbal medicines are naturally occurring plant and animal based substances with minimal or no industrial processing that are used to treat diseases within some healing practices [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Some people rely on these medicines to meet their health requirements. According to WHO, a third of the world’s population has no regular access to essential modern medicine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In parts of Africa, Asia and Latin America, it is estimated that about half of the population faces shortages of minimum healthcare; due mainly to inadequacies in healthcare financing by the governments. This poses for glaring inequities in healthcare delivery in developing countries. Heavy burden of communicable diseases (HIV/AIDS, malaria, TB, pneumonia, diarrhoeas) coupled with the advent of growing threat of non-communicable diseases (NCDs) such as diabetes, cancer, hypertension, ischemic heart diseases; amongst many others, torment lives in developing countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The use of ethnomedicinal plants contribute to primary healthcare of people of the area that they are found [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and thus contribute a rich health to human beings. About 80% of people living in rural settings in developing countries use traditional medicine for their primary health care needs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and, generally, a number of cancer patients have been found to be using traditional medicine as primary therapy and/or as complementary medicine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].
</p>
