<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The chemical interactions between plants and the environment are mainly mediated by the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites, and much of these metabolites are derivatives of primary metabolites produced by plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0243111.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Primary metabolite citric acid is a key metabolic component of the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA cycle), generating energy and providing adaptive flexibility for adverse environments. Most secondary metabolite biosynthesis starts from basic pathways, such as glycolysis or shikimic acid pathways [
 <xref rid="pone.0243111.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Shikimic acid is a precursor for the aromatic amino acids, alkaloids, tannins, and lignin. According to the type of secondary metabolites in plants, they can be divided into three major classes of biosynthetic pathways including nitrogen-containing compounds (cyanogenic glycosides, alkaloids, and glucosinolates), phenolic compounds (flavonoids and phenylpropane), and terpenes (isoprenoids). In this study, we investigate some metabolic pathways including phenolic acid, flavonoid, iridoid biosynthesis, glycolysis, TCA cycle, and alkaloid, then selecting the representative pathways for more detailed analysis. The biosynthesis OF metabolite is subject to dynamic regulation by metabolic feedback and environmental factors. Therefore, to future research how these metabolites distributed under oxidative stress is important. Specifically, chlorogenic acid and luteoloside, which is the chemical markers for evaluating the quality of LJF in Chinese Pharmacopoeia (2015 edition) [
 <xref rid="pone.0243111.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Chlorogenic acid is one of the most widely known derivatives of hydroxycinnamic acid in the plant kingdom, and numerous reports on the biosynthesis of chlorogenic acid have been published [
 <xref rid="pone.0243111.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. However, the biosynthetic pathway for generating chlorogenic acid is still controversial; hence, more studies remain to be carried out. The phenolic acid, flavonoid, and iridoid biosynthesis of LJF under salt stress were inferred in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0243111.g005">Fig 5</xref>. Generally, the biosynthesis of phenolic compounds is believed to be primarily regulated at the transcriptional level; the above synthetic pathway provided in the reference for phenolic acid synthesis facilitated a better understanding of its transcriptional regulation. Meanwhile, it also provides new ideas for the selection of regulatory genes for metabolic engineering under salt stress. And the published studies also focus on luteoloside and flavonoid biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0243111.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], the subgroup pathway including isoflavinoid, flavone, and flavonol biosynthesis also should be attentioned. Besides, the pathways of iridoid metabolites were also mentioned in the study. In the subsequent, we will utilize multivariate omics data [
 <xref rid="pone.0243111.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] to better understanding the molecular changes/mechanism of LJF under salt stress, the prognostic molecular pathways will be analyzed by integrating genomic, transcriptomic and proteomic. Overall, an in-depth study of the molecular mechanism and network regulation of bioactive constituents synthesis in medicinal plants under salt stress will be an crucial research directions.
</p>
