<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There have been several studies on the biological activity of extracts of this species (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-03529-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We can find Anti-Proteus [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and anti-Klebsiella [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] activities of the MeOH and water extracts of South African species, indicating their potential for blocking the onset of rheumatoid arthritis and preventing the onset of ankylosing spondylitis [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]; Inhibition on the growth of phagocytosed multidrug-resistant 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> of the MeOH/water extract of a species from Sintra, Portugal, suggesting that this plant may serve as a source of new antimicrobial agents that are effective against problematic drug-resistant intracellular infections [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]; neuroprotective properties of the 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane, CH
 <sub>2</sub>Cl
 <sub>2</sub>, AcOEt and MeOH extracts of a species from Faro, Portugal, suggesting that the consumption of leaves from 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> can contribute for a balanced diet and may add to the improvement of cognitive functions [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]; the effect of the MeOH/water extract of an undisclosed species in inhibiting the MDR efflux pumps, enhancing the killing of phagocytosed 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and promoting immune modulation, indicating that the resistance modifier and immunomodulatory effect of this plant extract can be exploited in the experimental chemotherapy of cancer and bacterial or viral infections [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]; antioxidant, metal chelating and anticholinesterase activities of MeOH extracts of species collected in the Algarve, Portugal, together with their fatty acid profile, indicating that 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> is a candidate on novel and alternative therapies for the treatment of neurological disorders associated with low levels of acetylcholine in the brain [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]; antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of the acetone/water extract of a species collected in Monastir, Tunisia emphasizing the beneficial cosmetic and therapeutic use of this plant [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]; antioxidant activity of the 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane, acetone, EtOH and water extracts of a species from Eastern Cape, South Africa, that may justify the traditional use of this plant in the management of common diseases in HIV/AIDS patients in Eastern Cape Province [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and inhibition of protein glycation, antioxidant and antiproliferative activities of the EtOH and EtOH/Water extracts of species collected in Sousse, Tunisia [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. From this study, and by HPLC analysis with standards, sinapic acid, ferulic acid, luteolin 7-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, hyperoside, isoquercitrin, ellagic acid and isorhamnetin 3-
 <italic>O</italic>-rutinoside were identified [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The results suggest that the 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> extracts could be used as an easily accessible source of natural antioxidants and as potential phytochemicals against protein glycation and colon cancer. More recently a study concerning the biological activity of the peel and flesh extracts (water, EtOH and acetone) of the fruits of a specimen of 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic>, collected in Algarve, Portugal, was published [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-03529" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Antioxidant, anti-microbial, enzymatic inhibitory properties and toxicity were evaluated and more than 80 compounds (mostly phenolic acids, flavonoids, and coumarins) were identified by HPLC-ESI-MS/MS, with or without standards. The potential use of the fruits of 
 <italic>C. edulis</italic> as sources of molecules and/or products to be used in the food, pharmaceutic, agriculture and cosmetic areas is suggested.
</p>
