<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fragrances and flavors are a key part of modern food, drinks, cosmetics, aromatherapy, and many other personal hygiene products. The most important activities in the flavor and fragrance industry are quality control, the search for natural sources for novel fragrant compounds, the development of sampling, and analytical technologies [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Currently there is no standard analytical method for the online direct analysis and monitoring of the fragrance active components during the processing and quality control stages. Traditional analytical techniques such as solid phase extraction (SPE) [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] and liquid/liquid extraction (LLE) [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] followed by gas or liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (GC-MS or LC-MS) [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] are routinely used in the analysis and quantification of the active components of the fragrance and flavors with exceptional sensitivity and specificity. However, sample collection and transfer to an offsite laboratory is required [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. These steps are labor intensive and time consuming and require skillful sample preparation personnel [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. There is a clear need for portable analytical technologies that are field ready to allow
 <italic class="italic"> in-situ</italic> analysis at the source [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. This is useful not only for quality control, but also for the development of new fragrant products to satisfy the increasing consumer demand [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. As it will be shown in this study, a portable mass spectrometer combined with a direct inlet membrane (DIM) probe can meet such criteria.
</p>
