<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Age related neurodegenerative diseases namely Parkinson's, Huntington's, and Alzheimer's diseases are increased among the human population (Aruoma et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Recently, investigations are ongoing to develop new strategies to reduce the disease progression since there is no effective cure for above mentioned disorders (Abushouk et al., 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Recent studies indicate that medicinal plants showed good neuroprotection (de Rus Jacquet et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The neuroprotective effect of aqueous extract from the leaves of 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> was investigated and reported by studying the learning capacity and memory in mice (Elsaey et al., 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Four doses of the extract were administrated and memory test was performed at two different Zeitgeber times (3:00-rest phase and 15:00-active phase). Insulin was administrated intranasal were treated as positive control. The results on the memory performance showed that intranasal administration of the extract improved the functions of memory close to the positive control insulin. The subchronic administration of the extract at the dose of 25 mg/kg showed significant differences at the Zeitgeber time 3:00 on memory and learning. Whereas, subchronic administration had no significant difference on memory and learning at the Zeitgeber time 15:00. Also it was observed that, in acute administration, there was no locomotor activity observed after intranasal administration of single dose of 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> extract neither with any dose nor at both Zeitgeber times. Also there was no significant difference on locomotor activity in sub-chronic administration of the extract. Based on the results, it was concluded that the aqueous extract of 
 <italic>M. peregrina</italic> enhanced the memory function of scopolamine induced amnesia in mice.
</p>
