<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0046">Vitamin E is also a fat soluble vital and has an antioxidative potential and regulates the host's immune responses (
 <xref rid="bib0088" ref-type="bibr">I Eze et al., 2016</xref>). The positive effect of vitamin E against chronic hepatitis was reported by 
 <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Andreone et al. (2001)</xref>. They suggested appreciable elevation in normalization of liver enzyme activity and HBV-DNA negativitization. Another vitamin that acts as an important antioxidant and enzymatic co-factor is Vitamin C. It acts as a co-factor in varied physiological processes such as hormone synthesis, immune potentiation and collagen synthesis (
 <xref rid="bib0109" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2013</xref>). The meta-analysis role of vitamin C in treatment and preventions of common cold was carried out by 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">Hemilä and Chalker (2013)</xref>. It was concluded in the view of evidences that vitamin C mega dose showed reduction in the frequency of common cold in the community. A study conducted by 
 <xref rid="bib0233" ref-type="bibr">Utomo and Meiyanto (2020)</xref> was aimed at elucidating the potential of 
 <italic>Curcuma sp., Citrus sp., Alpinia galanga</italic>, and 
 <italic>Caesalpinia sappan</italic> as an anti SARS-CoV-2 agent via its binding to 3 protein receptors. The protein targets identified were Receptor Binding Domain of spike glycol proteins (RBDS), protease domain of Angiotensin Converting Enzyme-2 PD-ACE2 and SARS-CoV-2 protease by employing molecular docking technique. The result of the study revealed that 
 <italic>Citrus</italic> sp. had the highest inhibitory potential against SARS-CoV-2, followed by galangal, sappan wood and curcuma species and it was further suggested that they might have antiviral potency against COVID-19. Additionally, different plant based sources of vitamins include, mushrooms, carrots, broccoli, almonds, citrus, guava, amla, avocados etc. 
 <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> describes the role of Vitamins (A, C, E and D) in combating COVID-19.
</p>
