<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec>
  <title>Context</title>
  <p> The traditional drying method, sun drying, for 
   <italic>Chrysanthemum morifolium</italic> Ramat. cv. Hang-ju (Compositae) (HJ) is widely replaced by sulphur fumigation (SF), which has an unknown effect on its efficacy.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Objective</title>
  <p> To investigate protective effects of nonfumigated HJ (NHJ) and sulphur-fumigated HJ (SHJ) water extracts against oxidative stress and lipid peroxidation.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Materials and methods</title>
  <p> Sprague-Dawley rats were administered high-fat diet to induce hyperlipidaemia and randomly divided into eight groups (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6): control, fenofibrate, NHJ and SHJ extracts (1, 2 or 4 g crude drugs/kg/d; intragastric administration for 8 weeks). Serum total cholesterol (TC), triglyceride (TG), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C), superoxide dismutase (SOD) and malondialdehyde (MDA) levels were detected. Human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) were treated with NHJ and SHJ extracts (50, 100 or 200 μg/mL) for 24 h, followed by oxidized low-density lipoprotein (ox-LDL, 20 μg/mL) for 2 h 
   <italic>in vitro</italic>. Cellular reactive oxygen species (ROS), SOD and MDA levels and apoptosis were evaluated.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p> NHJ was more effective than SHJ in decreasing serum TG, TC, LDL-C, LDL/HDL and MDA while increasing serum HDL-C and SOD levels at high doses. SHJ (IC
   <sub>50</sub>=19.9 mg/mL) suppressed HUVEC growth stronger than NHJ (IC
   <sub>50</sub>=186.7 mg/mL). At 200 μg/mL, NHJ was more effective than SHJ in downregulating ROS and MDA levels, reducing HUVECs apoptosis rate and elevating SOD activity in ox-LDL-treated HUVECs.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p> SF causes oxidative damage and attenuates antioxidative activity in ox-LDL-treated HUVECs, which promotes lipid peroxidation. SF is not recommended for processing HJ.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
