<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9. 
  <span class="italic">Nerium oleander</span>
 </div>
 <sec id="sec3.9.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.1. Botanical Study</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oleander is from 2 to 3 meters high. Its stems are glabrous and spread at the break a milky juice. The leaves are opposed by two or three, leathery, persistent, long lanceolate, and acute, with parallel veins, and tight on the stem. The flowers are pink, large, generally fragrant, and arranged in large terminal corymbs. The corolla is in saucer, with five petals welded by their base. The fruit is a follicle that sits in a cylindrical pod, and the seeds (which are rather infrequently formed) are hairy and have a feather [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">12</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.9.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.2. Biogeography</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The oleander is a plant native to Europe and Africa and is commonly found in the tropical and subtropical regions of the world [
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">53</a>]. This plant is grown in more northern regions. It grows spontaneously on the rocky banks of rivers, sometimes even in coastal areas, usually devolved to halophilic species. It adapts to drought and is very decorative [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.9.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.3. Toxic Part(s)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All parts of the plant are toxic to humans, animals, and some insects [
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">54</a>]. This shrub is highly poisonous, which should not be confused with a bay leaf, used constantly as a seasoning [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">12</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3.9.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.9.4. Phytochemistry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">(1) Active Ingredient</span>. The toxic principles are digitalis glycosides, present in all parts of the plant, thereof, cardenolides, which account for about 1.5% of the weight of the leaves.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oleandrine (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig12" href="#fig12">Figure 12</a>), the majority, is heteroside of oleandrose and oleandrigenin.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The seeds contain oleandrin and related compounds: odorosides, adigoside, and glucostrospeside [
   <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
   <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">55</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">(2) Chemical Structure</span>. Oleandrine (oleandroside) is a cardiotonic glycoside derived from an aglycone, oleandrigenin (16-acetylgitoxigenin), and a sugar oleandrose (2-deoxy-3-O-methylrhamnose), of the empirical formula C
   <sub>32</sub>H
   <sub>48</sub>O
   <sub>9</sub>. Pure oleandrin is in the form of colorless, odorless, and very bitter crystals. It is soluble in chloroform and ethanol and insoluble in water. See 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig12" href="#fig12">Figure 12</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
