<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">
 <italic>Millettia</italic> is a genus of legume in the Fabaceae family. This genus has about 150 species, which are abundant in the tropical and subtropical regions of the world (
 <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Manikandan et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <italic>Millettia peguensis</italic> is commonly called Moulmein Rosewood (
 <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">Packiyalakshmi et al., 2017b</xref>) and known as Tuma found in Bangladesh which is native to lower Burma and Siam, but cultivated in Burma, India and Pakistan too. It is planted for ornamental purposes, and showed eye-catching beauty during full bloom. This blooms with racemes of mauve pea-like flowers along with pinnate leaves and oval-shaped leaflets. From 
 <italic>Millettia peguensis</italic> several phytoconstituents were isolated, most notably flavonoids including pongamol, lanceolatin-B, kanjone, milletenone, ovaliflavanone-A, ovalitenone, pongaglabol and other bioactive phytoconstituents (
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Ganapaty et al., 1998</xref>). In addition, pongamol has been reported to have larvicidal activity against 
 <italic>Aedesaegypti</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">Narkhede et al., 2016</xref>) and pongaglabol for antioxidant activity (
 <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">Rao et al., 2020</xref>); lanceolatin - B has shown antibacterial and anti-inflammatory activity (
 <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">Rao et al., 2020</xref>), whereas pongaglabol has shown antiulcer activity (
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad et al., 1999</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Huo et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <italic>Millettia peguensis</italic> is reported with other versatile phytochemicals too in a different report including 9-methylheptadecane, eicosane, heneicosane, dodecyl hexyl ester, 2- bromododecane and other phytoconstituents (
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Ganapaty et al., 1998</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Packiyalakshmi et al., 2017</xref>). Moreover, the genus of 
 <italic>Millettia</italic> plants has shown the potentiality to work as insecticidal and pesticide agents along with antimalarial and antioxidant candidates (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Abiy et al., 2003</xref>). This study was conducted to evaluate the analgesic, antidiarrheal, antioxidant, cytotoxic, thrombolytic and antimicrobial activity of the leaves extract of 
 <italic>M. peguensis</italic> by biological and computational approaches.
</p>
