<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The isolate was grown on potato dextrose broth (PDB) with 140 r/min at 25°C for 5 days. The genomic DNA of mycelia was extracted by kit (Eppendorf, Holstein City, Germany). The internal transcribed spacer (ITS) regions and the small subunit (ITS1-5.8S-ITS2) of the rDNA genes were amplified using the primer set ITS1 (5′-TCCGTAGGTGAACCTGCGG-3′) and ITS4 (5′-TCCTCCGCTTATTGATATGC-3′) (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhao et al., 2010</xref>). Primers were synthesized by Shanghai Sangon Biological Engineering Technology &amp; Services Co., Ltd (Shanghai, China). PCR amplification was carried out in aqueous volumes of 25 μL. The reactions contained 0.5 μL template DNA (30 ng), 0.5 μL (10 μmol/L) of each primer, 5 × PCR buffer (with MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) 2.5 μL, 0.5 μL dNTP (2.5 mmol/L), 0.5 μL Taq polymerase (2.5 U/μL) and 20 μL ddH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O. PCR reactions were performed on a ABI 2720 thermal cycler (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, United States). Thermal cycling was carried out using an initial denaturation step at 98°C for 3 min, followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 98°C for 25 s, annealing at 55°C for 25 s and extension at 72°C for 60 s. Cycling was completed by a final elongation step at 72°C for 10 min. PCR products were purified using PCR purification kit (Shanghai Sangon Biological Engineering Technology &amp; Services Co., Ltd, Shanghai, China). Sequencing was performed with an ABI 3730XL automated sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, United States). Further, the sequence was analyzed and determined to search for similar sequences from the Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST) software
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup> algorithm at National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI). To construct the relevant phylogenic tree, MEGA 5.02 software was employed (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saitou and Nei, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tamura et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
