<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6343004</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">36483</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-36483-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> adaptation in sea water microcosms at elevated temperature provides insights into the putative mechanisms of its persistence and spread in the time of global warming</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mont&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>Itxaso</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ogayar</surname><given-names>Elixabet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pl&#x000e1;garo</surname><given-names>Ander Hern&#x000e1;ndez</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Esteve-Codina</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6409-8009</contrib-id><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Garrido</surname><given-names>J&#x000e8;ssica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Orru&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>Maite</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arana</surname><given-names>In&#x000e9;s</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kaberdin</surname><given-names>Vladimir R.</given-names></name><address><email>vladimir.kaberdin@ehu.eus</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000121671098</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11480.3c</institution-id><institution>Department of Immunology, Microbiology and Parasitology, </institution><institution>University of the Basque Country UPV/EHU, </institution></institution-wrap>48940 Leioa, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.473715.3</institution-id><institution>CNAG-CRG, Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG), </institution><institution>Barcelona Institute of Science and Technology (BIST), </institution></institution-wrap>Barcelona, Catalonia 08028 Spain </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2172 2676</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5612.0</institution-id><institution>Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF), </institution></institution-wrap>Barcelona, Catalonia 08003 Spain </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Research Centre for Experimental Marine Biology and Biotechnology (PIE-UPV/EHU), 48620 Plentzia, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0467 2314</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.424810.b</institution-id><institution>IKERBASQUE, Basque Foundation for Science, </institution></institution-wrap>Maria Diaz de Haro 3, 48013 Bilbao, Spain </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>289</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Discovering the means to control the increasing dissemination of pathogenic vibrios driven by recent climate change is challenged by the limited knowledge of the mechanisms in charge of <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. persistence and spread in the time of global warming. To learn about physiological and gene expression patterns associated with the long-term persistence of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> at elevated temperatures, we studied adaptation of this marine bacterium in seawater microcosms at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C which closely mimicked the upper limit of sea surface temperatures around the globe. We found that nearly 90% of cells lost their culturability and became partly damaged after two weeks, thus suggesting a negative impact of the combined action of elevated temperature and shortage of carbon on <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> survival. Moreover, further gene expression analysis revealed that major adaptive mechanisms were poorly coordinated and apparently could not sustain cell fitness. On the other hand, elevated temperature and starvation promoted expression of many virulence genes, thus potentially reinforcing the pathogenicity of this organism. These findings suggest that the increase in disease outbreaks caused by <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> under rising sea surface temperatures may not reflect higher cell fitness, but rather an increase in virulence enabling <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> to escape from adverse environments to nutrient rich, host-pathogen associations.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100003339</institution-id><institution>Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness | Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x00026;amp;#x00ED;ficas (Spanish National Research Council)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>CGL2015-70929-R</award-id><award-id>PT17/0009/0019</award-id><award-id>PT17/0009/0019</award-id><award-id>CGL2015-70929-R</award-id><award-id>CGL2015-70929-R</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ogayar</surname><given-names>Elixabet</given-names></name><name><surname>Esteve-Codina</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Garrido</surname><given-names>J&#x000e8;ssica</given-names></name><name><surname>Arana</surname><given-names>In&#x000e9;s</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaberdin</surname><given-names>Vladimir R.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2"><italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> is a heterotrophic Gram-negative luminous bacterium inhabiting marine environments and showing a preference for temperate and tropical waters. In its natural habitats, <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. can be found attached to either biotic or abiotic surfaces<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, in a free living state as well as in symbiotic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> or host-pathogen<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> interactions with other organisms, occasionally causing diseases or even death of the infected organisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">The most recent studies have revealed a wider spread of pathogenic vibrios and this phenomenon was documented along with a gradual increase in sea surface temperature taking place in the time of global warming (GW)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Consistent with the above trends, there have been a concomitant increase in the cholera or/and gastroenteritis outbreaks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> apparently caused by the consumption of water contaminated with pathogenic vibrios<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. As the average temperature of water increases towards the equator, more cases of <italic>Vibrio</italic>-related diseases were reported in countries such as India or those in the Caribbean<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Moreover, a number of recent reports clearly point to the emergence of <italic>Vibrio</italic>-associated diseases in Europe including some countries where the presence of virulent variants of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>vulnificus</italic> and other pathogenic strains could barely been detected previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. This alarming statistics includes discovery of pathogenic <italic>Vibrio</italic> species in several unexpected locations such as finding of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>cholerae</italic> in estuaries of Portugal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>parahaemolyticus</italic> on the French Atlantic coast<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> and the highly pathogenic strain <italic>V</italic>. <italic>parahaemolyticus serovar</italic> O3:K6 in Spain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">In accordance with the overall increase in the occurrence of <italic>Vibrio</italic>-associated diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, several highly virulent <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> strains able to provoke mass mortality in both marine invertebrates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> and various fishes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> have been reported as well. <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> is notoriously known for being an important pathogen of cultured penaeid shrimp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> and its wider occurrence in aquaculture farms causes serious problems for the seafood industry, especially in tropical countries where temperatures are generally higher. As the forecast is not promising, it is conceivable that the ocean is going to experience even more devastating consequences of GW in the coming years, which could likely lead to further spread of <italic>Vibrio</italic>-associated infections.</p><p id="Par5">The ubiquitous presence and further spread of <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. indicate that these marine bacteria are able to easily adapt to changing environmental conditions including those caused by GW. Several studies have previously examined their adaptation by analyzing phenotypical and gene expression changes taking place in <italic>Vibrio</italic> species facing different stress conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Analysis of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> adaptation revealed that deprivation of nutrients (starvation) can trigger profound morphological changes leading to reduction of cell size and conversion of rod-shaped bacteria into their coccoid-like variants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In addition, when environmental conditions become unfavorable (e.g. limitation of nutrients, low temperature, low salinity or ultra violet (UV) radiation), <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> can occasionally acquire the <underline>v</underline>iable <underline>b</underline>ut <underline>n</underline>on<underline>c</underline>ulturable (VBNC) phenotype<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> and preserve it until the adverse conditions are eliminated, subsequently being able to recover from this state of dormancy and resume growth.</p><p id="Par6">An important characteristics that enables vibrios to successfully strive in marine ecosystems is their metabolic versatility, in particular, their capacity to use a wide variety of organic substances (e.g. D-glucose, N-acetyl-D-glucosamine, L-asparagine aconitate <italic>etc</italic>.) as a primary carbon source. Moreover, the use of different carbon sources is, in turn, facilitated by the ability of <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. to secrete various hydrolytic enzymes (amylases, gelatinases, lipases and chitinases) converting the naturally occuring biopolymers (e.g. proteins, polysaccharides, chitin <italic>etc</italic>.) into smaller, easily metabolizable compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">Although changing environments are known to have a great impact on marine bacteria, little is known about how the physiology, metabolic preferences and adaptation mechanisms of <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. are affected by the main environmental factors (elevated temperature, ocean acidification, suboptimal salinity concentration, <italic>etc</italic>.) caused by the ongoing GW. In order to learn more about <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. responses to GW and their possible contribution to survival and pathogenicity of <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp., we studied phenotypical and gene expression changes that occur during the time-dependent adaptation of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> in seawater microcosm at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C which is close to the upper limit of sea surface temperature (SST) recently observed in some regions of the globe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p><sec id="Sec2"><title>Experimental procedures</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Survival assays, bacterial cell count and size measurements</title><p id="Par8">To assess the combined effect of carbon limitation and elevated temperature on physiology and appearance of <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 14126&#x02122;, cells were aerobically grown overnight at 26&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (optimal temperature for <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> growth) in Marine broth (MB) (Panreac) and three 20&#x02009;mL aliquots of the stationary phase cultures were independently diluted (1:20) with sterile natural seawater to obtain 400&#x02009;mL suspensions with a final density of 10<sup>8</sup> cells mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The resulting inoculates of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> were incubated in dark with shaking (90&#x02009;rpm) at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C within 21 days. The experiments were carried out in 1&#x02009;L glass flasks beforehand cleaned with H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (97%, v/v), rinsed with deionized water and heated at 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;h to avoid any presence of residual organic matter.</p><p id="Par9">The seawater was sampled in the Port of Armintza in the Bay of Biscay, 43&#x000b0;26&#x02032;24&#x02033;N and 2&#x000b0;54&#x02032;24&#x02033;W and then was filter sterilized and autoclaved. The concentration of dissolved organic carbon (DOC) previously measured in the same area is in the range of 0.2&#x02013;0.4&#x02009;mM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, which is nearly 200 times lower than the concentration of organic carbon in MB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nrmicro1752//tables/1">https://www.nature.com/articles/nrmicro1752/tables/1</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par10">Periodically, samples were collected for further analysis. The total number of cells was determined by filtering aliquots of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> suspensions (withdrawn after 3, 6, 9, 13 and 21 days of incubation) through 0.22 &#x003bc;m pore-size polycarbonate membrane filters (Millipore), followed by staining of the attached cells with acridine orange and direct counting individual cells using epifluorescence microscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. The microscope (Eclipse E400, Nikon) was equipped with a video camera Hamamatsu 2400 (Hamamatsu Photonics, Japan) enabling to obtain high resolution images for their subsequent analysis by Scion Image 1.62<sup>a</sup> software to determine the size of individual cells as described by<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Approximately 150&#x02013;200 cells were measured in each sample, and, according to their length, the cells fell into three groups:&#x02264;1.2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m, &#x0003e;1.2&#x02013;2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m and &#x0003e;2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">Cultivability expressed as colony-forming units (CFU) was evaluated by spreading aliquots (withdrawn after 2, 3, 5, 7, 9, 12, 15, 17, 19 and 21 days of incubation) obtained by consecutive dilutions of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> suspensions on Marine Agar (MA, Oxoid) followed by incubation for 24&#x02009;h at 26&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p id="Par12"><italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells present in the control (overnight culture) and test samples (i.e after 3, 6 and 21 days of incubation in seawater at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) were fixed by adding 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 3% formalin to each sample (1&#x02009;mL) and were further stored at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The suspensions of the fixed cells were filtered through 0.22 &#x003bc;m pore-size membrane filters (GTTP filters, Millipore) and the cells attached to the filters were further examined by scanning electron microscopy (SEM) at the Advance Research Core Facility Unit (SGIker) of the University of the Basque Country. Briefly, the filters with the attached <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells were dehydrated by sequentially immersing them (for 5&#x02009;min each time) in water/ethanol solutions containing increasing concentrations of ethanol (30, 50, 70, 90, and 100%, respectively) followed by overlaying with hexamethyldisilazane, incubation for 5&#x02009;min and drying on air. Finally, the samples were coated with a layer of 15&#x02009;nm gold by using an Emitech K550X Sputter Coater, and imaging was further carried out by examining samples in a Hitachi S4800 scanning electron microscope.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RNA isolation, sequencing and processing of RNAseq data</title><p id="Par13"><italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 14126&#x02122; cultures were grown in triplicate overnight (12&#x02013;16&#x02009;h) at 26&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in MB, and 20&#x02009;mL of each culture were individually diluted (1:20) with sterile seawater (originated from the same batch of sterile seawater used in the survival assays) and further incubated in 1&#x02009;L glass flasks with shaking (90&#x02009;rpm) at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Aliquots of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> suspensions were withdrawn after 12&#x02009;h, 3 and 6 days of incubation, mixed (8:1) with stop solution (5% phenol in ethanol) and then incubated on ice for 15&#x02013;20&#x02009;min. The cells were collected by centrifugation (15&#x02009;min, 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 4400&#x02009;g) and the resulting cell pellets were further used to isolate total RNA by employing TRIzol reagent and PureRNA mini Kit (Invitrogen) following the vendor&#x02019;s instructions.</p><p id="Par14">After verifying the quality of the purified RNA by using Bioanalyzer (Agilent), it was further processed with the assistance of the General Genomic Service (SGIker) of the University of the Basque Country. The libraries were prepared from total RNA by using ScriptSeq Complete kit (Illumina) optimized for bacterial RNA. The complete kit included the Ribo-Zero rRNA Removal Kit and ScriptSeq v2 Kit with ScriptSeq Index PCR Primers Set. The Ribo-Zero rRNA Removal kit was used to deplete 275&#x02013;400&#x02009;ng of total RNA with ribosomal RNA following the low input protocol. The samples depleted with rRNA were then concentrated with RNA Clean &#x00026; Concentrator-5 kit (Zymo Research) for recovery and preservation of large RNA fragments (&#x0003e;200 nt) and afterwards were used to prepare stranded RNA-Seq libraries according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Further RNA sequencing and bioinformatics analysis were carried out at the National Center for Genomic Analysis (CNAG) in Barcelona integrated with the Center for Genomic Regulation (CRG). The libraries were sequenced on HiSeq. 4000 (Illumina) in a paired-end mode with a read length of 2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;76&#x02009;bp using HiSeq. 4000 SBS kit in a fraction of a HiSeq. 4000 PE Cluster kit sequencing flow cell lane following the standard protocol.</p><p id="Par15">Image analysis, base calling and quality scoring of the run were processed using the manufacturer&#x02019;s software Real Time Analysis (RTA 2.7.6) and followed by generation of FASTQ sequence files by CASAVA. The processed RNA-seq reads were mapped against <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 43516&#x02122; reference genome (available at ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genomes/genbank/; accession number GCA_001558435.1) with STAR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> and were further quantified with RSEM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Information about some sRNAs initially absent in the annotation of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; 43516&#x02122; genome was added to the annotation file by performing a highly restrictive BLAST search by using the sequences of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>campbellii</italic> ATCC&#x000ae; BAA-1116&#x02122; sRNAs retrieved from RFAM and BSRD databases as queries. Functional annotation of other genes was performed by blasting each assembled gene sequence to find homology to other V. <italic>harveyi</italic> genes already annotated in the NCBI database and the functional annotations of the best hits was used for the final annotations of transcripts revealed by RNA-seq. Differential expression analysis was performed with DESeq. 2&#x02009;R<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> and genes with false discovery rate (FDR)&#x0003c;5% and fold change &#x0003e;2 were considered significant and were further used to construct temporal clusters. Time series cluster analysis according to the soft clustering algorithm was performed with Mfuzz bioconductor package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> with k&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 found to be optimal to obtain the minimal average cluster overlap. Gene ontology enrichment of the differentially expressed genes was performed with GOstats<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. All raw and processed RNA-seq data were deposited into the GEO archive (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) and are publicly available under accession number GSE113564.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Effects of prolonged incubation of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells in seawater at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C on their culturability and morphology</title><p id="Par16">Experiments were done with three independent microcosms (biological replicates) prepared by diluting aliquots of the stationary phase cultures (control) with sterile seawater and analyzing the appearance and culturability of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> populations after 12&#x02009;hours, 3, 6, 14 and 21 days of incubation. While determining culturable populations in aliquots withdrawn at different time points and analyzed by spreading on MA plates, a 10-fold decrease in the number of culturable cells was observed after three weeks of incubation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> counts obtained during its persistence in seawater at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The number of total (&#x02022;) and culturable (&#x025cb;) bacteria were estimated as described in Materials and Methods. The data are mean values from three independent experiments with errors bars representing the standard deviations calculated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36483_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e788"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">Moreover, the loss of culturability was accompanied by a marked reduction of cell size that became readily distinguishable already after 3 days of incubation. Furthermore, a gradual increase of the fractions of smaller cells was observed until the last day of the measurements (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In other words, while 75.5% of the cells in the control sample represented by the overnight culture (day 0) had size between 1.2 to 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m, this number has decreased to 27.4% after 3 days of incubation and the percentage of longer cells continued decreasing progressively until day 6, when nearly all cells (i.e. 95%) were shorter than 1.2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Size distribution of <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> cells during their persistence in seawater at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The values were obtained by analyzing cell images captured by epifluorescence microscopy and processed as described in Materials and Methods. The bars show the percentage of cell within each size range (&#x025a0; &#x02264;1.2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m; <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36483_Figa_HTML.gif" id="d29e805"/> &#x0003e;1.2 &#x02212;&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m and <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36483_Figb_HTML.gif" id="d29e808"/> &#x0003e;2&#x02009;&#x000b5;m, respectively).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36483_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e811"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">The observed size reduction was further corroborated by the results of scanning electron microscopy (SEM). SEM confirmed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) the appearance of cells with a coccoid-like morphology (i.e. with a nearly spherical shape) after 3 to 6 days of incubation. Moreover, the electron microscopy revealed a considerable number of damaged cells, thus indicating that prolong incubation (&#x0003e;6 days) under carbon limitation at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C can lead to the loss of cell integrity.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Morphology and integrity of <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> populations incubated in seawater at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Scanning electron microscopy images were obtained for the cells present in the initial inoculate (control) as well as those incubated at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3, 6 and 21 days, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36483_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e828"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p id="Par19">Besides monitoring cell culturability and morphological changes, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> adaptation was also analyzed at the whole transcriptome level. To carry out this analysis, total RNA was isolated from the initial inoculate (control) and from <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells after their incubation in sterile seawater for 12&#x02009;h, 3, 6, 14 and 21 days. Total RNA samples were extracted from replicate cultures, i.e. they were originated from three independent cell cultures (biological replicates) grown in parallel. Electrophoretic profiles of RNA samples isolated from cells incubated for 14 and 21 days revealed that they contained a considerable fraction of degraded RNA (apparently accumulating due to cell damage beginning after prolong incubation of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells in seawater (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). RNA purified from the control (t&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) and microcosms at early time points (12&#x02009;h, 3 and 6 days) were used for RNA sequencing.</p><p id="Par20">Based on the results of RNA sequencing and their processing (see Materials and Methods), a list of the differentially expressed genes with false discovery rate less than 5% and fold change &#x0003e;2 was compiled (see Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Further bioinformatics analysis of this list made it possible to reveal six clusters of genes with similar expression profiles (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Two of them (clusters 1 and 5) were gradually upregulated during the course of the experiment and included a number of genes (see Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) primarily related to transport, virulence (clusters 1 and 5) and stress responses (cluster 5). The other four clusters (i.e. clusters 2, 3, 4 and 6) contained numerous genes controlling various cellular functions. The expression of these genes either was initially decreased and then remained low (clusters 2, 3 and 6) or was transitionally upregulated (cluster 4) at later time points. While clusters 2 and 3 were primarily represented by metabolic genes (e.g. genes controlling carboxylic acid and nucleotide metabolism, respectively), the other two (clusters 4 and 6) comprised the genes playing important roles in the processing of genetic information (namely, transcription and translation, respectively).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Gene co-expression clusters. Temporal expression patterns were obtained for the time-points corresponding to <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> incubation in seawater at 30&#x02009;<sup>o</sup>C for 12&#x02009;hours, 3 days and 6 days. Gene membership values are color-encoded with red and green shades denoting high and low membership values of genes, respectively. Scaled expression values (z-scores) are used for cluster visualization.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_36483_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e881"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Some examples of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> genes and their products highly up- or down-regulated during persistence in seawater microcosm at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Systematic name</th><th rowspan="2">Gene product (specific biological pathway)</th><th colspan="3">Log<sub>2</sub> Fold change (time after exposure to seawater)</th><th rowspan="2">Gene expression cluster</th></tr><tr><th>12&#x02009;h</th><th>3 d</th><th>6 d</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Amino acid metabolism</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS23670</td><td>Methylmalonate-semialdehyde dehydrogenase (CoA acylating)</td><td>&#x02212;2.325</td><td>&#x02212;3.377</td><td>&#x02212;2.733</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS15645</td><td>Alanine dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;2.877</td><td>&#x02212;2.910</td><td>&#x02212;3.289</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01790</td><td>Ornithine cyclodeaminase</td><td>&#x02212;2.714</td><td>&#x02212;4.302</td><td>&#x02212;3.209</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS07820</td><td>Argininosuccinate synthase</td><td>&#x02212;2.225</td><td>&#x02212;2.890</td><td>&#x02212;2.258</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS07290</td><td>Aspartate carbamoyltransferase</td><td>&#x02212;1.401</td><td>&#x02212;1.345</td><td>&#x02212;1.897</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS07295</td><td>Aspartate carbamoyltransferase regulatory subunit</td><td>&#x02212;1.251</td><td>&#x02212;1.976</td><td>&#x02212;1.289</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25000</td><td>Glutamate synthase</td><td>&#x02212;0.858</td><td>&#x02212;1.233</td><td>&#x02212;1.597</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS11745</td><td>Glutamate synthase subunit beta</td><td>&#x02212;1.595</td><td>&#x02212;2.359</td><td>&#x02212;1.828</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01370</td><td>Alkaline serine protease</td><td>&#x02212;1.378</td><td>&#x02212;3.486</td><td>&#x02212;2.372</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS14635</td><td>Serine protein kinase PrkA</td><td>&#x02212;1.385</td><td>&#x02212;1.333</td><td>&#x02212;2.215</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01665</td><td>4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase</td><td>&#x02212;2.624</td><td>&#x02212;2.794</td><td>&#x02212;3.415</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS03245</td><td>Ribonucleotide-diphosphate reductase subunit beta</td><td>&#x02212;1.553</td><td>&#x02212;2.794</td><td>&#x02212;2.503</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS14510</td><td>Uridine phosphorylase</td><td>&#x02212;1.682</td><td>&#x02212;2.946</td><td>&#x02212;3.119</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Carbon metabolism</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Citrate, glyoxylate &#x00026; 2-methylcitrate cycles</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS17025</td><td>Citrate synthase/methylcitrate synthase</td><td>&#x02212;2.020</td><td>&#x02212;1.656</td><td>&#x02212;2.315</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS06380</td><td>Aconitate hydratase B</td><td>&#x02212;1.588</td><td>&#x02212;2.634</td><td>&#x02212;2.372</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS10235</td><td>Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (ATP)</td><td>&#x02212;1.458</td><td>&#x02212;3.015</td><td>&#x02212;2.504</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Glycolysis and gluconeogenesis</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS06930</td><td>Phosphoglycerate kinase</td><td>&#x02212;1.341</td><td>&#x02212;2.545</td><td>&#x02212;2.503</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS10235</td><td>Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (ATP)</td><td>&#x02212;1.458</td><td>&#x02212;3.015</td><td>&#x02212;2.504</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS04660</td><td>Type I glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;1.325</td><td>&#x02212;2.871</td><td>&#x02212;2.660</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Lipid biogenesis</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS16785</td><td>Lipid A biosynthesis lauroyl acyltransferase</td><td>0.664</td><td>0.993</td><td>1.203</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25885</td><td>Choline dehydrogenase</td><td>1.176</td><td>1.370</td><td>0.993</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS03425</td><td>Acyl-CoA thioesterase</td><td>0.878</td><td>1.704</td><td>1.073</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS06930</td><td>Phosphoglycerate kinase</td><td>&#x02212;1.341</td><td>&#x02212;2.545</td><td>&#x02212;2.503</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS26865</td><td>Glycerophosphoryl diester phosphodiesterase</td><td>&#x02212;2.629</td><td>&#x02212;3.534</td><td>&#x02212;2.947</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS23675</td><td>Acyl-CoA dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;2.053</td><td>&#x02212;2.768</td><td>&#x02212;2.308</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS23680</td><td>Enoyl-CoA hydratase</td><td>&#x02212;2.034</td><td>&#x02212;2.947</td><td>&#x02212;2.470</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS27060</td><td>Beta-ketoacyl-ACP reductase</td><td>&#x02212;1.347</td><td>&#x02212;2.564</td><td>&#x02212;2.983</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS03900</td><td>Malonyl CoA-acyl carrier protein transacylase</td><td>&#x02212;1.815</td><td>&#x02212;2.683</td><td>&#x02212;2.368</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Acetyl-CoA-dependent metabolism</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS14965</td><td>Peptidoglycan-associated lipoprotein</td><td>&#x02212;1.663</td><td>&#x02212;2.943</td><td>&#x02212;2.801</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS04550</td><td>Bifunctional acetaldehyde-CoA/alcohol Dehydrogenase</td><td>&#x02212;1.470</td><td>&#x02212;3.161</td><td>&#x02212;2.871</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS08465</td><td>Acetyl-CoA synthetase</td><td>&#x02212;1.601</td><td>&#x02212;2.312</td><td>&#x02212;2.177</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Processing of genetic information</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS06035</td><td>Elongation factor G</td><td>&#x02212;1.316</td><td>&#x02212;2.547</td><td>&#x02212;2.559</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS12075</td><td>Energy-dependent translational throttle protein EttA</td><td>&#x02212;1.550</td><td>&#x02212;2.247</td><td>&#x02212;2.244</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS02125</td><td>Translation initiation factor IF-3</td><td>&#x02212;1.436</td><td>&#x02212;2.093</td><td>&#x02212;2.476</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Ribosome biogenesis</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS07900</td><td>30S ribosomal protein S12</td><td>&#x02212;1.454</td><td>&#x02212;2.108</td><td>&#x02212;2.716</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS10850</td><td>50S ribosomal protein L22</td><td>&#x02212;0.954</td><td>&#x02212;2.066</td><td>&#x02212;2.065</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS03245</td><td>Ribonucleotide-diphosphate reductase subunit beta</td><td>&#x02212;1.553</td><td>&#x02212;2.794</td><td>&#x02212;2.503</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Transporters and ancillary factors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Energy-dependent transport TonB-ExbB-ExbD complex</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS26550</td><td>Biopolymer transporter ExbB</td><td>1.623</td><td>2.108</td><td>1.740</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS19445</td><td>TonB-system energizer ExbB</td><td>0.201</td><td>1.186</td><td>1.025</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>ABC transporters</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS26870</td><td>ABC transporter substrate-binding protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.683</td><td>&#x02212;4.749</td><td>&#x02212;3.279</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS19380</td><td>Amino acid ABC transporter</td><td>&#x02212;1.236</td><td>&#x02212;1.698</td><td>&#x02212;1.907</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS00950</td><td>Amino acid ABC transporter substrate-binding protein</td><td>&#x02212;1.188</td><td>&#x02212;2.888</td><td>&#x02212;2.524</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01680</td><td>Peptide ABC transporter substrate-binding protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.146</td><td>&#x02212;4.524</td><td>&#x02212;3.021</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01780</td><td>Polyamine ABC transporter ATP-binding protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.676</td><td>&#x02212;3.963</td><td>&#x02212;3.018</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01795</td><td>Spermidine/putrescine ABC transporter substrate-binding protein</td><td>&#x02212;2.751</td><td>&#x02212;4.780</td><td>&#x02212;3.382</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Other transporters</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01055</td><td>EamA family transporter</td><td>0.950</td><td>1.603</td><td>1.870</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25015</td><td>Long-chain fatty acid transporter</td><td>0.640</td><td>0.909</td><td>1.212</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS21850</td><td>MFS transporter</td><td>1.249</td><td>1.445</td><td>1.537</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS17670</td><td>PTS mannitol transporter subunit IIA</td><td>1.036</td><td>1.597</td><td>1.373</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Protein turnover and folding</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Protein degradation</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01370</td><td>Alkaline serine protease</td><td>&#x02212;1.378</td><td>&#x02212;3.486</td><td>&#x02212;2.372</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS12810</td><td>Aminoacyl-histidine dipeptidase</td><td>&#x02212;1.960</td><td>&#x02212;2.991</td><td>&#x02212;2.215</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS10020</td><td>Oligopeptidase A</td><td>&#x02212;1.105</td><td>&#x02212;1.895</td><td>&#x02212;2.198</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01150</td><td>Peptidase A24</td><td>0.249</td><td>1.061</td><td>1.581</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01675</td><td>Peptidase M20</td><td>0.859</td><td>0.886</td><td>1.368</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS24140</td><td>Peptidase M50</td><td>1.118</td><td>0.888</td><td>1.354</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25255</td><td>Peptidase S8</td><td>0.698</td><td>0.813</td><td>1.005</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS18135</td><td>D-alanyl-D-alanine carboxypeptidase</td><td>&#x02212;1.318</td><td>&#x02212;2.530</td><td>&#x02212;2.336</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS01705</td><td>Xaa-Pro aminopeptidase</td><td>&#x02212;2.220</td><td>&#x02212;4.042</td><td>&#x02212;3.019</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Protein folding</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25315</td><td>Molecular chaperone</td><td>0.594</td><td>1.004</td><td>1.011</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS05430</td><td>Molecular chaperone</td><td>&#x02212;1.777</td><td>&#x02212;1.784</td><td>&#x02212;2.056</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS00890</td><td>RNA chaperone ProQ</td><td>&#x02212;1.198</td><td>&#x02212;1.487</td><td>&#x02212;2.016</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Energy production</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS03195</td><td>Cytochrome c nitrite reductase subunit NrfD</td><td>0.565</td><td>1.438</td><td>0.764</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS00765</td><td>Cytochrome-c oxidase, cbb3-type subunit III</td><td>&#x02212;1.764</td><td>&#x02212;2.531</td><td>&#x02212;2.308</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>ATP synthesis coupled proton transport</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS09605</td><td>F0F1 ATP synthase subunit delta</td><td>&#x02212;1.768</td><td>&#x02212;3.170</td><td>&#x02212;2.672</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS09595</td><td>F0F1 ATP synthase subunit gamma</td><td>&#x02212;1.825</td><td>&#x02212;3.548</td><td>&#x02212;2.778</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Fumarate reductase (complex II)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS08265</td><td>Fumarate reductase flavoprotein subunit</td><td>&#x02212;1.862</td><td>&#x02212;2.041</td><td>&#x02212;1.584</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS08280</td><td>Fumarate reductase subunit D</td><td>&#x02212;1.508</td><td>&#x02212;2.045</td><td>&#x02212;1.847</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Stress responses</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Cell envelope stress: Phage-shock-protein response</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS15985</td><td>Phage shock protein PspA</td><td>&#x02212;0.908</td><td>0.819</td><td>&#x02212;1.526</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS15995</td><td>Envelope stress response membrane protein PspC</td><td>&#x02212;1.042</td><td>&#x02212;0.263</td><td>&#x02212;1.819</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Stringent response</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS11565</td><td>Stringent starvation protein B</td><td>&#x02212;1.121</td><td>&#x02212;0.789</td><td>&#x02212;1.168</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Antioxidative defence</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS17640</td><td>Catalase</td><td>1.260</td><td>2.075</td><td>1.668</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS21845</td><td>Glutaredoxin, GrxB family</td><td>0.713</td><td>1.418</td><td>0.700</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Nitric oxide detoxification</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS24635</td><td>Nitrite reductase large subunit</td><td>1.472</td><td>1.227</td><td>1.433</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>DNA damage, repair and synthesis</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS18185</td><td>Deoxyribodipyrimidine photolyase</td><td>1.446</td><td>1.734</td><td>1.280</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS23750</td><td>DNA mismatch repair protein MutT</td><td>1.004</td><td>0,776</td><td>1.593</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Iron uptake, storage &#x00026; utilization</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS26680</td><td>Ferric reductase</td><td>0.938</td><td>1.185</td><td>1.140</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Iron uptake/transport</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS21155</td><td>Iron permease</td><td>0.959</td><td>1.295</td><td>1.249</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS23515</td><td>Iron ABC transporter</td><td>1.203</td><td>1.009</td><td>0.937</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Iron storage</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS07875</td><td>Bacterioferritin</td><td>&#x02212;2.859</td><td>&#x02212;2.868</td><td>&#x02212;3.496</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS12375</td><td>Ferredoxin, 2Fe-2S type, ISC system</td><td>&#x02212;0.365</td><td>&#x02212;0.256</td><td>&#x02212;1.152</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Iron cluster biogenesis</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS16405</td><td>Cysteine desulfurase</td><td>&#x02212;2.740</td><td>&#x02212;3.362</td><td>&#x02212;3.312</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Virulence factors involved in</bold>
<bold><italic>V. harveyi</italic></bold>
<bold>pathogenicity</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS26540</td><td>Putative heme utilization radical SAM enzyme HutW</td><td>1.028</td><td>1.301</td><td>0.458</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS20930</td><td>virK protein</td><td>0.708</td><td>1.912</td><td>1.755</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Quorum Sensing</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS06465</td><td>LuxR family transcriptional regulator</td><td>&#x02212;1.543</td><td>&#x02212;2.549</td><td>&#x02212;2.843</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS19310</td><td>Sensor histidine kinase</td><td>1.253</td><td>1.080</td><td>1.148</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25660</td><td>TonB-dependent siderophore receptor</td><td>1.338</td><td>1.520</td><td>1.380</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Chemotaxis, Motility &#x00026; Biofilm</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25425</td><td>Chemotaxis protein</td><td>0.892</td><td>1.340</td><td>1.235</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS21340</td><td>Flagellar biosynthesis protein FlhB</td><td>0.891</td><td>1.557</td><td>1.256</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25995</td><td>Pilus assembly protein CpaF</td><td>1.152</td><td>1.522</td><td>1.409</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Secretion systems</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS15160</td><td>EscJ/YscJ/HrcJ family type III secretion inner membrane ring protein (T3SS)</td><td>1.077</td><td>1.212</td><td>1.477</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS23415</td><td>Type VI secretion protein</td><td>1.769</td><td>1.838</td><td>1.741</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">
<bold>Drug efflux &#x00026; Antibiotic resistance</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS20560</td><td>Bcr/CflA family drug resistance efflux transporter</td><td>0.695</td><td>1.286</td><td>1.148</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>AL538_RS25145</td><td>Polyketide cyclase</td><td>0.622</td><td>1.104</td><td>1.046</td><td>5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par21">Ongoing GW profoundly affects the physicochemical parameters and biological variety of natural aquatic systems. The relatively low level of dissolved organic matter in marine environments was shown to constrain bacterial growth in seawater microcosms (e.g<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>.) and is believed to be one of the major factors accountable for the presence of coccoid-like bacterioplankton in marine ecosystems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. To investigate the combined impact of elevated temperatures and limitation of carbon on <italic>Vibrio</italic> species, we used <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> as a model organism and studied its persistence in seawater microcosms at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C known to be within the upper limit of sea surface temperature observed in some areas of the global oceans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">Analysis of cell morphology by fluorescence and electron microscopy revealed a discernible reduction of cell size by 3&#x02009;day after exposure to microcosm conditions. <italic>In silico</italic> processing of cell images corroborated the overall reduction of cell size until the sixth day of incubation with no significant changes afterwards (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The transition to the coccoid-like phenotype is consistent with the previously documented response of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> to carbon limitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Similar changes in morphology (i.e. size reduction and shape alterations) have been reported in old cell cultures of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>parahaemolyticus</italic> and <italic>V</italic>. <italic>angustum</italic> subjected to carbon starvation in marine mineral medium under laboratory conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. In natural aquatic systems, carbon concentration varies and brief periods of carbon abundance are normally interspersed with long periods of its scarcity. Therefore, it is quite common that free-living bacteria have reduced size in their natural habitats due to the shortage of carbon sources<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. Comparison of three independent experiments performed with the same <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> strain and under the same laboratory settings at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> and 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (present work), demonstrates that reduction of cell size and occasional acquisition of a coccoid-like phenotype occur in a wide range of temperatures (i.e. from 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C to 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C). Moreover, elevated temperature (i.e. 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) and shortage of carbon appear to limit the cell&#x02019;s capacity to cope with stress and ultimately lead to the appearance of damaged cells seen in 21-day-old populations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The appearance of damaged cells is congruent with a higher percentage of degraded RNA detected in <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells after 14 and 21 days of incubation (data not shown). Moreover, an increase in the number of damaged cells is also consistent with a 90% loss of culturability within the entire population (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) observed during the same period of time (i.e. after 14 days). Thus, in contrast to <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> persistence and preservation of culturability at 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, its exposure to limitation of carbon at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C leads to the higher vulnerability of the stressed cells to damage, which apparently causes their faster injury and potential death.</p><p id="Par23">To learn about the major adaptation mechanisms that <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> and likely other <italic>Vibrio</italic> species trigger to cope with elevated temperatures and limitation of nutrients in their natural habitats, we used RNA sequencing to obtain transcriptome profiles of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> following its incubation in seawater microcosm at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 12&#x02009;hours, 3 and 6&#x02009;days. Comparison of these transcriptome data with those obtained for the control samples (initial inoculate) revealed a large number of genes that were differentially expressed during the incubation. Time series clustering analysis of the expression data (see Experimental procedures) revealed six distinct co-expressed clusters (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), each comprising a set of genes with similar time-dependent expression profiles. The differentially expressed genes were further grouped according to their biological functions and presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>.</p><p id="Par24">The fast morphological changes and accumulation of cells with damaged membranes (see above) indicate that <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> was unable to properly control expression of genes involved in cell envelope biogenesis and associated metabolic pathways. The expression of phage shock proteins PspA, PspB and PspC (cluster 4) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), known for their role in relieving membrane stress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>, is consistent with this explanation. In contrast to the previously described gradual upregulation of these genes in <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> grown at 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, in this work, expression of these genes under limitation of carbon at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C decreases after 6 day of incubation. This indicates the failure of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> to engage the products of the phage shock operon in the adaptation process.</p><p id="Par25">Another example of &#x0201c;unexpected&#x0201d; response concerns lipid biogenesis and transport. Although the shrinkage of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cell envelope associated with the reduction of cell size is anticipated to lead to a discharge of extra lipids and other membrane components for further recycling, we surprisingly found that expression of genes controlling lipid turnover decreased. A number of genes that are involved in lipid degradation via &#x003b2;-oxidation pathway (i.e. gene encoding phosphoglycerate kinase, glycerophosphoryl diester phosphodiesterase, acyl-CoA dehydrogenase, enoyl-CoA hydratase, beta-ketoacyl-ACP reductase, malonyl CoA-acyl carrier protein transacylase) (clusters 2 and 3) were strongly downregulated. The downregulation of genes controlling &#x003b2;-oxidation pathway as well as those involved in further conversion of acetyl-CoA, the key cellular metabolite generated via &#x003b2;-oxidation pathway, by the enzymes of the glyoxylate cycle (clusters 2 and 3) was unexpected and, in fact, was opposite to their upregulation at 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C observed in our previous work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Thus, it seems likely, that, despite the considerably fast shrinkage of cell envelope and concomitant release of free lipids under carbon limiting conditions at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> fails to upregulate the key genes, the products of which are involved in lipid recycling. Nevertheless, the upregulation of some genes coding for long-chain fatty acid transporters (AL538_RS25015) could indicate that <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> might try to deal with an excess of lipids accumulated due to reduction of cell size by changing their subcellular localization or exporting them outside of cells. In addition to some anticipated problems with lipid recycling, the shrinkage of cell envelope could additionally be hindered by discoordinate expression of major enzymes (for example, murein L,D-transpeptidase (cluster 4) and D-alanyl-D-alanine carboxypeptidase (cluster 3)) involved in peptidoglycan remodeling. Besides alterations in expression of genes controlling cell envelope biogenesis, another large group of the affected genes included those related to the <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> central carbon metabolism. Analysis of their regulation revealed a fast downregulation of many genes involved in carboxylic acid metabolism (e.g. aconitate hydratase B (<italic>acnB</italic>), phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase; see Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> in Supplementary Data) as well as those controlling carbon storage such as the one encoding CsrB known for its roles in post-transcriptional control of gene expression. The downregulation of these genes is likely caused by limitation of carbon in seawater and it was observed already after 12&#x02009;hours of incubation. Moreover, the initial rate of downregulation was considerably faster in the present study (i.e. at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) than that previously observed at 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, thus pointing to the overall increase in the rate of the cellular response to carbon scarcity at elevated temperatures. In addition, we found that, while decreasing the intensity of the central carbon metabolism, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> apparently attempts to switch to utilization of alternative carbon sources by upregulating a number of genes (e.g. alpha-amylase (cluster 1) and several alpha- and beta-mannosidase genes (belonging to clusters 1 and 5) encoding various hydrolases able to convert some polysaccharides naturally present in seawater into smaller metabolizable sugars.</p><p id="Par26">An additional option to scavenge carbon sources from a carbon-limiting environments consists in secretion of proteinases able to degrade polypeptides potentially present in the environment (e.g. within the infected host cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>) into oligopeptides or amino acids for their further uptake by the starved cells. This strategy is less costly then <italic>de novo</italic> protein synthesis and is likely preferred by <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> unable to maintain the required level of amino acids during its persistence in seawater microcosm under carbon-limiting conditions. Consistent with this scenario, the key enzymes involved in amino acid biosynthesis (i.e. arginine-succinate synthase, hydroxyproline-2-epimerase or ornithine cyclodeaminase from cluster 2; carbamoyl-phosphate synthase small subunit, cluster 3; glutamate synthase, cluster 6) were downregulated. Concomitantly, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> upregulated a number of genes (cluster 1) coding for various proteinases such as the subtilisin-serine peptidase S8 and protease M20. Most members of the peptidase S8 family are secreted and they are known to be implicated in the pathogenesis along with other metalloproteases by damaging host tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. The periplasmic peptidases belonging to M20 family are carboxy-metallo-proteases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup> appear to assist the uptake of peptides by converting them into free amino acids in the periplasm. In contrast to the above examples, several protease genes were found to be downregulated. Their repression could be caused by different factors including the high cost of their operation (such as ATP-dependence of oligopeptidase A), reduced cellular needs in some specialized enzymes (e.g. proteases (HtpX and metalloprotease RseP) involved in protein quality control) or simply due to their redundancy (see Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>).</p><p id="Par27">Under carbon limitation and elevated temperature, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> also up- and downregulates a large number of transporter-encoding genes primarily found in clusters 1 and 5 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Some upregulated genes control (i) the energy-dependent transport mediated by the TonB-ExbB-ExbD complex, (ii) multidrug efflux transporters that belong to the <underline>m</underline>ultidrug <underline>a</underline>nd <underline>t</underline>oxic compound <underline>e</underline>xtrusion (MATE) family and (iii) membrane transport proteins of the <underline>m</underline>ajor <underline>f</underline>acilitator <underline>s</underline>uperfamily (MFS) that assist movement of small solutes across cell membranes. Many genes coding for ABC- and PTS-type transporters (clusters 2, 3 and 5) were downregulated, thus indicating that the transport of the corresponding molecules (certain sugars and amino acids) is likely taken over by alternative transport systems or is deactivated due to its redundancy.</p><p id="Par28">Marine bacteria in the open ocean experience limitation of iron<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, an essential metal vital for all living organisms. Consistent with the necessity to deal with low concentrations of iron in seawater microcosms, we observed that a number of genes involved in iron uptake/transport and storage were up- and downregulated, respectively. Moreover, incubation in seawater seems to activate some adaptive mechanisms aimed at protecting <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells from the possible damage potentially caused by reactive oxygen species (ROS) and/or nitric oxide (NO). Consistently, we found that <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> upregulated several stress-responsive genes (cluster 5) encoding catalase, alkyl hydroperoxide reductase subunit F, glutaredoxin as well as some nitrate reductases and cytochrome <italic>c</italic> nitrite reductase subunit NrfD able to minimize (or reduce) the damaging effects of ROS and / or NO.</p><p id="Par29">Incubation at elevated temperature also affected regulation of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> genes controlling its virulence and ancillary mechanisms (i.e. production and secretion of virulence factors, biofilm formation and motility). We found that, in addition to increased expression of lytic enzymes including various glycosidases and proteinases, <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> upregulated a number of genes encoding the Type III<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>, Type I<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>, Type IV<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> and Type VI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup> secretion systems involved in transport of virulence factors.</p><p id="Par30">Similarly, upregulation was observed for structural proteins of flagella and pilus (flagellar biosynthesis proteins FlhB and FliR from cluster 5; pilus assembly proteins CpaB, CpaF, PapD, PilN, PilZ, TadB and TadE FliR from cluster 1 and 5) as well as ancillary enzymes such as peptidase A24 (gene AL538_RS01150) required for the type IV pilus formation, secretion of toxin and enzymes, gene transfer and biofilm formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. The upregulation of the above genes can play an important role in cell motility and attachment during the initials steps of infection. Moreover, the overall increase in motility and capacity to attach to biotic surfaces could also increase <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> chances to find new sources of food (e.g. <italic>via</italic> attachment to sea shells whose components (e.g. amino polysaccharides) can further be processed by secreted hydrolyzes to yield amino sugars in carbon-limiting environments.</p><p id="Par31">Finally, we found that the gene coding for LuxR, a transcription factor mediating the quorum sensing (QS) response in a large variety of <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. was markedly downregulated, thereby suggesting that QS might not play a significant role in <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> response to elevated SST and carbon limitation. Meanwhile, many genes encoding for proteins of two-component (sensor histidine kinase/response regulator) systems (CreC, UhpB and others, cluster 1 and 5) playing essential roles in sensing environmental signals and accordingly adjusting gene expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> were upregulated. Several two-component systems previously described in vibrios and shown to be upregulated in the present study are involved in pathogenicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. Therefore, their upregulation might enhance the pathogenic potential of <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> exposed to elevated temperature and carbon limitation in seawater microcosm.</p><p id="Par32">In summary, we observed a significant size reduction and acquisition of coccoid-like morphology by <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cells in seawater microcosms during their long-term incubation under carbon limitation at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Since morphological changes, loss of culturability and cell damage are more pronounced at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C than at 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, our data suggest that shortage of carbon at elevated temperature has a negative effect on <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic>. Despite its adverse effect on <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> survival due to counter adaptive downregulation of some metabolic pathways (e.g. those controlling &#x003b2;-oxidation pathway), incubation in sea water microcosm at 30&#x02009;&#x000b0;C readily enhances expression of many known virulence factors (i.e. lytic enzymes, components of the T3SS secretion system and iron-chelating compounds; reviewed in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>) apparently accountable for the increased presence of pathogenic <italic>Vibrio</italic> species in the microbiota of marine invertebrate during the warm seasons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup> and therefore potentially important for the spread of <italic>Vibrio</italic>-associated diseases in response to GW<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. As the morphological, physiological and gene expression changes were observed in seawater microcosms, the rate and extent of <italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. responses to elevated temperature and limitation of carbon in their natural habitats are not necessarily the same and can likely be modulated by protozoan grazing, intensity of solar radiation and other environmental factors influencing the dynamics of marine ecosystems. Therefore, it is conceivable that some of the conclusions are limited by the experimental design.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec10"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_36483_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Table S1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-36483-0.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness grant CGL2015-70929-R, Ikerbasque (Basque Foundation for Science) and pre-doctoral grants PRE-2013-1-901 (I.M.) from the Basque Government and PIF15/101 (E.O.) from the University of the Basque Country. A.E.-C. is funded by ISCIII of the MINECO (Ref: PT17/0009/0019) and cofinanced by FEDER.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>I.M. and V.R.K. conceived the experiment(s), I.M., E.O., M.O. and I.A. conducted the experiment(s), I.M., E.O., A.H.P., A.E.-G. and J.G.-G. analyzed the results, I.M. and V.R.K. wrote the manuscript. I.M., I.A. and A.H.P. prepared the figures. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Visick</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio</italic> biofilms: so much the same yet so different</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2008.12.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19231189?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19231189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFelice</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienfang</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial production of tetrodotoxin in the pufferfish <italic>Arothron hispidus</italic></article-title><source>Nat Prod Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1630</fpage><lpage>1640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14786410903003780</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19851930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19851930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Owens, L., Busico-Salcedo, N. <italic>Vibrio harveyi:</italic> Pretty problems in paradise. In: Thompson, FL, Austin, B, Swings, J (eds) The Biology of Vibrios. ASM Press., Washington, D. C., 266&#x02013;280 (2006)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruwandeepika</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Presence of typical and atypical virulence genes in vibrio isolates belonging to the Harveyi clade</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>888</fpage><lpage>899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2010.04715.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20345385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20345385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Roux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The emergence of <italic>Vibri</italic>o pathogens in Europe: ecology, evolution, and pathogenesis (Paris, 11-12th March 2015)</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>830</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00830</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26322036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26322036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio vulnificus</italic>: disease and pathogenesis</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2009</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1723</fpage><lpage>1733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01046-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19255188?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19255188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JG</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Cholera and other types of vibriosis: a story of human pandemics and oysters on the half shell</article-title><source>Clinical infectious diseases: an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</source><year>2003</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/375600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12856219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker-Austin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio</italic> spp. infections</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-018-0005-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30002421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30002421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Urtaza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinanes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>DePaola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate anomalies and the increasing risk of <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> and <italic>Vibrio vulnificus</italic> illnesses</article-title><source>Food Res Int</source><year>2010</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1780</fpage><lpage>1790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2010.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMichael</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodruff</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change and human health: present and future risks</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2006</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)68079-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16530580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16530580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisharat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><collab>Climate change</collab></person-group><article-title>and the emergence of <italic>Vibrio vulnificus</italic> disease in Israel</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2006.07.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16949069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16949069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vezzulli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruzzo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ocean warming and spread of pathogenic vibrios in the aquatic environment</article-title><source>Microb Ecol</source><year>2013</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-012-0163-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23280498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23280498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The update, Global Health Workforce Statistics, World Health Organization, Geneva, (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/hrh/statistics/hwfstats/">http://www.who.int/hrh/statistics/hwfstats/</ext-link>)2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letchumanan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic>: a review on the pathogenesis, prevalence, and advance molecular identification techniques</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>705</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2014.00705</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25566219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25566219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vezzulli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate influence on <italic>Vibrio</italic> and associated human diseases during the past half-century in the coastal North Atlantic</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>E5062</fpage><lpage>5071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1609157113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27503882?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27503882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> non-O1 and non-O139 bacteremia in a non-traveler Portuguese cirrhotic patient: first case report</article-title><source>Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2013</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gastrohep.2012.09.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23164747?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23164747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Julie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ecology of pathogenic and non-pathogenic <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> on the French Atlantic coast. Effects of temperature, salinity, turbidity and chlorophyll a</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2009.02136.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20100246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20100246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker-Austin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emerging <italic>Vibrio</italic> risk at high latitudes in response to ocean warming</article-title><source>Nature Climate Change</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate1628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Urtaza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spread of Pacific Northwest <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> strain</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>369</volume><fpage>1573</fpage><lpage>1574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc1305535</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24131194?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24131194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Urtaza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Environmental determinants of the occurrence and distribution of <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> in the rias of Galicia, Spain</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01307-07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17981951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17981951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Urtaza</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological investigation of a foodborne outbreak in Spain associated with U.S. West Coast genotypes of <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic></article-title><source>Springerplus</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>87</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40064-016-1728-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26848427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26848427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harvell</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate warming and disease risks for terrestrial and marine biota</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>2158</fpage><lpage>2162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1063699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12077394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> and <italic>V</italic>. <italic>harveyi</italic> cause detachment of the epithelium from the midgut trunk of the penaeid shrimp <italic>Sicyonia ingentis</italic></article-title><source>Dis Aquat Organ</source><year>2004</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/dao060021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15352521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15352521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soto-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lizarraga-Partida</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerra-Flores</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Gill</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virulence of luminous vibrios to <italic>Artemia franciscana nauplii</italic></article-title><source>Dis Aquat Organ</source><year>2003</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/dao053231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12691194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of gastroenteritis caused by <italic>Vibrio carchariae</italic> in cultured marine fish</article-title><source>Mar Biotechnol (NY)</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10126-002-0018-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14961260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and Characterization of Pathogenic <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> (<italic>V</italic>. <italic>carchariae</italic>) From the farmed marine cobia fish <italic>Rachycentron canadum</italic> L. with Gastroenteritis Syndrome</article-title><source>World J Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:WIBI.0000040402.44340.0e</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic>: a significant pathogen of marine vertebrates and invertebrates</article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2006.01989.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16869892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16869892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Erken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Noorian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McDougald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental reservoirs and mechanisms of persistence of <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic></article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>375</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2013.00375</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24379807?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Townsley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sison-Mangus</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yildiz</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> to low-temperature shifts: CspV regulation of Type VI secretion, biofilm formation, and association with zooplankton</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>4441</fpage><lpage>4452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00807-16</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27208110?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Farmer, J. J. The Family Vibrionaceae. In: Dworkin, M., Falkow, S., Rosenberg, E., Schleifer, K.-H., Stackebrandt, E. (eds) The Prokaryotes 3rd edn. Springer Science and Business Media, New York, 495&#x02013;507 (2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaberdin</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unveiling the metabolic pathways associated with the adaptive reduction of cell size during <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> persistence in seawater microcosms</article-title><source>Microb Ecol</source><year>2015</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-015-0614-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25903990?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25903990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in the <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> cell envelope subproteome during permanence in cold seawater</article-title><source>Microb Ecol</source><year>2016</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-016-0802-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27324654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27324654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orruno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaberdin</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arana</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival strategies of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Vibrio spp</italic>.: contribution of the viable but nonculturable phenotype to their stress-resistance and persistence in adverse environments</article-title><source>World J Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2017</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>45</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-017-2218-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28161849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28161849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramaiah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Straube</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Entry of <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> and <italic>Vibrio fischeri</italic> into the viable but nonculturable state</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2002.01666.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12067379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chr&#x000f3;st, R. J. Microbial Ectoenzymes in Aquatic Environments. In: Overbeck J., Chr&#x000f3;st R. J. (eds) Aquatic Microbial Ecology. Springer, New York, N. Y (1990).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kizhakudan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlation between changes in sea surface temperature and fish catch along Tamil Nadu coast of India - an indication of impact of climate change on fisheries?</article-title><source>Indian J Fish</source><year>2014</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>115</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salas-Perez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-G&#x000e1;ndara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal and spatial fluctuations of sea surface temperature and chlorophyll a levels due to atmospheric forcing in a tropical coastal lagoon</article-title><source>Ciencias Marinas</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7773/cm.v42i1.2551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso-S&#x000e1;ez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in marine prokaryotic community induced by varying types of dissolved organic matter and subsequent grazing pressure</article-title><source>J Plankton Research</source><year>2009</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1373</fpage><lpage>1383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/plankt/fbp081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hobbie</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of nuclepore filters for counting bacteria by fluorescence microscopy</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1977</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1225</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><?supplied-pmid 327932?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">327932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measurement of bacterial size via image analysis of epifluorescence preparations: description of an inexpensive system and solutions to some of the most common problems</article-title><source>Sci Mar</source><year>1997</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>407</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title><source>BMC bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>323</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-323</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21816040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq. 2</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25516281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Futschik</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlisle</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noise-robust soft clustering of gene expression time-course data</article-title><source>J Bioinform Comput Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>965</fpage><lpage>988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S0219720005001375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16078370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falcon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using GOstats to test gene lists for GO term association</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btl567</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17098774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of nutrient deprivation on <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1983</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>930</fpage><lpage>940</lpage><?supplied-pmid 6639037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6639037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felter</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphology and round body fermation in <italic>Vibrio marinus</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1969</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><?supplied-pmid 4895849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4895849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novitsky</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological characterization of small cells resulting from nutrient starvation of a psychrophilic marine vibrio</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1976</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><?supplied-pmid 984833?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">984833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ducklow, H. W. Bacterioplankton. In: Steele, J, Thorpe, S, Turekian, K (eds) Encyclopedia of Ocean Sciences. Elsevier Ltd, Amsterdam, 269&#x02013;275 (2001).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pierrehumbert</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change and the tropical Pacific: the sleeping dragon wakes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1355</fpage><lpage>1358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.4.1355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Jane</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological changes of <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> under cold and starvation stresses</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2008.11.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19101053?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19101053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmquist</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjelleberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in viability, respiratory activity and morphology of the marine <italic>Vibrio</italic> sp. strain S14 during starvation of individual nutrients and subsequent recovery. FEMS Microbiol</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1993</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.1993.tb00034.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stretton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Danon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjelleberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in cell morphology and motility in the marine <italic>Vibrio</italic> sp. strain S14 during conditions of starvation and recovery</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1997</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1997.tb10166.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McDougald, D., Kjelleberg, S. Adaptative Responses of Vibrios. In: Thompson, FL, Austin, B, Swings, J (eds) The Biology of Vibrios. ASM Press., Washington, D. C., 133&#x02013;155 (2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joly</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Managing membrane stress: the phage shock protein (Psp) response, from molecular mechanisms to physiology</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2010.00240.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20636484?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20636484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cysteine protease is a major exotoxin of pathogenic luminous <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> in the tiger prawn, <italic>Penaeus monodon</italic></article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.1999.00555.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10389258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saulnier</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A large-scale epidemiological study to identify bacteria pathogenic to Pacific oyster <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic> and correlation between virulence and metalloprotease-like activity</article-title><source>Microb Ecol</source><year>2010</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-009-9620-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20012275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20012275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity, structures, and collagen-degrading mechanisms of bacterial collagenolytic proteases</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>6098</fpage><lpage>6107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00883-15</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26150451?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26150451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawlings</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary families of metallopeptidases</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1995</year><volume>248</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0076-6879(95)48015-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7674922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coale</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What controls dissolved iron concentrations in the world ocean?</article-title><source>Marine Chemistry</source><year>1997</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4203(97)00043-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing regulates type III secretion in <italic>Vibrio harveyi</italic> and <italic>Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>3794</fpage><lpage>3805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.12.3794-3805.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15175293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delepelaire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type I secretion in gram-negative bacteria</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2004</year><volume>1694</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2004.05.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15546664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15546664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juhas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Type IV secretion systems: tools of bacterial horizontal gene transfer and virulence</article-title><source>Cell Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2377</fpage><lpage>2386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2008.01187.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18549454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18549454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A view to a kill: the bacterial type VI secretion system</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2013.11.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24332978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24332978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LaPointe</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The type 4 prepilin peptidases comprise a novel family of aspartic acid proteases</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>1502</fpage><lpage>1510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.2.1502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10625704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bassler</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How bacteria talk to each other: regulation of gene expression by quorum sensing</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5274(99)00025-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10607620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capra</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Laub</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of two-component signal transduction systems</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-micro-092611-150039</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22746333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22746333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geszvain</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Visick</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hybrid sensor kinase RscS integrates positive and negative signals to modulate biofilm formation in <italic>Vibrio fischeri</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2008</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>4437</fpage><lpage>4446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00055-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18441062?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18441062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Wilson</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tischler</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazinski</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Camilli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> hybrid sensor kinase VieS contributes to motility and biofilm regulation by altering the cyclic diguanylate level</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2008</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>6439</fpage><lpage>6447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00541-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18676667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18676667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shikuma</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of VpsS, a hybrid sensor kinase, enhances biofilm formation in <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2009</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>5147</fpage><lpage>5158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00401-09</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19525342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19525342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruwandeepika</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis, virulence factors and virulence regulation of vibrios belonging to the Harveyi clade. Reviews in</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1753-5131.2012.01061.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>characterisation of the pacific oyster microbiome during a summer mortality event</article-title><source>Microb Ecol</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-018-1226-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30097682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30097682</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>