<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Generally it is known that cicindelids are insects with narrow or even very narrow habitat specialization (e.g., Freitag, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">1979</xref>; Ganeshaiah &amp; Belavadi, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">1986</xref>; Jaskuła, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Jaskuła &amp; Płóciennik, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Jaskuła et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Knisley &amp; Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">1984</xref>; Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">1984</xref>; Satoh &amp; Hori, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Satoh et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Schultz &amp; Hadley, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>; Zerm &amp; Adis, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). This specialization makes the group very sensitive for environmental changes especially resulting from human activity (Arndt et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Knisley, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Knisley and Hill, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>). Although as for now there is a lack of such data for Philippine arboreal tiger beetles, similar results are obtained in case of epigeic species studied in this country (Jaskuła et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">in prep.</xref>). Moreover, there are numerous published examples of negative impact of alien/invasive plant species on animal/insect diversity in areas where they were introduced (e.g., Dostál et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Harvey &amp; Fortuna, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>), even if gradually some of insect species start to use alien plants as food or habitat (e.g., Brändle et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Karolewski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Meijer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Novotny et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Taking all these facts into consideration, one can note that high abundance of endemic predatory tiger beetles (Cabras et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) occurring not only on native but also on invasive/alien tree species in Lanao del Sur is unusual and surprising, until we will pay attention on biology and ecology of both arboreal Cicindelidae and tree species on which these beetles were recorded in current study. Both 
 <italic>Tricondyla</italic> and 
 <italic>Neocollyris</italic> tiger beetles are known as day active predators hunting on trees and bushes on different small insects, with preference of ants (Clausen, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">1940</xref>; Naviaux, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Trautner &amp; Schawaller, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>; R. Jaskuła—personal observation). On the other hand, most (all?) tree species which were recorded by us as attractive for arboreal tiger beetles can be characterized by presence of extrafloral nectaries on different parts of the plants (Weber et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). For example, 
 <italic>Spathodea campanulata</italic> has nectaries on fruits, sides of midrib, surface of the leaves, flower pedicels, and external surface of the petals (Elias &amp; Prance, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">1978</xref>; Seibert, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">1948</xref>; Zimmermann, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">1932</xref>), and in 
 <italic>Hibiscus tiliaceus</italic>, they are present on leaf base, main nerve, and sepals (Savage et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Sugiura et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Zimmermann, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">1932</xref>), while 
 <italic>Acacia mangium</italic> has them on basal parts of leaf stalks (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). In 
 <italic>Erythrina fusca</italic>, their presence was unspecified (Feinsinger &amp; Swarm, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">1978</xref>; Savage et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>) but other species classified in this genus have external nectaries on stipules and on the sepals (Zimmermann, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">1932</xref>). In case of 
 <italic>Mangifera indica</italic>, some sources state that nectaries are present on young leaves, petioles, and developing fruits (Peng, 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) while other suggest that they are absent in the species (Weber et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37149-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
</p>
