<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">The major constituent of 
 <italic>C. citrates</italic> is citral which is alone or in combination with other componentshas been used as antimicrobial, antioxidant, chemo-protective and antispasmodic properties.Chitra Devi et al
 <italic>.</italic> reported that methanolic extracts of aerial parts (stems &amp; leaves) and roots 
 <italic>C. citrates</italic> (having citral as the main active constituent) displayed vasorelaxation on the phenylephrine-stimulated contractions in a dose-dependent manner. Citral effects synthesis and release of NO to produce vasorelaxantion by inhibiting the attenuation caused by L-NAME. Moreover, leaves extract may affectsthe synthesis of prostacyclin to induce relaxation. Furthermore, the relaxant effect of the combination of the extract of root, stems and leaves may be due to the blockage of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> ion channels (endothelium-independent) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR188">188</xref>]. Fresh leaf extract of Cymbopogon citrates in combination with other herbal medicines like fruits’extract of Citrus medica and fresh leaf extract of Persea americanacan reduce hypertension in rats induced by sucrose and ethanol. This mixture can be used to protect kidney, liver and vascular endothelium damaged by chronic utilization of sucroseand ethanol [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]. Ray reported that decoction of lemongrass has been produced a major effect on mean arterial pressure on the administration of twice-a-day [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR189">189</xref>]. From the dairy of Bastos et al. an intravenous bolus inoculation of citronellol (acyclic monoterpenoid) formed an antihypertensive effect in Wistar rats by blocking calcium channels as well asmodifying caffeine-gated and IP
 <sub>3</sub> dependent intracellular stores of Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>. Lemongrass oil can capability to suppress the activity of ROS. Interestingly, citral reduces iNOS and NF-kB activity and produce anti-inflammatory actions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>].
 <graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="13659_2020_281_Figo_HTML" id="MO21" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</p>
