<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fv/Fm is one of the most important parameters of chlorophyll fluorescence in plant leaves, and its value will not change significantly under natural conditions. However, it will decrease under stress (high temperature, low temperature, drought, etc.) [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01227" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01227" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The results of this study showed that the Fv/Fm of leaves decreased significantly, indicating that the detached leaves were damaged. Among them, 
 <italic>W. chinensis</italic> leaves exhibited the lowest values, while those of 
 <italic>W. trilobata</italic> were the highest. It was suggested that the leaves of 
 <italic>W. trilobata</italic> were the least damaged, while the leaves of 
 <italic>W. chinensis</italic> were the most seriously damaged. Drought stress is often accompanied by oxidative stress, and the accumulation of ROS in plants increases significantly. It was found that drought could increase the accumulation of ROS in rice leaves [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01227" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The results demonstrated that the accumulation of ROS in detached leaves increased. A large amount of ROS can cause toxicity to plant cells, which can destroy biological macromolecules, attack cell membranes, and accelerate leaf damage [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01227" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In this experiment, the accumulation of ROS in the leaves of 
 <italic>W. chinensis</italic> was the highest, and that in the leaves of 
 <italic>W. trilobata</italic> was the lowest, indicating that the leaves of 
 <italic>W. chinensis</italic> were under the most serious oxidative stress. MDA is a product of membrane lipid peroxidation and can indicate the damage of stress to plants. The content of MDA and the change of plasma membrane permeability are important indicators reflecting the degree of membrane lipid peroxidation and plasma membrane damage. In the study of 
 <italic>Zoysia japonica</italic>, it was found that with the extension of the drought time, the content of MDA in leaves increased gradually [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01227" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The results revealed that the content of MDA in detached leaves increased significantly, indicating that the detached leaves were damaged. Among them, the content of MDA in leaves of 
 <italic>W. chinensis</italic> was the highest, and that of 
 <italic>W. trilobata</italic> was the lowest, indicating that the leaves of 
 <italic>W. chinensis</italic> were the most seriously damaged.
</p>
