<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Plastidic markers are generally thought to be inherited exclusively through the maternal germ line, based on different mechanisms such as mitotic exclusion of plastids or plastid degeneration in the sperm cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0207763.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. However, around 20% of tested Angiosperms show biparental inheritance of plastids based on different mechanisms [
 <xref rid="pone.0207763.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Whether biparental inheritance is active in 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum</italic> is not known. It cannot be excluded, since one of the showcases where plastidic biparental inheritance has been demonstrated is a different member of the Lamiaceae, 
 <italic class="italic">Nepeta cataria</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0207763.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. However, without further evidence, the claim to demonstrate the hybrid nature of 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">citriodorum</italic> (a synonym for 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">x africanum</italic>) using plastidic markers [
 <xref rid="pone.0207763.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] seems inappropriate. Thus, the tight separation of the 
 <italic class="italic">tenuiflorum</italic> haplotype from the other 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum</italic> species 
 <italic class="italic">per se</italic> cannot rule out that pollen from 
 <italic class="italic">tenuiflorum</italic> can fertilise flowers from haplotype I, nor that haplotype I pollen can fertilise a 
 <italic class="italic">tenuiflorum</italic> flower. (These events would not leave any trace in the plastidic genome in case of maternal plastid inheritance). However, we can state that the distinct/discrete haplotype differences are found in all four tested loci of the chloroplast genome, indicative of a relatively long history of divergence, while the divergence of the different “species” within haplotype I seems to be much shorter (or not even at a stage, where it has become irreversible).
</p>
