<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Glucose is the main energy source in the human body, being obtained generally by degrading more complex molecules like starch, sucrose, or lactose. After the initial action of salivary and pancreatic α-amylase, the digestion is continued in the small intestine epithelium by α-glucosidase (along with maltase and lactase) with the release of absorbable glucose, fructose, or galactose. Therefore, inhibition of α-glucosidase and α-amylase can reduce the amount of absorbable glucydic fractions from the digestive tract, being capable of preventing postprandial hyperglycemic peaks. The mechanism is clinically validated for acarbose and miglitol, two α-glucosidase inhibitors which are used in the treatment of type 2 diabetic patients. A significant inhibitory effect on α-glucosidase was demonstrated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> for cuminaldehyde a main component in cumin essential oil. Cuminaldehide showed an IC50 value of 0.5 µg/ml, being only slightly inferior to acarbose, proving also a strong inhibitory effect on aldose reductase (IC50 of 0.085 µg/ml) which may suggest additional protective effects against toxic actions of sorbitol in diabetic neuropathy (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Lee, 2005</xref>). Also, the inhibition of α-glucosidase was demonstrated by another 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study investigating the essential oil from 
 <italic>Laurus nobilis</italic> L., which showed a 90% inhibition of the enzyme (IC50 of 1.748 µg/ml), the main chemical constituent responsible for the effect being 1,8-cineole (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Sahin Basak and Candan, 2013</xref>). The research of 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Özek (2018)</xref> identified a significant inhibition of α-amylase for the essential oil from 
 <italic>Tanacetum praeteritum</italic> subsp
 <italic>. praeteritum</italic> (Horw.) Heywood, in the I
 <sub>2</sub>/KI method with IC50 of 1.02 µg/ml, suggesting that 
 <bold>thujone</bold> is the main component responsible for the effect.
</p>
