<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot5-medicines-04-00070" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Antifungal Screening</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The broth microdilution method was performed to determine antifungal activity as previously reported [
  <a rid="B31-medicines-04-00070" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-medicines-04-00070">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-medicines-04-00070" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-medicines-04-00070">32</a>]. Briefly, cultures of 
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> (ATCC 18804) and 
  <span class="italic">Cryptococcus neoformans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">neoformans</span> (ATCC 24067) were initially grown on potato dextrose agar (PDA) plates for 72 h at 37 °C. A single colony was used to inoculate approximately 5 mL of potato dextrose broth (PDB) which was subsequently grown for an additional 24 h at 37 °C. 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus niger</span> (ATCC 16888) cultures were grown on PDA plates for 5 days at room temperature (RT, 22 °C). 
  <span class="italic">A. niger</span> conidia were collected, placed in PDB, and filtered through sterile cheesecloth into fresh PDB. The absorbance of the fresh solution was read at 625 nm and adjusted accordingly with PDB to an absorbance of 0.15. Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) were determined in triplicate using 96-well plates. 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. neoformans</span> were diluted in 3-(
  <span class="italic">N</span>-morpholino)propanesulfonic acid (MOPS) buffered Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI) medium to 2000 cells/mL whereas 
  <span class="italic">A. niger</span> was diluted with PDB to an OD
  <sub>625</sub> of 0.15. Initially, 50 μL of MOPS buffered RPMI was added to each well of the plate. In the first row, 50 μL of essential oil was added and mixed well, then 50 μL of this mixture was removed and then added to the medium in the next row. This serial dilution process was repeated for each row of the plate, with the removed volume from the last row being discarded. To each well was added 50 μL of cells to achieve a final volume of 100 μL. 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. neoformans</span> were incubated at 37 °C for 48 h. The 
  <span class="italic">A. niger</span> plates were incubated at RT for 6 days. The MIC was determined from turbidity or growth on the plates in comparison to positive and negative controls. In order to verify the results, MIC determinations were carried out in nine replicates. A combination of Cyprodinil and Fludioxonil served as the positive control with MOPS buffered RPMI serving as the negative control.
 </p>
</sec>
