<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In two studies, Tualang honey was compared with hydrofibre, hydrofibre silver or chitosan gel on full-thickness burn wounds in rats inoculated with 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> or 
 <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>. The first study by Khoo et al. (2010) found that the Tualang honey-treated group had more improved wound contraction and control over 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> growth than the hydrofibre- and hydrofibre silver-treated groups [
 <xref rid="B123-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. A study by Sukur et al. (2011) showed that topical application of Tualang honey on burn wounds contaminated with 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>A. baumannii</italic> provided a faster healing rate than chitosan gel or hydrofibre silver treatment [
 <xref rid="B124-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Meanwhile, another study showed that the oral treatment of Tualang honey enhanced anastomotic wound healing in large bowel anastomosis in rats by increasing the number of fibroblasts and decreasing inflammatory cells, leading to increased wound strength [
 <xref rid="B125-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. A clinical trial looking into Tualang honey’s effect on promoting the post-tonsillectomy healing process has been conducted by comparing sultamicillin-treated group and sultamicillin + Tualang honey-treated group. Tualang honey was topically administered intraoperatively and 4 ml orally three times daily for 7 days after surgery. The results obtained showed that the healing process was much faster in the Tualang honey + sultamicillin-treated group [
 <xref rid="B126-nutrients-13-00197" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. The multiple studies discussed above found Tualang honey to yield better wound-healing improvement than the current antibiotic or topical treatment, which could suggest the use of Tualang honey as a wound dressing.
</p>
