<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cyanidin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, or kuromanin is a flavonoid, a subgroup of anthocyanins that is found in a variety of vegetables and fruits. The ROS are involved in DNA damage, lipid peroxidation, protein and nucleic acid, which resulted into different diseases including Alzheimer’s disease (AD). This can be controlled using natural products, which may slow down its progression by acting as cholinesterase inhibitor, reducing oxidative stress, and preventing neuron damage. This neurodegenerative disorder is identified by excess of amyloid beta (Aβ) fibrils, which accumulates, in the extracellular spaces of brain and tau protein [
 <xref rid="B169-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. The neuro decline is thought to be associated with these two proteins. Anthocyanins contain a pseudo aromatic ring C that increases their structural planarity and promotes amyloid fibril disruption due to effective incorporation of anthocyanins inside the amyloid beta fibril groove. They can also cross the membrane separating the blood from the cerebrospinal fluid and prevent neuron degeneration. The compounds of anthocyanin subcategory can therefore be potentially employed as a therapeutic agent in those diseases that are mediated by oxidative stress. Cyanidin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, an anthocyanin, can therefore act as neuroprotective agent [
 <xref rid="B170-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. Similarly, another flavonoid rich plant named gangobilobia may be used in the treatment of age-related dementia and Alzheimer’s disease. Butyrylcholinesterase is an enzyme, found in the blood plasma of humans. Two types of neurotoxic inhibitors of cholinesterase are usually used for AD that are active against acetylcholinesterase (AChE) and butyrylcholinesterase (BChE). Increasing acetylcholine results in better neuron transport and in turn, better cognitive function [
 <xref rid="B171-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>]. Flavonoids have been extensively used as BChE inhibitors (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-05243-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The 
 <italic>Hypericum lydium</italic> plant show AChE and BChE inhibition with total FC varying from 4.97 ± 4.56 to 156.44 ± 5.51 mg [
 <xref rid="B172-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. The cholinesterase inhibition potential could be linked with a higher number of polyphenolics and flavonoids. Procyanidins, a class of flavonoids, improve cognitive function by means of CREB-SIRT1 [
 <xref rid="B173-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Stachys cretica</italic> extracts showed relief of oxidative stress, decrease in Alzheimer’s disease, hyperglycemia, and melisma. A number of phenolic compounds have been identified in the extract of 
 <italic>Stachys cretica</italic> (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-05243-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05243-f008">Figure 8</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B174-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Actinidia arguta</italic> fruits have six flavonols, seven flavanols, seven phenolic acids, and one anthocyanin with the ability to inhibit AChE and BChE [
 <xref rid="B175-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>]. Most of these extracts and purified flavonoids are active against AD in preclinical studies in murine models that provided very favorable results. It is therefore important to explore these flavonoids in clinical trials so that their usefulness can be shared with the AD patients.
</p>
