<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0125" class="p">To date, the natural occurrence of bacteriophages and their interactions with bacteria in natural oil reservoirs has not been studied in much detail. As far as we are aware, no viruses have been directly isolated from an oil reservoir. Only studies at a genomic level have revealed hints of the presence of viruses. Oil-water mixture samples from a production well of the water-flooded Chinese Qinghai oilfield were compared in taxonomic and functional compositions of the microbial communities in the oil and water phases by pyrosequencing and application of a GeoChip4.0 [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. In that study, 38 of 40 detectable virus genes were found. Three of the detected genes showed significant differences in abundance between crude oil and water phase. Holin type 3 for bacterial lysis was more abundant in the oil phase, while the host recognition T2 type and the sliding clamp T4 for replication were both greater in the water phase. Because of the higher abundance of phage genes in the water phase, it was hypothesized that microbes are protected from phages by the oil phase [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Yet, holin type 3 abundance was higher in oil than in water phase, indicating phage-interactions and bacterial lysis directly within the oil phase [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. As a paradigm of life, microorganisms can only live in a water phase. Thus, microbes in the oil phase are either physically partitioned into the oil during the production process, where they cannot live, or they are present in microdroplets of water dispersed in the oil. In the latter case, they would again be subject to viruses if these are present in the droplet. Another genomic study on 
 <italic class="italic">Thermococcus sibiricus</italic> isolated from oil concluded that the oil environment is poorly invaded by bacteriophages because they only found a single CRISPR containing 24 repeat spacer units. However, it is known that other species of the order 
 <italic class="italic">Thermococcales</italic> harbor multiple CRISPR loci carrying more repeat spacer units [
 <xref rid="bib0575" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>].
</p>
