<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As presented in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-pharmaceuticals-13-00479">Table S1</xref>, in addition to 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil, in some cases after hydrodistillation, the decoction water (the remaining hydrodistillation aqueous phase) was also collected [
 <xref rid="B12-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Conversely, in some studies, extraction from the aerial parts of the plant was performed using different solvents (hexane, dichloromethane, ethanol, diethyl ether, ethyl acetate, 
 <italic>n</italic>-butanol, and water) [
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Furthermore, in some cases, the extracts were obtained by ultrasound [
 <xref rid="B9-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The extracts obtained from the aerial parts of the plant were characterized by the presence of different polyphenol classes, in particular, flavonoids (apigenin, kaempferol, luteolin, naringenin, quercetin, sakuranetin, sterubin), phenolic acids (caffeic acid, chlorogenic acid, 2-methoxysalicylic acid, 3-methoxysalicylic acid, rosmarinic acid, salvianolic acids I and K and derivatives), phenolic terpene (carnosol) and hexoside and glycoside derivatives; other compounds identified were steroid (β-sitosterol), triterpenoids (oleanolic acid, ursolic acid), and xanthophyll lutein [
 <xref rid="B9-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-pharmaceuticals-13-00479">Figure S1</xref> the chemical structures of several compounds present in the extract are presented. In opposition to 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil, in which the composition is extensively characterized, the extract phenolic profile has been less investigated and diverse chromatographic peaks detected during the phytochemical characterization remain unidentified. 
</p>
