<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The pomegranate fruit is a fleshy berry with a nearly round shape, crowned by a prominent calyx. Its relatively thick peel has an outer colored skin and the fruit's inner structure contains multi-arils chambers separated by membranous walls (Holland et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). The edible part of the pomegranate fruit, the arils, contains seeds and a special layer of cells (juice cells) that are of epidermal origin and protrude from the outer epidermal cells of the seed (Fahan, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1976</xref>; Holland et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). The external fruit color ranges from yellow, green or pink overlaid with pink to deep red or deep purple. The color of the juicy layer can vary from white to deep red (Holland et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Various parts of the pomegranate fruit were traditionally used as treatments against various ailments including stomachaches and bacterial infections (Holland and Bar-Ya'akov, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). The traditional usages were strengthened by modern scientific studies focused on health beneficial metabolites and their therapeutic effects and mechanisms of action on human and animal health. These studies were thoroughly reviewed in recent years. Most of the therapeutic effects of the pomegranate fruit were attributed to its secondary and primary metabolites, such as polyphenols, including flavonoids, anthocynains and hydrolizable tannins, fatty acids, and lipids (Seeram et al., 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006a</xref>; Lansky and Newman, 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Jurenka, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Viuda-Martos et al., 
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Teixeira da Silva et al., 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Holland and Bar-Ya'akov, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Wu and Tian, 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). These metabolites were found in all fruit parts, including the fruit peel (ellagitannis, flavonoids, anthocyanins), arils (ellagitannis, flavonoids, anthocyanins), seeds (fatty acids, lipids), and membranous walls (mostly ellagitannins). Anthocyanin biosynthesis occurs in parallel in the arils and in the fruit peel. These two tissues are not necessarily correlated in their activity with respect to color production, and often, the two tissues display different colors (Holland et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Dafny-Yalin et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). The same situation could appear in other biochemical pathways responsible for other important metabolites.
</p>
