<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0205">Cytokines are soluble protein mediators important for the orchestration of inflammatory responses of the human body [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. However, excessive production of these mediators may significantly contribute to shock, multiple organ failure, and death [
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>]. Studies have shown snake venom components can produce large quantities of pro-inflammatory cytokines and mediate tissue damage because of their synergetic and important actions in initiating and promoting inflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Inflammatory cytokines are also implicated in the development of hepatic necrosis and activation of Kupffer cells leading to increased vascular permeability and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. We observed in this study that 
 <italic>N. haje</italic> display a significant ability to up-regulate TNF-α and IL-1β levels in serum and brain tissue of untreated rats confirming the venom activating specific immune responses most especially pro-inflammatory cytokines [
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> This is consistent with previous studies using 
 <italic>Viper russelli</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], 
 <italic>Montiviper abornmuelleri</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], 
 <italic>Bothrops asper,</italic> and 
 <italic>Bothrops jararaca</italic> venoms [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The hydrolytic action of phospholipase A2 (PLA2) present in the venom on the polyunsaturated fatty acid of the cell membranes produces arachidonic acid (a precursor to inflammatory mediators) resulting in the exacerbation of the inflammatory cascades [
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> However, antivenom and partitions of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> significantly reduced the pro-inflammatory cytokines levels. The anti-inflammatory effect of extract partitions of 
 <italic>M. oleifera</italic> was more evident in groups treated with low dose (300 mg/kg) of the extract partition with 
 <italic>n</italic>-hexane showing the least values and this may suggest that the partitions are most effective at low concentration against pro-inflammatory cytokine production.
</p>
