<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although some Brazilian propolis essential oils, mainly those derived from green propolis, have been characterized previously [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref036">36</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref049">49</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref050">50</a>], this is the first study to undertake the characterization of BRP essential oil. Only the ethanolic and methanolic extracts of BRP have been tested being isoflavones the main isolated compounds [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref051">51</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref052">52</a>]. Thus, we hypothesized that the essential oil (EO) of BRP could provide some volatile compounds with important biological properties, which are probably lost or eliminated in the other extraction methods. In fact, methyl eugenol, a phenylpropene, was the major volatile component isolated from EOP and most of the other isolates were classified as sesquiterpenes. Along similar lines, it is known that the Brazilian green propolis also has a predominance of sesquiterpenes. Nerolidol, β-caryophyllene, spathulenol, and δ-cadinene have been identified as other major volatile components of green propolis [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref029">29</a>]. Studies have revealed that EO constituents make up a diverse family of low-molecular-weight organic compounds with extreme variations in biological activity. Based on their chemical structure, the active compounds of EOs can be divided into four major groups: terpenes, terpenoids, phenylpropenes, and “others” [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref053">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of the volatile compounds present in EOP have already been credited with having antiparasitic activity. These chemical entities include β-caryophyllene, α-pinene, α-bergamotene, and (E)-β-farnesene [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref054">54</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref055">55</a>]. Additionally, methyl eugenol isolated from the essential oil extracted from the plant 
  <span class="italic">Agastache rugosa</span> showed significant nematicidal activity against 
  <span class="italic">Meloidogyne incognita</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref056">56</a>]. Methyl eugenol is a specific constituent of Brazilian red propolis, among another types of propolis, which was revealed for the first time in 2008 [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref057">57</a>]. Therefore, in this work, we hypothesized that methyl eugenol, a phenylpropene with the major concentration in EOP and the sesquiterpenes may be responsible for the antiparasitic activity against 
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">vaginalis</span> exhibited here. However, further studies should be performed with the isolated constituents of EOP to identify the specific antiparasitic agents.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In spite of the anti-
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">vaginalis</span> activity, a higher cytotoxicity level was observed at the EOP concentration that presented 0% viability of trophozoites after 24 h of exposure (500 μg/mL) compared to a lower concentration (200 μg/mL), which was not toxic for CHO-K1 cells but reduced parasite proliferation by 70%. Therefore, it is hypothesized that cytotoxicity could be a limiting factor for the parenteral use of EOP, but its use in topical forms for the treatment of trichomoniasis, through topical vaginal application, appears to be an interesting alternative. It is well known that topical application allows for the delivery of higher drug concentrations to the vaginal epithelium at lower treatment doses [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref058">58</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A previous study has evaluated the effects of compounds with guaiacyl and syringyl structures (as degradation products of lignin) and natural aromatic acids and their aldehydes on 
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">vaginalis</span> and found that the tested compounds exhibited antiparasitic activity with MIC values ranging from 10 to 200 μg/mL. Isoeugenol, a phenylpropene generated by a propenyl-substituted guaiacol, was the most potent effector against 
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">vaginalis</span> with a MIC value of 10 μg/mL [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref059">59</a>], which is much lower than MIC found here for EOP. Since EOP is a complex mixture containing mainly methyl eugenol, a phenylpropene with similarities with isoeugenol in chemical structure, and sesquiterpenes in low concentrations, it is expected a different biological result in comparison to the use of each isolated compound.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, some studies have revealed that red propolis extracts from different geographical regions have significant potential as antiparasitic agents. The ethanolic extract of red propolis obtained from Nigeria, when tested against 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma brucei</span>, demonstrated potent antiparasitic activity in both sensitive and resistant strains [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref060">60</a>]. In another study, four samples of ethanolic extracts of Brazilian propolis were tested against 
  <span class="italic">Leishmania amazonensis</span>. Three extracts of green propolis and one of red propolis were tested, and all of them were capable of reducing parasite loads in infected macrophages. Nevertheless, the extract obtained from BRP showed maximal activity against 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">amazonensis</span> while being non-toxic to the macrophage cultures [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref061">61</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently, the antiparasitic activity of BRP has attracted the attention of researchers. Polymeric nanoparticles of the BRP extract and the ethanolic extract of BRP have demonstrated anti-leishmanial activity against 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">(V</span>.
  <span class="italic">) braziliensis</span>, with IC
  <sub>50</sub> values of 31.3 μg/mL and 38.0 μg/mL, respectively, demonstrating the potential of BRP in the composition of pharmaceuticals for leishmaniasis therapy [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref012">12</a>]. Additionally, when ethanolic extracts from various types of green, brown and red propolis from different regions of Brazil were tested against 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma cruzi</span> Y-strain epimastigotes, an inhibitory effect on parasite growth was observed in the first 24 h for all the types of propolis. However, only the ethanolic extracts of BRP presented a persistent 
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">cruzi</span>-inhibitory effect after 96 h, suggesting red propolis as a potential alternative for the therapeutic treatment of Chagas disease [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref010">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we also confirmed that EOP has the potential to be used as an adjuvant in a veterinary vaccine formulation. In our study, a recombinant endoglycosidase CP40 (rCP40), encoded by the 
  <span class="italic">cp40</span> gene of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pseudotuberculosis</span>, was used as the antigen as its antigenic properties have been previously confirmed [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref034">34</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref062">62</a>]. Our results confirmed that association of the rCP40 protein with EOP improves the immune response to this target compared to the administration of either of these components alone. We observed that the combination of the rCP40 with EOP led to IgG absorbances higher than those found by other researchers using traditional adjuvants such as saponin or Freund’s complete adjuvant [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref034">34</a>]. Herein, we used for the first time EOP as an adjuvant. In fact, this is the first study to evaluate the effect of BRP as a vaccinal adjuvant.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared to the administration of rCP40 alone, a combination of the recombinant protein with EOP was able to induce increases of 7.4-, 4.4- and 10.8-fold higher levels of total IgG, IgG1, and IgG2a, respectively. One of the most important challenges currently facing adjuvant research is the search for the ‘perfect mix’: an optimal, safe formulation whose different components are not only additive but also synergistic in nature, and whose administration gives rise to the desired robust immune response [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref063">63</a>]. In this study, we observed a synergistic effect when EOP was associated with rCP40. Along similar lines, another recent study has reported that the use of 3% palm oil with a bacterin of recombinant 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">coli</span> carrying the Omp40 protein resulted in an enhancement of IgG levels and of CD4
  <span class="sup">+</span> and CD8
  <span class="sup">+</span> T-cell responses, while administration of the bacterin without adjuvant failed to stimulate the humoral and cell-mediated immunities [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref064">64</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Until 42 days after immunization, the IgG2a production levels were higher than those observed for IgG1, which is indicative of a T-helper 1 cell (Th1) response. In mice, Th1 cells aid in the activation of macrophages and cytotoxic T-cells and in the production of opsonizing and complement-activator immunoglobulin isotypes, such as IgG2a. Hence, it is widely believed that the primary function of Th1 cells is the generation of immunity against intracellular pathogens [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref034">34</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref065">65</a>]. Vaccine formulations that enhance Th1 levels and CD8
  <span class="sup">+</span> T-cell responses are highly sought after as they are effective for immunization against pathogens for which there are no currently licensed vaccines (examples: HIV-AIDS, malaria, and tuberculosis) [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref066">66</a>]. EOP has the potential to serve as an excellent adjuvant for immunization purposes. Once propolis is considered both safe and non-toxic when administered to animals or humans [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref026">26</a>], EOP could be a good adjuvant to be used in important vaccines, and further investigations using this substance should be conducted.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The immunostimulatory effect of EOP may be attributed to the high levels of methyl eugenol (13.1%). Eugenol is a phenylpropene that is commonly found in essential oils; previous studies have established that eugenol stimulates the immune response in mice by promoting the T-cell response and natural killer activity [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref067">67</a>]. It is also possible that sesquiterpenes could be involved in the adjuvant effect of BRP essential oil as it is known that they also activate the immune system by influencing local inflammation and promoting phagocytosis [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref068">68</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the studies involving the effect of BRP on the immune system are recent and have extensively investigated the in vivo and in vitro effects of hydroalcoholic extracts of BRP on the inflammation process [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref016">16</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref019">19</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref069">69</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref070">70</a>]. BRP reduces nitric oxide levels and diminishes the levels of some pro-inflammatory cytokines, chemokines and genes associated with inflammatory signaling in macrophages [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref017">17</a>]. Additionally, BRP modulates neutrophil migration by interfering in rolling and adhesion processes through reduction of the levels of TNF-α, IL-1β, CXCL1/KC and CXCL-2/MIP-2 and reduction of calcium influx [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref070">70</a>]. In vivo, BRP has been seen to promote protective effects against ulcerative colitis in a rat model, reducing gross and histological inflammatory lesions and decreasing the levels of myeloperoxidase and iNOS in colon tissue [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref069">69</a>]. Moreover, mice treated orally with BRP showed improved cutaneous wound healing through faster wound closure, reduction of inflammatory infiltrate, and downregulation of the transcription factor pNF-κB and the inflammatory cytokines TGF-β, TNF-α and IL-6 [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref019">19</a>]. Antinociceptive activity of BRP towards neurogenic and inflammatory pain in mice was also observed without emotional and motor side effects [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref018">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The immunomodulatory properties of propolis seem to be contradictory since propolis sometimes acts in the inhibition, as in the anti-inflammatory properties, and other times in the stimulation of the immune system, as in the adjuvant properties. This phenomenon is probably caused by the chemical complexity of propolis as a result of the synergism among the components, which can be varied according to the methods of extraction of the bioactive compounds [
  <a rid="pone.0191797.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191797.ref071">71</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
