<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, we have tested whether the application of cell wall-degrading enzymes prior to hydrodistillation has a positive effect on the extraction efficiency. We have followed previously described protocols [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and applied separate and combined pretreatments with cellulase, pectinase, and xylanase to plant material. Prior to the extractions, we used a small-scale enzyme assay and confirmed the activity of all enzymes under the reaction conditions. However, the application of enzymes did not result in a significant increase in the yield of the essential oil above the reflux extraction pretreatments, suggesting that, in our case, the enzymatic activity had only a minor effect on the yield. On the contrary, the positive impact of enzyme application on the yield of essential oils was reported in multiple recent studies [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. For instance, enzyme-assisted extraction pretreatment was used prior to hydrodistillation of bay laurel [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], rosemary, and thyme leaves [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and reportedly resulted in an increase in essential oil yield (up to 109% for thyme leaves). However, these studies were lacking a no-enzyme control, and the observed yield increase was calculated by comparison with no-pretreatment control. In our case, the extraction results were compared to no-pretreatment control (HD) as well as to reflux extraction pretreatment (HD-RE), that served as a no-enzyme control since it was performed in the same conditions as the enzyme-assisted extraction pretreatments (MiliQ water at 40 °C for 1 h), only without addition of enzyme(s). In comparison to no-pretreatment control, an increase in essential oil yield was significant for all enzyme pretreatments individually, as well as for their combination, and there were no significant differences between each individual pretreatment. Unexpectedly, reflux extraction resulted in approximately the same essential oil increase as the enzyme-assisted pretreatments, leading to the conclusion that essential oil yield increase can be more attributed to reflux extraction pretreatment 
 <italic>per se</italic> (i.e., soaking of macerated plant material in warm water) than to enzymatic degradation of the cell wall. The positive effect of the soaking of plant material alone, as observed here, could not be properly assessed and compared with the effect of enzymes in the previous studies that were lacking no-enzyme controls [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Our results are congruent with the results of Dimaki and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] who analyzed the effect of enzyme pretreatments on hydrodistillation and ultrasound-assisted extraction of 
 <italic>Sideritis</italic> sp. essential oil. They have used both no-pretreatment and no-enzyme control (i.e., preincubation in acidic medium) and also found that enzymatic pretreatment was not superior to the mere soaking of plant material in an acidic buffer. Also, acidic and enzymatic pretreatments prior to the ultrasound-assisted extraction resulted in a similar increase in extraction yield in comparison to no-pretreatment control. In conclusion, our results and results of Dimaki et al. [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-04818" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] point out that the application of enzymatic pretreatments with the aim to increase the yield of essential oils, although often reported, should be carefully re-evaluated.
</p>
