<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All EO treatments applied to the SBM substrate decreased the population of 
 <italic>F. succinogens</italic> but increased those of 
 <italic>R. albus</italic>, 
 <italic>S. bovis</italic>, and 
 <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic>. All EO treatments applied to BGH decreased the 
 <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> population. According to Lin et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-08-01605" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], the populations of 
 <italic>F. succinogenes</italic> and 
 <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> decreased with the application of a combination of different EO (thyme oil, oregano oil, cinnamon oil, and lemon oil) to a mixed substrate containing ground maize and 
 <italic>Leymus chinensis</italic> hay (1:1 ratio). Unfortunately, specific contributions of each EO type were not documented. In another study, the application of single EO, such as clove oil, eucalyptus oil, garlic oil, origanum oil, and peppermint oil, to a mixed substrate containing alfalfa and concentrate (1:1 ratio) has also decreased the populations of 
 <italic>F. succinogenes</italic> and 
 <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-01605" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. These previous studies have indicated that the application of EO has negative effects on 
 <italic>F. succinogens</italic> and 
 <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic> populations, which supports the results of the EO in this study on SBM and BGH substrates, respectively. Nevertheless, certain fibrolytic bacteria populations were increased by certain EO, which indicates that different bacteria had different susceptibility to different EO. For example, in the SBM substrate, the application of SA led to the highest increases in the populations of 
 <italic>R. albus</italic> and 
 <italic>S. bovis</italic>, while GA and IN increased the population of 
 <italic>R. flavefaciens</italic>. The different active compounds of these wormwood species (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-08-01605-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) may explain the differential results on specific fibrolytic rumen bacteria. Although the present study showed that the effectiveness of EO to improve rumen fibrolytic bacterial populations depended on the wormwood spp. and substrate, more research is needed to understand which specific wormwood EO components have the beneficial and deleterious effects.
</p>
