<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infections caused by fungi are termed fungal infections or mycoses. Fungal infections have been considered a serious health problem and life-threatening diseases in recent years, especially in immunodeficiency conditions [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Severe fungal diseases result from other health challenges such as human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), asthma, cancer, organ transplantation, and corticosteroid treatments [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. In Nigeria, fungal infections (cryptococcal antigenemia, subclinical histoplasmosis) have been implicated in HIV/AIDS patients and neonatal intensive care babies [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. In Cameroun, esophageal candidiasis, cryptococcal meningitis, 
 <italic>Pneumocystis</italic> pneumonia, disseminated histoplasmosis, and invasive aspergillosis were prevalent in adults, while tinea capitis was prevalent among school children ([
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. In Mozambique, disseminated 
 <italic>Emergomyces</italic> and recurrent 
 <italic>Candida</italic> vulvovaginitis were common among HIV patients [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Some hospitalized patients are at risk of contracting fungal infections [
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Besides, emerging and reemerging fungal infections due to recent therapies for autoimmune and cancer-related diseases (hematopoietic stem cell transplant) are becoming public health concern [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Different parts of 
 <italic>Calotropis procera</italic>, a flowering plant that belongs to the family Asclepiadaceous, have been utilized in traditional medicine for the treatment of infections which include eczema, cutaneous infections, leprosy, and syphilis, as well as malaria. In a study on antifungal activity of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>procera</italic>, there was complete inhibition of 
 <italic>Microsporum</italic> and 
 <italic>Trichophyton</italic> species after ten days of inoculation with water extract at different concentrations [
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>].
</p>
