<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The methanol fraction of the ethanol extract from 
 <italic class="italic">D. aegyptium</italic> (at a dose of 50 mg/kg) decreased both hyperglycemia and ameliorated oxidative stress, which contributed to its antidiabetic activities [
 <xref rid="B198-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">198</xref>]. These could be related to insulinimimetic and antioxidant effects of the extract [
 <xref rid="B198-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">198</xref>]. The mechanism of action, as well as the active principles, are still not known [
 <xref rid="B198-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">198</xref>]. The methanol extract (70% methanol) of 
 <italic class="italic">D. bipinnata</italic> was proven useful in the restoration of euglycemic levels (250 and 500 mg/kg) [
 <xref rid="B157-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">157</xref>] while the hydroalcoholic extract of 
 <italic class="italic">E. crus-galli</italic>’s grains exhibited significant antidiabetic activity in diabetic rats (400mg/kg and 200mg/kg) as well as antioxidant activity and both protection and regeneration of pancreatic β-cells [
 <xref rid="B195-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">195</xref>]. Moreover, studies concerning acute toxicity showed that this extract does not cause major toxic effects [
 <xref rid="B195-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">195</xref>]. These activities may be related to quercetin, which was reported to be present in 
 <italic class="italic">D. bipinnata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B53-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">E. crus-galli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B90-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>] extracts and is recognized for its antidiabetic properties [
 <xref rid="B144-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">144</xref>]. Likewise, the ethyl acetate root extract of 
 <italic class="italic">P. australis</italic> was reported to have antidiabetic activity related to activation of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor (PPARy). Nonetheless, the active principles and the exact mechanism of action are not known [
 <xref rid="B199-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">199</xref>]. Ong and co-workers (2017) demonstrated the anti-obesity activity of 
 <italic class="italic">E. indica</italic>’s methanol extract using obese rats; its properties seem to be due to pancreatic lipase inhibition (27.01 ± 5.68%) [
 <xref rid="B200-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">200</xref>,
 <xref rid="B201-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">201</xref>]. Similarly, the plant extract showed antidiabetic activities against diabetic rats [
 <xref rid="B202-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">202</xref>]. 
</p>
