<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Field-collected achenes were germinated, raised to maturity, and allowed to produce self-fertilized achenes under uniform glasshouse conditions, to yield 64 inbred (selfed full-sib) lines (8–12 lines per population × 3 populations × 2 collection years). Plants were grown in 2:5 coarse sand: Pro-mix™ (Premier Horticulture Inc., Quakerstown, PA USA) fertilized with 20:20:20 soluble NPK (JR Peter's, Allentown, PA USA), with supplemental HID light when insolation between 0800 and 1800 h was &lt; 750 μE, from November–February 2001 (1994 collections) or November–February 2006 (2005 collections). Achenes produced were air-dried and stored with desiccant at 4°C. Appreciable seed aging effects are unlikely under such conditions (Fenner and Thompson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">2005</xref>); high germination rates for both inbreeding generations (average germination percentages ≥ 70%) confirm their absence. Still, since 1994 collections were stored longer than those from 2005, we tested for possibly confounding seed age effects. We experimentally tested for effects of achene age differences on seedling growth, the aspect of development most likely affected by seed age (Bewley and Black 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">1994</xref>; Smith and Berjak 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">1995</xref>). There was no difference (
 <sc>anova</sc>
 <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.5, 
 <italic>n</italic> = 45) between 1994- and 2005- collected achenes in the biomass of d 10 seedlings raised in Open/Mesic glasshouse conditions (July 2007). We repeated this test after a second ‘refresher’ generation to compare the same 1994- and 2005-collected lines using achenes they produced in August 2006 (i.e., of identical age). In this second test, 
 <sc>anova</sc> also showed no effect of collection year on seedling biomass (
 <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.2, 
 <italic>n</italic> = 55). The identical growth responses of 1994 and 2005 achenes for certain traits and treatments (Results) are consistent with specific evolved changes rather than overall loss of vigor due to seed age. A field experiment using 1994- and 2005-collected achenes of identical age confirmed significant differences between collection years in physiological and phenological responses to full sun (T. Horgan-Kobelski and S. E. Sultan, unpublished manuscript).
</p>
