<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> sp. are protozoal parasites which result in cutaneous and visceral leishmaniasis. Different clinical studies exhibit the development of self-curable to detrimental conditions, depending upon the immune responses triggered by the affected host (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Noormehr et al., 2018</xref>). Chemotherapy with pentavalent antimonials (like sodium stibogluconate or meglumine antimoniate) and other antileishmanial drugs (amphotericin B, fluconazole, pentamidine, and miltefosine) are optimal for leishmanial therapy. However, due to adverse effects, high cost, difficult infusion routes, low cure, and increasing resistance are of significant concern in developing more efficient ways in leishmaniasis therapy. Moreover, the efficacy of the drug used in the treatment also varies for different leishmanial sp. (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Noormehr et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Alti et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Calvo et al., 2020</xref>). In self-treatment, the innate immune cells (phagocytes) detect and engulf the causal agents, which induces 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> assassination by producing reactive oxygen species, nitric oxide, and tumor necrosis factors (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Olekhnovitch et al., 2014</xref>). After innate immune responses, respective activation and production of CD8
 <sup>+</sup>, NK, and IFN cells by TH1 immunity results in killing of 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> parasites (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Noormehr et al., 2018</xref>). In susceptible conditions, the defense system fails to overcome infections, and follows incorrect TH2 immune responses along with antibody response, which is the key factor to generate new ways of parasite elimination. Metal nanoparticles inhibit proliferation and viability of infected cells, which is contingent with the NP strength and time of exposure (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Rosas-Hernández et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Fanti et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
