<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To study the effects of soil treatment, interspecific competition and competitive species identity on the growth of either 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> or the competitor, we used a three-factor design. To quantify competition, we grew each competitor species in the presence and absence of an 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> individual in the same pot (e.g., 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet &amp; Keddy, 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2010</xref>) in both soil treatments. We also grew 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> alone as a reference to calculate its response to competition with the other species. Each treatment combination ((27 species + 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic>) × 2 soil treatments × 2 competition treatments) was replicated 6 times for a total of 744 pots. Pots (650 mL volume, 6.4 cm wide × 25 cm deep; D40 R; Stuewe and Sons Inc., Tangent, Oregon, USA) were filled with either 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history or untreated field soil and were randomly arranged in a checkerboard pattern across 53 trays (57 N25T; Stuewe and Sons Inc., Tangent, Oregon, USA) to minimize competition for light between pots. To induce germination, all seeds were cold stratified for 30–120 days based on information provided by seed suppliers. Cold stratification times were staggered to ensure all species germinated at the same time. After stratification, seeds were moved to the University of Guelph Phytotron greenhouse and germinated in a medium of 2/3 top soil and 1/3 silica sand and then transplanted into experimental treatments. Because of slow germination in some species, they were planted in two groups separated by two weeks. All plants were grown for the same number of days and were completely randomized across the greenhouse benches. 100 mL of 1/4 strength 18-9-18 N:P:K fertilizer (Plant Products, Leamington, Ontario, Canada) was added once to all pots in both soil treatments to promote seedling establishment. Because an equal amount of fertilizer was added to all pots, nutrient differences between the 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> history and control soil treatments remained. After 63 days, when herbaceous competitor plants had reached reproductive maturity, the aboveground parts of plants were harvested, separated according to species, dried at 60 °C for 48 h and weighed.
</p>
