<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The aromatic volatile oil (essential oil, EO), which is steam-distilled from the foliage, is among the world’s most traded essential oils in terms of volume. The study of EO has attracted much attention for its anti-microbial, antibacterial, antiseptic, fungicidal, and nematicidal activities [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. EO has a long history of use against the effect of cold, flu, sinusitis, rhinitis and other respiratory infections [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Tests in vitro showed that EO from 
 <italic class="italic">E. globulus</italic> leaves might be exploited as natural antibiotic for the treatment of several infectious diseases caused by 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Treatment of refrigerated pork with EO led to a significant decrease in 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas</italic> spp. count and to an increase of customer acceptance [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. EO from 
 <italic class="italic">E. globulus</italic> and its major compound 1,8-cineole were tested against 
 <italic class="italic">A. flavus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. parasiticus</italic>: it was found that the antifungal activity was due not only to the 1,8-cineol, but to the whole phytocomplex [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. A common need is the availability of natural extracts with pleasant taste and/or smell, combined with a preservative action aimed at avoiding lipid deterioration, fungal growth, oxidation and spoilage by microorganisms. The use of essential oils as functional ingredients in food, beverages and cosmetics is gaining increasing interest because of their relatively safe status, their wide acceptance by consumers, and their exploitation for potential multi-purpose functional use [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-00226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
