<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In salt marsh ecosystems, plants are distributed along the elevational gradient according to their sea-water inundation tolerance. Plants with ecophysiological traits that promote resistance to higher flooding frequency and inundation time, such as aerenchyma formation, conservative water use, or the production of N-rich solutes for osmotic adjustment [
 <xref rid="B14-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], usually occur at low elevations (LE) [
 <xref rid="B16-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], whereas plants lacking these traits have a higher fitness at high elevations (HE). Sea coach 
 <italic>Elytrigia atherica</italic> is an example of the latter. It is a dominant species in the late stage of the salt marsh natural succession in areas that are usually located higher above sea level due to silt accretion [
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This tall grass stands out for being highly competitive, as demonstrated by its wide distribution—the species occurs in salt marshes across the North Atlantic Coast from Northern Portugal to Southern Denmark—and for reducing the plant diversity of natural salt marsh communities at high elevation sites [
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. 
 <italic>Elytrigia atherica</italic> is expanding into recently drained low elevation and younger sites, where it outcompetes most other mid-successional species, causing a reduction in plant diversity that is comparable to an exotic species invasion [
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Its successful expansion to the low marsh with altered (a)biotic conditions has been attributed to the high chance of establishment once a seedling has germinated, due to clonal spread, its ability to form aerenchyma and the relative unpalatability for salt marsh grazers, such as geese [
 <xref rid="B16-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The different conditions found in low elevation salt marsh compared to high elevation marshes have led to the formation of two 
 <italic>E. atherica</italic> ecotypes with a genetic differentiation in plants that grow at a distance longer than 100 m apart [
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] but also within patches of &lt;5 m [
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Furthermore, phenotypic differences have been observed in traits such as shoot length, number of spikelets per spike and ramet numbers between HE and LE ecotypes [
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-08-01619" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. One factor that potentially could also impact the invasiveness of this plant species is the extent to which the LE and HE ecotype of 
 <italic>E. atherica</italic> differ in relation to their association with beneficial microbes, which could contribute to their extension into LE salt marsh sites.
</p>
