<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the demographic report, the world population stands at 7625 million people, with an annual growth rate of approximately 74 million people [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The United Nations (UN) has estimated that by 2050 the population will reach 9.2 billion people [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The current economic model (linear economy) has allowed rapid industrial and cultural development. However, its extracting, consuming, and disposal structure negatively impacts the availability of natural resources that supply the world population. Population growth also generates more natural resources and food consumption. Despite this, current resources are limited to supply the necessary food for the growing population and the generation of large amounts of waste [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. These wastes are transported to sanitary landfills every year, reducing the available land for agriculture, causing damage to health and the environment [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In response to the problem, the use (or reuse) of waste would facilitate food supply to the growing population, reducing the indiscriminate use of human consumption resources [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The circular economy drastically transforms the culture and the system of extraction, production, and consumption towards a system of restoration and regeneration of natural resources’ value, limiting the excessive use of raw materials and energy and avoiding the unnecessary generation of waste [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In the circular economy, a system is established where the products are designed in such a way that the generation of waste is minimal or wholly eliminated, implementing a culture in which the product is designed to give it a second useful life, with added value and also, the reduction of energy and raw material consumption [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
