<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The aspects that currently focus on the circular economy are guided by the Ellen MacArthur Foundation’s butterfly diagram, based on two elements capable of processing everything that surrounds us in such a way that nothing is thrown away or wasted [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. These elements are divided into technical and biological cycles. What belongs to the biological cycle must be compostable (compost for the soil) or used to generate biogas (gas obtained from the decomposition of organic waste). On the other side, everything is recycled without losing quality through maintenance, remanufacturing, or reuse [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, the diagram focused on a completely closed and consecutive cycle is hardly executable in the economy due to the increase in energy costs and unavoidable material losses [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Velenturf et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-26-00515" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] propose an integrated diagram in which the production-consumption system and the biophysical environment are related to the environment and the aspects determined in the circular economy. This diagram is based on the integration of avoidable waste and industrial materials within the production system. The uncontrolled biophysical environment relates to the human being’s production and consumption system, using the biophysical environment’s natural resources, turning them into industrial products. In this way, the biological (natural) and technological (industrial) terms are replaced. Raw materials can be of natural or industrial origin, forming part of biological and chemical processes for their reincorporation in the biophysical environment. Industrial materials are redesigned at the end of their useful life and do not affect the biophysical environment. Those that do not need to be redesigned are reintegrated, reducing uncontrolled leaks of waste by redesigning the production and consumption system’s infrastructure.
</p>
