<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The anticancer activity of the plant has been reported in literature [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Cytotoxic properties of the polysaccharides obtained from 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> were examined. Cytotoxic activity on human breast cancer cells (MCF-7) and lung cancer cells (HCC827) and immune-enhancement effect were examined. The results indicated that 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">amara</italic> polysaccharides displayed good immune-enhancement activity by stimulating the production of tumor necrosis factor-
 <italic class="italic">α</italic> (TNF-
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>) and interleukin-6 (IL-6) in RAW264.7 cells and by promoting the mRNA expression levels of inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS), TNF-
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>, interleukin-1
 <italic class="italic">β</italic> (IL-1
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>), and IL-6. Moreover, phosphorylated extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK), phosphorylated c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), phosphorylated p38, and phosphorylated p65 were significantly enhanced in 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> var 
 <italic class="italic">amara</italic> polysaccharides-treated RAW264.7 cells [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Isolimonic acid and ichanexic acid from ethyl acetate extract of 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> were isolated by using chromatographic methods. The compounds for their inhibitory action on human colon cancer cells (HT-29) proliferation, apoptosis, and on noncancerous (COS-1 fibroblast) cells were investigated. The compounds displayed an increment in the cell counts in G2/M stage, demonstrating a potential effect in the cell-cycle arrest [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>].
</p>
