<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experimentally, there are several animal models of gout which are mainly monosodium urate crystal deposition-induced acute inflammation, potassium oxonate-induced hyperuricemia, and carrageenan-induced inflammation. In fact, uric acid is considered as a weak organic acid, and it is able to be ionized to monosodium urate crystal at pH = 7.4 and at 37°C. Consequently, uric acid and urate crystals could deposit into the tissues, particularly joints and kidney, contributing to tissue damage [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The formation of monosodium urate crystals lead to the activation of macrophages that play a role in the secretion of inflammatory cytokines as IL-1 
 <italic>β</italic>. These mediators initiate with complement of (activated at crystals surfaces) a neutrophilic influx that is pathophysiologic feature of acute-gout. During the infiltration, crystals activate neutrophils, which contribute to the production of additional proinflammatory mediators such as arachidonic acid products (prostaglandine E2 and leukotriene B4). Monosodium urate crystals could persist into the joint fluid between attacks, which suggest that the inflammatory potential of monosodium urate crystals may be modulated by synovial fluid elements [
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Potassium oxonate is a selective competitive inhibitor of uricase that play a key role in the conversion of uric acid to allantoin. Then, it induced hyperuricemia in rodents by blocking the effect of liver uricases [
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Indeed, it was reported that potassium oxanate-induced hyperuricemic in rats developed a high level of renal proteins (URAT1 and GLUT9) and decreased the level of OTA1. However, the involved mechanisms are not clear yet [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. The carrageenan-induced paw edema is another experiment model of gout that involves several inflammatory mediators such as TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> and IL-1 
 <italic>β</italic>. In fact, TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> triggers IL-1 
 <italic>β</italic> release and cytokine-induced neutrophil chemoattractant 1 which play a key role in the stimulation of the prostaglandins synthesis by cyclooxygenase-2. Furthermore, TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> activates iNOS responsible for NO synthesis, and then the responses of neutrophils increases to inflammatory stimuli [
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].
</p>
