<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Essential oils containing phenolics and flavonoids were extracted from Nerium sp. (E1), Mentha asp. (E2), Aloevera (E3) and Eucalyptus sp. (E4) and were assessed for their antimicrobial activities against bacterial and fungal species. The experiment was done in 96 well plate by micro dilution technique. Proper controls were taken in different wells. After incubation, absorbance was taken and average results were presented in (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). In (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), the result obtained from treatment against a bacterium is shown. Bacterial strain chosen for this study was Staphylococcus aureus, as it is a commensal bacterium and also a major human bacterial pathogen with wide variety of clinical manifestation [
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. S. aureusis Gram positive bacteria with coccus shape. It is sensitive to antibiotic, which was used as positive control in this experiment [
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In case of Nerium sp. (E1), higher concentrations of plant extracts showed a strong activity against the pathogen. At higher concentrations, activity was as good as antibiotics used as 50µg/ml. At lower concentrations, the activity against the pathogen is negligible and growth is not hampered (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). A similar result was seen in case of Mentha Sp. (E2) and Aloe vera (E3) extracts. In all the three cases higher concentration was working efficiently to kill the bacterial pathogen, but the lower concentrations were not as efficient. Sometimes, it even looks like that lower concentrations are favouring the growth of the organism (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). This may be attributed to the chemistry of the active ingredients in essential oils, where biological properties i.e. (antimicrobial capability) get altered and instead of growth inhibiting, they transform as growth promoting stuffs. Results from essential oil extracted from Eucalyptus sample (E4) were different. It showed a significant growth reducing capability even at lower concentrations. In case of Eucalyptus oils, higher as well as lower concentrations were effective killer of the bacteria and showed an activity similar to antibiotics used as control. Thus, we can say that Eucalyptus essential oil has a great potential in decreasing the growth of gram-positive bacteria. Interestingly though, when all the four essential oils were compared at higher active concentrations, results did not show Eucalyptus as the best among four (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). In this comparison, Mentha sp. showed significantly greater growth retarding capability, which was better than even the antibiotics used as positive control. Similar experiment was performed to see the efficacy of these essential oils against a fungal pathogen, results of which is present in (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Candida albicans was the ideal choice for this study, as this fungus residesas a harmless commensal with most of the humans. However, under favourable condition, C. albicans can cause infections ranging from superficial infections of the skin to life-threatening systemic infections [
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Results presented in (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), showed similar antifungal activity as was shown for antibacterial activity. All the four plant extracts showed great response at higher concentrations, when compared to lower concentrations. Growth inhibition at higher concentration was comparable to, or even better than control antibiotics. Lower concentrations used for different essential oils were showing non-significant difference from growth control in three out of four cases. Only in the case of Eucalyptus oil, even the lower concentrations showed growth inhibition. Eucalyptus oil was the best antifungal agent among the four plant extract tested, even when we compared the higher concentrations of all four extracts. The activity shown by Eucalyptus oil against C. albicans was significantly better than the positive control (antibiotics). Different groups from different countries has done related work and showed similar promising results. Gulluce et al.[
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] also performed the antimicrobial and anti-oxidant properties of essential oil from menthalongifolia and found that essential oil possesses strong antimicrobial properties against 30 isolates. Kiran and Prasad, [
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] also performed the antimicrobial studies of Nerium oleander leaf by extracting them using cold maceration extraction method in methanol and chloroform employing well diffusion method against different bacterial and fungal isolates viz. E. Coli, B. subtilis, A. brasiliensis and C. albicans. Eucalyptus essential oil antimicrobial activity and found antibacterial activity with varying magnitudes, depending on the size of inoculums and the concentration of essential oil. Hassan et al.[
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] studied the antidiarrhoeal; antimicrobial and cytotoxic activities of ethanol-extracted leaves of yellow oleander (Thevetiaperuviana) and found poor antimicrobial activity of the plant extract. Bachir and Benali,[
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] examined the in-vitro antimicrobial activities of essential oil of the leaves of Eucalyptus globulus. The results obtained showed that essential oil of the leaves of E. globules has antimicrobial activity against gram-negative bacteria (E. coli) as well as gram-positive bacteria (S. aureus).
</p>
