<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The aim of emulsifiers addition (such as proteins, polysaccharides, etc.) to emulsion systems is to form interfacial surfaces, due to their capability to adsorb onto oil–water interfaces [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The emulsifying properties of flaxseed proteins (FP) were already reported [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Other essential constituents of the flaxseed are polysaccharides—called flaxseed gum (FG). This gum is also used in emulsion preparation in order to enhance the emulsion stability [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The mechanism of emulsion stabilization by flaxseed gum is based on increasing the viscosity and decreasing the interfacial tension [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The valorization of FOCE (flaxseed oil cake extract, which is a mixed liquid matrix of flaxseed protein and flaxseed gum) in terms of food science is not yet a deeply explored issue. However, there are reports about its technological applications, including stabilization of emulsion systems. Available reports indicate that this valuable agro-industrial by-product fits the idea of circular economy and “zero waste” trends [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In previous works it was demonstrated that FOCE can be applied as an emulsifying agent for stable emulsions with flaxseed oil, due to strong FG and FP synergistic oil binding and water holding abilities [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Moreover, it was reported that the spray drying process has a positive influence on the emulsifying properties of FOCE-based spray-dried powders [
 <xref rid="B12-foods-10-00256" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
