<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-foods-07-00007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Peaches and nectarines (
  <span class="italic">Prunus persica</span> (L.) Batsch) are fruit rich in vitamins, fibers and other phytochemical compounds, such as carotenes and polyphenols, which are important for a healthy diet [
  <a rid="B1-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-foods-07-00007">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-foods-07-00007">2</a>]. Stone fruit are consumed worldwide and represent one of the most important fruit. In recent years, peach and nectarine production increased progressively [
  <a rid="B3-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-foods-07-00007">3</a>] and the main global producer is China with over 12 million tons, followed by Spain and Italy, which produce 3 million tons annually [
  <a rid="B4-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-foods-07-00007">4</a>]. Peaches and nectarines are the 3rd most important fruit crop in the European Union after apples and pears [
  <a rid="B5-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-foods-07-00007">5</a>]. During storage, the quality characteristics and some commercial parameters of these fruit can decrease, at a rate depending on the storage conditions, due to postharvest diseases and senescence processes [
  <a rid="B6-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-foods-07-00007">6</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most common postharvest pathogens on stone fruit are 
  <span class="italic">Monilinia</span> spp. (
  <span class="italic">M. fructigena</span> Honey, 
  <span class="italic">M. fructicola</span> (G. Winter) Honey, and 
  <span class="italic">M. laxa</span> (Aderh. and Ruhland) Honey), agents of brown rot, 
  <span class="italic">Botrytis cinerea</span> Pers. agent of gray mold, 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium expansum</span> Link, agent of blue mold, 
  <span class="italic">Alternaria</span> spp., agent of black mold, and 
  <span class="italic">Rhizopus stolonifer</span>, Ehrenb., agent of Rhizopus rot [
  <a rid="B7-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-foods-07-00007">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-foods-07-00007">8</a>]. On peaches, postharvest losses can cause even higher damage than preharvest diseases [
  <a rid="B9-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-foods-07-00007">9</a>]. Crop protection in Europe should be performed in the orchard because only one fungicide (fludioxonil) can be used on stone fruit after harvesting, but the supermarket chains typically request either no further postharvest treatments or a limited number of active ingredients, as residues, on the fruit. The last fungicide has to be applied 1 or 2 weeks before harvesting, to guarantee a high level of fruit protection against pathogens during storage, and to remain below the maximum residue limits imposed by European legislation [
  <a rid="B10-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-foods-07-00007">10</a>]. Moreover, consumer attention is attracted by environmentally friendly production practices, preferring foods treated with natural products instead of conventional pesticides [
  <a rid="B11-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-foods-07-00007">11</a>]. At present, 
  <span class="italic">Monilinia</span> spp. control depends on an integrated strategy based on orchard fungicide spray programs and maintenance of proper storage conditions in the packinghouse and during distribution [
  <a rid="B12-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-foods-07-00007">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, intense research efforts focus on developing innovative, unconventional, sustainable strategies to preserve fruit quality and decrease food losses. The most promising control approaches are the use of microorganisms and natural products with intrinsic antimicrobial properties [
  <a rid="B13-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-foods-07-00007">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-foods-07-00007">14</a>]. Essential oils (EOs) represent a powerful tool to reduce the environmental impact of fruit production [
  <a rid="B15-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-foods-07-00007">15</a>]. The efficacy of plant EOs has been extensively evaluated in vitro [
  <a rid="B16-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-foods-07-00007">16</a>], but a few studies have been performed in vivo [
  <a rid="B17-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-foods-07-00007">17</a>]. However, these treatments may modify the organoleptic characteristics of fruit, changing taste or flavor during cold storage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antifungal activity of EOs is determined by their chemical composition. In particular, aldehydes, phenols and ketones considerably inhibit pathogen growth. Thymol, carvacrol and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-anisaldehyde have a proven fungicidal activity and EOs rich in these components showed the highest inhibitory activity against many postharvest pathogens, such as 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium digitatum</span> [
  <a rid="B18-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-foods-07-00007">18</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</span> [
  <a rid="B19-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-foods-07-00007">19</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">R. stolonifer</span> [
  <a rid="B20-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-foods-07-00007">20</a>]. EOs of thyme (
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span>) and savory (
  <span class="italic">Satureja montana</span>) are mainly composed of thymol and carvacrol [
  <a rid="B21-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-foods-07-00007">21</a>], which are highly effective in controlling fungal pathogens. Generally, the efficacy of EOs is investigated through direct contact with fruit, by application through spraying or dipping [
  <a rid="B22-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-foods-07-00007">22</a>]. However, these application methods can have undesired effects, including phytotoxicity and organoleptic modification of treated fruit. Only a few studies have reported the efficacy of EO treatments through biofumigation, focusing on phytopathological aspects [
  <a rid="B23-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-foods-07-00007">23</a>]. Scientific research recently started to pay particular attention to the assessment of the antifungal activity of EO vapors [
  <a rid="B24-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-foods-07-00007">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-foods-07-00007">25</a>]. Fumigation with thyme and savory EOs resulted in effective control of several postharvest pathogens, showing antifungal activity against 
  <span class="italic">Colletotrichum</span> [
  <a rid="B26-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-foods-07-00007">26</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Penicillium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Mucor</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Trichoderma</span> spp. [
  <a rid="B27-foods-07-00007" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-foods-07-00007">27</a>] The use of EOs through fumigation avoids the direct contact with the product, reducing the possibility of influencing the sensorial profile.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study was to investigate the effect of the vapor phase of thyme and savory EOs, applied by fumigation through slow-release diffusors, on both quality parameters and postharvest diseases of peaches and nectarines, during cold storage and shelf life. Savory and thyme solid diffusors were prepared at two different concentrations and they were used to treat naturally infected peaches and nectarines. In order to clarify how essential oils diffuse and persist in cold rooms, the atmospheric composition of the storage cabinets was analyzed during cold storage. At the same time, the antimicrobial activity of essential oil vapors was evaluated in vitro on conidial germination of 
  <span class="italic">M. fructicola</span> and 
  <span class="italic">B. cinerea</span>, two of the main postharvest pathogens of peaches and nectarines.
 </p>
</sec>
