<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Comparative studies have revealed that the method of depolymerization strongly influences the properties of carrageenan oligomers [
 <xref rid="B178-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">178</xref>]. The chemical depolymerization (free radical or mild acid hydrolysis), produced oligomers with lower Mw (1.2–3.5 kDa) than the enzymatic depolymerization using a recombinant kappa-carrageenase from 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudoalteromonas carrageenovora</italic>, yielding 2.2 kDa oligomers from 
 <italic class="italic">Chondrus armatus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Kappaphycus alvarezii</italic> k-carrageenans and 4.3 kDa oligomers from 
 <italic class="italic">Tichocarpus crinitus</italic> κ/β-carrageenans. Low molecular weight derivatives obtained by mild acid hydrolysis showed higher antiviral activity than those obtained by free radical depolymerization, which were more active than those enzymatically prepared. Sun et al. [
 <xref rid="B176-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>] observed that mild acid hydrolysis caused higher saccharide degradation than H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> depolymerization and κ-carrageenase digestion; the original sulfate content was substantially retained and all the hydrolysates had stronger reducing power than the polysaccharide, with H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> hydrolysates being the most potent. After free radical treatment at 40 °C for 4 h, the low-molecular weight oligosaccharides from κ-carrageenan ranged from disaccharide to octasaccharide. The degradation with a κ-carrageenase hydrolyzing the β-1,4 linkages to a series of homologous, even-numbered oligosaccharides (An-G4S)n, yielding 2, 4, 6, 8 and 10 DP, being dominant the tetra- and hexasaccharides [
 <xref rid="B176-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>]. Whereas for H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> treatment, the scavenging ability increased with time as a result from the increment of –COOH groups, the scavenging ability of HCl hydrolysates and enzymatic hydrolysates decreased when the molecular weight decreased. Other combinations have been suggested, i.e., radical depolymerization, and high-pressure homogenization led to several samples of various and controlled molar masses of 
 <italic class="italic">Halymenia durvillei</italic> [
 <xref rid="B95-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>].
</p>
