<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The three most commercially exploited carrageenans are kappa (κ-), iota (ι-) and lambda (λ-) carrageenans, which can be separately provided or as a well-defined mixture, since most of the seaweeds contain hybrid carrageenans [
 <xref rid="B22-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Mu and nu carrageenans are the precursors in carrageenan, which are converted to kappa and iota, respectively, by means of alkaline modification. In the natural state, unmodified kappa and iota carrageenans account for around 30% mu and nu-carrageenans, remaining less than 5% after alkaline modification, randomly distributed within the repeating structures [
 <xref rid="B103-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. Origin, species or extraction processing conditions notably affect the type and quality of carrageenan isolated. The carrageenan types vary among species from the 
 <italic class="italic">Cystocloniaceae</italic> family predominantly produce iota-carrageenans; the 
 <italic class="italic">Gigartinaceae</italic> family lead to hybrid kappa-iota carrageenans and lambda-family carrageenans (sporophytic plants); the 
 <italic class="italic">Phyllophoraceae</italic> family produces kappa-iota hybrid-carrageenans [
 <xref rid="B104-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>]. Commonly, κ-carrageenan is commercially isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">Kappaphycus alvarezii</italic> red seaweed through a hot extraction process, whereas λ-carrageenan is more hygroscopic and it is usually extracted from red seaweeds of the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Gigartina</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">Chondrus</italic> by drum dryer or alcohol precipitation process [
 <xref rid="B105-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. Concerning ι-carrageenan, it is commercially extracted from 
 <italic class="italic">Eucheuma denticulatum</italic> by the freeze thaw or gel process [
 <xref rid="B106-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. The highest carrageenan yields can exceed 70% (dry basis) for some species such as 
 <italic class="italic">B. gelatinum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">K. alvarezii</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">K. striatum</italic>. Other species have values close to 30%, such as 
 <italic class="italic">E. denticulatum</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">C. crispus</italic>. Sulfate content in carrageenans varies from 20% in κ-carrageenan, to 33% in ι-carrageenan and to 41% in λ-carrageenan [
 <xref rid="B107-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. It is well known that the carrageenans gelation process is affected by the biopolymer content, temperature, ionic strength of the solution and the cation type and content, being the most effective K
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> and Rb
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>. In general, iota carrageenans form soft and elastic gels with higher gelling temperatures than κ-carrageenans [
 <xref rid="B108-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. In contrast, λ-carrageenan did not form gels, being used solely as thickening agent [
 <xref rid="B109-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>]. Gelling temperatures ranged from 32 to 36 °C for the κ-carrageenans, whereas ι-carrageenans exhibited values of 70–74 °C. Gel strengths, elastic modulus at 25 °C, varied between 4000–6500 Pa for alkali pre-treated samples [
 <xref rid="B24-marinedrugs-17-00314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
