<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0190" class="p">Growth performance outcomes demonstrated progressive but fractional losses in fish performance indicators as PPB fraction (or protein input) increased, generally significant across all treatments, but not between neighbouring treatments. The main effect was on performance indicators growth, daily weight gain and FCR, rather than mortality and carcass composition. In terms of commercial viability, up to 66% of the fishmeal could be substituted with purple phototrophic bacteria without a major impact on the fish performance parameters for the first 28 d of the trial, noting that the impact is progressive after 28 d. It is important to consider that the Diet 4 in the present study contained zero fishmeal and the results are consistent with other studies where complete substitution was considered. For example, replacement of fishmeal with soybean and poultry meal in barramundi diets resulted reduced weight gain and increased feed conversion that was significant when replacement was 66% or 100% (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Glencross et al., 2016</xref>). Indeed, over the duration of the trial FCR remained at around 1 for diets with 33% and 66% of FM replaced by PPB. The reason for the increased FCR and decreased daily weight gain at high replacement levels need to be further investigated. Similar impact on growth and feed conversion was noted in Arctic charr fed on diets with 40% FM replaced by intact baker's yeast (
 <italic class="italic">S. cerevisiae</italic>) or filamentous fungal biomass (
 <italic class="italic">Rhizopus oryzae</italic>) (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vidakovic et al., 2016</xref>). The negative effect of yeast inclusion on FCR and final weight was abrogated in Arctic charr by pre-lysing the yeast cells (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vidakovic et al., 2016</xref>) resulting in improved apparent digestibility of the protein and amino acids in the diet (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Langeland et al., 2016</xref>). It is therefore possible that pre-lysis of PPB biomass may increase the performance at higher substitution rates and is worthy of further study, albeit that there would be additional processing cost. Other potential factors impacting final weight and FCR may include the presence of nucleic acids in the PPB biomass, as high levels would increase the energy cost for barramundi to metabolise them. While nucleotides are semi-essential nutrients in many animals including fish and shrimp (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burrells et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carver and Walker, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Do et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hoang Do et al., 2013</xref>), nucleic acids need first to be processed via the salvage pathway prior to supplying to new genetic material during growth. Moreover, excess nucleotides need to be excreted and accrue a metabolic cost. As a consequence, levels must be optimised for each species and age as requirement decreases in older animals (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Do et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li and Gatlin, 2006</xref>). Similar considerations apply to complex carbohydrates that could lead to gut irritation and lower digestibility. These will be tested in future digestibility experiments. We demonstrated successfully that the inclusion up to 33% FM replacement with PPB would have little or no impact on barramundi growth performance. Therefore, we can recover resources from wastewater, transform them into PPB biomass and convert it to a useful feed ingredient, reducing the reliance on wild caught fishmeal. In contrast, deleterious effects on growth, feed intake and feed conversion have been reported when microalgae were used at concentrations as low as 12% total inclusion (14.2% FM substitution) with 
 <italic class="italic">Phaeodactylum tricornutum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sorensen et al., 2016</xref>) and 20% total inclusion for defatted 
 <italic class="italic">Nannochloropsis</italic> biomass (
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sorensen et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
