<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010" class="p">Neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer's Disease (AD), Parkinson's disease, Multiple Sclerosis (MS) results in slow neuronal death that accompanied with losing cognitive functions and sensory dysfunction.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">1</sup>
 </xref> Recently, these diseases associated with different multifactorial etiologies, social, and financial problems.
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">2</sup>
 </xref> Anti-inflammatory agents have also been suggested to postpone the progression of neurodegenerative diseases such as AD. Different studies have shown that nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may reduce the risk of developing AD.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">5</sup>
 </xref> Pathological processes including inflammation, oxidative stress, apoptosis, mitochondrial dysfunction, and genetic factors lead to neuronal degeneration in Parkinson's disease (PD).
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">6</sup>
 </xref> It has been reported that excessive lipid peroxidation may destroy cholinergic neurons in AD
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">7</sup>
 </xref> and dopaminergic neurons in PD.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">8</sup>
 </xref> Different enzymatic antioxidant such as superoxide dismutase (SOD)
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">9</sup>
 </xref> and non-enzymatic antioxidant such as total thiol groups
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">10</sup>
 </xref> exist in the brain. Central nervous system (CNS) also contains high level of polyunsaturated fatty acids is more sensitive to peroxidation reactions (9). Low antioxidant activity of the brain with respect to other tissues has been made the brain tissue susceptible to oxidative damage.
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">11</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
