<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the castor oil-induced diarrheal model, the crude leaves extract of 
 <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> significantly prolonged the diarrheal onset and the frequency of stooling at middle and higher tested doses. This study is in line with other study which showed the hydromethanolic crude extract of 
 <italic>Indigofera spicata</italic> at 200 and 400 mg/kg.bw doses had statistically significant inhibition of the frequency of defecation. [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] The significant antidiarrheal activity of this plant could be due to the probable localization of secondary metabolites to inhibit castor oil-induced fluid secretion. Besides, the crude leaves extract of 
 <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> (200 and 400 mg/kg.bw) showed a significant percentage of diarrheal inhibition as compared to the controls which can further corroborate its antidiarrheal potential to undergo further investigation. Surprisingly, at the maximum tested doses (400 mg/kg.bw), the crude extract of 
 <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> showed almost comparable effect with the standard drug. This dose-dependent effect of the crude extract may be probably due to the augmentation of the therapeutic concentration of the secondary metabolites as a result of increased dose. Nonetheless, at the dose of 100 mg/kg.bw, the extract was devoid of significant antidiarrheal effect in this model. Phytochemical screening study showed that the leaves extract of 
 <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> was endowed with alkaloids, flavonoids, polyphenols, terpenoids, cardiac glycosides, and saponins. [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] Previous studies showed that terpenoids and steroids like phytosterols have a capacity to inhibit the production of prostaglandin E2 [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], which has a crucial role in the stimulation of intestinal secretions. [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] Accordingly, the significant antidiarrheal activity observed in the 
 <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> crude extract at different doses could probably be linked to the presence of these secondary metabolites in the crude extract. Besides, Moazedi et al. [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] reported that the hydroalcoholic leaves extract of 
 <italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> had a significant antispasmodic effect on rat ileum. This could probably suggest its antidiarrheal effect by inhibition of castor oil-induced gastrointestinal motility.
</p>
