<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Compounds of a biological origin that elicit plant defense response and thus produce higher quantities of secondary metabolites are produced in two ways. Biotic elicitors are either compounds coming from pathogens, i.e., exogenous in origin or are compounds/hormones produced as a response to the pathogen that in turn triggers the plant’s defense response (endogenous elicitors). Plant 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures have been used as factories for the enhanced production of medicinally secondary metabolites through the application of many different exogenous and endogenous elicitors (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">Srivastava et al., 2019</xref>). Exogenous biotic elicitors include bacterial lysates, microbial enzymes, polysaccharides (chitin), and yeast extracts. For instance, cellulase, which directly serves bacteria and fungi and helps in attacking plant cell walls, has been shown to enhance the production of glycyrrhizin up to 8.6-fold through the application of cellulase to the hairy roots of 
 <italic>G. glabra</italic> L. Besides, mannan oligosaccharides derived from the cell wall of yeasts (
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">De Oliveira et al., 2014</xref>) have also been reported to trigger the enhanced production of glycyrrhizin (7.8-fold compared to control) in hairy root cultures of 
 <italic>G. glabra</italic> L. It should be reiterated here that glycyrrhizin possesses a demonstrated activity against the previously epidemic SARS-CoV. This saponin from licorice roots can inhibit the replication of SARS-associated coronavirus with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> value ranging from 300 to 600 mg/L (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Cinatl et al., 2003</xref>). Similarly, methyl jasmonate, a very important endogenous biotic elicitor has been shown to be effective in enhancing the production of glycyrrhizin up to almost 109 micrograms/g dry weight after 5 days of elicitation with 100 mM of methyl jasmonate. The study also demonstrated the role of other elicitors such as chitosan and yeast extract on the production of glycyrrhizin and demonstrated their effectiveness (
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">Wongwicha et al., 2011</xref>). Other biotic elicitors ascorbic acid, eugenol, salicylic acid, and yeast extract have been employed for the enhancement of glycyrrhizin in cell cultures of 
 <italic>Abrus precatorius</italic> (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Karwasara et al., 2010</xref>).
</p>
