<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sixteen spiro-indan type compounds were isolated from cannabis (
 <bold>126</bold>–
 <bold>141</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02774-f009">Figure 9</xref>). Compound 
 <bold>126</bold> was isolated in 1976 from an Indian cannabis variety using silica gel column chromatography and given the name cannabispiran [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In the same year, the compound was also isolated by another research group from a South African variety and named cannabispirone; cannabispirenone (
 <bold>127</bold>) was also identified from the South African cannabis variety [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Bercht et al. used NMR and mass spectrometric analysis to prove the chemical structures of 
 <bold>126</bold> and 
 <bold>127</bold>, while Ottersen et al. used X-ray crystallography to confirm the chemical structure of 
 <bold>126</bold> [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The cannabispirenone isomer (
 <bold>128</bold>), with interchangeable methoxy and hydroxyl groups, was isolated from Mexican marihuana, and its chemical structure was established by 
 <sup>1</sup>H NMR and EIMS analysis, [
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Cannabispiradienone (
 <bold>129</bold>) was isolated from Thai cannabis, and its chemical structure was elucidated based on 
 <sup>1</sup>H NMR spectroscopy and confirmed by hydrogenation to give cannabispiran (
 <bold>126</bold>) [
 <xref rid="B70-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Two spiro-indans named cannabispirol (
 <bold>130</bold>) and acetyl cannabispirol (
 <bold>131</bold>) were detected by Yukihiro and Nishioka in the benzene extract of the dried leaves of Japanese cannabis. The benzene extract was chromatographed on a polyamide column followed by silica gel chromatography to yield compounds 
 <bold>130</bold> and 
 <bold>131</bold> [
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Compound 
 <bold>130</bold> was also isolated from a South African variety of cannabis grown in Mississippi by Turner’s group and named 
 <italic>β</italic>-cannabispirol. The orientation of the hydroxyl group was determined by 
 <sup>1</sup>H NMR analysis of 
 <bold>130</bold> and its acetate derivative (
 <bold>131</bold>) [
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Three spiro-indans were isolated from an ethanolic extract of a seized hashish sample from Saudi Arabia and were chemically identified as 5-hydroxy-7-methoxyindan-1-spiro-cyclohexane (
 <bold>132</bold>), 7-hydroxy-5-methoxyindan-1-spiro-cyclohexane (
 <bold>133</bold>), and 5,7-dihydroxyindan-1-spiro-cyclohexane (
 <bold>134</bold>) through a combination of spectral and chemical analysis. The methanolic fraction of hashish was subjected to flash chromatography and further purified through silica gel column chromatography to afford compounds 
 <bold>132</bold>–
 <bold>134</bold> [
 <xref rid="B72-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Isocannabispiran (
 <bold>135</bold>) has been isolated from a Panamanian variety of cannabis by repeated chromatography. The structure was chemically elucidated as 5′-hydroxy-7′-methoxy-spiro-(cyclohexane-1,1′-indan)-4-one by spectroscopic means as well as direct comparison with cannabispiran (
 <bold>126</bold>) [
 <xref rid="B73-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Radwan et al. (2008) isolated 7-O-methyl-cannabispirone (
 <bold>136</bold>) from an extract of a high potency cannabis variety using normal phase chromatography followed by C
 <sub>18</sub>-HPLC [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], while isocannabispiradienone (
 <bold>137</bold>) and 
 <italic>α</italic>-cannabispiranol (
 <bold>138</bold>) were obtained from the dichloromethane extract of decarboxylated 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> hemp that was subjected to C
 <sub>18</sub> flash chromatography, followed by silica gel gravity column chromatography and HPLC. The chemical structures were established using HR-ESIMS and NMR (
 <sup>1</sup>H, 
 <sup>13</sup>C, HSQC and HMBC) data [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Recently, three new cannabispirans (
 <bold>139</bold>–
 <bold>141</bold>) have been obtained from the leaves of 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic>. Cannabispirketal (
 <bold>139</bold>) and the glycoside, 
 <italic>α</italic>-cannabispiranol-4′-O-β-glucopyranose (
 <bold>140</bold>) were isolated from an ethanolic extract, and their chemical structures were determined by 1D NMR (
 <sup>1</sup>H NMR, 
 <sup>13</sup>C NMR) and 2DNMR (COSY, HSQC, HMBC and ROESY) [
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. In 2018, Nalli et al. isolated prenylspirodienone (
 <bold>141</bold>) and proved its chemical structure by extensive NMR and ESI-MS analysis. Moreover, they proposed the bio-synthetic pathway from this compound [
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].
</p>
