<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">CRISPR-Cas9 can be employed efficiently to mutate multiple 
 <italic>fads2</italic> genes simultaneously in salmon. However, mosaic effects are common, embodied by different indels among tissues and individuals. Exon skipping found in the 
 <italic>Δ6fads2-a</italic> gene during transcription was predicted to result in the production of truncated proteins and strengthen the CRISPR-induced disruption of LC-HUFA synthesis in 
 <italic>Δ6abc/5</italic>
 <sup>Mt</sup> salmon. Down-regulation of the targeted 
 <italic>Δ5fads2</italic>, 
 <italic>Δ6fads2-a</italic> and 
 <italic>Δ6fads2-b</italic> genes were found in liver, which likely cause a decrease of LC-HUFA synthesis. On the other hand, the transcription of 
 <italic>elovl5a</italic>, 
 <italic>elovl5b</italic> and 
 <italic>elovl2</italic> genes in the LC-HUFA synthesis pathway was not affected. Since 
 <italic>srebp1</italic> genes were up-regulated in 
 <italic>Δ6abc/5</italic>-mutated salmon the 
 <italic>elovl</italic> genes were not likely regulated by this transcription factor. Increased 
 <italic>de-novo</italic> fatty acid synthesis and lipogenesis was observed after 
 <italic>Δ6abc/5</italic>
 <sup>Mt</sup> and could also be regulated by SREBP1. In addition, the level of transcriptional changes of 
 <italic>fasn</italic> and 
 <italic>acc1</italic> genes involved in fatty acid synthesis were much higher when the fish was fed plant oil as compared to fish oil. This suggests that these genes were regulated by one or more transcriptional factors in addition to SREBP1. PPAR or SREBP2 are likely candidates. Increased fatty acid β-oxidation was also observed after 
 <italic>Δ6abc/5</italic>
 <sup>Mt</sup> and was likely regulated by PPAR. The CRISPR-mutation of 
 <italic>Δ6bc</italic>
 <sup>Mt</sup> genes surprisingly revealed over 3000 DEGs in liver of salmon, and the DEGs were not enriched in any lipid metabolism pathways. The reason for the high number of DEGs in 
 <italic>Δ6bc</italic>
 <sup>Mt</sup> salmon was unclear and needs to be further investigated.
</p>
