<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">L. plantarum</italic>, an intestinal bacteria, produces hydroxy fatty acids (i.e., 10-hydroxy-
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-12-octadecenoic acid [HYA], 10-hydroxy-
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-11-octadecenoic acid [HYC], 10-hydroxy-octadecanoic acid [HYB]) and oxo fatty acids (10-oxo-
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-12-octadecenoic acid [KetoA], 10-oxo-
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-11-octadecenoic acid [KetoC], 10-oxo-octadecanoic acid [KetoB]) as intermediate products of CLA production (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>). Recently, these metabolic intermediates have been shown to contribute to the regulation of host health and diseases. HYA is the first metabolite produced from linoleic acid by 
 <italic class="italic">L. plantarum</italic>, and it enhances intestinal barrier function and suppresses the development of DSS-induced colitis in mice in a GPR40-dependent manner (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>). Furthermore, HYA prevents 
 <italic class="italic">Helicobacter</italic> infections by blocking their futalosine pathways, which is an alternative menaquinone biosynthetic pathway and an essential metabolic pathway for the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Helicobacter</italic>. Moreover, HYA treatment suppresses the formation of lymphoid follicles in the gastric mucus layer after 
 <italic class="italic">H. suis</italic> infection, and therefore HYA treatment protects mice against the formation of gastric mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue lymphoma induced by infection with 
 <italic class="italic">Helicobacter</italic> (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>). HYA also ameliorates the pathological scores of atopic dermatitis in NC/Nga mice by decreasing plasma IgE levels and reducing mast cell infiltration into the skin (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>). KetoA enhances adiponectin production and glucose uptake in a proliferator-activated receptor γ (PPARγ)-dependent manner, and is effective for the prevention and amelioration of metabolic abnormalities associated with obesity (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>).
</p>
