<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The use of in vitro assays in veterinary parasitology, especially a series of tests for the evaluation of action against the main stages of a parasite (eggs, larvae and adults), is advantageous for the choice of substances to be tested in vivo [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. These assays are rapid, inexpensive and simple. They reduce the number of animals that are necessary for in vivo testing, and permit the combined and optimized assessment of a series of compounds for both the development of new drugs and the study of resistance to different anthelmintics. Within this context, different approaches have used this experimental strategy for the study of anthelmintic agents, including those against 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the development of new anthelmintic agents, it is important that the parasite species, and even its strain, be the most representative of the livestock in reality, especially when this type of economical activity faces different challenges [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Haemonchus contortus</span> strain, Embrapa 2010, is known to be resistant to the main classes of commercially available anthelmintic drugs, such as benzimidazoles, macrocyclic lactones and imidazothiazoles [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. In fact, this anthelmintic resistance profile is very similar to that found on sheep farms throughout Brazil, particularly in the State of São Paulo [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils consist of a mixture of volatile and lipophilic compounds with a strong and characteristic odor. Terpenes and terpenoids are their main chemical constituents. These compounds differ by the presence of an oxygen atom in terpenoids and a methyl radical in terpenes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. In view of the low solubility of essential oils in water, a tensoactive solution or solvent was used to increase the solubilization of these substances in the present experiments. Tween 80 at 3% (v/v) and at 2% (v/v) was used in the EHT and AWMT, respectively, while 1% DMSO (v/v) was used in the LDT because L1 larvae are more sensitive to Tween 80 than to DMSO [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. The negative and positive controls used in the different tests yielded the expected results, demonstrating appropriate standardization of the experimental protocol and, consequently, the reliability of the findings obtained (Tables 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human knowledge of essential oils originated in the pre-Christian era [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Anthelmintic properties, including against 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span>, have been described for a large number of essential oils such as those of 
  <span class="italic">Croton zehntneri</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Eucalyptus staigeriana</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Cymbopogon martinii</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Lippia sidoides</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> was more effective in the EHT than the oils of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span> and especially of 
  <span class="italic">A. nobile</span>. In fact, the IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of the 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> oil was about 2.0–2.5 times lower than that of the other two oils tested (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). In the LDT, the oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span> exhibited the best performance, with an IC
  <sub>50</sub> value that was about 2.5 and 6.5 times lower than those obtained for the oils of 
  <span class="italic">A. nobile</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span>, respectively, and was therefore the most potent against larval development (Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>). The variations in anthelmintic performance between the different tests and oils might be explained by qualitative and quantitative differences in the composition of the essential oils studied (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) and different sensitivity to the various developmental stages of 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span>. However, similar results were obtained in the AWMT for the oils tested, which did not permit a clear distinction of their pharmacological efficacy for this assay (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). Furthermore, regardless of the variations in absolute IC
  <sub>50</sub> values, all oils acted effectively and in a dose-dependent manner against the three developmental stages of 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span>, which is a relevant finding.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the chemical compounds shown in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, some of the volatile compounds identified are major constituents or are common in the different plant species studied. For example, limonene was identified as a major constituent in the oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span> (56.37%). Limonene is characteristic of species of the genus 
  <span class="italic">Citrus</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. However, although at low concentrations, limonene was also found in the oil of 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> (0.52%) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Myrcene was identified at low concentration in the oils of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Borneol, butyl acetate, camphene, 1,8-cineol and sabinene, also at low concentrations, can be found in both the oils of 
  <span class="italic">A. nobilis</span> and of 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Except for α-thujene, which occurs in the oils of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">A. nobilis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> at proportions of 2.85%, 8.82% and 0.31%, respectively, no other compound identified occurred simultaneously in the three types of oils studied (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>), a finding supporting the chemical diversity of the oils. In fact, the essential oils studied here are composed of a wide diversity of compounds that represent a vast repertoire of active biomolecules of biotechnological interest. This permits the theoretical establishment of a natural product library for structure-activity correlation studies that are important for current pharmacology [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linalool acetate and trans-sabinene hydrate are the major constituents of plants of the family Lamiaceae, especially in the genus 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. These were also the two main compounds identified in the oil of 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> (35.97% and 29.17%, respectively) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). In addition to limonene (see above), other compounds present in the oil of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span> should be mentioned, including γ-terpinene and β-pinene at proportions of 11.42% and 11.86%, respectively (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Two major constituents are present in the oil of 
  <span class="italic">A. nobilis</span>, isobutyl angelate (29.26%) and isoamyl angelate (15.27%) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). These compounds, which are major constituents of all three oils studied, might be the main substances responsible for the different anthelmintic activities observed in this study. However, we cannot rule out that different compounds act synergistically to establish the final pharmacological effect in each case, or that compounds present in small or trace amounts are involved in the anthelmintic effect observed. In the latter case, α-thujene was not a major constituent in any of the oils studied, but was found in all three of them, although at variable low proportions (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). This compound may represent a common functional link between the three different oils, all of them exhibiting anthelmintic activity.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the representative importance of major constituents of each oil studied, some of these compounds possess known anthelmintic properties, highlighting their potential importance in final anthelmintic activity. The evidence for the activity of such compounds can be direct or indirect, as observed for 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span>. For example, limonene is found in the oils of different plants with anthelmintic activity, such as 
  <span class="italic">Lippia sidoides</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cymbopogon martinii</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Eucalyptus staigeriana</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. This compound accounts for 96.0% of the composition of the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Citrus sinensis</span>, causing 100% inhibition of 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span> eggs and larvae in vitro at most concentrations tested [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Linalool acetate is known for its anthelmintic activity against 
  <span class="italic">Ascaris lumbricoides</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. Although not a major constituent of any of the oils, 1,8-cineole was present in both the oil of 
  <span class="italic">A. nobilis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span>. This compound is well known to be effective against the egg and larval stage of 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In view of the economic impacts of gastrointestinal infections on sheep farming, which are increasingly aggravated by anthelmintic resistance, the identification and development of new therapeutic options for prevention, control or eradication of this problem is essential [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. In this respect, there has been intensified search for botanical anthelmintics against 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span> because of the advantages of these agents, such as low cost and easy access, especially in less developed countries with biodiversity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. Since botanical anthelmintics may contain different compounds that act synergistically and throughout the life-cycle of the parasite, they may be less susceptible to pharmacological resistance, although this suggestion is controversial [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Finally, additional advantages are that botanical anthelmintics are generally well tolerated by animals from a toxicological point of view and appear to leave fewer residues in animal products such as meat and milk [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The application of ethnopharmacological/chemotaxonomic-based strategies is important to optimize studies of botanical anthelmintic agents in order to increase the success of developing new plant-derived or herbal agents of interest for the pharmaceutical-veterinary industry [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Although in vivo studies are still needed, the present work preliminarily validates the ethnopharmacological and chemotaxonomic data that indicate the use of 
  <span class="italic">C. aurantifolia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">A. nobile</span> and 
  <span class="italic">L. officinalis</span> as anthelmintics. This is the first study testing the essential oils of these plants against 
  <span class="italic">H. contortus</span>, highlighting their ethnopharmacological use and pharmaceutical-veterinary value.
 </p>
</sec>
