<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The concept of “nutraceutical” was first introduced in the survey study conducted in France, United Kingdom and Germany, where they found that rating of diet by the consumers was much higher compared to the other factors such as exercise or hereditary to achieve a good health [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. DeFelice was the first to introduce the word “nutraceutical” by coalescing the two words “nutrition” and “pharmaceutical” and define it as “food or a part of food which not only impart health benefits but also contributes in preventing or treating various diseases”. Moreover, in broad terms nutraceuticals can be summarized as bioactive components which play a vital role in human beings by maintaining their normal physiological functions and well-being [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Notably, nutraceuticals have been designed in such a way, that it could be useful for the betterment and maintenance of human health without causing any harm due to their natural occurrence [
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Nutraceuticals of plant, animal origin or live microorganisms offer great opportunities for food scientists and food industries to produce novel foods or food components for the future needs of human beings to stay healthy [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Nutraceuticals have been classified in various ways based upon their understanding and applications. Naturally available food sources are considered for their nutraceutical values. They can be characterized as antioxidants, dietary fibre, prebiotics, polyunsaturated fatty acids, probiotics, vitamins, polyphenols and spices [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The sudden rise in demand of nutraceutical products is mainly due to their therapeutic properties in various ailments such as the common cold, hypertension, heart disease, arthritis, dyslipidemia, diabetes, cancer, depression, inflammatory bowel disease, and increased life span by postponing aging, integrity of the body and support of smooth normal functioning. Therefore, nutraceuticals could play an important role in the improvement of health as well in chronic disease prevention [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Nutritionally potent 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> are considered a powerhouse of energy, because of their ability to revitalize several organ systems. Moreover, according to various scientific reports, the 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> active component cordycepin is considered very useful due to its potential application in various ailments (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-02735-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Several pharmaceutical as well as nutraceutical preparations made from 
 <italic>Cordyceps</italic> dry powder (
 <xref rid="molecules-25-02735-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) are marketed and reported to protect renal and hepatic functions, improve intracellular energy exchange, increases oxygenation and natural endurance, remove toxins from the body, control blood glucose level and lipid profile, delays the aging process, stimulates the natural metabolism of energy and nourishes the body’s immune system [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-25-02735" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
</p>
