<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The fact that some sessile marine invertebrates such as corals are capable of maintaining their body surface free of fouling inspires researchers to suspect that these invertebrates might adopt a chemical defense strategy by secreting secondary metabolites as potent antifouling agents. Indeed, during past years a lot of antifouling metabolites have been identified from varieties of sessile marine invertebrates [
 <xref rid="B11-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. As part of our continuous searching for environmentally beneficial antifouling compounds from marine resources, the gorgonian coral 
 <italic class="italic">S. suberosa</italic> has been systematically investigated, resulting in the isolation of many antifouling compounds involving one novel butenolide [
 <xref rid="B18-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] and two unusual cholestane derivatives [
 <xref rid="B19-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. This current study reports the isolation and structure-activity relationship of subergorgic acid (SA) from 
 <italic class="italic">S. suberosa</italic> and the synthesis of its derivatives as antifouling agents. SA was first isolated by Long et al. from the gorgonian coral 
 <italic class="italic">S. suberosa</italic>, whose structure has been established as an unusual tricyclic sesquiterpene (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="marinedrugs-17-00101-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B20-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Interestingly, our biological test indicated SA exhibited a significantly non-toxic inhibitory effect against the settlement of 
 <italic class="italic">B. amphitrite</italic> with EC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> being 1.25 ± 0.14 μg/mL and LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> &gt; 25 μg/mL, which is consistent with data (EC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> 1.2 μg/mL, LC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> &gt; 200 μg/mL) reported by Qi et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-17-00101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. In addition to its excellent antifouling effect, there was a huge amount of SA present in the gorgonian coral 
 <italic class="italic">S. suberosa</italic>, strongly prompting our research interest in SA. Thus, the structure-activity relationship of SA as a potent antifouling compound was studied to identify the bioactive functional groups, followed by the design and synthesis of SA derivatives.
</p>
