<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>This study updated the potential distribution of the Asian tiger mosquito 
   <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> in México and provided estimates to model uncertainty. We also assessed the potential distribution of natural 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in México to map areas with circulation potential of 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic>. The distribution of 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> covered the states across Northern México, the Gulf of México, the Pacific Coast of México, Central México, and the southeast of México. The ecological niche model of the 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections anticipated its occurrence in the southeast of México, the Chiapas border with Guatemala, and Veracruz. While these results can prioritize vector surveillance and control programs for decision-makers, it is still necessary to establish active surveillance programs to validate the ecological niche of natural 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> populations in México.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>The Asian tiger mosquito 
   <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> is currently the most invasive vector species, with a widespread global distribution. 
   <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> is the potential vector of diverse arboviruses, including Zika and dengue. This study updated the ecological niche model of 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> and inferred the potential distribution of natural 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in México. The ecological niche models were constructed based on diverse model settings to better estimate the potential distributions and uncertainty indices of both 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> and its natural 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in México. The distribution of 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> covered the states across Northern México, the Gulf of México, the Pacific Coast of México, Central México, and the southeast of México. The ecological niche model of the natural 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> populations anticipated the occurrence of natural 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in the southeast of México, the Chiapas border with Guatemala, and Veracruz. These results can be used to prioritize vector surveillance and control programs in México for strategic and future decision-making; however, it is still necessary to establish active surveillance programs to assess model predictions based on the independent sampling of 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> from different invasion zones in México. Finally, vector surveillance should also screen the natural 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infections in 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> to validate 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> predictions across México, particularly in the southeast of México.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
