<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many researchers have already studied larvicidal potentials of plant derived compounds, extracts and essential oils against various insects, with the aim of finding active phyto-chemicals to replace synthetic insecticides. High cost of various commercial insecticides beside their food and environmental safety concerns, toxicity problems and increasing resistance rates have made their utilization undesirable (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>). Anti-larval activity of essential oil from a wild grown 
 <italic class="italic">B. persicum</italic> against 
 <italic class="italic">An. stephensi</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Culex pipiens</italic> has been previously reported with LC 
 <sub class="sub"> 50 </sub> values of 27.72 and 20.61ppm respectively (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>). According to the results of our study, the essential oil, methanol total extract and petroleum ether fraction of both wild and cultivated samples had significant larvicidal activity against late third and early fourth instar larvae of 
 <italic class="italic">An. stephensi</italic>. The larvicidal potential of γ-terpinene, cuminaldehyde and ρ-cymene, main constituents of both wild and cultivated type 
 <italic class="italic">B. persicum</italic> fruits, against various insect larvae has been previously proved in several experiments. γ-Terpinene has shown potent larvicidal activity with LC 
 <sub class="sub"> 50 </sub> value of 29.21 ppm against 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles anthropophagus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>) and 30.7 and 29.8ppm against 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes albopictus</italic> respectively (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>). Zahran and Abdelgaleil (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>) documented toxicity of cumin aldehyde on 
 <italic class="italic">Culex pipiens</italic> larvae, which was more stronger than other tested monoterpenes in that experiment, with LC 
 <sub class="sub"> 50 </sub> values of 38.9 and 21.4ppm for 24 and 48h exposures respectively. Anti-larval potential of ρ-cymene, the other main constituent, towards 
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopticus</italic> has also been demonstrated (LC 
 <sub class="sub"> 50 </sub> = 19.2 and 46.7ppm) (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>). Higher lethal effect of the petroleum ether fraction in comparison to the methanol fraction, suggests higher potency of non-polar components than polar phenolics towards 
 <italic class="italic">An. stephensi</italic> larvae. LC 
 <sub class="sub"> 50 </sub> value of 85.9933 and 62.7814ppm for petroleum ether fraction from wild and cultivated types makes it suitable choice for further studies to isolate the active principles. Anti-larval activity of efficient samples from cultivated type was comparable to those from wild grown, so it can be concluded that cultivation of 
 <italic class="italic">B. persicum</italic> has not affected chemical constituents’ biosynthesis or concentration, which are responsible for larvicidal activity of the fruit.
</p>
