<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This is the first time that these thirty-seven EOs extracted from Vietnamese plants were described for anti-trypanosomal activity in vitro. Some of these EOs were already reported to be tested on the same model, such as 
 <italic class="italic">D. ambrosioides</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">M. alternifolia</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">O. gratissimum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], but they were extracted from plants collected in other countries with possibly different compositions. Based on a preliminary screening, half of them showed a potential activity on 
 <italic class="italic">Tbb</italic> with less than 3% of viable parasites at 25 nL/mL (or 10 nL/mL for four of them). Within these nineteen EOs, the one extracted from 
 <italic class="italic">C. cassia</italic> revealed the strongest effect (IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 1.77 ± 0.15 nL/mL), 17 EOs showed moderate activity with IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values between 2–20 nL/mL, and one EO extracted from 
 <italic class="italic">P. indica</italic> showed less interesting activity with an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 21.29 ± 1.38 nL/mL. In order to identify the most selective EOs, the cytotoxicity on two different mammalian cell lines, WI38 and J774, was evaluated in parallel. Four samples extracted from 
 <italic class="italic">C. longa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. zedoaria</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">L. cubeba</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Z. officinale</italic> displayed SI from 14 to &gt; 19 (WI38) and 11 to &gt; 19 (J774). GC analyses led to the identification of more than 85% of their components. We observed the predominance of sesquiterpenes in EOs extracted from rhizomes of the three Zingiberaceae species (
 <italic class="italic">C. longa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. zedoaria</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Z. officinale</italic>) while monoterpenes were the major compounds in the EO extracted from fruits of a Lauraceae species (
 <italic class="italic">L. cubeba</italic>).
</p>
