<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As mentioned before, it is very important to emphasize the composition complexity of EOs, making it difficult to identify active compounds [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Indeed, in these mixtures, most components were found in low percentages, while two or three accounted for 20%–70% of the whole oil [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Major compounds can be studied easier and are often considered as responsible for EO biological activities. However other constituents could of course contribute to the activity through a higher efficacy, additional and/or synergistic activity [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. For example, eucalyptol, which was characterized as the major component (accounts from 27% to 55%) in four of our tested EOs: 
 <italic class="italic">A. aromaticum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">E. blanda</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">H. coronarium</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">L. cubeba</italic> (leaves) (data not shown), was not effective on 
 <italic class="italic">Tbb</italic> as shown by its high IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value (83.15 µg/mL) [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. However these EOs showed a moderate effect in this study with IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> values in the range of 8–16 nL/mL. On the contrary, antagonistic effects may also occur between constituents of these mixtures [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. An interesting example is terpinolene, which accounts for 55% of our 
 <italic class="italic">C. indica</italic> EO (data not shown). This compound was shown to have a very strong activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Tbb</italic> bloodstream form (IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> = 0.035 ± 0.05 μg/mL or 0.041 nL/mL) [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-24-01158" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>], however the IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of our 
 <italic class="italic">C. indica</italic> EO was 330 times higher (13.22 ± 4.54 nL/mL). The difference in the experiment design could also be another explanation.
</p>
