<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Allergic rhinitis (AR) is one of the common allergic diseases affecting 30% of the world population (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Tohidinik et al., 2019</xref>). It is also known as hay fever, typically causes symptoms of runny nose, clear nasal discharge, sneezing nasal pruritus and airflow obstruction caused by immunoglobulin E (IgE)-mediated reactions. AR is triggered by potential allergens and involves mucosal inflammation driven by type 2 helper T (Th2) cells (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Wheatley and Togias, 2015</xref>). AR is one of the types of allergy that manifest an abnormal regulation of the immune system. Epidemiological studies have revealed that the prevalence of AR has increased progressively in more developed countries, and currently affects 10–40% of adults and 2–25% of children (
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Zhang, 2019</xref>). It is one of the common types of allergic condition which might not appear to be serious as it is not associated with severe morbidity and mortality but affects the quality of life. The allergic disease may also substantially cause an economic burden to the patient due to inadequate management of the allergic disease (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Zuberbier et al., 2014</xref>). Thus, the needs on medication and alternative therapy to alleviate the symptoms are very crucial. There are some diseases particularly allergic reactions that have been found to be associated with AR. The prevalence of AR has shown an increasing pattern in a similar fashion to that of asthma (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Asher et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Tohidinik et al., 2019</xref>). It was found that eczema in infancy might have a causal effect on AR in children with and perhaps without asthma (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Hopper et al., 2012</xref>). There is a close epidemiologic relationship of allergic conjunctivitis with AR (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Bielory, 2010</xref>). Genetic factor might be one of the etiologies of AR as a study has shown that having a parent with AR may double the risk (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Westman et al., 2013</xref>). Seeing that it might be leading to development of other diseases, this health issue requires great involvement of patients and healthcare professionals.
</p>
