<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The search strategy employed in this review includes internationally accepted databases, namely, ScienceDirect, Scopus, Web of Science, and PubMed, using specific keywords of both whole plant products and plant extracts, pain, and analgesic and antinociceptive effects. For investigation, a combination of keywords was used [pain; analgesic; antinociceptive; plant extract] + [
 <italic class="italic">Betonica officinalis</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Glechoma hederacea</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Hyptis pectinata</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Lavandula</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Leonurus cardiaca</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Lamium</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Melissa officinalis</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Marrubium vulgare</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Ocimum</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia</italic>;
 <italic class="italic">Satureja hortensis</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Stachys lavandulifolia</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Scutellaria lateriflora</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Sideritis</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Teucrium</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus</italic>; 
 <italic class="italic">Ziziphora tenuior</italic>] + [Lamiaceae; botanical genus]. Case reports, case studies, 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> relevant studies, and comparative studies were included in this search strategy. Additionally, text books and potentially relevant reviews were explored and included in the reference list. The literature search was confined to the period between 2003 and December 2017. Several articles before 2000 were also included in order to point out the universal interest in natural products with potential applicability in therapy. The dynamic character of the field is reflected in the number of recent publications. For example, a search with the keywords “Lamiaceae family and pain” in ScienceDirect yields 152 titles in 2015, 111 in 2016, and 129 in 2017, and 23 papers will be published in the first months of the next year (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>).
</p>
