<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">During early stages of growth and development, more than 40% of the mesocarp weight is composed of sugars. Sugars continue to increase and accompany the rapid fruit growth period and then start to decline concomitant with oil accumulation (
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kilaru et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al. (2002)</xref> reported high total sugar concentrations (up to 44%, 40 and 22% of total dry weight) in the flesh, seed, and peel of 
 <italic class="italic">Persea americana</italic> cv. Hass after 2 months of fruit set. Five different soluble sugars were followed during growth and development: sucrose, fructose, glucose, mannoheptulose, and perseitol. These five sugars constituted 98% of the total soluble sugar content of the fruit (
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2002</xref>). In general, sucrose levels were low in all tissues (seed, peel, and flesh) and did not fluctuate much. For very young fruitlets the predominant sugars in seeds, peel and flesh of avocado corresponded to glucose, fructose, D-mannoheptulose, and perseitol but as fruit rapid expansion phase culminated then decreased levels of fructose and glucose were reported (
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2002</xref>). In general, the most abundant sugars in avocado corresponded to C
 <sub class="sub">7</sub> sugars (mannoheptulose and perseitol). During early stages of growth, mannoheptulose corresponded to 12, 19, and 12% of the total soluble sugars in the peel, flesh, and seed, respectively, and perseitol corresponded to 9, 15, and 10% of the total soluble sugars in the peel, flesh and seed, respectively (
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2002</xref>). Once, surpassed the rapid expansion phase, then mannoheptulose concentrations decreased in seed and flesh but still remained high in the peel (
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2002</xref>). However, 
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cowan (2004)</xref> reported higher contents of mannoheptulose in avocado cv. Hass mesocarp from 2 months after fruit set on (210 days after fruit set, 78 mg g
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) and the contents of perseitol remained stable during early stages of growth and during development (around 55 mg g
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). Perseitol instead decreased in the peel and flesh. Legal minimum maturity for Hass avocado in California corresponds to 20.8% (dry matter content) and as fruit matured, D-mannoheptulose decreased but perseitol varied very little. For starch, the peel and flesh of avocado accumulated very little content of starch and did not vary during early stages of development. Instead, for early stages of development the seed accumulated low amounts of starch (&lt;1%) but as it started to increase its weight, starch content in the seed corresponded to 30% of its dry weight (
 <xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2002</xref>). Cessation of sugar accumulation coincides with oil accumulation. 
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kilaru et al. (2015)</xref> state that the carbon available for oil biosynthesis in avocado fruit seems atypical. High expression of different genes associated with glycolysis as potential source of pyruvate for fatty acid synthesis was reported by 
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kilaru et al. (2015)</xref>.
</p>
