<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lignin can improve the properties of protein-lignin bioplastics in high percentages, which may hold promising application as a replacement of protein. Chantapet et al. (2012) evaluated the function of KL on the properties of new resulting bioplastics and on the extrusion process. Wheat gluten (WG) was extruded with KL in a corotating twin screw extruder with circular die. The processability of WG in extrusion was enhanced by the KL with 10–50 wt % contents: both residence time and die pressure for all mentioned screw speeds and feed rates were decreased. The introduction of 10–30 wt % KL reduced elongation at break and water absorption of KL/WG materials, and enhanced Young’s modulus and tensile strength [
 <xref rid="B98-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>]. Fish protein-reinforced bioplastics were explored to investigate the effect of KL on protein rheological and functional properties and aggregation. Fish protein powder was blended with 0–70% KL and 30% glycerol. Compression molding was used to develop the bioplastics. Solubility of protein increased in the presence of KL in sodium dodecyl sulfate buffer, which indicated that the molecular weight of the protein decreased. Mechanical properties increased with the introduction of KL, while KL addition caused a decrease of water absorption and storage modulus of the bioplastics. A capillary rheometer revealed that the viscosity also decreased at experimental temperature [
 <xref rid="B94-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>]. A variety of bioplastics from lignosulfonates and soy protein isolate with a weight ratio of 4:6 to 10:0 were fabricated through compression molding. The outcomes reported that the content of lignosulfonate from 30 to 40 parts could significantly improve Young’s modulus, tensile strength and elongation at break. Water uptake analysis of the bioplastics suggested that the effect of water on the swelling and the damage of the bioplastics was restricted by the intense interaction between soy protein isolate and lignosulfonates. The improved properties were attributed mainly to the formation of crosslinked structures between lignosulfonates and soy protein and the occurrence of the beneficial microphase separation [
 <xref rid="B93-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>].
</p>
