<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Using an 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> approach based on isothermal microcalorimetry in conjunction with Illumina Miseq sequencing of the faecal microbiota and metabolite profiling, Adamberg et al. [
 <xref rid="B379-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">379</xref>] compared the impact of different oligo- and polysaccharides (galacto- and fructooligosaccharides, resistant starch, levan, inulin, arabinogalactan, xylan, pectin and chitin), as well as a glycoprotein mucin, representing an indigenous substrate, on the growth and metabolism of the faecal microbiota. Apart from chitin, more than 70% of all substrates were fermented by the faecal microbiota with total heat generation up to 8 J/mL. Overall, the different fibre types supported the growth of specific microbiota and different metabolic routes. Arabinogalactan stimulated the growth of several health-promoting genera, including 
 <italic class="italic">Bifidobacterium, Bacteroides, Coprococcus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Lachnoclostridium</italic>. Propionic acid was enhanced by arabinogalactin, xylan and mucin but not by galacto-, fructooligosaccharides or inulin. Fermentation of mucin resulted in the generation of acetate, propionate and the highest amount of butyrate and supported the growth of species from the following genera, 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium, Lachnoclostridium</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Parabacteroides</italic>. The authors suggest that only a diverse spectrum of glycans in the diet can contribute to a diverse microbiota. Chung et al. [
 <xref rid="B380-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">380</xref>] determined the impact of growth substrate complexity and multiplicity on species diversity of the human colonic microbiota 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> whereby anaerobic fermenters were supplied continuously with single carbohydrates (arabinoxylanoligosaccharide, pectin or inulin), or with a mix of all three, or a mix of all three plus resistant starch, β-glucan and galacto-mannon as energy sources. Over the first six days, inulin supported less microbial diversity than the other single carbohydrates, the mix of three, or the mix of six carbohydrates. While the communities did not differ substantially at phylum and family levels, marked differences were observed at species level. The overall results strongly suggest that strategies to increase microbial diversity should employ complex nondigestible substrates mixtures. 
</p>
