<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Few studies have investigated the impact of high sugar containing diets on the microbiota. However, recently, Sen et al. [
 <xref rid="B381-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">381</xref>] investigated the impact of high fat/high sugar (sucrose), low fat/high sugar and low fat/low sugar diets on Sprague-Dawley rats. As expected, both the high fat/high sugar and low fat/high sugar diets for four weeks caused significant increases in body weight and body fat compared to the low fat/low sugar diet. The high sugar and high fat diets resulted in gut microbiota dysbiosis which was characterised by an overall decrease in microbial diversity, a bloom in clostridia and bacilli and a marked decrease in 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> species. There was also an increase in the Firmicutes: Bacteriodetes ratio. Specifically, the low fat/high sugar diet caused an increase in two 
 <italic class="italic">Proteobacteria</italic> members, namely 
 <italic class="italic">Sutterella</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bilophila</italic>. The high sugar diet also induced gut inflammation and triggered a remodelling of the gut brain axis [
 <xref rid="B381-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">381</xref>]. In mice, a high sugar (sucrose) diet increased Clostridiales belonging to the Firmicutes phylum which was also observed for the high fat diet [
 <xref rid="B382-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">382</xref>]. The high sugar diet also caused a decrease in the order Bacteroidales which belongs to Bacteroidetes. Lactobacillales was also significantly increased on the high sugar diet. Thus, overall the high sugar diet altered more bacterial orders and genera than the high fat diet. The increase in Clostridiales and decrease in Bacteroidales on the high sugar diet was related to poor cognitive flexibility. Di Luccia et al. [
 <xref rid="B383-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">383</xref>] reported that a high fructose diet induced markers of metabolic syndrome, inflammation and oxidative stress in rats, but these were significantly reduced when the animals were treated with antibiotics or faecal samples from control rats fed a standard diet. Since the number of members from the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Coprococcus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus</italic> were increased by the high fructose diet but reduced by antibiotics and faecal transplant, the results suggest a correlation between their abundance and metabolic syndrome.
</p>
