<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">
   <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> sp. represent the most common cause of fungal infections worldwide. In the present work, we have evaluated the activity of an essential oil extracted from pistachio hulls against a number of standard and clinical strains of 
   <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> sp.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">
   <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> ATCC 64550, 
   <italic class="italic">C. parapsilosis</italic> ATCC 22019, 4 clinical strains of 
   <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>, 3 clinical strains of 
   <italic class="italic">C. parapsilosis</italic> and 3 clinical strains of 
   <italic class="italic">C. glabrata</italic> were used. All clinical isolates were identified by species-specific PCR-based methods. Susceptibility studies were performed using pistachio hull essential oil alone or in combination with antifungal compounds. The interactions between pistachio hull essential oil and selected antifungal compounds were also evaluated using the checkerboard method and the mechanisms of interaction investigated by droplet size distribution.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">Pistachio hull essential oil was fungicidal at the concentrations between 2.50 and 5.0 mg/ml. D-limonene and 3-Carene were the components with major activity. An antagonistic effect was observed with all combinations tested.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">The antifungal activity of pistachio hull essential oil could be used to help control resistance in 
   <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> species. More studies need to be performed to elucidate the mechanisms responsible for the activity of pistachio hull essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
