<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Most volatile compounds present in VOO are six straight-chain carbons (C6) aldehydes and alcohols, and their corresponding esters, produced by enzymes of the lipoxygenase (LOX) pathway (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Olías et al., 1993</xref>). The action of these enzymes on polyunsaturated fatty acids, such as linoleic (LA) and, especially, linolenic (LnA) acids is part of the general LOX pathway in plants that is involved in stress-induced defense responses against abiotic and biotic stresses. Biotic stress due to pathogen attack has been shown to result in the emission of these volatile compounds (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Heiden et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prost et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kishimoto et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Piesik et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rani et al., 2017</xref>), and their antimicrobial activity has been found to vary among compounds (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nakamura and Hatanaka, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prost et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shiojiri et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yi et al., 2009</xref>). Compounds with five straight chain carbons (C5), which are, similarly, synthesized through the LOX pathway, also affect the aroma of olive oil (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Angerosa et al., 2000</xref>). The contribution of volatile compounds to VOO aroma depends on the ratio of their concentration to odor threshold, where the ratio is the odor activity value (OAV) of the volatile compound (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Grosch, 1994</xref>); theoretically, the compound will only contribute to the aroma of the oil when its OAV is greater than one.
</p>
