<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>EOs are liquid mixtures of volatile components produced by aromatic plant secondary metabolism. The main components are monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes and, to a lesser extent, aromatic and aliphatic compounds, therefore, the complex mixtures of compounds usually include terpenoids, alcohols, ethers, esters, ketones, and aldehydes in variable concentrations, and can be obtained by over 60 families of plants [
 <xref rid="B34-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Concentration variability leads to significant heterogeneity in the products used in different studies and makes a comparison among results difficult [
 <xref rid="B35-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Generally, EOs contain about 20–60 components up to more than 100 single substances, at quite different concentrations. Usually, two or three are the major components at high concentrations (20–70%) compared to other components present in trace amounts [
 <xref rid="B6-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. EOs show characteristic physical properties (e.g., color and solubility in water) that can represent some criteria for the classification and qualification to different groups [
 <xref rid="B36-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The use of EOs is limited due to the following drawbacks: hydrophobicity (and, consequently, insolubility in water); instability (caused by hydrolysis and oxidation); high volatility [
 <xref rid="B37-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Therefore, nowadays the researchers’ efforts are focused on the possibility to use innovative formulation for the EO encapsulation. However, the therapeutic application of EOs as pure compounds was studied, mainly for external applications (mouthwashes or inhalation), since it is generally safe, except for some skin reactions and UV sensitivity (the exposure to sunlight could cause irritation or darkening of the skin). It is important to not exceed in the amount of the administered dose of EO and to avoid their application on broken skin, which would induce the occurrence of significant systemic absorption and, therefore, serious side effects. The administration of EOs by inhalation is the most rapid way (followed by the topic one). The use of strong oils (for direct inhalation or for diffusing) is not recommended because they may cause eye irritation. EOs oral administration is rare, even if it is considered safe, and the EOs are generally diluted in olive oil or milk.
</p>
