<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous indications suggest food-derived bioactive peptides can regulate the body’s physiological functions. These food-derived peptides have been demonstrated to exert potential health benefits to humans and thus serve as functional foods. In relation to this, soy proteins isolated from soybeans (
 <italic>Glycine max</italic> L.) were demonstrated to have ACE2 inhibitory properties (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In the first ACE2 inhibitory study using food products, 
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Takahashi et al. (2015)</xref> demonstrated the ACE2 inhibitory activity of soybean (
 <italic>Glycine max</italic> L.) and its isolated bioactive protein. In their study, the bioactive protein, nicotianamine, intensely inhibited the ACE2 activity at 84 nM concentration. Similarly, bioactive peptides from rapeseed, Leu-Tyr (LY), Arg-Ala-Leu-Pro (RALP) and Gly His-Ser (GHS), have been shown to modulate the ACE2 activity in spontaneously hypertensive rats (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2019</xref>). In this study, ACE2 expression markedly increased following oral administration of the peptides (30 mg/kg) both at the gene and protein levels. A related study had also demonstrated that administration of bioactive peptides (10 mg/kg/day) from blue-green algae, 
 <italic>Spirulina platensis (Arthrospira platensis)</italic>, upregulates the expression of ACE2 in spontaneously hypertensive rats (
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2017</xref>). The fact that these specific peptides modulate ACE2 expression and subsequent activity hints to their bioactivity. However, the pharmacokinetics and mechanisms behind these physiological effects remain largely unknown and may require extensive investigations before becoming practically applicable. Additionally, food components interact with peptides in different ways that may affect the availability of peptides within the matrix (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Chakrabarti et al., 2018</xref>). As such, to recommend foods rich in ACE2 modulatory peptides, further research is needed to determine the release, stability and mechanisms of bioactive peptides following normal digestion. Furthermore, hydrolysates from pre-digestion when subjected to normal digestion may produce different peptide sets (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Chakrabarti et al., 2018</xref>). In this case, investigations are needed to demonstrate if the identified physiological effects are abolished, unabolished or changed.
</p>
