<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the appearance of the first cases, reported in December 2019 in Wuhan, China, the new pandemic disease Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has claimed millions of victims and caused hundreds of deaths around the world. Forthwith, Chinese teams sequenced SARS-CoV-2
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> and its important nonstructural proteins (nsp) were revealed, which included spike protein, 3-chymotrypsin-like cysteine protease (3CLpro), also named main protease (Mpro), papain-like protease (PLpro), and RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp).
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> The spike protein binds the virus to the human receptor - a metallopeptidase named angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), while the 3CLpro and the PLpro provide components for packaging new virions from large viral polyproteins translated on host ribosome, and finally the RdRp replicate the SARS-CoV-2 RNA genome.
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> Due to their importance in the viral replication stages, 3CLpro and RdRp have been highlighted as fundamental targets in computational strategies, such as molecular docking.
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> Nowadays, molecular docking represents a powerful, rational and low-cost tool, which allows understanding how these important nsps interacts with ligands at the active site, thus supporting the design and screening of new antiviral agents against COVID-19.
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> Regarding the ligands, drugs used against other human diseases and natural products present in medicinal plants, such as flavonoids, have been the main candidates in virtual screening approaches.
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> On the other hand, since many people have almost none access to medicines, including indigenous tribes and riverside dwellers in Amazon, medicinal plants could be the only possibility of treatment. Thus, the study of these therapeutic plants is a matter of human solidarity and can play an important role in saving lives. 
 <italic>Dysphania ambrosioides</italic> (L.) Mosyakin &amp; Clemants (Syn. 
 <italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L.) is one medicinal plants commonly found in tropical and subtropical regions and, therefore, accessible as therapeutic agents. 
 <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic> is popularly known in Brazil as “mastruz” or “Erva-de-Santa-Maria” and has been used to treat a number of health problems, such as infections, sinusitis, gastritis, inflammations, and flu.
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> From the phytochemical viewpoint, this species is a promising source of flavonoid glycosides, such as rutin, nicotiflorin, and other quercetin and kaempferol derivatives.
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> These flavonoids present great biological potential, including antioxidant and antiviral activities, and some are mentioned as potential substances against Covid-19.
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> Since 
 <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic> and several other flavonoid-producing sources are used worldwide, the absorption, metabolism, and pharmacokinetics of flavonoids have been intensively investigated, and glucuronide and sulfates can be highlighted as important metabolite products in this process.
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Thus, in the present study, we screened rutin and nicotiflorin, two of the most abundant flavonoid glycosides from 
 <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic>, along with some of their putative derivatives in the human organism using molecular docking, in order to test them as potential inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp.
</p>
