<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our study, the attraction of adults to lures, at least immediately after overwintering, was confirmed by both trap captures and plant sampling. Kirkpartick et al. [
 <xref rid="B26-insects-11-00866" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] estimated the plume reach for pheromone-baited sticky traps to be approximately 3 m. Indeed, all the sampled host plant species hosted higher numbers of 
 <italic>H. halys</italic> when they were located in proximity of a pheromone-baited trap (less than 5 m). This corroborates that the pheromone affects foraging behavior, potentially increasing the overall acceptability of the host plant resource or reducing 
 <italic>H. halys</italic> dispersal from them [
 <xref rid="B26-insects-11-00866" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-insects-11-00866" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Moreover, commercial pheromone lures seemed to be effective immediately following their placement in the field, from early/mid-April. The early attractiveness to overwintered adults was previously investigated in other studies with contrasting results [
 <xref rid="B19-insects-11-00866" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-insects-11-00866" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-insects-11-00866" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Such attractiveness might have important implications in early season management of 
 <italic>H. halys</italic>, by placing the lure on a favorite host plant. The effectiveness of pheromones for the initial attraction of dispersed adults could be coupled with the retention time given by the plant, in order to apply targeted management strategies. For example, attract-and-kill strategy requires the target pest to be attracted and retained in a spatially limited location by using a high dosage of pheromones in combination with a host plant, where it can be controlled to successfully preserve the main crop [
 <xref rid="B27-insects-11-00866" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Our results suggest, for instance, a list of favorite host plants, such as common ash, peach, poplar, and walnut, to be used for such an early season management.
</p>
