<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In terms of physical properties, EOs are volatile compounds which can easily evaporate and/or decompose even at room temperature due to very low boiling point and direct exposure to light or oxygen, respectively (
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>). Furthermore, conventional formulations of EOs can oftentimes cause skin irritation and sensitization. Several approaches including the application of vesicular systems such as niosomes (
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>) have been developed to resolve these problems. Niosomes are non-ionic surfactants and have been used in drug (
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>) or gene delivery (
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>). In drug delivery, niosomes are capable of increasing skin penetration and acting as a local depot to provide sustained release of topically applied drugs in the dermis. Due to properties such as biodegradability, non-toxicity, non-immunogenicity, low cost, and superior chemical and storage stabilities, niosomes offer several advantages over other vesicular systems (
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). EOs’ entrapment in the hydrophobic region of niosomes can improve their permeability and stability features, consequently reducing skin irritation properties of EOs (
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>). Niosomal formulations can improve the stratum corneum functions by attenuating water loss from trans-epidermal skin and increasing skin smoothness by replacing its lost lipids. Furthermore, the residence time of drug in the stratum corneum and epidermis increases and its systemic absorption decreases following application of niosomal systems (
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>). It was previously shown by Manosroi, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. that niosomal encapsulation of 
 <italic class="italic">Mimusops elengi</italic> flower extract reduced extract cytotoxicity on human skin fibroblast and also enhanced its physical stability (
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>).
</p>
