<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are many conventional methods for oil/water separation such as skimming, centrifugation, air floatation, applying an electric field, ultrasonic method, and biological treatments. However, the chances of secondary pollution and the high cost of these methods limit their efficient utilization [
 <xref rid="B8-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Polymer membranes claim good flexibility, processability, and are most probably used in manipulating superhydrophobic membranes [
 <xref rid="B9-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Experimental techniques of phase separation, chemical etching, vapor deposition, sol-gel process, and electrospinning fabricate porous superhydrophobic/superoleophilic polymer-based membranes [
 <xref rid="B10-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Out of all these processing methods, the technique of electrospinning is versatile and efficient in manufacturing nanofibrous membranes with superior structure and composition [
 <xref rid="B11-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The electrospun membranes possess good porosity, large surface area, and fine flexibility that leads to high permeate flux when the oil/water separation is complete [
 <xref rid="B14-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Reports reveal the fabrication of electrospun superhydrophobic membranes from polyurethanes, polyvinyl chloride, polysulfones, polystyrene (PS), cellulose acetate etc. [
 <xref rid="B15-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. The superhydrophobic nature of a particular membrane often depends on the roughness of the surface and on low surface energy [
 <xref rid="B20-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], and is often achieved by proper surface treatments. The surface roughness also increases with the incorporation of nanoparticles, which leads to the formation of polymer nanocomposite membranes. Among the nanomaterials, CNT is widely applied in fabricating oil/water separating membranes due to their outstanding properties such as low density, good mechanical strength, hydrophobicity and high porosity [
 <xref rid="B22-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-materials-12-00709" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. 
</p>
