<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On cumulative analysis of all the results, it could be inferred that 
 <italic>Tellimagrandin-II</italic> and 
 <italic>O-Demethyldemethoxycurcumin</italic>, were highly potential hits, as these compounds feature significant interactions with ACE2 binding region coupled with key glycosylation site (ASN343) of spike protein. Recent mutagenesis studies strongly suggest that the targeting ASN343 glycosylation to be the most potential inhibitory mode. Moreover, the infectivity of SARS-CoV-2 showed reduction to almost 1,200-folds when both ASN331 and ASN343 were mutated in spike protein. This shows the significance of blocking these glycosylation sites on the receptor binding domain (
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>). Viral glycosylation holds a major role in pathogenesis, as it mediates protein folding, shaping viral tropism, and host invasion (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>). Blocking of glycosylation not only aids in preventing viral pathogenesis, but also facilitates immune recognition of the virus (
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>). Based on the number of intermolecular interactions with active residues, glycosylation sites, and proximal residues to active site, Tellimagrandin-II with a binding energy of −8.2 kcal/mol from 
 <italic>S. aromaticum</italic> may have a higher affinity toward the spike protein in comparison with all other compounds. Moreover, it also formed a stable complex, as inferred by molecular dynamics simulation. The hydrolysable tannin Tellimagrandin-II is traditionally known to possess antiviral activity; while hydrolysable tannins as a whole class are well-known antiviral agents (
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>). Tannins are known to inhibit various viral activities like attachment and penetration of virus and inhibition of reverse transcriptase (
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>). Tellimagrandin-II is the first polyphenolic ellagitannin formed from 1,2,3,4,6-pentagalloyl-glucose, and is an isomer of punicafolin or nupharin A, also known as Cornustannin 2 or Eugeniin (C
 <sub>41</sub>H
 <sub>30</sub>O
 <sub>26</sub>; Molecular Mass 93,866 g/mol). The compound is isolated from the dried flower bud of 
 <italic>S. aromaticum</italic> (Clove). Earlier studies showed that ethanol extract of 
 <italic>S. aromaticum</italic> to possess strong inhibition of recombinant NS2BNS3 proteases of DENV-2 and 3; while its bioactivity guided fractionation yielded eugeniin (
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>), isobiflorin (5,7-dihydroxy-2-methylchromone-8C-β-d-glucopyranoside), and biflorin (5,7-dihydroxy-2-methylchromone-6C-β-d-glucopyranoside). Interestingly the eugeniin from 
 <italic>S. aromaticum</italic> and 
 <italic>Geum japonicum</italic> is found to inhibit α-glucosidase and possess significant antiviral activity against wild-type HSV-1 and HSV-2. Moreover, eugeniin also targets thymidine-kinase deficient or acyclovir as well as phosphonoacetic acid (PAA)-resistant HSV-1 at EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 5.0 μg/ml, with CC
 <sub>50</sub> of 69.5 μg/ml (
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>). Unlike nucleoside analogs, Eugeniin is reported to inhibit viral DNA polymerase and late protein syntheses in HSV-infected Vero cells, in a non-competitive manner with respect to dTTP (
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>). Animal studies revealed that Eugeniin at 0.3 mg/kg at oral and intraperitoneal dose retard the development of skin lesions of HSV-1-infected mice; while at 6 or 50 mg/kg it significantly prolonged the mean survival times and or reduced mortality without toxicity. However, at an oral dose of 50 mg/kg it reduced virus yields in the skin and brain of infected mice with higher bioavailability. Moreover, Eugeniin enhance the anti-HSV-1 activity of acyclovir, and interact with the polymerase near PAA-binding site (
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>). Eugeniin in pure form demonstrated potent inhibition of NS2BNS3 proteases of DENV-2 and 3 at IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 94.7 nM and 7.53 μM; while moderate inhibition was found with isobiflorin and biflorin at 58.9 and 89.6 μM (
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>). Furthermore, the kinetic studies revealed a competitive inhibition at same binding site of both proteases; while the 
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> value of eugeniin is reported as 125.2 nM for DENV2 protease, and 7.1 μM for DENV3 protease (
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>).
</p>
