<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Secondly, O-Demethyldemethoxycurcumin from 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> was predicted to be a promising molecule for inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis. It should be noted that O-Demethyldemethoxycurcumin not only confers inhibitory effects on the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein as per our prediction, but is also well-proven to be involved in Endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress reduction (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>). It is well-known that ER stress reduction is crucial in viral replication and infection, and is an essential aspect in reducing the infection level, as the complete secretory mechanism of the virus occurs in ER (
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>). Moreover, ER stress is one of the major problems in SARS-CoV-2 infection, as the synthesis and folding of transmembrane protein loses balance and the amount of proteins entering the ER increases drastically. This loss of balance culminates in the aggregation of unfolded proteins in the ER, which in turn triggers the ER stress response that initiates to assist the organelle for homeostasis. SARS-CoV-2 activates the Unfolded protein response (UPR) and hijack the signaling pathways for its benefit to infect rapidly, hence the reduction of ER stress in the body can be a potential way of blocking SARS-CoV-2 infection (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>). Curcumin and its derivatives are treated as miraculous molecules in many infectious diseases as well as in immunomodulation. The derivatives of curcumin in combination with advanced drug delivery systems may work in a multi-faceted way for the treatment and prevention of SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>). A recent computational study showed that curcumin exhibit strong binding affinity to Spike protein of SARS-CoV-2, ACE2 receptor of host, and their complex (RBD of viral S protein and ACE2; RBD/ACE2-complex) with the binding affinity values of −7.9 kcal/mol; −7.8 kcal/mol; and −7.6 kcal/mol; – 9.1 and– 7.6 kcal/mol, respectively. Moreover, molecular dynamics simulation also substantiated the curcumin's interaction within RBD site, thereby predicts the possibility of therapeutic strategy against SARS-CoV2 (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>).
</p>
