<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flavonoids are major secondary metabolites with extensive distribution in plants and pharmacological potentials [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. They are non-nitrogenous compounds responsible for pigmentation in fruits, leaves, and petals [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], which are majorly sourced from fruits, vegetables, and cereals [
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Flavonoids, known for their interaction with neurological signalling pathways [
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], have therapeutic effects in neurodegenerative disease conditions. Dietary flavonoids have biochemical anticancer mechanisms by making the aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AhR) the target site [
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and similarly in Alzheimer's disease (AD) and atherosclerosis [
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and chemoprevention and disease therapy [
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. They are also key in reducing the risk of chronic conditions and the improvement of blood pressure [
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Notably, [
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] has elucidated the use of dietary flavonoids in alternative medicine in relation to the control and management of epileptic conditions. Flavonoid content was high in the acetone and ethanol extracts of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> flesh and peel, including the boiled peel extract in both fruits, but was the highest in the acetone extract of each of the flesh and peel of both fruits, a similar observation in ethyl acetate extracts of the muli cultivar of banana [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. There was undetected to fairly low flavonoid content in the aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> in this study. However, the flavonoid content in 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> boiled peel extract in this study is comparable to the observation in the aqueous extract of 
 <italic>Rubus niveus</italic> fruit [
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] and is also comparable to similar pharmacological profiles such as antiproliferative, antioxidant, and enzyme inhibitory activities of 
 <italic>Rubus caesius</italic> L. [
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Generally, the higher phytochemical contents detected in the acetone and ethanol extracts over the aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> fruits suggest the superior extractive potency of organic solvents over the somewhat weaker potency in aqueous solvents [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. This observation, particularly in acetone solvents, is not far-fetched due to the nature of the solvent's polarity, with extensive significance on the components and activity of bioactive compounds [
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Furthermore, [
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] has buttressed the point about organic solvents' high extraction efficiency.
</p>
