<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antioxidants are compounds that neutralise free radicals and can be supplied in diets. Dietary antioxidants have key pharmacologically important roles such as male reproductive health improvement [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], insulin resistance, and lowered risk of type II diabetes [
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Essentially, antioxidants facilitate regular body functions such as normal cell growth, immune support, and prevention of degeneration at molecular levels, including the stemming of premature ageing [
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Furthermore, research workers have mirrored areas such as the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> evaluation of the biological activities of unripe 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> against the oxidative and cell-damaging phenomenon of lipid peroxidation in the pancreatic organ of rats [
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Antioxidant potential was evaluated with the DPPH, ABTS, and FRAP assays, in order to account for the variances present in the mode of activity of antioxidants. There was a generally low DPPH activity in the acetone, ethanol, and aqueous extracts of the flesh and peel, as well as the boiled peel extracts in 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic>. This could be accounted for due to the reported direct relation between DPPH radical scavenging activity and proanthocyanidin content [
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Inhibition of ABTS
 <sup>+</sup> (%) by the extracts was generally higher than in DPPH, alluding to a lower IC
 <sub>50</sub> value than DPPH, which is explainable by the variations in the mechanism in the two radical antioxidant reaction assays. The organic extracts (acetone and ethanol) predominantly had the highest DPPH scavenging activity in the peel, flesh, and boiled peel extract of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic>. This observation can be attributed to the implication of phenolic content in the antioxidative mechanism [
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. The synergistic relationship between phenolic compounds and antioxidant activity in plants has also been elucidated [
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>–
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Reference [
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] similarly observed good antioxidant scavenging activity in the peel of 
 <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>, 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>, 
 <italic>Ipomoea batatas</italic>, and 
 <italic>Raphanus sativus</italic>. ABTS inhibition was the highest in aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic> peels and was even higher in the boiled peel extracts of 
 <italic>M. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. paradisiaca</italic>. The high phenolic content can be reflective of the observed antioxidant activity, especially because phenols and especially flavonoids are bioactivity precursors [
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>–
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] and key contributory factors to the antioxidative potential of plants [
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
