<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The present study investigated the characteristics of SAEO after encapsulation in HPCD. The results of the FT-IR and 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H NMR spectra confirmed that SAEO was successfully encapsulated in the HPCD cavity. Hydrophobic SAEO became a water-soluble encapsulation complex. However, the compositions of SAEO and its relative content were different from those before encapsulation. In addition to 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-anethole and 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-anethole, the relative content of most components decreased. The components that contained an ether bond were more easily encapsulated into the HPCD cavity as compared to the other components, which may result in changes in the antimicrobial properties of SAEO. The results of the molecular modeling indicated that the embedded modes of the three main components were inserted into the cavity of HPCD on the isoallyl (or allyl) side. In addition, the components with higher contents formed complexes with HPCD more easily. The volatile stability of SAEO after encapsulation was evaluated by electronic nose, and the data showed that the “sulfur-organic” and “sulf-chlor” smell of the encapsulation solution was significantly lower than the SAEO and water mixture due to the embedding effect of the HPCD. This indicated that encapsulation significantly reduced the irritating smell of SAEO and makes the clathrate have a sustained release effect. The results of the antibacterial test indicated that the inhibitory effect of SAEO on 
 <italic class="italic">Rhizopus stolonoifer</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> markedly increased following the formation of the encapsulation complex due to the improvement of water solubility of SAEO. Furthermore, the antibacterial stability of the inclusion complex in 24 h was generally superior to that of free SAEO on account of the encapsulated slow release effect.
</p>
