<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">Ethanol production is probably the most intensively investigated application of lignocellulose-derived sugars. The yeast 
 <italic class="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, the most established organism for ethanol production, efficiently converts glucose and other hexoses to ethanol. In addition, the yeast 
 <italic class="italic">Brettanomyces bruxellensis</italic> and the bacterium 
 <italic class="italic">Zymomonas mobilis</italic> can produce ethanol under industrial conditions (Blomqvist and Passoth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2015</xref>; Gupta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2016</xref>); it has for instance been shown that 
 <italic class="italic">B. bruxellensis</italic> can ferment oat straw hydrolysate to ethanol (Tiukova et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">2014</xref>). Those industrial ethanol producers have a high ethanol tolerance and they can adapt to inhibitors present in lignocellulose hydrolysate (e.g. Blomqvist et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2011</xref>; Tiukova et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, these microorganisms cannot assimilate xylose and other pentoses derived from hemicellulose. To obtain an economically feasible ethanol process from lignocellulose, it is also desirable to convert the hemicellulose sugars to ethanol. Substantial efforts have been made to obtain xylose-fermenting, inhibitor-tolerant 
 <italic class="italic">S. cerevisiae</italic> strains (Passoth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">2014</xref>; Passoth 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">2017a</xref>). Finally, by a combination of metabolic and evolutionary engineering of industrial 
 <italic class="italic">S. cerevisiae</italic> isolates, strains were obtained that can ferment both glucose and xylose in lignocellulose hydrolysate. These strains overexpress specific transporters for xylose, the pentose-phosphate pathway, and the xylose assimilation pathway—either xylose reductase/xylitol dehydrogenase of the xylose-fermenting yeast 
 <italic class="italic">Scheffersomyces stipitis</italic> (Garcia Sanchez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2010</xref>) or a codon-optimised xylose isomerase from 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium phytofermentans</italic> (Demeke et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2013a</xref>; Demeke et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">2013b</xref>, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Second-generation ethanol production technology has in principle reached maturity for commercial production. The Danish company Inbicon established a pilot plant, which has the capacity to generate 576 kg (730 l) ethanol per hour from wheat straw (Larsen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">2012</xref>). The ethanol plant in Crescentino, Italy, is the world’s first second-generation ethanol plant on commercial scale. It produces about 40,000 metric tons of ethanol per year from 270,000 tons of biomass—wheat and rice straw and the energy crop giant cane (
 <italic class="italic">Arundo donax</italic>) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biochemtex.com/en/references/crescentino" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.biochemtex.com/en/references/crescentino</ext-link>, accessed 1/12/2018). Construction of another ethanol plant (Clariant sunliquid) in Romania started in 2018. This plant, supported by the 7th Framework Programme of the European Union, has a projected capacity of 50,000 metric tons per year from cellulosic agricultural residues (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sunliquid-project-fp7.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.sunliquid-project-fp7.eu/</ext-link>, accessed 4/4/2019). A number of commercial second-generation ethanol plants with a total capacity of about 530 million litre ethanol per year have been established in the USA and Brazil, most of them operating with straw as part of the feedstock mix. However, especially in times of low mineral oil prices, the costs for second-generation bioethanol are high compared to prices of fuels generated from fossil resources and first-generation ethanol. Due to this, competitive second-generation bioethanol production is still difficult to obtain, despite the substantial reductions in greenhouse gas emissions compared to fossil fuels. The high costs mainly arise from the need for extensive pretreatment of the lignocellulose, with concomitant high costs for equipment and thus capital (Lantz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">2018</xref>; Lynd et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2017</xref>). This might be overcome by modifying handling of feedstock. Mixing wood chips from short rotation coppice and wheat straw resulted in higher monomeric sugar release after pretreatment compared to treatment of the sole feedstocks. Blending also can mitigate supply risks due to seasonal biomass shortage. Under those conditions, prices of $60–69 per ton were calculated (Dou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">2019</xref>).
</p>
