<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Although stemborer species and the fall armyworm have been considered a serious constraint to maize production, few studies have illustrated the interactions among these complexes of pest species. System dynamics, first developed by Forrester
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>, offers a useful method to understand and describe such interactions. That approach, that was originally developed for engineering and administration studies is increasingly been applied to other fields such agriculture, health, economic, and social science
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. The method takes in consideration a set of elements that interact continuously as a component with structure, which undergoes changes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. The analysis of the system structure (model) by scenarios provides an understand the system behaviour with time. Using differential equations and the Routh–Hurwitz criteria, Mwalusepo et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> studied the stability of insect species competing for resource. The study revealed that when a species feeds on a resource, the species will be able to establish and sustain a stable population that fluctuates based on the resource availability. However, in a competing context with many species feeding on a single resource, it is observed that the combinations of three parameters (half-saturation, growth rate and mortality rate) determine which species has the upper edge on the resource. In another study, Neill
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> applied matrix model of the competition coefficients to study the community of species to reveal different patterns of interspecific interactions and estimate the maximum number of interacting species expected in a community. This work therefore aims at developing and evaluating models that represents the interactions of maize stemborer species and 
 <italic>S. frugiperda</italic> populations and their associated parasitoids in a multi-species community in maize fields.
</p>
