<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Chia flour is one of the most studied for baking processes. In general, wheat breads reduce their volume, increase hardness and present darker crumbs as the level of chia flour increases, as some research on bread fortification [
 <xref rid="B11-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>] or the substitution of saturated fats for chia flour [
 <xref rid="B39-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] has shown. However, some studies have reported an increase in the volume and a reduction of the hardness of breads with less than 10% chia flour [
 <xref rid="B85-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>]. These differences may be due to the wheat flours used, the formulations used or the time of fermentation. In fact, the fermentation time was optimised in these two studies compared to the previous ones, which used a fixed fermentation time. This would indicate that the doughs enriched with chia flour would not support an excess of fermentation. Thus, the drop in volume and the consequent increase in the hardness of the breads may be due to the loss of strength of the dough and the breakage of the gluten network during fermentation, as shown by Steffolani et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Other research, focused on other oilseeds such as sesame [
 <xref rid="B37-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] or pumpkin [
 <xref rid="B35-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] at levels above 14%, showed a decrease in the volume of the breads when they were enriched with flours of these seeds or protein concentrates made from them. However, Koca and Anil [
 <xref rid="B86-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>] did not observe differences in the volume of breads enriched with flaxseed flour at levels between 5% and 20%, which the authors attributed to the functionality of flaxseed gum. Likewise, Skrbic and Filipcev [
 <xref rid="B38-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] did not observe differences either between the specific volumes or between the hardness of the breads, both white and whole, made with sunflower seeds. The differences with other investigations may be due to the incorporation of seeds and not flours, so the interaction of the components of the seeds with the components and the gluten is lower. However, a certain relaxation of the doughs was observed in this study since a decrease in the height/width bread ratio of the breads with 12% addition was observed. In general, the addition of oilseeds seems to have a smaller effect on the volume of the breads than the addition of oilseed flours. The incorporation of oilseeds as flour can have a positive effect or not modify the volume of the breads if they are incorporated in small proportions, while it shows a negative influence on the volume when the quantities exceed a certain level. This was exactly what Mentes et al. [
 <xref rid="B98-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>] observed in a study on the enrichment of wheat breads with ground flaxseed, where the negative effects began to be noticed after adding 20% flaxseed, and an increase of the volume with levels of 10% flaxseed. Similarly, Sayed-Ahmad et al. [
 <xref rid="B99-foods-07-00191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">99</xref>] observed that the incorporation of chia seed powder (full fat) at levels between 4–6% did not modify the hardness of the whole breads, while its inclusion in cakes (defatted venues) even reduced it.
</p>
