<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Occup Environ Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Occup Environ Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Int J Occup Environ Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJOEM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The International Journal of Occupational and Environmental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2008-6520</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2008-6814</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Shiraz: NIOC Health Organization</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6524741</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31041921</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15171/ijoem.2019.1681</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Flood in Iran: A Consequence of the Global Warming?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yadollahie</surname><given-names>Mahboobeh</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A01">The IJOEM</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1"><bold>Correspondence to</bold> Mahboobeh Yadollahie, MD, Deputy Editor, The IJOEM E-mail: <email>mahboobeh.yadollahie@theijoem.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license><license-p>
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</ext-link>.
</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.theijoem.com">http://www.theijoem.com</self-uri><counts><fig-count count="2"/><ref-count count="12"/><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta><notes><p>
<bold>Cite this article as:</bold> Yadollahie M. The flood in Iran: A consequence of the global warming? <italic>Int J Occup Environ Med</italic> 2019;10:54-56. doi: 10.15171/ijoem.2019.1681
</p></notes></front><body><p>
Global warming is perhaps the most dangerous environmental obstacle the world currently facing with. It has crept into our lives. From mid- to late-20<sup>th</sup> century, we have witnessed enormous changes in the frequencies of natural disasters throughout the globe&#x02014;droughts, floods, storms, heat waves, to name only a few.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup>
</p><p>
Global warming has resulted in variable patterns in rainfall causing flood or drought from place to place. It affects the water cycle with consequent more severe and frequent extreme weather disasters such as droughts, floods, tropical cyclone and tsunami activity, tectonic and volcanic activity, and famine.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Drought, flood and extreme temperature significantly affect the economy and decrease the agricultural product and global food supplies by about 10%.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup>
</p><p>
Recently, we have had unbelievably high incidents of unexpectedly devastating typhoons in various parts of the world. Example is the huge blizzard in spring in the USA.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Another example is the heavy seasonal rains and flood that struck several governorates of Iraq, Iran, and Afghanistan in late March and early April, leaving behind several dead bodies and destroying several cities and hundreds of villages. According to the <italic>Guardian</italic> &#x0201c;Afghanistan has been hit with the worst flooding in seven years, with 20 dead, thousands of homes swept away and many families, already displaced by drought, forced to leave their homes for the second time.&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> In central and northern governorates of Iraq, heavy rain over 10 days caused flooding and damage; Tigris river overflowed down to adjacent areas in Iran.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup>
</p><p>
Many parts of Iran have also been affected. Because of the climatic changes, Iran has suffered drought since almost 30 years ago. This prolonged drought has changed many ecosystems in Iran. Many lakes and rivers have dried up. People have moved and settled in lands where once used to be the river banks and beds. Parts of jungles have disappeared and lands subsided (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1</xref>). All these resulted in a catastrophe.
</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><graphic xlink:href="ijoem-10-54-g001"/><statement><p> Land subsidence in a road, Fars province, southern Iran</p></statement></fig><p>
Recently, a devastating flood struck parts of Iran (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2</xref>). Almost all provinces had heavy rain falls. The ground, which had not been protected by trees and bushes, was washed away by heavy rain; mud flowed into residential places, cities and villages. Massive destruction of infrastructures, home, agricultural land, and animal husbandry was just a small part of what happened in the country; roads were closed causing trouble to help the needed people. According to a Red Cross report &#x0201c;Heavy rains and flash floods have affected more than 2000 cities and towns across almost all of Iran's 31 provinces, according to the Iranian Red Crescent. An estimated 10 million people have been affected in some way, including more than half a million have been displaced from their homes&#x02014;some permanently. At least 78 people have been killed and more than 1136 injured.&#x0201d;<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup>
</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><graphic xlink:href="ijoem-10-54-g002"/><statement><p>Devastating flood in Shiraz, southern Iran</p></statement></fig><p>
During the acute phase of such a catastrophe, people mostly suffer from loss of their family members, home, farms, facilities, invasion of rodent to the city, <italic>etc</italic>. At the time of injury, they need medical attention, food, water and temporary shelters. Nonetheless, the most important problem for these homeless people is severe physical and psychological trauma they had experienced. After termination of the disaster, all of those who came for help return home, leaving behind a group of victims still in desperate need of help, even more than before. Gradually, starvation and malnutrition begin to surface. Starvation, unemployment, and low sanitary measures make them prone to serious medical conditions such as infection, particularly zoonotic and chronic diseases. The victims are threatened by not only physical illness but also mental ailments caused by the crisis. Many of them find them to have no choice but to immigrate to another place, putting them at risk of solastalgia with increasing psychological distress.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>
</p><p>
Economic crisis is another problem after a disaster. The recent flood struck Iran destroyed thousands of kilometers of roads, numerous homes and infrastructural facilities costing at least US$ 8 billion. Worse, for the imposed US sanctions on Iran, the financial aids provided by other countries and international bodies could not reach Iran, although according to the US officials, the sanctions are not supposed to affect the health of people.<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>
</p><p>
Invasion of southern parts of Iran by a swarm of desert locusts (<italic>Schistocerca gregaria</italic>) soon after the flood, was another major problem.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> After the flood and increase in humidity, a swarm of locusts immigrated from Saudi Arabia and Kuwait to Iran. They were able to eat the remaining agricultural products the flood could have not destroyed. The large amount of locusts now available as food to ravens and certain types of wolves, would increase the number of these animals, causing another shock to the local ecosystem and consequent environmental problems.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>
</p><p>
In many affected areas with hot climate, people can no longer stay in tents provided by the Iranian Red Crescent. For the presence of water all over the area, the place is an ideal environment for proliferation of insects. Therefore, enough protection by using fly nets, for example, should be used, or we will witness an increase in the frequency of diseases such as malaria and leishmaniasis.
</p><p>
The global warming is a reality. Some politicians believe that working for prevention of global warming is a waste of time and resources. If we are going to ignore these alarming signs of the global warming, we should at least prepare for facing similar (if not worse) catastrophic events in forthcoming years.
</p><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s1"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p> None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Organization WM. Atlas of Mortality and Economic Losses from Weather, Climate and Water Extremes (1970&#x02013;2012). In: (WMO) WMO, ed. WMO-No. 1123, 2014.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Masood</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohail</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>The Deadly Heat Wave of Pakistan, June 2015</article-title><source>Int J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26498053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><article-title>The influence of global warming on natural disasters and their public health outcomes</article-title><source>Am J Disaster Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18268873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lesk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowhani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramankutty</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>Influence of extreme weather disasters on global crop production</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>529</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26738594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Schmidt AW, A; Lada, B. LIVE: Low visibility, difficult travel remain threats in central US following the worst of deadly spring blizzard, 2019. Available from <uri xlink:href="https://www.accuweather.com/en/weather-news/live-monster-spring-storm-unleashes-heavy-snow-triggers-hazardous-travel-conditions-across-central-us/70007946">https://www.accuweather.com/en/weather-news/live-monster-spring-storm-unleashes-heavy-snow-triggers-hazardous-travel-conditions-across-central-us/70007946</uri> (Accessed April 12, 2019).
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Gurdian T. 'Chilling reality': Afghanistan suffers worst floods in seven years, 2019. Available from <uri xlink:href="www.theguardian.com/global-development/2019/mar/06/chilling-reality-afghanistan-suffers-worst-floods-in-seven-years">www.theguardian.com/global-development/2019/mar/06/chilling-reality-afghanistan-suffers-worst-floods-in-seven-years</uri> (Accessed March 26, 2019).
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
OCHA Iraq in collaboration with humanitarian partners. Iraq-Floods: Update No. 1 (as of 3 April 2019): UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs, 2019. Available from <uri xlink:href="https://reliefweb.int/report/iraq/iraq-floods-update-no-1-3-april-2019">https://reliefweb.int/report/iraq/iraq-floods-update-no-1-3-april-2019</uri> (Accessed April 5, 2019).
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
Federation IRC. Iran floods: Two million people in need of humanitarian aid, 2019. Available from <uri xlink:href="https://media.ifrc.org/ifrc/press-release/iran-floods-two-million-people-need-humanitarian-aid/">https://media.ifrc.org/ifrc/press-release/iran-floods-two-million-people-need-humanitarian-aid/</uri> (Accessed April 15, 2019).
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Padhy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Panigrahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Mental health effects of climate change</article-title><source>Indian J Occup Environ Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26023264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Habibzadeh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Economic sanction: a weapon of mass destruction</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2018</year><volume>392</volume><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30139528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazelles</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Periodic temperature-associated drought/flood drives locust plagues in China</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fashing</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fashing</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><article-title>Behavior of geladas and other endemic wildlife during a desert locust outbreak at Guassa, Ethiopia: ecological and conservation implications</article-title><source>Primates</source><year>2010</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20333438</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>