<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fresh-cut lettuce is prone to enzymatic browning and has been associated with the activity of three enzymes: polyphenol oxidase, peroxidase, and phenylalanine ammonia lyase-PAL [
 <xref rid="B46-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The use of natural products, i.e., ascorbic acid and EOs as anti-browning agents has been previously studied and results are promising [
 <xref rid="B4-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B4-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] reported that the application of 0.05% clove EO and eugenol (used alone) decreased fresh-cut lettuce browning by significantly inhibiting the activities of PAL, PPO, and POD. The use of phytoncide (EO derived from pine leaves) (1% diluted in 95% ethanol) was able to decrease the activity of PPO, POD, and PAL of fresh-cut lettuce stored at 12 days at 4 °C. In our study, EO+AA and EO+Chitosan decreased POD activity on the fourth day of storage, while EO, EO+Chitosan, EO+AA, and Chitosan+AA also decreased POD activity on the last day of storage. The application of AA in the present study was found to increase CAT activity, while Chitosan+AA decreased POD and increased PPO activity. It has been suggested that AA does not interact directly with PPO, as it can reduce o-quinones (enzymatically produced) to their precursor diphenols [
 <xref rid="B72-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. A study by Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B73-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] showed that polysaccharide-based edible coatings (alginate, chitosan, and carrageenan) are able to inhibit fresh-cut lettuce enzymatic browning by maintaining total phenols content as well as decreasing PPO and PAL activities throughout storage. In the same study, it was suggested that among the studied edible coatings, chitosan (1%) was the most effective [
 <xref rid="B73-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Interestingly, increased SOD and POD, and at the same time decreased PPO activity, was reported throughout storage (up to 15 days at 4 °C), with the application of 1% chitosan on cut lettuce [
 <xref rid="B73-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. In our study, the combination of Chitosan+AA and Chitosan+EO increased PPO activity during the second and fourth day of storage, respectively. Moreover, the findings in our study suggest that the Chitosan+AA increased SOD activity on the second day, while when chitosan was applied alone resulted in decreased SOD and CAT activity on the fourth day of storage.
</p>
