<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many studies have assessed the antimicrobial effects of EOs on the microbial load of fresh produce [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], indicating the importance of safe and high-quality produce for the consumer. For instance, the application of thyme EO on minimally processed lettuce exhibited high bacteriostatic activity against mesophilic and psychtotrophic bacteria, 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, and yeast and molds counts [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In another study, thyme and tea tree EOs used alone or in combination resulted to great reduction of 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 population (up to 2 log) inoculated on fresh lettuce leaves stored at 10 °C [
 <xref rid="B74-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Bagamboula et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] reported that thyme and basil EOs at the concentrations applied (0.5 and 1%) were able to reduce both inoculated (
 <italic>Shigella sonnei</italic> and 
 <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic>) and indigenous flora populations on fresh-cut lettuce (up to 2 log reduction). On the other hand, one of the main activities chitosan exhibits when applied to plants is its antimicrobial activity, and it has been previously assessed by researchers against a wide range of microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B28-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Goñi et al. [
 <xref rid="B75-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] reported that the preharvest application of chitosan (0.1% 
 <italic>w/v</italic>) during the last development stages controlled lettuce’s native microflora, as well as reduced 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> survival inoculated on the edible plant parts. Another study reported lower microbial load of total bacteria and the presence of 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> in ready-to eat lettuce when treated with allyl- and benzyl-isothiocyanates and chitosan [
 <xref rid="B76-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. In the present study, chitosan decreased lettuce’s TVC and yeast and mold counts after six days of storage at 7 °C. In addition, EO, along with EO+Chitosan, EO+AA, and Chitosan+AA, resulted in lower yeast and molds counts on the fourth day of storage, highlighting the antimicrobial activities of the examined natural compounds. These results are in accordance with studies that suggest that when chitosan is applied alone or in combination with antimicrobial compounds can inhibit microbial growth [
 <xref rid="B32-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Noticeably, the combination of citric and ascorbic acid was not able to remove 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> cells from lettuce leaves and prevent biofilm formation [
 <xref rid="B78-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. However, the application of AA (1%) alone or in combination with marjoram EO and hydrosol resulted in the reduction of TVC and yeast and molds counts of shredded carrots stored at 4 °C for up to nine days [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Akbas and Ölmez [
 <xref rid="B16-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] also reported that dipping of inoculated iceberg lettuce leaves on ascorbic acid solutions (0.5 and 1 %) were able to reduce 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> population by almost 2 log and 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> by 1 log.
</p>
