<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the main issues in fresh-cut vegetable processing is the browning of the cut surface which is an undesirable feature leading to reduced marketability products (darkening and softening), loss of nutritional value, and the development of off-flavors [
 <xref rid="B21-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Browning results from enzymatic and non-enzymatic reactions that are favored by the disruption of plant cell wall during processing and the exposure of phenolic compounds to oxygen and enzymes [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. The effects of natural products as anti-browning agents applied on fresh produce have been previously assessed [
 <xref rid="B4-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The application of oxalic and ascorbic acid on lettuce aliquots maintained phenolic content on high levels compared to citric acid and cysteine application [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In this study, the application of EO+AA and Chitosan+AA combinations increased lettuce’s phenolic content after four and six days of storage. Interestingly, in a study by Viacava et al. [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] it has been shown that the application of thyme EO on minimally processed lettuce increased total phenolics, total flavonoids, and antioxidant capacity. Ascorbic acid and carotenoid content were increased with the use of EO+AA. According to Altunkaya and Gökmen [
 <xref rid="B18-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], color changes have been linked with the degradation of ascorbic acid and this might explain the positive effects of EO and EO+AA on the color of fresh-cut lettuce throughout storage time. Interestingly, fresh-cut lettuce’s chlorophylls decreased during storage, though the application of Chitosan+AA and EO maintained their levels up to the last day of storage. Another study reported that high green-tea extract concentration (up to 1% 
 <italic>w/v</italic>) prevented ascorbic acid and carotenoid loss of fresh-cut lettuce [
 <xref rid="B61-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].
</p>
