<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The production of active oxygen species (i.e., H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, superoxide-O
 <sup>2•-</sup>, hydroxyl-OH
 <sup>•</sup>, singlet oxygen-
 <sup>1</sup>O
 <sub>2</sub>) has been linked with lipid peroxidation, production of brown pigments and core browning, pigment bleaching (chlorophyll and carotenoids), and other processes that lower postharvest quality of fruit and vegetables [
 <xref rid="B56-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In this study, H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> was increased with the use of EO, AA, and their combination (EO+AA) on the second day, while decreased H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> levels were revealed with the use of Chitosan+AA at the end of storage. Increased lipid peroxidation was also found with Chitosan+AA on the second day, whereas EO application showed lower MDA levels after six day of storage at 7 °C. An increase in H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and MDA levels was reported during storage of fresh-cut rocket and melon at 4 and 20 °C with MDA levels lower than 0.3 nmol g
 <sup>−1</sup> fresh weight, which suggested a moderate lipid peroxidation level according to Cavaiuolo et al. [
 <xref rid="B68-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Noticeably, Ferrante et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] reported higher lipid peroxidation values on fresh-cut lamb’s lettuce leaves compared to intact ones, when stored at 4 °C up to 8 d (values up to 0.041–0.051 nmol kg
 <sup>−1</sup> MDA), confirming that processing (i.e., cutting) induces plant stress and increases lipid peroxidation that utterly result to low quality products presenting postharvest disorders such as tissue browning and leaf yellowing. Additionally, in another study the use of AA when combined with marjoram EO and hydrosol increased the H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> and MDA levels of shredded carrots suggesting that applied treatments might also induce oxidative stress and affect the quality of the end product [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-10-00575" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
