<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Synthesis of Aldehyde-functionalized Polymers</div>
 <div list-type="order" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Synthesis of Aldehyde-Precursor Monomer N-(2,2-Dimethoxyethyl) Methacrylate (DMEMA) 
    <div list-type="order" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Place 200 mL of a 20% w/v NaOH solution into a 500 mL 3 neck round-bottom flask.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Cool the solution in an ice bath and maintain a temperature of 0 °C with ice during the reaction.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Add 50 mL of aminoacetyl aldehyde dimethyl acetal to the cooled NaOH solution.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Add in 0.1 g of TEMPO ((2,2,6,6-Tetramethylpiperidin-1-yl)oxyl) and stir at 400 rpm using a magnetic stir bar until the TEMPO fully dissolves.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Add 48 mL of methacryloyl chloride dropwise using a burette over 2 h.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>After 2 h, cover the reaction vessel with aluminum foil and leave to stir overnight.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Extract the product by adding the reaction product to 75 mL of petroleum ether in a 1 L separation funnel, shaking, degassing, and discarding the top layer.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Repeat step 2.1.7 three times by adding the bottom layer product from each extraction step as the raw product to the next extraction cycle.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Remove the final bottom layer product and transfer to a 100 mL beaker.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Add ~5 g magnesium sulfate (Mg
       <sub>2</sub>SO
       <sub>4</sub>) to beaker with monomer until a "snow globe" effect is observed.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Filter through a 100 mL Buchner funnel to remove the Mg
       <sub>2</sub>SO
       <sub>4</sub>.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Rinse the beaker twice with ~75 mL of tert-butyl methyl ether, pouring the rinse solution through the funnel each time.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Transfer the product to a 500 mL round-bottom flask and evaporate the solvent using a rotary evaporator at room temperature 200 RPM to collect the final product.</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Synthesis of Aldehyde-Functionalized Polymers ​Note: The following specific recipe is provided for the PNIPAM-mimetic POEGMA precursor polymer (PO
    <sub>10</sub>) with 30 mol% aldehyde functionalization. PNIPAM and POEGMA precursor polymers with different phase transition temperatures can be prepared using the same general method but modifying the type and ratio of the core monomers used (see section 1.2 for modifications for various POEGMA polymers)
    <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">21</a>
    <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">25</a>
    <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">27</a>. 
    <div list-type="order" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Weigh out 37 mg of 2,2'-azobis(2-methylpropionate) (AIBMe), 3.10 g of diethylene glycol methacrylate M(EO)
       <sub>2</sub>MA, 0.1 g of oligo ethyleneglycol methacrylate (OEGMA
       <sub>475</sub>, 475 g/mol, n=7-8 ethylene oxide repeat units), 1.30 g of N-(2,2-dimethoxyethyl) acrylamide (DMEMA) and 7.5 µL of thiolglycolic acid (TGA) into a 20 mL glass scintillation vial.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>For PO
       <sub>0</sub> (room temperature transition temperature POEGMA), use 4.0 g of M(EO)
       <sub>2</sub>MA (no OEGMA
       <sub>475</sub>). For PO
       <sub>100</sub> (no transition temperature POEGMA), use 4.0 g of OEGMA
       <sub>475 </sub>(no M(EO)
       <sub>2</sub>MA). Note: Intermediate phase transition temperatures can be achieved based on the use of intermediate mixtures of M(EO)
       <sub>2</sub>MA and OEGMA
       <sub>475</sub>, according to Lutz 
       <span class="italic">et al</span>.
       <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">23</a>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Dissolve all reagents in dioxane (5 mL/g total monomer) in a round bottom flask with one or more necks.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Purge the reaction with nitrogen (UHP grade) flow for 30 min.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Once purged, place flask in a pre-heated oil bath maintained at 75 °C for 4 h under nitrogen and 400 rpm magnetic stirring.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>After 4 h, remove the solvent using a rotary evaporator set to 50 °C and 200 rpm.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Dissolve the resulting polymer product in 100 mL of deionized H
       <sub>2</sub>O.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Add 50 mL of 1 M HCl into the dissolved solution and stir under magnetic stirring (400 RPM) for 24 h to fully hydrolyze the acetal functionalities in DMEMA.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>After reaction completion, transfer the polymer solution into dialysis tubing, as per step 1.13.</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Lyophilize the dialyzed sample to obtain a final dried polymer product.</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
