<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In humans, oxidative stress is tightly linked to inflammation, claimed as a central physiological process in the pathogenesis of numerous chronic diseases including diabetes, aging, and cancer [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Concretely, the inflammatory process can exacerbate oxidative stress and vice versa [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In fact, many experimental data have indicated the existence and contribution of oxidative stress in several chronic diseases [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Therefore, the screening of sample’s antioxidant property is an integral part of our study. Of the serious chronic diseases, diabetes is a complicated disorder with different types requiring varied treatment methods. The most common diabetes is type 2, which causes the elevation of bloodstream sugar level. A potential approach to mitigate type 2 diabetes’ effects can be mentioned to inhibit important enzymes involving in glucose formation, in which α-amylase is a crucial enzyme acting on starch [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Additionally, a strong correlation between diabetes and skin manifestations was reported via clinical tests and practical trials [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Among skin problems, hyperpigmentation resulting in freckles is attributed to the over-formation of melanin through an abnormal tyrosinase activity at both normal melanocytes and malignant melanoma cells [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. For that reason, the simultaneous inhibition on α-amylase and tyrosinase can be an effective solution to avoid the symptom of type 2 diabetes and skin hyperpigmentation. In cancer cases, chronic myeloid leukemia (CML) is a severe disorder, caused by the unregular proliferation of myeloid cells in the bone marrow. K562 is a typical CML cell line relating to an extraordinary increase in the production of white blood cells [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Meg-01 cell line is also considered to be derived from the myeloid origin, which involve in proliferating nonfunctional immature cells, another type of CML [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-10-00069" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Therefore, simultaneous inhibition on both K562 and Meg-01 can be a potential solution in preventing the development of CML. Furthermore, the synergic suppression against oxidative stress, tyrosinase and α-amylase enzymes, and K562 and Meg-01 cell lines could be a prospective approach for developing natural products, which can prevent multiple human health problems.
</p>
