<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">Inflammation, characterized by redness, swelling, heat and pain, is a body’s defense response to stimulation. However, excessive or long-term inflammatory response can lead to tissue damage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Indigo naturalis and its some active ingredients have been proved to have significant anti-inflammatory effects, whose mechanism is the down-regulation of some inflammation factors and the inhibition of NO production [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. For instance, indigo naturalis and its main compound indigo can reduce the expression of TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>, IL-1, IL-6, IL-10, IL-22 and other inflammatory factors in plasma of UC mice via antagonizing TLRs/NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B pathway and activating AhR pathway, thus improving inflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Indigo naturalis also can improve the oxidative stress level of colon tissue by increasing superoxide dismutase (SOD) and decreasing malondialdehyde (MDA) level, so as to control and reduce inflammatory reaction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Indirubin inhibits the production of inflammatory cytokines through a variety of signaling pathways, and has a certain dose-dependent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. A study found that indirubin significantly inhibited TLR4 and NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B signaling and decreased the level of inflammatory cytokines in mice with lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced acute lung injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Except for the NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B signaling pathway, indirubin also inhibits the MAPK signaling by decreasing the phosphorylation of extracellular ERK, P38, and JNK in LPS-induced mouse mastitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Another study found that indirubin can also reduce crypt deformation and mucosal damage, and reduce the infiltration of inflammatory cell in colonic mucosa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Additionally, indigo naturalis can also play an anti-inflammatory role by inhibiting intracellular Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> concentration. In formyl-L-methionyl-L-leucyl-L-phenylalanine (FMLP)-activated human neutrophils, indigo naturalis could significantly reduce O2(.-) generation and elastase release, inhibit calcium mobilization and reduce phosphorylation of extracellular p38 MAPK, JNK and some regulated kinase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. While indigo naturalis not affect cellular cAMP levels. Interestingly, neither indirubin, indigo nor tryptanthrin had similar effects in FMLP-activated human neutrophils and this result indicates that there are some unknown activities. Although indigo naturalis has significant anti-inflammatory effect, its anti-inflammatory mechanism and active ingredients need to be further explored.
</p>
