<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fatty acid composition of vegetable oils plays an important role in determining the quality of biodiesel. The present results showed an interesting finding that 
 <italic class="italic">Azospirillum</italic> in combination with quarter dose of NP fertilizers (SPQ) gave a considerable increase in oleic acid content. Oleic acid is an important fatty acid to obtain good quality biodiesel production, improving biodiesel properties such as cold flow properties, oxidation stability, specific gravity, cetane number and viscosity. Therefore, supplementing PGPR (Plant Growth Promoting Rhizobacteria) with quarter doses of NP fertilizers would help to improve the quality of oil suitable for biodiesel production. The present findings are in line with those of Dhanasekar and Dhandapani [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] who reported that application of PGPR such as 
 <italic class="italic">Azospirillum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Azotobacter</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Rhizobium</italic> in combination with chemical fertilizers significantly influenced the seed yield and oil quality in sunflower. In the present study, a single inoculation of 
 <italic class="italic">Azospirillum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Azotobacter</italic> also enhanced oleic acid content compared to that of control which is in agreement with the findings of Texier [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] who reported that inoculation of sunflower with PGPR improved the unsaturated/saturated fatty acids ratio and also seed oil content. Similarly, Choudhury and Kennedy [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] reported that inoculation of sunflower with nitrogen fixing bacteria increased the phosphorus level which in turn influenced the seed oil content and the unsaturated/saturated fatty acids ratio. Previously, various scientists [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>; 
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] reported that the presence of PGPR (specifically nitrogen fixing bacteria) in the rhizosphere and their relationship with the plants improved the nitrogen use efficiency of the plant. Moreover, the production of hormones by the PGPR not only stimulates the development of the roots but also enhanced the nutrient acquisition capability of the plants. These changes impart the alterations in metabolic processes which are responsible for the improved yield and oil quality of the crops. Taken together these facts, the inoculation of PGPB (Plant Growth Promoting Bacteria) reduces the use of fertilizers which are of important environmental concerns of the day. Jha et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] reported that transformation of 
 <italic class="italic">Azospirillum brasilense</italic> ACP and its functional expression in 
 <italic class="italic">Brassica juncea</italic> not only increased oleic acid and linoleic acid but also resulted in a parallel reduction of C22:1. Our results indicated that half dose of NP fertilizers resulted in improving the fatty acid composition in terms of oleic acid which confirm the findings of Texier [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] who demonstrated that in oil seed crops, during the process of seed development, the fatty acid composition is under genetic control and the process of fatty acid biosynthesis requires the C and N skeleton and thus nitrogen fertilizers play an important role in modifying the fatty acid composition of oil seed crops. Di Benedetto et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] reported that the PGPB isolated from the soil of South Italy showed improved nutrient and nitrogen use efficiency of the wheat crop. This nutrient/nitrogen use efficiency of the crops is an important factor for the metabolic processes which provide nutrients (C, N) for the biosynthesis of fatty acids. Hence, the nitrogen use efficiency play important role in alteration of fatty acid composition of the respective crop. Gopinath et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] reported that fatty acid methyl esters significantly influenced the cetane number of biodiesel, which increases with increase in chain length and decreases with degree of unsaturation. In the present study, the ratio of monounsaturated (oleic acid)/polyunsaturated (linolenic acid) was significantly increased by the SPQ treatment which plays important role in the improvement of the oil quality and oxidation stability with perspective to biodiesel production. Polyunsaturated fatty acids are more prone to oxidation and lead to poor storage properties of biodiesel as compared to monounsaturated fatty acids [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0201738.g005" class="xref">Fig 5A and 5B</xref> showed that there is a negative correlation between monounsaturated (oleic acid) and polyunsaturated (linolenic acid) which leads toward the improvement of oxidation stability of the oil and it is a very important finding of the study.
</p>
