<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For good quality biodiesel production, the properties of oil play an important role. Acid value is an important variable for monitoring the quality of biodiesel during transeterification reaction and storage. According to the present study, maximum reduction in acid value was resulted by BTQ treatment in cv. Saif-32. These findings are in parallel to that of Abd El-Gawad et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] who reported that 
 <italic class="italic">Azotobacter chroococcum and Bacillus megaterium</italic> reduced the acid value and peroxide value of canola as compared to the control. Similar findings were reported by Nosheen et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] that acid value, free fatty acid contents and specific gravity of canola oil were significantly reduced by the application of 
 <italic class="italic">Azospirillum</italic> and chemical fertilizers treatments. The reduction in the above mentioned parameters lead towards the decrease in engine corrosion, rancidity and density of oil; hence, indirectly improved the quality of oil for biodiesel production and also reduce the use of chemical fertilizers. Dodos et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] reported that due to increase in acid value of vegetable oil, formation of shorter fatty acid and acidic secondary oxidation products occurred which leads to the corrosion of engine [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The decrease in acid value might be due to the production of phytohormone by PGPR as Ullah and Bano [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] reported that application of cytokinin decreased the acid value of safflower oil. The lower acidity of vegetable oil and biodiesel leads to a considerable increase in oxidation stability and improved storage properties of the fuel [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Results in the current study indicated that treatment SP resulted in maximum reduction of free fatty acid content of oil followed by BT, BTF and BTQ treatments respectively. It is reported that the yield of biodiesel is highly influenced by the presence of free fatty acid in the oil during base catalysed transesterification reaction [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The presence of free fatty acid contents in higher amount resulted in soap formation and ultimately leading to the reduction of biodiesel yield and quality [
 <xref rid="pone.0201738.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>].
</p>
