<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic> biofilm disruption assays were performed as previously reported (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taweechaisupapong et al., 2012</xref>). Briefly, a loop from a 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> culture in SDA grown for 24 h at 37°C was resuspended in Yeast Peptone Dextrose (YPD) broth (1% yeast extract, 2% peptone, and 2% dextrose) and further incubated for 24 h at 37°C. Then, cells were washed with PBS (pH 7.4) (0.8% NaCl, 0.02% KH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>PO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, 0.31% Na
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>HPO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>⋅12H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O, and 0.02% KCl). Cell density was adjusted to 1 × 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> CFU/mL, and then 100 μL of this suspension was added to 96-well microtiter plates and incubated for 24 h at 37°C to allow biofilm adhesion and formation. Then, the wells were washed 3 times with PBS and the essential oils (0.28–2.2 mg/mL, prepared in RPMI) were added and incubated for 24 h, at 37°C. Essential oil-free wells, with DMSO in a maximum concentration of 1% (v/v), and biofilm-free wells were also included as positive and negative controls, respectively. Biofilm mass was quantified using crystal violet according to 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raut et al. (2013)</xref>. Briefly, after treatments and medium removal, biofilms were fixed with 99% methanol for 15 min. The supernatant was removed, and the wells air-dried. Then, a solution of crystal violet (0.02%) was added to each well and allowed to stain the biofilm for 15 min. Wells were washed 2–3 times with sterile distilled water. Absorbed stain was released by addition of 150 μL of acetic acid (33%) and transferred to fresh wells. The optical density (OD) was read at 620 nm using a microplate reader. The percentage of biofilm formation was calculated by comparing the OD of treated biofilm with that of control biofilm. Biofilm viability was assessed according to the method described by 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saharkhiz et al. (2012)</xref> with some modifications. Briefly, after the treatments, the medium was removed and 100 μL of a XTT (1 mg/mL in PBS) solution containing 4 μM of menadione (10 mM in acetone) was added to biofilms prewashed with PBS. After 2 h of incubation at 37°C in the dark, the absorbance was read at 490 nm. Biofilm viability was calculated by comparing the absorbance of treated samples with that of positive controls. Results are presented as mean ± SEM of three independent experiments performed in duplicate.
</p>
