<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <title class="title">ABSTRACT</title>
 <p class="p">The objective of this study was to evaluate the effects of 2 Mexican oregano essential oils (MOO), from 
  <italic class="italic">Poliomintha longiflora</italic> Gray (
  <bold class="bold">PLG</bold>) and 
  <italic class="italic">Lippia berlandieri</italic> Schauer (
  <bold class="bold">LBS</bold>), in drinking water (
  <bold class="bold">DWt</bold>) on the performance, slaughter variables, and meat quality of broilers over a 40 D period of growth. A total of 180 non-sexed Ross-308 broilers (1-day-old) were randomly assigned to 3 treatments with 6 replications each (10 birds per replicate): 
  <bold class="bold">CON</bold> = DWt control (without MOO); PLG = DWt + 400 mg/L of PLG; and LBS = DWt + 400 mg/L of LBS. The CON, PLG, and LBS broilers body weights were similar (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) at all times. Feed intake (
  <bold class="bold">FI</bold>) was different by treatment (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) at 7 and 28 D, and water intake (
  <bold class="bold">WI</bold>) was different (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) at day 28. The CON treatment was highest (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) at 28 D for FI and WI, whereas LBS was lowest (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Weight gain (
  <bold class="bold">WG</bold>) for CON, PLG, and LBS broilers was similar (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &gt; 0.05), although WG for CON was slightly higher. In CON broilers, slaughter weight was highest (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), but thigh yield was lowest (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The CON and PLG treatments were lower (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in thigh and leg cooking losses. The PLG treatment presented the highest values (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for breast-meat redness, saturation index, shear force, odor, taste, and overall sensory acceptability. The LBS was higher (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for breast-meat shear force, cohesiveness and resilience, but lower (
  <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) for sensory attributes. Mexican oregano essential oils at 400 mg/L can serve as natural alternative additives in DWt to improve broiler production and meat quality.
 </p>
</abstract>
