<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Moreover, the higher lipid peroxidation after using extracts V1 and V2 may also be caused by lowest level of rutin and rosmarinic acid in these extracts. Both these polyphenols are powerful antioxidants, and their higher level in F1–F3 extracts guarantees protection of membrane phospholipids. Rutin that is known for its antioxidant activity, in the case of other skin cells, has been shown as a molecule that not only directly reacts with free radicals but also inactivates enzymes responsible for their generation [
 <xref rid="B28-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Furthermore, rutin protective effect on the skin relates to its involvement in intracellular signaling leading to cytoprotective proteins expression, antioxidant enzymes activation, as well as apoptosis prevention [
 <xref rid="B54-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Moreover, rutin antioxidant action significantly prevents lipid oxidative metabolism, which might be observed as lower lipid peroxidation products level, but also decreased level of other lipid metabolism markers such as isoprostanes or endocannabinoids, which are known as pro-inflammatory mediators [
 <xref rid="B55-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. On the other hand, rutin also shows cytotoxic action against various types cancer cells [
 <xref rid="B56-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], which can be connected with a higher level of lipid peroxidation products in cancer cell compared to non-transformed cells what was also observed in this study. Simultaneously, also rosmarinic acid that level is the highest in studied extracts, additionally increases skin cells antioxidant capacity. It has also been shown that rosmarinic acid can stimulate the activity of antioxidant enzymes such as glutathione peroxidase, catalase, and superoxide dysmutase [
 <xref rid="B59-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], as well as prevent lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B61-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The cytoprotective action is visible mainly in skin melanocytes, but not in the case of melanoma, which is partially confirmed by data for other cancer types [
 <xref rid="B62-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].
</p>
