<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nowadays, for a variety of high-performance industrial applications, including microfluidic devices, controllable drug delivery systems, self-cleaning surfaces, films and screens for solar cells, optical displays, and greenhouse coverings, it is important to control the wetting behavior of liquids on the device surfaces, in order to have lubrication and water-repellent coatings. Liquid behavior on a surface can range from complete spreading, as in the “tears of wine” effect, to minimal wetting, as observed on a superhydrophobic lotus leaf [
 <xref rid="B1-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. In particular, the devices developed for photovoltaic and optical applications, to retain high efficiency of all their components during their lifetime, require complex packaging solutions consisting of several layers, each of which have a specific functionality, such as acting as a moisture and liquid barrier, self-cleaning, anti-reflection and thermal radiation properties, flexibility, transparency, etc. [
 <xref rid="B2-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The combination in one layer more functionalities can offer the possibility of simplifying the packaging structure, and thus its manufacturing cost, ensuring also high efficiency and durability. Therefore, many research and technological efforts are devoted in pursuing this aim by means of different strategies (e.g., mechanical treatments, exposure to flames or corona discharge, wet-chemical treatments, etc.) able to modify the properties of the encapsulating layers, specially the polymeric ones [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-polymers-11-00257" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
