<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This experiment had both mycorrhizal fungus treatments and nutrient access treatments. The mycorrhizal fungus treatments (M
 <sup>+</sup>) included inoculation with 50g 
 <italic>Glomus etunicatum</italic> inoculum (The 
 <italic>Glomus etunicatum</italic> has a new name, 
 <italic>Claroideoglomus etunicatum</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0234410.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], purchased from the Institute of Nutritional Resources, Beijing Academy of Agricultural and Forestry Sciences, BGGAM0046), and the control without 
 <italic>Glomus etunicatum</italic> (M
 <sup>-</sup>), containing probable 500 spores as well as hyphae and colonized root pieces. The nutrient access treatments for the competition compartment interconnecting two planting compartments by mycorrhizal networks, which used 20um nylon mesh and 0.45um nylon mesh in different ways. As follows: (1) the competitive utilization nutrient treatment (Cu) was to use the 20μm double-nylon mesh on the baffle plate of the central competition compartment and the planting compartments on both sides, allowing the AM mycelia in planting compartments of 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>adenophorum</italic> and 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>annua</italic> commonly entering into the competition compartment, and form an interconnected mycorrhizal networks among all three compartments; (2) the single utilization nutrient treatment (Su) used 20μm double-nylon mesh on one side of the baffle plate between the competition compartment and one planting compartment and a 0.45μm nylon mesh on the other side between the competition compartment and the other planting compartment, allowing the AM mycelium of one planting compartment of 
 <italic>E</italic>. 
 <italic>adenophorum</italic> or 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>annua</italic> to pass through the competition compartment to utilize nutrients. (3) the non-utilization of nutrients treatment (Nu) which in contrast to Cc and Su, used the 0.45μm nylon mesh to separate both planting compartments from the central compartment, so that the nutrient resources of the competition compartment could not be utilized by both species as their associated mycelia could not cross the fine 0.45μm nylon mesh.
</p>
