<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-15-00651" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Possible Alternatives: Advantages and Disadvantages</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Food lipids are made up of glycerides, principally triglycerides. Saturated fatty acids, especially myristic, palmitic and stearic acids, are the main compounds of mammal fats, while polyunsaturated fats are prevalent in fish oils [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-15-00651">12</a>,
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-15-00651">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-15-00651">18</a>]. Cooking oils derived from vegetables contain lesser quantities of saturated fats. Oleic acid prevails in olive oil and linoleic acid in corn, sunflower, grape seed, and safflower oil. Coconut and palm kernel oil have notably higher quantities of saturated fats than other oils. Linoleic and linolenic acids are found in abundance in soybean oil [
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-15-00651">18</a>]. Some vegetable oils, such as margarine, undergo many processes of hydrogenation that allow the polyunsaturated fatty acids to assume trans structures, losing their profile of metabolic safety (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-15-00651-t001" href="#ijerph-15-00651-t001">Table 1</a>) [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-15-00651">4</a>,
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-15-00651">12</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The possible alternatives to palm oil use in the food industry are the following [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-15-00651" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-15-00651">19</a>]: (1) saturated animal fats, solid or semi-solid at room temperature, such as butter, lard or tallow: they have been gradually eliminated or substituted for their unfavourable health consequences; (2) saturated vegetable fats, solid at room temperature, such as cocoa butter (the most expensive fat), coconut and palm kernel: their use is limited owing to their correlation with increased plasmatic low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol levels; (3) other vegetable oils, rich in mono/polyunsaturated fats and fluid at room temperature, from fruits (olives), seeds (sunflowers), legumes (peanuts, soy and especially rapeseed) and grains (corn, rice), despite their nutritional qualities, they are disadvantageous in industrial use, owing to both their costs and their limited shelf life. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the substitution of saturated fats with unsaturated ones could be favourable from a nutritional viewpoint, but it involves decreases in crunchiness, palatability and some preservation properties, causing a series of disadvantages, especially in the preparation of bakery products. It is extremely important to recommend that the consumer pay attention to what is reported on the product’s label: the use of palm oil in processed products is often linked to other ingredients, such as animal and vegetable fats. The standards for food labelling require information about the ingredients but not their precise quantities. Generally, however, nutritional labels report information on the content of saturated fats. </p>
</sec>
