<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mixed ANOVA with type-III sums of squares was used to test for differences between sampling years in soil moisture (% of field capacity), light availability (% available PAR) and the proportion of low- and high-light microsites. The model tested for the effects of year (2009 vs. 1994), population site (nested within year) and sampling date (early vs. late) for all variables, and also for the effect of height (canopy vs. mid-canopy) for light measurements, depth (0–10 cm vs. 20–30 cm) for soil moisture measurements and ceptometer transect (nested within year, population, sampling date and height) for percentage available PAR. Measurement height (or depth) and sampling date were included as terms in the analysis because they were of interest as distinct samples of different aspects of the population's environment, though separate analyses conducted with data from the different depths or sampling dates as unique datasets rendered similar results. Transect was treated as a random factor. All other factors were treated as fixed. Initially, all interactions were tested, but because the interactions were not of primary interest, interactions for which 
 <italic>P</italic>&gt; 0.2 in the initial analysis were dropped from subsequent analyses. Because depth was NS for soil moisture, the two depths were pooled in correlation analyses (see below). Because soil samples for nutrient analysis were pooled from each site, depth and sampling date, we did not statistically test for differences among populations in soil properties. Mean nutrient content values were calculated for each population in each year, and these population-mean values for 1994 and 2009 were categorized according to current guidelines for soils in this region (University of Connecticut Soil Testing Lab, 
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://soiltest.uconn.edu/factsheet.php" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://soiltest.uconn.edu/factsheet.php</uri>, University of Massachusetts Soil and Plant Tissue Testing Lab, 
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://soiltest.umass.edu/fact-sheets/soil-test-interpretation-recommendations" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://soiltest.umass.edu/fact-sheets/soil-test-interpretation-recommendations</uri>).
</p>
