<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0250">With the studies depicting different pharmacological potentials of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L., it becomes evident that more studies need to be conducted using different approaches. For example, antidiabetic study conducted by Aljarah and Hammed (2019) using 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> enzyme inhibition studies lack the usage of animal models and human cell lines [
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. In addition, a dose-dependent evaluation of the plant extracts is essential in order to understand the optimum dosage and toxicity. Analysis of binding of individual compounds could be done using molecular docking, which can become a pavement for drug development process. Also, studies need to focus on feasible experimental designs, which can give better yields, less toxicity and more pharmacological effect. If more studies with novel pharmacological models are available, one can compare these studies and suitable methods can be assayed to develop a specific dosage and formulation. The anxiolytic EPM model by Komaki et al. (2016) has highlighted the need for further evaluation of the mechanism behind the observed effect [
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. More elucidations need to be done with respect to the brain activity, secretion of hormones, and blood pressure upon the administration of different doses of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. extracts. Further, a study conducted by Elbahnasawy et al. (2019) has discussed the anthelminthic activity of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> that could be better represented using turkey as an animal model, instead of isolating the parasite from its feces [
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Furthermore, the evaluation of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. activity on dental caries need to be conducted using anti-infective or antibacterial assay primarily because the caries is principally caused by bacteria. In total, these studies depict 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L.as a storehouse of different pharmacological properties attributed to the presence of various phytochemical compounds. Thus, isolation, identification and determination of the pharmacological properties of individual compounds needs to be focused. A summary of the pharmacological properties of different extracts and isolated compounds of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. is given (
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). With this, one can understand the pharmacological evaluations done so far, and can further refine the research methodologies.
</p>
