<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Millennia of co-evolution between plants and pathogenic bacteria have led to complex defense strategies; invaded plants produce myriads of bactericidal and/or antipathogenic secondary metabolites that target different mechanisms. Although, the present African plants review highlights antivirulence properties, it is interesting to note that some of these plants also harbor bactericidal compounds with effects similar to those of conventional antibiotics. A relevant example is 
 <italic>Platostoma rotundifolium</italic> in which compounds that exert bactericidal activities against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> (ursolic and corrosolic acid) coexist with compounds with antivirulence activities against 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (cassipourol, β-sitosterol, and α-amyrin) [
 <xref rid="B70-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Presumably, such a strategy allows plants to increase their probability of success in controlling bacterial invasions; this highlights that combined therapies, i.e., the use of two or multiple drugs with different antibacterial mechanisms of action, may represent an optimal strategy to sustainably struggle against bacterial infections, notably when a pathogen agent has not been specifically identified. In an empirical way, this type of strategy is adopted by tradipractices that often propose mixtures of medicinal plants to treat patients [
 <xref rid="B15-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-antibiotics-09-00830" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Thus, a combination of bactericidal agents and virulence inhibitors is expected to represent an effective therapeutic strategy to efficiently overcome bacterial infections. In this scenario, antivirulence agents would thwart the ability of bacteria to provoke severe infections or to evade immune defenses of the host, which conversely preserves or reinforces the bactericidal effectiveness of antibiotic agents; a rapid clearance of bacteria, including bacterial persister cells, by immune defenses would then be expected at each stage of invasion (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antibiotics-09-00830-f002">Figure 2</xref>). Furthermore, in a synergistic approach, the efficiency of antibiotics could be achieved at lower concentrations, minimizing a selective pressure that is known to generate resistant bacteria spreading with collateral damages towards the commensal and symbiotic bacteria of the host.
</p>
