<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the Coagulase-Negative 
 <italic>Staphylococci</italic> (
 <italic>CoNS</italic>) isolates tested in this study, high sensitivity rate was observed against almost all antibiotics used; however, for clindamycin and cefepime, there was 100% resistance. After testing 
 <italic>CoNS</italic> strains isolated from a university teaching hospital in China (similar to the site of the current study—Korle-Bu Teaching Hospital) for antibiotic resistance, Ma et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-medsci-09-00023" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] observed clindamycin to be among antibiotics having resistance rate between 30 and 70%. In that study, antibiotics were placed into three categories based on resistance levels of the 
 <italic>CoNS</italic> strains to these antibiotics: high resistance (resistance rate &gt;70%), including penicillin G, oxacillin and erythromycin; medium resistance (resistance rate between 30 and 70%), including tetracycline, clindamycin, ciprofloxacin, trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole and chloramphenicol; and low resistance (resistance rate &lt;30%), including rifampicin, ceftizoxime and gentamicin [
 <xref rid="B45-medsci-09-00023" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Also, high resistance rates of 
 <italic>CoNS</italic> have been observed in southern Ethiopia for amoxicillin, amoxicillin-clavunilic acid, ampicillin, and tetracycline as 88.9%, 77.8%, 77.8% and 77.8% respectively [
 <xref rid="B42-medsci-09-00023" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Therefore, the finding of high susceptibility rate against almost all antibiotics used in this study can be considered a positive one since one of the characteristics of 
 <italic>CoNS</italic> is their resistance to multiple antimicrobial agents commonly used for the treatment of 
 <italic>staphylococcal</italic> infections. Also, the high resistance rates of 
 <italic>CoNS</italic> observed in other studies [
 <xref rid="B42-medsci-09-00023" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-medsci-09-00023" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and the fact that 
 <italic>CoNS</italic> have become increasingly recognized as important agents of nosocomial infection [
 <xref rid="B45-medsci-09-00023" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] puts the finding of high susceptibility observed in this study in a promising light.
</p>
