<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Synergistic insecticidal activities existed in many cases, not only between constituents of essential oils, but also between monoterpenoid compounds [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], essential oils [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], and synthetic insecticides [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. In addition, some essential oils or its major constituents can also be used in combination with synthetic pesticides. This can enhance the insecticidal activities of conventional pesticides, while, at the same time, reduce the development of resistance. The mixture of four kinds of essential oils can remarkably increase the toxicity of abamectin, fenpropathrin, matrine and propargite against pest mites [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. It has been reported that zanthoxylum oil, artemisia oil, thuja leaf oil and 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia annua</italic> oil can enhance the toxicity of fipronil against 
 <italic class="italic">Plutella xylostella</italic> at a low concentration of 1 μL/mL [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. It should be noted that although plant essential oils can act as synergists of insecticides, antagonistic action against certain pesticides may also occur. Tong and Bloomquist evaluated the effects of 14 plant essential oils on the toxicity of carbaryl and permethrin against 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes aegypti</italic> and found that six essential oils had significant synergistic effect on carbaryl. Paradoxically, all of the 14 essential oils decreased the toxicity of permethrin [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Blends of 
 <italic class="italic">S. montana</italic> essential oil and 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigra</italic> essential oil (1:1) were also found to have an antagonistic effect [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. These findings reminded us that not only the synergism but also the antagonism should be taken into account when we use essential oils to control pests. Whether thyme oil and its major constituents have the synergistic or antagonistic effect on other essential oils and conventional pesticides is the focus of our future studies.
</p>
