<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53">
 <italic>A. verlotiorum Lamotte</italic>, (Asteraceae), an entire plant might be used for the cure and prevention of leucorrhoea, tonic emmenagogue, dermal infections, fever, influenza (Sussman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR333">1980</xref>; Wong Ting Fook 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR364">1980</xref>; Adjanohoun et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR387">1983</xref>; Fakim 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">1990</xref>; Gurib-Fakim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">1993</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">1996a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">b</xref>). The chemical constituents obtained from this pant also employed as hemostatic, stomachic, to control dysmenorrhea, metrorrhagia, antispasmodic and skin ailments. The leave contents of the plant suggest an essential oil which contains abundant chemical constituent like germacrene that obtained in the yield of around 23.6% (Gurib-Fakim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">1996a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">b</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">1997</xref>). 
 <italic>A. annua</italic> plants kill the parasites integrated with malaria and dengue fever. Explorers commenced by imparting artemisia extract against the parasite larvae originated from the mosquito’s kin 
 <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> female (malaria) together larvae originated from 
 <italic>Ades aegypti</italic> which disseminates dengue fever. The extract of 
 <italic>A. annua</italic> demonstrated the tenacious larvicidal effects, remedy for fever, liver gall bladder disorders, now it is being assessed for flatworm infection as well as contamination produced by schistosomiasis (Biesen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2010</xref>; Hossain et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">2014</xref>; Noori et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR245">2014</xref>; Darvishpor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2018</xref>; Zeb et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR379">2018</xref>). It is also estimated by some explorers that a particular methanol extract of 
 <italic>A. pallens</italic> mitigates APAP (Acetaminophen) persuaded renal poisoning in rats via showing its anti-inflammatory as well as antioxidative properties (Honmore et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">2014</xref>). 
 <italic>A. capillaris</italic> plant is also used to control atopic dermatitis (AD) that is an inflammatory, chronically relapsing, and non-contagious stage. It is also employed as medication for treating pruritic and skin related problems (Ha et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2014</xref>).
</p>
