<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This paper describes a study regarding the association of 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">piperita</italic> EO with several antimicrobial agents against a large panel of bacteria and fungi strains. Gentamicin and ampicillin were chosen as antibacterial agents, whereas amphotericin B, fluconazole and miconazole were chosen as antifungals. On the whole, 
 <strike class="strike">a</strike> synergism between 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">piperita</italic> EO and antimicrobials was found. The FIC indices for the association of gentamicin and 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">piperita</italic> EO indicate, indeed, a very strong synergistic mode of action for all tested Gram-positive and Gram-negative strains. As a consequence, the combination of these two compounds allows for a significant reduction of the amount of gentamicin needed to inhibit bacteria strains. For example, a 33-fold reduction for gentamicin for 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus cereus</italic> ATCC 10876 (FICI = 0.08), a 50-fold reduction for 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</italic> ATCC 6633 (FICI = 0.07) and 4-fold reduction for 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 43300 (methicillin resistant 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>) (FICI = 0.30) were observed. Mixtures of ampicillin and 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">piperita</italic> EO show marked synergistic effects against 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli ATCC</italic> 25922 (FICI = 0.08) and 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus subtili</italic>s ATCC 6633 (FICI = 0.13). Conversely, no evident synergistic effect was observed for ampicillin (FICI = 0.55) against Gram-negative strains as 
 <italic class="italic">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> ATCC 19606, 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 19833, and 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 27853. The results against Gram-negative bacteria as 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> are of particular interest as these bacteria are difficult to treat with commonly employed antibacterial drugs. Generally, a synergistic effect was also observed against yeast strains, although it was less evident than against bacteria. This result may conceivably depend on the poor interaction between the EO with azoles and amphotericin B. Further investigation would allow a more complete understanding of the antimicrobial potential of this association and may be useful for the preparation of new agents for the cure of infections caused by these important pathogens.
</p>
