<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Eimeria tenella</italic> pathogens belong to the Eimeriidae family and the Apicomplexa phylum, which invades the cecal epithelium of birds, resulting in massive injury and economic loss. We evaluated the ameliorative effect of 
   <italic>Rumex nervosus</italic> (RN) leaf powder against 
   <italic>E. tenella</italic>-induced coccidiosis in broiler chickens. Chickens infected with 
   <italic>E. tenella</italic> were treated with 1, 3, and 5 g/kg RN, respectively. Salinomycin sodium (Sacox
   <sup>®</sup>), an anti-coccidial agent, was used as a reference drug. Results have shown that RN contains Gallic acid and 13 phytochemicals, which require further investigation in vitro or in vivo to ascertain whether the anti-coccidial activity, if there, is a direct or indirect link to reduce the number of fecal oocysts in the bird. The lesion score and bloody diarrhea were also decreased after infection. Moreover, the coccidial challenge adversely affected (
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) the performance measurements in the RN- and Sacox-treated groups compared with the uninfected–unmedicated control (NC) group. Interestingly, these parameters were positively affected by natural and synthetic treatments compared with infected–unmedicated control (PC); however, the values were not significant. In conclusion, RN at the highest dose is a promising shrub with a moderate anti-coccidial activity when used to cure avian coccidiosis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>Coccidiosis a huge economic burden in poultry farms where the pathogen 
   <italic>Eimeria</italic> harms animal well-being and survival. Besides synthetic anti-coccidial drugs, natural herbs appear to be an alternative way to prevent avian coccidiosis. 
   <italic>Rumex nervosus</italic> (RN), a phytogenic shrub, has received considerable attention in recent years due to its significant anti-microbial effects; however, limited knowledge exists about its potential anti-coccidial functions. This study was conducted to evaluate the prophylactic and therapeutic activities of RN leaf powder in broilers infected with 
   <italic>Eimeria tenella</italic>. Infected chickens received a commercial diet containing 1, 3, or 5 g RN powder/kg diet compared to infected broilers that treated with Sacox (PC) or compared to uninfected broilers that received a commercial diet alone (NC). Results showed that RN powder significantly (
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) reduced the lesion scores and suppressed the output of oocysts per gram (OPG) in chickens’ feces. Although RN was unable to minimize the weight gain loss due to emeriosis, RN at level 1 g improved the feed conversion ratio. Therefore, RN powder, at 5 g, possesses moderate anti-coccidial effects and hence could be used to treat avian coccidiosis in field conditions; however, further studies are required to investigate, in vitro or in vivo, the anti-coccidial potential of active ingredients.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
