<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To allow species identification of the 26 bacterial endophyte genomes, the genus of each bacterial isolate was initially assigned by 16S rRNA gene comparison to the NCBI BLAST database coupled with genome identification using the taxonomic sequence classification system Kraken2 v2.0.6-beta and RefSeq complete bacterial genomes. Using this preliminary identification as a guide, full species assignment was then achieved by combining average nucleotide identity (ANI) and core-gene phylogenomics. The MinHash-based ANI tool FastANI (Jain 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) was used to identify RefSeq genomes of the same genus with high sequence similarity to each endophyte isolate. RefSeq genomes of each genus were downloaded using a NCBI genome download script available at GitHub (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kblin/ncbi-genome-download" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/kblin/ncbi-genome-download</ext-link>). Up to 30 genomes with &gt;90% sequence identity to each isolate, in addition to other endophyte isolates of the same genus, were passed to an alignment-based ANI tool, PyANI (Pritchard 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) for enhanced ANI accuracy. A core-gene phylogeny was constructed for each genus comprising genomes (Refseq and endophyte isolates) with &gt;95% sequence identity to a given isolate, in addition to type strains and additional species representatives. Core-gene alignments were generated with Roary v3.13.0 (Page 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) implementing MAFFT v7.407 (Katoh and Standley 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and using genome annotations produced with Prokka v1.12. Maximum-likelihood phylogenetic trees were constructed using RaxML v8.2.12 with a general time reversible substitution model and gamma model of rate heterogeneity; and visualised with FigTree (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/</ext-link>). In addition, for comparison genome sequences were also uploaded to the Type (strain) Genome Server (TYGS) bioinformatics platform available (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tygs.dsmz.de" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://tygs.dsmz.de</ext-link>) for whole genome-based taxonomic analysis (Meier-Kolthoff and Göker 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). This platform provides both species assignment and digital DNA–DNA hybridisation (dDDH) values to the closest type strain genomes available.
</p>
