<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase-interacting multifunctional protein 2 (AIMP2), a scaffold in the multi-tRNA synthetase complex (MSC), dissociates from the MSC and influences the activity of the p53, TGF-β, tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α), and Wingless/int-1 (WNT) signaling pathways [
 <xref rid="B41-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. A splicing variant of AIMP2 lacking exon 2 (AIMP2-DX2) correlates positively with cancer by compromising the tumor-suppressive function of native AIMP2 through competitive interactions with p53 fuse-binding protein (FBP) and TNF receptor-associated factor 2 (TRAF2) [
 <xref rid="B43-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Lim et al. showed that AIMP2-DX2 binds with heat shock protein 70 (HSP70) and is stabilized by blocking the seven in absentia homolog 1 (Siah1)-dependent ubiquitination of AIMP2-DX2, which leads to cancer progression in vivo [
 <xref rid="B44-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Representative AIMP2-DX2 inhibitors (
 <bold>28</bold>~
 <bold>30</bold>) are described in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biomolecules-10-01625-f011">Figure 11</xref>. Based on this mode of action of AIMP2-DX2, the protein–protein interaction inhibitor BC-DXI-495 (
 <bold>28</bold>) was found to specifically inhibit the AIMP2-DX2 + HSP70 interaction and suppress cancer cell growth in vitro (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 4.2 μM, luciferase assay; EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 14.2 μM, cell viability assay, A549 cells) and AIMP2-DX2-induced tumor growth in vivo (~50% decrease, 50 mpk, ip [intraperitoneal injection], 2 weeks, H460 stably expressing AIMP2-DX2 WT [wild type], BALB/cSLC mice). Consecutively, Sivaraman et al. reported BC-DXI-843 (
 <bold>29</bold>), which was optimized from BC-DXI-495 [
 <xref rid="B45-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; 
 <bold>29</bold> significantly improved in vitro activity in luciferase and cell viability assays (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.92 μM, luciferase assay; EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.2 μM, cell viability assay, A549 cells). The in vivo efficacy of 
 <bold>29</bold> in the H460 xenograft mouse model was comparable with that of 
 <bold>28</bold> by inhibiting ~60% tumor growth (50 mpk, bid [bis in die, twice a day], ip, 2 weeks). In the same context, Lee et al. separately developed the 2-aminophenylpyrimidine derivative 
 <bold>30</bold> for AIMP2-DX2 interaction inhibition with &gt;80% tumor growth inhibition in an H460 xenograft mouse model [
 <xref rid="B46-biomolecules-10-01625" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].
</p>
