<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An invasion of the Asian tiger mosquito, 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>, into the UK is a major public health concern. This species is not only an aggressive nuisance biter, but also a known vector of arboviruses such as dengue, chikungunya, yellow fever, and Zika [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The ability of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes to lay desiccation-resistant eggs has enabled their introduction into cities across the globe, often via used tire shipments [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. According to the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> populations have already established throughout the vast majority of Italy and southern France [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Although this species has not yet established in the UK, it has been introduced in Kent, a coastal county in the southeast of the UK, where 37 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> eggs were found in September of 2016 [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Owing to the warming climate, the UK is expected to become increasingly suitable for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> establishment; projections of climate and human population conditions into future decades suggest that if introduced, the vector species could establish throughout most of England and southern Wales during the 2060s [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Another recent model predicts that the UK will report 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> presence by either 2050 or 2080, depending on the patterns of future greenhouse gas emissions [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
