<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Predation by copepods has been identified as a biological method for controlling 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> in Europe following the success of past field trials [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Cyclopoid copepods from India, the US, Australia, Vietnam, and Italy, including copepod species from the genera 
 <italic>Macrocyclops</italic> and 
 <italic>Mesocyclops</italic>, have proven to be effective predators of local mosquito larvae [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In the UK, laboratory experiments using cyclopoid copepods from Northern Ireland against 
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> mosquito larvae from Surrey, UK and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> larvae from Montpellier, France have supported the use of copepods as biocontrol agents [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Previous work indicates that the attack rates of 
 <italic>Macrocyclops albidus</italic> and 
 <italic>Megacyclops viridis</italic> predators against 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>pipiens</italic> prey tend to increase with temperature [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, the use of UK copepods as predators of invasive 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> larvae has not been thoroughly examined over the range of temperatures that the invasive larvae are predicted to experience. Due to the potentially negative impacts of exporting copepods to non-native regions for biocontrol purposes [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], it is important to investigate the performance of copepods local to the predicted sites of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> establishment: London and South East England [
 <xref rid="pone.0246178.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
