<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p class="p"> The plant kingdom is rich with a numerous number of plants with various medical properties which can be used to treat various medical issues. Sri Lanka is a country full of biodiversity which is gifted with many plant resources. It has a rich history of traditional medicine systems consisting of Ayurveda, Unani, and Deshiya Chikitsa, where these plant resources are used as remedies for the diseases. In the traditional medicine system, various plant parts such as leaves, roots, fruits, flowers, and bark are used to treat disease conditions. Although less attention is paid to the medicinal importance of the flowers, some of them have been used to treat many diseases from the ancient time. Some properties of the flowers may differ from the properties of the other plant parts. For example,
   <italic class="italic"> Sesbania grandiflora</italic> (Katuru murunga) flowers have shown anticancer properties against various cell models whereas some flowers have shown antispermatogenic properties. Flowers of
   <italic class="italic"> Woodfordia floribunda </italic>(Militta) are added as fermenting agents in the preparation of Arishtas in Ayurveda. Also the most popular Clove oil is obtained from the flower buds of
   <italic class="italic"> Syzygium aromaticum </italic>(Karabu-neti) which is used to treat toothaches since it has antibiotic and antiseptic properties. This article gives an overview of herbal flowers used in the traditional medicine system of Sri Lanka and their pharmacological importance.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title"> Method</title>
  <p class="p"> A comprehensive literature survey was done on the medicinally important flowers in Sri Lanka. Data was collected from Libraries of Ayurveda in Sri Lanka and from scientific databases.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title"> Results</title>
  <p class="p"> According to the survey many flowers are used as astringent, cardiac tonic, and febrifuge. Also some flowers are used to treat dysentery, diarrhoea, and indigestion. Some flowers are useful in the treatment of bleeding piles while some are useful in the treatment of asthma and bronchitis.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title"> Conclusion</title>
  <p class="p"> It was revealed that there are many flowers with valuable therapeutic effects. Traditional medicine systems prevailing in Sri Lanka have made use of these flowers with therapeutic effects to cure so many diseases. The review of medicinally important herbal flowers provides knowledge and pharmacological leads which will help for the wellbeing of the human beings. Although there are phytochemical studies done to identify the chemical compounds on some flowers, chemical composition of many flowers remains unrevealed. So further studies need to be done to identify the chemical composition of these flowers.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
