<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The therapeutic benefits of ginkgo (
 <italic>Ginkgo biloba</italic> L., Ginkgoaceae) extracts have long since been known, with a long-standing history of use in traditional Chinese medicine (Chassagne et al., 2019). More recently, experimental and clinical studies have revealed the potential benefits of ginkgo for a wide range of pathological conditions, including neuroprotective activities (Singh et al., 2012; Mohanta et al., 2014; Montes et al., 2015; Datta et al., 2017; Mojaverrostami et al., 2018; Shu et al., 2019). Regarding its chemical composition, two main groups of bioactive metabolites are considered responsible for ginkgo medicinal effects: terpene lactones (Ginkgolides A, B, C and J and bilobalide) and ginkgo flavones (quercetin, kaempferol and iso-rhamnetin glycosides as the main flavonoids, together with biflavonoids ginkgetin/isoginkgetin; 
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>
 </bold>) (Wilkinson and Fraunfelder, 2011; Ude et al., 2013). The pharmacologically active ginkgo leaf extracts are available as standardised preparations EGb 761 and LI1370 (Evans, 2013).Free radical quenching properties, reduction of platelet aggregation and improved blood flow of ginkgo extracts are attributed to the antioxidant and radical scavenging properties of ginkgo flavonoids and terpenoids, along with the potent platelet activating factor inhibition of ginkgolides (Wilkinson and Fraunfelder, 2011; Singh et al., 2012; Sin et al., 2013). In addition, flavonoids probably reduce oxidative damage to lipid membranes (Singh et al., 2012). Consequently, due to vascular factors and oxidative damage are hypothesized as potential mechanisms in AMD pathology, an interest in using ginkgo extract has aroused for AMD treatment. Currently, ginkgo extract is considered safe within the daily dose range (Sin et al., 2013). It is worth mentioning, however, the increased risk of bleeding because ginkgolides are potent platelet activating factor antagonists (Evans, 2013). 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments have shown the beneficial effects of EGb 761 on functional retinal impairment, retinal microcirculation and retinal tissue protection from oxidative stress (Spadiene et al., 2013; Martinez-Solis et al., 2019). Preliminary clinical studies have investigated the efficacy of ginkgo extracts (Evans, 2013), including two randomized controlled trials with positive effects on vision in patients with AMD (
 <bold>
  <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
 </bold>). According to Evans (2013) and Sin et al. (2013), deeper research on ginkgo clinical efficacy should be carried out.
</p>
