<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our research addressed the question of whether nonnative species will be better potential range-expanders than native species because of their propensity to have less negative plant–soil microbe interactions, or a net positive plant–microbe interactions, after invading a new area (
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Diez 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). The germination success of the nonnative species, 
 <italic>E. uniflora</italic>, across all temperature and soil treatments, underscores the invasive potential of this nonnative species (
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Liu 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Langeland 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2008
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Stricker and Stiling 2013</xref>). Invasiveness may depend on the physiology of the invaders, and their ‘pre-adaptations’ (
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Rejmanek and Richardson 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">Parker and Hay 2005</xref>). In particular, 
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Rejmanek and Richardson (1996)</xref> found that the best measures of invasiveness of 
 <italic>Pinus</italic> species were factors of mean seed mass, minimum juvenile period and the average time between large seed-producing events, with the most invasive species having lower average seed mass, shorter juvenile periods and short times between when large crops of seeds are released. It is relatively intuitive that these characters confer a greater degree of invasiveness to a given species. If a species reaches maturity quickly, devotes less energy to each individual seed, and has short intervals between seed crops, this may quickly result in the outnumbering of other co-occurring species, especially in disturbed, open habitats. Our invasive study species had extremely high levels of germination and accrued a large amount of biomass in the 12 weeks following germination, relative to the native congeners.
</p>
