<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The biological activities of some 
 <italic>Nepeta</italic> species endemic to Turkey, namely, 
 <italic>Nepeta italica</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>cadmea</italic>, 
 <italic>N. nuda</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>glandulifera</italic>, 
 <italic>N. meyeri, N. conferta,</italic> and 
 <italic>N. cadmea</italic> have been previously investigated [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, endemic 
 <italic>Nepeta baytopii</italic> has received little scientific attention. In an earlier study conducted by Dirmenci et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], the morphological description and threatened categories of four 
 <italic>Nepeta</italic> species were reported. In their study, 
 <italic>N. baytopii</italic> were described as perennial with a height of 25–70 cm. The plant has longer-spreading hairs and sessile glands. Leaves are ovate-triangular, and the colour of the corolla is lilac. In the paper, the plant is described as an endangered species based on IUCN categories. In another study performed by Kılıc et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-01176" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], three 
 <italic>Nepeta</italic> species were investigated for determining the essential oil composition, and one of the species was 
 <italic>N. baytopii</italic>. In light of the above-mentioned point, this study was designed to provide additional data and novel insights on 
 <italic>N. baytopii.</italic> In this sense, this work focuses on the evaluation of the hexane, ethyl acetate, methanol, water/methanol, and water extracts and essential oil prepared from 
 <italic>N. baytopii</italic> aerial parts. Biological properties, namely, antioxidant and enzyme-inhibitory properties of all extracts and essential oil, were determined by using in vitro spectrophotometric methods. To determine the cytotoxic effects of the methanol and water extracts, three cell lines (HepG2, B16A5 and S 17) were used. Moreover, methanol and water extracts and essential oils were chemically characterised by using chromatographic methods. It is anticipated that gathered data herein will contribute towards establishing baseline data on this endemic species with significant medicinal potential.
</p>
