<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Purpose:</italic>
  </bold> The aim of the present study was to investigate the chemical properties of wild Tagetes minuta L. (family Astreacea) collected from Northern Iran during the flowering period concerning the chemical combination of the essential oil along with its antioxidant properties and composition of fatty acids.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Methods:</italic>
  </bold> The essential oil of the plant was extracted by a Clevenger approach and analyzed using gas chromatography-mass spectroscopy (Capillary HP-5ms GC/MS Column). Fatty acid contents of this species as a result of hexane extraction were analyzed by means of gas chromatography (GC-FID) while their phenolic contents were analyzed by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC-UV). In this research also the total polyphenolic (TPC) and total flavonoid (TFC) content was determined spectrophotometrically while the antioxidant activity was evaluated using the DPPH (2,2'-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl) bleaching method.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Results:</italic>
  </bold> GC/MS analysis of the essential oil identified monoterpenoid fractions (52.13%) as the main components and among them dihydrotagetone (23.44%) and spathulenol (10.56%) were the predominant compounds. The evaluation of fatty acid content revealed that saturated acids were prevailing compounds and the major components are: palmitic (30.74±0.4%) and capric (24.15±0.5%) acids. Chromatographic separation of its phenolic contents indicated that this herb contain sinapic acid derivatives rather than hydroxybenzoic acid derivatives. Also the essential oil showed an effective antioxidant capacity (TPC=153.27±0.9 mg/g, TFC=63.79±0.1 mg/g, IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 29.31±0.8 µg/ml).
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>
   <italic>Conclusion:</italic>
  </bold> The results proved that the plant could be used for nutritional and pharmaceutical purposes.
 </p>
</abstract>
