<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Traditional healers and the community have used the roots of 
  <italic>Ajuga integrifolia</italic> for the treatment of diabetes mellitus. It is not scientifically validated for its antidiabetic activity previously. Therefore, the objective of the present study was to determine the hypoglycemic and antidiabetic activity of 
  <italic>Ajuga integrifolia</italic>. 
  <italic>Ajuga integrifolia</italic> roots' crude extract and solvent fractions were prepared. The doses of 100 mg/kg, 200 mg/kg, and 400 mg/kg of crude root extract and solvent fractions were used on normoglycemic, oral glucose loaded, and streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice models to determine their hypoglycemic and antihyperglycemic activities. The crude extract and solvent fractions' effect on bodyweight was also evaluated on streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice. A standard drug in all cases was glibenclamide (5 mg/kg), and the blood glucose level was measured by using a glucose meter. Data analysis was performed by using Statistical Package for Social Sciences version 21. One-way analysis of variance followed by Tukey's post hoc multiple comparison test was used to analyze the data. 
  <italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. Hydromethanolic crude extract and its aqueous fraction of 
  <italic>Ajuga integrifolia</italic> root showed a considerable blood glucose lowering activity at all doses. Both the repeated daily doses of the crude extract and the repeated daily doses of the aqueous fraction of 
  <italic>Ajuga integrifolia</italic> root extract revealed the similar effect in lowering the fasting blood glucose level in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice models. It was also found that groups treated with the 
  <italic>Ajuga integrifolia</italic> at the doses of 200 mg/kg and 400 mg/kg showed significant (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) bodyweight improvement at the 14
  <sup>th</sup> day of treatment compared to the respective baseline bodyweight, and the diabetic control group showed significant (
  <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) reduction in bodyweight at the 14
  <sup>th</sup> day compared to the baseline. This study revealed that crude extract and solvent fractions of 
  <italic>Ajuga integrifolia</italic> root possess significant antidiabetic activity which supports its traditional use for the treatment of diabetes mellitus.
 </p>
</abstract>
