<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Background:</bold> Essential oils (EOs) have shown antimicrobial, antioxidant, and antiproliferative activity, which may, alone or in combination with other substances, potentially be used for the development of new drugs. However, their chemical variability, depending on the species, varieties, or geographical origin (among other factors) determines different bioactivities that need to be evaluated. 
  <bold class="bold">Methods:</bold> The antioxidant activity of 
  <italic class="italic">Corymbia citriodora</italic> and eight 
  <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> species EOs was determined using two different methods: the scavenging ability of 2,2′-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulphonic acid) (ABTS
  <sup class="sup">+•</sup>) and peroxyl free radicals or oxygen radical absorbance capacity (ORAC). Antibacterial activity was evaluated using the microorganisms 
  <italic class="italic">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> (strains D39 and TIGR4), and 
  <italic class="italic">Haemophilus influenza</italic> (strain DSM 9999). The essential oils’ minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) was assessed using a microdilution method. The antiproliferative activity was determined using the THP-1 cell line (human acute monocytic leukaemia) with methylthiazolyldiphenyl-tetrazolium bromide assay (MTT). 
  <bold class="bold">Results:</bold>
  <italic class="italic">Corymbia citriodora</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus viminalis</italic> EOs showed the highest ABTS and peroxyl free radical scavenging capacity. 
  <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus globulus</italic> EO showed a high potential to treat 
  <italic class="italic">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> infections. 
  <italic class="italic">Haemophilus influenzae</italic> was the respiratory pathogen that showed the highest resistance to all EOs, including tea tree EO. After 96 h of incubation, at 25 μg/mL, 
  <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus radiata</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus viminalis</italic> EOs showed highest cytotoxic activity against the THP-1 cell line. 
  <bold class="bold">Conclusions:</bold> Despite their specific bioactivities, no single EO showed simultaneously good antioxidant, antimicrobial, and antiproliferative activity.
 </p>
</abstract>
