<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The subject of fungal cell wall-originating BDG contribution to the circulation has been well described in numerous publications, including multiple meta-analyses [
 <xref rid="B43-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. This occurs as a result of the normal processes of the fungal life cycle in which the cyclical processes of wall polysaccharide synthesis and degradation occur [
 <xref rid="B38-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Minute quantities of wall material, including BDG, are sloughed into the peri-fungal environment and migrate to the circulation. In the case of fungemia, in which the fungi are growing in the bloodstream, the contribution to the circulation is direct. The longitudinal characterization of circulating BDG titers typically demonstrates rising BDG levels early in infection, followed by slow declines which may only return to baseline well after successful disease resolution [
 <xref rid="B50-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Another route of entry to the circulation was described by Hong et al. 2004, among others, in which phagocytosed fungal cells are degraded by hydrolytic processes within the phagolysosomes followed by externalization of degraded material [
 <xref rid="B23-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. BDG from phagocytosed yeast sacculi was demonstrated to be processed by macrophages both in vivo and in vitro. In the latter experiments, externalized BDG titers rose in the cell culture supernatants while declining within the cells. This may be a process that influences the observed slow decline of circulating BDG post-therapeutic success [
 <xref rid="B52-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
