<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study was designed to determine the immunomodulatory activity of the concoction of 
 <italic>C. sativum</italic> and 
 <italic>C. fenestratum</italic>. This was first ascertained by the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> anti-inflammatory activity using the carrageenan-induced rat paw edema model and the results showed a significant anti-inflammatory activity of the concoction. Since HED of concoction showed a significant level of anti-inflammatory activity at both first and second phases of inflammation, it was selected as the optimum dose for subsequent experiments to determine possible mechanisms of its anti-inflammatory activity. Further, this study demonstrated significant inhibition of nitric oxide and superoxide anion production by rat peritoneal cells and also 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> membrane stabilizing capacity reflecting their possible contribution to the anti-inflammatory mechanisms. The specific inhibition of the expression of iNOS by the oral administration of the concoction confirmed the marked decrease of NO production by the rat peritoneal cells. The immunomodulatory activity was also shown by the enhancing effect on specific immune responses as evident by the high antibody titers raised against SRBC antigens following oral administration of concoction. This study reports for the first time the immunomodulatory activity of the concoction of 
 <italic>C. sativum</italic> and 
 <italic>C. fenestratum,</italic> including 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> anti-inflammatory activity with mechanisms, that is, inhibition of ROS and RNS production and also the inhibition of iNOS gene expression by rat peritoneal cells and the immunomodulation to enhance antigen specific antibody response. Further, the findings of this study validate the use of the concoction (or decoction of 
 <italic>C. sativum</italic> and 
 <italic>C. fenestratum</italic>) for its traditional claims and use for treatment of cold and as a treatment at early stage of infections.
</p>
