<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have shown that CC leads to an increase in the number of harmful bacteria in the soil, a significant decrease in the number of beneficial bacteria, and has a severe impact on the soil microenvironment (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Caporaso et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">She et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2017</xref>). Intercropping can effectively increase the number of beneficial bacteria in the soil and reduce the proportion of harmful fungi (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Negawo and Beyene, 2017</xref>). Furthermore, it has been shown that the increased number of fungi in the soil when an intercropping system is used may significantly improve soil fertility compared to when a single crop is grown (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Machado, 2009</xref>). The results showed intercropping with turmeric or ginger did not change the dominant phyla in the microbial community, but did significantly change the abundance of a number of different microbial species (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). The dominant microbial phyla, such as Actinobacteria, Verrucomicrobia, Acidobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Mortierellomycota and Glomeromycota, were similar to those reported by previous studies (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Chen L. et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen P. et al., 2020</xref>). Interspecies interactions may affect the abundance of some soil microbial populations, but they do not affect population diversity (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2019</xref>). Previous research has shown that the above-mentioned dominant bacterial groups participate in soil N and P cycling (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Fierer et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Pham et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Sekar et al., 2018</xref>), which improves the growth of medicinal plants. Actinomycetes found for ecological sites in the soil or the plant rhizosphere environment directly prevents pathogens from infecting plants, and reduces the number of pathogens through spatial competition and antibiosis (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Samac et al., 2003</xref>). Previous Study have found that Actinomyces could secrete more the extracellular hydrolase, and destroys the cell walls and cell membrane of pathogenic fungi through the action of hydrolase, which reduced the pathogenicity and population density of pathogenic bacteria, and directly inhibits the normal growth of pathogenic bacteria (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Ligon et al., 2000</xref>).
</p>
