<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar to heat, there are currently no RCTs that have investigated the efficacy of medicinal cannabis for endometriosis; however, emergent evidence for its use in managing chronic pain has been reported (
 <xref rid="hoaa028-B54" ref-type="bibr">Klimkiewicz and Jasinska, 2018</xref>). There exists a plausible rationale for the use of medicinal cannabis in endometriosis-associated pain and concurrent symptoms via modulation of the endocannabinoid system, which can impact neuropathic and inflammatory pain, along with the psychological experience of the pain (
 <xref rid="hoaa028-B15" ref-type="bibr">Bouaziz 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). A recent survey of Australian women with confirmed endometriosis noted that 1 in 10 respondents was utilizing cannabis, for symptom management, with cannabis rated as the highest self-management strategy for the pain of all those assessed (
 <xref rid="hoaa028-B6" ref-type="bibr">Armour 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019b
 </xref>). Furthermore, significant improvements in sleep, nausea, gastrointestinal upset, anxiety and depression were self-reported, along with 56% of women in the cannabis-using cohort being able to reduce their pharmaceutical usage by 50% or more (
 <xref rid="hoaa028-B82" ref-type="bibr">Sinclair 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). Medicinal cannabis is not risk-free but the majority of reported adverse events tend to be mild and self-limiting (
 <xref rid="hoaa028-B62" ref-type="bibr">Lintzeris 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>). Potential cannabis dependence (reported in 4–9% of users) (
 <xref rid="hoaa028-B3" ref-type="bibr">Anthony 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="hoaa028-B88" ref-type="bibr">Volkow 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>) and possible psychosis must also be considered in heavy, chronic users, although whether this applies to medicinal products, as it is in illicit use, is unclear at this time.
</p>
