<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Patients have mainly renal or adrenal disease as the root cause oftheir raised blood pressure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].Other than this Factors like Nitric oxide NO and cardiac output and peripheral vascular resistance also play important role in hypertension [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].Over aim to write this review is to collect information on the anti-hypertensive effects of natural herbs in animal studies and human involvement as well as to recapitulate the underlying mechanisms, from the bottom of cell culture and ex-vivo tissue data. According to WHO natural herbs/shrubs are widely used in increasing order to treat almost all the ailments of the human body, worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The type of phytochemical constituents present in any natural plant makes it useful to treat a particular ailment or group of ailments. The treatment with medicinal herbs/shrubs is essential and cheaper treatment with lesser rates of side effects as compared to allopathic treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Hypertension is a critical health problem and worse other cardiovascular diseases. Diuretics, alone or with other antihypertensive agents are in use regularly, to decline increased blood pressure by decreasing blood volume at the cost of dangerous and undesirable side effects. Interestingly, the use of drugs from natural sources as alternativesis the best choice for the treatment of hypertension and other diseases related to it [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Dubick explained that Plants are the regular industrial units for the invention of chemical constituents, they used as an immunity booster to enhance the natural capacity of the body to fight against different health problems as well as herbal medicines and food products also. In cultural, religious and folk traditions, herbal plants are explained as curative remedies for almost all of the ailments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Since 1970, native plant medicines are also included in World Health Organization policies mainly for developing countries of the world. According to the United Nations World Health Organization, 80% population of the world (around 5.6 billion people) consumes medicines from natural plants for major health concerns [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. This review provides a bird’s eye analysis primarily on the traditional utilization, phytochemical constituents and pharmacological values of medicinal herbs used to normalize hypertension [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].
</p>
