<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Antimicrobial Activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The microbiological activity of essential oils was studied in the Microbiology Laboratory of the Faculty Estacio SEAMA. It used two strains of bacteria, one Gram-positive (
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, ATCC 25923) and another,Gram-negative (
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>, ATCC 25922), being performed according to the rules and procedures of Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) [
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. The test for evaluation of the antibacterial activity was performed in triplicate.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec2.7.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7.1. Culture Media</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The medium Mueller-Hinton (MH) agar was used for antimicrobial activity assays and prepared according to manufacturer's instructions, followed by release of 25 mL of agar medium per Petri dish of 90 × 15 mm.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.7.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7.2. Bacterial Suspension and Inoculum</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The growth of Mueller-Hinton agar, after incubation for 24 hours at 37°C, peaked up from 2 to 4 colonies in 1 mL of sterile 0.85% saline solution, until a turbidity similar to the 0.5 McFarland scale obtained a final concentration of 1,5 × 10
   <span class="sup">8</span> UFC/mL.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.7.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7.3. Evaluation of Antimicrobial Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate the antimicrobial activity of essential oils, we used the disk agar diffusion method. Each bacterial suspension was plated (in triplicate) with the aid of a stereodisposable swab across the surface of Mueller-Hinton agar. A solution was prepared with a solubilized concentration of 250 mg/mL with Tween 80 and then, dilutions were held to obtain concentrations of 100, 50, and 10 mg/mL. After that, it was soaked on filter paper discs (Whatman, type 3) of 6 mm diameter each 10 L concentrations, respectively. After incubation of the plates at 35°C for 24 hours, a reading of the results by measuring the halo formed around disks containing the oil was performed. The result of each dilution, the average of the three measurements, and susceptible halo of an equal size or greater than 8 mm diameter were considered [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The disk-diffusion experiment was controlled by using disks containing the antibiotics reference: cefoxitin, oxacillin, and gentamicin to verify the sensitivity of the test microorganism and negative controls were impregnated with discs containing water and Tween 80.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
