<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The fixed oil of 
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. was evaluated for its acute toxicity in mice. Oral dose administration of the oil in the mice showed a LD
 <sub>50</sub> value of 28.8 ml/kg, while intraperitoneally administration exhibited a LD
 <sub>50</sub> value of 2.06 ml/kg (
 <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr">Zaoui et al., 2002</xref>). It was observed that oral and intraperitoneal administration of the oil at all doses resulted in behavioral perturbations with immediate agitation, temporary writhing, followed by a quiet attitude period and sedation. Diarrhea was generally observed and the animals died 12 h after oil administration. In a chronic toxicity study, the rats were administered a daily woral dose of 2 ml/kg body wt. for 12 weeks. The leukocyte and platelet counts were observed and showed that there was a significant difference as compared to the control (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Besides, the platelet and leukocyte counts were significantly reduced as compared to the control (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). The compound believed to cause toxicity in 
 <italic>Petasites hybridus</italic> (L.) G. Gaertn., B. Mey. and Schreb. is pyrrolizidine alkaloids (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Dreger et al., 2009</xref>). The secondary metabolite in the plants known with its hepatotoxic, cardiotoxic, pneumotoxic and nephrotoxic properties provides a defense mechanism against herbivores. Acute toxicity study of 
 <italic>P. hybridus</italic> extract in Wistar rats revealed oral LD
 <sub>50</sub> value of ≥2500 mg/kg body weight with 833–1250-fold, and intraperitoneal LD
 <sub>50</sub> value of approximately 1000 mg/kg body weight with 333–500-fold higher than the recommended human doses of common butterbur extract (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Danesch and Rittinghausen, 2003</xref>). Hemorrhagic necrosis, hepatomegaly, and ascites were found to be the signs of acute toxicity. Moreover, hepatic veins obstruction that results in venous-occlusive disease while in chronic poisoning, liver failure due to necrosis, fibrosis, and cirrhosis were some of the effects observed in subacute toxicity testing (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Aydın et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
