<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Maltitol is a disaccharide polyol, consisting of sorbitol and glucose, with a sweetness of 75–90% that of sucrose [
 <xref rid="B78-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>]. It is used in the food industry for the production of hard candies, chewing gum, chocolates, baked goods, and ice cream. Maltitol absorption ranges from 5–80%, however, several authorities have agreed to consider maltitol absorbability as being 45% of the ingested amount [
 <xref rid="B82-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Before its absorption, maltitol needs to be hydrolyzed by the intestinal brush-border disaccharidases in its two components. Thus, the liberated glucose is completely absorbed, whereas the liberated sorbitol is only partially absorbed, as described above. Unabsorbed maltitol passes to the colon where it is fermented by the gut bacteria. As a result of its metabolism and fermentation, maltitol contributes 2.1–2.4 kcal/g. Moreover, in humans, maltitol consumption affects blood glucose level. It has been shown that the oral administration of 50 g of maltitol determined a blood glucose maximal increment of approximately 15–20 mg/dL [
 <xref rid="B101-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>]. An increment of postprandial blood glucose has observed also with lower doses. Only an oral administration of 10 g of mannitol showed no effects on postprandial glycemia [
 <xref rid="B101-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>]. Therefore, caution must be exercised when administering foodstuffs containing maltitol to KD-treated patients. With regard to gastrointestinal distress following maltitol consumption, several studies have shown that doses of 30–35 g of maltitol do not cause significant gastrointestinal symptoms, whereas a dose of 40 g of maltitol caused mild borborygmus and flatus, without laxation. Diarrhea occurred only for very high doses of maltitol (45–90 g) [
 <xref rid="B102-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. 
</p>
