<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lactitol is a disaccharide polyol used in the food and pharmaceutical industries. It has a low sweetness, approximately 30–40% that of sucrose [
 <xref rid="B78-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>]. Once ingested, lactitol passes through the small intestine almost completely unbroken because of the very low activity of β-galactosidase in humans [
 <xref rid="B105-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. Only 2% of ingested lactitol is, indeed, hydrolyzed in galactose and sorbitol [
 <xref rid="B82-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. These two are, respectively, completely and partially absorbed and, on reaching the liver, are metabolized and stored as glycogen or released as glucose into the bloodstream [
 <xref rid="B82-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Unabsorbed lactitol is intensively fermented by the gut bacteria, with the production of volatile fatty acids, particularly butyric acid, and H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> gas [
 <xref rid="B79-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. Consequently, lactitol supplies up to 2.4 kcal/g without raising blood glucose levels [
 <xref rid="B107-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. Concerning the gastrointestinal distress following the consumption of lactitol, since almost all of the ingested lactitol reaches the large intestine, it can pull water into the gut causing osmotic diarrhea [
 <xref rid="B91-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>]. Moreover, given the intense production of gases, it can cause flatulence. Human studies have shown that the consumption of low doses of lactitol, up to 10 g/day, causes little gastrointestinal distress [
 <xref rid="B108-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>], while higher doses frequently lead to gastrointestinal symptoms, like flatulence, borborygms, colic, motion frequency, and loose stools [
 <xref rid="B102-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-nutrients-11-01104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>]. 
</p>
