<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the invasion process, the resistance of local communities mainly depends on the presence of dominant ants [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] rather than species diversity [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The competition between invasive and native ant species has been substantially studied for a long time [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The interactions between the invasive Argentine ant (
 <italic>Linepithema humile</italic> (Mayr)) and native species have demonstrated that the competitive ability of 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> stems from numerical dominance, aggressiveness, superior interference and exploitation competition, and the ability to quickly recruit to food [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For instance, Carpintero and Reyes-López [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] conducted a bait experiment where 
 <italic>L. humile</italic> aggressively displaced large numbers of native ant species from the bait, whereas native species did not. In the study of Buczkowski and Bennett [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], Argentine ants aggressively outcompeted the native ant 
 <italic>Tapinoma sessile</italic> (Say) from the baits through efficient interference competition and monopolized bait resources (exploitation competition). Studies considering the competition of invasive species facing dominant native species, and especially facing other invasive species, are less frequent. However, although invasions by the Argentine ant lead to an almost systematic exclusion of native ants and decreased ant community richness, some dominant native ants can resist (e.g., 
 <italic>Iridomyrmex rufoniger</italic> (Lowne) [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]; 
 <italic>Tapinoma</italic> group 
 <italic>nigerrimum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]). Similarly, some invasive species can also resist, as shown for 
 <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic> (Buren), where the competitive outcomes depended on the number of workers in each colony [
 <xref rid="B19-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
