<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Insights into the molecular targets for antitumor activity revealed simple oxygenated xanthone as promising PKC modulators, using an in vivo yeast phenotypic assay. Methoxylated xanthone derivatives were found to be promising PKC activators showing high selectivity for individual PKC isoforms, proving their utility for a detailed study of the physiological and pathophysiological roles of PKC isoforms [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In contrast, simple oxygenated xanthones, with an aldehyde in position C-1, were found to be potent inhibitors of PKC [
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. This result led us to explore this type of substituent in simple oxygenated xanthones and to discover the inhibitor of the TAp73 interaction with MDM2 and mutant p53 with promising antitumor activity against neuroblastoma, 1-carbaldehyde-3,4-dimethoxyxanthone (
 <bold>7</bold>). This xanthone was able to release TAp73 from its interaction with both MDM2 and mutant p53, enhancing TAp73 transcriptional activity, cell cycle arrest, and apoptosis in p53-null and mutant p53-expressing tumor cells [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Putative metabolites with 1-(hydroxymethyl)- or carboxylic acid at position C-1 were inactive and since this compound was found to be a TAp73 activator, we investigated its antitumor potential towards neuroblastoma, discovering its potent effect in patient-derived neuroblastoma cells, both alone and in combination with conventional chemotherapeutics [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Very recently, xanthone 
 <bold>7</bold> was encapsulated in nanostructured lipid carriers (NLCs) by ultrasonication, obtaining final loaded NLCs with mean particle sizes suitable for topical application and high encapsulation efficiencies. These loaded formulations seemed to be more cytotoxic against melanoma A375 cell line than unloaded NLCs, which indicates the potential use of NLCs as a carrier for this Tap73 activator with potent antiproliferative effect on melanoma A375 cell lines, improving its efficacy [
 <xref rid="B72-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>].
</p>
