<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under the experimental conditions of the present study it was revealed that the dominant constituent for 
  <span class="italic">O. basilicum var. purpureum</span> is methyl chavicol (estragol), whereas the major component for the other variety of the same species, 
  <span class="italic">O. basilicum var. thyrsiflora</span> is linalool. At the same time, the chemical composition of 
  <span class="italic">O. citriodorium</span> hybrid plant differed substantially from the first two basil varieties: it had significant aldehyde content, represented by citral, with another prevalent constituent being nerol (monoterpene alcohol). Neither citral nor nerol was detected in the two other species of 
  <span class="italic">Ocimum</span> (see Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). We observed that the essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">O. citriodorum</span> species displayed the highest antimicrobial activity against the most of microorganisms tested. The experiments showed that essential oils from all three varieties of basil can significantly inhibit the growth of ampicillin-resistant strain of 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> bacteria. It is interesting to notice, that the observed antibacterial activities of the essential oils from O
  <span class="italic">. citriodorum</span> and 
  <span class="italic">O. basilicum var. purpureum</span> against 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> where much higher in case of ampicillin-resistant strain than in the case of a non-resistant one. At the same time, the essential oil from 
  <span class="italic">O. thyrsiflora</span> cultivar displayed the same, relatively high antibacterial activity in both cases (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils from all three basil cultivars tested showed high inhibition activities against fungi and high radical scavenging activity. Among the three, the essential oil from the 
  <span class="italic">O. thyrsiflora</span> variety displayed the highest ability to neutralize free radicals and showed results similar to the positive control.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils from all three varieties exhibited some tyrosinase inhibitory activity, although it wasn’t particularly high.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils from both 
  <span class="italic">O. citriodorum</span> and 
  <span class="italic">O. thyrsiflora</span> varieties of basil show high inhibition rates against 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> bacteria, which makes it possible to consider using these oils as active natural ingredients for the treatment of skin irritations, since 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> is extremeley common on the skin of patients with certain dermatological diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], and it is often considered to be a major culprit in causing skin irritation and soft tissue infections [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. At the same time, the combination of very strong antioxidant properties with some tyrosinase inhibition abilities makes the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">O. thyrsiflora</span> a good candidate to be used as a multifunctional cosmetic active in various cosmetic formulas, namely as an antioxidant with some additional skin brightening properties.
 </p>
</sec>
