<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the case of oil palm biomass, OPF fibre showed the lowest composition of lignin. This fibre generated after being mechanically pressed to obtain sugar juice, leaving over the soft fibrous structure with lignin composition of less than 20%, as shown in 
 <xref rid="molecules-23-01381-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. This biomass has been successfully pre-treated into sugar for various fermentation processes, such as biobutanol [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-23-01381" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] and bioethanol [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-23-01381" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-23-01381" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. However, the major challenge for utilizing this biomass as a fermentation substrate is the logistic approach to transfer the raw OPF to the processing plant since it is generated in the plantation area [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-23-01381" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Another potential oil palm biomass is OPEFB. This biomass is the most abundant oil palm biomass that is produced in the mill that has been widely reported as a promising feedstock for sugar production. This is because this biomass is comprised of sugar of above 70% (cellulose + hemicellulose) and the lignin content is less than 25%, as shown in 
 <xref rid="molecules-23-01381-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. Another abundant oil palm biomass that is produced in the mill is OPMF. However, a part of this biomass is burned in the boiler for steam and electricity generation in the mill. Besides, this biomass composed of 25–28% of lignin, higher than the lignin content presence in OPEFB. Studies have been conducted to pretreat OPMF to produce sugar [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-01381" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-23-01381" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-23-01381" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. 
</p>
