<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antibacterial activity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was determined by broth microdilution method which deals with preparing two-fold dilutions of the antimicrobial agent (
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>). A series of twofold dilutions were dispensed in 96-well microtitration plate (100 μL in each well). Then 10 μL of inoculum containing 10
  <span class="sup">5</span> CFU/mL bacteria were added to each well and incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. After incubation, 20 μL of INT solution 0.5% (w/v) was added to the wells and the microplates were further incubated for 30 min at 37 °C. A well-defined pink color in the wells signified positive microbial growth. Finally, the lowest concentration of the formulation that prevented bacterial growth was recorded as the MIC value.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To monitor the antimicrobial activities of MEO and nMEO, the disk diffusion method was employed (
  <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">24</a>). Inoculate containing 10
  <span class="sup">5</span> CFU/mL bacteria was used to uniformly lawn Muller-Hinton agar plates. The two-fold MEO dilutions ranging from 4000 to 250 μg/100 μL were prepared by dissolving them in 10% dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) with 0.5% (v/v) Tween 80. Muller-Hinton-broth with 0.5% (v/v) Tween 80 was used for preparing nMEO two-fold dilutions ranging from 2000 to 250 μg/100 μL. Empty sterilized discs (6.4 mm) were impregnated with 100 μL of different concentrations and placed on the agar surface. Paper disc moistened with 10% DMSO or empty niosome were used as a vehicle control and blank, respectively. Also antibiotic discs including ciprofloxacin and gentamicin were used as positive controls. After 24 h of incubation at 37 °C, the zone of inhibition was measured.
 </p>
</sec>
