<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Up to now, a plenty of studies have confirmed diverse therapeutic potentials of EOs including antifungal, antibacterial, antioxidant, cytotoxic, anti-diabetic, and anti-nociceptive features (
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>). Additionally, MEO has shown potent antioxidant, anti-mutagenic, antimicrobial, antiviral, and antifungal effects. According to ample evidence, EOs’ therapeutic effects are likely to be associated with their unique components. For instance, the potent antibacterial activity of EOs has mostly been related to the oxygenated terpenoids such as 1,8-cineole, linalool, and α-terpineol. Likewise, α-caryophyllene, a well-known component of MEO and another EOs, has been reported to function effectively as an antiviral (
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>). However, several evidences have indicated that environmental factors as well as other ones such as harvesting season, vegetative period of plant, and length of distillation affect the content of EOs chemical compositions (
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>
  <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>). Mahboubi, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. considered 1,8-cineole (36.1%), α-pinene (22.5%), and linalool (8.4%) to be the main constituents of MEO, collected from Iran, whose composition content order is similar to that of the results obtained from present study (
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>). Contrarily, other studies determined the constituents of MEO have yielded varying results. For example, the main constituents of Turkian MEO include linalool (36.5%) and linalyl acetate (16.3%) whereas Italian samples are comprised of α-pinene and 1,8-cineole (
  <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>). Despite having potent therapeutic potentials, EOs are unstable due to evaporation or decomposition even at room temperature (
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>). To overcome these problems, several methods are developed to stabilize EOs. Previous studies have shown that solid lipid nanoparticles were capable of reducing rapid evaporation of essential oil (
  <a rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref33">33</a>). Liolios, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. study indicated that encapsulation of carvacrol and thymol in liposome dramatically increased antimicrobial activity (
  <a rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref34">34</a>). Unique features of niosomes including superior chemical and storage stabilities makes them a promising carrier for MEO in topical formulations compared to liposomes. However, different niosomal formulations present various physical properties that influence the EE% of active compounds. Hence, we have analyzed the effects of various molar ratios of different surfactants on features of niosomal formulations in the presence of Chol. We found that vesicle yield was low in the presence of Span 20 and Span 80 which could be due to short alkyl chain (C12) of Span 20 and unsaturated alkyl chain of Span 80 (
  <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">35</a>). Based on findings of this study, S/T 60 formulations have larger vesicles sizes while S/T 40 formulations have higher EE% which increases with increment of the amount of Chol from 30 to 50 molar ratios (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05). In line with our results, a previous study has revealed that alkyl chain length and hydrophilic-lipophilic balance (HLB) of used surfactants have a significant effect on size and EE% of formulations (
  <a rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref36">36</a>). Moreover, the length of alkyl chain in turn influences HLB value of the surfactant. Therefore, the higher EE% will be achieved with the higher HLB values of the surfactants (
  <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">37</a>). Ruckmani, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. showed that a decrease in EE% values was accompanied by increased length of the alkyl chain of surfactants (
  <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">37</a>) while Guinedi, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. reported that lower HLB surfactants led to higher EE% (
  <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">38</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of the present study also revealed that all nMEO were stable at 4 °C during 3 months. Additionally, the results showed that increasing Chol content from 30 to 50 molar ratios enhances stability at 4 °C during 3 months. Chol increases the membrane rigidity and stability by altering fluidity of chains in bilayers and increasing the degree of orientational order (
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>
  <a rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref39">39</a>). A previous study determined the stability of 
  <span class="italic">Gymnema sylvestre</span> extract-loaded niosome through assessing the changes occurring in color, pH, and EE% before and after 90 days of being stored at 4 ± 1 °C, 25 ± 2 °C and 37 ± 2 °C. Their results showed the formulations were found to be stable at 4 ± 1 °C (
  <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">22</a>). Much consistent with findings of the present study, another study reported similar results about the size of vesicles under the same conditions (
  <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">35</a>) and the increase in the size may be related to aggregation of vesicles during the storage time (
  <a rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref40">40</a>). Of all the formulations, F6 had higher stability and lower size changes during storage time and high EE%. Based on the above-mentioned reasons, F6 formulation was selected as the preferred formulation for the next steps including the evaluation of release profile and antibacterial activity. The rate of active constituent release should be determined in order to achieve an optimal delivery system with desired release characteristics for formulation. However, the rate of release and drug retention from niosomal formulation depends on type of drug, so that it can change significantly. In addition, the drug efflux from the vesicles is affected by the chemical structure of the cholesterol and non-ionic surfactants (
  <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>). In many cases, the drug release profile of niosomal formulations the same as our result is biphasic such as acid ascorbic and α-tocopherol (
  <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The initial rapid phase may have wide implications for desorption of drug from the surface of niosomes. Also, the second phase is likely to be associated with the entrapped drug being released from the formulation which is a time-consuming process. Being a stabilizing agent, Chol slowed down release of active constituent. Furthermore, the amount of drug released is related to the EE%, whose high amounts led to less drug release (
  <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>). It may be concluded that gradual release of MEO may decrease its decomposition and as well increase its efficacy during time. nMEO inhibited the growth of 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus, S. epidermidis, S. marcescens</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">B. subtilis</span> at lower concentrations than those of MEO. Similarly, in a study conducted by Salvagnini, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., MEO has been reported to show an antibacterial activity against 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus, S. epidermidis, E. coli, B. subtilis</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">S. marcescens</span> (
  <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">41</a>). Moreover, Yadegarinia, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., demonstrated that MEO functions against 
  <span class="italic">E. coli, S. aureus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> (
  <a rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref42">42</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alteration of bacterial cell membrane permeability, adsorption of vesicles, or the potential fusion to bacterial cell were considered as mechanisms capable of increasing antibacterial activity or decreasing bacterial resistance in nisin/EDTA nanoniosomes. Niosome encapsulation of nisin/EDTA could be gradually released in the medium, hence resulting in longer and higher antibacterial activity during the time (
  <a rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref43">43</a>). Previous investigations have indicated that several parameters, such as size, lamellarity, and Chol content could influence the antibacterial activity of niosomal formulations. Akbari, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. showed that MICs of niosomal ciprofloxacin were two to eight-fold higher than the free drug against 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and, moreover, that the best antibacterial effect was achieved with the S/T 40: Chol (50:50 molar ratio) (
  <a rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref44">44</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
