<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0016">
 <italic>Smallanthus sonchifolius</italic> (Poepp.) H.Rob., commonly known as yacon, is a perennial herbaceous plant native to the Andean regions of South America (
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Caetano et al., 2016</xref>). Yacon is consumed as a safety dietary supplement and because of its low glucose content and high fructooligosaccharide levels putative antidiabetic effects were suggested (
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Delgado et al., 2013</xref>). Indeed, this suggestion is supported by the hypoglycemic (
 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Aybar et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Baroni et al., 2008</xref>) and hypolipidemic (
 <xref rid="bib0087" ref-type="bibr">Miura et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0052" ref-type="bibr">Habib et al., 2011</xref>) reported activities. Also, a potential use in metabolic disorders could be proposed based on the anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties (
 <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Feltenstein et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0118" ref-type="bibr">Sousa et al., 2015</xref>). Besides the above mentioned evidences, enhydrin (
 <bold>1</bold>), a melampolide (
 <italic>cis,trans</italic>-germacranolide) and the major sesquiterpene lactone component in leaves of 
 <italic>S. sonchifolius</italic>, has proven to be effective reducing post-prandial glucose levels and a useful compound for blood glucose control by the induction of a late increase in plasma insulin in streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic rats (
 <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">Genta et al., 2010</xref>). More recently, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments showed that enhydrin (
 <bold>1</bold>) is effective in the management of post-prandial hyperglycemia through inhibition of α-glucosidase in the small intestine (
 <xref rid="bib0112" ref-type="bibr">Serra-Barcellona et al., 2017</xref>). The inhibition of this enzyme has been linked to the presence of the α,β-unsaturatedγ-lactone ring system (
 <xref rid="bib0134" ref-type="bibr">Yin et al., 2014</xref>), similar to the intact 
 <italic>exo</italic>-methylene-γ-lactone group in 
 <bold>1</bold> (
 <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). Thus, the anti- α-glucosidase activity of enhydrin could be derived from this interaction. In addition, the alkylation of nucleophilic sites of factors involved in early stages of the inflammatory cascade described above allows to relate the anti-inflammatory properties reported for 
 <bold>1</bold> with the presence of the 
 <italic>exo</italic>-methylene-γ-lactone ring system (
 <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Feltenstein et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0083" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
