<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While evolutionary change in plant defence in response to herbivory is well‐documented (Agrawal, Hastings, Johnson, Maron, &amp; Salminen, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Ågren, Hellström, Toräng, &amp; Ehrlén, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Benkman, Smith, Maier, Hansen, &amp; Talluto, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Uesugi, Connallon, Kessler, &amp; Monro, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), few studies have examined whether an invasive plant's defence strategies evolve following re‐association with a specialist enemy. In one well‐known example, Zangerl and Berenbaum, (
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>) reported that invasive wild parsnip plants collected during their early establishment period exhibited markedly lower levels of defensive furanocoumarins than plants collected after the accidental introduction of a specialist herbivore, the parsnip webworm. Their findings strongly implicate the evolution of increased herbivore resistance following re‐association. Other studies have found conflicting evidence of adaptation to biocontrol. In a study of adaptation of tansy ragwort, (
 <italic>Jacobea vulgaris</italic>) to its introduced biocontrol agent, the herbivorous Chrysomelid beetle 
 <italic>Longitarsus jacobaeae</italic>, Rapo, Müller‐Schärer, Vrieling, and Schaffner, (
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) reported that New Zealand populations exposed to biocontrol exhibited lower levels of alkaloids compared to those never exposed, while in North America the pattern was reversed. On the other hand, Franks et al. (
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>) found no evidence of evolutionary change in defence in Floridian populations of the invasive plant 
 <italic>Melaleuca quinquenervia</italic> following the introduction of two herbivorous biocontrol agents.
</p>
