<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Plants, especially herbs and spices, have been the major sources for the extraction of numerous natural products with bioactive properties [
 <xref rid="B13-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The reference matrix chosen for this study is rosemary, a well-known ornamental and aromatic plant that has been cultivated along the Mediterranean Sea and widely applied for different purposes. It contains phenolic compounds of great interest for their high antioxidant activities, which are attributed to known carnosol, carnosic, and rosmarinic acids as main constituents [
 <xref rid="B14-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. After the production of rosemary essential oils, the natural phenolic compounds in the residual rosemary have still gained growing interest for direct extraction. Although water or its ethanolic mixture have been recognized as green solvents for extracting rosemary in a sustainable and safe manner, the low extraction yield and unsuitability for the extraction of maximal bioactive compounds other than a single volatile or non-volatile compound limit its application [
 <xref rid="B17-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Recently, the application of vegetable oils as alternative solvents for extracting bioactive compounds in various fields has been revisited. These non-polar edible solvents have the advantage of being non-toxic, non-volatile, and non-irritating. Moreover, the endogenous micronutrients like phospholipids, sterols, monoglycerides, and diglycerides are not handicaps for food, cosmetic, or nutraceutical applications [
 <xref rid="B19-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Considering the polarity of oil constituents and the previous experience, it is believed that such bio-based solvents could also be used for the total valorization of rosemary based on the biorefinery and green extraction concept [
 <xref rid="B20-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-antioxidants-08-00140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>].
</p>
