<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-medicines-04-00027" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Antifungal Assays</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strains of 
  <span class="italic">C. tropicalis</span> (URM-6741), 
  <span class="italic">C. krusei</span> (URM-6391), 
  <span class="italic">C. albicans</span> (URM-6543), 
  <span class="italic">C. parapsilosis</span> (URM-6557), and 
  <span class="italic">C. glabrata</span> (URM-6393) were obtained from the University Recife Mycologia (URM) from the 
  <span class="italic">Departamento de Micologia</span> of 
  <span class="italic">Universidade Federal de Pernambuco</span>. The yeasts were grown overnight at 30 °C in Petri plates containing Sabouraud dextrose agar (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany), and inocula for use in the assays were prepared by diluting scraped cell mass in 0.85% NaCl, adjusting to 0.5 in McFarland. Cell suspensions were finally diluted to 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> CFU/mL for use in the assays. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The minimal inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of the essential oils were determined through the microdilution technique. Firstly, 100 µL of Sabouraud dextrose broth (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) were taken into the wells of a 96-well microtiter plate. The first well of each row was used as a sterility control and contained only culture medium. Next, 100 µL of the emulsion of oil emulsion (80 μL/mL) were placed in the second well of a row and two-fold serial dilution was then performed until a concentration of 0.04 μL/mL was reached. In each well, aliquots of 10 µL of the microorganism inoculum were dispensed. In parallel, a negative control containing only microorganism and medium was run to assure the viability of the yeast strains. It was also performed a positive control using the antifungal fluconazole (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). Assays were performed in triplicate and plates were incubated at 30 °C for 48 h. After this period, 10 µL of the dye 2,3,5-triphenyl tetrazolium chloride (0.5%, 
  <span class="italic">w</span>/
  <span class="italic">v</span>) was added in each well to detect bacterial growth. The MIC was defined as the lowest oil concentration that promoted inhibition of yeast growth. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the determination of the MIC, aliquots from the wells where there was growth inhibition, as well as from positive and negative controls, were subcultured on Petri plates containing Sabouraud dextrose agar (Merck). After 24 h at 30 °C, the microbial growth was observed and the number of CFU was counted. The minimal fungicide concentration (MFC) was defined as the lowest oil concentration that reduced the number of CFU in 99.9% in comparison with the initial inoculum. </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the MFC/MIC ratio, the antifungal activity was classified as follows: if MFC/MIC = 1 or 2, the effect was considered fungicidal; if MFC/MIC ≥ 4, the effect was defined as fungistatic.</p>
</sec>
