<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the objectives of agriculture is the constant supply of vegetables. To achieve this goal, a high germination and survival rate of the seedlings is of vital importance. To stimulate germination rate, many factors are evaluated, including light, temperature, and chemical treatments, but treatments with magnetic field (MF) are often neglected despite their potential stimulating effect [
 <xref rid="B196-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. The MF technology can be directly applied on the seeds or on the irrigation water used for seedling growth. Poinapen et al., (2013) evaluated the effect of applying static MF on seeds in combination with intrinsic seed viability factors, such as relative humidity with regard to seed germination in 
 <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> (tomato). They found that the most pronounced effects of static MF treatment occurred mainly during seed imbibition rather than during later developmental stages [
 <xref rid="B196-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. Gonzalez Aguilera et al., (2016) investigated whether irrigation with MF-treated water had an influence on seed performance of 
 <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>. In comparison to the control group, they noted a substantial increase in seed germination (36%), plant height (97%), stem diameter (12%) and even the number of leaves (5%). By using the MF technology on the irrigation water, the seed germination process was accelerated and the development of tomato seedlings stimulated [
 <xref rid="B197-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. In another study on different crops, the effect of MF-treated water on seed germination and their survival was evaluated with a very positive outcome. These included bean (
 <italic>Vicia faba</italic>), tomato (
 <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>), pumpkin (
 <italic>Cucurbita maxima</italic>) and cucumber (
 <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B198-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. The application of this technology accelerated the germination process in all these plant species, but the greatest survival was evidenced in bean, cucumber and tomato seedlings. Besides their higher survival rate, seedlings could be transferred earlier to other cultivation areas where they continued their growth. As such, production costs are reduced at this stage of agricultural work. Similar observations were made when coffee seedlings were cultured in vitro and MF treatment was applied [
 <xref rid="B199-antioxidants-09-01048" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>]. Application of MF during the establishment, multiplication and acclimatization phases of growing coffee seedlings resulted in a stimulation of the photosynthetic activity and hence better functional capacity of the leaves in combination with decreased oxidative stress, leading to improved seedling growth. As this is a safe technology, application of MF might offer a solution to improve the in vitro plant growth environment that corresponds to the current requirements of environmental protection and agricultural development.
</p>
