<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-metabolites-07-00065" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Terpenes are the largest and most diverse family of natural products. Within these compounds both primary metabolites (hormones, carotenoids, chlorophylls and sterols), necessary for plant growth and survival, and secondary metabolites, that are not directly involved in growth and/or development, can be found [
  <a rid="B1-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-metabolites-07-00065">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-metabolites-07-00065">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-metabolites-07-00065">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-metabolites-07-00065">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-metabolites-07-00065">5</a>]. The latter compounds have also considerable commercial importance due to their uses in food, perfume, cosmetic and pharmaceutical industries [
  <a rid="B6-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-metabolites-07-00065">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-metabolites-07-00065">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-metabolites-07-00065">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-metabolites-07-00065">9</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All terpenes originate from the universal C5 precursor IPP and its isomer DMAPP. In plants, both compounds are formed through two pathways [
  <a rid="B10-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-metabolites-07-00065">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-metabolites-07-00065">11</a>]: the cytosolic MVA pathway, which comprises several enzymatic reactions from acetyl coenzymeA condensation through mevalonate iphosphate decarboxylation, and the plastidial MEP pathway starting from the reaction between pyruvate and glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="metabolites-07-00065-f001" href="#metabolites-07-00065-f001">Figure 1</a>). 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MVA pathway is primarily regulated at the level of the 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A (HMG-CoA) reductase (HMGR) [
  <a rid="B1-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-metabolites-07-00065">1</a>,
  <a rid="B12-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-metabolites-07-00065">12</a>], and it is known that HMGR activity regulates the metabolic flux through the MVA pathway and the eventual production of the isoprenoid end-products [
  <a rid="B13-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-metabolites-07-00065">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-metabolites-07-00065">14</a>]. The scenario seems to be more complex in the case of the MEP pathway. In fact, the MEP pathway can be regulated by several enzymes, including 1-deoxy-
  <span class="sc">d</span>-xylulose 5-phosphate (DXP) synthase (DXS), DXP reductoisomerase (DXR) [
  <a rid="B15-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-metabolites-07-00065">15</a>] and hydroxymethyl-butenyl 4-diphosphate (HMBPP) reductase (HDR) [
  <a rid="B13-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-metabolites-07-00065">13</a>,
  <a rid="B15-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-metabolites-07-00065">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-metabolites-07-00065">16</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, it is assumed that the MVA pathway is responsible for providing precursors for the synthesis of sesquiterpenes and triterpenes, while the MEP pathway donates precursors for monoterpenes, diterpenes and tetraterpenes [
  <a rid="B17-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-metabolites-07-00065">17</a>]. Although both pathways are thought to operate independently under normal conditions, interactions between them have been repeatedly reported [
  <a rid="B18-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-metabolites-07-00065">18</a>]. Thus, experiments with labelled products and/or treatments with specific inhibitors (mevinoline and fosmidomycin that respectively block the MVA and MEP pathways) illustrate that the compartmental division between the two pathways is not complete since common metabolites from both pathways can be exchanged, in both directions, through the plastidial membrane [
  <a rid="B11-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-metabolites-07-00065">11</a>,
  <a rid="B19-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-metabolites-07-00065">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-metabolites-07-00065">20</a>]. Therefore, the relative contribution of the MVA and MEP pathways for the biosynthesis of plant terpenes and the factors controlling this distribution especially under physiological conditions of growing plants remain uncertain for each plant species. It is still assumed, however, that monoterpenes are primarily synthesized in the plastids via the MEP pathway-derived IPP and DMAPP [
  <a rid="B21-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-metabolites-07-00065">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spike lavender (
  <span class="italic">Lavandula latifolia</span> Medicus) is an aromatic shrub of high economic importance due to its essential oil, composed mainly of monoterpenes [
  <a rid="B22-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-metabolites-07-00065">22</a>]. The main constituents in spike lavender oil from flowers are the monoterpenes linalool, cineole and camphor, while the main constituents in the oil from leaves are cineole and camphor [
  <a rid="B23-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-metabolites-07-00065">23</a>]. All monoterpenes are derived from geranyl diphosphate molecule (GPP). In the case of camphor, GPP is transformed via cyclisation of linaloyl pyrophosphate into bornyl pyrophosphate, followed by a hydrolysis reaction that produces borneol, which finally is oxidized to camphor. In the case of cineole, the GPP intermediate is first converted into α-terpineol by the α-terpineol synthase and this monoterpene is converted into cineole by the cineole synthase [
  <a rid="B24-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-metabolites-07-00065">24</a>] (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="metabolites-07-00065-f002" href="#metabolites-07-00065-f002">Figure 2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to its high economic interest, the composition and quality of spike lavender oil has been widely studied including chemical composition of essential oil from some Spanish wild populations [
  <a rid="B26-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-metabolites-07-00065">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-metabolites-07-00065">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-metabolites-07-00065">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-metabolites-07-00065">29</a>]. All these studies revealed a great intraspecific variability in the chemical composition of oils that can be attributed to several variation sources: genotypic, climatic, geographical and/or seasonal [
  <a rid="B28-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-metabolites-07-00065">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-metabolites-07-00065">29</a>,
  <a rid="B30-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-metabolites-07-00065">30</a>,
  <a rid="B31-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-metabolites-07-00065">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-metabolites-07-00065">32</a>,
  <a rid="B33-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-metabolites-07-00065">33</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modifications of yield and composition of the spike lavender essential oil by genetic engineering may have important scientific and commercial applications. Until now, three genes involved in the first steps of the synthesis of terpenes have been overexpressed in spike lavender, the 
  <span class="italic">Arabidopsis</span> HMG1, DXS and DXR genes, encoding the respective HMGR1S, DXS and DXR enzymes. As expected, the overexpression of the DXS gene produced a significant increase of the end-product monoterpenes derived from an elevated supply of precursors of the MEP isoprenoid pathway without affecting the chlorophyll and carotenoid content [
  <a rid="B34-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-metabolites-07-00065">34</a>]. Surprisingly, the overexpression of the DXR enzyme did not lead to an increase of monoterpenes or photosynthetic pigments [
  <a rid="B35-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-metabolites-07-00065">35</a>]. In contrast, the overexpression of the HMG1 gene from 
  <span class="italic">Arabidopsis</span>, led to an increased yield of essential oil since transgenic T0 plants accumulated significantly more essential oil constituents as compared to controls (up to 2.1- and 1.8-fold in leaves and flowers, respectively). These transgenic plants also increased its amount of the end-product sterols, β-sitosterol and stigmasterol (average differences of 1.8- and 1.9-fold, respectively), but did not accumulate more carotenoids or chlorophylls as compared to controls. The potential of the mevalonate pathway for enhanced isoprenoid production by upregulation of HMGR and other enzymes of the pathway as well as its interaction with the MEP pathway have been updated recently [
  <a rid="B36-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-metabolites-07-00065">36</a>]. The increased levels of essential oil and sterols observed in the transgenic T0 plants were maintained in the progeny that inherited the HMG1 transgene. Therefore, genetic manipulation of the MVA pathway also increases essential oil yield in spike lavender, suggesting a contribution for this cytosolic pathway to monoterpene and sesquiterpene biosynthesis in leaves and flowers of the species [
  <a rid="B37-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-metabolites-07-00065">37</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The incorporation of 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C- or 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C-labelled tracer compounds into the current metabolism is one of the most powerful tools to determine the metabolites biosynthetic pathways. To study primary and secondary metabolism in plants, general precursors (e.g., glucose) or more specific intermediates can be used as tracers and supplied to plant tissues maintained either in vitro (e.g., plant cell cultures, stem or leave cultures, seedlings) [
  <a rid="B38-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-metabolites-07-00065">38</a>,
  <a rid="B39-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-metabolites-07-00065">39</a>] or ex vitro [
  <a rid="B39-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-metabolites-07-00065">39</a>]. By studying the presence and distribution of the labelled atoms in the final products, it is possible to reconstruct the metabolic pathways followed [
  <a rid="B39-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-metabolites-07-00065">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The use of 
  <span class="sup">13</span>CO
  <sub>2</sub> as a tracer is a powerful tool, since this strategy represents the possibility of studying metabolic pathways in plants by mimicking, as much as possible, their physiological growth conditions [
  <a rid="B40-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-metabolites-07-00065">40</a>,
  <a rid="B41-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-metabolites-07-00065">41</a>,
  <a rid="B42-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-metabolites-07-00065">42</a>]. The labelling period (pulse) is followed by a chase period in which the plants grow under normal conditions and natural 
  <span class="sup">13</span>CO
  <sub>2</sub> abundance for several hours/days. During that time, unlabeled products and intermediates are produced, that also are used in the production of the final metabolites. Therefore, complex patterns of [
  <span class="sup">12</span>C]- and [
  <span class="sup">13</span>C]-isotopologues are expected to be found in the final natural products. The analysis of complex isotopologue mixtures in 
  <span class="sup">13</span>CO
  <sub>2</sub>-labelled natural products became possible recently, because of the remarkable improvement made in NMR and mass spectrometry techniques [
  <a rid="B40-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-metabolites-07-00065">40</a>,
  <a rid="B42-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-metabolites-07-00065">42</a>,
  <a rid="B43-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-metabolites-07-00065">43</a>,
  <a rid="B44-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-metabolites-07-00065">44</a>,
  <a rid="B45-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-metabolites-07-00065">45</a>,
  <a rid="B46-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-metabolites-07-00065">46</a>]. 
  <span class="sup">13</span>CO
  <sub>2</sub> feeding has also been used to measure plastidic DMAPP concentrations and to quantify the 
  <span class="italic">de novo</span> production of volatile and nonvolatile isoprenoids in some species [
  <a rid="B47-metabolites-07-00065" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-metabolites-07-00065">47</a>]. In this paper, we describe the 
  <span class="sup">13</span>CO
  <sub>2</sub> labelling conditions necessary to study the incorporation of 
  <span class="sup">13</span>CO
  <sub>2</sub> into cineole and camphor in wild type (WT) and HMGR5 transgenic spike lavender plants. The results are aimed to clarify the possible contribution of the MVA pathway to the biosynthesis of both monoterpenes in the species. 
 </p>
</sec>
