<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par70">The MIC and MBC results from this experiment showed that the root extract of 
 <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> has the ability to inhibit and kill bacteria. The MIC of an extract is regarded as good if the values are less than 0.1 mg/mL, moderate if it is between 0.1 and 0.625 mg/mL and weak when it is above 0.625 mg/mL [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Based on this, the MIC of 80% hydro-methanolic crude extract of 
 <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> was ranged from moderate to weak against the tested bacteria strains. This might be related with their zone of inhibition during agar well diffusion assay. According to CLSI (2015a), compounds having a higher zone of inhibition has an ability to inhibit bacterial growth with a smaller concentration as compared with compounds having a low zone of inhibition. In addition, MBC of plant extract were one or more dilution factor greater than MIC values for each bacteria except for 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. It may indicate the sensitivity of test extract for those common diarrhoea causing bacteria [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. However, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> is known to utilize its high level intrinsic and acquired resistance mechanisms to counter most antibiotics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. In addition, recent finding showed that biofilm-mediated resistance and formation of multidrug-tolerant persister cells are responsible for recalcitrance and relapse of infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. On the other hand, the promising activity of plant extract against 
 <italic>S. flexneri, S. typhi and E. coli</italic> might be used for treatment of bloody diarrhoea [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], inflammatory induced diarrhoea [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], traveller diarrhoea and food poisoning [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] respectively.
</p>
