<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The primary mechanism for antimicrobial activity of CS relies on the interaction between the negatively charged carboxylate (-COO-) groups on the exterior of the bacterial cell membranes and the positively charged amino (-NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>) groups of CS [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. The disruption of the cell membranes is the result of this electrostatic binding process [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>], and elevated levels of lipid peroxidation and protein leakage (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01695-f005" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>). According to Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B115-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>], amino protonation and the subsequent cationic production might be responsible for the antimicrobial activity of CS with high molecule weight since its ultra-long molecular chain was suitable for binding 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>. Additionally, microbial deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) and diffused hydrolysis product interaction could prompt protein and mRNA synthesis restriction (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01695-f005" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B116-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. Differences in the composition, structure, thickness, and electrochemistry of the cell membrane also affect the sensitivity of different microorganisms to the inactivation of CS. More importantly, the antimicrobial activity of coating films should be mainly due to the activity of NPs incorporated into the coating films. The antimicrobial mechanism of NPs is summarized in the next section.
</p>
