<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to Davoodbasha et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], the bactericide containing CS and AgNPs was able to destroy bacteria by interacting with the positively charged cationic polymer, and the negatively charged bacterial membrane, increasing the hole formation and the permeability of the membrane, and inducing cell death (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01695-f005" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>]. As reported by Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>], the transmission electron microscopy (TEM) images showed the presence of many pits and gaps on the cell membrane when 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> was exposed to AgNP. The primary hypothesis is rooted in the chemical communication of Ag
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> ions responsible for surrounding the NPs with sulfur and nitrogen groups present in amino acids on the bacterial cells [
 <xref rid="B119-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>]. Furthermore, it was possible that the AgNPs disturbed the signaling pathway inside the bacterial cells resulting in the delamination of the cytoplasmic membrane and inducing the decay of cell wall [
 <xref rid="B100-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">121</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">123</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">124</xref>]. The synthesized NPs caused disorganization of the bacterial cytomembrane and leakage of cytoplasmic contents [
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>]. Furthermore, Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B110-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>] suggested that the embedded AgNPs could accumulate electrons, which were photogenerated in the conduction band of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. This process produced holes in the valence of the TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and prevented the electrons from reconnecting to the holes, inducing the increased quantum efficiency of the photochemical reaction [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B126-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">127</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">129</xref>]. Variations in the antimicrobial effect might be evident due to the size, shape, concentration, clarity, capping agent and surface chemistry of NPs, as well as their capacity to discharge free biocidal metal ions [
 <xref rid="B130-molecules-24-01695" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">130</xref>].
</p>
