<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on environmental conditions, bacteria modify cell morphology and protein synthesis to optimize growth, survival, and propagation (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Woldemeskel and Goley, 2017</xref>). The short term (1 h) exposure to a sublethal level of ethanol reduced the levels of the cell division protein FtsZ, while the relative amount of the cell shape-determining protein MreB was unaffected. In rod-shaped bacilli, MreB controls cell length and promotes elongation of the cell wall, whereas FtsZ, a tubulin-like protein, is involved in the arrangement of the cell division septum and the resulting cell poles (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Margolin, 2009</xref>). Both proteins are also involved in the synthesis of the glycan strands of peptidoglycan (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Uehara and Park, 2008</xref>). Interestingly, ethanol stress was observed to downregulate the synthesis of FtsZ at the poles of other G+ bacteria (e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Bokhorst-Van et al., 2011</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guevara et al. (2015)</xref> showed that the level of MreB increased during moderate heat, carvacrol and thymol treatments. 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Braschi et al. (2018b)</xref> investigated the effects of the natural antimicrobials assayed in this study on the morphological and physiological changes of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> and detected no significant effects on cell shape and dimension. In contrast, their flow cytometry results showed that cell membrane permeabilization, without a loss of esterase activity and cell membrane potential, was the common mechanism of action for all the antimicrobials assayed. 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Braschi et al. (2018a)</xref>, studying the expression of genes whose products are involved in cell elongation and division (fusA and ftsE and ftsZ), showed significant underexpression of only the first two genes when 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> was exposed for 1 h to trans (E)-2-hexenal and thyme EO. Previously, monoterpenes (e.g., citral, carvacrol, and thymol) were shown to primarily affect membrane structures, increasing membrane fluidity and permeability and leading to disturbances in the respiration chain, resulting in a subsequent dissipation of the proton-motive force (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lambert et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bakkali et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Somolinos et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hyldgaard et al., 2012</xref>). In addition, 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zengin and Baysal (2014)</xref>, studying the effects of other terpenic natural antimicrobials against Gram-negative and Gram-positive pathogens, showed an increased cell constituent release and significant modification of the outer cell structures.
</p>
