<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previously, 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> strains were shown to regulate flagellar motility according to temperature (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cordero et al., 2016</xref>) and salt stresses (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Durack et al., 2013</xref>). First, sublethal levels of natural antimicrobials were shown to affect the level of flagellin (FlaA) in a dose-dependent manner. Except for (E)-2-hexenal, the highest concentrations of natural antimicrobials considered did not significantly increase the levels of FlaA. The decreased level of flagellar proteins observed in most stressful conditions could be related to an energy saving mechanism under very stringent and harsh conditions, as previously observed in numerous studies for a variety of stresses (low temperature and osmotic stress) (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shen and Higgins, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hingston et al., 2015</xref>). However, persistence and the ability to form biofilms were not decreased in mutant strains with some deleted flagellar genes (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Todhanakasem and Young, 2008</xref>). Overall, adaptation to different antimicrobials leads to modification of the amount of some ribosomal proteins involved in translation, ribosomal structure and biogenesis (30S ribosomal proteins S1, S2, S3, and S8 and 50S ribosomal proteins L5, L7/L12, L25, and L31). Previously, 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> cells were shown to decrease the level of S1 protein under combined stresses (low pH, high salinity and low temperature) (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">He et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guevara et al. (2015)</xref> showed that the level of L7/L12 increased during moderate heat, carvacrol and thymol treatments. 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> cells exhibited increased levels of some ribosomal proteins (S1 and L25) when exposed to ethanol alone. In the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus</italic>, L25 (Ctc) works as general stress protein, showing a σ
 <sup class="sup">B</sup>-dependent promoter, and it was induced during osmotic, heat, oxidative and starvation stresses (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hecker and Volker, 1998</xref>). In 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic>, the expression of Ctc is dependent on σ
 <sup class="sup">B</sup>, an alternative factor encoded by sigB (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cacace et al., 2010</xref>). The transcription of σ
 <sup class="sup">B</sup>-dependent genes, which encode proteins related to transport, general stress response and metabolism, increased in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> under environmental stresses (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chan and Wiedmann, 2008</xref>). Ctc protein synthesis was observed to be upregulated in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> cells under osmotic stress (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gardan et al., 2003</xref>) and cold adaptation (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cacace et al., 2010</xref>). Consequently, ethanol-stressed cells could better survive during osmotic stress. In contrast, 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> cells treated with a sub-lethal dose of (E)-2-hexenal, and especially, citral, exhibited inhibited Ctc synthesis, which could cause a decrease in survival under osmotic and cold stresses (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gardan et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cacace et al., 2010</xref>).
</p>
