<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As observed in other sequenced genomes, 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> harbors regulatory proteins that play important roles in cell adaptation to different niches. First, this study showed that natural antimicrobials differently affected the level of synthesis of proteins involved in transcription (the GTP-sensing transcriptional pleiotropic repressor CodY, a GntR family transcriptional regulator, the transcription elongation factor GreA and the transcriptional regulatory protein DegU). CodY is a major cellular global regulator, serving as a repressor and activator of metabolic and virulence genes in G+ bacteria. Recently, CodY was shown to serve as a repressor or an activator of different genes regulating carbon and nitrogen metabolism, bacterial motility, stress related and virulence functions and metabolic adaptations in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> strains (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lobel and Herskovits, 2016</xref>). Interestingly, specific combinations of ethanol and carvacrol or (E)-2-hexenal reduced the relative abundance of CodY. In addition, cells treated with ethanol and citral were inhibited in the synthesis of the transcription elongation factor GreA. 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> strains were previously observed to exhibit increased levels of GreA under heat and antimicrobial adaptation (55°C, 0.3 mM carvacrol and 0.3 mM thymol for 30 min) (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guevara et al., 2015</xref>) during treatment with lactic acid (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Omori et al., 2017</xref>). GreA is an essential factor in the RNA polymerase elongation complex and protects proteins against aggregation. The overexpression of GreA was observed to increase bacterial resistance to heat and oxidative stress (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Li et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Omori et al., 2017</xref>). Consequently, cells treated with ethanol and citral, which showed the lowest level of GreA, could decrease the adaptability to heat and oxidative stress. Ethanol strongly increased the levels of the transcriptional regulatory protein DegU, which plays a role in motility, chemotaxis, biofilm formation and virulence in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gueriri et al., 2008</xref>). The inductive effect of ethanol was reduced by adding carvacrol, (E)-2-hexenal and thyme EO due to the modulation of DegU phosphorylation by acetyl phosphate. The use of ethanol alone, and especially ethanol plus carvacrol at 35 mg/l or thyme EO at 100 mg/L, significantly increased the relative amounts of several proteins related to carbohydrate transport and metabolism. Some of these proteins (the PTS mannose transporter subunit IIAB, glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase, bisphosphoglycerate-independent phosphoglycerate mutase and triosephosphate isomerase) were reported to be overexpressed in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes CECT 4031</italic> cells adapted at 55°C alone or in the presence of EOs (55°C and 0.3 mM carvacrol and 0.3 mM thymol) for 30 min (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guevara et al., 2015</xref>). The overexpression of proteins involved in carbohydrate transport and metabolism could be useful to compensate for partially impaired energy generation caused by antimicrobials interacting with the bacterial cytoplasmic membrane. Previously, the relative amount of enzymes related to carbohydrate metabolism in 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> were shown to be affected during a redox shock (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ignatova et al., 2013</xref>). When natural antimicrobial compounds were added to ethanol-containing medium, 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> Scott A adapted the synthesis of carbohydrate related proteins depending on the type and the specific concentrations of the natural antimicrobials used. Overall, carvacrol at 35 mg/L and thyme EO at 100 mg/L produced the highest induction in protein synthesis compared to citral, and especially (E)-2-hexenal. Redox shock also alters the pI or Mr of proteins, resulting multiple spots for the same protein. We observed that antimicrobial treatments drive the PTMs of several proteins. Horizontal spots (e.g., alcohol acetaldehyde dehydrogenase, formate acetyltransferase, and pyruvate kinase) can be attributed to PTMs such as phosphorylation, which play an important role in signal transduction and in the regulation of enzyme activities in bacteria (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ignatova et al., 2013</xref>). Several phosphorylated glycolytic enzymes are “moonlighting” proteins localized to the cell wall that interact with host components, increasing the adhesion and biofilm formation.
</p>
