<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Stress proteins, such as glutathione-disulfide reductase, were induced in the cells treated with carvacrol at 35 mg/L and thyme EO at 100 mg/L and play a key role in maintaining the low intracellular redox potential required to have such molecules in their reduced form. Other proteins that were induced in the antimicrobial treatments, such as DnaK, are able to protect microbial cells during environmental stresses such as heat, acid, osmotic conditions. 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kamdem et al. (2011)</xref> studied the effects of sublethal concentrations of carvacrol, (E)-2-hexenal, and citral on the heat resistance of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> 56LY. They demonstrated that the sublethal concentrations of the antimicrobial compounds used [i.e., 50 mg/L citral, 65 mg/L (E)-2-hexenal, and 30 mg/L carvacrol] did not prevent the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> at 37°C but did enhance its inactivation. Between 55 and 63°C, the presence of the aroma compounds reduced by the time needed for a 5-log reduction of the microbial counts of the pathogenic species considered by approximately two-thirds. On the other hand, the effect of the increasing temperature on the toxicity of ethanol, essential oils and their components is well known (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lanciotti and Guerzoni, 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guerzoni et al., 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gardini et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lanciotti et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ndagijimana et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Belletti et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Patrignani et al., 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). In fact, their antimicrobial activities are dependent on their logP, which enhances the partitioning of the molecules into the microbial membranes.
</p>
