<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among different considered solvents, water, ethanol, methanol, and acetone are the most used solvents employed for the preparation of phenolic extracts from walnut kernel (refer to 
 <xref rid="molecules-24-02133-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> for further details). It has been shown in some studies that among the solvents used, methanol is considered as an appropriate solvent for the extraction of phenolics. The prepared methanolic extracts possess higher antioxidant content and radical scavenging activity. For example, Carvalho, et al. [
 <xref rid="B131-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">131</xref>] prepared methanolic, and petroleum ether extracts from walnut seed, green husk, and leaf and evaluated their TPC and antioxidant properties. It has been demonstrated the highest TPC, and DPPH scavenging activity for the methanolic seed extract, followed by leaf and green husk and much lower or absent antioxidant action was seen for the prepared petroleum ether extracts. In an investigation to evaluate the antioxidant activity, phenolic, and mineral contents of the walnut kernel as a function of pellicle color among different genotypes, authors used methanol as the extraction solvent [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. Kafkas, et al. [
 <xref rid="B132-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">132</xref>] characterized the fatty acid profile, tocopherols and total phenol content of 10 walnut cultivars, namely Bilecik, Chandler, Hartley, Howard, Maraş 12, Maraş 18, Midland, Pedro, Şen and Serr. The methanolic extracts were used for the determination of the TPC of kernel samples from different selected walnut cultivars. In another study by Dodevska, et al. [
 <xref rid="B133-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">133</xref>], the quality of fifteen selected Serbian plant foods was characterized, and the methanolic extracts were considered for assessing the TPC of walnuts. It has been shown that the methanolic extract of walnut and the component ellagic acid in the extract exhibit anti-inflammatory activity in human aorta endothelial cells and osteoblastic activity in the cell line KS483 [
 <xref rid="B134-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">134</xref>]. The results of another study using the prepared methanolic extract demonstrated that walnut modulates the activation of microglia through alteration in intracellular calcium concentration [
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">135</xref>].
</p>
