<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cystic echinococcosis (CE) is a zoonotic parasitic disease which is caused by the larval form of 
 <italic>Echinococcus granulosus</italic> tapeworm.[
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] CE has a worldwide distribution but is mostly prevalent in the rural areas, in which it is transmitted in a cycle between dogs (definitive host), as domestic livestock, and humans, as the intermediate host.[
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] CE may develop in humans after the accidental ingestion of tapeworm eggs excreted with the feces of an infected dog. The eggs hatch in the intestine of the herbivore, penetrate into the intestinal wall, and reach the livers (50%–70%), lungs (20%–30%), or any other organs through the portal system, in which they develop to a hydatid cyst.[
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] At present, surgical intervention (conventional or laparoscopic approaches) is the ideal treatment for CE. In addition, cyst puncture, aspiration, injection of chemicals, and reaspiration, chemotherapy with benzimidazole compounds, and watching and waiting for inactive, clinically silent cysts are the substitute treatments to surgery, particularly for the patients who cannot tolerate surgery.[
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] Through the surgery for dropping threat of intraoperative outflow of protoscoleces (cyst contents) and followed by the repetition of CE and secondary infection, it is necessary to apply effective protoscolicidal agents.[
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] At this time, the accessible protoscolicidal agents including hypertonic saline and silver nitrate are connected with some serious adverse effects such as biliary tract fibrosis and liver necrosis.[
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Therefore, the expansion of new helpful scolicidal agents, mainly from natural resources with little side effects and higher efficiency, is extremely important for surgeons.
</p>
