<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Reviews have reported antimicrobial activity of plants and derivative essential oils, extracts, and other phytoconstituents.[
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] Essential oils are an important supply of new antimicrobial agents as a result of their two imperative properties: further protection to people and environment in addition to low risk of the appearance of microbial resistance, given that they have components which possibly will indicate a range of mechanisms of antimicrobial effects.[
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] Cinnamomum zeylanicum Blume (Lauraceae) has long been used as a spice and flavoring agent in different cultures around the world for several centuries. True cinnamon or 
 <italic class="italic">C. zeylanicum</italic> is the inner bark of a small evergreen tree, which is considered a medication for respiratory, digestive, and gynecological disorders.[
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] A range of pharmacological functions in antitumor, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, antimicrobial, and antidiabetic terms has been attributed to this plant.[
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] Previous investigations have found cinnamaldehyde, camphene, linalool, a-phelendrene, a-terpinene, and limonene as the main constituents of 
 <italic class="italic">C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil.[
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] However, some factors such as location and seasonal variations could affect the chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of this essential oil.[
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] This study analyzes the chemical composition of the essential oil obtained from 
 <italic class="italic">C. zeylanicum</italic> bark, its scolicidal effects on protoscoleces of 
 <italic class="italic">E. granulosus</italic>, and its toxicity in mice.
</p>
