<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The polyester plasticizer is usually prepared by polycondensation of dibasic acid and diol. It is called “permanent plasticizer” because of its large molecular weight, better water resistance, excellent oil and solvent extraction and longer service life [
 <xref rid="B38-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Polyester plasticizer also has the characteristics of low toxicity and safety. It is suitable for application in the fields with high health and safety requirements for plastic products such as beverage hoses, interior decoration, children’s toys, wire and cable. In addition, polyester plasticizers are especially suitable for surface finishing of floor tiles that are resistant to pollution, water or solvents due to its good durability. Traditional polyester plasticizers can be classified into adipic acid esters, sebacic acid esters and phthalic acid esters according to the type of dibasic acid structure. However, these polyester plasticizers are all derived from petrochemical resources and are against requirements of sustainable development. Renewable biodegradable polyester plasticizers have been paid more attention by industry and academia due to its good research and application prospects [
 <xref rid="B39-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Moreover, compared with DOP, polyester plasticizers still have the disadvantages of poor plasticizing efficiency, poor processability and low temperature performance [
 <xref rid="B40-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Lindström et al. examined the influence of molecular weight and branching on the performance of polyester [
 <xref rid="B42-polymers-10-01303" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. They chose linear and branched poly(butylene adipate)s (PBA) to study the relationship between plasticizing effect and chemical structure. They prepared the samples with molecular weight ranging from 2000 to 10,000 g/mol, along with the content of branching agent between 0% and 1.8%. They concluded that the degree of branching is most decisive in plasticizing efficiency. They also investigated the migration of polyester plasticizer for PVC.
</p>
