<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mechanism of action with which the essential oils exert their larvicidal activity is not completely described. Pratti et al. suggest that instant death is due to severe damage of Malpighian tubules, since they are responsible for the excretion, not only of electrolytes and metabolites, but also of the high volume of water naturally present in insect larvae environment [
 <xref rid="B50-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. There are reports suggesting that spice essential oils have neurotoxic poisoning-type effect on insects, similar to the ones produced by organophosphate and carbamate insecticides, by inhibition of the of the acetylcholinesterase enzyme (AChE) [
 <xref rid="B51-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. In a comparative study of the vapor action of essential oils from plants of the Lamiaceae family on 
 <italic class="italic">R. dominica</italic> adults, it was observed that the essential oils inhibited about 65% of AChE activity, while limonene lowered only 2% of the enzymatic activity [
 <xref rid="B52-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Furthermore, these authors found that the essential oils significantly increased the levels of cyclic adenosine monophosphate (AMP) (even at very low concentrations), which suggests a possible action on octopamine. Similar results were obtained by Enan in flies and cockroaches exposed to eugenol and α-terpineol [
 <xref rid="B53-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. In silico studies have demonstrated that terpenes can interact with AChE of 
 <italic class="italic">A. aegypti</italic>, by joining a hydrophobic site of the enzyme, with an interaction with glycine 412, 409, abd 412 and isoleucine 413 amino acids [
 <xref rid="B54-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. Another proposed mechanism of action has been presented by Priestley et al., who suggest that thymol acts on GABA receptors of 
 <italic class="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> [
 <xref rid="B55-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. 
</p>
