<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">Partial cDNAs of HLFs were cloned into pQE30Xa in a way that the first amino acid of the respective HLF (without the signal sequence) was located directly adjacent to the factor Xa protease cleavage site. The cDNA sequences of interest were amplified using appropriate primer pairs and Q5® High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (New England Biolabs, Frankfurt a. M., Germany). For the expression pQE30Xa, clones containing inserts encoding the HLF variants of interest were transformed into appropriate 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strains. Two flasks, each containing 500 ml of lysogeny broth (LB) medium with ampicillin, were inoculated with 10 ml of a preculture. From the start of inoculation, optical densities were determined in a regular frequency. At an OD
 <sub>600</sub> = 0.5, the expression of hirudin and HLF variants was induced by adding IPTG to a final concentration of 1 mmol/l. After 4 h of expression, cells were harvested, the pellet was carefully resuspended in binding buffer (20 mmol/l Tris/HCl, 500 mmol/l NaCl, 5 mmol/l imidazole, pH 7.9), and the cells were sonicated using a Sonopuls homogenizer (Bandelin, Berlin, Germany). After centrifugation for 1 h at 4 °C and 4500 rpm (appr. 3900×
 <italic>g</italic>) in a Labofuge 400R (Thermo Scientific, Schwerte, Germany), the supernatant was loaded on a self-packed column containing Ni-iminodiacetic acid (IDA) His-Bind® resin (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany). Washing and elution steps were performed as recommended by the manufacturer of the resin. Equal volumes of every fraction were analyzed by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) on 20% gels. Prior to the treatment with factor Xa protease, fractions of interest were dialyzed twice for 24 h at 4 °C against a 100-fold excess of reaction buffer (20 mmol/l Tris/HCl, 100 mmol/l NaCl, 2 mmol/l CaCl
 <sub>2</sub>, pH 8.0) in a dialysis membrane with a molecular weight cutoff (MWCO) of 5000 (Roth, Karlsruhe, Germany). The final volume was approximately 10 ml.
</p>
