<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045" class="p">Whilst there are no studies on use of PPB as a bulk ingredient, there are a number of studies investigating PPB as feed supplement at very low inclusion rates in economically important species such as Nile tilapia, marble goby, barramundi and 
 <italic class="italic">Tor tambroides</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Banerjee et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chowdhury et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Loo et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shapawi et al., 2012</xref>). These studies utilised axenic cultures (
 <italic class="italic">Rhodovulum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Marichromatium</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodospeudomonas</italic> sp.) grown on artificial media in the formulation of their diets. All studies, except 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shapawi et al. (2012)</xref> reported significantly better survival and/or improved growth during the early life stages of the animals with some studies indicating unbalanced formulation for lipids or proteins (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Banerjee et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chowdhury et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shapawi et al., (2012)</xref> only reported trends of increased growth, improved survival rate and better feed conversation ratio when fish were fed with 0.3% bacterial biomass. 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Loo et al. (2015)</xref> fed PPB directly to marble goby fries by mixing it with tank water or by feeding it to fish via rotifer and artemia, with both methods resulting in improved survival. This effect was confirmed in crucian carp at PPB addition rates of 0.1% (1:10,000 of the total food intake) (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kobayashi and Tchan, 1973</xref>) as well as in fry of loach, goldfish, carp, ark shell, and sweetfish that prey on phototrophic bacteria soon after hatching (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kobayashi and Kobayashi, 1995</xref>). These studies have demonstrated positive impacts of PPBs as a food supplement at rather low inclusion rates, utilising axenic cultures. They therefore represent more probiotic studies rather than a bulk feed substitute for fishmeal (whole or partial) and do not address the overall objective of fishmeal replacement with microbial protein. In contrast, the present study aims to evaluate the potential of a mixed PPB culture as a substitute for fishmeal in commercial aqua feeds. For this purpose, PPB grown on synthetic wastewater serve as proxy for PPB biomass generated on non-sterile sources. The main objectives were; (a) characterisation of the PPB product produced in a 1 m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> wastewater pilot fed with synthetic wastewater (and the comparison with PPB grown on real wastewater), (b) determination of the effects of 33%, 66% and 100% fishmeal replacement with this product on performance of the fish (barramundi, 
 <italic class="italic">Lates calcarifer</italic>) in terms of growth, mortality, feed conversion and whole-body composition, relative to a fishmeal feed control and (c) to determine the potential value of the PPB product in aquaculture and the potential impacts on the PPB technology as a whole.
</p>
