<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antioxidant effects of 
 <italic>F. alnus</italic> are mainly attributed to some leaves’ polyphenols including trifolin, 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid, rosmarinic acid, quercetin, chlorogenic acid and ferulic acid. Trifolin is a kaempferol 3-galactoside flavonoid, and few studies detected this polyphenol in plants. Leaf extracts of 
 <italic>Zanthoxylum bungeanum</italic> showed strong antioxidant effects in a previous study and were attributed to specific polyphenols such as trifolin (31.24  mg/g) [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In our study, 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaric acid showed noticeable antioxidant effects, which is in agreement with pervious investigations on other plants [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Rosmarinic acid antioxidant activities were comparable to antioxidant standards. In a previous investigation on the Saudi-origin 
 <italic>Artemisia abrotanum</italic>, a strong antioxidant activity was detected and it was attributed to several polyphenols including rosmarinic acid [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>P. harmala</italic> is mainly attributed to polyphenols such as hydrocaffeic acid, cynaroside and protocatechuic acid. 
 <italic>Elsholtzia bodinieri</italic> showed antioxidant effects attributed to specific flavonoids including cynaroside [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Protocatechuic acid is a phenolic acid commonly found in plants and has a strong antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01086" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. This activity is attributed to chelating metal ions and scavenging free radicals. Hydrocaffeic acid is not commonly found in plants as the caffeic acid. In the current study, we found high concentrations in the leaves of 
 <italic>P. harmala</italic>. These high concentrations are associated with the high antioxidant effects. 
</p>
