<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, walnut oil increased testicular antioxidant enzymes and decreased MDA levels when administered alone. Walnut oil also prevented the ravaging effects of nitrite on sperm parameters and testicular antioxidant enzymes when administered with nitrite. It has been reported that walnut contains significant amounts of antioxidants, omega- 3 fatty acids and vitamin E, minerals, iron, sodium, calcium, magnesium, manganese, copper, potassium, phosphorus, protein, and fiber, which make it a varied nutritious meal (
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cosmulescu 
  <italic class="italic">et al.,</italic> 2009
 </xref>). Therefore, it is reasonable to infer that the antioxidant constituents of walnut boosted the testicular non-enzymatic and enzymatic antioxidants to effectively scavenge free radicals and thus prevent lipid peroxidation. The consequence is hereby reflected in increased sperm count and motility. This finding is in accordance with the reports of 
 <xref rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ojobor 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (2017)
 </xref>. Moreover, vitamin E, a chain-breaking non-enzymatic antioxidant also found in walnut, inhibits lipid peroxidation in membranes by scavenging peroxyl (RO•) and alkoxyl (ROO•) radicals (
 <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akang 
  <italic class="italic">et al.,</italic> 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saleh &amp; Agarwal, 2002</xref>). The ability of vitamin E to maintain a steady state rate of peroxyl radical reduction in the plasma membrane depends on the recycling of vitamin E by external reducing agents such as ascorbate, found in walnut. The improved sperm parameters are also attributed to the abundant amount of vitamin E and zinc present in walnut oil, which are known male fertility agents as reported by 
 <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ajaiyeoba &amp; Fadare (2006)</xref>. Seeds of 
 <italic class="italic">T. conophorum</italic> have been reported to contain reasonable amounts of zinc and vitamin E (
 <xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ojobor 
  <italic class="italic">et al.,</italic> 2015
 </xref>). Furthermore, our study showed histological abnormalities in the testicular tissue of rats given nitrite such as sloughing and shortening of the seminiferous epithelium, which led to decreased counts of cells of the spermatogenic series. This is in agreement with a previous study by 
 <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akintunde 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (2014)
 </xref>, in which nitrite led to the sloughing off of germ cells in the seminiferous tubules and evident increases in histological lesions in the seminiferous tubules and epithelial lining of the testes among tested rats (
 <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Akintunde 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2010
 </xref>). Interstitial hyperplasia and absence of Sertoli cells in the seminiferous lumen concur with the study of 
 <xref rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pant &amp; Srivastava (2000)</xref>, who reported effects on the histopathology of the testes of adult male mice after exposure to 900ppm potassium nitrate via drinking water in a study evaluating the endocrine disrupting effects of in-utero exposure to nitrate in rats. It has been clear for decades that testosterone produced in the interstitial cells of Leydig is a necessary prerequisite for the maintenance of established spermatogenesis (
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zirkin, 1998</xref>). The reduced cellularity of the interstitium in the testes of the rats treated with nitrite alone might have produced a decrease in testosterone and consequently poor spermatogenesis.
</p>
