<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The principal mechanisms which mediate the cytotoxic effects of EOs are activation of cell death by inducing apoptosis and/or necrosis processes, cell cycle suspension, and the loss of essential organelles (Sharifi-Rad et al., 2017a). Several effects occur because of the lipophilic nature and low molecular weight of the main components made up of EOs which enable them to cross cell membranes, alter membrane composition and changing membranes resulting in lower production of ATP, changes in pH gradient, and depletion of mitochondrial ability leading to cell death (
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Dhifi et al., 2016</xref>). EOs can damage cytoplasm function by disrupting respirational processes in bacterial cells (
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Akhtar et al., 2019</xref>). Mitochondrial efficacy impeded by suppressing the function of mitochondrial dehydrogenases associated with ATP biosynthesis, such as lactate dehydrogenase, malate dehydrogenase, and succinate dehydrogenase (
 <xref rid="ref83" ref-type="bibr">Nazzaro et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="ref110" ref-type="bibr">Soylu et al. (2006)</xref> revealed that EOs from medicinal plants such as oregano (
 <italic>Origanum syriacum</italic> var. bevanii (Holmes) Letsw.), thyme (
 <italic>Thymbra spicata</italic> L. subsp. spicata), lavender (
 <italic>Lavandula stoechas</italic> L. subsp. stoechas), rosemary (
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L.), fennel (
 <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> Mill.), and laurel (
 <italic>Laurus nobilis</italic> L.) have been screened for late blight disease in tomatoes. The treatment with EOs caused loss of cell wall integrity and eased plasma membrane permeability with major morphological changes in the hyphae of targeted fungal pathogen. Phenolic-rich Lavandula’s antifungal function showed that EOs was also capable of acting as an antifungal agent by disrupting the cycle and inhibiting the synthesis of ATP in mitochondria. Mitochondria experienced significant degradation of the internal structure with a reduction in the mitochondrial cristae.
</p>
