<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with OASIS Tables v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing-oasis-article1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pharm Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pharm Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IPHB</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">iphb20</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pharmaceutical Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1388-0209</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1744-5116</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7269084</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32401104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13880209.2020.1760316</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1760316</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chemical composition and broad-spectrum anthelmintic activity of a cultivar of toothache plant, <italic>Acmella oleracea</italic>, from Mizoram, India</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">P. B. Lalthanpuii and K. Lalchhandama</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2514-3553</contrib-id><name><surname>Lalthanpuii</surname><given-names>Pawi Bawitlung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9135-2703</contrib-id><name><surname>Lalchhandama</surname><given-names>Kholhring</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><institution>Department of Life Sciences, Pachhunga University College</institution>, Aizawl, Mizoram, <country>India</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">CONTACT Kholhring Lalchhandama <email>chhandama@pucollege.edu.in</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage seq="50">393</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="IPHB_58_1760316.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p><bold>Context:</bold> A variety of <italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> (L.) R.K. Jansen (Asteraceae) is used by the Mizo people of India and Myanmar for intestinal helminthiasis.</p><p><bold>Objective:</bold> To perform a chemical analysis of the plant extract using gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) and test the anthelmintic activity on intestinal parasites.</p><p><bold>Materials and methods:</bold> An extract of the aerial parts was prepared in hexane and analysed using GC-MS. Survival test was performed <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> on the cestode, <italic>Taenia tetragona</italic>, and the nematode, <italic>Ascaridia perspicillum</italic>. Concentrations of 1.25, 2.5, 5, 10 and 20&#x02009;mg/mL, prepared in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) with 1% dimethylsulphoxide (DMSO), were tested. Negative control was maintained in PBS with DMSO, and albendazole was used as a reference drug. Each treatment consisted of six worms and was done until death was confirmed. Scanning electron microscopy was used to describe the structural changes.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> Nineteen compounds were detected. The major compounds were fatty alcohols such as 3,7,11,15-tetramethylhexadec-2-en-1-ol and (9<italic>Z</italic>)-9-hexadecen-1-ol. Important bioactive compounds including an alkylamide, <italic>N</italic>-isobutyl-(2<italic>E</italic>,4<italic>Z</italic>,8<italic>Z</italic>,10<italic>E</italic>)-dodecatetraenamide, and a triterpenoid, lupeol, were also confirmed. The lethal concentration (LC<sub>50</sub>) of the plant extract was 5128.61&#x02009;ppm on <italic>T. tetragona</italic> and 8921.50&#x02009;ppm on <italic>A. perspicillum</italic>. Tegumental shrinkage, erosion of microtriches, and distortion of the suckers were observed on the cestode. The nematode showed collapse of the lips and shrunk cuticle.</p><p><bold>Conclusions:</bold>
<italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> contains important bioactive compounds, which are responsible for the broad-spectrum anthelmintic activity. Further study on the pharmacology of the compounds is warranted.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Alkylamide</kwd><kwd>cestode</kwd><kwd>cuticle</kwd><kwd>fatty alcohol</kwd><kwd>nematode</kwd><kwd>scanning electron microscopy</kwd><kwd>tegument</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Science and Engineering Research Board</named-content><named-content content-type="funderidentifier">10.13039/501100001843</named-content></funding-source><award-id>EMR/</award-id><award-id>/</award-id><award-id>53</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">University Grants Commission</named-content><named-content content-type="funderidentifier">10.13039/501100001501</named-content></funding-source><award-id>MRPBIOC-</award-id><award-id>-</award-id><award-id>5</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>The study was funded by the Science and Engineering Research Board [EMR/2016/004053] and the University Grants Commission of India [MRPBIOC-2013-36855]. </funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="11"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="4036"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Helminthiases are among the neglected tropical diseases that attract less attention than other infections chiefly because their immediate symptoms are not life-threatening. They are the major cause of morbidity in humans and decreased productivity in veterinary livestock. In fact, they are now the most prevalent infectious diseases in humans. The World Health Organization (WHO) reports in 2019 that soil-transmitted helminths infect 1.5 billion people (WHO <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2019a</xref>), while schistosomiases alone accounts for 220 million cases (WHO <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>), thereby surpassing malaria (at 219 million cases) as the most prevalent infection. It is also vitally crucial to admit that the situation due to helminthiasis is exacerbated by a pervasive anthelmintic resistance in major helminths to all available anthelmintic drugs. The need for improvements of these drugs and alternative sources of drugs is utterly compelling (Becker et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Schulz et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p><p>Among well-established medicinal plants, <italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> (L.) R.K. Jansen (Asteraceae) is interesting because of its multifaceted applications in traditional medicines and cuisines (Abeysiri et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The common name, toothache plant, is given owing to its practical usage in dental health care. It is commonly consumed either cooked or raw as a vegetable or used as food seasoning because of its unique menthol-like minty flavour (Paulraj et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). It is used in the treatment of anaemia, cancer, constipation, diuresis, fever, flatulence, inflammation, liver abscess, peptic ulcer, and ulcer (Dubey et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). It is also used in severe malaria cases and has been shown to be effective on malarial parasites (Spelman et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In addition, it is known in Indian medicine as an aphrodisiac and is used as a therapy for impotency. It is also used for treating articular rheumatism, dysentery, snakebite, and tuberculosis (Prachayasittikul et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The plant extract has been successfully tested for anti-inflammatory (Kim et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), analgesic, antipyretic (Chakraborty et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), antimicrobial, antioxidant (Savadi et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), and insecticidal activities (Simas et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>The Mizo people of India and Myanmar have cultivated this plant as a common vegetable and have produced a variety. This variety is easily noticeable with its highly serrated and corrugated leaves, and the dome-shaped and completely yellow inflorescence, which are not found in the type species. In their traditional medicine, the plant is a versatile remedy for gastric problems, headaches, dysentery, oral and dental infections, rheumatism and stuttering in children. Its pungent odour is used to ward off mosquitos and other insects (Lalthanpuii et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). One of its most unique applications among the Mizo people is as an anthelmintic agent in non-specific intestinal helminthiases. Therefore, it is pertinent to investigate the medicinal property of this plant for its bioactive compounds and actual anthelmintic activity.</p></sec><sec id="s0002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0003"><title>Preparation of plant material</title><p><italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> was harvested in November 2018 from a plantation in Ngopa, a village in Mizoram, India, located between 23.8861&#x000b0;N and 93.2119&#x000b0;E. The specimen was authenticated by Ashiho Asosii Mao, botanist (Scientist F) at the Botanical Survey of India, Shillong, and catalogued (PUC-A-17-1) in the herbarium section of Pachhunga University College, Aizawl, India. The aerial parts were dried in the shade at room temperature. The hexane extract was prepared in a 5&#x02009;L Soxhlet apparatus. The extract slurry was concentrated by evaporating and recovering the solvent in a vacuum rotary evaporator (Buchi Rotavapor<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> R-215). The semi-solid extract obtained was stored at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until further use.</p></sec><sec id="s0004"><title>Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</title><p>The plant extract was analysed in a single quadrupole GC-MS system (Thermo Scientific TRACE&#x02122; 1300 ISQ&#x02122; LT). Solution of the extract was prepared in acetonitrile (50&#x02009;mg in 3&#x02009;mL). As a stationary phase, a non-polar column TR-5MS (260F142P, 30&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mm &#x000d7; 0.25&#x02009;&#x000b5;m with film thickness of 0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) was used. The injector port and oven temperature were set 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Helium was used as a carrier gas, and was released into the oven chamber at a constant flow rate of 1&#x02009;mL/min. Sample was injected in a volume of 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;L in split mode at the splitting ratio 1:50. The mass spectrometer was run with an ionization electron energy of 70&#x02009;eV. Ion source and transfer line temperature were set at 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The total running duration was 55&#x02009;min. The final chromatogram was generated with Thermo Scientific&#x02122; Xcalibur&#x02122; software. Compounds were identified based on their retention time, chemical formula and molecular weight from libraries of Wiley Registry&#x02122; and National Institute of Standards and Technology database.</p></sec><sec id="s0005"><title>Anthelmintic efficacy</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> anthelmintic activity was studied on the cestode, <italic>Taenia tetragona</italic>, and the nematode, <italic>Ascaridia perspicillum.</italic> The study was approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee of Pachhunga University College (PUC-IAEC-2016-Z2 of 10/08/2016). Freshly killed fowls were obtained from the Rural Slaughter House, Aizawl, Government of Mizoram. The helminth parasites were collected from the intestines of six naturally infected local fowls, <italic>Gallus gallus domesticus</italic> Linn. Acmella <italic>oleracea</italic> hexane extract was prepared in different concentrations (<italic>viz.</italic> 1.25, 2.5, 5, 10, and 20&#x02009;mg/mL) by dissolving in 0.9% neutral phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) with 1% dimethylsulphoxide (DMSO). Albendazole (ZENTEL<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, a product of GlaxoSmithKline, with a standard dosage of 20&#x02009;mg/mL) was prepared similarly as a reference drug. Control consisted only of PBS with DMSO. Batches of two worms were introduced into each media maintained at 37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and each test was done in triplicates.</p><p>Anthelmintic efficacy was assessed in terms of duration of survival. Data were presented as normalized statistical means against control&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation. The lethal concentration (LC<sub>50</sub>) was calculated using Probit analysis. Significance of the anthelmintic activity was determined using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test, and the level of significance was considered when <italic>p</italic> value was less than 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="s0006"><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p>Worms in control media and those treated with 20&#x02009;mg/mL of the plant extract were processed for scanning electron microscopy. They were fixed in 10% neutral formaldehyde (buffered with 0.1&#x02009;M sodium cacodylate) at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4&#x02009;h. Secondary fixation was done with 1% osmium tetroxide at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. Dehydration was done in acetone. After treating with tetramethylsilane for 15&#x02009;min, they were dried in an air-drying chamber at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. They were mounted on metal stubs and sputter coated with gold in JFC-1100 (JEOL Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) ion-sputtering chamber. Finally, they were observed under a JSM-6360 scanning electron microscope (JEOL Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) at an electron accelerating voltage of 20&#x02009;kV.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0007"><title>Results</title><sec id="s0008"><title>GC-MS analysis</title><p>Gas chromatogram of <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>, and the list of corresponding chemical compounds identified from mass spectra is given in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In total, 19 compounds were identified. 3,7,11,15-Tetramethylhexadec-2-en-1-ol was by far the most abundant compound with relative abundance of 99.8%, followed by 9-hexadecen-1-ol (80.4%) and <italic>N</italic>-isobutyl-(2<italic>E</italic>,4<italic>Z</italic>,8<italic>Z</italic>,10<italic>E</italic>)-dodecatetraenamide (67%). Other major compounds were 2,5-dimethyl-5-hexen-3-ol, 6,10,14-trimethylpentadecan-2-one, and propanoic acid. An interesting bioactive compound, lupeol or (3&#x003b2;)-lup-20(29)-en-3-yl acetate was also detected in moderate amount.</p><fig id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Gas chromatogram of the hexane extract of <italic>A. oleracea.</italic> Total retention time is 55&#x02009;min.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0001_B"/></fig><table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Compounds identified from the hexane extract of <italic>A. oleracea</italic> using GC-MS.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Sl No</th><th align="center">Retention time (minute)</th><th align="center">Relative abundance (%)</th><th align="center">Compound</th><th align="center">Formula</th><th align="center">Molecular weight (Da)</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left">1.</td><td align="char" char=".">5.06</td><td align="char" char=".">14.2</td><td align="left">5,9-Dimethyl-1-decanol</td><td align="left">C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>26</sub>O</td><td align="char" char=".">186</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2.</td><td align="char" char=".">7.03</td><td align="char" char=".">15.4</td><td align="left">9-Octadecenamide</td><td align="left">C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>35</sub>NO</td><td align="char" char=".">281</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3.</td><td align="char" char=".">9.31</td><td align="char" char=".">35.5</td><td align="left">2,5-Dimethyl-1,5-heptadiene-3,4-diol</td><td align="left">C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>16</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">156</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4.</td><td align="char" char=".">10.80</td><td align="char" char=".">22.9</td><td align="left">(<italic>E</italic>)-4,4-Dimethyl-2-pentene</td><td align="left">C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>14</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5.</td><td align="char" char=".">12.75</td><td align="char" char=".">63.2</td><td align="left">2,5-Dimethyl-5-hexen-3-ol</td><td align="left">C<sub>8</sub>H<sub>16</sub>O</td><td align="char" char=".">128</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6.</td><td align="char" char=".">22.58</td><td align="char" char=".">35.8</td><td align="left">Pentanoic acid, isobutyl 3-hydroxy-2,2,4-trimethylpentanoate</td><td align="left">C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>24</sub>O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">216</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7.</td><td align="char" char=".">23.14</td><td align="char" char=".">55.5</td><td align="left">Propanoic acid, 2-methyl,3-hydroxy-2,2,4-trimethylpentyl ester</td><td align="left">C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>24</sub>O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">216</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8.</td><td align="char" char=".">26.10</td><td align="char" char=".">80.4</td><td align="left">(9<italic>Z</italic>)-9-Hexadecen-1-ol</td><td align="left">C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>32</sub>O</td><td align="char" char=".">240</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9.</td><td align="char" char=".">28.49</td><td align="char" char=".">47.9</td><td align="left">Caryophyllene oxide</td><td align="left">C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>24</sub>O</td><td align="char" char=".">220</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10.</td><td align="char" char=".">33.71</td><td align="char" char=".">31.2</td><td align="left">7-Hydroxy-6, 9<italic>a</italic>-dimethyl-3-methylene-decahydro-azuleno[4,5-<italic>b</italic>] furan-2,9-dione</td><td align="left">C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>20</sub>O<sub>4</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">264</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11.</td><td align="char" char=".">34.02</td><td align="char" char=".">61.7</td><td align="left">6,10,14-Trimethylpentadecan-2-one</td><td align="left">C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>36</sub>O</td><td align="char" char=".">268</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12.</td><td align="char" char=".">34.57</td><td align="char" char=".">33.0</td><td align="left">Spiro[tricyclo[4.4.0.0(5,9)]decane-10,2-oxirane] 1-methyl-4-isopropyl-7,8-dihydroxy-, 8(<italic>S</italic>)-</td><td align="left">C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>24</sub>O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">252</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13.</td><td align="char" char=".">35.98</td><td align="char" char=".">40.3</td><td align="left">8-Acetyl-5,5-dimethyl-nona-2,3,8-trienoic acid, methyl ester</td><td align="left">C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>20</sub>O<sub>3</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">236</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14.</td><td align="char" char=".">37.15</td><td align="char" char=".">31.13</td><td align="left">Butyl 4,7,10,13,16,19-docosahexaenoate</td><td align="left">C<sub>26</sub>H<sub>40</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">384</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15.</td><td align="char" char=".">39.22</td><td align="char" char=".">99.8</td><td align="left">3,7,11,15-Tetramethylhexadec-2-en-1-ol</td><td align="left">C<sub>20</sub>H<sub>40</sub>O</td><td align="char" char=".">296</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16.</td><td align="char" char=".">40.55</td><td align="char" char=".">67.0</td><td align="left"><italic>N</italic>-Isobutyl-(2<italic>E</italic>,4<italic>Z</italic>,8<italic>Z</italic>,10<italic>E</italic>)-dodecatetraenamide</td><td align="left">C<sub>16</sub>H<sub>25</sub>NO</td><td align="char" char=".">247</td></tr><tr><td align="left">17.</td><td align="char" char=".">43.55</td><td align="char" char=".">20.0</td><td align="left">Bufa-20,22-dienolide, 14,15, -epoxy-3,11-dihydroxy-, (3<italic>a</italic>,5<italic>a</italic>,11<italic>a</italic>,15<italic>a</italic>)</td><td align="left">C<sub>24</sub>H<sub>32</sub>O<sub>5</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">400</td></tr><tr><td align="left">18.</td><td align="char" char=".">48.37</td><td align="char" char=".">19.4</td><td align="left">9-Desoxo-9-x-acetoxy-3,8,12-tri-<italic>O</italic>-acetylingol</td><td align="left">C<sub>28</sub>H<sub>40</sub>O<sub>10</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">536</td></tr><tr><td align="left">19.</td><td align="char" char=".">53.05</td><td align="char" char=".">28.3</td><td align="left">(3&#x003b2;)-Lup-20(29)-en-3-yl acetate</td><td align="left">C<sub>32</sub>H<sub>52</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td align="char" char=".">468</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s0009"><title>Anthelmintic efficacy</title><p>The anthelmintic efficacy of albendazole and <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract on the cestode, <italic>T. tetragona</italic>, is given in <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Significant concentration-dependent effects were seen in all the tests for both the drug and the plant extract. Normalized survival values against control indicated that albendazole took 23.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.93&#x02009;h and 4.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88&#x02009;h to kill all the worms at the lowest and highest concentrations, respectively. The plant extract took 72.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.94&#x02009;h and 31.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.05&#x02009;h to kill at similar concentrations. <xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the efficacy of albendazole and <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract on <italic>A. perspicillum</italic>. Albendazole took 25.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78&#x02009;h and 1.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.44&#x02009;h to kill all the nematodes at the lowest and highest concentrations respectively. While the plant extract took 89.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.06&#x02009;h and 41.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.61&#x02009;h to kill at similar concentrations. LC<sub>50</sub> of the plant extract was 5128.61&#x02009;ppm on <italic>T. tetragona</italic> and 8921.50&#x02009;ppm on <italic>A. perspicillum</italic>.</p><table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Efficacy of albendazole and the hexane extract of <italic>A. oleracea</italic> on <italic>T. tetragona</italic>.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Treatment</th><th align="center">Dose (mg/mL)</th><th align="center">Normalized survival time (hour) in mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</th><th align="center"><italic>t</italic> Value</th><th align="center"><italic>t</italic> Critical value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="char" char=".">100.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.56</td><td align="center">NA</td><td align="center">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Albendazole</td><td align="center">1.25</td><td align="char" char=".">023.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.93<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">58.32</td><td align="char" char=".">2.26</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2.5</td><td align="char" char=".">020.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">74.53</td><td align="char" char=".">2.45</td></tr><tr><td align="center">5</td><td align="char" char=".">016.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.66<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">77.66</td><td align="char" char=".">2.45</td></tr><tr><td align="center">10</td><td align="char" char=".">012.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">81.85</td><td align="char" char=".">2.45</td></tr><tr><td align="center">20</td><td align="char" char=".">004.39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.88<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">86.56</td><td align="char" char=".">2.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract</td><td align="center">1.25</td><td align="char" char=".">072.13&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.94<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">25.07</td><td align="char" char=".">2.46</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2.5</td><td align="char" char=".">062.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">32.10</td><td align="char" char=".">2.31</td></tr><tr><td align="center">5</td><td align="char" char=".">059.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.67<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">32.56</td><td align="char" char=".">2.26</td></tr><tr><td align="center">10</td><td align="char" char=".">043.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">46.15</td><td align="char" char=".">2.31</td></tr><tr><td align="center">20</td><td align="char" char=".">031.65&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1">*</xref></td><td align="char" char=".">51.10</td><td align="char" char=".">2.23</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><label>*</label><p>Significantly different at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 against control; NA&#x02009;=&#x02009;not applicable; <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Efficacy of albendazole and the hexane extract of <italic>A. oleracea</italic> on <italic>A. perspicillum.</italic></p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Treatment</th><th align="center">Dose (mg/mL)</th><th align="center">Normalized survival time (hour) in mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</th><th align="center"><italic>t</italic> Value</th><th align="center"><italic>t</italic> Critical value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left">Control</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">100.00&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.21</td><td align="center">NA</td><td align="center">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">Albendazole</td><td align="char" char=".">1.25</td><td align="char" char=".">025.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">127.60</td><td align="center">2.26</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">2.5</td><td align="char" char=".">019.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">149.00</td><td align="center">2.37</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">5</td><td align="char" char=".">012.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">160.20</td><td align="center">2.37</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="char" char=".">007.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">132.00</td><td align="center">2.23</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">20</td><td align="char" char=".">001.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">187.30</td><td align="center">2.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract</td><td align="char" char=".">1.25</td><td align="char" char=".">089.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">015.40</td><td align="center">2.23</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">2.5</td><td align="char" char=".">063.75&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">061.72</td><td align="center">2.26</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">5</td><td align="char" char=".">056.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">080.36</td><td align="center">2.37</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">10</td><td align="char" char=".">046.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">092.44</td><td align="center">2.31</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char=".">20</td><td align="char" char=".">041.70&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2">*</xref></td><td align="center">105.60</td><td align="center">2.37</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF2"><label>*</label><p>Significantly different at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 against control; NA: not applicable; <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p>Scanning electron microscopy revealed that untreated <italic>T. tetragona</italic> has globular anterior end called sucker, which contains two types of attachment organs, namely rostellum and suckers as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>. The main body (strobila) is composed of a series of body segments called proglottids. The body surface called tegument is smooth because of numerous hair-like microtriches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>). Remarkable structural changes were seen on <italic>T. tetragona</italic> after treatment with 20&#x02009;mg/mL of <italic>A. oleracea</italic> hexane extract as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004 F0005 F0006">Figures 4&#x02013;6</xref>. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref>, the scolex appears as massively distorted. The general body surface called tegument is severely shrunken and wrinkled. A sucker is focussed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0005">Figure 5</xref> showing irregularly oriented spines, the parasitic holdfast devices. Some of the spines are clumped and some are detached. Spines are totally removed at the lower area. The body segments (proglottids) are extensively shrunk and folded. There are no signs of hair-like projections called microtriches indicating complete surface erosion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0006">Figure 6</xref>).</p><fig id="F0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Scanning electron microscopic image of the anterior end of untreated <italic>T. tetragona</italic>. The bulbous scolex and neck are visible. An apical rostellum is surrounded by four oval-shaped suckers.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0002_B"/></fig><fig id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Portion of the body (strobila) of untreated <italic>T. tetragona</italic>. Body segments (proglottids) indicate smooth tegument.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0003_B"/></fig><fig id="F0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Scanning electron microscopic image of the anterior end of <italic>T. tetragona</italic> treated with <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract. Due to severe shrinkage suckers are hardly visible on the top and bottom of the scolex. Rostellum is lost.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0004_B"/></fig><fig id="F0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Magnification of the scolex of <italic>T. tetragona</italic> treated with <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract. A single sucker indicates removal and detachment of spines.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0005_B"/></fig><fig id="F0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Body segments (proglottids) of <italic>T. tetragona</italic> treated with <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract. The proglottids are all wrinkled and folded.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0006_B"/></fig><p>Untreated <italic>A. perspicillum</italic> has smooth body surface called cuticle. At the anterior end there are three lips each of which contains eye-like protrusions called amphids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0007">Figure 7</xref>). The general body is smooth with transverse striations or rings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0008">Figure 8</xref>). The effects of <italic>A. oleracea</italic> hexane extract on <italic>A. perspicillum</italic> are most prominent on the head as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0009">Figure 9</xref>. The three lips indicate severe damage with a number of scars. The sensory organs, amphids, are lost. There is also shrinkage on the cuticle behind the lips. Shrinkage extends throughout the main body (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0010">Figure 10</xref>), and is most severe at the posterior region of the body where transverse rings are distorted, and the tail end is abnormally distorted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0011">Figure 11</xref>).</p><fig id="F0007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Scanning electron microscopic image of the anterior region of untreated <italic>A. perspicillum</italic>. The three lips are visible. One of the lips has eye-like amphid.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0007_B"/></fig><fig id="F0008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Body surface of untreated <italic>A. perspicillum.</italic> The cuticle is smooth with transverse lines.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0008_B"/></fig><fig id="F0009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Scanning electron microscopic image of the anterior region of <italic>A. perspicillum</italic> treated with <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract. The three lips are damaged. There are no signs of eye-like amphids.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0009_B"/></fig><fig id="F0010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10.</label><caption><p>Body surface of <italic>A. perspicillum</italic> treated with <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract. Shrinkage of the cuticle is evident.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0010_B"/></fig><fig id="F0011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 11.</label><caption><p>Tail end of <italic>A. perspicillum</italic> treated with <italic>A. oleracea</italic> extract. The cuticle is severely shrunk and folded. The pointed tail is deformed.</p></caption><graphic content-type="black-white" xlink:href="IPHB_A_1760316_F0011_B"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s0011"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> is already known to be a rich source of important bioactive compounds such as amides, &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-amyrinester, miricilic alcohol glycosides, sitosterol, saponins, stigmasterol, and triterpenes which are attributed to different biological activities (Lemos et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Paulraj et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). <italic>N</italic>-Isobutyl-(2<italic>E</italic>,4<italic>Z</italic>,8<italic>Z</italic>,10<italic>E</italic>)-dodecatetraenamide recorded here is also reported from other species of <italic>Acmella</italic> (Leng et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). This compound and other <italic>N-</italic>alkylamides are established to be the principal bioactive compounds in the genus <italic>Acmella</italic>, <italic>Wedelia acapulcensis</italic> var<italic>. parviceps</italic> (S.F.Blake) Strother (Asteraceae), and <italic>Heliopsis longipes</italic> (A.Gray) S.F.Blake (Asteraceae). These compounds have been shown to have analgesic, neuroprotective, antioxidant, antimutagenic, anticancer, anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, and insecticidal activities (Barbosa et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Lupeol is also interesting because it has been experimentally demonstrated for antiparasitic activities in leishmaniasis and trypanosomiasis (Machado et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), and anticancer (Bhattacharyya et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), and anti-inflammatory activities (Shen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).</p><p>Structural damages observed on <italic>T. tetragona</italic> in this study are among the hallmark effects of anthelmintic compounds. The body surfaces of helminths are sensory in function and constitute the direct interface between the parasites and the host. As such, they are the primary target sites of anthelmintics (Taman and Azab <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). As their parasitic adaptation, cestodes lack internal digestive system so that their body surface (specifically called tegument) with its hair-like microtriches serves as an organ of chemoreception and absorption of nutrients from the host&#x02019;s intestine (Rana and Misra-Bhattacharya <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Thus, anthelmintics primarily attack the tegument.</p><p>Albendazole and flubendazole were experimentally shown to cause damage on the rostellum, development of swellings or blebs on the tegument, erosion of the microtriches, and increased vesiculation on the cestode, <italic>Echinococcus granulosus</italic> (Elissondo et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Albendazole alone also caused severe shrinkage, obliteration of microtriches and disintegration of the tegument in <italic>Raillietina echinobothrida</italic> (Lalchhandama <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). A combination therapy of albendazole-praziquantel against <italic>Mesocestoides corti</italic> caused important structural damages including deformity of the suckers, erosion of the tegument and disintegration of the microtriches (Markoski et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>).</p><p>Highly lipophilic in nature, albendazole is one of the most diffusible anthelmintic molecules through the cuticle of nematodes. This property is important in drug action because the cuticle is chemically a highly specialized proteinaceous complex and is impermeable to most molecules. It has been shown that the drug enters through the cuticle of <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic> and <italic>Ascaris suum</italic> by passive diffusion (Alvarez et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). In the cuticular and the underlying muscle tissues, albendazole prevents polymerization of microtubules by competitively binding to &#x003b2;-tubulins to cause paralysis and death (Abongwa et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Ivermectin diffuse through the cuticle and effectively inhibits muscle contraction in <italic>Caenorhaditis elegans</italic>, <italic>H. contortus</italic> and <italic>Oncocerca ochengi</italic> (Yates et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Cyclotides, a family of plant peptides, are known to directly attack the cuticle of <italic>H. contortus</italic> and <italic>Trichostrongylus colubriformis</italic> (Colgrave et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Natural cysteine proteinases are also found to cause disintegration of the cuticular proteins in different nematodes (Luoga et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Therefore, our observations on the structural changes on the cuticle of <italic>A. perspicillum</italic> indicate that <italic>A. oleracea</italic> also directly targets the cuticle to cause deleterious anthelmintic effects.</p></sec><sec id="s0012"><title>Conclusions</title><p><italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> as an anthelmintic plant in Mizo traditional medicine is effective on both the cestode, <italic>T. tetragona</italic> and the nematode, <italic>A. perspicillum</italic>. The plant extract caused structural damages on the tegument of cestodes and cuticle of nematodes, thereby exerting characteristic broad-spectrum anthelmintic effects. Detection of alkylamide and lupeol from the plant extract is interesting as these compounds are established for their specific pharmacological activities. These compounds are among the lead molecules with anthelmintic properties and this necessitates further investigation to understand the specific compounds and their precise biological actions.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>GC-MS facility was provided by the Directorate of Forensic Science Laboratory, Government of Mizoram, Aizawl, India. Scanning electron microscopy was done at the Sophisticated Analytical Instrument Facility (SAIF), North Eastern Hill University, Shillong, India.</p></sec><sec id="s0013"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">[WHO] World Health Organization: Fact Sheet &#x02013; Soil-transmitted helminth infections. <year>2019a</year> Geneva (Switzerland): World Health Organization; [accessed 2019 Sep 2]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/newsroom/fact-sheets/detail/soil-transmitted-helminth-infections">https://www.who.int/newsroom/fact-sheets/detail/soil-transmitted-helminth-infections</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">[WHO] World Health Organization: Fact Sheet &#x02013; Schistosomiasis. <year>2019b</year> Geneva (Switzerland): World Health Organization; [accessed 2019 Sep 2]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/schistosomiasis">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/schistosomiasis</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abeysiri</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dharmadasa</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abeysinghe</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samarasinghe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Screening of phytochemical, physico-chemical and bioactivity of different parts of <italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> Murr. (Asteraceae), a natural remedy for toothache</article-title>. <source>Ind Crops Prod</source>. <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>852</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>856</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abongwa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>A brief review on the mode of action of antinematodal drugs</article-title>. <source>Acta Vet (Beogr)</source>. <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>152</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29416226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mottier</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanusse</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Drug transfer into target helminth parasites</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol</source>. <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17236810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabaa-Srur</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Spilanthol: occurrence, extraction, chemistry and biological activities</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Farmacogn</source>. <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liwanag</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Akogun</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belizario</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gyorkos</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Imtiaz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keiser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krolewiecki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Toward the 2020 goal of soil-transmitted helminthiasis control and elimination</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0006606</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30106975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sekar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhowmick</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>CDKN2A-p53 mediated antitumor effect of lupeol in head and neck cancer</article-title>. <source>Cell Oncol</source>. <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Devi</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanjebam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khumbong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thokchom</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Preliminary studies on local anesthetic and antipyretic activities of <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic> Murr. in experimental animal models</article-title>. <source>Indian J Pharmacol</source>. <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>279</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21206617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colgrave</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craik</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotze</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Cyclotide interactions with the nematode external surface</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>2160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2166</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20211894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maity</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saraf</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Phytochemistry, pharmacology and toxicology of <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic>: a review</article-title>. <source>Adv Pharmacol Sci</source>. <volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. 423750 (1-9).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elissondo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dopchiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ceballos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruni</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanusse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denegri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> effects of flubendazole on <italic>Echinococcus granulosus</italic> protoscoleces</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16374619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kwun</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eum</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <etal>et&#x000a0;al.</etal></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Suppression of lung inflammation by the methanol extract of <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic> Murray is related to differential regulation of NF-&#x003ba;B and Nrf2</article-title>. <source>J Ethnopharmacol</source>. <volume>217</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29432855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalchhandama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> effects of albendazole on <italic>Raillietina echinobothrida</italic>, the cestode of chicken, <italic>Gallus domesticus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Young Pharm</source>. <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>374</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21264097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalthanpuii</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalawmpuii</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalhlenmawia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanlaldinpuia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lalchhandama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<chapter-title>Chemical constituents and some biological properties of the traditional herbal medicine <italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> (Asteraceae)</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalchhandama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Science and Technology for the Future of Mizoram</source>. <publisher-loc>New Delhi (India)</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allied Publishers</publisher-name>, p. <fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pessoa</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alencar</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Craveiro</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>The essential oil of <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic> Murr</article-title>. <source>J Essent Oil Res</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>370</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keng</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Detection of bioactive compounds from <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic> (L.) plants and its various <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> culture products</article-title>. <source>J Med Plants Res</source>. <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luoga</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mansur</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buttle</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duce</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Behnke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The relative anthelmintic efficacy of plant-derived cysteine proteinases on intestinal nematodes</article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24176056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandjo</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steindel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pizzolatti</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biavatti</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Synthesis of lupeol derivatives and their antileishmanial and antitrypanosomal activities</article-title>. <source>Nat Prod Res</source>. <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28715940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markoski</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trindade</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laschuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Galanti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zaha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Praziquantel and albendazole damaging action on <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> developing <italic>Mesocestoides corti</italic> (Platyhelminthes: Cestoda)</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Int</source>. <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16325461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulraj</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Palpu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The genus <italic>Spilanthes</italic> ethnopharmacology, phytochemistry, and pharmacological properties: a review</article-title>. <source>Adv Pharmacol Sci</source>. <volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>510298</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24454346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prachayasittikul</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prachayasittikul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruchirawat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prachayasittikul</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>High therapeutic potential of <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic>: a review</article-title>. <source>Excli J</source>. <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27092032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Misra-Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Current drug targets for helminthic diseases</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>1819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1831</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23529336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savadi</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Study on immunomodulatory activity of ethanolic extract of <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic> Murr. leaves</article-title>. <source>Indian J Nat Prod Resour</source>. <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x000fc;rlimann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Keiser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Preventive chemotherapy in the fight against soil-transmitted helminthiasis: achievements and limitations</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol</source>. <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>590</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>602</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29858018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2019</year>
<article-title>Geraniol and lupeol inhibit growth and promote apoptosis in human hepatocarcinoma cells through the MAPK signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biochem</source>. <volume>120</volume>:<fpage>5033</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5041</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30506710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simas</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dellamora</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schripsema</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lage</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira Filho</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wessjohann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuster</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Acetylenic 2-phenylethylamides and new isobutylamides from <italic>Acmella oleracea</italic> (L.) RK Jansen, a Brazilian spice with larvicidal activity on <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title>. <source>Phytochem Lett</source>. <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spelman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Depoix</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mouray</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grellier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>The traditional medicine <italic>Spilanthes acmella</italic>, and the alkylamides spilanthol and undeca&#x02010;2e&#x02010;ene&#x02010;8, 10&#x02010;diynoic acid isobutylamide, demonstrate <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> and <italic>in&#x000a0;vivo</italic> antimalarial activity</article-title>. <source>Phytother Res</source>. <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1098</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22692989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Azab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Present-day anthelmintics and perspectives on future new targets</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>2425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2433</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24894082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Portillo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolstenholme</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The avermectin receptors of <italic>Haemonchus contortus</italic> and <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source>. <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1193</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13678634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>