<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results of the present study also revealed that all nMEO were stable at 4 °C during 3 months. Additionally, the results showed that increasing Chol content from 30 to 50 molar ratios enhances stability at 4 °C during 3 months. Chol increases the membrane rigidity and stability by altering fluidity of chains in bilayers and increasing the degree of orientational order (
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>). A previous study determined the stability of 
 <italic class="italic">Gymnema sylvestre</italic> extract-loaded niosome through assessing the changes occurring in color, pH, and EE% before and after 90 days of being stored at 4 ± 1 °C, 25 ± 2 °C and 37 ± 2 °C. Their results showed the formulations were found to be stable at 4 ± 1 °C (
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>). Much consistent with findings of the present study, another study reported similar results about the size of vesicles under the same conditions (
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>) and the increase in the size may be related to aggregation of vesicles during the storage time (
 <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>). Of all the formulations, F6 had higher stability and lower size changes during storage time and high EE%. Based on the above-mentioned reasons, F6 formulation was selected as the preferred formulation for the next steps including the evaluation of release profile and antibacterial activity. The rate of active constituent release should be determined in order to achieve an optimal delivery system with desired release characteristics for formulation. However, the rate of release and drug retention from niosomal formulation depends on type of drug, so that it can change significantly. In addition, the drug efflux from the vesicles is affected by the chemical structure of the cholesterol and non-ionic surfactants (
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>). In many cases, the drug release profile of niosomal formulations the same as our result is biphasic such as acid ascorbic and α-tocopherol (
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>).
</p>
