<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemicals and materials, such as 
  <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seed (black cumin seed), were purchased from local markets in Iran and India. The pure standard of TQ (66%) and LA (60%) were provided by Aldrich Chemical Company (Milwaukee, WI, USA). High-performance liquid chromatography grade methanol and n-hexane were supplied by Fisher Scientific (Pittsburgh, PA, USA).
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection and storage of 
   <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> seeds
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> L. seeds were cleaned under running tap water, rinsed with distilled water, and air-dried in oven at 40°C overnight. The dried seeds then were ground into powder and sieved through a 250 µm filter. The samples were kept frozen in amber flasks until analyzed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supercritical fluid extraction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, 150 g of the powdered sample was subjected into SFE equipment (SFE-1000F, Thar US Technology, Pittsburgh, PA, USA) at extraction temperature of 40°C under 60 MPa. SFE flow rate was maintained at 20 mL/min using a variable flow restrictor. The yield was collected within 3 hours. The collected pressure and temperature were 0.1 MPa and 25°C, respectively. The extraction was carried out with pure CO
   <sub>2</sub>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Solvent methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> powder of 10 g was measured by mean of digital scale (Shimadzu, Tokyo, Japan) and placed in flask. A total of 50 mL of solvent was added to each flask. The top of the flasks was covered by aluminum foil. The flasks were shacked using Shaking Incubator (Heidolph Unimax 1010, Heidolph Instruments GmbH &amp; Co. KG Walpersdorfer, Schwabach, Germany) at 5–7 rpm for 4 hours. The extracts were filtered by One Man paper (no 1) twice. The extracts were evaporated by means of rotatory evaporator (Heidolph Laborota 4000, Germany). The yields were measured by digital scale (Shimazu) and protected from light by aluminum foil. The oils were kept in a refrigerator (−80°C) for further analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of fatty acid composition of extracted 
   <span class="italic">N. sativa</span> oil was performed by means of a gas chromatography (Thermo Finnigan TRACE GC-Polaris Q, San Jose, CA, USA) equipped with mass spectrometry detector (Thermo Finnigan) and DB-Wax column (60 m ×0.25 mm id ×0.25 µm film thickness; Supleco, MA, USA). Helium was used as a carrier gas (1 mL/min). Oven temperature was programmed at 70°C for 5 minutes, then raised up to 230°C at 2°C/min and held for 10 minutes at 230°C. Injector temperature was 230°C. EI mass spectra was recorded at 70 eV ionization voltage over the mass range 40–400 u. For gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) analysis, 0.5 µL of extract and mixture solvent (1:10) containing n-hexane and methanol (1:1 v/v) was injected under split mode (1:33).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
