<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Al, As, B, Ca, Cd, Co, Cr, Cu, Fe, Hg, I, K, Li, Mg, Mn, Na, Ni, P, Pb, Se, Si, Sn, Sr, V and Zn contents in aerated-parts powder samples were assessed using ICP–MS on a quadruple mass-spectrometer Nexion 300D (Perkin Elmer Inc., Shelton, CT 06484, USA) equipped with the 7-port FAST valve and ESI SC DX4 autosampler (Elemental Scientific Inc., Omaha, NE 68122, USA) in the Biotic Medicine Center (Moscow). Rhodium 103 Rh was used as an internal standard to eliminate instability during measurements. Quantitation was performed using an external standard (Merck IV, multi-element standard solution), potassium iodide for the iodine calibration and the Perkin–Elmer standard solutions for P, Si and V, and all the standard curves were obtained at 5 different concentrations. For quality control purposes, internal controls and reference materials were tested together with the samples on a daily basis. Microwave digestion of samples was achieved according to standard method [
 <xref rid="B54-plants-09-00375" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] with sub-boiled HNO3 (Fluka #02650 Sigma-Al-drich, Co) in the Berghof SW-4 DAP-40 microwave system (Berghof Products + Instruments GmbH 72800 Eningen, Germany), diluted 1:150 with distilled deionized water. Trace levels of Hg and Sn in samples were not taken into account and, accordingly, they were excluded from the Tables. The instrument conditions and acquisition parameters were: plasma power and argon flow, 1500 and 18 L min
 <sup>−1</sup>, respectively; aux argon flow, 1.6 L min
 <sup>−1</sup>; nebulizer argon flow, 0.98 L min
 <sup>−1</sup>; sample introduction system, ESI ST PFA concentric nebulizer and ESI PFA cyclonic spray chamber (Elemental Scientific Inc., Omaha, NE 68122, USA); sampler and slimmer cone material, platinum; injector, ESI Quartz 2.0 mm I.D/; sample flow, 637 μL min
 <sup>−1</sup>; internal standard flow, 84 μL min 
 <sup>−1</sup>; dwell time and acquisition mode, 10–100 ms and peak hopping for all analytes; sweeps per reading, 1; reading per replicate, 10; replicate number, 3; DRC mode, 0.55 mL min
 <sup>−1</sup> ammonia (294993-Aldrich Sigma-Aldrich, Co., St. Louis, MO 63103 USA) for Ca, K, Na, Fe, Cr and V, optimized individually for RPa and RPq; STD mode, for the rest of analytes at RPa = 0 and RPq = 0.25.
</p>
