<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">In Hogsback, a village in the vicinity of the Amathole Mountain in the Eastern Cape Province, South Africa, 
 <italic>B. disticha</italic> (specifically the bulb part) is extensively utilized by rural dwellers as herbal mixtures. In this geographical location, 
 <italic>B. disticha</italic> is commonly used to treat a wide range of health conditions such as headaches, chest pains, abdominal pain, and cancer. It is also used to sedate and calm psychotic patients as well as to treat mental illnesses (
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Neergaard et al., 2009</xref>). 
 <italic>B. disticha</italic> is a bulbous plant that belongs to the family of Amaryllidaceae known to possess an exclusive group of alkaloids termed Amaryllidaceae alkaloids that are isolated from plants of all genera of this family (
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Nair and Van Staden, 2014</xref>). The bulb part of the plant is covered in thick dry scales and is found underground, whereas the flower protrudes above the ground. The Amaryllidaceae is a monocotyledonous family that is widely distributed across the globe and consisted of 59 genera with over 850 species (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Cedrón et al., 2010</xref>). Countries such as South America and South Africa are reported to be regions with major diversity that contain 28 genera and 19 genera of this family, respectively (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Cedrón et al., 2010</xref>). There are over 500 alkaloids that have been discovered in Amaryllid species across the globe with 193 of which are found in South Africa and thus, representing 39% of the global complement of structures that have been isolated from 88 species comprising 14 genera and three tribes (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Bastida et al., 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Nair et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Viladomat et al., 1997</xref>). As a result, the alkaloid compounds from 
 <italic>B. disticha</italic> have attracted a huge interest in phytomedicine research due to the biological properties (
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Nair and Van Staden, 2014</xref>).
</p>
