<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent changes in global climate conditions influence species composition and accelerating the presence of invasive plant species in natural environments. Species that spread outside their native habitat and rapidly and effectively adapt to new environments are known as invasive species [
 <xref rid="B1-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The spread of invasive species often benefits from ecosystem changes and habitat disturbances that weaken the natural species and open an ecological niche for invaders. Hence, invasive species can influence the biodiversity, thus limiting the growth of natural plant species due to a higher occurrence of an invasive species, which could lead to ecosystem degradation [
 <xref rid="B2-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The fast adaption to multiple stress factors in environments could also lead to a replacement of native species and it may increase economic costs due to production losses in agriculture and forestry [
 <xref rid="B3-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In Europe, 11% of the 12,000 identified species have caused damage to the economy, society, and the environment [
 <xref rid="B4-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Reference [
 <xref rid="B5-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] states that hundreds of invasive species find their pathways through horticulture, agriculture, etc., and the linearly increasing trend of invasive species numbers (from 1970 to 2007) indicates higher impacts of invasive species in the future. Reference [
 <xref rid="B6-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] pointed out that not only invasive species have an impact on native plants, since several factors often interact with the environment that influence species distributions. In recent years, the need to precisely understand the ecological impacts of invasive species in ecosystems has become a key in designing and prioritizing natural resource management approaches [
 <xref rid="B2-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], since the behaviour and impact of invasive species is still not well understood [
 <xref rid="B3-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Furthermore, a high number of invasive plant are species spreading in natural environments, which increases the demand of management practices [
 <xref rid="B5-sensors-21-00471" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].
</p>
