<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Oleuropein is recognised to have antiviral, antimicrobial and antifungal properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Moreover, oleuropein has noted hypoglycaemic and hypotensive properties, and is a powerful antioxidant [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Oleuropein has proven to exert protective properties against cancer and heart disease, in addition to supporting immunoregulatory actions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Oleuropein inhibits migration and proliferation of human tumour cells in culture. Hamadi and Castellon [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] demonstrated that oleuropein irreversibly rounds cancer cells, preventing motility, replication and invasiveness, whilst these effects were reversible upon treatment removal in normal cells. The study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] demonstrated this reversibility through carrying out additional washing tests on Matrigel-free cultures of RPMI-7951 melanoma cells in addition to normal cells. After 48 h of extensive washing, normal cells flattened out and again became mobile, whilst cancer cells remained immobilized. This work was supported in vivo, when 1% oleuropein was administered to mice orally within drinking water leading to tumour regression in 9-12 days [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The cell rounding triggered by oleuropein is linked to the disruption of the actin cytoskeleton and actin filaments. In Hamadi and Castellon’s [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] study, it was established that this effect was somewhat offset by the addition of glucose in the culture media. Due to oleuropeins glucose moiety, it is likely that oleuropein enters the cell through glucose transporters (GLUTs). Removing oleuropeins glucose moiety with β-glucosidase decreases its anti-proliferative activity, demonstrating that entry of oleuropein into the cell is at least partially dependent on the glucose moiety [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Human malignancies are associated with elevated glucose uptake and enhanced expression of several GLUT isoforms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. This explains how normal cells can reverse the rounding effects of oleuropein treatment, as normal cells have low expression of GLUTs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].
</p>
