<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chitosan biopolymer is generally recognized as safe due to its non-toxicity, biocompatibility, and biodegradability. It has gained a great deal of attention in last few years as an encapsulation wall material because of some of its properties such as being insecticidal, antimicrobial, antioxidant, and having film-forming properties [
 <xref rid="B217-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>,
 <xref rid="B218-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>,
 <xref rid="B219-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="B220-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>]. Therefore, chitosan has been used to encapsulate EOs such as clove [
 <xref rid="B221-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>], 
 <italic>Cuminum cyminum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B215-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">215</xref>], 
 <italic>Bunium persicum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B222-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>], and 
 <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> [
 <xref rid="B217-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>]. Singh et al. [
 <xref rid="B211-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>] found that while chitosan-encapsulated 
 <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> EO inhibited the growth of 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic> and aflatoxin B
 <sub>1</sub> secretion at 60 and 20 μL/L, respectively, unencapsulated EO had the similar activity at 300 and 200 μL/L. The encapsulated 
 <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> EO had two times higher radical scavenging activity than unencapsulated EO. In addition to its antioxidant activity, the phenolic content increased with encapsulation, and the increase in phenolic content resulted in the prolonged shelf life of stored herbal raw material. Moreover, the nanoencapsulation of EOs such as 
 <italic>Thymus zygis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B223-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>] and 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> [
 <xref rid="B216-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">216</xref>] enhanced the antifungal activity against 
 <italic>Alternaria alternata</italic> and 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic>, respectively, when compared with free EOs. The activity of nanoencapsulation has been studied not only under in vitro conditions but also under in vivo conditions such as on food products. Gonçalves et al. [
 <xref rid="B224-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">224</xref>] studied the encapsulated 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> EO as a natural preservative in food products and showed that encapsulated thyme EO increased the induction time of oxidation, the cake shelf life up to 30 days, as well as the antimicrobial activity. Zein-encapsulated 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> and 
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> EOs showed higher antimicrobial and antioxidant activities. Moreover, tested EOs protected from thermal degradation at baking processes [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
