<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to nanoencapsulation, there are also several microencapsulation studies of EOs [
 <xref rid="B225-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">225</xref>,
 <xref rid="B226-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">226</xref>]. For instance, the morphological and sensorial properties of Jujube (
 <italic>Ziziphus jujuba</italic> Mill) fruit with microencapsulated 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> (ginger) EO in chitosan and sodium carboxymethyl cellulose were enhanced while maintaining the nutritional value [
 <xref rid="B227-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">227</xref>]. On the surface of untreated jujube fruits, severe blackspots were observed after 7 days of storage; however, no rotten jujube fruits were observed in samples with microencapsulated EOs. Red and decay index were measured for the evaluation of freshness and the sensory properties of jujube fruits. An increment of red index, which is the degree of maturity, was restricted with EO microencapsulation. Sensory evaluations of EO microencapsulated fruit samples were carried out by 10 panelists. For appearance, crunchiness, firmness, and juiciness, they reported that EO microencapsulated fruits had better sensory quality characteristics [
 <xref rid="B227-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">227</xref>]. In another study, ripening in 
 <italic>Syringe</italic> EO microencapsulated (SEOM) 
 <italic>Prunus persia</italic> fruit has been delayed. Additionally, ethylene production was lower than the control during the storage period. SEOM application resulted in an increase in the peach-like aroma and decrease in the grass-like aroma, mainly in the last period of storage, protecting the peach aroma during cold storage [
 <xref rid="B228-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">228</xref>]. The use of cyclodextrin as an encapsulating agent in microencapsulation is also recommended due to its unique advantages including heat and oxidative stability [
 <xref rid="B226-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">226</xref>]. Generally, during storage the color of vegetables may change. With EO microencapsulation, there was no significant difference in the color of lettuce compared to the untreated sample during the entire storage period. However, L* and (-a*/b*) scores of samples treated with free EO were observed to decrease compared to the untreated sample during storage. It was also found that microencapsulated beta cyclodextrin complexes with thyme EO showed higher antimicrobial activity and protected the EO from degradation. Additionally, antimicrobial activity of this complex was observed during the storage of pork meat system [
 <xref rid="B229-molecules-25-04711" ref-type="bibr">229</xref>].
</p>
