<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-ijms-19-00610" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Free radicals are naturally present in the living organism, and they include reactive oxygen species (ROS) and reactive nitrogen species (RNS) [
  <a rid="B1-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijms-19-00610">1</a>]. They are produced during metabolism of energy in the cell as a result of the reduction of oxygen with one electron which forms superoxide anion (O
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">•−</span>) and with 2 or 3 electrons which forms H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> by the action of enzymes such as oxidases and with production of hydroxyl radical (OH
  <span class="sup">•</span>). Furthermore, nitric oxide (NO) with anionic superoxide (O
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">•−</span>) gives peroxynitrite (ONOO
  <span class="sup">−</span>), which is RNS [
  <a rid="B2-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijms-19-00610">2</a>].Pollutions of air and water, toxins, drugs, heavy metals, pesticides, and cigarette smoke play an important role in the production of ROS [
  <a rid="B3-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijms-19-00610">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the ROS present in physiological concentration, they play an important role in the maintenance and the functioning of the body, but when their production exceeds the capacity of the cells to trap them, they start a state of oxidation called oxidative stress [
  <a rid="B4-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijms-19-00610">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the oxidative stress is moderate, the intervention of endogenous antioxidant systems of the organism can handle the situation to return to the physiological state. However, when oxidative stress becomes chronic, it leads to the appearance of several diseases such as cardiovascular diseases, neurodegenerative diseases, diabetes and cancer [
  <a rid="B5-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijms-19-00610">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijms-19-00610">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijms-19-00610">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijms-19-00610">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijms-19-00610">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijms-19-00610">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijms-19-00610">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exogenous antioxidants such as vitamin E and C, phenolics, flavonoids, flavonols, flavones and carotenoids have been found to mitigate the activity of the endogenous antioxidant defense and can protect against diseases that result from oxidative stress [
  <a rid="B12-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijms-19-00610">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Argania spinosa (Sapotaceae)</span> is an endemic tree of south-western Morocco, which gives valuable Argan oil. The extraction of this oil was made by three methods: (i) a traditional method which is very slow and produces oil with an insufficient quality of conservation due to the water added during the process of extraction; (ii) a mechanical press which does not require the addition of water during extraction; and (iii) a solvent extraction method which produces oil with unsatisfactory organoleptic properties compared to the oil extracted by traditional method or by mechanical press. This technique is exclusively used to prepare the oil for cosmetic purposes [
  <a rid="B13-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijms-19-00610">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijms-19-00610">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Argan oil is rich in antioxidant compounds such as caffeic acid, vanillic acid, ferulic acid, resorcinol and catechin [
  <a rid="B15-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijms-19-00610">15</a>]. Several studies have shown that Argan oil has beneficial effects against many diseases such as cardiovascular diseases, obesity, cancer, and diabetes [
  <a rid="B16-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijms-19-00610">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijms-19-00610">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijms-19-00610">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijms-19-00610">19</a>,
  <a rid="B20-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijms-19-00610">20</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil is an odorous product of organic compounds found naturally in aromatic plants, and it is obtained by hydro distillation, steam distillation, and pressing techniques [
  <a rid="B21-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijms-19-00610">21</a>,
  <a rid="B22-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijms-19-00610">22</a>]. The clove (
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span>) is a tree from (
  <span class="italic">Myrtaceae</span>) family, and its essential oil has been reported to be one of the strongest essential oil in its antioxidant activity; this is due to the chemical composition especially eugenol.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies have shown that exposure to H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> is an effective technique for inducing oxidative stress in animals. H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> can cause elevation of OH
  <span class="sup">•</span> via the Fenton reaction: Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span> + H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> → Fe
  <span class="sup">3+</span> + 
  <span class="sup">•</span>OH + OH
  <span class="sup">−</span> [
  <a rid="B23-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijms-19-00610">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijms-19-00610">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijms-19-00610">25</a>,
  <a rid="B26-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijms-19-00610">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this context, the present study was designed to explore the antioxidant content of Argan oil and 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil, and to investigate the protective effect of Argan oil administered alone and the effect of the formulation of 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil emulsified in Argan oil against the harmful toxicity induced by H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>. 
 </p>
</sec>
