<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Over the last decades, tens of thousands of metabolites have been described from the fungal kingdom, many of which possess diverse medicinal properties including antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral, and antitumor. However, fungal natural products with antiviral properties were less lengthily investigated. Nevertheless, the number of fungal antiviral studies is gradually increasing, particularly, those that are related to medicinal mushrooms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Although, many of the selected molecules in the below table (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) have a wide range of bioactivities, we focused our scope on their antiviral properties. The described chemicals, belong to an array of fungal terpenes, and they were selected through an extensive literature search. 6-epi-ophiobolin K is a member of the ophiobolins group of sesterterpenoids, having a molecular formula C
 <sub>25</sub>H
 <sub>36</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>. It is produced by a strain of a 
 <italic>Neosartorya</italic> sp, and it showed HIV-1-integrase inhibitory activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. 6β,9α-dihydroxy-14-
 <italic>p</italic>-nitrobenzoylcinnamolide is a rare sesquiterpenoid molecule (formula C
 <sub>22</sub>H
 <sub>25</sub>NO
 <sub>8</sub>) with antiviral activity against H3N2 and EV71, and it is produced by the marine-derived ascomycete fungus 
 <italic>Aspergillus ochraceus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]
 <italic>.</italic> Equisetin is a tetramic acid like compound isolated from 
 <italic>Fusarium equiseti</italic>, with substituted aliphatic bicyclic ring, having molecular formula C
 <sub>22</sub>H
 <sub>31</sub>NO
 <sub>4</sub> and shows inhibition activity on HIV-1 integrase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Integracide A (C
 <sub>32</sub>H
 <sub>50</sub>O
 <sub>8</sub>S) and integracide D (C
 <sub>36</sub>H
 <sub>58</sub>O
 <sub>8</sub>) also show inhibition of the HIV-1 integrase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], and are tetracyclic triterpenoids made by 
 <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp. The oblongolides are tricyclic compounds derived from the fungus 
 <italic>Phomopsis sp</italic>. BCC 9789 and display anti-HSV-1 activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The last two compounds derived from ascomycete fungi included in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> are stachyflin, with molecular formula C
 <sub>23</sub>H
 <sub>31</sub>NO
 <sub>4</sub>, and stachybotrylactam, C
 <sub>23</sub>H
 <sub>31</sub>NO
 <sub>4</sub>, sesquiterpene derivatives isolated from the 
 <italic>Stachybotrys sp</italic>. that exhibit inhibition on HSV-1, H1N1 and H2N2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The table also includes molecules characterised from basidiomycete species such as the sesquiterpene Illudin S, C
 <sub>15</sub>H
 <sub>20</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>, which is a highly reactive molecule that can bind to the DNA and cause its damage and was first isolated from the Jack o’ Lantern mushroom 
 <italic>Omphalotus illudens</italic>, showing inhibition of HSV-1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]
 <italic>.</italic> The bis-sesquiterpene agrocybone, molecular formula C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>36</sub>O
 <sub>5</sub>, has an eight-ring structure derived from the binding of two molecules of illudane via Diels–Alder reaction and shows weak antiviral properties against the respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Triterpenoids with antiviral activity have been abundantly described as being isolated from the fruiting bodies of 
 <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> mushrooms
 <italic>,</italic> such as the lanosterol derived triterpenoid ganoderic acid Y, molecular formula C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>46</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>, as well as many closely related triterpenoids, including the oxidized lanostane triterpenoids lucidenic acid P, C
 <sub>29</sub>H
 <sub>44</sub>O
 <sub>7</sub>, lucidumol B, C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>50</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>, and ganolucidic acid A, C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>44</sub>O
 <sub>6</sub> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ganoderma colossum</italic> produces the lanostane triterpenes schisanlactone A, formula C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>40</sub>O
 <sub>4</sub>, colossolactone E, C
 <sub>32</sub>H
 <sub>54</sub>O
 <sub>6</sub>, and colossolactone V, C
 <sub>35</sub>H
 <sub>54</sub>O
 <sub>9</sub>, which show anti-HIV-1 protease activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Another species of the 
 <italic>Ganoderma</italic> genus, 
 <italic>Ganoderma pfeifferi</italic>, produces antiviral triterpenoids such as lucidadiol, C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>48</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>, ganoderone A, with molecular formula C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>46</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub>, applanoxidic acid G, C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>40</sub>O
 <sub>8</sub>, and lucialdehyde B, C
 <sub>30</sub>H
 <sub>44</sub>O
 <sub>3</sub> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].
</p>
