<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Bioactive compounds are organic molecules with normally small molecular weight that can be produced by both Ascomycetes and Basidiomycetes. Literature reports on fungal antiviral sources reveal that most known bioactive molecules have been isolated from Ascomycetes and Basidiomycetes, providing insights into the competence of those two phyla as producers of therapeutic compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The studies indicated also that the biosynthetic gene clusters of the bioactive metabolites’ dominance are generally lower in number in basidiomycetes compared to the ascomycetes. However, this difference reflects the bias from the use of different techniques and tools in isolating and characterising the bioactive compounds, and not their genuine productivity of biologically active metabolites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Current reports on fungal diversity prediction, suggested that less than 10% of fungal species are described, which again demonstrates the great potential of fungi as a source of antivirals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Above that, medicinal mushrooms played an important role in natural remedies, their healing power has been subjected to vast scientific research, such as the edible mushroom shiitake. Many other species of mushroom-forming fungi exhibited potential to produce natural antivirals. Reports on mushrooms bioactivities, linked their ability in defeating viral infections to the presence of two types of chemicals: polysaccharides and terpene like compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. However, other types of biologically important molecules have been reported from mushrooms, implying the potential content of structurally diverse biomolecules that are awaiting discovery [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Historically, terpene derivatives are one of the most widespread naturally occurring products, that are predominantly found in the form of aromatic oils. Such products were mainly used, for instance, for religious reasons in the olden Egypt. Camphor (a terpene isolated from essential oils of camphor tree) for example, was first introduced to Europe by Arabian traders ten centuries ago. In 1818 researchers were able to analyse turpentine oils and then propose the term “terpene” instead of camphor, which was used to describe extracted crystalline oxygenated molecules from essential oils. Further analysis by other researchers has resulted in the description of the building block “isoprenic” of this molecule [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The role of mevalonic acid in cholesterol biosynthesis and its incorporation in the synthesis of many terpene compounds was defined in 1956. Following this, thousands of terpenoids were structurally and functionally characterised. Apart from their antimicrobial activities, terpenes have also been reported as hormones and photosynthetic pigments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].
</p>
