<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A large number of studies have already established the diverse pharmacological benefits of organic or aqueous crude extracts of 
 <italic>G. pentaphyllum</italic> or of a saponin-rich extract preparation. The extracts have shown significant activities against coronary spasm and arrhythmia,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>
 </sup> diabetes,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>
 </sup> and the development of cancerous cells.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>
 </sup> The saponin-rich extracts also exhibited excellent activities against platelet aggregation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>
 </sup> and inhibited the growth of 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>(
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref>) and 
 <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>
 </sup> A recent study by Nguyen et al. reported that two saponins, damulins A and B (
 <bold>15</bold> and 
 <bold>16</bold>; 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>), isolated from 
 <italic>G. pentaphyllum</italic> are potential activators of AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>
 </sup> AMPK is responsible for the regulation of blood sugar levels and lipid metabolism, consequently resulting in weight loss. Gauhar et al. performed a follow-up 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> study that reported the antiobesity effect of 
 <italic>G. pentaphyllum</italic> extract in obese mice.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>
 </sup> The antiobesity effect of 
 <italic>G. pentaphullum</italic> was established by a clinical trial in humans by Park et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref>
 </sup> The effects on body weight, fat loss, and metabolic markers of Korean participants were investigated in a 12-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial, which suggested that 
 <italic>G. pentaphullum</italic> supplementation may be effective for treating obese individuals.
</p>
