<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several restoration experiments have been conducted to test biotic resistance in an invasion context. Unfortunately, a case study for the control 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> has not yet been conducted. Based on this study, restoration of native plant cover controlled up to 100% of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> establishment. 
 <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> is an exotic invasive plant in the wetlands of North America, and, in an experiment in a salt marsh, the transport of a halophyte into the marsh reduced rhizome growth of 
 <italic>Phragmites australis</italic> by 60% (Peter &amp; Burdick, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0085" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). A diversity effect (mixtures are more resistant than monocultures of a species) was also found with the selection effect of 
 <italic>Spartina alterniflora</italic>, and, in a freshwater mesocosm experiment, biotic resistance was significantly different among functional groups (Byun et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). In the present study, the strongest biotic resistance was found in rapidly growing annual plants that showed a priority effect. In another experiment that examined environmental effects, flooding always reduced invasion success, and flooding assisted or inhibited biotic resistance depending on the adaption of species to the environment (Byun et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Biotic resistance is particularly effective with low propagule pressure (Byun et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Other studies also examined the restoration of native plants to control invasive plants, including 
 <italic>Centaurea diffusa</italic> (Meiman, Redente, &amp; Paschke, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), 
 <italic>Centaurea solstitialis</italic> (Dukes, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>), 
 <italic>Rapistrum rugosum</italic> (Cutting &amp; Hough‐Goldstein, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Simmons, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0100" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>), 
 <italic>Cardaria draba</italic>,
 <italic> Cirsium arvense</italic>,
 <italic> Bromus tectorum</italic> and 
 <italic>B. japonicas</italic> (Perry, Cronin, &amp; Paschke, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), 
 <italic>Arundo donax</italic> (Quinn &amp; Holt, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), 
 <italic>Agropyron cristatum</italic> (Bakker &amp; Wilson, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>), and 
 <italic>Persicaria perfoliata</italic> (Cutting &amp; Hough‐Goldstein, 
 <xref rid="ece32799-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>).
</p>
