<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Acute kidney injury (AKI) is characterized by a rapid loss of renal function. Drug-induced AKI accounts for up to 60% of all cases, resulting in a severe threat particularly to hospitalized patients, but there are no effective treatments. Four polyherbal formulas, 
  <italic>Bojungikki-tang</italic> (BJ), 
  <italic>Palmijihwang-tang</italic> (PJ), 
  <italic>Oryeong-san</italic> (OR), and 
  <italic>Wiryeong-tang</italic> (WR), have long been used for treatments of symptoms of kidney disease in traditional Korean medicine. Even though they are commercially available, evidences supporting the efficacy on AKI are still lacking. Therefore, the effectiveness of polyherbs on AKI and the underlying mechanisms were examined. Renal cell damage was induced by cisplatin at 20 
  <italic>μ</italic>M and 16 
  <italic>μ</italic>M in proximal tubular epithelial cell lines of rat NRK-52E and human HK-2, respectively. The cells were treated with the polyherbal formals for 3 days, and the cell viability, antioxidant activities, and apoptosis were examined. In addition, the proliferative effects were assessed under serum-free conditions. The results were compared with those of the vehicle-treated cells as a control. Three polyherbs BJ, PJ, and WR but not OR showed strong free radical scavenging activities in the 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) assay. The treatments of BJ, PJ, OR, and WR significantly increased the cell viabilities under cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity. Consistent with the results of the DPPH assay, superoxide dismutase and catalase activities were increased in the cisplatin-induced cell model treated with BJ, PJ, and WR but not with OR. However, annexin-V-positive cells and cleaved caspase 3 expression were significantly reduced in the cell model treated with all of the polyherbs. Cell proliferation was observed in treatment with all of the polyherbs, which was particularly evident in the OR-treated cells. This provides effective complementary evidences to promote the development of traditional herbal formulas to treat AKI.
 </p>
</abstract>
