<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Virgin olive oil is also enriched in some minority components, such as polyphenols, which are well known for their antimicrobial activity on certain bacteria [
 <xref rid="B13-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] as well as for their anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects [
 <xref rid="B14-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Because of this behavior, the specific influence of polyphenols on the intestinal microbiota has similarly been studied in several foodstuffs [
 <xref rid="B15-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. However, not all commercial olive oils have the intact polyphenol content. Virgin olive oil is extracted mechanically from olives with no chemical intervention and contains relatively high amounts of phenolic compounds and tocopherols. In contrast, if the acidity of the virgin oil is too high; it may undergo a chemical treatment to improve this condition and it is then transformed in refined olive oil (ROO). ROO has the same fatty acid composition as the virgin oil from which it is derived but it looses most of the minority components in the process as well as the palatability and the bouquet [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. This is why it is commercialized only after 10–15% of virgin olive oil has been added, which improves its organoleptic properties. In fact, virgin olive oil has an average polyphenol content of 150–400 mg/kg while refined olive oil has only a residual presence (0–5 mg/kg) [
 <xref rid="B18-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The loss of the unsaponifiable matter is important since it could change some of the healthy properties attributed to virgin olive oil. This importance is magnified by the fact that the commercialization of ROO is significant since, according to the local Ministry of Agriculture [
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], there was 60% consumption of this fat versus 40% consumption of virgin and extra virgin olive oils during 2016 in Spain, the main olive oil producer and one of the leading consumers of this fat in the World. Moreover, ROO is preferred by American consumers over some virgin olive oils, probably because of its milder flavor, according to a recent inquiry [
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. 
</p>
