<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec024" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils have demonstrated a wide range of biological activities (e.g. antibacterial, antifungal, antioxidants, etc…) and remain promising sources of new therapeutics [
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref037">37</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref038">38</a>]. A growing attention has been given to the antiviral capacity of essential oils against arboviruses as illustrated for dengue serotype 2 (DEN-2) virus [
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref039">39</a>], Yellow Fever virus (YFV) [
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref040">40</a>], and Japanese Encephalitis virus (JEV) [
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref041">41</a>]. To the best of our knowledge, none of the available essential oils used as topical mosquito repellents have not yet been investigated for their antiviral capacity against mosquito-borne viruses. In here, we investigated such inhibitory effects of three common essential oils of CC, PG and VZ at non-toxic concentrations against RRV infection.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For this study, HEK293T cells were selected for their high sensitivity to the viral cytopathic effect, in contrast to the resistant skin cell lines [
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref042">42</a>]. In addition, we used a representative RRV strain to provide a fast and representative evaluation of essential oils against the alphaviruses family.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cytopathic effect of RRV-T48 on HEK293T cells observed after 30 h post-infection (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196757.g001" href="#pone.0196757.g001">Fig 1A</a>) and the time-limited cytoprotective effect of the tested essential oils at 32 h post-infection clearly indicated the best opportunity to control RRV infection at the early stages. Specific assays (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196757.g002" href="#pone.0196757.g002">Fig 2</a>) showed that the essential oils do not have virucidal activity and could not interfere with virus entry at the two non-toxic concentrations tested (0.1×CC
  <sub>10</sub> and 1×CC
  <sub>10</sub>). Thus, we carried out further investigations to determine the inhibitory effect of the essential oil on viral replication. This was supported by the time course of infection of RRV-
  <span class="italic">ren</span>Luc at MOI 2 that reached a maximum at 36 hours (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196757.g003" href="#pone.0196757.g003">Fig 3A</a>), leading us to select the endpoint of monitoring at 24 h post-infection for both the luciferase activity and the residual infectivity upon different treatments by the essential oils (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196757.g005" href="#pone.0196757.g005">Fig 5</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, the time-of-addition assay showed that the additional supply of the essential oils of CC and PG prior or during or the viral adsorption (pre-treatment or co-treatment) provides the most significant inhibition of the viral replication (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196757.g006" href="#pone.0196757.g006">Fig 6A</a>). The viral replication was also reduced in post-treatment (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196757.g006" href="#pone.0196757.g006">Fig 6A</a>), but only the PG essential oil exhibited a marked effect on the residual infectivity (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196757.g006" href="#pone.0196757.g006">Fig 6B</a>). This latter result suggests that the PG essential oil may also interfere with the post-transcriptional stage of the virus life cycle.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, the results showed the high potential of the PG essential oil against RRV, as it has low cytotoxicity (CC
  <sub>50</sub> &gt; 1000 μg.mL
  <span class="sup">-1</span>) and displays noteworthy inhibitory effects when present prior, during or after infection. The CC essential oil, which presented the highest cytotoxicity (CC
  <sub>50</sub> = 49.5 ± 20.5 μg.mL
  <span class="sup">-1</span>), exhibited a moderate antiviral activity when introduced prior or during the viral absorption. In contrast, there was no evidence for an inhibitory effect from the VZ essential oil. The contribution of the major components of essential oils to their antiviral properties has been claimed in the case of HSV-1 [
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref043">43</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0196757.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196757.ref045">45</a>]. PG and CC essential oils are monoterpene-rich essential oils in contrast to the non-active VZ essential oil that is mainly constituted by sesquiterpenes. Thus, we propose that antiviral capacity is related to the monoterpene composition, and the actual molecular components deserve to be characterized and explored further.
 </p>
</sec>
