<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM) is an ancient practice of therapy involving use of various forms of herbal medicines, exercise, acupuncture, dietary therapy and massage. It has been proven to be an effective approach to treat various health problems including viral infections. Recently, some reports were published regarding the effectiveness of the TCM in the prevention and treatment of COVID-19. According to the reports, TCM has been identified to be much effective in the treatment and prevention of COVID-19 and had played vital role in controlling the spread of the disease in China (
 <xref rid="B241" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>–
 <xref rid="B243" ref-type="bibr">243</xref>). Use of decoction based on the TCM principles among the medical professionals prevented the iatrogenic infection of the virus. TCM exhibited excellent curative potential; mainly responsible for early control over the spread of new viral infection and thought to be main reason for faster cure rate and discharge from the hospitals in China in comparison to other countries (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B241" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B244" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B245" ref-type="bibr">245</xref>). Treatment of COVID-19 based on TCM has also achieved good results as in one of the study (
 <xref rid="B246" ref-type="bibr">246</xref>), it was reported that out of 1016 diagnosed COVID-19 patients in Hunan province of China, 981 were treated with TCM and 95.76% (779 patients) of them were discharged. Moreover, out of the 233 hospitalized patients, all were cured using TCM with 100% recovery rate (
 <xref rid="B246" ref-type="bibr">246</xref>). In another study, 51 out of 52 COVID-19 patients receiving TCM treatment, showed either improvement or were cured and discharged, with one death (
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr">247</xref>). Decoction prepared from a mixture of Chinese herbs is the most popular therapy of COVID-19 in TCM and the herbs including 
 <italic>Armeniacae Semen Amarum, Gypsum fibrosum, Glycyrrzhiae Radix et Rhizoma</italic> and 
 <italic>Ephedra herba</italic> were the most commonly mentioned in Chinese guidelines (
 <xref rid="B241" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B248" ref-type="bibr">248</xref>).
</p>
