<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Microbial diseases, especially of bacterial origin are very prevalent. A large number of people get sick due to microbial infections every year. This causes a big burden on any country's social as well as financial health. Empiric mode of treatment, which use a repetitive and wide use of antibiotics, has brought a serious threat in the biomedical and clinical sectors by the emergence of multidrug resistant pathogens. Such cases has given an open opportunity to organisms and compelled them to synthesize different types of β-lactamases due to which the efficiency of β-lactamases has been challenged and led to parlous outbreak of drug resistant organisms causing tremendous harm to the human beings [
 <xref rid="R01" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>-
 <xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The administration of antibiotics in the viral infections hampers the immune system of the body and sometimes offers the normal flora of human body to become opportunistic and cause chronic problems [
 <xref rid="R05" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="R06" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].The plant extracts have immense potential to combat bacterial, fungal, protozoan and viral diseases without any known side effects. Presence of secondary metabolites such as flavonoids, alkaloids, tannins, and terpenoids make them suitable candidate among antimicrobial agent [
 <xref rid="R07" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. They are shown to exhibit antimicrobial properties against a wide range of Gram-positive as well as Gram-negative bacteria [
 <xref rid="R08" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Elizabeth et. al, [
 <xref rid="R04" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], studied the antibacterial activity and phytochemical screening of Dialium guineense seed extract against enteric bacteria. Yaraksa, [
 <xref rid="R03" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] reported the use of five different medicinal herbs (i.e. Tristaniopsis burmanica, Capparis zeylanicaLinn., Markhamia stipulata, Caryota maxima and Amphineurion marginatum). Their applicability has not only confined to the antimicrobial properties, rather they also possess anti-inflammatory activity.
</p>
