<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Various herbal or polyherbal dosages and formulations of 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> such as gels, emulsified concentrate, and nanoemulgel have shown improved wound healing, anti-inflammatory, and antimicrobial activity [
 <xref rid="B151-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>,
 <xref rid="B152-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,
 <xref rid="B153-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>,
 <xref rid="B154-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. Still, there has not been ample progress in the context of formulation development by utilizing either the whole 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> L. plant or its extracts. Therefore, this could be a good way to innovate several dosage forms by investing more in progressive technology to enhance the commercial value of this invasive plant. There is a dearth of patents that have been filed and approved for 
 <italic>Ageratum</italic> spp. formulations. China has patented a 
 <italic>Candida</italic> (
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, 
 <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, 
 <italic>C. krusei</italic>) resistant medicine for treating deep and systemic fungal infections containing pogostone screened from various contents of 
 <italic>Ageratum</italic> oil owing to its relatively higher bacteriostatic properties [
 <xref rid="B156-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. A herbal formulation for the treatment of several hair problems has also been patented based on this species [
 <xref rid="B157-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Application of alien invasive plant 
 <italic>A. conyzoides</italic> L. in control of golden apple snail has been patented based on the claim that a dry powder of the plant can kill 
 <italic>Pomacea canaliculate</italic> [
 <xref rid="B158-molecules-26-02933" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. Moreover, world governments should regulate the use of harmful biocides more strictly to encourage the development of safer and economic natural substitutes for fungi management. To establish a clinical role for this medicinally important herb, the hitches mentioned in the preceding paragraphs need to be removed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02933-f005">Figure 5</xref>).
</p>
