<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <italic class="italic">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> is one of the most common food-borne bacteria that causes gastrointestinal symptoms. In the present study we have investigated the molecular basis of the anti-
  <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> effect of peppermint essential oil (PEO), one of the oldest EO used to treat gastrointestinal diseases. Transcriptomic, quantitative reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) and proteomic, two-dimensional polyacryl amid gel electrophoresis (2D-PAGE) methods have revealed that, in the presence of a sublethal concentration of PEO, the expression of several virulence-associated genes was decreased (
  <italic class="italic">cheY</italic> 0.84x;
  <italic class="italic"> flhB</italic> 0.79x;
  <italic class="italic"> flgE</italic> 0.205x;
  <italic class="italic"> cadF</italic> 0.08x;
  <italic class="italic"> wlaB</italic> 0.89x;
  <italic class="italic"> porA</italic> 0.25x;
  <italic class="italic"> cbf2</italic> 4.3x) while impaired motility was revealed with a functional analysis. Scanning electron micrographs of the exposed cells showed that, unlike in the presence of other stresses, the originally curved
  <italic class="italic"> C. jejuni</italic> cells straightened upon PEO exposure. Gaining insight into the molecular background of this stress response, we have revealed that in the presence of PEO
  <italic class="italic"> C. jejuni</italic> dominantly exerts a general stress response that elevates the expression of general stress genes like
  <italic class="italic"> dnaK</italic>,
  <italic class="italic"> groEL</italic>,
  <italic class="italic"> groES</italic> (10.41x, 3.63x, and 4.77x). The most important genes
  <italic class="italic"> dps</italic>,
  <italic class="italic"> sodB</italic>, and
  <italic class="italic"> katA</italic> involved in oxidative stress responses showed however moderate transcriptional elevations (1,58x, 1,55x, and 1,85x).
 </p>
</abstract>
