<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The processing of feed ingredients can reduce the microbiological risks entering the food chain by applying thermal and non-thermal inactivation treatment. However, another aim of the present study was to increase the knowledge of how the insect diet could impact this industrial processing, i.e., BSF biomass drying and oil extraction. Therefore, the analysis of drying profiles related to different diets and conditions (washed or non-washed BSF biomass) was performed. The first finding is related to the convenience in operating a good separation between BSF and its substrate. In case this operation is not done before processing, the final product becomes very difficult to separate (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="animals-09-00278-f004" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>). Moreover, drying is important in terms of energy consumption and the duration of the process is related to its economic convenience. According to Spranghers et al. [
 <xref rid="B26-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], the content of moisture was not significantly different in BSF pre-pupae reared on substrates of various origins (including vegetable matter), being around 60% of the total fresh biomass. This is the most important parameter to consider in the drying process. In our laboratory experiments, the percent residue weight (
 <italic class="italic">Wr</italic>) of BSF biomass was approximately the same for all the theses and the differences in the drying profiles appeared to be mostly related to the initial insect mass than to the different content of water. The large-scale drying, which had a yield of 33% d.m. on the total fresh insect biomass, confirmed this finding. These data perfectly agree with the study by Tschirner and Simon [
 <xref rid="B59-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>], who found about 30% d.m. content for BSF prepupae reared on control and protein diet. Although the water content did not vary significantly in the different drying theses, and the d.m. content was in agreement with literature data, the comparison of drying profiles highlighted interesting differences. In fact, BSF biomass coming from VMD rearing was faster in drying than BSF biomass originated by SD rearing, starting from the 180th minute of the heating process. This phenomenon is particularly remarkable in a circular economy system because it involves considerations about energy and, therefore, cost saving. In Spranghers et al. [
 <xref rid="B26-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], fat content is higher in pre-pupae reared on vegetable waste (about 37% d.m.) than in those reared on chicken feed or digestate (34 and 22% d.m., respectively). Our nutritional analysis of VMD BSF biomass assessed that oil content was 35.62%. Lipid and protein content in fat body cells showed modifications depending on the rearing substrates. Fat body of larvae reared on SD (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="animals-09-00278-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>C) showed a higher number of protein granules, but a lower dimension of lipid droplets, compared to larvae grown on VMD (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="animals-09-00278-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>D). Although morphological analysis of BSF organs provides an indication on the quality more than on the quantity of reserves present in the insect cells, it corroborates the hypothesis that a different quantity or distribution of the fat and protein amounts in the BSF reared on different substrates can affect the speed of the drying process. Preliminary comparative analyses (data not shown), demonstrated that BSF biomass originated from VMD has a reduced protein content and an increased fat amount in comparison to SD. These findings support the aforementioned morphological data.
</p>
