<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">After drying, another basic process is oil extraction, which has the aim to produce defatted insect meal to increase its shelf-life, especially meal oxidative stability. BSF oil is also an important economic resource, because it can represent an alternative to fish oil that is used to feed carnivorous fish or other animals, due to its high lipid content [
 <xref rid="B1-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. However, BSF inclusion in fish and poultry diet can negatively affect the fatty acid profiles of their meat, because the polyunsaturated fat content tends to decrease, while saturated and monounsaturated fat content tends to increase [
 <xref rid="B60-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. Therefore, in our study, the efficiency of oil extraction from the insect biomass was analyzed. Few reports on the extraction yield of oil obtained from insect mechanical pressing are available in the literature. However, the percentage of oil recovered (64%) in this study by mass oil extraction, was satisfying if compared to the 40% oil recovery obtained by Surrendra et al. [
 <xref rid="B63-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. Once the insect meal is obtained, an important aspect is the evaluation of its nutritional value for monogastric animals. In the last few years, the aquaculture industry has become increasingly interested in using insects to replace fishmeal in aquafeeds. Reviews on the use of insect meal as a feed ingredient in farmed fish are available [
 <xref rid="B64-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Recently, some studies investigated the effects of partial fishmeal substitution with BSF meal on fish growth performances showing that insect meal effectively supports fish growth [
 <xref rid="B64-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. On the basis of the chemical analysis presented in the Results, four fish diets were prepared with different substitution levels of fishmeal with insect meal. In the feeding trial, all the experimental diets were well accepted (no palatability issues) by rainbow trout that tripled their initial body weight. In line with previous studies conducted on rainbow trout [
 <xref rid="B67-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>], dietary inclusion of defatted BSF meal up to 30% did not affect growth performance. Indeed, in all treatments, the weight gain was very good, and no differences were found among dietary fish groups. In salmon, BSF could replace up to 100% of dietary fishmeal (corresponding to 25% of inclusion) without any significant effect on growth if methionine and lysine are supplemented to the diet [
 <xref rid="B65-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. In yellow catfish, a diet in which fishmeal protein was replaced by 25% of BSF meal gave the greatest growth performance and immune indices compared with the control diet containing 40% of fishmeal [
 <xref rid="B66-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. The reduced fish growth rate is usually due to a deficiency in lysine or methionine or to an imbalanced level of essential amino acids in the diet. In our feeding trial, the amino acid profile of experimental diets correlated well with trout requirement values, showing lysine and methionine levels comparable to control fishmeal-based diet, independently of BSF meal dietary inclusion.
</p>
