<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">At the end of the insect rearing process, leftovers resulted from the feeding activity of BSF larvae, were employed for the earthworm rearing. Earthworms recycle organic matter, increase nutrient availability, and improve soil structure, thus providing a service to the ecosystem. Vermicompost is the product of the composting process carried out by the worms and can be used for organic agriculture. In the past, attempts were carried out to grow earthworms and BSF contemporaneously. However, earthworms inoculated before organic waste decomposition by BSF could not survive, probably because of the acidic environment and high temperature created by the larvae and their excreta [
 <xref rid="B69-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. Furthermore, it is well known that BSF larvae can modify the microflora of the substrate in which they live, as they produce bactericidal, bacteriostatic, and fungicidal compounds [
 <xref rid="B70-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. This could be particularly detrimental for earthworms, as there is evidence that microorganisms provide food for them; while bacteria are of minor importance in their diet and algae are of moderate importance, protozoa and fungi are major sources of nutrients, as associated to earthworms’ intestinal tract [
 <xref rid="B71-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. Although a joint action with BSF is not possible, earthworms can intervene when the development of BSF larvae is completed, usefully employing the residuals of larval activity for their own growth and soil amendment production, as shown in 
 <xref rid="animals-09-00278-t008" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 8</xref> and 
 <xref rid="animals-09-00278-t009" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 9</xref>. Earthworm rearing was performed for 45 days only; therefore, data presented in this work are preliminary and had the aim to test the possible negative effect of BSF leftovers on earthworm development. In the tested ratio with peat moss, BSF leftovers not only did not affect earthworm survival, but also sustained their growth at least as the fruit and vegetable waste themselves. In general, the BSF leftovers are richer in N in comparison to fruit and vegetable wastes; therefore, they are positive starting material to lower the C/N ratio of the amendment. According to the Italian legislation [
 <xref rid="B72-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>], the ratio C/N in plant amendment should be &lt;25. This is the case of our mix of peat moss and BSF leftovers, after the earthworm action. Although this is not the only parameter that must be considered to define the product of the composting action as a plant amendment, it confirms the process feasibility.
</p>
