<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0075">THC, in comparison to curcumin, was found to be more stable at physiological conditions, more soluble in the aqueous medium, while curcumin more lipid-soluble than THC and more readily absorbed through the gastrointestinal tract in addition to having good stability in the plasma [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], which was the reason why THC was considered as an accessible form of curcumin in vivo [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] Thus, there is a possibility that differential absorption and metabolism of curcumin and tetrahydrocurcumin in cells determine their biological functions. THC demonstrated similar functional activities like curcumin. However, numerous 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies have proved that curcumin possesses better therapeutic properties than THC, including antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anti-cancer and, anti-viral. A comparative study of activities of both compounds has been summarized by BB Aggarwal 
 <italic>et al.</italic> However, there are some known functional differences between curcumin and THC due to their structural differences. Unlike curcumin, THC lacks α, β dienes that is the reason for its inability to form Michael adducts with intracellular proteins. However, curcumin may disrupt the formation of a disulfide bond by electrophilic dienone. Free thiols on cysteine-rich proteins were available to react with Michael acceptors of curcumin but not with THC [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Recently, in contrast to curcumin, THC found incapable of inhibiting HDAC1 (histone deacetylase) and PCAF (acetyltransferase) due to the absence of double bonds, which form Michael acceptor moiety in curcumin. Studies confirmed the previous speculation that THC possesses a different mechanism to deal with cancer than that of curcumin [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
