<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="fsn3508-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animal protein is still far more expensive than their plant counterpart for most dwellers of the developing countries, and for years this has aroused the rigorous researches on underutilized legumes and oilseeds that can be used as protein source in food ingredients and functional foods formulation (Chavan, McKenzie, &amp; Shahidi, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0016">2001</a>; Sreerama, Neelam, Sashikala, &amp; Pratape, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0050">2010</a>). The nutritional and functional properties of protein isolate from legumes and oilseeds has increased their rate of application in meats and sausages, baked and extruded products, salad dressings and frozen desserts (Asgar, Fazilah, Huda, Bhat, &amp; Karim, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0011">2010</a>; Day, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0018">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conophor nut (
  <span class="italic">Tetracarpidium conophorum</span>), commonly called African walnut, is one of the greatly underutilized oilseeds belonging to the family 
  <span class="italic">Euphorbiaceae</span>. The monoecious and high‐climbing plant produce seeds which become dark brown with hard testa when mature. Its economic importance lies in the edibility of its oil‐rich seeds which are consumed in Sub‐Saharan Africa (Enujiugha, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0023">2008</a>). The nut is rich in minerals and high‐quality proteins (Odoemelam, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0041">2003</a>; Edem, Dosunmu, &amp; Bassey, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0020">2009</a>). This makes it a potential plant protein that can supplement the monotonous starchy staples being consumed by many in developing countries with little or no alternatives.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bitter after‐taste of raw conophor nut upon reaction with water has greatly limited its use in food product development. Till date, neither is there any final product application reported for the oil‐rich seed nor any use as protein supplement. Processing through the application of heat has been reported to reduce antinutritional factors and toxic contents in nuts and legumes resulting in more effective use of the seeds (Devappa &amp; Swamylingappa, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0019">2008</a>; Arinola &amp; Adesina, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0009">2014</a>). Toasting, aside from reducing antinutrients, improves the taste and nutrient quality of food products and lowers the moisture contents, thus increasing the shelf life. The amino acid composition and functional properties of cashew nut were reported to have improved due to processing (Fagbemi, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0025">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent times, the food industries employ more of the protein concentrates and isolates from plants rather than the flour protein with their naturally occurring matrices that include carbohydrates and lipids (Arogundade, Eromosele, Ademuyiwa, &amp; Eromosele, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0010">2009</a>; Shevkani, Kaur, Kumar, &amp; Singh, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0049">2015</a>). Soy and wheat are among the most used plant protein isolate and concentrates, however, due to the allergenicity of these plants, the search for alternative is imperative (Boye et al., 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0014">2010</a>). The full‐fat seed, defatted flour, and protein isolate of raw conophor nut had been shown to exhibit several desirable functions that could enhance its use in the food system (Enujiugha, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0022">2003</a>; Ndie, Nnamani, &amp; Oselebe, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0040">2010</a>; Gbadamosi, Abiose, &amp; Aluko, 
  <a rid="fsn3508-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3508-bib-0028">2012a</a>). However, there is the need for improvement on these functionalities to further enhance the desirability of conophor nut as a food ingredient.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, conophor nut was processed by boiling and toasting and the effect of these heat processing operations on the nutritional quality and functional characteristics of the defatted oil seeds and protein isolates were analyzed along with the amino acid composition. This is expected to provide information on the possible uses of conophor proteins as potential functional ingredients and food supplements.</p>
</sec>
