<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to nitrogen pollution and protein resource shortage, the use of antibiotic growth promoters has promoted bacterial resistance, leading to less efficient treatments for animal bacterial diseases [
 <xref rid="B6-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. Several countries in Europe have completely banned the addition of antibiotics to livestock feed [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. In China, although the inclusion of antibiotics in feed for growing-finishing pigs is still a common practice, it has increasingly received safety concerns from consumers. Therefore, further researches are needed to develop effective and safe alternatives for growth and disease prevention in pigs. As desirable alternatives to antibiotics, herbal feed additives have been reported to improve performance of pigs by enhancing their intestinal health [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Oregano essential oil (OEO) is mainly composed of natural and volatile aromatic compounds, which have antimicrobial and antioxidative activities [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Our previous studies suggested that OEO supplementation could reduce the population of 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> in the ileum and improve the small intestinal morphology and antioxidant enzyme activities of pigs [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. However, it should be pointed out that the basal diet for these studies was a normal protein diet that met or exceeded the NRC [
 <xref rid="B14-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] nutrient requirement estimates. Recent studies have shown that dietary protein levels affect pig intestinal bacteria, intestinal morphology, and digestive function [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Moreover, the activity of antibiotics and their alternatives (such as probiotics) was reported to be affected by dietary protein supply [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. However, no research is available about the influences of OEO inclusion in a reduced-protein diet on growth performance, gut microbiota, intestinal morphology, and antioxidative capacity of growing-finishing pigs. Moreover, the effect of adding OEO as an alternative to antibiotics to a reduced-protein diet on the performance and health status of pigs also remains largely unknown.
</p>
