<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fresh leaves of 
   <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> L. samples were harvested from the local market at Sfax (Tunisia) (N: 34.4426°, E: 10.4537°) during the vegetative stage in June 2013. The samples were identified and authenticated by a senior botanist, Pr. Ferjani Ben Abdallah, at the Faculty of Science of Sfax, University of Sfax (Tunisia). From 50 individual 
   <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> L. plants each, a total of 80–100 leaves (≈ 12 cm
   <span class="sup">2</span> in size) were randomly collected from the base to the apex. The fresh leaves were mixed and immediately dried in the shade away from light at room temperature. After drying, the samples were grounded to a fine powder that was used for the extraction of essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil preparation</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MpEO was extracted by the steam distillation method. A mass of 3 kg of dry plant material was hydrodistillated for 2 h in a Clevenger-type apparatus. The recovered (0.47%) essential oil was dried with anhydrous Na
   <sub>2</sub>SO
   <sub>4</sub>, and stored at 4 °C.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> essential oil composition
  </div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MpEO compositional analysis of the volatile constituents was performed on a Hewlett-Packard gas chromatograph GC: 5890 series II. The fused HP-Innowax capillary column (polyethylene glycol, 30 m, 0.25 μm, ID, 0.25 mm film thickness) was directly connected to the mass spectrometer. Nitrogen was used as a carrier gas at a flow rate of 1.2 ml/min. Oven temperature was initially set at 50 °C (1 min) and gradually raised to 250 °C (5 min) at 7 °C/min. The temperatures of the injection port and detector were maintained at 250 and 280 °C, respectively. The mass spectrometer was operated (full scan-mode) in the EI-mode at 70 eV.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Component identification</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil components were identified based on their mass spectra and computer matching with the data available in the Wiley 275 library (Wiley, New York).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vitro antioxidant activities test</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity of the MpEO was determined by two methods and compared with the activity of silymarin, a standardized extract of the milk thistle seeds that containes a mixture of flavonolignans. Silymarin has a number of potential mechanisms including chemoprotective effects from environmental toxins and anti-inflammatory activity and is used as a drug.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurement of free radical-scavenging action</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2,2-Diphenyl picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radicals scavenging activity was assessed according to Blois [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], with a slight modification. Different concentrations of the MpEO and silymarin (5–100 μg/ml) were mixed with 1 ml of 0.1 mM DPPH in ethanol solution and 450 μL of 50 mM Tris-HCl buffer (pH 7.4) was added. The solution was incubated at 37 °C for 30 min and the reduction of DPPH free radicals was measured by reading the absorbance at ʎ = 517 nm. Silymarin was used as reference standard. The activity is given as % DPPH scavenging and calculated according to the following equation:
   <div id="Equa" class="disp-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{DPPH}\ \mathrm{scavenging}=\left[\left(\mathrm{control}\ \mathrm{OD}-\mathrm{sample}\ \mathrm{OD}\right)/\mathrm{control}\ \mathrm{OD}\right]\times 100 $$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
      <span class="mo">%</span>
      <span class="mtext">DPPH scavenging</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div close="]" open="[" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div close=")" open="(" class="mfenced">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mtext">control</span>
          <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
          <span class="mi">OD</span>
          <span class="mo">-</span>
          <span class="mtext">sample</span>
          <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
          <span class="mi">OD</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">/</span>
        <span class="mtext">control</span>
        <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
        <span class="mi">OD</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <span class="mn">100</span>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity of MpEO is expressed as IC50, defined as the concentration of MpEO required to cause a 50% decrease in initial DPPH concentration. Each sample was analyzed six times.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scavenging of superoxide anion</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of MpEO on the generation of superoxide anion was measured according to the method described by Yen &amp; Chen, 1995 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Superoxide anion was generated in a non-enzymatic system and determined by spectrophotometric measurement for the reduction of nitroblue tetrazolium. The reaction mixture, which contained 100 μL of essential oil in ethanol, 800 μL of 1 M phosphate buffer (pH 7.4), 400 μL of distilled water, 100 μL of 0.1 M Na
   <sub>4</sub>EDTA, 100 μL of 1.5 mM NBT and 50 μL of 0.12 mM riboflavin was incubated at ambient temperature for 5 min, and the color was read at ʎ = 560 nm against blank samples.
   <div id="Equb" class="disp-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{superoxide}\ \mathrm{anion}\ \mathrm{scavenging}=\left[\left(\mathrm{blank}\ \mathrm{OD}-\mathrm{sample}\ \mathrm{OD}\right)/\mathrm{OD}\ \mathrm{blank}\right]\times 100 $$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M4" display="block" class="math">
      <span class="mo">%</span>
      <span class="mtext">superoxide anion scavenging</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div close="]" open="[" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div close=")" open="(" class="mfenced">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mtext">blank</span>
          <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
          <span class="mi">OD</span>
          <span class="mo">-</span>
          <span class="mtext">sample</span>
          <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
          <span class="mi">OD</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mo">/</span>
        <span class="mi">OD</span>
        <span width="0.25em" class="mspace"/>
        <span class="mtext">blank</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <span class="mn">100</span>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where blank OD is the absorbance of the control reaction and sample OD is the absorbance in the presence of MpEO. The IC50 was calculated from the plot of the inhibition percentage against the essential oil concentration. Each sample was analyzed six times.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vivo antioxidant properties</div>
  <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animal</div>
   <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Male 
    <span class="italic">Wistar</span> rats, weighing about 200–220 g, were purchased from the Central Pharmacy of Tunisia (SIPHAT, Tunisia). They were housed at 22 ± 3 °C with light/dark periods of 12 h and a minimum relative humidity of 40%. The animals had free access to commercial pellet diet (SICO, Sfax, Tunisia) and water ad libitum. The general guidelines for the use and care of living animals in scientific investigations were followed [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. The handling of the animals was approved by the Tunisian Ethical Committee for the Care and Use of laboratory animals.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental design</div>
   <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After acclimatizing to the laboratory conditions for 1 week, 70 rats were divided into 7 groups of 10 animals and treated for 7 days as follow [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]:
   </p>
   <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rats of group 1 served as normal control and received saline orally daily for 7 days and were injected with 1 ml/kg BW of just olive oil (the solvent of CCl
    <sub>4</sub>) on the 7 day. The rats of group 2 served as CCl
    <sub>4</sub>-hepato and renotoxicity control and were received saline orally daily for 7 days and were injected with 1 ml/kg BW of CCl
    <sub>4</sub> and olive oil mixture on the 7 day (a single intraperitoneal injection). The CCl
    <sub>4</sub> dose was selected according to the reference dose for chronic oral exposure (RFD) as recommended for CCl
    <sub>4</sub> (CASRN 56–23-5) [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rats of group 3 were pretreated orally seven times with a dose of 50 mg/kg BW of reference drug silymarin with an interval of 24 h [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rats of groups 4, 5, 6 and 7 were pretreated orally seven times with doses of 5, 15 and 40 mg MpEO /kg BW, respectively with an interval of 24 h [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After pretreatment with either silymarin or MpEO for 7 days, the rats of groups 3, 4, 5 and 6 received a single intraperitoneal injection of CCl
    <sub>4</sub> (1 ml/kg BW) on the 7 day.
   </p>
   <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rats were killed 24 h after vehicle or CCl
    <sub>4</sub> single injection. The animals in the different groups were killed by cervical decapitation to avoid stress conditions.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample collection</div>
   <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Serum was prepared by centrifugation (1500×
    <span class="italic">g</span>, 15 min, 4 °C; Beckman-Coulter, Marseille, France) and stored at −80 °C for further biochemical assays. The liver and kidney tissues were immediately removed and dissected over ice-cold glass slides and a part was homogenized (10% 
    <span class="italic">w</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span>) with an Ultra Turrax homogenizer in ice-cold, 1.15% KCl-0.01 M sodium, potassium phosphate buffer. Homogenates were centrifuged at 10000×
    <span class="italic">g</span> for 20 min at 4 °C. The resulting supernatants were used for immediate lipid peroxidation and protein oxidation determination. Homogenate aliquots were stored at −80 °C for further biochemical assays. Other parts of these livers and kidney tissues were fixed in 10% formaldehyde solution and processed for paraffin sectioning and histological studies.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biochemical assays</div>
  <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biochemical markers in plasma</div>
   <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plasma levels of aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), γ-glutamyl transpeptidase (γ-GT), cholesterol (TC), triglycerides (TG), low-density lipoprotein (LDL), high-density lipoprotein (HDL), creatinine and urea rates were measured in plasma samples by standardized enzymatic procedures using commercial kits from (Biolabo, Maizy, France) on an automatic biochemistry analyzer (Vitalab Flexor E, Diamond Diagnostics, Holliston, MA).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Protein quantification</div>
   <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Protein content in liver and kidney tissues were determined according to the method of Lowry et al. [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>] using bovine serum albumin as a standard.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lipid peroxidation</div>
   <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Malondialdehyde concentrations (marker for lipid peroxidation) in liver and kidney tissues were determined spectrophotometrically according to Draper &amp; Hadley [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Briefly, an aliquot of liver and kidney extracts supernatant was mixed with 1 ml of 5% trichloroacetic acid and centrifuged at 2500×
    <span class="italic">g</span> for 10 min. One ml of thiobarbituric acid reagent (0.67%) was added to 500 μl of supernatant and heated at 90 °C for 15 min. The mixture was cooled and the absorbance measured at 532 nm using a spectrophotometer (Jenway UV-6305, Essex, England). The malondialdehyde values were calculated using 1,1,3,3-tetraethoxypropane as standard and expressed as nmol of malondialdehyde/mg of protein.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determination antioxidant enzyme activities in liver and kidney tissue</div>
   <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Catalase (CAT) activity was measured according to Aebi [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. A total of 20 μL tissue homogenate (about 1.5 mg proteins) was added to 1 ml phosphate buffer (0.1 M, pH 7) containing 100 mM H
    <sub>2</sub>O
    <sub>2</sub>. Rate of H
    <sub>2</sub>O
    <sub>2</sub> decomposition was followed by measuring the decrease in absorbance at 240 nm for 1 min. The enzyme activity was calculated using an extinction coefficient of 0.043 mM
    <span class="sup">−1</span> cm
    <span class="sup">−1</span> and expressed in international units (I.U.), i.e. in μmol H
    <sub>2</sub>O
    <sub>2</sub> destroyed/min/ mg protein, at 25 °C.
   </p>
   <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity was estimated according to Beyer and Fridovich [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. The reaction mixture contained 50 mM of tissue homogenates in potassium phosphate buffer (pH 7.8), 0.1 mM EDTA, 13 mM L-methionine, 2 mM riboflavin and 75 mM nitro blue tetrazolium (NBT). The developed blue color in the reaction was measured at 560 nm. Units of SOD activity were expressed as the amount of enzyme required to inhibit the reduction of NBT by 50% and the activity was expressed as units/mg of protein, at 25 °C. Glutathione peroxidase (GPx) activity was measured by the procedure of Flohe and Gunzler [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. One milliliter of reaction mixture containing 0.3 ml of phosphate buffer (0.1 M, pH 7.4), 0.2 ml of 2 mM glutathione (GSH), 0.1 ml of sodium azide (10 mM), 0.1 ml of H
    <sub>2</sub>O
    <sub>2</sub> (1 mM) and 0.3 ml of liver and kidney supernatant were prepared. After incubation at 37 °C for 15 min, the reaction was terminated by adding 0.5 ml 5% TCA. Tubes were centrifuged at 1500×g for 10 min and the supernatant was collected. To 0.1 ml of this reaction supernatant, 0.2 ml of (0.1 M pH 7.4) and 0.7 mL of 5,5 dithiobis-(2-Nitrobenzoic acid) (DTNB, 0.4 mg/ml) were added. After mixing, absorbance was recorded at 420 nm and the enzyme activity was calculated as μmol of GSH oxidized/min/mg protein.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Histopathological studies</div>
   <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the time of sacrifice, the liver and kidney tissues were removed and fixed in 10% formaldehyde solution and washed. The tissues were dehydrated in increasing gradient of ethanol, finally cleared in toluene and embedded in molten paraffin wax. Sections were cut at 4–5 μm thickness and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E). The slides were photographed with an Olympus UTU1X-2 camera connected to an Olympus CX41 microscope (Tokyo, Japan).</p>
   <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The histological damage in liver was quantified by measuring the index of tissue large numbers of inflammatory cells such as lymphocytes together with hepatic sinusoidal inflammation, hepatocyte necrosis and devastating liver architecture. Moreover, the histological damage in kidney was quantified by measuring the index of tissue the glomerular and tubular necrosis. To evaluate the severity of lesions, the degree of liver and kidney damage was graded according to a zero to four-point scoring system [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>], where 0 indicates no damage, I indicates slight damage (1–25%), II indicates discrete damage (26–50%), III indicates moderate damage (51–75%) and IV indicates severe damage (76–100%).The tabulation of data and the statistical analysis were made in accordance with the number of animals with established scores. All the parameters were quantified by a single observer who was not aware of the treatment groups.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
   <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All values are expressed as mean ± SE for continues variables or as median with inter quartile range [25%, 75%] where appropriate. The results were analyzed by One-Way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey test for multiple comparisons using SPSS for Windows (version. 12) or ANOVA-on-ranks with Dunn’s correction. Differences were considered significant at 
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
