<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>AMD treatment focuses on antioxidant substances to prevent or reduce oxidative stress effects, and anti-VEGF substances to reduce neovascularisation, among others. In view of the results of this review, several medicinal plants and natural products might be a beneficial supplementary treatment or an alternative treatment, depending on the AMD type. On the one hand, and according to background knowledge (Datta et al., 2017; Bungau et al., 2019), retinal diseases linked to ageing, such as AMD, are associated with oxidative stress. On the other hand, the late AMD form includes the chorioidal neovascularisation complex, which is associated with serious retina problems (Mitchell et al., 2018). Among medicinal plants and according to the most up-to-date scientific background, saffron, ginkgo, bilberry and blueberry, and curcuma or turmeric, are the most reported possibilities. Regarding natural products, carotenoids and polyphenols are the most commonly used with positive results on AMD prevention or treatment. Among medicinal plants, saffron improves visual function at safe doses far below the lethal dose, as clinical trials show (Falsini et al., 2010; Piccatdi et al., 2012; Marango et al., 2013; Lashay et al., 2016; Riazi et al., 2017; Broadhead et al., 2019; Di Marco et al., 2019). These positive effects appear to be mainly related to antioxidant ability, although the mechanism of action seems complex by ranging from antioxidant activity to gene expression control (Natoli et al., 2010). The same occurs with berry extracts from bilberry and blueberry, whose beneficial effects on AMD are due mainly to the antioxidant ability, together with their capability to improve eye blood flow (Osada et al., 2017; Huang et al., 2018). Although the effects of both species are similar, the main active phytochemicals differ, with carotenoids for saffron and polyphenols (flavonoids) for bilberry and blueberry. The medicinal plants that possess antioxidant and antiangiogenic properties are curcuma and ginkgo. These species are useful in late AMD when neovascularisation exists. However, curcuma, and its main active principle, curcumin, possess low solubility and oral bioavailability that must be compensated for by the addition or presence of non-curcuminoid components to increase their bioavailability (Antony et al., 2008). Regarding isolated compounds, carotenoids (including A vitamin) and polyphenols are the most reported natural products used for AMD treatment with positive results. The former are antioxidant substances responsible for saffron activity. Among these substances, lutein and zeaxanthin are more recommended for reducing the AMD risk than carotene (AREDS, 2014). Furthermore, no clinically significant adverse reactions attributable to lutein and zeaxanthin are reported. However, anti-VEGF activity is not described and would not, therefore, be effective in reducing neovascularisation. Carotenois have different effects, according to the studies consulted. Most of them show positive results in the prevention and protection of AMD. However, there are clinical trials and epidemiological studies that show that these substances do not have a clear beneficial effect on AMD, because they could not delay their progression. Perhaps the heterogenization of researches is one of the causes that produce these differences. Among polyphenols, it is worth highlighting two substance types, stilbenes and flavonoids, more specifically, RV as stilbene, and quercetin and anthocyanidins as flavonoids. The main action of RV is antioxidant (Abu-Amero et al., 2016). Thus, in principle, it could be a good substance for preventing or reducing AMD without neovascularisation, but its anti-inflammatory and anti-oxidant properties combined can be used against AMD with neovascularisation (Fernandez-Araque et al., 2017). Finally, and according to the information found in consulted articles, vitamins C and E show no clear relation with AMD improvement. Despite positive results being reported, in all cases the authors agree that more research, including clinical trials, are necessary to understand the mechanism of action of certain substances, and to know doses and dose regimens to ensure that these treatments are safe and effective. In order to fill in all review information, we would like to make a final reflection and a proposal. According to AREDS 2 (Age-Related Eye Disease Study 2), taking vitamin and mineral supplements daily improves AMD, particularly in the case of dry AMD, when there are many drusen (AREDS2 et al., 2012). This study proposes taking nutritional supplements every day to reduce the risk of suffering from late or wet AMD. The components of this supplement include vitamin C, vitamin E, lutein, zeaxanthin, zinc and copper (Chew et al., 2015). In addition, Khoo et al. (2019) commented that several antioxidants, such as anthocyanins, carotenoids, flavonoids and vitamins reduce the risk of getting eye-related diseases. They stressed that the combined antioxidants and vitamins have a synergistic effect that improves prevention and reduces the risk of macular degeneration. Based on these reflections and all the information in our review work, we can make a proposal to use medicinal plants with anti-VEGF properties and natural antioxidant products to treat and improve AMD. Therefore, Curcuma or Ginkgo plus lutein, zeaxanthin and vitamins may be a good option, but clinical trials are necessary.</p>
