<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the past 30 years, over 47 bioactive polysaccharide fractions have been isolated and purified from the fruiting body, mycelium and cultured medium of 
 <italic>G. frondosa</italic> using different extraction methods. As previously reported, 
 <italic>G. frondosa</italic> contains 3.8% water-soluble polysaccharides on a dry weight basis, of which 13.2% was (1→3, 1→6)-β-D-glucan [
 <xref rid="B46-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and others include heteroglycan or the heteroglycan/protein complex [
 <xref rid="B47-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Among these bioactive polysaccharide fractions, the D-fraction and the MD-fraction (purified D-fraction) [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], which are regarded as the most important bioactive polysaccharides, have been officially used as antitumor, anticancer and immunomodulatory agents [
 <xref rid="B48-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Through structural characterization, Nanba and Kubo discovered the complex structure of the β-D-glucan in the D-fraction. Unlike other mushroom-derived β-glucans that contained a (1→3) main chain with (1→6) branches only, the β-D-glucan in D-fraction possessed both a (1→6) main chain with (1→3) branches and a (1→3) main chain with (1→6) branches [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The high molecular weight of the D-fraction was considered a factor contributing to its strong immunomodulatory effects [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-10-00095" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-10-00095-f003">Figure 3</xref> shows a typical structure of the D-fraction. The D-fraction and the MD-fraction could be extracted and fractionated from both the mycelium and fruiting body of 
 <italic>G. frondosa</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="foods-10-00095-f004">Figure 4</xref> is a general flowchart for the extraction and purification of the MD-fraction as reported by Nanba and coworkers. The MD fraction is typically extracted from the dried 
 <italic>G. frondosa</italic> powder with boiling water and then isolated by ethanol precipitation. The precipitate (crude MD fraction) is further fractionated through column chromatography, including ion exchange and gel permeation chromatography, to obtain the purified MD fraction.
</p>
