<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5206676</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep39857</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep39857</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of the Global Warming Potential of Biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> Emission in Life Cycle Assessments</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Weiguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zhonghui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Xinfeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Zhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>von Gadow</surname><given-names>Klaus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Junming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Shanshan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Yuchun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>School of Natural Resources, West Virginia University</institution>, Morgantown, WV 26506, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Jilin Province Academy of Forestry Research</institution>, Changchun, 130033, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>School of Forest Resources and Environmental Science, Michigan Technological University</institution>, Houghton, MI 49931, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Organismal Biology (EEOB), Iowa State University</institution>, Ames, IA 50011, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>Burckhardt Institute, Georg-August University G&#x000f6;ttingen</institution>, G&#x000f6;ttingen, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="a6"><label>6</label><institution>Institute of Chemical Industry of Forest Products CAF</institution>, Nanjing, Jiangsu, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>xinfengx@mtu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>01</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>39857</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017, The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Biomass is generally believed to be carbon neutral. However, recent studies have challenged the carbon neutrality hypothesis by introducing metric indicators to assess the global warming potential of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> (GWP<sub>bio</sub>). In this study we calculated the GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors using a forest growth model and radiative forcing effects with a time horizon of 100 years and applied the factors to five life cycle assessment (LCA) case studies of bioproducts. The forest carbon change was also accounted for in the LCA studies. GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors ranged from 0.13&#x02013;0.32, indicating that biomass could be an attractive energy resource when compared with fossil fuels. As expected, short rotation and fast-growing biomass plantations produced low GWP<sub>bio</sub>. Long-lived wood products also allowed more regrowth of biomass to be accounted as absorption of the CO<sub>2</sub> emission from biomass combustion. The LCA case studies showed that the total life cycle GHG emissions were closely related to GWP<sub>bio</sub> and energy conversion efficiency. By considering the GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors and the forest carbon change, the production of ethanol and bio-power appeared to have higher GHG emissions than petroleum-derived diesel at the highest GWP<sub>bio</sub>.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Biomass is generally considered as a carbon neutral energy resource because the emissions from biomass combustion will be absorbed by plants through photosynthesis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. The first comprehensive guideline for estimating greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions and sinks alleged that &#x0201c;CO<sub>2</sub> emission resulting from bioenergy consumption should not be included in a country&#x02019;s official emission inventory&#x0201d;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. According to the guidelines compiled by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), CO<sub>2</sub> emission from bioenergy sources should not be counted in national greenhouse gas inventories because the emission from bioenergy sources is already fully included in the Agriculture, Forestry and Other Land-Use (AFOLU) sector<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. Therefore, bioenergy is always referred as a carbon neutral source of energy and promoted by government policies as a substitute for fossil fuels. For the same reason, no carbon tax is applied for burning biomass in any country around the world.</p><p>Due to the assumption of zero climate change potential of biomass combustion, the methods for assessing its global warming impact in environmental analysis tools (e.g. SimaPro, GaBi) usually do not include the biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission and even treat biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission as a negative impact<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>. In addition, most of the life cycle assessment (LCA) studies conducted on bioenergy systems also claim that CO<sub>2</sub> emission from biomass has no global warming potential (GWP). Cherubini and Str&#x000f8;mman reviewed 94 LCA studies of bioenergy systems and found that only one single case study included an account of the climate change impact of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. Shonnard <italic>et al</italic>. reviewed 74 LCA case studies in the Pan American region and found that most of the articles assumed carbon neutrality of biomass combustion<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. This carbon neutrality assumption, which could reduce the GWP of a bioenergy system, might be suitable if the rotation length of biomass were as short as in the case of perennial grass. However, the assumption may not hold when the rotation lengths are long, especially such as those of boreal forests which can be 100 years<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. The exclusion of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission in LCA also brings an unfair comparison of the GHG emissions from bioenergy and fossil fuel systems, although biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission is fully accounted for in the AFOLU sector.</p><p>More recently, researchers have become aware that CO<sub>2</sub> emission from biomass combustion may have, to some extent, a climate change impact because the CO<sub>2</sub> emitted by biomass combustion is a one-time pulse and remains in the atmosphere for several years. Johnson strongly asserted that biomass fuel might not always be carbon neutral and could in fact have a far greater impact than fossil fuels<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. Searchinger <italic>et al</italic>. also questioned the carbon neutrality assumption and suggested that shorter rotation lengths would be able to lower the GWP by absorbing the emissions after biomass combustion<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>. Several recent studies have proposed a method to calculate the GWP of CO<sub>2</sub> emission derived from biomass, providing estimates of GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors for different scenarios<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. The GWP<sub>bio</sub> was calculated by the relative radiative forcing effect during its stay in the atmosphere. With a 100-year time horizon, their estimates of GWP<sub>bio</sub> fell in the range of 0.34&#x02013;0.62 when the rotation length was 100 years. Cherubini <italic>et al</italic>. estimated GWP<sub>bio</sub> for rotation lengths from 1to 100 years and revealed a negligible GWP<sub>bio</sub> for short rotation lengths<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. If the forest stands were harvested for long-lived wood products, the GWP<sub>bio</sub> could be as low as -1if the wood products were collected for bioenergy after decommissioning<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>.</p><p>The application of GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors is straight forward. These factors can be considerably lower than 1, implying an advantage of bioenergy compared to fossil fuels in a climate change perspective. However, Holtsmark articulated the weakness of the previous methods which neglected the effect of harvesting on the dynamics of the major carbon pools in forest stands, such as logging residues and soil carbon<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. He defined a no residue harvest baseline scenario and determined the GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors of other scenarios by comparing them to this baseline. The derived GWP<sub>bio</sub> in a 100-year time horizon was 1.54 for no residue harvested and 1.25 for 25% of residues harvested. In another study, Holtsmark included the albedo effect by collecting residues, which slightly reduced GWP<sub>bio</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>.</p><p>These earlier studies provided fundamental results to bring a fair comparison of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions from bioenergy and fossil fuel. However, two considerations need to be clarified for a more accurate accounting: 1) the residue, if not collected, will decompose slowly and emit CO<sub>2</sub> into the atmosphere over the following years, and 2) the harvest of biomass or timber will result in further emissions from dead organic matter. Thus, a method to estimate GWP<sub>bio</sub> accurately should address these considerations. In our study, we analyzed the GWP<sub>bio</sub> by applying an accounting model considering long-lived wood products and the decomposition of wood residues. The GWP<sub>bio</sub> factor also applied to five LCA studies of bioproducts to estimate the potential of biomass utilization in reducing carbon emissions.</p><sec disp-level="1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Forest Stand Modeling</title><p>A forest stand storing 80 tC/ha live biomass was harvested at the start (t&#x02009;=&#x02009;0). The biomass accumulation after harvesting was estimated by a Chapman-Richards function: <inline-formula id="d32e384"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e385" xlink:href="srep39857-m1.jpg"/></inline-formula>, where <italic>B(a)</italic> is the mass of biomass measured in tC/ha (tC: metric ton carbon equivalent) and <italic>a</italic> the stand age; the <italic>b</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> are empirical parameters assumed to be known. The harvest activity resets all the living biomass to zero. This function provides a reasonable growth of the stand as a function of its age. Three sets of parameter configurations were used to allow the stand to grow back to its previous carbon level after harvesting in 30, 50 and 100 years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>The average merchantable timber is assumed to be a proportion of live biomass. We are using the proportion <italic>&#x003b8;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.48 proposed by L&#x000f8;ken <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. The merchantable timber is thus calculated as: <italic>T(a</italic>)&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>&#x003b8;B(a</italic>), where <italic>T(a)</italic> is the merchantable timber and <italic>B(a)</italic> is live biomass. The unit of <italic>T(a)</italic> and <italic>B(a)</italic> is metric ton in carbon equivalent (tC). In this study, we assumed a proportion <italic>&#x003c9;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.25 of residues is collected for bioenergy. The biomass not harvested is considered to be dead organic matter (DOM). The decomposition process is simulated by Yasso07 with average amounts of compartments in the residue (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S1</xref> in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">supporting information</xref>). Yasso07 is a widely-used model for simulation of biomass decomposition<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. The decomposition rate is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> in the Atmosphere</title><p>Once fossil fuel derived CO<sub>2</sub> is emitted to the atmosphere, the decay rate is not following a simple trajectory. The fraction of the initial pulse of CO<sub>2</sub> at time <italic>t</italic> is labeled as <italic>y(t)</italic> and calculated as follows:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq2"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e468" xlink:href="srep39857-m2.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> are estimated parameters. This model is based on the Bern2.5CC carbon cycle model using a CO<sub>2</sub> concentration of 378&#x02009;ppm in the atmosphere<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. The parameters are average values of a set of climate models and set as <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.217, <italic>y</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.224, <italic>y</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.282, <italic>y</italic><sub>3</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.276, <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;394.4, <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>2</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;36.54, <italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>3</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.304<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq2">Equation (1)</xref> takes into account the CO<sub>2</sub> uptake from the oceans and the terrestrial biosphere. Because <italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0, there is always a portion of CO<sub>2</sub> remaining in the atmosphere at any time.</p><p>When residue is collected for bioenergy, the initial pulse of CO<sub>2</sub> is <italic>E(&#x003c9;</italic>)&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c9;(B(a</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub><italic>)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;T(a</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub>)), where <italic>a</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub> is the stand age at harvest. After harvesting, stand age <italic>a</italic> equals <italic>t</italic>. Let <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub><italic>(t)</italic> as CO<sub>2</sub> remains in the atmosphere after the pulse of <italic>E(&#x003c9;)</italic> at time <italic>t</italic>, and <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub><italic>(t)</italic> as CO<sub>2</sub> emission from decomposition at time <italic>t</italic> if the residue is not collected. Hence, we have the following equations:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq3"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e608" xlink:href="srep39857-m3.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p><disp-formula id="eq4"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e611" xlink:href="srep39857-m4.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p><disp-formula id="eq5"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e614" xlink:href="srep39857-m5.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>) are mass allocation coefficients for the residue if the residue is used for bioenergy or is not removed respectively. <italic>B</italic>&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) is the increment of live biomass after harvesting. Because the stand is harvested for timber and these timber products usually do not emit CO<sub>2</sub> to the atmosphere immediately, we consider two scenarios. In the first case, the timber products have a pulse of CO<sub>2</sub> right after harvesting (<italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%); in the other case the timber products do not emit any CO<sub>2</sub> before the end of the rotation (<italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100%). <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub> is percentage of long-lived woody products in the total merchantable timber. The detailed calculation of the mass allocation coefficients are presented in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">supporting information</xref>. <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub>(<italic>t)B</italic>&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub>(<italic>t</italic>)&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c3;</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub>(<italic>t)B</italic>&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) will be set to zero once these value are lower than zero because CO<sub>2</sub> absorbed by biomass regrowth can fully compensate for the CO<sub>2</sub> remaining in the atmosphere. If the residues are not collected, they decompose and emit CO<sub>2</sub> into the atmosphere. Thus, the emission from decomposition is subtracted and the CO<sub>2</sub>remaining in the atmosphere at time <italic>t</italic> is as follows:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq6"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e735" xlink:href="srep39857-m6.jpg"/></disp-formula></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Global Warming Potential</title><p>The Global Warming Potential is used in this study as a standard estimation to compare the climate change impact of GHG emissions. The GWP is introduced as a relative measure by comparing the amount of heat that a greenhouse gas traps in the atmosphere to the amount of heat trapped by a similar mass of CO<sub>2</sub>. The GWP relies heavily on radiative forcing where the radiative forcing of CO<sub>2</sub> (<inline-formula id="d32e747"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e748" xlink:href="srep39857-m7.jpg"/></inline-formula>) is 1.37&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>&#x02009;W m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x02009;ppb<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> by Myhre <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>. The absolute global warming potential (AGWP) of a CO<sub>2</sub> pulse of <italic>E(&#x003c9;</italic>) is calculated as follows:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq8"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e773" xlink:href="srep39857-m8.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>where <italic>T</italic> is the time horizon for integration in the GWP. The IPCC introduced three time horizons for this purpose, i.e., 20, 100 and 500 years. In this study, we considered <italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100 as the time horizon which is generally used to estimate the overall GHG emissions in most LCA studies.</p><p>Similarly, the AGWP<sub>bio</sub> is calculated based on the remaining fraction of the initial pulse of CO<sub>2</sub> by subtracting the decomposition of DOM. The AGWP<sub>bio</sub> is:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq9"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e795" xlink:href="srep39857-m9.jpg"/></disp-formula></p><p>and the GWP<sub>bio</sub> is then defined as:</p><p><disp-formula id="eq10"><inline-graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e803" xlink:href="srep39857-m10.jpg"/></disp-formula></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>LCA Case Studies</title><p>In order to analyze the effect of this adjusted GWP<sub>bio</sub> factor, five biomass to bioproducts pathways were tested: biomass to ethanol (BTE), biomass to liquid fuel via fast pyrolysis (BLFP), coal and biomass to liquids (CBTL), biomass to bio-power and biomass to pellet fuel. The cradle-to-grave assessments included residue collection, transportation, storage, preprocessing, bioproduct conversion, distribution, final usage and waste disposal. These studies focused on GHG emissions derived from fossil fuels and biomass combustion. The functional unit (FU) of the system was 1,000&#x02009;MJ of energy equivalent bioproduct produced. The GHG emissions of petroleum-derived diesel with 98.8&#x02009;kg CO<sub>2</sub> eq/FU were used as a baseline to determine the advantage of biomass on climate change impact<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. The impact of GHGs was calculated using 100-year global warming potentials<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. All the GHG emissions were calculated in CO<sub>2</sub> equivalent (kgCO<sub>2</sub> eq). The system boundaries are defined in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Information</xref> and the detailed life cycle inventory data are also available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Information</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. Traditional LCA quantifies the emissions related to the production of bioproduct and the harvest of biomass. Several researchers suggest that emissions related to land use change and forest carbon change should be included<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Although the forest stand in this study is allowed to regrow and the land use does not change, forest carbon change induced by biomass collection was accounted for in the LCA studies. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">supporting information</xref> for details regarding the method of calculating forest carbon change.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors</title><p>As explained in the methods section, we examined two scenarios: 1) <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0% where the timber products emit CO<sub>2</sub> at the same time as biomass combustion, and 2) <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1000% indicated all timber products do not emit CO<sub>2</sub> before the end of the rotation. Compared to fossil fuel derived CO<sub>2</sub> which decays with the interaction of ocean-atmosphere systems, these scenarios allow an increasing decay rate of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere if the harvested stand is re-established and allowed to regrow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>, <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub><italic>(t), E</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub><italic>(t)</italic> and <italic>y(t)E(w)</italic> are the amount of CO<sub>2</sub>remaining in the atmosphere from biomass combustion, decomposition and fossil fuel, respectively. The curve representing <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub><italic>(t)-E</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub><italic>(t)</italic> is not a decay curve but the curve that we used to calculate GWP<sub>bio</sub>. Higher values of &#x003c3; (representing a longer lifespan of timber products) allow higher decay rate of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1b,d,f</xref>). Higher biomass growth rate could also effectively increase the decay rate of biomass derived CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>). It took 21, 32 and 49 years, assuming <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%, to eliminate all the biomass derived CO<sub>2</sub> when the rotation length was 30, 50 and 100 years. If <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100%, the corresponding periods were 14, 20 and 30 years.</p><p>The GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors in this study were significantly lower than 1 and related to the rotation length and the mass allocation coefficient (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). All our assumptions led to lower GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors when compared to earlier studies, especially when wood products have a long lifespan (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2">Table 2</xref>). Sensitivity analyses were conducted on rotation length and &#x003b7;<sub>1</sub>. The GWP<sub>bio</sub> varied between 0.13 and 0.32 as the rotation length changed from 30 years to 100 years (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S3</xref>). The GWP<sub>bio</sub> was linearly related to &#x003b7;<sub>1</sub> as it changed from 0% to 100%.</p><p>The model allowed the modification that the CO<sub>2</sub> absorbed in previous years was excluded from the atmosphere over the following years. The model also subtracted the emission from the decomposition of residues if they were not harvested. Decomposition was considered to be slow but could have a positive global warming impact in a young stand where the biomass accumulation is slow (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Table S3</xref>). These modifications allowed a logical explanation of the benefits from regrowth of a forest stand.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>GHG emissions of Case Studies</title><p>Without considering biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission, all five bioproducts had lower GHG emissions in comparison with petroleum-derived diesel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>). The production of pellet fuel had the lowest GHG emissions, at only 4.8% of petroleum-derived diesel. The production of ethanol and bio-power also produced low GHG emissions. Liquid fuels produced by fast pyrolysis had higher GHG emissions compared to the production of ethanol, bio-power and pellet fuel. The highest emissions were estimated from CBTL, amounting to 90% of the emissions from petroleum-derived diesel.</p><p>When considering the biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission in LCA, we found that most of the biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission was produced in &#x0201c;conversion&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;final usage&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t3">Table 3</xref>). All the energy usage in &#x0201c;feedstock collection&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;transportation&#x0201d; and bioproduct &#x0201c;distribution&#x0201d; was assumed to be provided from fossil energy. In the production of bio-power in particular, 99% of the total biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> was accounted for by emission in the &#x0201c;conversion&#x0201d; process. In the production of bio-power, all biomass was combusted at the facility site and no further emissions were assumed in the end usage.</p><p>The GHG emissions from ethanol and bio-power were very low compared to other bioproducts if the GWP<sub>bio</sub> factor was zero, but both appeared to have high GHG emissions when the rotation length was 100 years and <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%. When forest carbon change was accounted for in the LCA study, both had higher GHG emissions than petroleum-derived diesel. The GHG emissions of CBTL did not exceed those of petroleum-derived diesel in all cases due to the low percentage of biomass required to produce liquid fuels.</p><p>Generally, shorter rotation lengths and higher mass allocations benefit the environment more in terms of GHG emissions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b,c,d</xref>). To produce the same bioproduct, the GHG emissions were the lowest when the rotation length was 30 years. It was 1.4&#x02013;41.4% and 2.5&#x02013;39.2% less than the GHG emissions when the rotation length was 50 years and 100 years, respectively. To produce the same bioproduct, the GHG emissions when <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0% were 1&#x02013;25% higher than the GHG emissions in the <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100% scenario in all cases.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors</title><p>Our model assumed that the primary objective of harvesting is for timber products which usually have a longer lifespan than biomass. It was also assumed that the dynamics of soil carbon would not be affected by a small percentage (&#x02264;25%) of residue removal. The portion of biomass regrowth accounted for CO<sub>2</sub> absorption depended on the percentage of CO<sub>2</sub> remaining in the atmosphere from biomass combustion. We examined two mass allocation scenarios. If the wood products emitted CO<sub>2</sub> before the end of the rotation, the mass allocation coefficient would fall between these two scenarios. A long lifespan of timber products allows a high mass allocation coefficient, and short rotations imply rapid regrowth of a forest stand. Thus, the decay rate of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> increases with decreasing rotations and increasing lifespan of timber products. The forest carbon change due to harvesting was attributed to timber and biomass collection and allocated based on their mass.</p><p>The GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors in all scenarios are significantly lower than 1. This indicates the advantage of biomass when compared to fossil fuels. An even lower GWP<sub>bio</sub> factor would be possible if growth would be more vigorous at a younger age of the forest stand. The GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors correlates with rotation length, but this relationship should not be over exploited. It merely implies that higher growth rates may accelerate the decay of CO<sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere. In reality, the rotation length of a forest stand is relatively long. For fast growing tree species such as eucalypts, the rotation length is at least 15&#x02013;18 years<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>. The pulse of CO<sub>2</sub> from biomass combustion can be neglected in the case of perennial grasses which rotation length is 1 or 2 years<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>.</p><p>The high GWP<sub>bio</sub> factor in Holtsmark&#x02019;s results could be reasonable if, as assumed in his study, all the trunks and harvested residues were used for biomass combustion. This suggests that all the changes of major carbon pool in the stand should be accounted for by biomass combustion. Nonetheless, in most cases stands are harvested for timber. In Cherubini <italic>et al</italic>.&#x02019;s study, the forest model was modified to allow more vigorous growth in younger stands leading to slightly lower GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. Recent estimates of GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors may be too optimistic because no negative effects on the growth of biomass were included, like natural disturbances and climate change. Natural disturbance, like wild fire, drought, insect and pathogen outbreaks, will reduce biomass growth and even induce more emission to the atmosphere<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. These negative effects will increase the possibility of high GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors, but relevant scenarios may be more realistic for research and policy decisions. The impact of climate change on the growth of biomass is complex. Both negative effects<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> and positive effects<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref> were found in earlier investigations. Moreover, harvest level may also be increased for biomass because of high energy demands in the future, which in turn will lead to a higher GWP<sub>bio</sub> factor.</p><p>The GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors were not calculated for longer time horizon (&#x0003e;100 years), but previous studies have shown that these values may be even lower<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. Thus, biomass will be a good substitute of fossil fuels in the long run<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. Growth of biomass can even bring negative GWP if longer time horizons are considered, because biomass will continue to grow and absorb CO<sub>2</sub>. But in this study, the CO<sub>2</sub> remaining in the atmosphere was set to zero once the increment of biomass growth fully compensates the CO<sub>2</sub> emission. Part of the reason for that strategy is the assumption that the forest stand absorbs CO<sub>2</sub> if it is not harvested, which implies that the extra absorption of CO<sub>2</sub> is not due to residue collection. Additionally, the extra absorption of CO<sub>2</sub> is external to the studied system (LCA boundary). Considering these CO<sub>2</sub> reductions may involve some kind of double accounting.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>GHG emissions of Case Studies</title><p>Without considering biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission, the life cycle GHG emissions of the five cases closely resembled previous studies<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. The production of pellet fuel had the lowest GHG emissions because of the high energy conversion efficiency and low energy consumption. The reason that the production of ethanol and bio-power had low GHG emissions was the low energy demand in the production of ethanol and the self-sufficiency of power plants on energy. Liquid fuels produced by fast pyrolysis required high electricity input, which led to higher GHG emissions compared to the production of ethanol, bio-power and pellet fuel. CBTL emitted the highest GHG because the large proportion of GHG emissions from the combustion of coal could not be ignored even in conventional LCA studies.</p><p>Although the CO<sub>2</sub> emission from burning biomass is compensated by the growth of biomass, the CO<sub>2</sub> emission will remain in the atmosphere for a certain time. Thus, it is necessary to consider the GWP of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> when conducting LCA. Otherwise, the total GHG emissions will be systematically underestimated. By calculating biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> in the LCA studies, we found CBTL had a small amount of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission compared to the other four bioproducts. This is because a small portion of biomass (8%) was needed to produce 1,000 MJ of energy equivalent liquid fuels. Given that biomass was the only feedstock for the other four bioproducts, their biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission were closely related to their energy conversion efficiencies which were 25.6% for BTE<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>, 73.6% for BLFP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref> and 24% for bio-power<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>. Usually no waste was assumed in the production of wood pellets<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>. By increasing the energy conversion efficiency, biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission could be effectively reduced.</p><p>When the biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission was multiplied by a nonzero GWP<sub>bio</sub> factor, higher GHG emissions were expected in the LCA case studies. This effect was more pronounced when the biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission was high in the production of a bioproduct, such as ethanol and bio-power. The consideration of forest carbon change added more emissions to the total GHG emissions<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>. When a cradle to grave LCA was modeled, the LCI should quantify all the emissions associated with the activities and their effects to produce the product. By adding biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission and forest carbon change, an unbiased comparison could be made between biofuel and fossil fuel, although a significant increase of GHG emissions from biofuel should be expected. However, in this study, the forest carbon change was analyzed at forest stand scale because the timber harvest and residue collection are all occurred in stand scale. In addition, the focus on stand scale fits the objective of this study as well. Here, the study is an attributional LCA model which will not consider effects from outside of the system boundary. Once the study is expanded to landscape level, the forest carbon change could be different.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Policy Implications</title><p>Renewable fuel standard (RSF2) indicates that forest residue makes up less than 1% of the total feedstock under current scenario<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>. Most of the biofuels are produced from corn, soybean, agricultural residue, and grasses. These feedstocks have short rotation period and their GWP of biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> can be ignored<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. However, as the renewable fuel volume increases year by year, more forest residue need to be collected for biofuels. To be qualified as renewable energy for cellulosic fuels, the life cycle GHG emissions should be 60% less than the life cycle GHG emissions of the 2005 baseline average gasoline or diesel fuel (92&#x02009;kg/1,000 MJ)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref>. Thus, the direct influence of GWP<sub>bio</sub> is that some cellulosic fuel or biopower turn to be non-renewable energy, such as BTE, BLFP and biopower. The other influence is that more short rotation biomass will be used in the future scenarios. Therefore, the GWP<sub>bio</sub> provides a solid scientific reference to policy makers when making decisions for the utilization of forest residues. However, it is not a simple work to decide the best pathway for forest residue and bioproducts. Many factor should be considered, such as residue availability, cost, market demand, convenience for distribution and usage, GHG emissions and existing facilities. If only GHG emissions are emphasized, pellet fuel is the best choice because it has low emissions in all scenarios.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Additional Information</title><p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Liu, W. <italic>et al</italic>. Analysis of the Global Warming Potential of Biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> Emission in Life Cycle Assessments. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>
<bold>7</bold>, 39857; doi: 10.1038/srep39857 (2017).</p><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d32e32" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep39857-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e35" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplemental Information</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep39857-s2.doc"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank NREL (National Renewable Energy Laboratory) for providing the online database US LCI for public usage. We also thank Dr. Bjart Holtsmark of Statistics Norway for sharing background information on his modeling approach. This research is supported by the Special Research Program for Public-welfare Forestry (201204309) and Research Program of Department of Forestry of Jilin Province (2014&#x02013;006).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ragauskas</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>The Path Forward for Biofuels and Biomaterials</article-title>. <source>Sci</source>. <volume>311</volume><bold>(5760)</bold>, <fpage>484</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zeman</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<source>Carbon neutral hydrocarbons</source>. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences, <volume>366</volume>(<bold>1882)</bold>, <fpage>3901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3918</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><italic>Estimation of greenhouse gas emissions and sinks</italic>; Final report from the OECD experts meeting; Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development: Pairs, France (1991).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Gytarsky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <italic>IPCC Guidelines for national greenhouse gas inventories</italic>, Prepared by the National Greenhouse Gas Inventories Program. Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change: Geneva, Switzerland, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipcc-nggip.iges.or.jp/public/2006gl">http://www.ipcc-nggip.iges.or.jp/public/2006gl</ext-link> (2006) (Date of access: 10/05/2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Frischknecht</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <italic>Implementation of Life Cycle Impact Assessment Methods: Data v2.0. ecoinvent report No. 3</italic>; Swiss center for Life Cycle Inventories: Zurich, Switzerland (2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<italic>IPCC Third Assessment Report. The Scientific Basis. Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</italic>; Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change: Geneva, Switzerland, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/ipccreports/tar/wg1">https://www.ipcc.ch/ipccreports/tar/wg1</ext-link> (2001) (Date of access:01/05/2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Pachauri</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Reisinger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<italic>IPCC Fourth Assessment Report. The Physical Science Basis. Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC)</italic>.Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change: Geneva, Switzerland, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/publications_ipcc_fourth_assessment_report_wg1_report_the_physical_science_basis.htm">https://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/publications_ipcc_fourth_assessment_report_wg1_report_the_physical_science_basis.htm</ext-link> (2007) (Date of access: 02/05/2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Str&#x000f8;mman</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Life cycle assessment of bioenergy systems: State of the art and future challenges</article-title>. <source>Bioresource Technol.</source>
<volume>102</volume><bold>(2)</bold>, <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>451</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shonnard</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>A Review of Environmental Life Cycle Assessments of Liquid Transportation Biofuels in the Pan American Region</article-title>. <source>Environ. Manage.</source>
<volume>56</volume><bold>(6)</bold>, <fpage>1356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1376</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26041501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berntsen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Str&#x000f8;mman</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hertwich</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>CO<sub>2</sub> emissions from biomass combustion for bioenergy: atmospheric decay and contribution to global warming</article-title>. <source>GCB Bioenergy</source>. <volume>3</volume><bold>(5)</bold>, <fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Goodbye to carbon neutral: Getting biomass footprints right. Environ</article-title>. <source>Impact Asses</source>. <volume>29</volume><bold>(3)</bold>, <fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>168</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Searchinger</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Fixing a Critical Climate Accounting Error</article-title>. <source>Sci</source>. <volume>326</volume><bold>(5952)</bold>, <fpage>527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>528</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pingoud</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ekholm</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Global warming potential factors and warming payback time as climate indicators of forest biomass use</article-title>. <source>itig. Adapt. Strategies Glob. Chang</source>. <volume>17</volume><bold>(4)</bold>, <fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>386</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Stromman</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Climate impacts of bioenergy: Inclusion of carbon cycle and albedo dynamics in life cycle impact assessment</article-title>. <source>Environ. Impact Asses</source>. <volume>37</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guest</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cherubini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Stromman</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The role of forest residues in the accounting for the global warming potential of bioenergy</article-title>. <source>GCB Bioenergy</source>. <volume>5</volume><bold>(4)</bold>, <fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>466</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holtsmark</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantifying the global warming potential of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions from wood fuels</article-title>. <source>GCB Bioenergy</source>. <volume>7</volume><bold>(2)</bold>, <fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>206</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holtsmark</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A comparison of the global warming effects of wood fuels and fossil fuels taking albedo into account</article-title>. <source>GCB Bioenergy</source>. <volume>7</volume><bold>(5)</bold>, <fpage>984</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>997</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Asante</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Adamowicz</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Carbon sequestration and the optimal forest harvest decision: A dynamic programming approach considering biomass and dead organic matter</article-title>. <source>Journal of Forest Economics</source>
<volume>17</volume><bold>(1)</bold>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>L&#x000f8;ken</surname><given-names>&#x000d8;.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eriksen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Astrup</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<italic>The total biomass of trees in Norway</italic>. Norwegian Institute for Forest and Landscape: &#x000c5;s, Norway (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuomi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laiho</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Repo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Liski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Wood decomposition model for boreal forests</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Model.</source>
<volume>222</volume>, <fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>718</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Joos</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Carbon dioxide and climate implse response functions for the computation of greenhouse gas metrics: a multi-model analysis</article-title>. <source>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>2793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2825</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Myhre</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Anthropogenic and natural radiative forcing</article-title>. In: <source>Climate change 2013: The physical science basis. Contribution of working group I to the fifth assessment report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source>. <name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>T. F.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plattner</surname><given-names>G.-K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tignor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boschung</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nauels</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>Cambridge University Press, <source>Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA</source> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Keesom</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Unnasch</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moretta</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Consultancy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<italic>Life cycle assessment comparison of North American and imported crudes</italic>. Alberta Energy Research Institute: Alberta, Canada, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eipa.alberta.ca/media/39640/life%20cycle%20analysis%20jacobs%20final%20report.pdf">http://www.eipa.alberta.ca/media/39640/life%20cycle%20analysis%20jacobs%20final%20report.pdf</ext-link> (2009) (Date of access: 15/04/2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Economic and Environmental Analyses of Biomass Utilization for Bioenergy Products in the Northeastern United States</article-title>. <source>Diss. West Virginia University</source> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mckechnie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mabee</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Forest bioenergy or forest carbon? Assessing trade-offs in greenhouse gas mitigation with wood-based fuels</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>795</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21142063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koellner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>UNEP-SETAC guideline on global land use impact assessment on biodiversity and ecosystem services in LCA</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Life Cycle Assess.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1202</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gadow</surname><given-names>K. v.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<source>Modeling forest development</source>. Kluwer Academic Publishers, Dordrecht: <fpage>212</fpage> p (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Merino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balboa</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soalleiro</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Nutrient exports under different harvesting regimes in fast-growing forest plantations in southern Europe</article-title>. <source>Forest Ecol. Manag.</source>
<volume>207</volume><bold>(3)</bold>, <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>339</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhungana</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &#x00026;<name><surname>Clifton-Brown</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Costs of producing miscanthus and switchgrass for bioenergy in Illinois</article-title>. <source>Biomass Bioenerg.</source>
<volume>32</volume><bold>(6)</bold>, <fpage>482</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>V. H.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Climate change and forest disturbances</article-title>. <source>Bioscience.</source>
<volume>51</volume><bold>(9)</bold>, <fpage>723</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>734</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Westerling</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>H. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cayan</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Swetnam</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Warming and earlier spring increase western US forest wildfire activity</article-title>. <source>Sci</source>. <volume>313</volume><bold>(5789)</bold>, <fpage>940</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>943</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Colwell</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardelus</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Longino</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Global warming, elevational range shifts, and lowland biotic attrition in the wet tropics</article-title>. <source>Sci</source>. <volume>322</volume><bold>(5899)</bold>, <fpage>258</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boisvenue</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Running</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Impacts of climate change on natural forest productivity - evidence since the middle of the 20th century</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume><bold>(5)</bold>, <fpage>862</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>882</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fantozzi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Buratti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Life cycle assessment of biomass chains: Wood pellet from short rotation coppice using data measured on a real plant</article-title>. <source>Biomass Bioenergy</source>. <volume>34</volume><bold>(12)</bold>, <fpage>1796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1804</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Life cycle environmental impacts of selected US ethanol production and use pathways in 2022</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>44</volume><bold>(13)</bold>, <fpage>5289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5297</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20527764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Life cycle assessment of gasoline and diesel produced via fast pyrolysis and hydroprocessing</article-title>. <source>Biomass Bioenergy</source>. <volume>45</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Life cycle assessment of energy and GHG emissions during ethanol production from grass straws using various pretreatment processes</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Life Cycle Assess.</source>
<volume>17</volume><bold>(4)</bold>, <fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>401</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Snowden-Swan</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Male</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<italic>Summary of Fast Pyrolysis and Upgrading GHG Analyses</italic>. Richland, WA, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnnl.gov/main/publications/external/technical_reports/PNNL-22175.pdf">http://www.pnnl.gov/main/publications/external/technical_reports/PNNL-22175.pdf</ext-link> (2012) (Date of access: 16/04/2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Tarka</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. Affordable, low-carbon diesel fuel from domestic coal and biomass. In Proc. 25th Annual Pittsburgh Coal Conf., Pittsburgh, PA. (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Spath</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<italic>Life cycle assessment of coal-fired power production</italic>. National Renewable Energy Lab.: Golden, CO. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nrel.gov/docs/fy99osti/25119.pdf">http://www.nrel.gov/docs/fy99osti/25119.pdf</ext-link> (<year>1999</year>) (Date of access: 15/04/2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yancey</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tumuluru</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name> &#x00026; <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>C. T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Drying, Grinding and Pelletization Studies on Raw and Formulated Biomass Feedstock&#x02019;s for Bioenergy Applications</article-title>. <source>J. Biobased Mate. Bioenergy</source>. <volume>7</volume><bold>(5)</bold>, <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>558</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Environmental Protection Agency. Regulation of Fuels and Fuel Additives: Changes to Renewable Fuel Standard Program; Final Rule, Washington D.C., United States, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2010-03-26/pdf/2010-3851.pdf">https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2010-03-26/pdf/2010-3851.pdf</ext-link> (2010) (Date of access: 10/08/2016).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> In this study, Weiguo Liu, Zhonghui Zhang and Xinfeng Xie developed the conception of the work. Zhen Yu, Klaus von Gadow, Junming Xu, Shanshan Zhao and Yuchun Yang helped to do literature review and provided parameter settings for the models. Data analysis and interpretation was done by group discussions with all authors involved. Weiguo Liu wrote the main manuscript text. All authors reviewed the manuscript and provided critical revision.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Carbon decay patterns for different scenarios.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Rotation length 30-year, <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%; (<bold>b</bold>) Rotation length 30-year, <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100%; (<bold>c</bold>) Rotation length 50-year, <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%; (<bold>d</bold>) Rotation length 50-year, <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100%; (<bold>e</bold>) Rotation length 100-year, <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%; (<bold>f</bold>) Rotation length 30-year, <italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100%.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep39857-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>GHG emissions of biomass to bioproduct pathways under different scenarios.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) no biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission; (<bold>b</bold>) RL&#x02009;=&#x02009;30; (<bold>c</bold>) RL&#x02009;=&#x02009;50 and (d) RL&#x02009;=&#x02009;100. Note: Fossil &#x02013; GHG emissions from fossil fuel; Biogenic &#x02013; accountable biogenic GHG emissions from biomass; FC &#x02013; accountable forest carbon change; RL &#x02013; Rotation length.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep39857-f2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Parameter settings for the Chapman-Richards function.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Set #</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Forest Type</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Rotation</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>b</italic><sub>1</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>b</italic><sub>2</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>b</italic><sub>3</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Tropical rain forest</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">30 years</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">428.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0253</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.64</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Holtsmark<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Temperate deciduous forest</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">50 years</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">198.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0253</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.64</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Htsmark<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Boreal forest</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">100 years</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">103.067</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.0245</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.6925</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Asante <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>GWP<sub>bio</sub> factors for different scenarios with a 100-year time horizon.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Rotation: # of years</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">GWP<sub>bio</sub><hr/></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Holtsmark<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Cherubini <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Guest <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>&#x003b7;</italic>l&#x02009;=&#x02009;0%</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50"><italic>&#x003b7;</italic><sub><italic>l</italic></sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100%.</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.13</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.18</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.24</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.16</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.30</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.21</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">1.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.60</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.58</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Biogenic CO<sub>2</sub> emission from all processes.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Technology</th><th colspan="6" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Percentage of each process<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Total (kg CO<sub>2</sub> eq)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Feedstock Collection</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Transportation, Storage and Preprocessing</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Thermochemical conversion</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Distribution</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Final Usage</th><th align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">Waste Disposal</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BTE</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">65.72</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">34.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.02</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">289</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">BLFP</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">47.42</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">52.55</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">144.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">CBTL</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.27</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">19.97</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">80.17</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">19.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Power</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.03</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">99.84</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.11</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.02</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">235.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" charoff="50">Pellet</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.00</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.19</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">2.05</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">97.74</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" charoff="50">57.62</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>