<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">Worldwide, tissue transplantation employs various technologies that allowed a great improvement in the last 50 years, such as the application of cryopreservation to ensure the continuous supply of grafts (Polge et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">1949</xref>; Pegg 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">1976</xref>; Bozic and Marjoua 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2012</xref>), which was later complemented by the quality management systems that induced a positive impact on developed countries healthcare systems (Bozic and Marjoua 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2012</xref>). In the case of developing countries that had initiated tissue transplant developmental measures (e.g. participation through the IAEA), regulatory improvements along with quality management systems, comparable to pharmaceutical regulations, must be established to lead to a funding of specialized infrastructure, industrial processes and human resources with high standard training (e.g. the use of cleanrooms for the control of air particles requires the support of quality systems, validation and risk management by trained and continuous training of personnel) (Warwick et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2009</xref>). To facilitate this development, the association with institutions that are experts in the field, such as the European Association of Tissue and Cell Banks (EATCB) must be made. Developing countries are in a position where lessons learned from such abovementioned associations can be drawn for the introduction of novel processes and new clinical applications. This has been estimated in the EU to be clinically-driven with the involvement and cooperation of three main groups: tissue establishments, clinicians and risk analysis made by local health authorities, creating a constant interaction between all parties involved (European Directorate for the Quality of Medicines &amp; Healthcare (EDQM) 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>). Developing countries can benefit from lessons learned from these associations from the EU, as they can facilitate the supply of the production-training ecosystem and participate in several events, where the state-of-the-art is exposed to an efficient life-cycle management, as they have experienced several years in process validation, risk prevention and continuous improvement systems. In particular, the training programs of “The International Council for Harmonization of Technical Requirements for Pharmaceuticals for Human Use (ICH)”
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4">4</xref> in relation to quality management concepts are required.
</p>
