<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The DNA from each sample was purified using a fecal DNA MiniPrep kit (D6010, Zymo Research, Irvine, CA, USA) according to manufacturer’s instructions. The obtained DNA then was purified using a DNA Clean &amp; Concentrator-25 kit (Zymo Research, Irvine, CA, USA) to produce about 50 ng/µL of DNA. The same amount of DNA from each group of animals was pooled into one sample per group representing one sample per intestine i.e., three samples were obtained from each group representing samples from ileum, caecum and colon. In total, six samples were obtained representing three intestines from both animal groups. Partial 16S rRNA genes (V3-V4) were PCR amplified followed by barcoding and library preparation of the resulting PCR products in a secondary PCR. Metagenomic libraries were prepared, sequenced, quality controlled, and assembled in an independent service laboratory (BaseClear, The Netherlands). Short paired sequence reads were generated using the Illumina MiSeq system (Illumina, IL, USA) and converted into FASTQ files using the BCL2FASTQ pipeline software, version 1.8.3 (Illumina, IL, USA). Subsequently, reads containing PhiX control signal were removed using an in-house filtering protocol. In addition, reads containing (partial) adapters were clipped (up to a minimum read length of 50 bp). The second quality assessment was based on the remaining reads using the FASTQC quality control tool version 0.11.5. Subsequently, the Illumina paired reads were merged into single reads (so-called “pseudoreads”) through sequence overlap. Chimeric pseudoreads were removed, and the remaining reads were aligned to a combination of the GreenGenes and RDP 16S gene databases. Based on the alignment scores of the pseudoreads, the taxonomic classes were assigned by associating each pseudoread to the best matching operational taxonomic unit (OTU). The results of the taxonomic classification were presented on the interactive online platform. The number of probiotic bacteria was recorded and the relative number of probiotics from all bacteria detected was counted in all intestines tested as an average number per group. The bacterial genera considered as probiotic bacteria was based on literature analysis [
 <xref rid="B49-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-animals-10-01734" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and included 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic>, 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus</italic>, 
 <italic>Faecalibacterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, 
 <italic>Enterococcus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Escherichia</italic>. Moreover, all the bacterial genera detected in the amount of ≥2%, irrespective of the animal group, were checked as to whether they were not mentioned as probiotic bacteria in scientific manuscripts.
</p>
