<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Moreover, turmeric EO showed potent antiarthritic and joint protective effects on an animal model of rheumatoid arthritis [
 <xref rid="B23-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. As a result of treatment with crude or refined turmeric oil (i.p.), joint swelling was dramatically inhibited (90–100% inhibition) in female rats with streptococcal cell wall-induced arthritis [
 <xref rid="B182-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. Turmeric EO was reported to have antihepatotoxic [
 <xref rid="B23-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>], antiatherosclerotic [
 <xref rid="B96-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>], hypothermic, anxiolytic, sedative, anticonvulsant [
 <xref rid="B81-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>], and spasmolytic [
 <xref rid="B185-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">185</xref>] activities. Turmeric EO protected against accelerated atherosclerosis, inflammation, and macrophage foam-cell formation induced by arterial injury through modulating the genes involved in plaque stability, lipid homeostasis, and inflammation [
 <xref rid="B184-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">184</xref>]. Turmeric EO (200 mg/kg) exhibited antifatty liver and hepatoprotective activities in acute ethanol-induced fatty liver in rats through decreasing the activities of serum enzymes and levels of serum triglyceride, serum total cholesterol, and hepatic malondialdehyde, while restoring the level of reduced glutathione as well as the activities of glutathione-
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>-transferase and superoxide dismutase [
 <xref rid="B186-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>]. The oil was markedly antimutagenic against sodium azide in the Ames test [
 <xref rid="B178-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">178</xref>,
 <xref rid="B187-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>]. Turmeric oil showed remarkable sedative and anesthetic effects in mice [
 <xref rid="B81-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>] and fish [
 <xref rid="B96-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>] in different experimental protocols. Interestingly, 
 <italic class="italic">ar</italic>-turmerone isolated from turmeric EO is a potent antivenom against snakebites. It neutralized both the hemorrhagic activity present in 
 <italic class="italic">Bothrops jararaca</italic> venom, and the lethal effect of 
 <italic class="italic">Crotalus durissus</italic> venom in mice [
 <xref rid="B188-nutrients-10-01196" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">188</xref>].
</p>
