<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">Serial tube dilution technique mentioned by Reiner et al. [
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]; was followed using nutrient broth medium to determine the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) values of methanol extract of 
 <italic>C. digyna</italic> and antibiotics against the four pathogenic bacteria and three pathogenic fungi. The stock solution was prepared by dissolving 1.024 mg of antibiotics in 2 mL of methanol. Thus solution with a concentration of 512 (μg/mL) was obtained. The standard antibiotic amoxicillin trihydrate solution was made by the same procedure as the concentration was 512 (μg/mL). Thirteen autoclaved test tubes were taken, nine of which were labeled as 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and the remaining three were allocated as C
 <sub>m</sub> (medium), C
 <sub>s</sub> (medium + compound) and C
 <sub>i</sub> (Medium + inoculum). Each of 12 test tubes was supplemented with 1 mL of sterile nutrient broth medium or potato dextrose broth medium. In the 1st test tube, 1 mL of the sample solution was added and mixed well. 1 mL content from the 1st test tube was transferred to the 2nd test tube by the sterile pipette and mixed uniformly. Then 1 mL of this mixture was transferred to the 3rd test tube. This process of serial dilution was preceded until the 9th test tube. 1 drop (10 μL) of properly diluted inoculum was added to each of the 9 test tubes and mixed well. For the control test tube, C
 <sub>s</sub> 1 mL of the sample solution was added, mixed well and 1 mL of this mixed content was discarded. This was to verify the medium's clarity in the presence of a diluted solution of the compound. 10 μL of the inoculum was added to the control test tube, C
 <sub>i</sub> to monitor the growth of the organism in the medium used. The control test tube, C
 <sub>m</sub> containing medium only was used to verify the medium's sterility. The control test tubes were incubated for 18–24 h at 37.5 °C.
</p>
