<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7810738</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">79562</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-79562-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tryptophan-derived metabolites and BAK1 separately contribute to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> postinvasive immunity against <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kosaka</surname><given-names>Ayumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pastorczyk</surname><given-names>Marta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pi&#x0015b;lewska-Bednarek</surname><given-names>Mariola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nishiuchi</surname><given-names>Takumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>Erika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suemoto</surname><given-names>Haruka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>Atsushi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Frerigmann</surname><given-names>Henning</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaido</surname><given-names>Masanori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mise</surname><given-names>Kazuyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bednarek</surname><given-names>Pawe&#x00142;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Yoshitaka</given-names></name><address><email>takano.yoshitaka.2x@kyoto-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.258799.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0372 2033</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Plant Pathology, Graduate School of Agriculture, </institution><institution>Kyoto University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kyoto, 606-8502 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413454.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1958 0162</institution-id><institution>Institute of Bioorganic Chemistry, </institution><institution>Polish Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>Noskowskiego 12/14, 61-704 Poznan, Poland </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9707.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2308 3329</institution-id><institution>Advanced Science Research Center, </institution><institution>Kanazawa University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kanazawa, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411756.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Bioscience and Biotechnology, </institution><institution>Fukui Prefectural University, </institution></institution-wrap>Fukui, 910-1195 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419498.9</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0660 6765</institution-id><institution>Max Planck Institute for Plant Breeding Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Carl-von-Linne-Weg 10, 50829 Cologne, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1488</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Nonhost resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> against the hemibiotrophic fungus <italic>Colletotrichum tropicale</italic> requires PEN2-dependent preinvasive resistance and CYP71A12 and CYP71A13-dependent postinvasive resistance, which both rely on tryptophan (Trp) metabolism. We here revealed that CYP71A12, CYP71A13 and PAD3 are critical for <italic>Arabidopsis&#x02019;</italic> postinvasive basal resistance toward the necrotrophic <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic>. Consistent with this, gene expression and metabolite analyses suggested that the invasion by <italic>A. brassicicola</italic> triggered the CYP71A12-dependent production of indole-3-carboxylic acid derivatives and the PAD3 and CYP71A13-dependent production of camalexin. We next addressed the activation of the CYP71A12 and PAD3-dependent postinvasive resistance. We found that <italic>bak1</italic>-<italic>5</italic> mutation significantly reduced postinvasive resistance against <italic>A</italic>. <italic>brassicicola</italic>, indicating that pattern recognition contributes to activation of this second defense-layer. However, the <italic>bak1</italic>-<italic>5</italic> mutation had no detectable effects on the Trp-metabolism triggered by the fungal penetration. Together with this, further comparative gene expression analyses suggested that pathogen invasion in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> activates (1) CYP71A12 and PAD3-related antifungal metabolism that is not hampered by <italic>bak1</italic>-<italic>5</italic>, and (2) a <italic>bak1</italic>-<italic>5</italic> sensitive immune pathway that activates the expression of antimicrobial proteins.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Microbiology</kwd><kwd>Molecular biology</kwd><kwd>Plant sciences</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2021</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The resistance of an entire plant species against all isolates of particular pathogens is called nonhost resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. <italic>Colletotrichum tropicale</italic> (hereafter <italic>Ctro</italic>), formally called <italic>C</italic>. <italic>gleosporioides</italic>, is a hemibiotrophic fungal pathogen that causes anthracnose on its host mulberry; however, it is not able to enter the nonhost <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> because <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> blocks pathogen entry via activation of preinvasive resistance. Preinvasive resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against <italic>Ctro</italic> involves <italic>PENETRATION2</italic> (<italic>PEN2</italic>) and <italic>PEN3</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Nonhost preinvasive resistance toward <italic>Ctro</italic> also needs <italic>EDR1</italic> (<italic>ENHANCED DISEASE RESISTANCE 1</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Importantly, even the <italic>pen2 edr1</italic> mutant is still not fully susceptible to <italic>Ctro</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, because strong postinvasive resistance is newly activated once <italic>Ctro</italic> enters epidermal cells of the mutants defective in the preinvasive resistance. We reported previously that <italic>Arabidopsis cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> double mutant is fully susceptible to the nonadapted pathogen <italic>Ctro</italic>, i.e., the mutant is defective in both preinvasive and postinvasve resistance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. CYP79B2 and CYP79B3 are key enzymes for the biosynthesis of tryptophan (Trp)-derived antimicrobial metabolites. CYP79B2/CYP79B3 convert Trp into indole-3-acetaldoxime (IAOx)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, and this precursor is then converted into several compounds for antimicrobial immunity, such as PEN2 substrates indole-glucosinolates (IGs), PAD3 (PHYTOALEXIN-DEFICIENT3)-dependent camalexin, and 4-hydroxy-ICN (4-OH-ICN) whose biosynthesis requires CYP82C2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. We have shown that the <italic>pen2 pad3</italic> mutant is partially defective in postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ctro</italic>, indicating that the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> phytoalexin, camalexin, is a critical factor for this.</p><p id="Par4">In addition to serving as a precursor of IGs and camalexin, IAOx can be also converted to indole-3-carboxylic acid and its derivatives (ICAs). We have shown recently that CYP71A12 but not CYP71A13 has an important contribution to the accumulation of ICAs in leaves upon both <italic>Ctro</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>cucumerina</italic> inoculation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. On the other hand, loss of CYP71A13 reduced camalexin accumulation in leaves upon infection by multiple pathogens<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, whereas a single loss of CYP71A12 did not reduce camalexin accumulation upon <italic>Ctro</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>cucumerina</italic> infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. These findings suggest distinct roles of these two homologous P450 monooxygenases in the responses toward pathogen infection. Importantly, the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic> double mutant exhibits a partial reduction in postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ctro</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, which was similar to that of the <italic>pen2 pad3</italic> plants. This indicates that CYP71A12-dependent synthesis of ICAs as well as camalexin synthesis is critical for postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ctro,</italic> whereas CYP71A12 and PAD3 are dispensable for the preinvasive resistance: <italic>Ctro</italic> cannot invade the <italic>pad3</italic> single mutant or the <italic>cyp71A12</italic> single mutant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">It has been reported that in addition to the above mentioned pests, camalexin is critical for the immunity of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to additional filamentous pathogens including a necrotrophic fungus <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic> (hereafter called <italic>Ab</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. However, it remains unclear whether CYP71A12 and ICAs are involved in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> immunity to other fungi including <italic>Ab.</italic></p><p id="Par6">Immune responses in plants, including biosynthesis of specialized metabolites, can be triggered by pattern recognition-receptor (PRRs). BAK1 (BRASSINOSTEROID INSENSITIVE 1-ASSOCIATED RECEPTOR KINASE 1) is known to act as a coreceptor with multiple PRRs, including FLS2 and EFR, via ligand-induced heteromerization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. BAK1 was initially identified as a positive regulator of the brassinosteroid response (BR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Correspondingly, the <italic>bak1</italic> null mutants such as <italic>bak1-4</italic> mutant have a defect not only in FLS2 and EFR-dependent immune responses, but are also hyposensitive to BR. In contrast to the null alleles, the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> allele is impaired in pathogen-associated molecular pattern (PAMP)-triggered immunity, but not in BR signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Importantly, <italic>bak1-5</italic> is more severely impaired in defense responses than the null mutant <italic>bak1-4</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">Here, we investigated whether CYP71A12-dependent synthesis of ICAs might be involved in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> immunity, especially postinvasive resistance, to <italic>Ab</italic> that infects Brassicaceae plants. As a result, we found that the invasion by <italic>Ab</italic> triggers the CYP71A12-dependent accumulation of ICAs as well as camalexin. Furthermore, evaluation of lesion development and microscopic observation of the pathogen invasion suggested the involvement of CYP71A12, together with PAD3, in postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab</italic>.</p><p id="Par8">We also asked how <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> recognizes <italic>Ab</italic> invasion to activate the CYP71A12 and PAD3-dependent postinvasive resistance. To this end we investigated function of BAK1 in immunity and ICAs formation and found that the two <italic>bak1</italic> mutations, especially <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic>, reduce postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab</italic>, revealing the involvement of a PRR system in the recognition of <italic>Ab</italic> invasion for the activation of defense. Unexpectedly, we found that the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation has no negative impact on the invasion-triggered activation of biosynthesis of camalexin or ICAs derived from Trp.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>CYP71A12 contributes to the immunity of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against the necrotrophic pathogen <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic> independently of CYP71A13 and PAD3</title><p id="Par9"><italic>Ab</italic> is a necrotrophic fungal pathogen that infects several Brassicaceae spp., including cabbage and canola but is restricted within limited lesions when inoculated on leaves of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> accession Col-0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. To investigate the roles of CYP71A12 in the postinvasive immunity of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against <italic>Ab</italic>, we used the Ryo-1 strain of <italic>Ab</italic> for the inoculation assay (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). During our former study on postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ctro</italic> we investigated Trp metabolism-related mutants including <italic>cyp71A12</italic> in the <italic>pen2</italic> background, because <italic>Ctro</italic> was not able to invade these mutants in the absence of the <italic>pen2</italic> mutation (15). In this study, to focus on postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab,</italic> we used these <italic>pen2</italic> background mutants for the <italic>Ab</italic> inoculation assay to exclude a potential effect of PEN2 on preinvasive resistance against this pathogen. Our evaluation of lesion development at 4&#x000a0;days postinoculation (dpi) revealed that the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic> mutant showed enhanced susceptibility to <italic>Ab,</italic> as compared with the <italic>pen2</italic> plants, indicating contribution of CYP71A12 to the immunity towards <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We also found that lesion development in the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant was not significantly different from that in the wild-type (WT) Col-0 leaves (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), suggesting that opposite with the impact on several filamentous pathogens<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, PEN2 has likely no detectable contribution to the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> immunity against <italic>Ab</italic> at least in the Col-0 accession.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic> are involved in the immunity of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against the necrotrophic pathogen <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic> (<italic>Ab</italic>). (<bold>A</bold>) Lesion development caused by <italic>Ab</italic> on <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> mutant plants with defects in Trp metabolism pathways. Conidial suspensions (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were drop-inoculated onto mature leaves of 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants. The photograph was taken at 4&#x000a0;days postinoculation (dpi). (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of lesion development. Conidial suspensions of <italic>Ab</italic> were drop-inoculated onto tested plants. At&#x000a0;4 dpi, lesion areas were measured and the relative values to Col-0 (WT plants) were calculated. Means and standard deviations (SDs) were calculated from three independent experiments. The statistical significance of differences between means was determined by Tukey&#x02019;s honestly significant difference (HSD) test. Means not sharing the same letter are significantly different (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).&#x000a0;N.D., not determined.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par10">We also found that the <italic>pen2 pad3</italic> mutants have increased susceptibility to the <italic>Ab</italic> Ryo-1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), indicating the importance of PAD3-dependent camalexin synthesis, consistent with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Also, an additional mutation in <italic>CYP71A13</italic> further increased lesion development in <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Opposite with <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12/A13</italic>, <italic>cyp82C2</italic> mutation did not cause significant changes in <italic>Ab</italic> development suggesting that <italic>CYP82C2</italic> together with 4-OH-ICN do not contribute to the immunity toward this pathogen (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We were unable to perform proper quantitative analysis of lesion development in the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutant at 4 dpi because the lesions had already merged. However, quantitative analysis at 3 dpi revealed that the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutant was the most susceptible to <italic>Ab</italic> among all tested genotypes (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). As <italic>PEN2</italic> appeared to be unlikely essential for the immunity against <italic>Ab</italic>, we also investigated the effects of the mutations of <italic>PAD3</italic>, <italic>CYP71A12</italic>, <italic>CYP71A13</italic> and <italic>CYP82C2</italic> on the immunity to <italic>Ab</italic> in the WT background in addition to the <italic>pen2</italic> background by using <italic>pad3</italic>, <italic>cyp82C2</italic>, <italic>cyp71A12</italic>, <italic>cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutants. The obtained result was similar to the finding on the mutations in the <italic>pen2</italic> background (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Biosynthesis of ICAs and camalexin occurs during postinvasive resistance toward <italic>Ab</italic></title><p id="Par11">Pastorczyk, M. et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> reported that (1) the expression of <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>PAD3</italic> is strongly induced in the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant defective in preinvasive resistance, but not in WT, upon the inoculation of the non-adapted pathogen <italic>Ctro</italic> and (2) <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>PAD3</italic> are involved in postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ctro</italic>. To assess whether <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>PAD3</italic> are expressed during postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>, we investigated the expression pattern of these genes at several time points after <italic>Ab</italic> inoculation (at 4, 12, 24, and 48&#x000a0;h postinoculation, hpi). Although lesion development by <italic>Ab</italic> in <italic>pen2</italic> was comparable to that in WT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), we used the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant for the analysis to exclude a potential contribution of PEN2 to preinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab.</italic></p><p id="Par12">We found that the expression of <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>PAD3</italic> started to be induced at 12 hpi in <italic>pen2</italic>, and the corresponding expression levels were stronger elevated at later time points (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). By contrast, we did not detect any induction at 4 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). In parallel, we also investigated the temporal infection behavior of <italic>Ab</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. We found that conidia of <italic>Ab</italic> had already germinated at 4 hpi, however, we did not detect any host invasion at this time (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). The fungus started to invade the <italic>pen2</italic> plants at 12 hpi and the invasion ratio became elevated at later time points (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B,D). These findings indicate a link between <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>PAD3</italic> induction and the initiation of host invasion in the <italic>Ab</italic>-<italic>Arabidopsis</italic> interactions, strongly suggesting that the expressions of <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>PAD3</italic> are triggered by <italic>Ab</italic> invasion. Furthermore, we also revealed that simultaneous loss of both <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>CYP71A13</italic> produced no detectable effects on the preinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C,D). These findings suggest that <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>CYP71A13</italic> are involved in the postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>. We also found that the invasion ratio of <italic>Ab</italic> in <italic>pen2</italic> was not significantly different from that in WT (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C), in contrast to the case of <italic>Ctro</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The invasion of <italic>Ab</italic> activates the expression of <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic>. (<bold>A</bold>) Expression of <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic> following <italic>Ab</italic> inoculation. Conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were spray-inoculated onto 4&#x02013;5-week-old <italic>pen2</italic> plants and kept at 100% humidity. The samples were collected at 4, 12, 24, and 48 hpi. Each gene transcript was quantified by quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) using the gene-specific primers listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. Values were normalized to the expression level of <italic>UBC21</italic>. The means and SDs were calculated from three independent experiments. Statistical comparisons between mock and <italic>Ab</italic> treated samples were conducted using two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> tests (**<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). (<bold>B</bold>) Quantitative analysis of the <italic>Ab</italic> invasion ratio among <italic>pen2</italic> plants. Conidial suspensions (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were drop-inoculated onto <italic>pen2</italic> plants and kept at 100% humidity. The inoculated leaves were collected at 4, 12, 24, and 48 hpi, and then subjected to a trypan blue viability staining assay. The presence or absence of invasive hyphae from at least 50 germinating conidia were counted in each experiment. The means and SDs were calculated from three independent experiments. Statistical comparisons of the <italic>Ab</italic> invasion ratios at 12, 24, and 48 hpi against that at 4 hpi were conducted using two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> tests (**<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). (<bold>C</bold>) <italic>PEN2</italic>, <italic>CYP71A12</italic>, and <italic>CYP71A13</italic> are dispensable for preinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>. Aliquots of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of <italic>Ab</italic> conidial suspension were drop-inoculated onto leaves of 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants. At 12 hpi, the inoculated leaves were collected and stained with trypan blue, and then invasive hyphae were observed by light microscopy. At least 50 germinating conidia were counted in each experiment. The means and SDs were calculated from three independent experiments. Statistical analysis using two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> tests showed no significant differences among the genotypes. (<bold>D</bold>) Light microscopy observations. At 12 hpi, a part of the germinating conidia developed invasive hyphae (arrows) inside the inoculated plants. The top images are focused on conidium and the bottom images are focused on invasive hypha. <italic>c</italic> conidium, <italic>g</italic> germ tube. Bars&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">We then assessed whether our observations made at the gene expression level could be supported with metabolite profiles. We found that the pathogen-induced accumulation of two ICAs, glucoside of 6-hydroxy-indole-3-carboxylic acid (6OGlcICA) and glucose ester of indole-3-carboxylic acid (ICAGlc), was detected at 24 hpi, but not at 4 hpi with <italic>Ab</italic> in both WT and <italic>pen2</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A; Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), which matched strongly with the gene expression data (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). Similar results were also obtained during the analysis of camalexin accumulation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Therefore, we conclude that the synthesis of ICAs and camalexin is triggered by <italic>Ab</italic> invasion.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Invasion by <italic>Ab</italic> induced CYP71A12-dependent biosynthesis of 6-hydroxy-ICA and PAD3-dependent biosynthesis of camalexin. (<bold>A</bold>) The accumulation of 6-hydroxy-ICA (6OGlcICA) and camalexin in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants inoculated with <italic>Ab</italic>. Conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were spray-inoculated onto Col-0 (WT) and <italic>pen2</italic> plants. As a control, water was sprayed as a mock treatment. The means of metabolites (nmol/g fresh weight, FW) and SDs from four biological independent samples are shown in the graph. The statistical significance of differences between means was determined by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test. Means not sharing the same letter are significantly different (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>CYP71A12</italic> is required for the <italic>Ab</italic>-triggered accumulation of 6OGlcICA, whereas <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A13</italic> are required for the accumulation of camalexin. Conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were spray-inoculated onto tested mutant lines. The statistical significance of differences between means in each time point was determined by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test. Means not sharing the same letter are significantly different (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Reduced accumulation of ICAs correlates with the breakdown of the postinvasive resistance toward <italic>Ab</italic></title><p id="Par14">We have reported recently that the accumulation of ICAs triggered by inoculation with <italic>P</italic>. <italic>cucumerina</italic> is reduced in the <italic>cyp71A12</italic>, but not in the <italic>cyp71A13</italic> mutant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. By contrast, the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>cucumerina</italic>-triggered accumulation of camalexin was reduced in the <italic>cyp71A13</italic>, but not in the single <italic>cyp71A12</italic> mutant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Therefore, we assumed that the CYP71A12-dependent production of ICAs contributes to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> postinvasive immunity to <italic>Ab</italic> independently of CYP71A13-dependent camalexin production. As mentioned above, we also found that the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutant exhibited more severe defects in postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> than the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), although the reason was not clear. To get further insights on these aspects, we investigated the Trp-related metabolite profiles of the aforementioned mutants: <italic>pen2</italic>, <italic>pen2 pad3</italic>, <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic>, <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic>, and <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic>.</p><p id="Par15">Obtained results revealed that the simultaneous loss of <italic>CYP79B2</italic> and <italic>CYP79B3</italic> completely abolished the <italic>Ab</italic>-triggered accumulation of ICAs and camalexin, whereas the loss of <italic>PAD3</italic> canceled camalexin accumulation, but had no effects on the accumulation of ICAs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B; Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). In the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic> mutant, the <italic>Ab</italic>-triggered accumulation of ICAs was reduced significantly compared with the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant, opposite with camalexin accumulation that was rather increased compared with <italic>pen2</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B; Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). These results further strengthen the idea that the accumulation of ICAs triggered by the <italic>Ab</italic> invasion is critical for the postinvasive resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against this necrotrophic fungal pathogen. In the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant, the ICA levels that accumulated upon <italic>Ab</italic> invasion were similar to those observed in the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic> mutant, but camalexin accumulation in the triple mutant was completely diminished, in contrast to <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B; Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>), further supporting the importance of CYP71A13 for the pathogen-induced accumulation of camalexin, but not ICAs.</p><p id="Par16">It is noteworthy that the leaves of <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant still accumulated clearly detectable amounts of ICAs at both 24 hpi and 48 hpi of <italic>Ab</italic>, whereas camalexin in this triple mutant was under the detection limit at the same time points (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B; Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). As mentioned above, the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutant exhibited a more severe phenotype to <italic>Ab</italic> inoculation compared with the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A,B; Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutant is entirely defective in the production of not only camalexin, but also ICAs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B; Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). Also, both <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> and <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutants are commonly defective in biosynthesis of the PEN2-dependent IG-hydrolysis products (leading to unidentified antifungal compounds), these data suggested that the different levels of susceptibility to <italic>Ab</italic> between <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> and <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> is likely caused by the differential accumulation of ICAs in these two mutants.</p><p id="Par17">In addition to ICAs and camalexin, CYP79B2/CYP89B3 enzymes are essential for biosynthesis of other Trp-derived metabolites including IGs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. The <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant lacks the PEN2-dependent IG-hydrolysis products, but retains the ability to produce IGs, which can be activated by another enzyme. It has been reported that IG biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is controlled by the transcription factors MYB34, MYB51, and MYB122, whereas these factors are dispensable for the pathogen triggered biosynthesis of camalexin and ICAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Thus, to assess the possibility that the different susceptibility to <italic>Ab</italic> between <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> and <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutants might be linked to IG biosynthesis, we compared phenotypes of <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> and <italic>cyp71A12 cyp71A13 myb34 myb51 myb122</italic> lines following <italic>Ab</italic> inoculation. We first performed the metabolite analyses on the <italic>cyp71A12 cyp71A13 myb34 myb51 myb122</italic> mutant leaves at 24 hpi of <italic>Ab</italic> (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>)<italic>.</italic> The obtained results showed that this mutant was defective in IG biosynthesis upon <italic>Ab</italic> infection. Subsequently, we tested susceptibility of this mutant towards <italic>Ab</italic> in an inoculation assay. We found that lesion development in the <italic>cyp71A12 cyp71A13 myb34 myb51 myb122</italic> mutant leaves was similar to that in the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). These results indicate that PEN2-independent IG hydrolysis is likely not involved in the postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>. Thus, the different susceptibility between the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant and the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutant is not linked to IG-deficiency. Together with the involvement of CYP71A12-dependent ICAs synthesis in the postinvasive resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against <italic>Ab</italic>, we consider that the remaining ICAs in <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> are still effective against <italic>Ab.</italic> Consistent with this idea, the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic> mutant was more susceptible to <italic>Ab</italic> than the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>The <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation reduces the postinvasive resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to <italic>Ab</italic>, independently of pathogen-triggered ICAs and camalexin biosynthesis</title><p id="Par18">Next, we asked how <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> recognizes the invasion by <italic>Ab</italic> to activate the biosynthesis of ICAs and camalexin. The candidate mechanism critical for this process is the PRRs-dependent PAMP recognition machinery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. When <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> recognizes PAMPs, at least some of the cognate PRRs, including FLS2 and EFR receptor-like kinases (RLKs), form complexes with coreceptors such as BAK1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Therefore, we decided to assess the possible involvement of BAK1 in the invasion-triggered accumulation of ICAs and camalexin. For this purpose, we used two mutant alleles of <italic>BAK1</italic>, <italic>bak1&#x02013;4</italic> and <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic>; of these, <italic>bak1&#x02013;4</italic> is a <italic>BAK1</italic> null allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, and <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> is a semi-dominant allele with a specific phenotype related to PAMP responsiveness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Importantly, it was reported that <italic>bak1-5</italic> is more severely impaired in elf18 and flg22 responses than the null mutant <italic>bak1-4</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">Because the main results on gene expression and metabolite accumulation were derived from the <italic>pen2</italic>-background mutants in this study, we used the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;4</italic> mutant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and the newly generated <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutant. We first performed <italic>Ab</italic> inoculation assay on these plant lines and found that both <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;4</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants have reduced immunity to <italic>Ab</italic>, although the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants were more susceptible than the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;4</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A,C). Similar results were observed for single <italic>bak1&#x02013;4</italic> and <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> as compared with WT plants (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S7</xref>). We then evaluated whether the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation would reduce preinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab</italic>. To assess this, we compared the invasion behavior of <italic>Ab</italic> in the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant with that in the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutant. The invasion ratio in the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutant was similar to that in the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant, suggesting that the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation does not have detectable impact on preinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). These results indicate that the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation reduces postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab</italic>, i.e., PRR systems likely function in the recognition of <italic>Ab</italic> invasion.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The <italic>bak1</italic> mutations reduced the immunity of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against <italic>Ab</italic>. (<bold>A</bold>) Quantification of lesion development. Conidial suspensions of <italic>Ab</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) were drop-inoculated onto true leaves of 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants. At 4 dpi, lesion areas were measured and the relative values to Col-0 (WT plants) were calculated. The means and SDs were calculated from three independent experiments. The statistical significance of differences between means was determined by Tukey&#x02019;s HSD test. Means not sharing the same letter are significantly different (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). (<bold>B</bold>) The <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation did not reduce preinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> in the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant. Aliquots of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of conidial suspension (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were drop-inoculated onto leaves of 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants of the tested mutants. At 12 hpi, the inoculated leaves were collected and stained with trypan blue, and then invasive hyphae were observed under light microscopy. At least 50 germinating conidia were counted in each experiment. The means and SDs were calculated from three independent experiments. Statistical analysis using two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> tests showed no significant differences between <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutants. (<bold>C</bold>) Lesion development caused by <italic>Ab</italic> on two <italic>pen2 bak1</italic> mutants. Conidial suspensions (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were drop-inoculated onto mature leaves of 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants. The photograph was taken at 4 dpi.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Because we found that the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation reduced postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab</italic>, we next investigated whether <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> would have negative effects on the <italic>Ab</italic> invasion-triggered activation of camalexin and ICAs biosynthesis. We checked the gene expression of <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic> in the <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutants after <italic>Ab</italic> inoculation. Surprisingly, the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation did not cancel the induced expression of <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic> in <italic>pen2</italic> (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). Furthermore, we found that the accumulation of camalexin and ICAs upon <italic>Ab</italic> invasion was not reduced in the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutant compared with the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). The accumulation level of ICAs was even higher in <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> than <italic>pen2</italic> at 48 hpi, which might be due to enhanced infection in <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S8</xref>). Collectively, these results indicate that the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation does not reduce the <italic>Ab</italic>-triggered activation of camalexin and ICAs biosynthesis, although this mutation reduces postinvasive resistance to <italic>Ab</italic>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation did not reduce the <italic>Ab</italic>-invasion triggered accumulation of 6-hydroxy-ICA and camalexin. (<bold>A</bold>) The <italic>Ab</italic>-invasion triggered activation of <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and <italic>PAD3</italic> expression in the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutant. Conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were spray-inoculated onto 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants. The samples were collected at 4, 12, 24, and 48 hpi. Each gene transcript was quantified by RT&#x02013;qPCR using the gene-specific primers listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. Values were normalized to the expression level of <italic>UBC21</italic>. The statistical comparison between <italic>Ab</italic>-treated <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>Ab</italic>-treated <italic>pen2 bak1-5</italic> at same time point samples was conducted using two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> tests and did not show significant differences. (<bold>B</bold>) The <italic>Ab</italic> invasion-triggered accumulations of 6-hydroxy-ICA (6OGlcICA) and camalexin were not canceled by the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation. Conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were spray-inoculated onto the tested mutant lines. The means of metabolites (nmol/g FW) and SDs from four biological independent samples are shown in the graph. The statistical comparison between <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1-5</italic> at same timepoint was conducted using two-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> tests (**<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>The <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation reduces the <italic>Ab</italic> invasion-triggered expression of defense-related genes, including <italic>GLIP1</italic>.</title><p id="Par21">We further investigated the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> sensitive pathways for postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>. We performed comparative expression profiling experiments in <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants following <italic>Ab</italic> invasion using microarray analysis. <italic>Ab</italic> was inoculated to each plant, and RNA isolated from inoculated leaves at 24 hpi was subjected to microarray analysis. We focused on differentially expressed genes associated with the immune response based on Gene Ontology (GO) data (GO term 0006955: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.informatics.jax.org">http://www.informatics.jax.org</ext-link>). As a result, we found that 14 genes had greater than a 2.5-fold change in expression. Interestingly, 11 were down-regulated, and three were up-regulated (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>), implying that, compared with the <italic>pen2</italic> plants, the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants exhibited a trend for reduced immune responses upon <italic>Ab</italic> invasion. Among the 11 down-regulated genes, four were shown previously to be involved in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> immune system using functional analyses such as the analysis of corresponding knockout mutants, including <italic>AED1</italic> (<italic>APOPLASTIC, EDS1-DEPENDENT 1</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, <italic>BGL2</italic>/<italic>PR2</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, <italic>GLIP1</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, and <italic>RLP2</italic>3 (<italic>RECEPTOR-LIKE PROTEIN 23</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Notably, the <italic>glip1</italic> plants were reported to be more susceptible to <italic>Ab</italic> than the WT plant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Subsequently, we performed reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT&#x02013;qPCR) analyses to investigate the expression levels of these four genes (<italic>AED1</italic>, <italic>BGL2</italic>/<italic>PR2</italic>, <italic>GLIP1</italic>, and <italic>RLP23</italic>) at 4, 12, 24, and 48 hpi in <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants inoculated with <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). As a control, we also investigated gene expression in the mock-treated plants. We confirmed that these four genes exhibited lower expression in the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> than in the <italic>pen2</italic> mutant at 24 hpi, consistent with the array data. Furthermore, the RT&#x02013;qPCR analysis revealed that the expression of <italic>AED1</italic>, <italic>BGL2</italic>/<italic>PR2</italic>, <italic>GLIP1</italic>, and <italic>RLP23</italic> was lower at 4 hpi than at 12, 24, and 48 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Together with our finding that <italic>Ab</italic> did not invade at 4 hpi, but started to invade at 12 hpi (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B), our results indicate that these genes are induced upon <italic>Ab</italic> invasion to function in postinvasive resistance. Such induced expression was continuously suppressed in the <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), further suggesting that this invasion-triggered expression depends on putative PRRs with function impaired in the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutant. It is also noteworthy that the invasion-triggered expressions of <italic>AED1</italic>, <italic>BGL2</italic>/<italic>PR2</italic>, <italic>GLIP1</italic>, and <italic>RLP23</italic> were time-dependent, i.e., induced expression started to be down-regulated at 12 hpi (<italic>RLP23</italic>) or 24 hpi (<italic>AED1</italic>, <italic>BGL2</italic>/<italic>PR2</italic>, <italic>GLIP1</italic>) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), which is in contrast to the invasion-triggered expressions of <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic>, which exhibited sustained elevations for up to 48 hpi (Figs. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The <italic>Ab</italic> invasion-triggered expression levels of <italic>AED1</italic>, <italic>BGL2/PR2</italic>, <italic>GLIP1</italic>, and <italic>RLP23</italic> were reduced by the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation. Conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were spray-inoculated onto 4&#x02013;5-week-old <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants, and then kept at 100% humidity. The samples were collected at 4, 12, 24, and 48 hpi. Each gene transcript was quantified by RT&#x02013;qPCR using the gene-specific primers listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. Values were normalized to the expression level of <italic>UBC21</italic>. The means and SDs were calculated from three independent experiments. The statistical analysis was conducted by a two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test. The expression levels of each gene between <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> were compared at the same time points and treatment (*<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par22">We recently reported that CYP71A12 is indispensable for postinvasive resistance to the hemibiotrophic pathogen <italic>Ctro</italic> that is not adapted to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. However, it remained obscure whether CYP71A12 is also involved in this invasion-triggered resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against other fungal pathogens.</p><p id="Par23">Here we found that the absence of functional CYP71A12 enhanced lesion development during colonization of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaves with the necrotrophic pathogen <italic>Ab</italic>, indicating that this enzyme is required for the immune response of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> against this fungus. <italic>CYP71A12</italic> was not induced at 4 hpi with <italic>Ab</italic> when the pathogen had not yet invaded, but it started to be induced upon <italic>Ab</italic> invasion (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). We also found that <italic>CYP71A12</italic> was dispensable for preinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). Collectively, these results demonstrate that <italic>CYP71A12</italic> is required for postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> as well as <italic>Ctro</italic>. Metabolic analyses showed that the enhanced accumulation of ICAs triggered by <italic>Ab</italic> invasion was reduced in the absence of functional CYP71A12. Thus, this enzyme is involved in the accumulation of ICAs following <italic>Ab</italic> invasion (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). Therefore, we consider that the CYP71A12-dependent synthesis of ICA and/or its derivatives upon <italic>Ab</italic> invasion is critical for postinvasive resistance to this fungus.</p><p id="Par24">We also showed that CYP71A13 contributes to the postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> via synthesis of camalexin, but not of ICAs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). The result suggests the importance of camalexin for this second layer of defense, which is further supported by our phenotypic analyses of mutants defective in <italic>PAD3</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p><p id="Par25">PEN2 is involved in preinvasive resistance against <italic>Ctro</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, but we here revealed that it is dispensable for preinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C,D). Furthermore, PEN1 is known to be required for preinvasive resistance against nonadapted powdery mildews<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, but dispensable for the <italic>Colletotrichum</italic> fungi and nonadapted <italic>Alternaria alternata</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. It is also noteworthy that PEN2 is involved in preinvasive resistance against <italic>A. alternata</italic>, in contrast with <italic>Ab</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Thus, the molecular components that underlie preinvasive resistance vary between fungal pathogens, probably because pathogens have evolved various strategies for plant entry. By contrast, once these pathogens enter <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, they commonly develop invasive structures inside the plants; thus, the hosts might deploy an universal defense systems to terminate further fungal growth.</p><p id="Par26">We found that the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutant is more susceptible to <italic>Ab</italic> than is the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutant (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Interestingly, this phenomenon is also observed in the infection by <italic>Ctro</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>cucumerina</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Metabolite analyses of plants upon <italic>Ab</italic> invasion revealed that camalexin accumulation in the <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> plants was almost the same as that in the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> plants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B). Importantly, the <italic>pen2 cyp71A1 cyp71A13</italic> plants reduced their accumulation of ICAs, but still produced them to some degree, whereas the <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> plants were entirely defective in this regard (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B, Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). Consistent with this finding, several independent metabolic branches are supposed to contribute to endogenous ICAs levels, including contribution of Arabidopsis aldehyde oxidase 1 and CYP71B6<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par27">We also compared the phenotype of <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> mutants with that of <italic>myb34 myb51 myb122 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> following <italic>Ab</italic> invasion and found no detectable differences in either mutants in terms of postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>, indicating that the difference between <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> and <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> mutants is not caused by PEN2-unrelated IG metabolism products (Supplementary Figs. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). Collectively, these findings suggest that the lower susceptibility in the former mutants is caused by residual ICAs, i.e., ICAs contribute to postinvasive resistance in a dose-dependent manner. This supports the idea that ICAs or their derivatives work as antifungal compounds as opposed to functioning as signaling molecules for plant immune responses. However, we cannot exclude a possibility that accumulation of so far not-reported IAOx-derivatives whose biosynthesis is not dependent on CYP71A12 and CYP71A13 contribute to the difference observed in susceptibility of <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic> and <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic> plants.</p><p id="Par28">We also investigated how <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> recognizes the invasion of fungal pathogens and then mounts its postinvasive resistance. We found that the two <italic>bak1</italic> mutations, especially the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation, reduce postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The finding that the negative effects of <italic>bak1-5</italic> on the postinvasive resistance towards <italic>Ab</italic> was higher than that of <italic>bak1-4</italic> is likely consistent with the previous works<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par29">Surprisingly, we found that the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation did not hamper the invasion-triggered expressions of <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic> and the subsequent accumulation of ICAs and camalexin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Thus, we postulate existence of another defense mechanism that is affected by the <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutation and required for postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Our further analyses revealed that this pathogen activates the expression of distinct defense-related genes, including <italic>AED1</italic>, <italic>BGL2/PR2</italic>, <italic>GLIP1</italic>, and <italic>RLP23</italic> (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Notably, expressions of these genes were induced following <italic>Ab</italic> invasion, and these were canceled in <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Therefore, we suggest that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> deploys a PRR system to sense the invasion of <italic>Ab</italic> and subsequently activate antifungal defense pathways that are uncoupled from the Trp-metabolism (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Summarized model for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>. The CYP71A12-dependent production of ICAs is required for postinvasive resistance against <italic>A. brassicicola</italic>. The CYP71A13- and PAD3-dependent production of camalexin is also required for postinvasive resistance against <italic>Ab</italic>. The <italic>bak1</italic> mutations (especially <italic>bak1-5</italic>) reduced the postinvasive resistance, however, invasion-triggered activation of these Trp-related pathways is not canceled by <italic>bak1-5</italic>. The <italic>bak1-5</italic> sensitive pathway control the expression of antifungal protein genes (e.g. <italic>GLIP1</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par30">Notably, it has been reported that the <italic>glip1</italic> mutant plants exhibit enhanced susceptibility to <italic>Ab</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. The recombinant GLIP1 protein exhibits antimicrobial activity that disrupts the <italic>Ab</italic> spores and hyphae<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> and triggers systemic acquired resistance against bacterial pathogens (e.g., <italic>Erwinia carotovora</italic> and <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic>) as well as <italic>Ab</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Thus, the enhanced susceptibility of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> to <italic>Ab</italic> in the presence of <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> might be partially caused by the reduced expression of <italic>GLIP1</italic>.</p><p id="Par31">It remains unclear how <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plant recognizes pathogen invasion and then activates Trp-related metabolite accumulation as key immune responses in postinvasive resistance. Because <italic>PAD3</italic> and <italic>CYP71A12</italic> were commonly induced by the invasion of diverse fungal pathogens such as <italic>Ab</italic> and <italic>Ctro</italic>, we suggest that <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> probably recognizes the cell damage that is commonly caused by pathogen invasion and then activates Trp-related metabolism. Further studies are needed to explore a recognition mechanism of pathogen invasion that activates these secondary metabolic pathways for antifungal defense.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Fungal materials</title><p id="Par32"><italic>C</italic>. <italic>tropicale</italic> (<italic>Ctro</italic>) (formerly <italic>Colletotrichum gleosporioides</italic> S9275) was provided by Shigenobu Yoshida (National Institute for Agro-Environmental Sciences, Japan); and <italic>A</italic>. <italic>brassicicola</italic> (<italic>Ab</italic>) strain Ryo-1 was provided by Akira Tohyama. Cultures of <italic>Ab</italic> were maintained on 3.9% (w/v) potato dextrose agar medium (PDA; Nissui Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) at 24&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the dark. <italic>Ctro</italic> was cultured on 2.5% (w/v) PDA (Difco, Detroit, MI, USA) at 24&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under a cycle of 16&#x000a0;h black light (FS20S/BLB 20&#x000a0;W; Toshiba, Tokyo, Japan) illumination and 8&#x000a0;h dark.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> lines and growth conditions</title><p id="Par33">The <italic>A</italic>. <italic>thaliana</italic> accession Col-0 was used as the WT plant. The mutants <italic>pen2-1</italic>, <italic>pen2-2</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, <italic>pad3-1</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>, <italic>cyp71A12</italic>, <italic>cyp71A12</italic>&#x000a0;<italic>cyp71A13</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, <italic>cyp82C2</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, <italic>bak1&#x02013;4</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, <italic>cyp79B2 cyp79B3</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, <italic>pen2 pad3</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, <italic>pen2 cyp82C2</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, <italic>pen2 cyp71A12</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, <italic>pen2 cyp71A12 cyp71A13</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, <italic>cyp71A12 cyp71A13 myb34 myb51 myb122</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>, <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;4</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> (generated in this study) were used in this study. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds were sown on rockwool (Grodan; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.grodan.com">http://www.grodan.com</ext-link>) and kept at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the dark for 2&#x000a0;days, and later grown at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with a cycle of 16&#x000a0;h light and 8&#x000a0;h dark in Hoagland medium.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Pathogen inoculation, lesion development analysis and trypan blue viability staining assay</title><p id="Par34">For spray inoculation assays of <italic>Ab</italic>, 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL of conidial suspension was spray-inoculated on 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants. For drop-inoculation, 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of conidial suspensions of <italic>Ab</italic> (1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) were placed onto each leaf. The inoculated plants were kept at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with a cycle of 16&#x000a0;h light and 8&#x000a0;h dark and maintained at 100% relative humidity. For analysis of lesion development following the inoculation of <italic>Ab</italic>, four drops of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L conidial suspension of each pathogen were drop-inoculated on each leaf, and 24&#x02013;50 lesions were evaluated in each experiment. The developed lesions were quantified using ImageJ image analysis software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://imagej.net">http://imagej.net</ext-link>) and relative values to WT (Col-0) plants were calculated. To measure lesion areas, yellowish areas were included as lesions. Trypan blue staining was conducted according to&#x000a0;the method previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. For the trypan blue assay, at least 50 lesions were investigated in each experiment. The <italic>Ab</italic> invasion ratio (%) was calculated by using the following formula: <italic>Ab</italic> invasion ratio (%)&#x02009;=&#x02009;(number of germinating conidia that developed invasive hyphae / number of germinating conidia)&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Generation of mutant plants</title><p id="Par35">The generation of <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> line used in this study was generated by crossing the <italic>pen2&#x02013;1</italic> mutant with <italic>bak1&#x02013;5</italic> plants. The genotype was checked with the corresponding specific primers for the derived cleaved-amplified polymorphic sequence (dCAPS) markers using dCAPS Finder 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://helix.wustl.edu/dcaps/dcaps.html">http://helix.wustl.edu/dcaps/dcaps.html</ext-link>), and the PCR products (WT or mutant types) were cleaved with appropriate restriction enzymes (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>RT&#x02013;qPCR analysis</title><p id="Par36">Seven <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaves inoculated with <italic>Ab</italic> (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) were collected from each of seven different plants of either WT Col-0 or mutant plants at corresponding time points. Total RNA was extracted using PureLink (TRIzol plus RNA purification kits, Life Technologies/Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) and treated with DNase (RQ1 RNase-free DNase; Promega, Madison, WI, USA; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.promega.com">http://www.promega.com</ext-link>) to remove DNA contamination. Takara Prime Script RT kits (Takara Bio Inc., Shiga, Japan; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.takara-bio.com">http://www.takara-bio.com</ext-link>) was used for the cDNA synthesis. Takara TB Green Premix Ex Taq I was used for RT&#x02013;qPCR, performed using the primers listed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>. Arabidopsis <italic>UBC21</italic> (At5g25760) was used as an internal control for normalizing the level of cDNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. RT&#x02013;qPCR analysis was performed using a Thermal Cycler Dice Real Time System TP800 (Takara). The expression levels of genes of interest were normalized relative to those of <italic>UBC21</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Metabolite analysis</title><p id="Par37">Conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) of <italic>Ab</italic> were spray-inoculated onto 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants and kept at 100% relative humidity. Leaf samples (100&#x02013;200&#x000a0;mg fresh weight) were collected at corresponding time points and frozen immediately in liquid nitrogen. The plant extracts containing Trp derivatives were extracted using DMSO and metabolite analyses were performed as described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Microarray analysis</title><p id="Par38"><italic>Ab</italic> conidial suspensions (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup>&#x000a0;conidia/mL) were spray-inoculated onto 4&#x02013;5-week-old plants of the <italic>pen2</italic> and <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> mutants. For each sample, five leaves were collected at 24 hpi and frozen immediately in liquid nitrogen. In total, eight samples (four biological replicates each of the mock and <italic>Ab</italic>-treated samples) were used for RNA extraction. Total RNA was extracted using Plant RNA Isolation Mini kits (Agilent Technologies., Santa Clara, CA, USA). Aliquots of 200&#x000a0;ng of total RNA were used to prepare Cy3-labeled cRNA using Agilent Low Input Quick Amp labeling kits. The labeled samples were hybridized onto an Agilent <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> microarray (ver. 4.0; 4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;44&#x000a0;K format). After hybridization and washing, the arrays were scanned using an Agilent microarray scanner (G2565BA). The images were analyzed using Agilent Feature Extraction software (ver. 10.7.3.1), and further analysis was performed using Agilent GeneSpring GX12.1 software. Signal normalization was based on the expression ratio of <italic>pen2 bak1&#x02013;5</italic> to <italic>pen2</italic>. Differentially upregulated genes were defined as having a greater than 2.5-fold increase in expression, and differentially downregulated genes were defined as having at least a 0.4-fold decrease in expression. Microarray data have been deposited in the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database GSE 124921.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec31"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_79562_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-020-79562-x.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank ABRC for providing <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> seeds. We also thank Shigenobu Yoshida (<italic>Ctro</italic>) and Akira Tohyama (<italic>Ab</italic>) for providing fungal pathogens. We also thank Yoshihiro Inoue for supports on the statistical analyses. This work was supported by Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Research (15H05780, 18H02204, 18H04780, 18K19212) (KAKENHI), by grants from the Project of the NARO Bio-oriented Technology Research Advancement Institution (Research program on development of innovative technology), and by the Asahi Glass Foundation. Work in the PB laboratory was supported by the National Science Centre SONATA BIS Grant (UMO-2012/07/E/NZ2/04098).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Y.T. and P.B. designed this research. A.K., M.P., M.P-B., T.N., E.O., H.S., A.I. and H.F. performed the experiments and analyzed the data. A.K., Y.T., P.B., E.O., M.K. and K.M. wrote the manuscript and prepared the figures.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par39">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonhost resistance and nonspecific plant defenses</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Plant. Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(00)00087-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10873843?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10873843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pre- and postinvasion defenses both contribute to nonhost resistance in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>1180</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1119409</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16293760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16293760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis PEN3/PDR8, an ATP binding cassette transporter, contributes to nonhost resistance to inappropriate pathogens that enter by direct penetration</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.038372</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16473969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bednarek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A glucosinolate metabolism pathway in living plant cells mediates broad-spectrum antifungal defense</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1163732</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19095900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19095900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Adio</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Denoux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucosinolate metabolites required for an Arabidopsis innate immune response</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>323</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1164627</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19095898?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19095898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiruma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Entry mode-dependent function of an indole glucosinolate pathway in Arabidopsis for nonhost resistance against anthracnose pathogens</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2429</fpage><lpage>2443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.110.074344</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20605856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20605856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosaka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonhost resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> against <italic>Colletotrichum</italic> species</article-title><source>J. Gen. Plant Pathol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10327-018-0799-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze-Lefert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonhost resistance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>-<italic>Colletotrichum</italic> interactions acts at the cell periphery and requires actin filament function</article-title><source>Mol. Plant Microbe Interact.</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-19-0270</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16570657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16570657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiruma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis <italic>ENHANCED DISEASE RESISTANCE 1</italic> is required for pathogen-induced expression of plant defensins in nonhost resistance, and acts through interference of <italic>MYC2</italic>-mediated repressor function</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>992</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04651.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21605210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21605210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiruma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glutathione and tryptophan metabolism are required for Arabidopsis immunity during the hypersensitive response to hemibiotrophs</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>9589</fpage><lpage>9594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1305745110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23696664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23696664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trp-dependent auxin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis: involvement of cytochrome P450s CYP79B2 and CYP79B3</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3100</fpage><lpage>3112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1035402</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12464638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12464638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bednarek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sulfur-containing secondary metabolites from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and other Brassicaceae with function in plant immunity</article-title><source>Chem. Bio Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1846</fpage><lpage>1859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201200086</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22807086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22807086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ttcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmotz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Glawischnig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multifunctional enzyme CYP71B15 (PHYTOALEXIN DEFICIENT3) converts cysteine-indole-3-acetonitrile to camalexin in the indole-3-acetonitrile metabolic network of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.066670</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19567706?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19567706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajniak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Clay</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattely</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new cyanogenic metabolite in Arabidopsis required for inducible pathogen defence</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>525</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14907</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26352477?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26352477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastorczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of CYP71A12 monooxygenase in pathogen-triggered tryptophan metabolism and Arabidopsis immunity</article-title><source>New Phytol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>225</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.16118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31411742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31411742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nafisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arabidopsis cytochrome P450 monooxygenase 71A13 catalyzes the conversion of indole-3-acetaldoxime in camalexin synthesis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2039</fpage><lpage>2052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.051383</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17573535?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17573535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomma</surname><given-names>BPHJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelissen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggermont</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deficiency in phytoalexin production causes enhanced susceptibility of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> to the fungus <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1999.00513.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10476063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10476063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sellam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacomi-Vasilescu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudhomme</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoneau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antifungal activity of brassinin, camalexin and two isothiocyanates against the crucifer pathogens <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic> and <italic>Alternaria brassicae</italic></article-title><source>Plant Pathol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2006.01497.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chinchilla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A flagellin-induced complex of the receptor FLS2 and BAK1 initiates plant defence</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>448</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05999</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17625569?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17625569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The receptor-like kinase SERK3/BAK1 is a central regulator of innate immunity in plants</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>12217</fpage><lpage>12222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0705306104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17626179?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis leucine-rich repeat receptor-like kinases BAK1/SERK3 and BKK1/SERK4 are required for innate immunity to hemibiotrophic and biotrophic pathogens</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2440</fpage><lpage>2455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.084301</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21693696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21693696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SERKing coreceptors for receptors</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2016.08.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27660030?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27660030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BAK1, an Arabidopsis LRR receptor-like protein kinase, interacts with BRI1 and modulates brassinosteroid signaling</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(02)00812-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12150929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12150929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BRI1/BAK1, a receptor kinase pair mediating brassinosteroid signaling</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(02)00814-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12150928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12150928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwessinger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation-dependent differential regulation of plant growth, cell death, and innate immunity by the regulatory receptor-like kinase BAK1</article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e1002046</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21593986?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narusaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The cDNA microarray analysis using an Arabidopsis pad3 mutant reveals the expression profiles and classification of genes induced by <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic> attack</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcg050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12721378?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12721378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frerigmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of pathogen-triggered tryptophan metabolism in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by MYB transcription factors and indole glucosinolate conversion products</article-title><source>Mol. Plant</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molp.2016.01.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26802248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26802248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of pattern recognition receptor signaling in plants</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri.2016.77</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27477127?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27477127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saijo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pattern recognition receptors and signaling in plant&#x02013;microbe interactions</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2018</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.13808</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29266555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29266555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibuya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SOBIR1 contributes to non-host resistance to <italic>Magnaporthe oryzae</italic> in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1577</fpage><lpage>1579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09168451.2016.1164586</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27023441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27023441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breitenbach</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contrasting roles of apoplastic aspartyl protease Apoplastic, enhanced disease susceptibility1-dependent1 and Legume Lectin-like Protein1 in Arabidopsis systemic acquired resistance</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.239665</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24755512?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24755512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leubner-Metzger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Meins</surname><given-names>F</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthukrishnan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functions and regulation of plant &#x000df; 1,3-glucanases (PR2)</article-title><source>Pathogenesis-Related Proteins in Plants</source><year>1999</year><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press LLC</publisher-name><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Secretome analysis reveals an Arabidopsis lipase involved in defense against <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2832</fpage><lpage>2847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.034819</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16126835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16126835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GDSL lipase-like 1 regulates systemic resistance associated with ethylene signaling in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2009</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2008.03772.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19077166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19077166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An RLP23&#x02013;SOBIR1&#x02013;BAK1 complex mediates NLP-triggered immunity</article-title><source>Nat. Plants</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>15140</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nplants.2015.140</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27251392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27251392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SNARE-protein-mediated disease resistance at the plant cell wall</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02076</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14586469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14586469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egusa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonhost resistance of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> against <italic>Alternaria alternata</italic> involves both pre- and postinvasive defenses but is collapsed by AAL-toxin in the absence of LOH2</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2013</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-08-12-0201-R</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23360532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23360532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ttcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The biosynthetic pathway of indole-3-carbaldehyde and indole-3-carboxylic acid derivatives in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.235630</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24728709?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24728709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;ttcher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Glawischnig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissection of the network of indolic defence compounds in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> by multiple mutant analysis</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2019</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2019.01.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30798200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30798200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of phytoalexin-deficient mutants of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and characterization of their interactions with bacterial pathogens</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>8955</fpage><lpage>8959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.91.19.8955</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8090752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8090752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcription activator-like effector nuclease-mediated generation and metabolic analysis of camalexin-deficient <italic>cyp71a12 cyp71a13</italic> double knockout lines</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.00481</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25953104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25953104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Slusarenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is susceptible to infection by a downy mildew fungus</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2152169?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2152169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Czechowski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Udvardi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheible</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and testing of superior reference genes for transcript normalization in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.063743</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16166256?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166256</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>