<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">C. zeylanicum</span> bark was collected from rural regions of Jiroft district (Kerman, Iran) in June 2014. The plant materials were identified by Dr. Mandegari, a botanist in Herbal Medicines Research Center, Kerman University of Medical Sciences, Kerman, Iran. Voucher specimen was deposited at Herbarium of Pharmacognosy Department of Faculty of Pharmacy, Kerman University of Medical Sciences, Kerman, Iran.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extraction/isolation of essential oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Air-dried bark (200 g) was subjected to hydrodistillation for 3 h by an all-glass Clevenger-type apparatus. The obtained essential oil was dried on anhydrous sodium sulfate and stored in darkness at 4°C in airtight glass vials closed under nitrogen gas until testing.[
   <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">24</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drug dilutions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil (0.1 mL) was dissolved in 0.97 mL of normal saline. In addition, to increase the dispersal of the essential oil, 0.03 mL of Tween 20 (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) was added to the test tube. Obtained solution was adequately mixed using a magnetic stirrer. Then, serial dilution was made to access the essential oil at concentrations of 100, 50, 25, 12.5, and 6.25 μL/mL. The selection of the essential oil dilutions was according to pilot experiments, which also indicated that normal saline plus Tween 20 had no effect on the growth of protoscoleces.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry analysis</div>
  <sec id="sec3-1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography analysis</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography (GC) analysis was carried out by a Shimadzu QP5050 with a HP-5MS column (30 m × 0.25 mm, film thickness 0.25 mm). The column temperature was retained at 60°C for 3 min and programmed to 180°C at a rate of 5°C/min and maintained constant at 275°C for 5 min. Injector and interface temperatures were 230 and 280°C, respectively. The flow rate of helium as carrier gas was (0.9 mL/min C.F). The percentages were calculated by electronic integration of FID peak areas without the use of response factors correction. Linear retention indices for all components were determined by coinjection of the samples with a solution containing homologous series of C8-C20 
    <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3-2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry analysis</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GC/mass spectrometry (MS) analysis was carried out by a Thermoquest-Finnigan gas chromatograph equipped with fused silica capillary DB-5 column (30 m × 0.25 mm, film thickness 0.25 mm) coupled with a TRACE mass (Manchester, UK). Helium was used as carrier gas with ionization voltage of 70 eV. Ion source and interface temperatures were 230 and 280°C, respectively. Mass range was from 40 to 300 U. Oven temperature program was the same given above for the GC.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of the essential oil components</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The constituents were identified using comparison of their relative retention time and mass spectra with those of standards Wiley 2001 library data of the GC/MS system or with those of showed in the literature data.[
   <a rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref25">25</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection of protoscoleces</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The protoscoleces of hydatid cysts were collected from the livers of naturally infected sheep and goats slaughtered at Kerman abattoir, Southeast of Iran and transferred to the Parasitology Laboratory at the Department of Parasitology and Mycology, Kerman University of Medical Sciences (Kerman, Iran). All hydatid cyst fluid aseptically aspirated by a 50 mL syringe and transferred into a glass tube was left for 30 min for protoscoleces to settle down. After throwaway the supernatant, the protoscoleces were washed two times with PBS (pH 7.2) solution. Finally, the number of protoscoleces per mL was adjusted as 2 × 10
   <span class="sup">3</span> protoscoleces in 0.9% NaCl solution with at least 90% viability rate.[
   <a rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref26">26</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effect on protoscoleces</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate scolicidal effects, various concentrations of the essential oil were evaluated during 5, 10, 20, and 30 min. Initially, 0.5 mL of the protoscoleces (2 × 10
   <span class="sup">3</span>/mL) solution was poured in each test tube. Then, 0.5 mL of different concentrations of the essential oil was added to test tubes. The tubes were mixed gently and then incubated at 37°C for 5, 10, 20, and 30 min. After incubation, 50 μL of 0.1% eosin stain was added to the remaining settled protoscoleces and mixed gently again. After 10 min of incubation, the upper portion of the solution was discarded. The remaining pellet of protoscoleces was then smeared on a glass slide and examined under a light microscope. The mortality rate of the protoscoleces was determined by counting 300 protoscoleces.[
   <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>] Moreover, normal saline plus Tween 20 and 20% hypertonic saline were used as negative and positive control, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Viability test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The viability was confirmed by flame cell motility and impermeability of the protoscoleces to 0.1% eosin (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) solution under a light microscope (Smyth &amp; Barrett, 1980). After exposure, live protoscoleces remained colorless and exhibited characteristic muscular movements and flame cell activity, whereas dead protoscoleces absorbed stain and colored red [
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>].[
   <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">28</a>]
  </p>
  <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Live (left) and death (right) protoscoleces of hydatid cysts after exposure with 0.1% eosin</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="PM-13-652-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toxicity</div>
  <sec id="sec3-3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animals</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forty-eight male NMRI mice (6–8 weeks old) were purchased from the Animal Breeding Stock Facility of Razi Institute of Iran (Karaj, Iran). Mice were kept in a colony room with a 12:12 h light/dark cycle at 21°C ± 2°C and were handled according to standard protocols for the use of laboratory animals. The experimental procedures performed in the present study were in line with the guidelines of the Kerman University of Medical Science (Kerman, Iran) for the care and use of laboratory animals (Permit no. 92/279).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3-4" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acute toxicity effects</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the acute toxicity, various doses of 
    <span class="italic">C. zeylanicum</span> essential oil (0.5–4 mL/kg) were intraperitoneally administrated into four groups (six mice in each group). The number of deaths was counted at 48 h after treatment. LD
    <sub>50</sub> values were determined by the Probit test in SPSS software.[
    <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">29</a>]
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3-5" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determination of clinical chemistry and hematological parameters</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Twenty-four mice were randomly divided into four groups with 8 mice per group. The first group (control) was administrated normal saline orally (orogastric gavage), and the second to fourth groups were orally administrated 
    <span class="italic">C. zeylanicum</span> essential oil at the doses of 0.05, 0.1, and 0.2 ml/kg, respectively, for 14 consecutive days.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following the experimental period, animals were fasted overnight and anesthetized. According to guidelines of the Kerman University of Medical Sciences (Kerman, Iran) for the care and use of laboratory animals, we used ketamine (100 mg/kg) and xylazine (10 mg/kg) combination for anesthesia which in it some alpha-2 adrenoreceptor agonists (i.e., xylazine and medetomidine) do have analgesic properties and other analgesics such as opioids were not used. Sodium pentobarbital (70 mg/kg, i.p.) was used as euthanasia agent and then the abdomen was opened, and blood samples were collected from the heart. In this work due to compliance with all standards of sterilization, we did not use any antibiotics. For hematological studies, total blood was collected into tubes containing ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid anticoagulant, and biochemical parameters, including hemoglobin, hematocrit, white blood cell counts, red blood cell counts, and platelet counts, were measured. To measure clinical chemistry parameters in serum, blood was collected into tubes containing no anticoagulant, allowed to clot, and serum was separated by centrifugation at 2000
    <span class="italic">g</span> for 20 min. The assays of aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), creatinine (Cr), blood urea nitrogen (BUN), and bilirubin (direct and total) were performed using Roche Diagnostics Kits (Mannheim, Germany).[
    <a rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref30">30</a>
    <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>]
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Obtained results are expressed as the mean ± standard error of mean. Data analysis was carried out using SPSS statistical package version 17.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). One-way ANOVA with Tukey's 
   <span class="italic">post hoc</span> test was used to assess differences between experimental groups. In addition, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.[
   <a rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref32">32</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
