<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cystic echinococcosis (CE) is a zoonotic parasitic disease which is caused by the larval form of 
  <span class="italic">Echinococcus granulosus</span> tapeworm.[
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>] CE has a worldwide distribution but is mostly prevalent in the rural areas, in which it is transmitted in a cycle between dogs (definitive host), as domestic livestock, and humans, as the intermediate host.[
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">2</a>
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">3</a>] CE may develop in humans after the accidental ingestion of tapeworm eggs excreted with the feces of an infected dog. The eggs hatch in the intestine of the herbivore, penetrate into the intestinal wall, and reach the livers (50%–70%), lungs (20%–30%), or any other organs through the portal system, in which they develop to a hydatid cyst.[
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>] At present, surgical intervention (conventional or laparoscopic approaches) is the ideal treatment for CE. In addition, cyst puncture, aspiration, injection of chemicals, and reaspiration, chemotherapy with benzimidazole compounds, and watching and waiting for inactive, clinically silent cysts are the substitute treatments to surgery, particularly for the patients who cannot tolerate surgery.[
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>] Through the surgery for dropping threat of intraoperative outflow of protoscoleces (cyst contents) and followed by the repetition of CE and secondary infection, it is necessary to apply effective protoscolicidal agents.[
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>] At this time, the accessible protoscolicidal agents including hypertonic saline and silver nitrate are connected with some serious adverse effects such as biliary tract fibrosis and liver necrosis.[
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>] Therefore, the expansion of new helpful scolicidal agents, mainly from natural resources with little side effects and higher efficiency, is extremely important for surgeons.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reviews have reported antimicrobial activity of plants and derivative essential oils, extracts, and other phytoconstituents.[
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>] Essential oils are an important supply of new antimicrobial agents as a result of their two imperative properties: further protection to people and environment in addition to low risk of the appearance of microbial resistance, given that they have components which possibly will indicate a range of mechanisms of antimicrobial effects.[
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">16</a>
  <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">17</a>] Cinnamomum zeylanicum Blume (Lauraceae) has long been used as a spice and flavoring agent in different cultures around the world for several centuries. True cinnamon or 
  <span class="italic">C. zeylanicum</span> is the inner bark of a small evergreen tree, which is considered a medication for respiratory, digestive, and gynecological disorders.[
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a>
  <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>] A range of pharmacological functions in antitumor, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, antimicrobial, and antidiabetic terms has been attributed to this plant.[
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>
  <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">21</a>
  <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">22</a>] Previous investigations have found cinnamaldehyde, camphene, linalool, a-phelendrene, a-terpinene, and limonene as the main constituents of 
  <span class="italic">C. zeylanicum</span> essential oil.[
  <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">21</a>] However, some factors such as location and seasonal variations could affect the chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of this essential oil.[
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>] This study analyzes the chemical composition of the essential oil obtained from 
  <span class="italic">C. zeylanicum</span> bark, its scolicidal effects on protoscoleces of 
  <span class="italic">E. granulosus</span>, and its toxicity in mice.
 </p>
</sec>
