<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">This paper aimed to evaluate the effect of herbal mixture (
  <italic class="italic">Mentha spicata</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Zingiber officinale</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Citrus sinensis</italic>) only and along with clomiphene citrate (CC) compared to CC on serum antioxidants, glycemic status, menstrual regulation, and rate of pregnancy. This single-blind randomized clinical trial was carried out on 60 infertile participants with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS) willing to be pregnant. They were randomly allocated into group 1 (
  <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 20) who received routine dose of CC pills (50–150 mg) for three menstrual cycles from the fifth day of menstruation for five days; group 2 (
  <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 20) who consumed herbal mixture daily (700 mg); and group 3 (
  <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 20) who used up herbal mixture along with CC for 3 months. Catalase (CAT), glutathione peroxidase (GPx), superoxide dismutase (SOD), malondialdehyde (MDA), fasting blood sugar (FBS), insulin, and homeostatic model assessment for insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) were measured in their blood samples. No statistically significant differences were observed between the three groups in terms of socio-demographic characteristics. After intervention, however, the levels of CAT in group 2 (adjusted mean difference (aMD): = 9.0; confidence interval (CI) 95% = 1.1–16.9) and group 3 (aMD = 12.2; CI 95% = 4.5–19.9), GPx in group 2 (aMD = 986.1; CI 95% = 141.1–1831.1) and group 3 (aMD = 1781.2; CI 95% = 960.7–2601.8), and SOD in group 2 (aMD = 55.1; CI 95% = 26.0–84.2) increased. While FBS in group 3 (aMD = −8.7; CI 95% = −14.7 to −2.7), insulin in group 2 (aMD = −5.6; CI 95% = −10.8 to −0.4), and HOMA-IR in group 2 (aMD = −1.3; CI 95% = −2.4 to −0.2) significantly decreased compared to the group 1. To summarize, herbal mixture supplements along with CC have beneficial effects on serum antioxidant levels, as well as glycemic biomarkers of infertile PCOS, menstrual regulation, and pregnancy rate.
 </p>
</abstract>
