<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although some of these have several drawbacks and lead to inconsistent results [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>,
 <xref rid="B164-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B169-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>,
 <xref rid="B170-molecules-26-00632" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. In this regard, we would like to provide critical thought. Undoubtedly, the computational tools are valid instruments for the drug identification process, but the support of these preliminary investigations with experimental biological data are strictly required. Although these feelings can appear obvious, we believe this concept should be stressed to avoid the spread of disinformation or to prevent equivocal scientific conclusions. Most investigations were carried out on therapeutic benefits of phytochemicals, according to their known antiviral, anti-inflammatory and immunoregulatory properties. Several research teams conclude by asserting that the use of polyphenolic compounds, anthraquinones and flavonoids, and steroid-based molecules for COVID-19 treatment can appear speculative. In fact, no clear evidence from well-drawn clinical trials has been reported so far. On the other hand, dietary use of these phytochemical derivatives is known to provide several benefits to humans. The safety and efficacy of the reported natural compounds in preclinical and clinical trials must be still assessed to establish their use and application in COVID-19 infection. In this perspective, the dietary nature and pleiotropic effects make natural occurring compounds a fascinating candidate for further investigation.
</p>
