<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <italic class="italic">In situ</italic> wettability measurements in hydrocarbon reservoir rocks have only been possible recently. The purpose of this work is to present a protocol to characterize the complex wetting conditions of hydrocarbon reservoir rock using pore-scale three-dimensional X-ray imaging at subsurface conditions. In this work, heterogeneous carbonate reservoir rocks, extracted from a very large producing oil field, have been used to demonstrate the protocol. The rocks are saturated with brine and oil and aged over three weeks at subsurface conditions to replicate the wettability conditions that typically exist in hydrocarbon reservoirs (known as mixed-wettability). After the brine injection, high-resolution three-dimensional images (2 µm/voxel) are acquired and then processed and segmented. To calculate the distribution of the contact angle, which defines the wettability, the following steps are performed. First, fluid-fluid and fluid-rock surfaces are meshed. The surfaces are smoothed to remove voxel artefacts, and 
  <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> contact angles are measured at the three-phase contact line throughout the whole image. The main advantage of this method is its ability to characterize 
  <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> wettability accounting for pore-scale rock properties, such as rock surface roughness, rock chemical composition, and pore size. The 
  <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> wettability is determined rapidly at hundreds of thousands of points. 
 </p>
 <p class="p">The method is limited by the segmentation accuracy and X-ray image resolution. This protocol could be used to characterize the wettability of other complex rocks saturated with different fluids and at different conditions for a variety of applications. For example, it could help in determining the optimal wettability that could yield an extra oil recovery (
  <italic class="italic">i.e.</italic>, designing brine salinity accordingly to obtain higher oil recovery) and to find the most efficient wetting conditions to trap more CO
  <sub class="sub">2</sub> in subsurface formations.
 </p>
</abstract>
