<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antimicrobial activity of 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil from the chemotype of Algarve and two chemotypes of Sesimbra (Estremadura) in Portugal, measured by disc agar diffusion method, was confirmed by Faleiro et al. [
 <xref rid="B21-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The tested microorganisms (
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> subsp., 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes EGD</italic>) presented different sensitivities. In particular, 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil (3 μL) from Algarve showed the highest activity against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> showing a diameter of the zone of inhibition of 13.7 and 15.7 mm for the flower and leaf, respectively, while 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil from Sesimbra (Estremadura) had the highest activity for 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> showing a diameter of the zone of inhibition of 13.3 mm for chemotype A. Additionally, the antimicrobial activity observed with 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil was explored to determine if it was due to the main constituents present in the different oil chemotypes (linalool, 1,8-cineole and linalool/1,8-cineole (1:1) mixture); for this purpose, the antimicrobial activity of these constituents alone was tested. It was concluded a higher antimicrobial activity of linalool compared with 1,8-cineole. Moreover, possible antagonist and synergistic effects of the various constituents of the essential oil were registered, once 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> was susceptible to linalool but not to the mixture of linalool plus 1,8-cineole, and for 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> the mixture of linalool plus 1,8-cineole produced a slight increase in the antimicrobial activity whereas was not susceptible to 1,8-cineole. In a previous work of the same authors, and using the same method, the results suggested that the higher antimicrobial activity of the 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil against 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> was associated to higher amounts of camphor present in 
 <italic>T. mastichina</italic> essential oil comparatively to the essential oils of other plants [
 <xref rid="B16-pharmaceuticals-13-00479" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
