<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The hydroalcoholic extracts of 
 <italic>E. indica</italic> and 
 <italic>E. suberosa,</italic> have shown percentages of inhibition of nitric oxide 21.5% to 89%. Given the polarity of the solvent used for the extraction, the participation of phenolic compounds in the reduction of nitric oxide was suggested [
 <xref rid="B54-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The production of NO and prostaglandins is regulated by iNOS and COX-2. iNOS is distinguished by generating more NO than the constituent members, it is involved in the development and maintenance of central and peripheral sensitization in inflammatory and neuropathic pain. NO can act as a neurotransmitter that affects spinal nociceptive processing in various pain models. COX-2 in macrophages increases in an oxidizing environment and, in turn, increases inflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="B114-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. So too, the ethanol and ethyl acetate bark extracts of 
 <italic>E. caffra</italic>, 
 <italic>E. latissima,</italic> and 
 <italic>E. lysistemon</italic> exhibited an important cyclooxygenase inhibiting activity. 
 <italic>E. caffra</italic> and 
 <italic>E. lysistemon</italic> displayed inhibition of more than 90% for both the 50 and 500 mg/mL doses, this suggested the presence of potent compounds in the bark, as flavonoids. 
 <italic>E. caffra</italic> is one of 
 <italic>Erythrina</italic> species most frequently used by traditional healers to relieve inflammation [
 <xref rid="B48-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. On the other hand, the administration of ethanolic extract of leaves from 
 <italic>E. neillii</italic> at 100, 250, and 500 mg/kg in the methotrexate-intoxicated rats significantly mitigated lipid peroxidation activity, with a significant decrease of malondialdehyde (MDA) in the hepatic tissue, and a significant increase of GSH and SOD activity, in a dose-dependent manner. Additionally. Additionally, a significant decrease in the hepatic tissue content of TNF-α was demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B71-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Likewise, the GSH, SOD, and CAT content significantly increased (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 to 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) in the groups treated with the methanol extract of 
 <italic>E. indica</italic> leaves [
 <xref rid="B52-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. All this compared with silymarin a potent antioxidant. It was suggested that flavones such Liquiritin, derived from plant licorice, increased SOD, CAT, GSH-PX enzymatic activity through activating the Nrf2/keap1 pathway and attenuation the ERK1/2/NF-κB pathway [
 <xref rid="B115-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Although it has been documented that the pathological effects of ROS on inflammation are due to the activation of several pro-inflammatory signaling pathways such as mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPK) [
 <xref rid="B105-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>], recently shown that some prenylated flavonoids induce the expression of HO-1 activating Nrf2 through the p38 MAPK pathway [
 <xref rid="B113-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>].
</p>
