<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Tradit Complement Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Tradit Complement Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Traditional and Complementary Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2225-4110</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Center for Food and Biomolecules, National Taiwan University. Production and hosting by Elsevier Taiwan LLC.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7833040</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2225-4110(20)31289-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcme.2020.12.001</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Anti-COVID-19 drug candidates: A review on potential biological activities of natural products in the management of new coronavirus infection</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Prasansuklab</surname><given-names>Anchalee</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Theerasri</surname><given-names>Atsadang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Rangsinth</surname><given-names>Panthakarn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Sillapachaiyaporn</surname><given-names>Chanin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Chuchawankul</surname><given-names>Siriporn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Tencomnao</surname><given-names>Tewin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>College of Public Health Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Graduate Program in Clinical Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, Department of Clinical Chemistry, Faculty of Allied Health Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Immunomodulation of Natural Products Research Group, Faculty of Allied Health Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Transfusion Medicine and Clinical Microbiology, Faculty of Allied Health Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Clinical Chemistry, Faculty of Allied Health Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Immunomodulation of Natural Products Research Group, Faculty of Allied Health Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x02217;&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Immunomodulation of Natural Products Research Group, Faculty of Allied Health Sciences, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, 10330, Thailand.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 Center for Food and Biomolecules, National Taiwan University. Production and hosting by Elsevier Taiwan LLC.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Center for Food and Biomolecules, National Taiwan University</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background and aim</title><p>The novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is now become a worldwide pandemic bringing over 71 million confirmed cases, while the specific drugs and vaccines approved for this disease are still limited regarding their effectiveness and adverse events. Since virus incidences are still on rise, infectivity and mortality may also rise in the near future, natural products are highly considered to be valuable sources for the discovery of new antiviral drugs against SARS-CoV-2. This present review aims to comprehensively summarize the up-to-date scientific literatures on biological activities of plant- and mushroom-derived compounds relevant to mechanistic targets involved in SARS-CoV-2 infection and inflammatory-associated pathogenesis, including viral entry, replication and release, and the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS).</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental procedure</title><p>Data were retrieved from a literature search available on PubMed, Scopus and Google Scholar databases and collected until the end of May 2020. The findings from <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> cell and non-cell based studies were considered, while the results of <italic>in silico</italic> studies were excluded.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and conclusion</title><p>Based on the previous findings in SARS-CoV studies, except <italic>in silico</italic> molecular docking analysis, herein, we provide a total of 150 natural compounds as potential candidates for development of new anti-COVID-19 drugs with higher efficacy and lower toxicity than the existing therapeutic agents. Several natural compounds have showed their promising actions on multiple therapeutic targets, which should be further explored. Among them, quercetin, one of the most abundant of plant flavonoids, is proposed as a lead candidate with its ability on the virus side to inhibit SARS-CoV spike protein-angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) interaction, viral protease and helicase activities, as well as on the host cell side to inhibit ACE activity and increase intracellular zinc level.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><alt-text id="alttext0010">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg"/></fig></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>2019-nCoV</kwd><kwd>Anti-viral</kwd><kwd>Therapeutic strategies</kwd><kwd>Natural compound</kwd><kwd>Herbal medicine</kwd><kwd>Plant</kwd><kwd>Mushroom</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="nomen0010"><title>List of abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="d0010">3CL<sup>pro</sup></term><def><p id="p0030">3-chymotrypsin-like main protease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0015">ACE</term><def><p id="p0035">Angiotensin-converting enzyme</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0020">ARB</term><def><p id="p0040">Angiotensin-receptor blocker</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0025">ARDS</term><def><p id="p0045">Acute respiratory distress syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0030">AT1R</term><def><p id="p0050">Angiotensin II type 1 receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0035">COVID-19</term><def><p id="p0055">Coronavirus Disease 2019</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0040">MERS-CoV</term><def><p id="p0060">Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0045">Nsp</term><def><p id="p0065">Non-structural protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0050">PL<sup>pro</sup></term><def><p id="p0070">Papain-like protease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0055">RAAS</term><def><p id="p0075">Renin&#x02013;angiotensin&#x02013;aldosterone system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0060">RdRp</term><def><p id="p0080">RNA-dependent RNA polymerase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0065">RTC</term><def><p id="p0085">Replication-transcription complex</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0070">SARS-CoV</term><def><p id="p0090">Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0075">SARS-CoV-2</term><def><p id="p0095">Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0080">TMPRSS2</term><def><p id="p0100">Transmembrane protease serine 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="d0085">V-ATPase</term><def><p id="p0105">Vacuolar-type H<sup>+</sup>-ATPase</p></def></def-item></def-list></sec><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0110">On 31 December 2019, several cases of pneumonia were reported in Wuhan, the epicenter of the outbreak in Hubei province of China.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The novel coronavirus was identified as Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) which causes Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> From the time of emergence until present, COVID-19 has spread worldwide in which a total of over 71 million confirmed cases with over 1.6 million death tolls has been reported by the World Health Organization (WHO). The COVID-19 positive cases continue rising and is widely distributed throughout the world with the prevalence ranging from highest in America, followed by Europe and South-East Asia, and lowest in Western Pacific region. Asymptomatic patients and patients with mild symptoms can be recovered under home care and isolation while patients with severe complications including acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) require intensive care unit (ICU) which involves oxygen therapy.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Currently, there is scant evidence from clinical trials for WHO to approve any standard drugs or vaccines as several trials have failed due to efficacy and safety concerns.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Natural compounds from plant and fungi sources have been recognized in their antiviral properties with numerous mechanisms to prevent infection and strengthen host immunity.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Herein, we reviewed potential antiviral compounds with multiple targets of action relating to coronaviruses including inhibiting of viral entry, replication and release, and compounds targeting renin&#x02013;angiotensin&#x02013;aldosterone system (RAAS) which exhibit promising effects against the disease. We also proposed future perspectives in adopting natural compounds to combat against the COVID-19.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Promising therapeutic strategies for the treatment of COVID-19 infection</title><p id="p0115">Presently, there is no clinically approved therapeutics for treating COVID-19, while the rapid human-to-human transmission of this viral infection has expanded worldwide. As the efficacy and safety of natural products on the treatment of a number of viruses including SARS-CoV and Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV), have been widely acknowledged for several years,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> the compounds derived from natural sources, e.g. plants and fungi, could have the potential to be a powerful anti-COVID-19 drug. In this review, we focused on four main categories of therapeutic strategies that aim to target the cellular machinery at each step of virus life cycle, starting from viral entry and replication to the release of viral progenies, as well as the RAAS which is a main target of the treatment of hypertension and has recently been proposed as another promising alternative in the treatment of COVID-19. The multiple potential therapeutic mechanisms, both specific and general, that could be capable of tackling COVID-19 infection are presented in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>
.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Schematic illustration of potential therapeutic mechanisms in COVID-19 infection. The potential therapeutic strategies for SARS-CoV-2 infection proposed here fall into four main categories based on the cellular and molecular machinery required for the viral life cycle and its related pathogenic mechanisms: inhibition of virus entry, inhibition of virus replication, blocking the release of viral progenies, and modifying the RAAS. The selective blockade of the S protein-ACE2 binding (&#x02776;), TMPRSS2 activity (&#x02777;), and endocytic pathway-associated proteins such as clathrin, the vacuolar-type H<sup>+</sup>-ATPase (V-ATPase), and cathepsin L (&#x02778;), prevent the internalization of virus within the cell. Virus multiplication can be blocked through direct inhibition of proteolytic activity of two viral proteases, 3CL<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup> (&#x02779;), and replicative activity of viral RTC components e.g., RdRp and helicase (&#x0277a;), or indirect enzyme inhibition by increasing intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> concentration (&#x0277b;). Silencing the expression and ion channel activity of viroporin 3a suppresses the release of viral particles from infected cells (&#x0277c;). Overactivation of Ang II/AT1R axis which contributes to excessive inflammation, can be suppressed by blockade of ACE (&#x0277d;) and AT1R (&#x0277e;). 3CL<sup>pro</sup>, 3-chymotrypsin-like protease; ACE2, angiotensin-converting enzyme 2; Ang, angiotensin; AT1R, angiotensin II type 1 receptor; E, envelope; MasR, mitochondrial assembly receptor; M, membrane; N, nucleocapsid; PL<sup>pro</sup>, papain-like protease; pp, polyprotein; RAAS, renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system; RdRp, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase; RTC, replication-transcription complex; S, spike; TMPRSS2, transmembrane protease serine 2.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig.&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0120">The first therapeutic strategy targets on the mechanisms of virus entry in which the selective blockade of molecules that facilitates the internalization of virus into the host cells could be effective to prevent infection. Upon the binding of a virus surface spike (S) protein to a cellular receptor angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), the SARS-CoV-2 generally enters into target host cells via two primary routes; viral membrane fusion and the more common endocytic uptake.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> The first entry mechanism is assisted by proteolytic activation of S protein by a host cell transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS2), which allows not only direct fusion of virus at the plasma membrane surface, but also release of viral genomic RNA into the cytoplasm. On the other hand, without the membrane bound protease TMPRSS2, the latter entry mechanism allows the whole viral particle to be uptaken via receptor-mediated endocytosis, before subsequently uncoated following the S protein cleavage by cathepsin L within the endosome, to unveil its RNA genome into the cell.</p><p id="p0125">The second and third therapeutic strategies focus on the inhibition of progeny virus production and release from infected cells. As far as the viral replication process is concerned,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> it begins with the translation of released genome of SARS-CoV-2, a single-stranded (positive-sense) RNA of approximately 30&#x000a0;kb in length, into two precursor polyproteins, pp1a and pp1ab. Both are further cleaved by virus-encoded proteases into several non-structural proteins (nsps) including two key replicative enzymes: the nsp12-RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) and the nsp13-helicase, to form the replication-transcription complex (RTC) for synthesizing a full-length genomic RNA (replication) or a nested set of subgenomic mRNA (transcription). These mRNAs are translated into all relevant structural proteins, which together with the viral genome are subsequently assembled into new virions and finally released outside the cell through viroporin-mediated viral budding.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0130">The last therapeutic strategy involves modulating the immune system with the RAAS which regulates blood pressure, fibrosis, and inflammation. In this system, angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) converts angiotensin I to angiotensin II which is then converted to lung-protective angiotensin-(1&#x02013;7) by ACE2. The angiotensin-(1&#x02013;7) is further recognized by its receptor, the G-protein coupled receptor Mas, to reduce blood pressure, fibrosis, and inflammation.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> However, as SARS-CoV-2 enters the cells by binding to ACE2, the normal functions of ACE2 are then suppressed. Therefore, instead of converting to angiotensin-(1&#x02013;7), the angiotensin II is largely bound to type 1 angiotensin II type 1 receptor (AT1R) which causing increased inflammation and other deleterious effects, particularly in the renal and cardiovascular systems.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Potential natural products as drug candidates against COVID-19</title><p id="p0135">The data presented in this review were obtained from PubMed, Scopus and Google Scholar database up to May 2020. The terms of natural compound, natural product, plant and mushroom were individually searched along with the terms corresponding to each target molecule. Here, we summarize plant- and mushroom-derived compounds that have been reported of antiviral activity with known therapeutic mechanisms specifically against SARS-CoV infection, performed by <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> cell or non-cell based experiments but not <italic>in silico</italic> method, as potential candidates to be further researched. We also propose certain promising natural compounds targeting general mechanisms involved in coronavirus infection (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). Additionally, the reports on natural compounds against SARS-CoV with unidentified mechanism of action were included in this review.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Natural bioactive compounds targeting viral entry</title><sec id="sec3.1.1"><label>3.1.1</label><title>The S protein-ACE2 interaction</title><p id="p0140">The S protein plays a pivotal role in the entry of coronaviruses into host cells by recognizing and binding to the ACE2 via multivalent bonds.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> The attachment of S protein to ACE2 receptor leads to the fusion between the viral envelope and host cell membrane resulting in successful transfer of viral genome into infected cells.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> S protein is composed of two functional subunits, S1 and S2. The S1 is responsible for binding to the host cell receptor through the receptor binding domain (RDB), while the S2 causes fusion of the viral and cellular membranes.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Sequence alignment results showed that the homology of the S protein RBD sequence between the beta coronaviruses SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 is 76%.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> A number of evidence revealed human ACE2 (hACE2) molecule as an entry receptor for both SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 S proteins.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Notably, S protein of SARS-CoV-2 was found to exhibit greater affinity to the ACE2 receptor than that of SARS-CoV.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> In addition, expression of ACE2 is ubiquitous with diverse functions, however its specific functions are demonstrated in several organs including lung, tongue, heart, kidney, gastrointestinal tract, pancreas and brain.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Accordingly, multiple symptoms could be observed in COVID-19 patients.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Several observations have been reported that the use of hydroxychloroquine, an ACE2 FDA-approved antagonist, was able to reduce mortality rate in hospitalized COVID-19 patients.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Therefore, it is apparent that the S protein-hACE2 interaction complex is the most crucial target for searching appropriate inhibitors to inhibit entry of the virus in the host cell.</p><p id="p0145">Several natural compounds have been demonstrated their activity to inhibit SARS-CoV entry to the host cell as shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>
. According to the literature, an anthraquinone compound, emodin, showed the potency to inhibit viral infection by blocking the binding of SARS-CoV S protein to ACE2 in a dose-dependent manner.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> The plant sources which are likely to contain emodin as their active constituent were also found effective in blocking SARS-CoV S protein and ACE2 interaction, with showing IC<sub>50</sub> values for aqueous extracts from the root of <italic>Rheum palmatum</italic>, the root and stem of <italic>Polygonum multiflorum</italic>, ranged from 1 to 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> Another previous study using the high-throughput screening technique revealed more promising natural antiviral compounds consisted in the extracts from Chinese herbs. Those small herbal molecules could strongly bind to the SARS-CoV S2 protein and inhibited the pseudovirus entry, possibly by interfering with the function of the S protein.<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>List of bioactive compounds from natural sources as potential anti-COVID-19 drug candidates and their mechanisms of action.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Compound</th><th>Class</th><th>Source</th><th>Biological action/Efficacy</th><th>Experiment</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Inhibiting the SARS-CoV S protein-ACE2 interaction</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Emodin</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Anthraquinone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Rheum palmatum</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Competitive biotinylated ELISA)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">94% inhibition at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (IFA)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Luteolin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Rhodiola kirilowii</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free and cell-based assay (FAC/MS and Luciferase assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Allium cepa</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;83.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tetra-O-galloyl-<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-<sc>d</sc>-glucose (TGG)</td><td align="left">Tannin</td><td align="left"><italic>Galla chinensis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free and cell-based assay (FAC/MS and Luciferase assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Inhibiting the endocytic machinery</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1-cinnamoyl-3,11-dihydroxy meliacarpin</td><td align="left">Terpenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Melia azedarach</italic></td><td align="left">increased endolysosomal pH (EC of 7.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (AO staining)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">25-O-acetyl-7,8-didehydrocimigenol 3-O-beta-<sc>d</sc>-xylopyranoside (ADCX)</td><td align="left">Terpenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Cimicifugae rhizoma</italic></td><td align="left">inhibited degradation activity by decreasing cathepsin expression, but not endolysosomal acidity (EC of 24&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (AO staining, DQ-BSA staining and WB)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Alantolactone</td><td align="left">Sesquiterpene lactone</td><td align="left"><italic>Inula helenium</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">neutralized endo-lysosomal pH and reducing the expression and activity of cathepsins (EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoTracker Red and AO staining, WB and Cathepsin activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr"><sup>76</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cleistanthin A</td><td align="left">Lignan glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Cleistanthus collinu</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the activity of V-type ATPase and elevated endolysosomal pH (EC of 0.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (pH sensitive fluorescent probe/LysoTracker Red staining and V-type ATPase activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr"><sup>77</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr"><sup>78</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cleistanthoside A tetraacetate</td><td align="left">Lignan glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Phyllanthus taxodiifolius</italic> Beille <xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">neutralized endolysosomal acidity and decreased the activity of V-type ATPase (EC of 50&#x000a0;nM)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoTracker Red staining and V-type ATPase activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr"><sup>78</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dauricine</td><td align="left">Alkaloid</td><td align="left"><italic>Rhizoma Menispermi</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">elevated endolysosomal pH, decreased the levels of active cathepsins and inhibited the activity of V-type ATPase (EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoSensor Yellow/Blue staining, WB and V-type ATPase activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Daurisoline</td><td align="left">Alkaloid</td><td align="left"><italic>Rhizoma Menispermi</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">elevated endolysosomal pH, decreased the levels of active cathepsins and inhibited the activity of V-type ATPase (EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoSensor Yellow/Blue staining, WB and V-type ATPase activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diphyllin</td><td align="left">Lignan lactone</td><td align="left"><italic>Cleistanthus collinus</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the activity of V-type ATPase (EC of 0.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (V-type ATPase activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr"><sup>79</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ginsenoside Ro</td><td align="left">Triterpenoid saponin</td><td align="left"><italic>Panax ginseng</italic></td><td align="left">raised endolysosomal pH and downregulating the expression and activity of cathepsins (EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (AO staining, WB and Cathepsin activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr"><sup>80</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Icariside II</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Epimedium koreanum</italic> Nakai</td><td align="left">decreased endolysosomal acidity (EC of 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (AO staining)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr"><sup>81</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Leelamine</td><td align="left">Terpene</td><td align="left"><italic>Pinus sylvestris</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">decreased endolysosomal acidity and inhibited cellular endocytosis (EC of 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoTracker Red staining and Internalization of fluorescent transferrin-A488)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Matrine</td><td align="left">Alkaloid</td><td align="left"><italic>Sophora flavescens Ait</italic></td><td align="left">inhibited endolysosomal acidification and reduced the expression and activity of cathepsins (EC of 2&#x000a0;mM)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoSensor Yellow/Blue, WB and Cathepsin activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Myrtenal</td><td align="left">Terpene</td><td align="left"><italic>Elettaria cardamomum</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the activity of V-type ATPase and reduced endolysosomal acidification (EC of 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (AO staining and V-type ATPase activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Oblongifolin C</td><td align="left">Benzophenone</td><td align="left"><italic>Garcinia yunnanensis</italic> Hu</td><td align="left">inhibited endolysosomal acidification and downregulated the expression and activity of cathepsins (EC of 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (AO staining, WB and Cathepsin activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr"><sup>82</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pulsatilla saponin D</td><td align="left">Triterpenoid saponin</td><td align="left"><italic>Pulsatilla chinensis</italic> (Bunge) Regel</td><td align="left">elevated endolysosomal pH and downregulated<break/>cathepsins (EC of 1.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoSensor Yellow/Blue, WB and Cathepsin activity assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr"><sup>83</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tetrandrine</td><td align="left">Alkaloid</td><td align="left"><italic>Stephania tetrandra</italic> S. Moore <xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">elevated endolysosomal pH in a concentration-dependent manner (EC of 1&#x02013;10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (LysoSensor Yellow/Blue staining)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Inhibiting the SARS-CoV 3CL</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic>pro</italic></bold></sup><bold><italic>activity</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02019;-(3-Methylbut-2-enyl)-3&#x02032;,4,7-trihydroxyflavane</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;30.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">4-Hydroxyderricin</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;81.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;50.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Betulinic acid</td><td align="left">Terpenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Breynia fruticose</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Broussochalcone A</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;88.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Broussochalcone B</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;57.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Broussoflavan A</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;92.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dihydrotanshinone I</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Hesperetin</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoid</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Isatis indigotica</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;60&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (ELISA)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hirsutenone</td><td align="left">Diarylheptanoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Alnus japonica</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;36.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr"><sup>85</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Isobavachalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;39.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isoliquiritigenin</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;61.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr"><sup>86</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kazinol A</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;84.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kazinol F</td><td align="left">Biphenyl propanoids</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;43.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kazinol J</td><td align="left">Biphenyl propanoids</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;64.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Methyl tanshinonate</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Allium cepa</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;52.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr"><sup>87</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-3-b-galactoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Machilus zuihoensis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;42.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr"><sup>87</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr"><sup>88</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rosmariquinone</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Savinin</td><td align="left">Lignoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Chamaecyparis obtuse</italic> var. <italic>formosana</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tanshinone I</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;38.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tanshinone IIA</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;89.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tanshinone IIB</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;24.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Xanthoangelol</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;38.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Xanthoangelol B</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;22.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Xanthoangelol D</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;26.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Xanthoangelol E</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Xanthoangelol F</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;34.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;32.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Xanthokeistal A</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;44.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Inhibiting the SARS-CoV PL</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic>pro</italic></bold></sup><bold><italic>activity</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02032;-O-Methyldiplacol</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02032;-O-Methyldiplacone</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;13.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02032;-O-Methylbavachalcone</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Psoralea corylifolia</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr"><sup>90</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02032;-O-Methyldiplacol</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02032;-O-Methyldiplacone</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">6-Geranyl-4&#x02032;,5,7-trihydroxy-3&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-dimethoxyflavanone</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;13.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Broussochalcone A</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Broussochalcone B</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cryptotanshinone</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Curcumin</td><td align="left">Polyphenol</td><td align="left"><italic>Curcuma longa</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr"><sup>85</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr"><sup>91</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dihydrotanshinone I</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Diplacone</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hirsutanonol</td><td align="left">Diarylheptanoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Alnus japonica</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr"><sup>85</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hirsutenone</td><td align="left">Diarylheptanoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Alnus japonica</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr"><sup>85</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Isobavachalcone</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Psoralea corylifolia</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr"><sup>90</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;13.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isoliquiritigenin</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;24.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr"><sup>86</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kaempferol</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Zingiber officinale</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;16.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr"><sup>92</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kazinol J</td><td align="left">Biphenyl propanoids</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Methyl tanshinonate</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mimulone</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neobavaisoflavone</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Psoralea corylifolia</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;18.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr"><sup>90</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Papyriflavonol A</td><td align="left">Favonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Broussonetia papyrifera</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Psoralidin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Psoralea corylifolia</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr"><sup>90</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Allium cepa</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr"><sup>84</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr"><sup>87</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rubranol</td><td align="left">Diarylheptanoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Alnus japonica</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr"><sup>85</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rubranoside A</td><td align="left">Diarylheptanoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Alnus japonica</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr"><sup>85</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rubranoside B</td><td align="left">Diarylheptanoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Alnus japonica</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr"><sup>85</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tanshinone I</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tanshinone IIA</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tanshinone IIB</td><td align="left">Tanshinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Terrestrimine</td><td align="left">Cinnamic amide</td><td align="left"><italic>Tribulus terrestris</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr"><sup>93</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tomentin A</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tomentin B</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tomentin C</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tomentin D</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tomentin E</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Paulownia tomentosa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr"><sup>89</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xanthoangelol</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xanthoangelol B</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xanthoangelol D</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;19.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xanthoangelol E</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Xanthoangelol F</td><td align="left">Chalcone</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica keiskei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Fluorescence-based deubiquitination)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Inhibiting the SARS-CoV helicase activity</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Myricetin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Camellia sinensis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited ATPase activity of SARS-CoV helicase with IC<sub>50</sub> of 2.71&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Colorimetry-based ATP hydrolysis assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr"><sup>94</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Allium cepa</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited duplex DNA-unwinding activity of SARS-CoV NTPase/helicase with IC<sub>50</sub> of 8.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FRET-based dsDNA unwinding assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr"><sup>95</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Scutellarein</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic></td><td align="left">inhibited ATPase activity of SARS-CoV helicase with IC<sub>50</sub> of 0.86&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (Colorimetry-based ATP hydrolysis assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr"><sup>94</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Increasing intracellular Zn2+</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caffeic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (3-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Catechin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Camellia sinensis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (2-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Catechol</td><td align="left">Phenol</td><td align="left"><italic>Allium cepa</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (2-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Epigallocatechin-3-gallate (EGCG)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoid</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Camellia sinensis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (36-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">increased the uptake of Zn<sup>2+</sup> in both cell (4-fold increase at EC of 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) and liposome model (16-fold increase at EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Fluorescent Zn<sup>2+</sup> indicator) and cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gallic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (8-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Genistein</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Glycine max</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (2-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Luteolin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Rhodiola kirilowii</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (12-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pyrithione</td><td align="left">Organic sulfur compound</td><td align="left"><italic>Allium stipitatum</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (3-fold increase at EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Radioactive Zn<sup>2+</sup> uptake)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr"><sup>96</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Quercetin</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoid</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Allium cepa</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (18-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">increased the uptake of Zn<sup>2+</sup> in both cell (2-fold increase at EC of 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) and liposome model (8-fold increase at EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Fluorescent Zn<sup>2+</sup> indicator) and cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><sub>[62]</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Resveratrol</td><td align="left">Polyphenol</td><td align="left"><italic>Vitis vinifera</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (7.5-fold increase at EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (AAS)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr"><sup>61</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rutin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Morus alba</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (4-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tannic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Camellia sinensis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (12-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Taxifolin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Silybum marianum</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (4-fold increase at EC of 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (using liposome model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x003b2;-thujaplicin (Hinokitiol)</td><td align="left">Terpene</td><td align="left"><italic>Chamaecyparis obtuse</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">increased intracellular Zn<sup>2+</sup> level (3-fold increase at EC of 125&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Radioactive Zn<sup>2+</sup> uptake)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr"><sup>96</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Inhibiting the viroporin 3a activity</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Afzelin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the ion channel activity of SARS-CoV 3a protein (17% inhibition at EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Voltage-clamp method in Xenopus oocyte model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Emodin</td><td align="left">Anthraquinone</td><td align="left"><italic>Rheum tanguticum</italic></td><td align="left">inhibited the ion channel activity of SARS-CoV 3a protein with IC<sub>50</sub> of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Voltage-clamp method in Xenopus oocyte model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr"><sup>97</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Juglanine</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Polygonum aviculare</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the ion channel activity of SARS-CoV 3a protein with IC<sub>50</sub> of 2.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Voltage-clamp method in Xenopus oocyte model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kaempferol</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Zingiber officinale</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the ion channel activity of SARS-CoV 3a protein (18% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Voltage-clamp method in Xenopus oocyte model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kaempferol-3-O-&#x003b1;-rhamnopyranosyl (1&#x000a0;&#x02192;&#x000a0;2) [&#x003b1;-rhamno pyranosyl(1&#x000a0;&#x02192;&#x000a0;6)]-&#x003b2;-glucopyranoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Clitoria ternatea</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the ion channel activity of SARS-CoV 3a protein (32% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Voltage-clamp method in Xenopus oocyte model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tiliroside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Althaea officinalis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">inhibited the ion channel activity of SARS-CoV 3a protein (52% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Voltage-clamp method in Xenopus oocyte model)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left"><bold><italic>Inhibiting the ACE activity</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">25-O-methylalisol F</td><td align="left">Triterpenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Alisma orientale</italic></td><td align="left">Reduced ACE and AT1R protein expression (&#x0223c;30% and &#x0223c;10% inhibition at EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (WB analysis)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr"><sup>98</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">3,5-dihydroxy-4- methoxybenzoic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Tamarix hohenackeri</italic></td><td align="left">46.2% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;mg/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr"><sup>99</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02032;-hydroxy Pd-C-III</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02032;-methoxy Pd&#x02013;C&#x02013;I</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;16&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ampleopsin C</td><td align="left">Stilbenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Vitis thunbergii</italic> var. <italic>Taiwanian</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;18.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr"><sup>101</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Apigenin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Adinandra nitida</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">30.3% inhibition at EC of 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr"><sup>102</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Asparaptine</td><td align="left">Organic sulfur compound</td><td align="left"><italic>Asparagus officinalis</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;113&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (3HB-GGG hydrolysis assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr"><sup>103</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caffeic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr"><sup>71</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Camellianin A</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Adinandra nitida</italic></td><td align="left">30.2% inhibition at EC of 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr"><sup>102</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Camellianin B</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Adinandra nitida</italic></td><td align="left">40.7% inhibition at EC of 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr"><sup>102</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Carlinoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Desmodium styracifolium</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;33.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr"><sup>104</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Catechin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;109&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chlorogenic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr"><sup>71</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chrysin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;146&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chrysoeriol</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Tamarix hohenackeri</italic></td><td align="left">57.6% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;mg/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr"><sup>99</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Coretincone</td><td align="left">Phenolic glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Coreopsis tinctoria</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;228&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr"><sup>106</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Curcumin</td><td align="left">Polyphenol</td><td align="left"><italic>Curcuma longa</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">76.9% inhibition at EC of 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr"><sup>107</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cyanidin-3-O-glucoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;174&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cyanidin-3-O-galactoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;206&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cyanidin-3-O-rhamnosdie</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;114&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cyanidin-3-O-sambubioside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Hibiscus sabdariffa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;117.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr"><sup>108</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cyanidin-3-O-&#x003b2;-glucoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Rosa damascena</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;138.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr"><sup>109</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Decursidin</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)-trans-Decursidinol</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Decursinol</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;18.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Delphinidin-3-O-sambubioside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Hibiscus sabdariffa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;141.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr"><sup>108</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Epicatechin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;73&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gallic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Tamarix hohenackeri</italic></td><td align="left">43.1% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;mg/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr"><sup>99</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gluco-aurantioobtusin</td><td align="left">Anthraquinone glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Cassia tora</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;30.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr"><sup>110</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)-Hopeaphenol</td><td align="left">Stilbenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Ampelopsis brevipedunculata</italic> var. <italic>hancei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isoferulic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Tamarix hohenackeri</italic></td><td align="left">30.6% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;mg/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr"><sup>99</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isoquercetrin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Tropaeolum majus</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">Reduced plasmatic ACE activity in SHR rats (43% inhibition at EC of 10&#x000a0;mg/kg)</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr"><sup>111</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isorutarine</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;68.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Junipediol A-8-O-&#x003b2;-d-glucoside</td><td align="left">Phenylpropa-noid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Apium graveolens</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;210&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr"><sup>112</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(<italic>S</italic>)-Malic acid 1&#x02032;-O-&#x003b2;-gentiobioside</td><td align="left">Organic acid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Lactuca sativa</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;27.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr"><sup>113</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mangiferin</td><td align="left">Xanthone glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Swertia chirayita</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">31.5% inhibition at EC of 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr"><sup>114</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Miquelianin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Cuphea glutinosa</italic></td><td align="left">32.1% inhibition at EC of 100&#x000a0;ng/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib115" ref-type="bibr"><sup>115</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>N</italic><sup>1</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>4</sup>,<italic>N</italic><sup>8</sup>-tris (dihydrocaffeoyl)spermidine</td><td align="left">Polyamine</td><td align="left"><italic>Solanum quitoense</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.6&#x000a0;ppm</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (3HB-GGG hydrolysis assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr"><sup>116</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Methyl gallate</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Tamarix hohenackeri</italic></td><td align="left">35.7% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;mg/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr"><sup>99</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Naringenin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;78&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Onopordia</td><td align="left">Polyphenol</td><td align="left"><italic>Onopordum acanthium L.</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr"><sup>117</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr"><sup>118</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Orotic acid</td><td align="left">Organic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Daucus carota</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">40.3% inhibition at EC of 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib119" ref-type="bibr"><sup>119</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pd&#x02013;C&#x02013;I</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pd-C-II</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pd-C-III</td><td align="left">Coumarin</td><td align="left"><italic>Angelica decursiva</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr"><sup>100</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Quercetin</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;151&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tamarix hohenackeri</italic></td><td align="left">48.6% inhibition at EC of 20&#x000a0;mg/mL</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr"><sup>99</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-3-O-galactoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;180&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-3-O-glucoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;71&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-3-O-glucuronic acid</td><td align="left">Flavonoid conjugate</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;27&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-3-O-rhamnoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-3-O-rutinoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;90&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-3-O-sulfate</td><td align="left">Flavonoid conjugate</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;131&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Quercetin-4&#x02032;-O-glucoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Malus domestica</italic><sup><italic>(</italic></sup><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;211&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>105</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Schaftoside</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Desmodium styracifolium</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;58.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr"><sup>104</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tannic acid</td><td align="left">Phenolic acid</td><td align="left"><italic>Camellia sinensis</italic><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">(a)</xref></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;230&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib120" ref-type="bibr"><sup>120</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Taxifolin</td><td align="left">Flavonoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Coreopsis tinctoria</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;145.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr"><sup>106</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vicenin 1</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Desmodium styracifolium</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub><xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>52.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr"><sup>104</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vicenin 2</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Desmodium styracifolium</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;43.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr"><sup>104</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vicenin 3</td><td align="left">Flavonoid glycoside</td><td align="left"><italic>Desmodium styracifolium</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;46.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr"><sup>104</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">(+)-&#x003b5;-Viniferin</td><td align="left">Stilbenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Vitis thunbergii</italic> var. <italic>taiwanian</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;35.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr"><sup>101</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">(+)-Vitisin A</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Stilbenoid</td><td align="left"><italic>Vitis thunbergii</italic> var. <italic>taiwanian</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (FAPGG degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr"><sup>101</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ampelopsis brevipedunculata</italic> var. <italic>hancei</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td><td align="left">Cell-free assay (HHL degradation assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>3HB-GGG&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3-hydryoxybutyryl-Gly-Gly-Gly; AAS&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Atomic absorption spectrophotometry; AO&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Acridine orange; ATP&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Adenosine triphosphate; DQ-BSA&#x000a0;= Dye quenched-bovine serum albumin; EC&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;The effective test concentration; ELISA&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay; FAC/MS&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Frontal affinity chromatography-Mass spectrometry; FAPGG&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;furylacryloyl-phenylalanyl-glycyl-glycine; FRET&#x000a0;= Fluorescence resonance energy transfer; HHL&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;hippuryl-L-histidyl-<sc>l</sc>-leucine; IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;The half maximal inhibitory concentration; IFA&#x000a0;= Immunofluorescence assay; SHR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;spontaneously hypertensive rat; WB&#x000a0;= WesternBlot.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0015">The study used commercial products. Here provides a natural source of compound as an example.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.2"><label>3.1.2</label><title>The plasma membrane protease TMPRSS2</title><p id="p0150">Recognized as a host trypsin-like serine protease, TMPRSS2 highly expressed in alveolar cells has been demonstrated to facilitate viral entry by priming of viral S protein. Inhibition of TMPRSS2 activity could prevent infection of coronaviruses including MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> Now, several synthetic drugs like camostat mesylate, nafamostat mesylate and bromhexine which are serine protease inhibitors showed potential to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 infection.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> However, on the side of natural products, only few compounds were reported. Xanthoangelol G isolated from <italic>Angelica keiskei</italic> was reported to inhibit a trypsin-like serine protease with its IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;value of 51.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> Notably, <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> cell-based and <italic>in&#x000a0;vivo</italic> experiments are needed to be done for the development of anti-SARS-CoV-2 drugs.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.1.3"><label>3.1.3</label><title>The endocytic machinery</title><p id="p0155">Clathrin-mediated endocytosis has been recognized as the primary cell entry route for multiple coronaviruses, including new emerging SARS-CoV-2, by utilizing the binding of viral S protein to host receptor ACE2 molecule.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> After endocytosis into the target cell, the viral particle undergoes the cleavage of S protein mediated by a pH-dependent cysteine protease cathepsin L at an acidic endolysosomal pH (&#x0223c;3.0&#x02013;6.5), which finally triggers membrane fusion between virus and endosome, followed by release of viral genetic material into the cytoplasm. Hence, targeting endocytic pathway-associated proteins are considered to be one of promising strategies for inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 entry.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> Following this idea, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref> summarizes natural compounds that have been reported with inhibitory effects on the vacuolar-type H<sup>+</sup>-ATPase (V-ATPase) activity, the expression and activity of cathepsins, or an increasing effect on lysosomal pH, which lead to impaired acidification and protein degradation of intracellular vesicles like endolysosome. Our search revealed that terpenes/terpenoids<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> and alkaloids<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> are two major classes of compounds acting through this strategy. In addition to individual compounds, some crude plant extracts have shown their potential for being developed as an anti-COVID-19 drug. The traditional Japanese herbal formulation named Maoto, prepared from a mixture of four plants (<italic>Ephedrae herba</italic>, <italic>Armeniacae semen</italic>, <italic>Cinnamomi cortex</italic> and <italic>Glycyrrhizae radix</italic>), was recently shown to inhibit endolysosomal acidification.<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> Zhuang et&#x000a0;al. also demonstrated that butanol crude fraction from <italic>C.&#x000a0;cortex</italic> was able to inhibit the clathrin-dependent endocytosis pathway as well as the infection of SARS-CoV using cell-based assays.<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Natural bioactive compounds targeting viral replication</title><sec id="sec3.2.1"><label>3.2.1</label><title>The 3-chymotrypsin-like main protease (3CL<sup>pro</sup>)</title><p id="p0160">The 3CL<sup>pro</sup> is an enzyme that plays important role in replication of coronaviruses. It is responsible for the cleavage of polyproteins to functional proteins. Base on the protein structures, 3CL<sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 show similarity of amino acid sequence at 96%, and both enzymes exhibit high conservation of active residues.<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> Therefore, small molecules with SAR-CoV 3CL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitory activity may also inhibit 3CL<sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV-2. Numerous studies have revealed for plant and mushroom derived natural compounds that could suppress SARS-CoV replication by blocking 3CL<sup>pro</sup> activity with IC<sub>50</sub> range from 8.3 to 92.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M in either cell-free or cell-based assays. Among them, hesperetin, a phenolic compound isolated from <italic>Isatis indigotica</italic> root exhibited the greatest inhibitory activity against SARS-CoV 3CL<sup>pro</sup> (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) in an African green monkey kidney (Vero) cell line and this effective dose did not toxic to the cells (CC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.7&#x000a0;mM).<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> Other phytochemical classes that have shown promise in the inhibition of this enzyme are lignoid, terpenoid, tanshinone and chalcone with IC<sub>50</sub> less than 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> Interestingly, the lignoid savinin was able to reduce both viral replication (Selective index&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;667) and cytopathic effect on SARS-CoV-infected Vero E6 cells.<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> The summary of bioactive compounds against SARS-CoV 3CL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitory activity is tabulated in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. Regarding to the similarity between 3CL<sup>pro</sup> of SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2, these natural compounds are interesting substances to screen as inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2 3CL<sup>pro</sup> activity furthermore.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.2"><label>3.2.2</label><title>The papain-like protease (PL<sup>pro</sup>)</title><p id="p0165">Similar to 3CL<sup>pro</sup>, the function of PL<sup>pro</sup> is essential for coronavirus replication by generating RTC through proteolytic processing of viral polyprotein. Hence, PL<sup>pro</sup> could be served as another attractive target of drug discovery for treatment of coronavirus infection, especially SARS-CoV-2. At present, there is no FDA approved PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor available, therefore identification of bioactive compounds from medicinal plants that specifically inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup> has been focused to develop a new class of anti-coronavirus drug. According to high similarity of protein sequences and active residues between SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup> (83%),<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref> the compounds that have been reported as inhibitors of SARS-CoV PL<sup>pro</sup> may also be effective against SARS-CoV-2. <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref> lists many interesting compounds from natural sources that exhibited SARS-CoV PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitory activity. The IC<sub>50</sub> values of the compounds ranged from 0.8 to 19.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, demonstrating their strong inhibitory potential. Among them, the cryptotanshinone and tanshinone IIA were regarded as two most excellent inhibitors.<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.3"><label>3.2.3</label><title>The replication/transcription complex (RTC)</title><p id="p0170">The replication of full-length genomic RNA and the discontinuous transcription of subgenomic RNA transcripts are crucial for the production of new coronavirus particles inside the host cell. Both processes are mediated by the coronavirus RTC composed of multiple viral nsps including two key replicative enzymes like the RdRp (nsp12) and helicase (nsp13),<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref> which are now considered as potential targets for COVID-19 therapy. Considering a strikingly high homology of nucleotide sequence, amino acid sequence and protein structure between SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 RdRp,<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref> the natural compounds with previous reports of inhibitory activities towards RdRp of SARS-CoV could also have the potential to suppress the activities of those enzymes of the SARS-CoV-2. It was shown that the water extract from <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic> exhibited a dose-dependent inhibition on SARS-CoV RdRp activity with the highest decrease by 74% in the treatment of 800&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL.<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref> That activity of <italic>H.&#x000a0;cordata</italic> was confirmed in another study by Fung et&#x000a0;al., along with <italic>Sinomenium acutum</italic>, <italic>Coriolus versicolor</italic>, <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> and a traditional Chinese herbal formula Kwan Du Bu Fei Dang. Their IC<sub>50</sub> values were 251.1, 198.6, 108.4, 41.9 and 471.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively.<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> The inhibitors of SARS-CoV helicase also serve as a potential drug candidate since this enzyme has a highly conserved sequence among coronaviruses and shares the similar structure to that of SARS-CoV-2.<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref> Herein, three plant-derived bioactive compounds that could be natural inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2 helicase are listed in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.4"><label>3.2.4</label><title>The zinc ion</title><p id="p0175">Zinc is an essential micronutrient that is required for various cellular metabolic processes, not only in human immunity but also in the replication of many viruses.<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref> Although Zinc ion (Zn<sup>2+</sup>) acts as a cofactor for several important viral enzymes such as RdRp, 3CL<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>, it is interesting that its high intracellular concentration was found to inhibit those enzyme activities of a variety of RNA viruses including SARS-CoV,<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> thus leading to subsequent decrease in the production of new virions. Therefore, Zn<sup>2+</sup> possesses antiviral properties through generating host immune responses and inhibiting viral replication. As of now, several researchers have suggested the use of Zn<sup>2+</sup> ionophore, a compound that stimulates cellular import of Zn<sup>2+</sup> (e.g., chloroquine and its derivatives), as a possible option for the treatment of COVID-19.<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> In <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>, we summarized some natural compounds with Zn<sup>2+</sup> ionophore activity. The most promising compound is epigallocatechin-3-gallate (EGCG), followed by quercetin, luteolin, tannic acid and resveratrol.<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Natural bioactive compounds targeting viral release</title><sec id="sec3.3.1"><label>3.3.1</label><title>The viroporin 3a</title><p id="p0180">The viroporins are small, pore-forming, viral-encoded accessory proteins with ion channel activity that have been known to play an essential role in mediating several processes in the life cycle of many viruses, including coronaviruses.<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> Viroporin 3a functions are strongly involved in the regulation of viral budding and release from infected cells.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Interestingly, this protein was found unique to SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 and not present in other known coronaviruses,<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref> thus the viroporin 3a protein can be an important potential therapeutic target for COVID-19. Summary of natural compounds with inhibitory effect on viroporin 3a activity is presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. Schwarz et&#x000a0;al. revealed that flavonoid compounds like kaempferol and its derivatives were capable of blocking the ion channel activity of SARS-CoV viroporin 3a protein. Among them, the most potent one is the glycoside juglanine, kaempferol 3-O-&#x003b1;-<sc>l</sc>-arabinopyranoside, exhibiting IC<sub>50</sub> of 2.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M.<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref> Another kaempferol glycoside tiliroside and the anthraquinone emodin also showed good inhibitory activity with and IC<sub>50</sub> of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M.<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Natural bioactive compounds targeting inflammation-related pathogenesis</title><p id="p0185">Upon binding to SARS-CoV-2 S protein, the ACE2 function is downregulated which leads to increased angiotensin II level and overactivation of the AT1R signaling, causing the deleterious effects associated with excessive inflammation on several tissues.<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr"><sup>67</sup></xref> Therefore, suppressing angiotensin II production by ACE inhibitors and blocking of AT1R by angiotensin-receptor blockers (ARBs) may be of benefit to ameliorate Ang II/AT1R-mediated inflammation in COVID-19 patients. Moreover, it was shown that an ARB could not only reduce AT1R activation, but also activate the AT2R, thus resulting in a production of vasodilation benefit.<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr"><sup>68</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0190">Currently, ACE inhibitors and ARBs are commonly prescribed in COVID-19 patients with severe symptoms. Even though risks of the use of hypertensive drugs were concerned, accumulating evidence has not suggested the association between the drugs and worse clinical outcomes.<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr"><sup>69</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr"><sup>70</sup></xref> Interestingly, a great number of natural compounds have been identified as potent ACE inhibitors and ARBs. Given that there are minimal side effects of using drugs from natural sources, those compounds with potential activity should be considered and investigated. Bioactive compounds derived from natural sources which possess ACE inhibitory activity are summarized in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. Among them, the excellent inhibitory properties against ACE were exerted by the phenolic caffeic acid and chlorogenic acid, and the stilbenoid hopeaphenol and vitisin A, with IC<sub>50</sub> less than 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M.<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr"><sup>71</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref> These two stilbenoids were also found to be resveratrol tetramers exhibiting multifaceted properties including anti-inflammation<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr"><sup>73</sup></xref> and antiviral infection as a potent inhibitor of hepatitis C virus helicase.<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr"><sup>74</sup></xref> However, only few compounds have shown the ability to block AT1R which one of them is [6]-gingerol, the major bioactive compounds present in <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>. According to the report by Liu and colleagues, it could inhibit AT1R activity with IC<sub>50</sub> of 8.2 &#x003bc;M as detected by cell-based calcium mobilization assay.<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr"><sup>75</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Anti-SARS-CoV natural compounds with unidentified mechanism of action</title><p id="p0195">Some natural occurring compounds have been reported their beneficial effect to inhibit SARS-CoV, even though their mechanisms of action have not yet been identified (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>
). Accordingly, the compounds from those previous studies might also have a potency to inhibit COVID-19 infection. Using HIV/SARS-CoV S pseudovirus and wild-type SARS-CoV, three anthocyanins derived from <italic>Cinnamomi cortex,</italic> cinnamtannin B1, procyanidin A2 and procyanidin B1, were reported their inhibitory activities against the infection of both viruses, but at least not through the inhibition of clathrin-mediated endocytosis.<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> This study also investigated the effects of some crude plant extracts and found that aqueous extract of <italic>Caryophylli Flos</italic> exhibited moderate inhibition to pseudovirus (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;58.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) and wild-type virus (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;50.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M).<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref> In addition, the natural alkaloid lycorine, isolated from <italic>Lycoris radiate,</italic> has been suggested as an anti-SARS-CoV compound with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 15.7&#x000a0;nM.<xref rid="bib121" ref-type="bibr"><sup>121</sup></xref>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>List of anti-SARS-CoV compounds from natural sources with unidentified mechanism of action.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Compound</th><th>Class</th><th>Source</th><th>Biological action/Efficacy</th><th>Experiment</th><th>Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Cinnamtannin B1</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoid</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Cinnamomi cortex</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;32.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (HIV/SARS-CoV S pseudovirus)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;32.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (Wild-type SARS-CoV)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Plaque reduction assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lycorine</td><td align="left">Crystalline alkaloid</td><td align="left"><italic>Lycoris radiata</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15.7&#x000a0;nM</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (CPE/MTS assay)</td><td align="left"><xref rid="bib121" ref-type="bibr"><sup>121</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Procyanidin A2</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoid</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Cinnamomi cortex</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;120.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (HIV/SARS-CoV S pseudovirus)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;29.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (Wild-type SARS-CoV)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Plaque reduction assay)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Procyanidin B1</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">Flavonoid</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Cinnamomi cortex</italic></td><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;161.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (HIV/SARS-CoV S pseudovirus)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Luciferase reporter assay)</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;41.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (Wild-type SARS-CoV)</td><td align="left">Cell-based assay (Plaque reduction assay)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0025"><p>CPE/MTS&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;cytopathic effect-based MTS reduction; IC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;the half maximal inhibitory concentration.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0030"><p><sup>(a)</sup> The study used commercial products. Here provides a natural source of compound as an example.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion and further prospects</title><p id="p0200">Emerged as the most devastating viral infection in this era for the human race, the COVID-19 pandemic has introduced &#x0201c;new normal&#x0201d; for changing life as we recognize it. As numbers of new COVID-19 infected cases are rising globally, disruption of the transmission chain to minimize this spread is seriously unavoidable. This rise in COVID-19 infection is hardly disrupted unless its infective mechanisms including entry, replication and release, and modification of RAAS can be properly eliminated by humans. Certainly, we are waiting for effective strategies including drugs and vaccines to fight against COVID-19. Due to the unavailability of drugs to treat this infection, natural compounds are a main area of anti-COVID-19 research discovery. Our review suggests that 24 natural compounds have showed their potential actions on multiple therapeutic targets, which should be further explored for anti-COVID-19 plant/mushroom-based medicines (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>
). The classes of these phytochemical compounds include chalcones (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7), flavonoids (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5), tanshinones (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5), phenolic acids (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3), polyphenol (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1), anthraquinone (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1), diarylheptanoid (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1) and biphenylpropanoid (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1). Among them, a natural flavonoid quercetin is found as a lead candidate with its ability on the virus side to inhibit SARS-CoV S protein-ACE2 interaction, viral protease and helicase activities, as well as on the host cell side to inhibit ACE activity and increase intracellular zinc level, thus making it very promising to reduce the disease burden. Although it is previously speculated that certain ACE inhibitors with an increased activity of ACE2 receptor may indeed enhance viral infectivity, recent studies revealed no substantial association between increased risks of infection and ACE inhibitor medications.<xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr"><sup>69</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr"><sup>70</sup></xref> Therefore, it is worth noting that many potential mechanisms of anti-COVID-19 natural agents are required to carefully and substantially investigated. Together with proper proactive investments, it is our great hope that qualified natural compound-based medicines from promising leads described here will be developed as anti-COVID-19 soon to benefit the human race in this &#x0201c;new normal&#x0201d; era.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Chemical structures of natural compounds with potential antiviral properties against multiple therapeutic targets for COVID-19.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig.&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Taxonomy (classification by EVISE)</title><p id="p0205">Emerging Infectious Disease, Viral Infection of Respiratory System, Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus, Cell culture, Molecular Biology, Traditional herbal medicine, Natural Product Analysis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0210">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Who</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Novel Coronavirus &#x02013; China</chapter-title><year>2020</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/csr/don/12-january-2020-novel-coronavirus-china/en/" id="intref0010">https://www.who.int/csr/don/12-january-2020-novel-coronavirus-china/en/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><volume>382</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31978945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><issue>10223</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of 138 hospitalized patients with 2019 novel coronavirus-infected pneumonia in wuhan, China</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Am Med Assoc</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;rapid advice guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) infected pneumonia (standard version)</article-title><source>Mil Med Res</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32029004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxychloroquine in patients with COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Diabetes Metab Syndr</source><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32417708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taccone</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorham</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxychloroquine in the management of critically ill patients with COVID-19: the need for an evidence base</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuzimoto</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isidoro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The antiviral and coronavirus-host protein pathways inhibiting properties of herbs and natural compounds - additional weapons in the fight against the COVID-19 pandemic?</article-title><source>Journal of traditional and complementary medicine</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32691005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panyod</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>C.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>L.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary therapy and herbal medicine for COVID-19 prevention: a review and perspective</article-title><source>Journal of traditional and complementary medicine</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32691006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiviral natural products and herbal medicines</article-title><source>Journal of traditional and complementary medicine</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24872930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS coronavirus entry into host cells through a novel clathrin- and caveolae-independent endocytic pathway</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From SARS to MERS, thrusting coronaviruses into the spotlight</article-title><source>Viruses</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome-associated coronavirus 3a protein forms an ion channel and modulates virus release</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>103</volume><issue>33</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>12540</fpage><lpage>12545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>South</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flynn</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ACE2 (Angiotensin-Converting enzyme 2), COVID-19, and ACE inhibitor and Ang II (angiotensin II) receptor blocker use during the pandemic: the pediatric perspective</article-title><source>Hypertension (Dallas, Tex.: 1979)</source><volume>76</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shete</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urgent need for evaluating agonists of angiotensin-(1-7)/Mas receptor axis for treating patients with COVID-19</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis : IJID : official publication of the International Society for Infectious Diseases</source><volume>96</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>351</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petitjean</surname><given-names>S.J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular interaction and inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 binding to the ACE2 receptor</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>4541</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32917884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain bound to the ACE2 receptor</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>581</volume><issue>7807</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32225176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tortorici</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veesler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural insights into coronavirus entry</article-title><source>Adv Virus Res</source><volume>105</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31522710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farzan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of SARS coronavirus spike receptor-binding domain complexed with receptor</article-title><source>Science (New York, N.Y.).</source><volume>309</volume><issue>5742</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1864</fpage><lpage>1868</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-based discovery of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus fusion inhibitor</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>3067</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24473083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of therapeutic targets for SARS-CoV-2 and discovery of potential drugs by computational methods</article-title><source>Acta Pharm Sin B</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic characterisation and epidemiology of 2019 novel coronavirus: implications for virus origins and receptor binding</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><issue>10224</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32007145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Receptor recognition by the novel coronavirus from wuhan: an analysis based on decade-long structural studies of SARS coronavirus</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Virol</source><volume>94</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wrapp</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cryo-EM structure of the 2019-nCoV spike in the prefusion conformation</article-title><source>Science (New York, N.Y.)</source><volume>367</volume><issue>6483</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1260</fpage><lpage>1263</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure analysis of the receptor binding of 2019-nCoV</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>525</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>140</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamming</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Timens</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulthuis</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lely</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Navis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Goor</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue distribution of ACE2 protein, the functional receptor for SARS coronavirus. A first step in understanding SARS pathogenesis</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Pathol</source><volume>203</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>U.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abokor</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2, ACE2 expression, and systemic organ invasion</article-title><source>Physiol Genom</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><article-title>The COVID-19 RISK and Treatments (CORIST) Collaboration. Use of hydroxychloroquine in hospitalised COVID-19 patients is associated with reduced mortality: findings from the observational multicentre Italian CORIST study</article-title><source>Eur J Intern Med</source><volume>82</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32859477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiang</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emodin blocks the SARS coronavirus spike protein and angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 interaction</article-title><source>Antivir Res</source><volume>74</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16730806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small molecules blocking the entry of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus into host cells</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Virol</source><volume>78</volume><issue>20</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>11334</fpage><lpage>11339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stange</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laufer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naujokat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candidate drugs against SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><year>2020</year><fpage>104859</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32360480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleine-Weber</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 cell entry depends on ACE2 and TMPRSS2 and is blocked by a clinically proven protease inhibitor</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remdesivir and chloroquine effectively inhibit the recently emerged novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) in&#x000a0;vitro</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32020029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maggio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Corsini</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repurposing the mucolytic cough suppressant and TMPRSS2 protease inhibitor bromhexine for the prevention and management of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Pharmacol Res</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>J.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chalcones isolated from Angelica keiskei inhibit cysteine proteases of SARS-CoV</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Enzym Inhib Med Chem</source><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clathrin-dependent entry of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus into target cells expressing ACE2 with the cytoplasmic tail deleted</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Virol</source><volume>81</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>8722</fpage><lpage>8729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17522231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting the endocytic pathway and autophagy process as a novel therapeutic strategy in COVID-19</article-title><source>Int J Biol Sci</source><volume>16</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1724</fpage><lpage>1731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32226290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barquero</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alch&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coto</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Block of vesicular stomatitis virus endocytic and exocytic pathways by 1-cinnamoyl-3,11-dihydroxymeliacarpin, a tetranortriterpenoid of natural origin</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Gen Virol</source><volume>85</volume><issue>Pt 2</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cycloartane triterpenoid ADCX impairs autophagic degradation through Akt overactivation and promotes apoptotic cell death in multidrug-resistant HepG2/ADM cells</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><volume>146</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29074104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzu</surname><given-names>O.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gowda</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leelamine mediates cancer cell death through inhibition of intracellular cholesterol transport</article-title><source>Mol Canc Therapeut</source><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1690</fpage><lpage>1703</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>B.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myrtenal-induced V-ATPase inhibition - a toxicity mechanism behind tumor cell death and suppressed migration and invasion in melanoma</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta Gen Subj</source><volume>1863</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30279148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>C.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural autophagy blockers, dauricine (DAC) and daurisoline (DAS), sensitize cancer cells to camptothecin-induced toxicity</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>8</volume><issue>44</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>77673</fpage><lpage>77684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29100416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrine, a novel autophagy inhibitor, blocks trafficking and the proteolytic activation of lysosomal proteases</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23002236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetrandrine blocks autophagic flux and induces apoptosis via energetic impairment in cancer cells</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>e1123</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24625982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masui</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabeshima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajisaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maoto, a traditional Japanese herbal medicine, inhibits uncoating of influenza virus</article-title><source>Evid base Compl Alternative Med : eCAM</source><volume>2017</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1062065</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Procyanidins and butanol extract of Cinnamomi Cortex inhibit SARS-CoV infection</article-title><source>Antivir Res</source><volume>82</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19428598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalonde</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning from the past: possible urgent prevention and treatment options for severe acute respiratory infections caused by 2019-nCoV</article-title><source>Chembiochem : a European journal of chemical biology</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>F.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-SARS coronavirus 3C-like protease effects of Isatis indigotica root and plant-derived phenolic compounds</article-title><source>Antivir Res</source><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16115693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>C.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>J.-T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific plant terpenoids and lignoids possess potent antiviral activities against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Med Chem</source><volume>50</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>4087</fpage><lpage>4095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17663539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.-N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X.-D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triterpene and sterol derivatives from the roots of Breynia fruticosa</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Nat Prod</source><volume>74</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1161</fpage><lpage>1168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21428418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tanshinones as selective and slow-binding inhibitors for SARS-CoV cysteine proteases</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem</source><volume>20</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>5928</fpage><lpage>5935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22884354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruggiero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Squeglia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maga</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berisio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;structural view of SARS-CoV-2 RNA replication machinery: RNA synthesis, proofreading and final capping</article-title><source>Cells</source><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalonde</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning from the past: possible urgent prevention and treatment options for severe acute respiratory infections caused by 2019-nCoV</article-title><source>Chembiochem : a European journal of chemical biology</source><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32022370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koon</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunomodulatory and anti-SARS activities of Houttuynia cordata</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>118</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18479853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunomodulatory activities of the herbal formula Kwan Du Bu Fei Dang in healthy subjects: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</article-title><source>Hong Kong medical journal&#x000a0;= Xianggang yi xue za zhi.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Obeid</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlenstiel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlenstiel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of zinc in antiviral immunity</article-title><source>Advances in nutrition (Bethesda, Md</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>710</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>te Velthuis</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Worm</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hemert</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zn(2+) inhibits coronavirus and arterivirus RNA polymerase activity in&#x000a0;vitro and zinc ionophores block the replication of these viruses in cell culture</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>6</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2010</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1001176</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc salts block hepatitis E virus replication by inhibiting the activity of viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Virol</source><volume>91</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Idid</surname><given-names>S.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can Zn Be a critical element in COVID-19 treatment?</article-title><source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clergeaud</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabbagh-Bazarbachi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Larrea</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Sullivan</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;simple liposome assay for the screening of zinc ionophore activity of polyphenols</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><volume>197</volume><issue>Pt A</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>923</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26617034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoene</surname><given-names>N.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of resveratrol and zinc on intracellular zinc status in normal human prostate epithelial cells</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source><volume>297</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>C632</fpage><lpage>C644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19553565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dabbagh-Bazarbachi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clergeaud</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quesada</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Sullivan</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Larrea</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zinc ionophore activity of quercetin and epigallocatechin-gallate: from Hepa 1-6 cells to a liposome model</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>62</volume><issue>32</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>8085</fpage><lpage>8093</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25050823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sze</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral membrane channels: role and function in the virus life cycle</article-title><source>Viruses</source><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>3261</fpage><lpage>3284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26110585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a novel protein 3a from severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><volume>565</volume><issue>1-3</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15135062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kaempferol derivatives as antiviral drugs against the 3a channel protein of coronavirus</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><volume>80</volume><issue>2-3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24458263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><series>Coronaviral Ion Channels as Target for Chinese Herbal Medicine</series><volume>vol. 3</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><comment>1</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Panikar</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective role of ACE2 and its downregulation in SARS-CoV-2 infection leading to Macrophage Activation Syndrome: therapeutic implications</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><volume>256</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>117905</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32504757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cracowski</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouhanick</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system and COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>Ann Endocrinol</source><volume>81</volume><issue>2-3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mancia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rea</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludergnani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apolone</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system blockers and the risk of covid-19</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulgarin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system inhibitors and risk of covid-19</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant, antidiabetic, and antihypertensive properties of echinacea purpurea flower extract and caffeic acid derivatives using in&#x000a0;vitro models</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Med Food</source><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28061036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerksen</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening and profiling stilbene-type natural products with angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitory activity from Ampelopsis brevipedunculata var. hancei (Planch.) Rehder</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Pharmaceut Biomed Anal</source><volume>108</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mi Jeong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davaatseren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitisin A suppresses LPS-induced NO production by inhibiting ERK, p38, and NF-kappaB activation in RAW 264.7 cells</article-title><source>Int Immunopharm</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>323</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a resveratrol tetramer as a potent inhibitor of hepatitis C virus helicase</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><volume>173</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26445091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[6]-gingerol: a novel AT&#x02081; antagonist for the treatment of cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><volume>79</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23479389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alantolactone induces apoptosis and improves chemosensitivity of pancreatic cancer cells by impairment of autophagy-lysosome pathway via targeting TFEB</article-title><source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source><volume>356</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30086361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref77"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cleistanthin A inhibits the invasion and metastasis of human melanoma cells by inhibiting the expression of matrix metallopeptidase-2 and -9</article-title><source>Oncology letters</source><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>6217</fpage><lpage>6223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29113270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and identification of cytotoxic diphyllin glycosides as vacuolar H(+)-ATPase inhibitors</article-title><source>Eur J Med Chem</source><volume>82</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24929344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref79"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of diphyllin as a novel V-ATPase inhibitor on TE-1 and ECA-109 cells</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29328465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of autophagosome-lysosome fusion by ginsenoside Ro via the ESR2-NCF1-ROS pathway sensitizes esophageal cancer cells to 5-fluorouracil-induced cell death via the CHEK1-mediated DNA damage checkpoint</article-title><source>Autophagy</source><volume>12</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>1613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27310928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref81"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Icariside II-induced mitochondrion and lysosome mediated apoptosis is counterbalanced by an autophagic salvage response in hepatoblastoma</article-title><source>Canc Lett</source><volume>366</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref82"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The natural compound oblongifolin C inhibits autophagic flux and enhances antitumor efficacy of nutrient deprivation</article-title><source>Autophagy</source><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>736</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24642486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref83"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic anti-breast cancer effect of pulsatilla saponin D and camptothecin through interrupting autophagic-lysosomal function and promoting p62-mediated ubiquitinated protein aggregation</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref84"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuk</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of polyphenols from Broussonetia papyrifera as coronavirus protease inhibitors</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Enzym Inhib Med Chem</source><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>512</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref85"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diarylheptanoids from Alnus japonica inhibit papain-like protease of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2012</year><comment>b12-00623</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref86"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grenier</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative evaluation of two structurally related flavonoids, isoliquiritigenin and liquiritigenin, for their oral infection therapeutic potential</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Nat Prod</source><volume>74</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1862</fpage><lpage>1867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21866899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref87"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>H.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>I.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.-T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.-H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory and free radial scavenging activities of the constituents isolated from Machilus zuihoensis</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>9451</fpage><lpage>9466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22075574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref88"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Binding interaction of quercetin-3-&#x003b2;-galactoside and its synthetic derivatives with SARS-CoV 3CLpro: structure&#x02013;activity relationship studies reveal salient pharmacophore features</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem</source><volume>14</volume><issue>24</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>8295</fpage><lpage>8306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17046271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref89"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis-Long</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geranylated flavonoids displaying SARS-CoV papain-like protease inhibition from the fruits of Paulownia tomentosa</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem</source><volume>21</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>3051</fpage><lpage>3057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23623680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref90"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis-Long</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic phytochemical displaying SARS-CoV papain-like protease inhibition from the seeds of Psoralea corylifolia</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Enzym Inhib Med Chem</source><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref91"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baratella</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magnetic purification of curcumin from Curcuma longa rhizome by novel naked maghemite nanoparticles</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>63</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>912</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25584520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref92"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bankeu</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khayala</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenta</surname><given-names>B.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isoflavone dimers and other bioactive constituents from the figs of Ficus mucuso</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Nat Prod</source><volume>74</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1370</fpage><lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21619045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref93"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis-Long</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Papain-like protease (PLpro) inhibitory effects of cinnamic amides from Tribulus terrestris fruits</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><volume>37</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1021</fpage><lpage>1028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24882413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref94"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of myricetin and scutellarein as novel chemical inhibitors of the SARS coronavirus helicase, nsP13</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem Lett</source><volume>22</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>4049</fpage><lpage>4054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22578462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><label>95</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref95"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the pharmacophore space of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) NTPase/helicase by dihydroxychromone derivatives</article-title><source>Bioorg Med Chem Lett</source><volume>19</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>4538</fpage><lpage>4541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref96"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krenn</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudernak</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holzer</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Kuppeveld</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seipelt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiviral activity of the zinc ionophores pyrithione and hinokitiol against picornavirus infections</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Virol</source><volume>83</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18922875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref97"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emodin inhibits current through SARS-associated coronavirus 3a protein</article-title><source>Antivir Res</source><volume>90</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><label>98</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref98"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel RAS inhibitor 25-O-methylalisol F attenuates epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition and tubulo-interstitial fibrosis by selectively inhibiting TGF-beta-mediated Smad3 phosphorylation</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><volume>42</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29655688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><label>99</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref99"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ACE and platelet aggregation inhibitors from Tamarix hohenackeri Bunge (host plant of Herba Cistanches) growing in Xinjiang</article-title><source>Phcog Mag</source><volume>10</volume><issue>38</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24914275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib100"><label>100</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiotensin-I-Converting enzyme inhibitory activity of coumarins from Angelica decursiva</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>24</volume><issue>21</issue><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib101"><label>101</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref101"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethanolic extracts and isolated compounds from small-leaf grape (Vitis thunbergii var. taiwaniana) with antihypertensive activities</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>60</volume><issue>30</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>7435</fpage><lpage>7441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22762395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib102"><label>102</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref102"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitory activities of ethanol extract and pure flavonoids from Adinandra nitida leaves</article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><volume>48</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1432</fpage><lpage>1438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20738217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib103"><label>103</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref103"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishizawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Top-down targeted metabolomics reveals a sulfur-containing metabolite with inhibitory activity against angiotensin-converting enzyme in Asparagus officinalis</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Nat Prod</source><volume>78</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25922884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib104"><label>104</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref104"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioassay-guided preparative separation of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitory C-flavone glycosides from Desmodium styracifolium by recycling complexation high-speed counter-current chromatography</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Pharmaceut Biomed Anal</source><volume>102</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>281</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib105"><label>105</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasuriya</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupasinghe</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antihypertensive properties of flavonoid-rich apple peel extract</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><volume>135</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>2320</fpage><lpage>2325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22980808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib106"><label>106</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref106"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New phenolic compounds from Coreopsis tinctoria Nutt. and their antioxidant and angiotensin i-converting enzyme inhibitory activities</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib107"><label>107</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref107"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhullar</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupasinghe</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin and its carbocyclic analogs: structure-activity in relation to antioxidant and selected biological properties</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>5389</fpage><lpage>5404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23666006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib108"><label>108</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref108"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ojeda</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez-Ferrer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamilpa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera-Arellano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tortoriello</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of angiotensin convertin enzyme (ACE) activity by the anthocyanins delphinidin- and cyanidin-3-O-sambubiosides from Hibiscus sabdariffa</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>127</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19808084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib109"><label>109</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref109"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flavonoids from the buds of Rosa damascena inhibit the activity of 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme a reductase and angiotensin I-converting enzyme</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>58</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20038104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib110"><label>110</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory activities of Cassia tora and its anthraquinone constituents on angiotensin-converting enzyme</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18803227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib111"><label>111</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref111"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasparotto Junior</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prando</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leme Tdos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms underlying the diuretic effects of Tropaeolum majus L. extracts and its main component isoquercitrin</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>141</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22465728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib112"><label>112</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref112"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simaratanamongkol</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umehara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Panichayupakaranant</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a new angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor from Thai edible plants</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><volume>165</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib113"><label>113</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref113"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagemann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunkel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity-guided discovery of (S)-malic acid 1&#x02019;-O-beta-gentiobioside as an angiotensin I-converting enzyme inhibitor in lettuce (Lactuca sativa)</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>60</volume><issue>29</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>7211</fpage><lpage>7217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22762370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib114"><label>114</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref114"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phoboo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto Mda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic-linked biochemical rationale for the anti-diabetic properties of Swertia chirayita (Roxb. ex Flem.) Karst</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22523004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib115"><label>115</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toson</surname><given-names>N.S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>M.C.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordignon</surname><given-names>S.A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>A.S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyphenols composition from leaves of Cuphea spp. and inhibitor potential, in&#x000a0;vitro, of angiotensin I-converting enzyme (ACE)</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>255</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>112781</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32209389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib116"><label>116</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref116"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forero</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Masatani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coy-Barrera</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spermidine derivatives in lulo (solanum quitoense lam.) fruit: sensory (taste) versus biofunctional (ACE-Inhibition) properties</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>64</volume><issue>26</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>5375</fpage><lpage>5383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27292771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib117"><label>117</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref117"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salehabadi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khajeh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabirmanesh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Biglar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amanlou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors by SPR biosensor and theoretical studies</article-title><source>Enzym Microb Technol</source><volume>120</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>123</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib118"><label>118</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref118"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souri</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziai</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amanlou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation, identification and molecular docking studies of a new isolated compound, from Onopordon acanthium: a novel angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Ethnopharmacol</source><volume>148</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>939</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23743058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib119"><label>119</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref119"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdullah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamarudin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant potential and angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitory activity of orotic acid-loaded gum Arabic nanoparticles</article-title><source>AAPS PharmSciTech</source><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>53</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30617521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib120"><label>120</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al Shukor</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Camp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>G.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitory effects by plant phenolic compounds: a study of structure activity relationships</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Agric Food Chem</source><volume>61</volume><issue>48</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>11832</fpage><lpage>11839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24219111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib121"><label>121</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref121"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of natural compounds with antiviral activities against SARS-associated coronavirus</article-title><source>Antivir Res</source><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15885816</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0215">This work was partially supported by Grant for Research, Ratchadaphiseksomphot Endowment Fund, <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100002873</institution-id><institution>Chulalongkorn University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, Thailand.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d35e4870"><p id="ntpara0010">Peer review under responsibility of The Center for Food and Biomolecules, National Taiwan University.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>