<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-ijms-19-00610" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this study showed that Argan oil and 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil has a protective effect on H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>-induced biochemical changes and histopathological injury in kidney, liver and brain. The results demonstrated that 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium</span>
  <span class="italic">aromaticum</span> essential oil has more antioxidant content than Argan oil. H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> causes significant increase in the lipid parameters, liver enzymes, and blood urea, significant increase in the liver and kidney weight, insignificant increase in the serum creatinine and significant decrease in the total protein and albumin. These H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>-induced biochemical changes have been alleviated with use of 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil or Argan oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition of 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil showed that eugenol and eugenol acetate were the main components, that was in agreement with other studies [
  <a rid="B31-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijms-19-00610">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijms-19-00610">32</a>]. The antioxidant content in 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil is higher than that found in Argan oil. Therefore 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil might be more powerful as an antioxidant than Argan oil, and this property most likely due to the chemical composition of 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil, which is rich in eugenol (87.03%) with a potent antioxidant activity [
  <a rid="B33-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijms-19-00610">33</a>,
  <a rid="B34-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijms-19-00610">34</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The in vivo study demonstrated that H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> given in the drinking water (0.5%) causes significant increase in AST and ALT, decreases total protein and albumin, and an elevation of blood urea levels [
  <a rid="B35-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijms-19-00610">35</a>]. Another study showed that administration of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> (0.1%) in drinking water in rats for 25 weeks induced an increase in the malondialdehyde levels, catalase activity, superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase in organs [
  <a rid="B36-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijms-19-00610">36</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study daily administration of (1%) of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> by gavage significantly increased the levels of LDH, ALT, AST, however, rats receiving H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> with Argan oil or 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil emulsified in Argan oil had lower levels of LDH, ALT and AST in comparison with H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> groups. The increase of ALT and AST is an index of liver damage and alterations of liver function due to the release of these enzymes into the bloodstream from the cytosol [
  <a rid="B37-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijms-19-00610">37</a>,
  <a rid="B38-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijms-19-00610">38</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results also showed that H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> causes a decrease in albumin and total protein levels, but in the treated groups there is a total protection against the diminution of albumin in the group which receives the Argan oil alone and in the group, that receives Argan oil with 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil. However, the protection against the diminution of total protein is better with Argan oil supplemented with 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil than Argan oil alone. The decrease in albumin levels may be due to inflammation or liver failure [
  <a rid="B39-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijms-19-00610">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blood electrolyte (Na
  <span class="sup">+</span>, K
  <span class="sup">+</span>, Cl
  <span class="sup">−</span>) and creatinine levels were not changed significantly during the experiments, but blood urea concentration was significantly increased in the group receiving H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> alone. Blood urea is a waste product of protein metabolism, synthesized in the liver and excreted by the kidney. Therefore, high blood urea could be due to renal damage which was not evident with stable and normal plasma creatinine. Furthermore, the elevated liver enzymes indicate abnormal liver function where low blood urea is expected. Therefore, mechanism of elevated blood urea with the use of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> needs further experiments. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the lipid profile the results showed that H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> causes dyslipidemia with a decrease in the level of HDL-C and an increase in the levels of TC, LDL-C, and VLDL, whereas other groups, which received H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> combined with Argan oil or with Argan oil and 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil, did not show similar dyslipidemia. It is well known that oxidative stress can induce lipid metabolism disorder and lipid peroxidation and this complication can cause many diseases such as cardiovascular diseases [
  <a rid="B5-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijms-19-00610">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the organ weight the results showed that H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> significantly increases the liver and kidney weight and relative weights while it decreases the brain weight and the brain relative weight. This was also observed with the co-administration of H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> with Argan oil. However, co-administration with the 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil and Argan oil did not affect the relative weight of the kidney. The changes in the weights and relative weights of the organs may be due to histopathological changes caused by H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2.</sub>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, the present data showed that H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> induces histopathological changes in the liver, brain and kidney that include dilatation in the central vein, binucleation and inflammation in the liver, congestion in the kidney, and congestion, and hemorrhage in the brain tissue. In the liver, the histopathological changed accompanied by elevation of liver enzymes. The brain is known as the most sensitive organ to oxidative stress because of its high oxygen consumption and low antioxidant content [
  <a rid="B40-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijms-19-00610">40</a>]. The results are in agreement with a recent study reporting that oxidative stress causes congestion and cerebral hemorrhage [
  <a rid="B41-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijms-19-00610">41</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The overproduction of free radicals following the gavage of rats by H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> is most likely the main cause of the histological and biochemical changes, which leads to an imbalance between the oxidant/antioxidant ratio.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the study shows that Argan oil and especially the mixture of Argan oil with 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil can reduce the oxidative stress that is caused by H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub>. This protection is obviously due to the bioactive molecules and antioxidants such as eugenol in clove essential oil and vanillic acid, syringic acid, vitamin E and ferulic acid in Argan oil [
  <a rid="B42-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijms-19-00610">42</a>,
  <a rid="B43-ijms-19-00610" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijms-19-00610">43</a>]. Further studies are needed to identify and characterize the most active materials in Argan oil and 
  <span class="italic">Syzygium aromaticum</span> essential oil that might be suitable to be tested in clinical setting.
 </p>
</sec>
