<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Identification of allelochemicals is of utmost importance for the development of new pesticides, and by now quite a lot of phytotoxic compounds are known. However, despite of all advantages of using natural substances as bioherbicides, there is a number of problems that prevent commercial use thereof. First, a relatively low activity associated with a low specificity should be addressed. In contrast to synthetic herbicides, which are usually targeted at a specific stage of metabolism, allelochemicals tend to affect simultaneously many physiological processes, but none of them is extremely affected [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Juglone, which main mode of action is associated with oxidative stress could serve as an exception. Second, allelochemicals are usually present in plants at low concentration and as a rule act synergistically, and a purified allelopathic compound may act on target plants with much higher or much lower strength [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Third, such allelochemicals as essential oils contain dozens of components, which composition and concentrations depend on many factors including season, climate, age, geographic region, plant genetics, etc. [
 <xref rid="B340-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">340</xref>]. Thus, the drawback of preparations based on natural substances could be variability of their composition and accordingly efficiency depending on the state of raw materials. Fourth, the reverse side of bioherbicides environmental friendliness (rapid decomposition) is their relative instability in the environment. Thus, it is most appropriate to use natural allelochemicals as the basis for developing new synthetic herbicides, but their chemical structures are often too complicated, and its synthesis at the industrial scale turns out to be extremely expensive [
 <xref rid="B341-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">341</xref>]. Finally, registration of new products includes very expensive regulatory approval procedures that would not be compensated for by the small profits from the limited use of these pesticides under specific environmental conditions and requirements (for example, in greenhouses or in organic farming) [
 <xref rid="B342-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">342</xref>]. This is very similar to a situation with transgenic plants. The main market share is occupied by crops grown on tens of millions of hectares (soybean, corn, cotton, rapeseed, etc.), while less common plants, such as horticultural plants, are not being commercialized since the cost of their registration would not be compensated for by profit obtained from growthing them.
</p>
