<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The medical use of mints for gastrointestinal affections is present in the works of most philosophers and physicians who came across them, from classical antiquity to present-day medicine. Mints have been consistently referred to as possessing anti-emetic and carminative properties, and being used to facilitate digestion and assist in the treatment of gastrointestinal disorders. Pliny was among the first to document these properties and, quoting Democritus, wrote that mints were a suitable treatment for vomiting [
 <xref rid="B17-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Aëtios of Amida (502–575), a Byzantine physician and writer, credits Kyrillos, the archbishop, with a recipe of a digestive composed of a mixture of plants, including pennyroyal macerated in vinegar [
 <xref rid="B38-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Paulus Aegineta left many references to the digestive benefits of mints. For stomach problems, he advised drinking ‘a draught of juice of endive sprinkled with mint’ or ‘a mixture of juice of kernel, pomegranate and mint’ [
 <xref rid="B31-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Centuries later, Hildegard von Bingen (1098–1179), a German Benedictine abbess and polymath, left many texts about the use of medical plants in her 
 <italic>Physica</italic>. To adding to her theoretical knowledge, she gained practical experience in the use of the plants that she grew in her monastery’s garden. To ease digestion, she advised consuming watermint and spearmint for they ‘warm the stomach’ [
 <xref rid="B39-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Trota, a prominent figure of the medical school of Salerno in the 12th century, was another female healer and medical writer to have contributed to extend knowledge on female healthcare. In her 
 <italic>Trotula</italic>, a famous compendium of texts on women’s medicine, she detailed several recipes involving mints [
 <xref rid="B40-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. For constipation one recipe consisted on cooking mint in honey and water, a beverage that was to be drunk by after bloodletting. Another recipe consisted in a mixture of wild celery, mints, cowbane, mastic, cloves, watercress, madder root, sugar, castoreum, zedoary, and gladden. This mixture was to be made into a very fine powder and be given with wine to relieve abdominal distension caused by trapped gas during pregnancy and the consequent risk of miscarriage. Another mention in the 
 <italic>Trotula, Potio Sancti Pauli</italic> (Saint Paul’s Potion), a potion including horsemint, was made to diverse gastric ailments. With the extended use of mints throughout Europe, several recipes began to appear among the royal apothecaries’ arsenals. For example, a recipe for a plaster made of wheat bread, cumin, wormwood, mint, and rose leaves figures in the long list of medicines to Katherine Neville, Duchess of Norfolk by John Clerk (15th century), king’s apothecary to Edward IV, which represents both the fear of epidemics and the need to correct the excesses of the aristocratic lifestyle [
 <xref rid="B41-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Mint medicines also appear in the apothecary’s list for Anne of Bohemia, first wife of King Richard II. Although the use given to mints in these lists is not specified, the intended treatment of gastrointestinal disorders is probable [
 <xref rid="B42-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
