<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Essential Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Citrus limonum</span> and
   <span class="italic"> Piper nigrum</span> essential oils were obtained commercially in Bellarome, RJ, Brazil commercial Ltda. According to the company,
   <span class="italic"> C. limonum</span> essential oil was obtained from the juice industry peel residue, which was pressed and the oil was washed out with water of the material, while the dried fruit of
   <span class="italic"> P. nigrum</span> was steam distilled for 60 minutes to obtain the essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Analysis by GC/MS</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The crude essential oil was analyzed on a GC-MS QP2010 (SHIMADZU) gas chromatograph equipped with a mass spectrometer using electron impact ionization detection. The gas chromatographic (GC) conditions were as follows: injector temperature: 260°C; detector temperature: 290°C; carrier gas (Helium): flow rate 1 mL/min; and split injection with split ratio 1 : 40. Oven temperature was raised from 60°C to 290°C at a rate of 3°C/min. One microliter of each sample, dissolved in CH2Cl2 (1 : 100 mg/
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L), was injected on a RTX-5 column (i.d. = 0.25 mm, length 30 m, film thickness = 0.25 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m). Mass spectra (MS) were recorded 70 eV and scan rate of 1 scan/s. The retention indices were calculated by interpolation of retention times of the substances to the retention times of a mixture of aliphatic hydrocarbons (C7-C40) (Sigma-Aldrich Corporation, St Louis, MO) analyzed in the same conditions (Van den Dool H. &amp; Kratz). The identification of substances was performed by comparison of their retention indices and mass spectra with those reported in literature [
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. The MS fragmentation pattern of compounds was also checked with NIST mass spectra libraries.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Preparation of the Samples for Acaricidal Test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment was conducted in two phases. Essential oils were tested separately and after mixing were performed at equal concentrations, in 1 : 1 proportions (50%
   <span class="italic"> Citrus limonum </span>and 50%
   <span class="italic"> Piper nigrum</span>). The essential oils of
   <span class="italic"> C. limonum</span> and
   <span class="italic"> P. nigrum</span> were dissolved in an aqueous solution with 2% dimethyl sulfoxide (v/v) as an emulsifying agent, as described by Gazim et al. in [
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>]. Solutions were serially diluted in order to obtain the concentrations of 2.5%, 5%, and 10% (v/v), obtaining a final volume of 5 mL. The emulsifying solution (2% DMSO) was used as the negative control. A control with water was also carried out. Amitraz (2 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL) and Deltamethrin (1 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL) in water were used as positive control. The test was repeated three times in duplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. 
   <span class="italic">Rhipicephalus microplus</span> Ticks for Bioassays
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The engorged females ticks of
   <span class="italic"> R. (B.) microplus</span> were collected from infested animals from a farm of Rio Grande do Sul (Brazil) without history of acaricide use. The tick population was maintained based on artificial infestations on calves at Faculdade de Veterinária from Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul (UFRS), Brazil. All experiments were conducted following the guidelines of the Ethics Committee on Animal Experimentation of UFRS and FEPAGRO. The ticks were thoroughly washed with tap water, dried on filter paper towel, and used in the adult immersion test.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Adult Immersion Test (AIT)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The AIT was performed as described by Drummond et al. [
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>] with minor modifications. The ticks were distributed to groups randomly (20 engorged females per group). The different groups of
   <span class="italic"> R. (B.) microplus</span> were immersed for 1 min in 5 mL of the respective concentrations (2.5%, 5%, and 10%) of
   <span class="italic"> C. limonum </span>and
   <span class="italic"> P. nigrum</span> by placing them directly into a 50 mL Falcon-type tube which was gently agitated at room temperature. In experiments of additive effects we used the ratio 1 : 1 (vol/vol) of each oil, with a final concentration of 2.5%, 5%, and 10%. Ticks were recovered from the solutions and dried and each group was transferred to Petri dish (9 cm diameter, 1,5 cm high), weighed, and kept in BOD incubator at a temperature of 28°C and relative humidity of 70–80% for oviposition. This experiment was performed three times in duplicate. The emulsifying solution (2% DMSO) was used as the negative control, while Amitraz (2 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL) and Deltamethrin (1 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>L/mL) in water were used as positive control. The mortality was observed during 15 days. The dead ticks were diagnosed based on three specific signs and features: increasing cuticle darkness and stopping Malpighian tube movement and hemorrhagic skin lesions. After 15 days, the eggs laid were placed in glass tube, weighed, and observed separately at the same condition of incubation for the next 30 days for visual estimation of hatching rate.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage inhibition of oviposition was calculated as follows.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reproductive index (RI) = average weight of eggs laid (mg)/average weight of females before treatment (g).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Percentage inhibition of oviposition (IO%) = RI of control group − RI of treated group/RI control group × 100.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Statistical Analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were expressed as the mean ± standard error of the mean (SEM). Groups were compared using ANOVA one-way test. A 
   <span class="italic">p</span> value of less than 0.05 was considered significant. Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism 6.0 (GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, USA) software.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The efficacy was assessed by measuring female mortality (%) and the lethal concentrations for 50% (LC50) and 90% (LC90) with their 95% confidence limits (CL) values were estimated by applying regression equation analysis to the probit transformed data of mortality.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
