<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Medicinal herbs have consistently played a significant role in managing various diseases as they are considered as very good resources of therapeutically valuable phytochemicals. Plants are traditionally used throughout the world for various treatments and many drugs have been isolated from them in the form of different extract. In recent years, many researches indicated the utilization of various medicinal plants to treat diseases in a specific part of the body system, such as the nervous system, cardiovascular systems, respiratory systems, digestive systems as well as in different body organs. Cultural and geographical factors of different plant also facilitates the management of various diseases in different forms, such as in the form of crude extracts, whole plants, plant pastes, infusions, etc. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Nutritionally valuable herbal plants are now used simultaneously for both food and medicinal purposes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Various parts of the herb which have been used for the management of diabetes mainly includes leaves, barks, seeds, fruits, stems, flower and in some cases whole plant itself. According to recent studies, 30000 plant species have been utilized for therapeutic intensions over the world and among them 800 plants specifically poses anti-diabetic properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. A certain number of indigenous herbal plants have been evaluated by using several experimental procedures in order to assess their therapeutic efficacy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Herbal medicines are already employed for the treatment of polygenic diseases in developed nations where the expenditure of standard medicines was not totally affordable for general population. Confirmation of hypoglycemic effect of some medicinal plant extracts has been made against second type of diabetes by using human cell lines and animal models. Presence of the components like polysaccharides, peptidoglycans, hypoglycans, glycosides, guanidine, steroids, carbohydrates, glycopeptides, terpenoids and alkaloids with antidiabetics properties have been confirmed in such type of extracts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Continuous investigation on medicinal properties of such extract is also recommended by expert committee members of WHO. In general, total consideration of herbal medicine in present healthcare system is still difficult due to inadequate presence of scientific and clinical evidences related to their effectiveness and safe application. To overcome such condition, necessity is there to perform more clinical practices on herbal drugs through applying various animal models and increasing awareness among common people is also required about ongoing researches related to the field.
</p>
