<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Inflammation is a common pathological phenomenon respective of various diseases. The effects of 
 <italic>Quercus species</italic> on anti-inflammation have been widely studied. Moreno-Jimenez et al. [
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] evaluated the anti-inflammatory activity in HT-29 cells from the leaves infusion of 
 <italic>Q. sideroxyla, Q. durifolia</italic>, 
 <italic>and Q. eduardii</italic>. The results demonstrated that 
 <italic>Q. sideroxyla</italic> decreased the levels of the inflammatory markers COX-2 and IL-8 by modulating the expression of NF-Κb. Besides, studies 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> have shown that triterpenes, isolated from acorns of 
 <italic>Quercus serrata</italic> var. 
 <italic>brevipetiolata</italic>, inhibit nitric oxide (NO) production and other proinflammatory cytokines [
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Moreover, lupeol isolated from white oak leaves (
 <italic>Quercus resinosa, Q. grisea, Q. laeta</italic>, 
 <italic>and Q. obtusata</italic>) was evaluated for their ability to inhibit COX-1 and COX-2 enzymes by the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> colorimetric COX (ovine) inhibitor assay. In this study, lupeol from 
 <italic>Q. obtusata</italic> demonstrated a differential effect to inhibit COX-2 without inhibiting COX-1 [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Additionally, (−)-epicatechin, procyanidin B3, and procyanidin B4 (7) obtained from the bark of 
 <italic>Quercus gilva Blume</italic> presented anti-inflammatory and antioxidative potency. The three compounds showed dose-dependent inhibitory activities on the gene expression of COX-2 and IL-1
 <italic>β</italic> [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Studies conducted by Vázquez-Cabral et al. [
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>] indicate that flavonols such as quercetin glucuronide and kaempferol 3-O-glycoside are glucuronidated by the action of the kombucha consortium and that these metabolites are effective antioxidant and anti-inflammatory agents in human macrophages.
</p>
