<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our findings were consistent with the results of some previous studies
 <sup>[</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>]</sup>. The antioxidative potential of plant extracts can be measured using various 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> assays, and each assay is based on at least one feature of antioxidant activity. The DPPH method is widely used to evaluate the antioxidant capacity of plant extracts. The maximum absorption of DPPH at 517 nm decreases when the stable radical is reduced to the DPPH by accepting an electron or hydrogen atom from an antioxidant
 <sup>[</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>]</sup>. Based on the results, the acetone extract of 
 <italic>A. repens</italic> exhibited the best DPPH scavenging capacity. It is worth mentioning that the type of extracted antioxidants depends on polarity, viscosity, and vapor pressure of the solvents. It has been demonstrated that the fewer viscose solvents can diffuse more easily into the plant pores, leading to the extraction of more diverse bioactive secondary metabolites
 <sup>[</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>]</sup>. In accordance with a number of studies, aqueous acetone is the most appropriate solvent for the high efficient extraction of antioxidant compounds and subsequent antioxidant activity. Zhao 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <sup>[</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>]</sup> have reported that the acetone/water solvent system is highly preferred to acquire the best antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> L. According to Kchaou 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <sup>[</sup>
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 </sup>
 <sup>]</sup>, the extracts obtained using aqueous acetone solvent displayed higher DPPH radical scavenging activity compared to other solvents, which is in agreement with our results.
</p>
