<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">We evaluated the inhibition of the solvent fractions on TNF-α-induced translocation of cytoplasmic p65/NF-κB to the cell nucleus. For this experiment, JIMT-1 cells were seeded (0.1 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> cells/well) in 12-well plates with a round glass cover slip in each of the wells. The cells were then allowed to attach to the cover slips by incubating at 37 °C in the CO
 <sub>2</sub> incubator for 48 h. After incubation, the cover slips were transferred to the wells of another 12-well plate containing 800 μL medium supplemented with 0.1% FBS and then incubated in CO
 <sub>2</sub> incubator for 20 min to stabilize the temperature. The solvent fractions of the medicinal plants were added to the final concentrations of 0.87 μg/mL for the ethyl acetate fraction of 
 <italic>V. leopoldi</italic>, 52 μg/mL for the aqueous fraction of 
 <italic>S. oxyacanthum</italic>, and 80 μg/mL for the chloroform fraction of 
 <italic>C. simensis</italic> and the plates were returned to the incubator for 1 h. Following this, TNF-α (25 ng/mL) was added and incubation continued for another 40 min. Then, the medium was removed, and the cells were fixed in 3.7% formaldehyde in PBS for 15 min and stored at 4 °C in 2 mL PBS. The cells were incubated in blocking buffer (1% bovine serum albumin [BSA] and 1% Tween 20 in PBS) for 1 h at room temperature to prevent nonspecific binding and to permeabilize the cells. Then, rabbit anti-p65/NF-κB primary antibody (ab76311) (Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) (diluted 1:250 in blocking buffer) was added, and the samples were incubated for 1 h at room temperature while being shaken gently. The samples were washed twice with PBS and then Alexa 488 anti-rabbit-conjugated secondary antibody (Molecular Probes, Inc., Eugene, USA) (diluted 1:500 in blocking buffer) was added. The plate was covered with aluminum foil, and the samples incubated for 1 h at room temperature while being shaken gently. Finally, the cover slips were mounted on glass slides using Mowiol as mounting medium (Sigma-Aldrich). The samples were kept at 4 °C and protected from light. The slides were imaged using an Olympus/Nikon epifluorescence microscope (Olympus Optical Co. Ltd., Japan) equipped with a digital camera (Nikon Imaging Japan Inc., Japan). The images were used for counting of the number of cells with positive nuclei in relation to all cells.
</p>
