<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Various herb species have been used worldwide in prevention and treatment of diseases for many centuries. Today, several drugs have been developed from plants that are active against many common diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>]. Among the aromatic plants belonging to the 
 <italic class="italic">Lamiaceae</italic> family, 
 <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>, commonly known as Rosemary, is a flavoured herb which is native to the Mediterranean region and grows in various countries in the world [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>]. The ROEO is a mixture of several major and minor compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>]. Debersac et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>] showed that 1,8-cineole is the major component of Rosemary essential oil, whereas, in other studies α-pinene was the main component, followed by 1,8-cineole, camphene, β-myrcene, borneol and camphor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>]. Essential oils represent an alternative “green “to be used in the cosmetic, pharmaceutical, agricultural and food fields while substituting chemical treatments. Biological activities of essential oils from various plants, including Rosemary, have been attributed to the presence of specific chemical compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. Several studies have demonstrated the antimicrobial [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>], antiproliferative [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>] and antioxidant [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>] activities of the ROEO. The oil of Rosemary is used as a biological preservative of food products [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>] due to its antioxidant and antimicrobial properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
