<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Through the systemic administration, targeted NPs arrive at the destination with the help of the bloodstream. The degradation and drug release of miss-targeted particles may impact the liver or kidney consequently (Chew &amp; Danti, 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). However, the implanted drug-loading materials deliver drugs directly and locally in implanted position, escaping the ‘danger’ in the bloodstream without facing the blood marrow barrier. Some studies revealed that bone metastasis models treated with locally administered ZA obtained a statistically significant increase in bone volume/tissue volume compared with treatment with systemic ZA administration (Nooh et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Ahangar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Local drug delivery systems can further improve drugs’ curative efficiency. These systems rely on implantable biomaterials and implantation operation, maximize the therapy efficiency of drugs, and minimize the toxicity to other organs (Newman &amp; Benoit, 
 <xref rid="CIT0083" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). They can reduce the frequency of drug administration because of a large number of drugs loaded and more sustained release, but run the risk of infection and inflammation after implantation (Sarigol-Calamak &amp; Hascicek, 
 <xref rid="CIT0105" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). When the tumors in bone marrow develop and cause bone destruction, the operation is necessary. After tumor resection, bone grafts are always implanted as a substitute for destroyed bone (Chen, Boda, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), but not enough to inhibit ongoing osteolysis and residual cancer cell proliferation. Therefore, these implanted materials can be modified as multifunctional local drug delivery systems to prevent further bone resorption in subsequent therapy and as bone grafts for the support of the bone function. The implantable materials for lessening osteolysis mainly included scaffolds and porous composite that need to be surgically implanted and locally injected self-assembly hydrogel. Titanium, polymers, calcium phosphate, CS, collagen, hyaluronic acid, alginate were commonly used to fabricate or modify these implantable materials. Solid-state processing (powder metallurgy, sintering of powders and fibers), liquid state processing (direct foaming and spray foaming), vapor deposition, and electrode position were exploited to fabricate porous materials (Sarigol-Calamak &amp; Hascicek, 
 <xref rid="CIT0105" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). 3D-print technology (Do et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0132" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) and electrospinning (Chen, Boda, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) were also employed to fabricate 3D multifunctional scaffolds (Yu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0143" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Porosity, biodegradability, swelling, and mechanical property of materials have an effect on local drug delivery manner (Chen, Boda, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Wu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0136" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).
</p>
