<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Chickpea oil is an adequate model for oxidation study due to is unique fatty acid profile, which is high in polyunsaturated acids (66%), and rich in linoleic (18:2 Δ 9, 12) and monounsaturated oleic (18:1 Δ 9) acids, accounting for 51% and 32%, respectively of the total fatty acids. These percentages are higher when compared to lentils, peas and beans [
 <xref rid="B9-plants-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. PUFAs are highly unstable and prone to deterioration when exposed to external factors such as air, ultraviolet light, temperature and internal factors, such as reactive oxygen species (ROS) and enzymatic activity. Besides the high percentage of PUFAs in chickpea, the high enzymatic activity (lipase and lipoxygenase (LOX)) contributes to lipid deterioration through hydrolysis and oxidation of fatty acids, being thus determinants in the nutritional quality of chickpea oil. Furthermore, chickpea composition changes due to the physiological events during germination. This process modifies the seed nutrient profile in preparation for growth and development of the embryo in a new plant. Among the changes is hormone production (gibberellins (GAs)), which in turn increases the activity of enzymes such as lipases. Lipases are responsible for hydrolysis of triglycerides to produce fatty acids and provide a source of energy and nutrients for the new plant [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The positive effect of selenium on mineral stress during germination over the increase in the activity of antioxidative enzymes has only been reported by [
 <xref rid="B11-plants-08-00113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], who researched the effect of cadmium over 
 <italic class="italic">Brassica napus</italic> seedlings. Chickpea’s oil oxidative stability during germination with selenium stress has not been studied. The main objective of this research was to assess oxidative stability, total phenolics, carotenoids, lipase and LOX activities as well as antioxidant activity of Kabuli chickpea (
 <italic class="italic">Cicer arietinum</italic> L.) oil extracted from sprouts with different amounts of selenium. This is a different approach in the study of selenization to produce functional foods, because the interest is not the final product, but a mechanism aimed to improve oil stability during germination.
</p>
