<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In animal models, BDG is primarily cleared through the liver [
 <xref rid="B102-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Human clinical conditions which result in reduced hepatic function have been shown to be associated with elevated serum BDG. Sanada et al. 2014 have described the relationship between serum BDG levels in the setting of pediatric end stage liver disease [
 <xref rid="B103-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. The liver clearance function was underscored by significantly higher BDG titers in portal blood relative to the peripheral circulation. There was a very significant negative correlation (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) between the pediatric end-stage liver disease patients score and the hepatic clearance of BDG in the transplant patients. Sanada et al. 2012 also described elevated serum BDG in end-stage liver disease patients with and without fungal infections. Of note, median hepatic clearance of circulating BDG was measured as 87.9% [
 <xref rid="B104-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Elevated patient peripheral blood levels of BDG pre-transplant predicted a much longer course of recovery (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and, post-operatively, fungal infections. The peripheral BDG titers in the infected patients were significantly higher than the uninfected patient levels, suggesting the potential of diagnostic utility despite compromised clearance. Recently, Moon et al. 2020 analyzed microbial translocation markers in the blood of hepatitis C virus infected patients [
 <xref rid="B85-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Serum BDG was significantly elevated in hepatic fibrosis (Ishak Score 0–2 and 5–6), relative to controls (Mann–Whitney, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 and 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively). That this may be due to inadequate clearance rather than intestinal translocation is suggested by observations that enhanced microbial translocation was not observed in HCV-infected chimpanzees which do not develop liver fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B105-jof-07-00014" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Thus, hepatic function status is an additional factor to be considered in the evaluation of the significance of circulating BDG titers.
</p>
