<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Microorganisms are responsible for several important infectious diseases, and despite the progress in the development of antibacterial drugs it is still of great urgency to find new antibacterial agents capable of controlling multidrug resistance pathogens [
 <xref rid="B161-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">161</xref>]. Several halophytic grasses are already known to possess antibacterial, antiviral and antifungal activities. For instance, polar extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">C. ciliaris</italic> revealed significant antibacterial and antifungal activities against 
 <italic class="italic">Proteus merabilis</italic> (MIC 0.234 mg/mL), 
 <italic class="italic">Klebsiella pnemoniae</italic> (MIC 1.21 mg/mL) and 
 <italic class="italic">Agerobacterium tumefaciens</italic> (MIC 4.24 mg/mL) [
 <xref rid="B162-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">162</xref>]. Padalia and co-workers [
 <xref rid="B163-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>], through disk diffusion assay, evaluated different extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">S. spontaneum</italic>’s aerial parts and concluded that the petroleum ether, ethyl acetate, acetone, and methanol extracts were active against gram-positive bacteria (inhibition zones of 10.0, 11.0, 12.5 and 10.0 mm, respectively) [
 <xref rid="B163-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>]. Some of the compounds found in 
 <italic class="italic">C. ciliaris</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. spontaneum</italic> are well known for their antimicrobial activity; however, its non-polar nature [
 <xref rid="B164-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">164</xref>] prevent their presence in polar extracts. This allowed us to conclude that only cholest-22-ene-21-ol could be present in the polar extract of 
 <italic class="italic">C. ciliaris</italic> and thus, be responsible for its activity [
 <xref rid="B56-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Therefore, more studies need to be conducted in order to identify the responsible compounds for the reported effects. 
</p>
