<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec31" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thermal analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The thermal analysis data are shown in Table 
  <a rid="Tab8" ref-type="table" href="#Tab8">8</a>. The thermal decomposition of the root powder comes through three common stages. In the first stage, broad and shallow endothermic DTA curve observed at 81.7 °C. In the second stage of decomposition is occurred on the DTA curve at 328.3 °C. A mass loss with a rate of 0.151 mg/min (at 75.9 °C) by heating the sample up to 0.373 mg/min (at 257 °C) is mentioned by the DTG curve. The highest mass loss was indicated in the second stage at 92.7% of TG at 275.7 °C and 1.167 mg/min at 328.3 °C of DTG curve. At this stage, pyrolysis was obtained when the temperature increased from 250 to 380 °C. Lignin decomposition was occurring in the range of 380–500 °C. The residual carbonaceous material in the previous steps was burnt at from 275 to 550 °C presenting an endothermic TG curve. The charred residue was produced by the destruction of low molecular compounds in the third and final stage of decomposition and yielded an ash residue. Finally, no mass loss was detected when the temperature increased from 550 °C to 800 °C. Representative thermo-gravimetric spectrum of the root is shown in additional file (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM6">6</a>: Figure S6).
  <div id="Tab8" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 8</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Results of TG and DTG (mass loss and temperature) of 
     <span class="italic">Anethum sowa</span> L. root powder
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th rowspan="2">Events</th>
      <th colspan="2">TG</th>
      <th colspan="2">DTG</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th>Mass loss (%)</th>
      <th>T
       <sub>onset</sub>-T
       <sub>offset</sub> (
       <span class="sup">O</span>C)
      </th>
      <th>Mass loss (mg/min)</th>
      <th>T
       <sub>onset</sub>-T
       <sub>offset</sub> (
       <span class="sup">O</span>C)
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>First step</td>
      <td char="." align="char">92.7</td>
      <td>T
       <sub>room</sub>-275
      </td>
      <td>0.151</td>
      <td>T
       <sub>room</sub>-75.9
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Second step</td>
      <td char="." align="char">53.3</td>
      <td>276–327</td>
      <td>0.373</td>
      <td>76–257</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Third step</td>
      <td char="." align="char">29.6</td>
      <td>328–358</td>
      <td>1.167</td>
      <td>258–328</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>% Residue</td>
      <td char="." align="char">25.9</td>
      <td>359–550</td>
      <td>-</td>
      <td>-</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
