<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Similar results of the composition of the essential oil were found in India by Chowdhury et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) describing the presence of β-caryophyllene and α-caryophyllene among the main components, but not for α zingiberene. On one hand, another study, also made in India with the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">M. paniculata</italic> leaves, found α-zingiberene and β-caryophyllene as major compounds representing 10% and 9.7%, respectively (Raina et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). On the other hand, the oil obtained in previous study does not show any similarity, since the major components were spathulenol (17.7%) and α-pinene (13.2%) (Li et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Such similarities and differences may be related to differences in climatic conditions of the regions from which the leaves were collected since those studied by Chowdhury et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) and Raina et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>) were collected in India, where the climate is tropical and humid subtropical, similar to the predominant climatic conditions in the region of Brazil where the samples of this study were collected. Furthermore, Li et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) collected the leaves in central China, where a dry continental climate dominates. A previous study reported factors that can alter the production or concentration of secondary metabolites in plants, such as seasonality, circadian rhythm, developmental stage and age, temperature, water availability, UV radiation, soil nutrients, altitude, atmospheric composition and tissue damage (Gobbo-Neto, 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Therefore, its understandable to be found differences in the composition of essential oils collected in different countries.
</p>
