<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cytotoxicity on host cells is a very important criterion for assessing the selectivity of the observed pharmacological activities and must be always included in parallel (Cos et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). The essential oil exhibited an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 63.73 μg/mL for tumourous cells of hepatocytes and IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 195.3 μg/mL for the fibroblasts, resulting in a selectivity index (IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> non-tumourous cells/IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> tumourous cells) equal to 3, which, according to the classification of Suffness and Pezzuto (
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1991</xref>), is good selectivity. The β-caryophyllene showed low cytotoxic effect at the highest concentration tested, 500 μg/mL, causing the death of about 20% of the fibroblasts and 18% of the hepatocytes. The mechanism of action of the essential oils against cancerous cells seems to be different from the mechanism of action of classical chemotherapeutic agent camptothecin presenting more selective cytotoxicity against cancer cells than on normal cells. Sesquiterpenes, such as elemene and 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-bisabolol, are reported to have high selectivity against gliomas (Edris 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). The essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">M. paniculata</italic> obtained in our work is rich in sesquiterpenes, which in previous studies showed antiproliferative action (Bardaweel et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Furthermore, the essential oil presents high quantity of α-zingiberene, which is described as a compound of high antitumour activity by nucleosomal DNA fragmentation (Lee, 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). The high selectivity index of the essential oil qualifies it to be investigated in more detail for use in the treatment of cancer, promoting death of cancer cells and preserving normal cells of death, which is a challenge for the current management of neoplasms (Bayala et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Based on the obtained results in the MTT assay, it was possible to verify that the cytotoxic effect of the essential oil cannot be attributed solely to its main compound, β-caryophyllene, but may represent a synergistic effect among all the components of the oil.
</p>
