<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Materials</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For preparation of 
  <span class="italic">P. roseum</span> essential oil (EO), aerial parts of the plant were collected from a herb garden (Kashan, Iran) during 2014. The identity of the plant was confirmed by professor Rahimian, Sari Agricultural and Natural Resources University (Sari, Iran). By using a Clevenger type apparatus, the essential oil of the plant was obtained by hydrodistillation. Gas chromatographic mass spectrometric (GC-MS) analysis was performed using a Shimadzu GC-9A with helium as the carrier gas on a DB-5 column (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d; film thickness 0.25 mm). GC–MS analysis was carried out on a Varian 3400 GC–MS system with oven temperature set at 40-250°C at a rate of 4°C; transfer line temperature, 260°C; carrier gas, helium with a linear velocity of 31.5 cm/s; split ratio, 1/60; ionization energy, 70 eV; scan time, 1 s: mass range, 40-300 amu.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metronidazole (MTZ), (Alborz daru, Tehran, Iran) was used as a standard antitrichomonal agent. All other chemicals used in the present study were of analytical grade.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Parasites</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span> were recovered by wet mount method from infected native pigeons. Forty native pigeons (6 to 8 weeks old) were purchased from local breeders in Babol city (Mazandaran Province, Iran). By using swabs moistened with saline solution, samples were taken from membranous lesions of oropharyngeal region of suspicious birds. To produce wet smears, swabs were rubbed over the surface of a microscope slide. Smears were then examined under a light microscope at X100 and X400 magnification to confirm 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span> as the causative agent of lesions. Parasite culture was prepared by immersing oral swabs in tryptone/ yeast extract/ maltose (TYM) medium supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (Sigma, Germany) and incubated at 37°C (Sansano-Maestre et al., 2009
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12"> ▶</a>). Cultures were observed over five consecutive days to check the growth of 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span>. Every 48 hr as the parasites in the logarithmic phase of growth presented more than 95% mobility and normal morphology, isolates were sub-cultured (Seddiek et al., 2014
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13"> ▶</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">In vitro</span>
  </span>
  <span class="bold"> assay</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> assay, we used the method described by Munoz et al., 1998 after making slight modifications. To examine the susceptibilities of 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae </span>toward 
  <span class="italic">P. roseum </span>EO and MTZ, sterile multi-well plates were used to incubate the trophozoites with different concentrations of the essential oil and drug dilutions. A volume of 100 µL of culture medium containing 1× 10
  <span class="sup">4</span> parasites was pipetted into each well. Also, prediluted MTZ and 
  <span class="italic">P. roseum </span>EO were added to wells to give final concentrations of 2.5, 5, 10, 20, 50, and 100 μg/mL. Tween 20 (0.01% of final concentration) was used as a solubilizing agent for 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> analysis. Control wells received only Tween 20 without any treatments. Subsequently, to generate anaerobic conditions, a layer of 50 µL of vaseline was added to wells based on the method developed by Munoz et al., 1998. All assays were done three times. The wells were examined using an inverted microscope every 24 hr for 3 successive days. The MIC was the lowest concentration of the drug in the well at which no motile parasite was observed. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">
   <span class="italic">In vivo</span>
  </span>
  <span class="bold"> assay</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The protocol used for the 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> study was in accordance with laboratory animal welfare guide of Pasteur Institute of Iran and has been approved by the ethics committee. Forty native pigeons ( &gt;6 weeks old) were examined and confirmed to be free of 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span> then experimentally infected with Trichomonas by inoculation of 4 × 10
  <span class="sup">4</span> trophozoites prepared in 1 mL of 48-hr culture medium. Seven days post-infection, birds were examined and those that were diagnosed as infected with 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span>, were randomly allocated into 5 groups as follows: the first group (CON) were infected but not medicated, EO 25 and EO 50 were the groups infected with 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span> and medicated with 25 and 50 mg/kg of 
  <span class="italic">P. roseum</span> essential oil, respectively. MTZ 25 and MTZ 50 groups were infected with 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span> and medicated with 25 and 50 mg/kg of metronidazole, respectively. All of the treatments were administered orally (PO) for 7 successive days. Birds of different groups were located in separate wire cages and fed with semisolid mixed grains diet in order to prevent starvation due to difficulty in swallowing because of trichomoniasis. The numbers of motile trophozoites recovered from the infected birds, were determined every day for seven consecutive days. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Statistical analysis</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used, followed by Newman Keul’s test as the 
  <span class="italic">post hoc</span> test to evaluate differences among means (SPSS ver. 18). A p value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. The growth inhibition percentage was determined using the following equation: 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">growth inhibition % = (A − B)/A × 100</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where A is the mean number of trophozoites in the control group and B is the mean number of trophozoites in the test group (Seddiek et al., 2014
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13"> ▶</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
