<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The soil moisture index in CLIMEX is used as a proxy for moisture availability, relying on observed correlations between soil moisture and relative humidity and/or rainfall 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Sutherst1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Watt1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Moisture parameters for 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>, not based on soil moisture, such as extended periods of leaf wetness (24 to 48 hours), high levels of rainfall and extended rainfall, have been associated with increased disease in the laboratory 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Tooley2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref> and under natural field conditions 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Davidson1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. These studies and those by Fichtner et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Fichtner1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> on the effect of soil drying on pathogen recovery, were used to infer and refine soil moisture parameter estimates. Extra drying of the substrate for the lower limit for growth (SM0), which was set to 0.2, was allowed for (expressed as a proportion of soil moisture holding capacity, where 1 =  saturation and &gt;1 indicates excess moisture, i.e. run-off). The lower soil moisture value for optimal population growth (SM1) was taken from Brasier and Scott 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Brasier6" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, as modified by Sutherst et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Sutherst3" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref> and subsequently applied by Venette and Cohen 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Venette1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> to 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>. Following iterative sensitivity analyses, the upper soil moisture value for optimal population growth (SM3) from these models was reduced from 3 to a more realistic value of 2, in order to indicate that wet conditions favour 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic> transmission and infection, but recognising that it was possible to have excessive amounts of rainfall and soil moisture.
</p>
