<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the screening process, we tested 109 extracts from 21 plant species for their antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic>, of which 21 extracts from 11 plant species showed MICs ranging from 8 to 128 μg/mL. Other studies also tested alcoholic or aqueous plant extracts on the same 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic> strain (ATCC® 33277) used in our study. For instance, Rosas- Piñón [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] screened 47 plant species from Mexico on 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic> and four species exhibited the best antibacterial activity with a MIC value of 125 μg/mL. Mohieldin, Muddathir [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] evaluated 24 Sudanese plant species on 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic>, and the best plant extract had a MIC value of 250 μg/mL. In a study evaluating Japanese herbal medicine, 27 Kampo formulations were tested on 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic> and the best remedy exhibited an MIC value of 250 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. In South Africa, eight plant species used traditionally for the treatment of oral diseases were examined, and the best extract showed an MIC value of 800 μg/mL [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. More generally, an extract with an MIC value less than 100 μg/mL is considered to have significant antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Therefore, of the 21 extracts tested in our investigation, 20 can be considered as having significant antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic>, and our identification of crude extracts with 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic> MICs as low as 8 μg/mL represents a step forward for the potential of plant-derived treatments for periodontitis.
</p>
