<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> is a member of Lamiaceae and belongs to a clade of New World Mentheae. The closely related genera that share similar morphology and habitat preference with 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> include 
 <italic class="italic">Dicerandra</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Piloblephis</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Stachydeoma</italic> spp., and the woody, southeastern U.S. species of 
 <italic class="italic">Clinopodium</italic> such as 
 <italic class="italic">C. ashei, C. georgianum, C. coccineum</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">C. dentatum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Despite the fact that 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> species are morphologically distinguishable, there are two problems about species status based on morphology. First, 
 <italic class="italic">C. brevifolia</italic> (endangered species) shares a lot of morphological characteristics with 
 <italic class="italic">C. canescens</italic> (relatively widespread in its range). Second, populations of 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> in Santa Rosa County, Florida, have morphological characteristics in common with both 
 <italic class="italic">C. glabra</italic> (endangered species) and 
 <italic class="italic">C. canescens.</italic> Due to the endangered status of four 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> species, it is important to resolve the species relationships, define species limits and elucidate the evolutionary processes in order to help with conservation plans. 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> was subjected to several phylogenetic analyses using four data partitions: plastid DNA, internal transcribed spacer (ITS), and two members of the GapC gene family [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. These analyses did not resolve species relationships in 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic>. In agreement morphological evidence, ITS results supported a monophyletic 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> while plastid DNA results did not. Some 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> populations showed moderate levels of inbreeding, but inbreeding does not seem as a major factor. Because previous analyses failed to resolve species relationships separately, combined analyses were carried out but the results still did not resolve the relationships within 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic>. Studies using genotype data from quickly evolving microsatellite loci suggested that both ancient interspecific hybridization and incomplete lineage sorting of ancestral polymorphism have likely occurred in 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> and that based on the patterns of genetic structure (which corresponds to species bounderies), 
 <italic class="italic">Conradina</italic> species have diverged genetically from one another (nonmonophyly) despite having unique distribution patterns and distinguishing morphological characteristics [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-07-00019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>].
</p>
