<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Unlike forest tree species with allelopathic properties nuciferous are considered to be agricultural crops; and any possibility of their cultivation together with other cultivated species possesses considerable interest. In order to select species that could be cultivated in vicinity of a walnut tree, Kocacaliskan and Terzi [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>] evaluated the walnut leaf extracts effect on germination and growth of 11 agricultural crops, both monocotyledons and dicotyledonous. The effect depended on the species, and the growth was inhibited to a greater extent than germination. It was unexpectedly demonstrated that the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Cucumis melo</italic> was stimulated by the extract, which indicates a possibility of its cultivation near the walnut trees. Experiments conducted in a greenhouse showed that walnut extracts were strongly inhibiting both vegetative and reproductive growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Fragaria×ananassa L.</italic> plants, and were reducing the N, K, Ca, Fe, and Mn content in leaves, as well as total soluble solid and vitamin C in berries [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>]. Allelochemicals could not only be washed out of leaves by rain, but also fall into soil from leaf litter. To assess allelopathic activity of the walnut leaf litter, it was added to the soil for cultivating the 
 <italic class="italic">Lactuca sativa</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">angustata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. Tree waste was inhibiting the shoot weight of lettuce especially during the early growth stage or with large amounts, while also reducing the chlorophyll 
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">b</italic> and carotenoids content. Twenty-eight compounds were identified with three solvent extracts, and some of them, such as lupenone, lupeol, fatty acids, and phenolic acids possess the allelopathic activity [
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>].
</p>
