<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Commonly used antifungal methods include the disc diffusion technique, macro and microbroth dilution assays, the food poisoning method, the volatile release plate method, as well as the use of electron microscopy. Certain methods like disc diffusion, well diffusion and agar dilution methods have been shown to produce unreliable and inconsistent results [
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B126-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]; this is primarily due to difficulties related to stable oil dispersion in aqueous media, lipophilic substance distribution in the aqueous medium, and various methods which are used to determine the number of viable microbes that will remain following the addition of EOs. In addition, true representation of activity is not possible with the disc and well diffusion methods, as different components diffuse through the agar at varying rates, and only the more water-soluble components, such as terpine 4-ol, are capable of agar penetration [
 <xref rid="B125-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. This phenomenon also occurs in the agar dilution method, where the incorporation of EO into agar can result in the loss of certain active compounds (e.g. terpinen-4-ol, linalool and limonene), either through evaporation or absorption into the petri dish plastic [
 <xref rid="B127-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. These techniques yield unreproducible outcomes for certain EOs, and are thus unreliable for assessments of the true behaviour of EOs. Usually, Tween 80 (a commercial polyoxyethylene sorbitan monooleate) will be added to emulate the oils for the study of the antifungal activity of hydrophobic and viscous EOs [
 <xref rid="B128-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. This may be linked to the fact that surfactants decrease the degradation rates of EOs, thereby causing the continued release of antimicrobial agents [
 <xref rid="B129-molecules-26-01093" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>].
</p>
