<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of agarwood transcends spiritual, cultural, and regional differences as evidenced in ancient texts and scriptures: Romans burned it to honor the dead and the Gods, Greeks and Chinese included it in their pharmacopoeias, while Arabs and Indians incorporated it in perfumery being “one of the finest aromatics” [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Logic behind these beliefs and practices is as mystifying as to how agarwood is formed. The most plausible explanation goes that the resinous product is only produced when the heartwood of an 
 <italic>Aquilaria</italic> tree (among other genera of family Thymelaeaceae) gets damaged by natural phenomenon or wounded by artificial means, with subsequent fungi infection [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Like a defense mechanism, agarwood production is the response of the tree to stress. Ironically, the same stress-induced resin is also known to have a calming effect [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This claim is supported by few modern pharmacological studies. Administration of either oil or extracts through oral, inhalational, or intraperitoneal injection demonstrated sedative activity as indicated by a decrease in spontaneous motor activity, hypothermic effect, and prolongation of hexobarbiturate-induced sleeping time in mice [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Likewise, individual constituents namely jinkoh-eremol, agarospirol, α-gurjunene, (+)-calarene, and benzylacetone resulted in sedation [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This makes agarwood a very promising starting material for finding novel or other existing compounds that may have activity. Concurrently, it is beneficial in trade and industry since strong competition in acquiring agarwood for medicinal purposes (e.g., for aromatherapy) will be minimized.
</p>
