<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Constituents responsible for the characteristic aroma are generally grouped into sesquiterpenes, chromones, and other volatile aromatic compounds [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Majority of the composition are attributed to the first two [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]; thus, not much attention is given to the last group. However, most of the analyses were conducted on oil and extracts which may already lost some fragrant components due to rigorous extraction processes [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Agarwood is obviously best experienced through burning and direct inhalation of the heated wood, like the way it is traditionally appreciated in incense ceremonies. The same can be said when profiling the aroma. Hence, capturing it in its closest natural form is critical. One of the first few attempts in analyzing agarwood aroma directly from the wood found the composition was remarkably different from the solvent extract [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Several volatile aromatic compounds were also detected, which are believed to be pyrolysis products of other constituents [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A more recent study utilized a headspace (HS) preheating system and found as much as one-third of the incense smoke was made up of aromatics [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These compounds have a great contribution to agarwood aroma and probably play a role in its sedative activity as well. They may even have effects on their own, as seen in benzylacetone [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], thereby making them worth exploring. Moreover, the characteristic aroma of agarwood is often described as a product of the perfect harmony brought about by many compounds [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-01320" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and in this entirety the aroma is experienced. Hence, it is also important to investigate their possible interaction in terms of pharmacologic activity.
</p>
