<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three distinct species have been studied: the Argentine ant 
 <italic>L. humile</italic>, the invasive garden ant 
 <italic>La. neglectus</italic> and the black garden ant 
 <italic>La. niger</italic>. 
 <italic>Linepithema humile</italic> is currently a widespread and abundant invasive species, forming supercolonies (arising from the low levels of intraspecific aggression among colonies), with polydomic, highly polygynous nests and totally sterile workers [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. 
 <italic>Lasius neglectus</italic> also forms polygynous colonies with the presence of several functional queens within the nest [
 <xref rid="B24-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This invasive species has ecological impacts on the biodiversity of Formicidae and other invertebrates (e.g., reducing the spatial and temporal foraging of native ants; [
 <xref rid="B25-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]). The range of 
 <italic>La. neglectus</italic> has increased rapidly and steadily in non-native locations over the last 30 years [
 <xref rid="B27-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. These two invasive species are present across almost all Europe and their distribution partly overlaps, especially in the easternmost part of Europe (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-animals-10-02451">Supplementary Material, Figure S1</xref>). 
 <italic>Lasius niger</italic> is a widespread monogynous species, inhabiting all of Europe and parts of Asia and North America and colonizing a broad diversity of environments, but particularly abundant in arable land, as well as in cities, parks and gardens [
 <xref rid="B23-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This species is aggressive towards other ants, including conspecifics [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-10-02451" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
