<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Chickens were reared on deep litter (wood shavings). Temperature and lightning regimes were in accordance with standards for the fattening of broiler chickens [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. During the entire fattening period the broiler chickens had free access to water and feed. Feeding of chickens was carried out as follows: fattening period lasted 38 days and the conventional feed mixtures (DeHEUS, Czech Republic), which are used in industrial factory farms of broilers in Slovakia, were fed in both groups. Chickens of the control group were fed only with conventional feed mixtures used in the four phases. The main components of feed mixtures are wheat, corn, soybean meal, rapeseed cake, and sunflower meal. At the beginning of fattening, feed mixture “BR1” (starter diet; Crude protein 22.4%, Fat 6.2%, Fibre 3.2%, Ash 5.4%, Methionine 0.6%, Vit. A 12500 IU, Vit. D
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> 4000 IU, and Vit. E 75 mg.kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, Ca 0.8%, P 0.58%) was administered during the first 10 days of fattening. From day 11 to day 21, birds consumed a growing diet 1 (BR2; Total protein 20.9%, Fat 6.2%, Fibre 3.4%, Ash 4.5%, Methionine 0.52%, Ca 0.6%, P 0.5%, Vit. A 10000 IU, Vit. D
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> 4000 IU, Vit. E 25 mg.kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). From day 22 to day 28 birds were fed growing diet 2 (BR3; Total protein 20.3%, Fat 6.9%, Fibre 3.1%, Ash 4.2%, Methionine 0.5%, Ca 0.5%, P 0.45%, Vit. A 10000 IU, Vit. D
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> 4000 IU, and Vit. E 25 mg.kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) and from 29
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> to the 38
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> day final diet (BR4; Total protein 19.3%, Fat 6.6%, Fibre 3.1%, Ash 3.9%, Methionine 0.48%, Ca 0.5%, P 0.41%, Vit. A 8000 IU, Vit. D
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> 2000 IU, and Vit. E 20 mg.kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). Chickens of the experimental group were fed in the same way, but fermented bioproduct was administered from the 11
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> day of fattening. Bioproduct was added into the feed mixture “BR2, BR3, and BR4” in the amount of 10% (10% of conventional feed mixture was replaced with bioproduct).
</p>
