<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the treatment of infestations of the human head louse, 
 <italic class="italic">Pediculus humanus capitis</italic>, there have been several recent advances to address problems caused by acquired resistance to conventional insecticides (
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feldmeier, 2014</xref>). Consequently, curing an infestation can be relatively easy but an age-old problem persists. After elimination of the lice, the dead eggs and empty eggshells (nits) remain firmly fixed to the hair. Numerous products have been marketed claiming to facilitate nit removal by dissolving the glue, digesting it with enzymes, or making it slide off the hair, but objective tests of these materials have shown that none of them really works any better than, or even as well as, off-the-shelf conditioning rinses or even just water (
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burgess, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lapeere et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ortega-Insaurralde et al., 2014</xref>) and some products, such as those based on essential oils, may actually bind louse eggs more firmly to the hairs (
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burgess, Brunton &amp; Burgess, 2016</xref>). Because none of the common hair treatments exhibits any detectable influence on that grip of the egg fixative material, it has created a challenge for inventors that is not helped by the conflicting and contradictory statements and claims about the nature of the fixative (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schmidt, 1939</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Barat &amp; Scaria, 1962</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carter, 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burkhart et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burkhart &amp; Burkhart, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Federal Trade Commission, 1998</xref>), which is why there have been many attempts to discover a chemical or best method to initiate release of louse eggshells from hair (
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Greene, 1898</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sacker, 1942</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bernstein, 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Upton, 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hayward &amp; Watkins, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McGuire &amp; Kross, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ozelkan, Zhang &amp; Malayev, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Acevedo, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mehlhorn et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kolender &amp; Kolender, 2017</xref>), a complex story we likened to the Arthurian legendary “Quest for the Holy Grail”. This project was initiated with the aim of identifying one or more chemicals effective to loosen the grip of the louse egg fixative in order to develop a genuinely effective consumer product.
</p>
