<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, the fossil record in amber is subject to bias, which may limit and distort the extent to which the fossil assemblage represents the living assemblage. There are two components to this bias: entrapment bias, which involves the non-random patterns by which organisms become engulfed in resin; and preservation bias, effectively the non-random patterns by which entrapped organisms decay or fossilize. To date research effort has focused on entrapment into the resin [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], and a number of variables such as resin viscosity, insect behaviour and habitat and plant defences have been found to be influential [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. For example, fossil assemblages in amber favour the preservation of small, terrestrial inclusions, because these are most easily entrapped in resin flows [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Subsequent to entrapment and entombment in resin it has been suggested that essentially all organisms are preserved [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. However, recent advances in 3D scanning techniques have revealed a cryptic and surprising variability of preservation quality of internal anatomy, even where external preservation quality is close-to “life-like”. The variation ranges from internally complete fossils, retaining minute details of the most decay-prone tissues, through to fossils preserving only the most decay resistant features, to some which are hollow moulds. This indicates that decay and preservation biases are operating once carcasses are entombed in resin [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Such bias may responsible for some of the patterns in the amber fossil record that cannot be explained by entrapment; for example, the occurrence of non-fossiliferous amber sites [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>], and taxa whose overrepresentation in amber (for example ants in some Cenozoic amber) cannot easily be explained by their behaviour [
 <xref rid="pone.0195482.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. The assessment of the ecological completeness of amber fossil assemblages requires understanding of bias in the preservation process of insects, as well as entrapment bias.
</p>
