<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">In quality control of TCM, since the composition and pharmacological effects of TCM are usually very complicated, single component, multiple components or even the global chemical profile with many components may be utilized to assess the quality of a specific TCM. Chemical reference substance (CRS) and herbal reference substance (HRS) in EP or CRS, reference extract and reference crude drug in ChP could be used as reference standards for TCM identification and compound quantification. Therefore, choosing the appropriate marker is very important for accurate and valid quality assessment of TCM, especially when active markers are not available in analysis. By comparing the markers used in both pharmacopoeias, interesting differences are observed. Of the TCM reviewed, besides different choices of active markers in analysis, EP has included many analytical markers, which serve solely for analytical purposes and irrespective of any pharmacological or therapeutic activity, in TCM identification and quantification. For example, aescin and arbutin are used as analytical makers for TLC identification of Anemarrhenae Asphodeloides Rhizoma and Notoginseng Radix; caffeine is used as reference for the determination of pinoresinol diglucoside in Eucommiae Cortex. While ChP has included many reference crude drugs in TCM identification. Among the 73 TCM reviewed, 37 in ChP employ reference extract or reference drug in TCM identification, and 12 of them include only reference drug in monographs for TLC identification. In addition, EP has included many specific references for system suitability assessment, while ChP uses the intensity markers or active markers in TCM identification or assay for this purpose. For example, in EP, isoeugenol and methyleugenol are used for the system suitability test of TLC identification of Ophiopogonis Radix. Propyl parahydroxybenzoate and saikosaponin A are employed for the system suitability of LC quantification for Bupleuri Radix. Moreover, 20 out of 73 TCM apply HRS in system suitability assessment of LC assay. From the above, it is shown that other than active markers, analytical markers and HRS or reference drug are also applied in monographs either as substitution of active markers or for method validation and system suitability assessment etc., so they are important alternates when active markers are not available or with high costs.</p>
