<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ab0005">
 <sec>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>Treatment of leishmaniasis with conventional synthetic drugs is a major global challenge. This study was designed to explore the leishmanicidal activity and apoptotic profile of three leaf extracts on 
   <italic>Leishmania tropica</italic> stages.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>The plants of 
   <italic>Quercus velutina, Calotropis procera</italic> and 
   <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> were gathered from Anbarabbad county, in the southeastern part of Kerman province and extracted by maceration method using methanol alcohol. Various concentrations of the extracts (1, 10, 100 and 1000 μg/mL) were used against L. 
   <italic>tropica</italic> stages to evaluate the inhibitory effect by colorimetric assay, macrophage model and flow cytometry. The MTT assay was conducted to determine the IC
   <sub>50</sub> and CC
   <sub>50</sub> values in promastigotes and J774-A1 macrophages, respectively. For intra-macrophage amastigotes, the leishmanicidal activity was evaluated by calculating the mean number of amastigotes in each macrophage and also IC
   <sub>50</sub> values. The promastigote or amastigote stages with no drug and complete medium without organisms were considered as positive and negative controls, respectively. Meglumine antimoniate (Glucantime) was also used as standard drug. Also, annexin V was used to assess the apoptotic profile. All treatment settings were incubated for a standard time of 72 h in triplicates. Data were analyzed by 
   <italic>t</italic>-test and ANOVA.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The findings showed that all plant extracts inhibited the proliferation rate of promastigotes and amastigotes (
   <italic>P</italic> ˂ 0.001); especially, 
   <italic>Q. velutina</italic> represented the lowest IC
   <sub>50</sub> in both stages. Besides, 
   <italic>Q. velutina</italic> showed the least number of amastigotes in each macrophage compared to the other groups (4.5 μg/mL). The percentage of parasitic apoptosis at 1000 μg/mL of 
   <italic>Q. velutina, C. procera, N. tabacum</italic> and Glucantime® were 37.4, 18.6, 8.5 and 52.4, respectively. Amastigotes (clinical stage) were significantly more susceptible to extracts and also Glucantime® than promastigotes (
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>This study revealed that all three extracts of 
   <italic>Q. velutina, C. procera and N. tabacum</italic> exhibited an effective antileishmanial activity and induced apoptosis against the L. 
   <italic>tropica</italic> promastigotes. Further investigations are essential to isolate and analyze the chemical compositions and their biological properties.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
