<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Although many invasive species are typically found within similar climatic envelopes in the introduced range as the native range (
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Petitpierre et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Atwater et al., 2017</xref>), the biotic environment is expected to show substantial differences (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Keane and Crawley, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Colautti et al., 2004</xref>). Because of this, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Blossey and Notzold (1995)</xref> hypothesized that escape from natural enemies in the introduced range should drive allocation of resources away from defense to growth or reproduction, resulting in the evolution of invasive traits (evolution of increased competitive ability [EICA]). Specifically, they predicted that introduced populations should evolve to produce more biomass than native populations and that specialist herbivores will experience improved performance on introduced populations relative to native ones. Many common garden experiments comparing native and introduced populations have sought to test the EICA hypothesis (for reviews see 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bossdorf et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Colautti et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Orians and Ward, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Felker-Quinn et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Hodgins et al., 2018</xref>). Evolutionary shifts in reproduction, growth, defense, and competitive ability have been identified in many cases (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Felker-Quinn et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Colautti and Lau, 2015</xref>), although only size seems to frequently increase during invasion, resulting in limited general support for the EICA hypothesis (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Blumenthal and Hufbauer, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Felker-Quinn et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
