<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> ethanol extract has been shown to have prominent anti-inflammatory effects both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, as indicated by its inhibition of TNF-
 <italic>α</italic> and PGE
 <sub>2</sub> production in LPS-induced macrophages and LPS-induced mice, respectively [
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. While there is limited evidence on the antisepsis potential of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> extract, a few compounds isolated from the plant, namely, asiaticoside, asiatic acid, and madecassoside, have shown antisepsis activities. Intraperitoneal injection of asiaticoside, a triterpenoid saponin, in CLP-induced mice, reduced the serum levels of IL-6 and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>, the expression of COX-2 and iNOS in lung tissue, and the severity of lung injury due to sepsis [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Importantly, asiaticoside treatment also improved the survival of CLP-induced mice [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. In a mouse model of LPS-induced ALI, asiaticoside demonstrated similar beneficial effects by decreasing the degree of lung damage [
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Asiaticoside has also been reported to attenuate liver injury in LPS-/D-galactosamine-induced mice and LPS-induced rats [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Asiatic acid is a major triterpene isolated from 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic>. Injection of asiatic acid via the intranasal route attenuated ALI via downregulation of TLR4 expression, suppression of NF-
 <italic>κ</italic>B activation, and subsequent inhibition of proinflammatory cytokines (IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, IL-6, and TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>) production in LPS-induced mice [
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Besides that, a more recent study found that the oral administration of asiatic acid resulted in increased survival rate and reduced organ damage in LPS-induced endotoxemic mice [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Madecassoside, another major triterpenoid, has also been associated with tissue protective effects 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. An intragastric injection of madecassoside has been shown to have cardioprotective effects against myocardial dysfunction in LPS-treated rats by reducing plasma TNF-
 <italic>α</italic>, preventing the fall in blood pressure and attenuating the severity of tachycardia [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Furthermore, an oral administration of madecassoside was able to prevent acute liver failure in LPS-/D-galactosamine-induced mice [
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
