<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flammability is the ability of vegetation (fuel) to burn (
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Fernandes &amp; Cruz, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Gill &amp; Zylstra, 2005</xref>) and is a measure of fire behavior (fire intensity/severity) used in vegetation fire risk mitigation studies (
 <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Keeley, 2009</xref>). Vegetation flammability may result from climatic and weather effects (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Bond &amp; Midgley, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Mutch, 1970</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Snyder, 1984</xref>). For example, in arid areas, dryness limits fuel accumulation and fires follow episodic rain, whereas in temperate areas, fuel loads are not limiting but fires follow the drying of those fuels (
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Bradstock, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Pausas &amp; Bradstock, 2007</xref>), however dry conditions may also result in an increase in fire risk caused by the availability of dried fuels (
 <xref rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr">Piñol, Terradas &amp; Llored, 1998</xref>). Fire-prone vegetation groups may furthermore have evolved traits that enhance their flammability and improve vegetation fitness in fire-dependent communities (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Bond &amp; Midgley, 1995</xref>). Correspondingly, species with high flammability traits may burn intensely, such that itself and the neighbour die, thereby facilitating recruitment—the “kill thy neighbour” hypothesis (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Bond &amp; Midgley, 1995</xref>). Flammability traits may thus provide resilience associated with fire tolerance (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Bond &amp; Midgley, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Calitz, Potts &amp; Cowling, 2015</xref>). Fire is accordingly one of the main determining factors of the ecology and distribution of ecosystems of the world, and is important for maintaining plant diversity (
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Bond, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Bond, Midgley &amp; Woodward, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Bond &amp; Keeley, 2005</xref>).
</p>
