<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biofilms are organized groups of microorganisms that live inside an extracellular polymer matrix that is self-sustaining and can adhere to various surfaces [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>], biotic and abiotic [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. Biofilms are often observed floating or submerged in liquids [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>] and can be composed of homogeneous or heterogeneous communities of bacteria within a polymer matrix, which is primarily composed OF polysaccharides as well as other biomolecules, such as proteins, lipids, and nucleic acids [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. Analyses of the polymer matrix have revealed that biofilms are hydrogels that exhibit viscoelastic behavior, allowing them to resist mechanical stresses [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many biofilms are present in a variety of microbial infections, including dental infections [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]; periodontitis [
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]; lung infections resulting from cystic fibrosis and facial filling [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]; chronic wounds [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>]; ear inflammation [
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]; implant-associate infections [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>]; chronic rhinosinusitis [
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]; contamination in intensive care units (ICU) [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>]; contact lens infections [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>]; and human gastrointestinal tract infections [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>]. Studies have shown that
  <span class="italic"> S. aureus</span> is the second most prevalent pathogen in ICUs [
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>] and often causes infections in women, with biofilms formed by this microorganism causing complications in urinary infection treatments [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biofilms protect microorganisms from external aggression and predator attacks [
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>], and some populations of biofilm-associated bacteria are resistant to antibiotics [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>]. Thus, the increased resistance of bacterial biofilms to antibiotics is problematic for the use of antimicrobial drugs [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>], driving the search for alternative medicinal plants that can be used to treat diseases [
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>]. In particular, it is necessary to identify new drugs that can serve as an alternative treatment of infections caused by microorganisms that are resistant to traditional therapies. One approach is the study of local medicinal plants with possible antimicrobial and antibiofilm properties.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils, which are natural products obtained from plants, contain volatile organic compounds that can be obtained from various parts of the plant, such as flowers, fruits, seeds, stems, AND roots [
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. These oils have demonstrated antioxidant, insecticidal, antiviral, antibacterial, antifungal, and antibiofilm activities [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>–
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">23</a>]. Among essential oils of botanical origin that have antimicrobial potential are those obtained from plant species of the genus
  <span class="italic"> Cinnamomum</span> (Lauraceae), such as
  <span class="italic"> C. zeylanicum </span>and
  <span class="italic"> C. cassia.</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">C. zeylanicum </span>is native to some regions of India and Ceylon; thus, it is known as “cinnamon-of-ceylon” [
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">24</a>]. This species has been used in folk medicine due to its many medicinal properties, including its activities as astringent, aphrodisiac, antiseptic, aperitif, aromatic, carminative, digestive, stimulant, hypertensive, sedative, tonic and vasodilator [
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">25</a>], antidiabetic, antinociceptive, astringent, and diuretic [
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">26</a>]. From the different parts of the plant, essential oils with various chemical compositions can be obtained, and essential oil from the stem bark contains up to 4% oil consisting of (E)-cinnamaldehyde (65-78%) and eugenol (4-10%), accompanied by low percentages of cinnamyl acetate, methyl-n-amyl-ketone, and mono- and sesquiterpenoids [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">27</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">C. cassia, </span>popularly known as “cinnamon-china”, is a perennial tree native to southern China and is widely cultivated in southern and eastern Asia (Taiwan, Laos, Thailand, Vietnam, India, Indonesia, and Malaysia) [
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">28</a>].
  <span class="italic"> C. cassia </span>is used in Western medicine, primarily in the treatment of diarrhoea, flatulent dyspepsia, cramps, colds, flu, cough, bronchitis, lack of appetite, renal weakness, arthritic angina, palpitations, spasms, vomiting, gastric ulcers, digestive complaints, and bacterial and fungal infections of the skin [
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">29</a>]. The trunk bark contains at least 1.0% essential oil, consisting of 70 to 90% (E)-cinnamaldehyde [
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">30</a>]. In addition, a study also reported that the essential oil of this species has antifungal activity against
  <span class="italic"> Candida albicans </span>[
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">31</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(E)-Cinnamaldehyde, the most abundant component of the essential oils of the
  <span class="italic"> Cinnamomum </span>species mentioned, is a phenylpropanoid that has proven activity against microorganisms [
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">32</a>]. Due to this already proven antimicrobial action, this work aimed to verify the action of essential oils and cinnamaldehyde against microbial biofilms of clinical interest.
 </p>
</sec>
