<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Background</bold>: The biotechnological potential of medicinal plants from Brazilian Caatinga and the Atlantic Forest has not been extensively studied. Thus, screening programs are important in prospecting for compounds for developing new drugs. The purpose of this study was to determine the chemical composition and to evaluate the anti-
  <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> activity of essential oils from leaves of 
  <italic class="italic">Hymenaea courbaril</italic> var. 
  <italic class="italic">courbaril</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Myroxylon peruiferum</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">Vismia guianensis</italic>. 
  <bold class="bold">Methods</bold>: The oils were extracted through hydrodistillation and their chemical compositions were analyzed by gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry. Antifungal activity against 
  <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">C. tropicalis</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">C. parapsilosis</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">C. glabrata</italic>, and 
  <italic class="italic">C. krusei</italic> was evaluated by determining the minimal inhibitory (MIC) and fungicidal (MFC) concentrations. 
  <bold class="bold">Results</bold>: The major compounds of the oils were caryophyllene oxide and 
  <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-caryophyllene for 
  <italic class="italic">H. courbaril</italic>; spathulenol, α-pinene, and caryophyllene oxide for 
  <italic class="italic">M. peruiferum</italic>; and caryophyllene oxide and humulene epoxide II for 
  <italic class="italic">V. guianensis</italic> oil. The oils showed antifungal activity against all the strains tested, and the MIC values ranged between 0.625 and 1.25 μL/mL and MFC from 0.625 to 2.5 μL/mL. 
  <bold class="bold">Conclusion</bold>: The essential oils from the species studied have the potential to be evaluated as clinical applications in the treatment of candidiasis.
 </p>
</abstract>
