<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Animals use dietary protein nitrogen to replace digestive enzymes and different compounds that are degraded and lost. It has been acknowledged that we should decrease the diet pollutant component that is excreted as much as possible. Many previous studies have highlighted that nitrogen output can be decreased, particularly through nutritional approaches [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Previous research has focused on the digestibility of nutrients supplied by protein and fiber-rich feedstuff. However, we noted a lack of information regarding the availability of nutrients from n-3-rich diets. In this study, we evaluated changes in nitrogen output, absorbed and retained nitrogen, and tissue composition as the effects of a mixture between EL:WM characterized by a higher content in n-3 PUFA. The relations between nitrogen digestibility and plasma parameters such as PUN and creatinine were determined as well. Our diet had a higher n-3 FA level as compared to the traditional diet, obtained by the addition of extruded linseed in association with walnut meal. An increasing emphasis is being place on pollution due to nitrogen from the livestock sector. Our question is how to feed piglets without negatively affecting the environment while also meeting consumer demands regarding the quality of products and the health status of the animals. Extruded linseed (n-3-rich ingredient) in association with walnut meal (n-6-rich byproduct) increased the n-3 FA composition in the diet 6.83 times and increased the ALA composition 8.11 times compared to the SM diet. The n-3:n-6 PUFA ratio in the LEW diet was 2.56. This was established as a ratio close to 1 which is required for the prevention of certain diseases [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-09-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-animals-09-00234" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. 
</p>
