<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Maki et al. studied the effect of adding oat containing β-glucan or wheat cereal products to the usual diet of 27 healthy male adults for two weeks on their postprandial lipemia following consumption of a high-fat meal [
 <xref rid="B134-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">134</xref>]. Both dietary treatments were matched for their energy and total fiber content. The postprandial serum peak TG concentration was lower and the postprandial serum TG concentration tended to be lower following consumption of the oat treatment but the postprandial FFA concentration was higher. Of note, Cara et al. did not observe any difference in postprandial serum-TG concentration following consumption of a meal containing 10 g β-glucan vs wheat fibers in healthy individuals [
 <xref rid="B124-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">124</xref>]. Dubois et al. compared the postprandial effects of an oat bran test meal (12.8 g fibers) following consumption for 14 days of either an oat bran supplemented diet (23.8 g fibers/day) or a basal low-fiber diet (2.8 g fibers/day) in six normolipemic men [
 <xref rid="B135-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">135</xref>]. Although it did not reach statistical significance, probably due to the low number of participants, the oat test meal following chronic consumption of oat elicited a slightly greater postprandial CM-TG concentration. However, the authors did observe significant differences in the postprandial concentrations of other lipid classes: postprandial plasma phospholipid, as well as plasma- and HDL-free cholesterol concentrations were increased while postprandial HDL-C ester concentration was decreased. The authors thus concluded that chronic consumption of oat exacerbates the acute effects of an oat meal on postprandial lipid concentrations. Wolever et al. provided 33 dyslipidemic participants for four months either a high soluble or insoluble fiber diet. The postprandial CM-TG concentration following consumption of a standardized fiber-free fatty liquid meal did not exhibit any difference when all subjects were considered but subjects with the APOε3 phenotype had a greater postprandial CM-TG concentration, due to an increase in the rate of fat absorption or CM synthesis or both, after soluble vs insoluble long-term fiber consumption [
 <xref rid="B136-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">136</xref>]. Bozetto et al. provided 20 overweight/obese subjects with T2D with a high carbohydrate/fiber diet (26 g fibers/1000 kcal) for eight weeks and showed that participants exhibited a lower postprandial plasma TG concentration as well as a lower TG concentration in the CM+VLDL fraction following consumption of a test meal rich in saturated fat after the dietary intervention [
 <xref rid="B137-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>]. In another study using a relatively similar design, the same group also observed a decrease in postprandial CM-cholesterol concentration in T2D patients [
 <xref rid="B138-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">138</xref>].
</p>
