<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The discussion regarding kinematic parameters can be quite difficult, as up to date, their biological meaning and correlation to semen quality and fertility still have to be definitively unveiled. TTO seems to alter velocity (VAP, VCL, and VSL) and distance (DAP, DCL, and DSL) parameters only when used at the highest studied concentration for kinematics; higher concentrations were not evaluated as TotM was not sufficiently relevant. These findings seem to suggest a quantitative impairment in speed, thus in distance, without alteration of the quality of movement as confirmed by the non-altered results of ALH, WOB, and BCF. Indeed, hyper-activated sperm subpopulation, showing abnormal movements, are characterized by increased ALH [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. The same pattern of velocity–distance alteration was noticed starting from 0.42 mg/mL of TER; corresponding to 1 mg/mL of TTO, but only regarding the straight-line parameters (VSL and DCL). This is particularly interesting as TER-treated samples seem to maintain good TotM (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) also at higher concentrations then the ones with kinematics alterations. Supposedly, modifications in kinematics parameters with maintained TotM may suggest early impairment, still allowing the spermatozoa to move but with less intensity. Overall, despite the relative lack of literature, different authors have reported how kinematics parameters, especially velocity-related ones, seem to have a good predictive potential when it comes to fertility [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. This is why CASA analyses play a pivotal role when evaluating interactions between new molecules with potential in the reproductive field and spermatozoa [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>].
</p>
