<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Abs1" class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
  <p id="Par1" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Cupressus macrocarpa</span> Hartw and 
   <span class="italic">Corymbia citriodora</span> (Hook.) K.D. Hill &amp; L.A.S. Johnson, widely grown in many subtropical areas, are used for commercial purposes, such as in perfumery, cosmetics, and room fresheners. Their potential as a source of antimicrobial compounds may be useful in different applications.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
  <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition of essential oils (EOs) from 
   <span class="italic">C. macrocarpa</span> branchlets and 
   <span class="italic">C. citriodora</span> leaves was analyzed by using gas chromatography–mass spectrometry (GC/MS). Antibacterial and antifungal activities were assessed by the micro-dilution method to determine the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs), and minimum fungicidal concentrations (MFCs), and minimum bactericidal concentrations (MBCs). Further, the antioxidant capacity of the EOs was determined via 2,2′-diphenypicrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-carotene-linoleic acid assays.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
  <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Terpinen-4-ol (23.7%), α-phellandrene (19.2%), 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-citronellol (17.3%), and citronellal were the major constituents of EO from 
   <span class="italic">C. macrocarpa</span> branchlets, and 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-citronellal (56%), 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-citronellol (14.7%), citronellol acetate (12.3%), isopulegol, and eucalyptol were the primary constituents of EO from 
   <span class="italic">C. citriodora</span> leaves. Antibacterial activity with MIC values of EO from 
   <span class="italic">C. citriodora</span> leaves was ranged from 0.06 mg/mL to 0.20 mg/mL, and MBC from 0.12 mg/mL against 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span> to 0.41 mg/mL. EO from 
   <span class="italic">C. macrocarpa</span> branchlets showed less activity against bacterial strains. The MIC values against tested fungi of the EO from 
   <span class="italic">C. citriodora</span> ranged from 0.11 to 0.52 mg/mL while for EO from 
   <span class="italic">C. macrocarpa</span> from 0.29 to 3.21 mg/mL. The MIC and MFC values of EOs against 
   <span class="italic">P. funiculosum</span> were lower than those obtained from Ketoconazole (KTZ) (0.20; 0.45; 0.29 and 0.53 mg/mL, respectively, vs 0.21 and 0.41 mg/mL. Antioxidant activity of the EO from 
   <span class="italic">C. citriodora</span> was higher than that of the positive control but lower than that of the standard butylhydroxytoluene (BHT) (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 5.1 ± 0.1 μg/mL).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
  <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results indicate that the EO from Egyptian trees such as 
   <span class="italic">C. citriodora</span> leaves may possesses strong bactericidal and fungicidal activities and can be used as an agrochemical for controlling plant pathogens and in human disease management which will add crop additive value.
  </p>
 </sec>
</div>
