<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-medicines-04-00063" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">New preferences for a minimum of processed food and recent changes in consumers’ concern about synthetic preservatives [
  <a rid="B1-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-medicines-04-00063">1</a>] have led to an increase in the use of natural preservatives in foods [
  <a rid="B2-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-medicines-04-00063">2</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant extracts have been employed by humans for thousands of years in traditional medicine. The Lamiaceae family contains important aromatic plants used in traditional and modern medicine and in the food and pharmaceutical industries. Rosemary, thyme, oregano, and sage are the most popular plants in Spanish traditional remedies and are often used for the treatment of gastritis, infections, dermatitis, bronchitis, and inflammation. Particularly, rosemary and sage have been extensively studied for their antioxidative and antimicrobial activity. The vegetation of Southeast Spain (Murcia) is rich in aromatic plants, and the province of Murcia is a major producer and processor of medicinal herbs [
  <a rid="B3-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-medicines-04-00063">3</a>]. Rosemary and thyme are mostly exploited for the extraction of essential oils (EOs). Among the &gt;3000 essential oils known, about 300 are of importance for the pharmaceutical, agronomic, and food industries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">EOs are volatile liquids, or semi-liquids, extracted from plants, usually by steam distillation [
  <a rid="B4-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-medicines-04-00063">4</a>]. They are limpid and rarely coloured, are soluble in organic solvents with a lower density than that of water, and are lipid soluble. They can be synthesized by all plant organs (flowers, leaves, stems, twigs, seeds, fruits, roots, wood, or bark) and are stored in secretory cells, cavities, canals, epidermic cells or glandular trichomes. EOs are complex mixtures of sesquiterpene and monoterpene hydrocarbons and alcohols, ketones, and aldehydes (their oxygenated derivatives). Essential oils may also encompass other chemical families like fatty acids, oxides, and sulphur derivatives [
  <a rid="B5-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-medicines-04-00063">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">EOs are of scientific and popular interest because (a) they may act synergistically with other techniques of preservation, (b) they are generally recognized as safe, and (c) they show antioxidant, antibacterial, antidiabetic, antimutagenic, non-toxigenic, and antimycotic properties which are promising for their use as bioactive compounds in different foods [
  <a rid="B6-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-medicines-04-00063">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main components of common essential oils can be classified into two structural families with respect to hydrocarbon skeleton: terpenoids, formed by the combination of two (monoterpene), three (sesquiterpene) or four (diterpene) isoprene units, and phenylpropanoids. Both terpenoid and phenylpropanoid families comprise phenolic compounds, sometimes identified as principal components of several EOs.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants synthesize essential oils for a variety of purposes, including protection of the plant against fungi and bacteria, allelopathic activity, defence against insects (terpenoids are known to repel animals and insects) and attraction of pollinators and dispersal agents to favour the dispersion of seeds and pollens (the aromas and scents of the plants are responsible for the attraction of insects by the essential oils, characterized by volatility and a strong odour). Essential oils can protect plants against viruses, bacteria, fungi, insects, and herbivores [
  <a rid="B7-medicines-04-00063" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-medicines-04-00063">7</a>]. The major activities of essential oils are antimicrobial, sedative, anti-inflammatory, bactericidal, antiviral, antifungal (fungicidal), and preservative for foods.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is also a growing interest in plant EOs as natural alternatives to synthetic additives. This review describes the biological activities of EOs from the Lamiaceae family, primarily the antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of essential oils and the structure–activity relationships and mechanisms of action of their active components. Finally, an overview will be provided of other preventive and therapeutic properties of EOs, such as anti-angiogenic and anti-tumour properties.</p>
</sec>
