<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. The Effect of the EOM on the Biochemical Parameters of Rats</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a> shows that no significant difference in blood glucose was apparent between the control group, the fatigue group, and the PEO group (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.05), but the blood glucose of rats in the EOM group was significantly higher than that of the fatigue group after swimming (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">4</a> show that the BLA level of the rats in the fatigue group was significantly higher than that of the control group after swimming (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05). However, inhalation of the EOM significantly decreased the concentrations of BUN and BLA in comparison with the fatigue group (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01 or 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001). The BUN and BLA concentrations were even lower than the PEO group and the control group (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a> show that the activity of GSH-PX and SOD (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) in the fatigue group was lower than in the control group, but the activity of SOD and GSH-PX in the EOM group was higher than in the fatigue group and the PEO group (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05 or 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig7" href="#fig7">Figure 7</a> shows that the MDA in rats in the fatigue group was significantly higher than in the control group after swimming (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05). However, EOM treatment significantly decreased the MDA in comparison with the other groups (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01 or 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001).
 </p>
</sec>
