<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Chemicals and Reagents</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A glucose assay kit was purchased from the Shanghai Rongsheng Biotech Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). A blood urea nitrogen (BUN) kit, blood lactic acid (BLA) kit, superoxide dismutase (SOD) kit, glutathione peroxidase (GSH-PX) kit, and malondialdehyde (MDA) kit were from Nanjing Jiancheng Biotechnology Institute (Nanjing, China). All other chemicals used were of analytical grade.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Preparation of Essential Oils</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Peppermint essential oil, orange sweet essential oil, and rosemary essential oil were purchased from the Beijing Maosi Commercial and Trading Co., Ltd. (Beijing, China). The clove essential oil came from Aroma Zone Distributors, France. The countries of origin were France and Spain (peppermint); the US and Australia (orange); Spain and France (rosemary); and Madagascar (clove). The material safety data sheets were supplied by 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.afuvip.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.afuvip.com</span> or 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aroma-zone.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.aroma-zone.com</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil mixture was made up of
   <span class="italic"> Citrus sinensis</span>/orange peel oil,
   <span class="italic"> Mentha piperita</span>/peppermint leaf oil,
   <span class="italic"> Syzygium aromaticum</span>/clove bud oil, and
   <span class="italic"> Rosmarinus officinalis</span>/rosemary flower and leaf oil in equal amounts. The positive control inhalers contained peppermint leaf essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. GC-MS Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oils were analyzed by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) using a Shimadzu GCMS-QP 2010 gas chromatograph-mass spectrometer (Kyoto, Japan). The instrument conditions were as follows: GC conditions: analytical column: HP-5MS 30 m × 0.25 mm, 0.25 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>m 5% phenyl methyl silicone; injection temperature: 250°C; injection mode: split ratio set to 20 : 1; oven program: 2 min at 50°C, 8°C/min to 240°C; column flow: 1 ml/min constant flow; carrier gas: helium. MS conditions were as follows: ionization mode: electron impact at 70 eV; ion source temperature: 230°C; transfer line temperature: 280°C; acquisition mode: scan (30–550 amu).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Identification of Components</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage composition of the essential oils was computed from the GC peak areas. Most constituents were tentatively identified by comparison of their GC Kovats retention indices (RI), determined with reference to a homologous series of C5–C28 n-alkanes and with those of authentic standards. Further identification was made by matching with compounds in a NIST Mass Spectral Library.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Animals</div>
  <sec id="sec2.5.1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.1. Animals and Care</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 48 adult male Wistar rats (200 ± 20 g) were purchased from the Beijing Vital River Laboratory Animal Technology Co., Ltd. (Certificate: SCXK (Beijing) 2012-0001). All rats were housed in conventional cages in a temperature (22°C–24°C) and light-controlled (12-hour light- dark cycle) room for 7 days [
    <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>] with standard rat chow and water ad libitum [
    <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>]. The experimental protocol was approved by the local Animal Care Committee at the Beijing University of Chinese Medicine. All the experimental procedures were carried out in accordance with the international guidelines for the care and use of laboratory animals.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.5.2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.2. Grouping of Animal</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The animals were randomly divided into 4 groups, with 12 rats in each group. The groups were the control group, the fatigue group, the essential oil mixture (EOM) group, and the peppermint essential oil (PEO) group. The EOM and PEO groups were, respectively, nebulized with a mixture of essential oils and peppermint oil (0.4 ml/kg of body mass of each kind of oil) mixed with 2 ml of distilled water, according to the method validated by Chen et al. [
    <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>]. The control group and fatigue group were nebulized with an equal volume of distilled water. All groups were nebulized 10 minutes after the end of swimming to exhaustion.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2.5.3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.3. Rat Fatigue Model</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Loaded swimming to exhaustion was selected as the fatigue model and evaluation index. Xiaoming et al. [
    <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>] noted that swimming has more advantages than other exercises such as the treadmill because training is not required since rodents have a natural swimming ability, and they would try to struggle to avoid drowning even when fatigue is extreme, assuring a high level of performance.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After 7 days acclimation, the weight loaded swimming to exhaustion was carried out as described by Chi et al. [
    <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>] with slight modifications. All of the rats were removed from the fatigue group, EOM group, and PEO group for the swimming to exhaustion in a pool (length 65 cm, width 50 cm, depth 50 cm, water depth 30 cm, and temperature 25 ± 1°C). A lead block (10% of body weight) was attached to the tail root of the swimming rat [
    <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>]. The rats were determined to be exhausted when they failed to rise to the surface to breathe after 7 s [
    <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>]. The rats in the control group were normally raised without any treatment until the end of the experiment. Swimming to exhaustion started at 5 p.m. every day for three days. All rats were fasted 12 hours before bleeding.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Swimming to Exhaustion Test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the rats were removed from each experimental group and made to swim while carrying a load. The swimming equipment and methods are consistent with the previously mentioned protocol.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The standard for exhaustion was submersion in the water for 7 s without the surfacing of the head. When a rat was placed on a plane, it was not able to complete the righting reflex. The swimming time was immediately recorded.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Assay of Biochemical Parameters</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After swimming, a blood sample was collected from the rats in a common tube by abdominal aortic access for the determination of blood glucose, BUN, BLA, SOD, GSH-PX, and MDA. The determination and method of operation were performed according to the recommended procedures provided with the kits.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2.8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.8. Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SPSS 17.0 software was utilized for the statistical analyses. The results were expressed as the mean ± standard deviation (SD). Differences between the treatment means were analyzed with Tukey's test for multiple comparisons. 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05 indicated a significant difference.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
