<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are many reports about plants to have the anti-melanogenic and antioxidant activity that decrease oxidative stress, which may have a high potential for the treatment of skin disorder. For example, the different extracts of aerial parts of 
 <italic class="italic">P. atlantica</italic> reduced oxidative stress, which may be attributed to the polyphenols, flavonoids, and anthocyanin widely found in the plant(
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>). In another study, the MeOH extract of 
 <italic class="italic">P. vera</italic> decreased the melanin secretion which was attributed to some antioxidant compounds in this plant. This study indicated the kojic acid, as a positive control, showed an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 0.05 mg/mL and higher concentrations of 
 <italic class="italic">P. vera</italic> can be used as an effective agent for skin disorders treatment such as melanoma cancer(
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>). Gourine, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. showed the aerial parts of 
 <italic class="italic">P. atlantica</italic> have the powerful antioxidant properties(
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>). Also MeOH and CH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>Cl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fractions of Nepeta satureioides indicated potential effects against melanin production in B16F10 melanoma cells and may contribute in cosmetic formulations of skin care products(
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>). The derivatives of kojic acid had inhibitory activity on tyrosinase. It seems that the presence of free hydroxyl group and methyl substitute in this compound confirmed inhibitory activity. In this study kojic acid (positive control) indicated an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 0.28 mM(
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>). The phenylpropanoid glycosides and flavonoids isolated from Teucrium polium L. var. gnaphalodes showed antioxidant and tyrosinase inhibitory activities. The authors exhibited jaranol showed the highest tyrosinase inhibitory activity (IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>0.041 mM) and poliumoside was the best antioxidant among the tested compounds. Kojic acid showed an IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 0.02 mM(
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>).
</p>
