<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to expanding into rangelands, where eastern redcedars reduce the amount of grazing land for cattle and sheep [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and browsing for wild ungulates [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], this species causes serious alterations in ecosystem services. For example, reductions in stream run-off and discharge are widespread where eastern redcedar is abundant [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. There is also evidence of alterations in nitrogen and carbon accumulation in eastern redcedar-encroached grasslands [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], and little or no increase in carbon storage in eastern redcedar soils on the Great Plains [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Additional ecosystem services that are reduced by niche- and range-expansion of eastern redcedar are bird populations that are grassland-dependent [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. In general, there is little evidence of resistance to encroachment by eastern redcedar due to diversity of competing plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. There are, however, considerable negative effects of eastern redcedar on the diversity of native plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], resulting in near monocultures of eastern redcedar (termed the ‘green glacier’ [
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]). The costs of removal of encroaching eastern redcedar are extremely high ([
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0242003.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], so alternative means of reducing their densities need to be sought.
</p>
