<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Jujube has a promising source of flavonoids, polysaccharides, terpenoids, saponins, nucleotides and others (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Here, the trophic ingredients having potential beneficial effects on hematopoietic function are highlighted. At present, a variety of flavonoids were isolated and identified in jujube (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Pawlowska et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2013</xref>). Flavonoids from jujube have been found to stimulate the expression of erythropoietin (EPO), a hormone stimulating blood production (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2011</xref>), and therefore we speculated that jujube flavonoid might be one of the active compounds that possessed the ability to induce the expression of EPO. Supporting this notion in the pHRE-Luc (the DNA promoter construct of 
 <italic>EPO</italic> gene, hypoxia response element) transfected cultured HEKT293T cells, the application of kaempferol at 10 μM for 24 h could significantly induce the transcriptional activity of pHRE-Luc with 127% of increase, as compared to control group (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, the quercetin-treated HepG2 cells showed a stimulation of EPO mRNA expression in a concentration-dependent manner (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Nishimura et al., 2017</xref>). Similarly, the protein level of HIF-1α was markedly up regulated at the treatment of 10 μM quercetin (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Nishimura et al., 2017</xref>). Indeed, kaempferol and quercetin derivatives, including kaempferol 3-O-rutinoside, quercetin, quercetin 3-O-rutinoside, quercetin 3-O-galactoside and quercetin 3-O-β-D-glucoside (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3A</xref>), were identified in jujube (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>). Therefore, jujube flavonoid can induce EPO expression, probably, through HIF-α protein accumulation. In addition, the combination of catalpol and puerarin with doses of 65.4 and 32.7 mg/kg, respectively, enhanced the expressions of EPO and EPO receptor in ischemic/reperfusion rats (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Xue et al., 2016</xref>). In parallel, puerarin was identified in the seeds of jujube (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2000</xref>). Flavonoids are common chemical presented in a wide range of plants. Plant extracts rich in aforesaid flavonoids are considered, therefore, potentially useful as therapeutic agents for anemia.
</p>
