<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>COVID-19 symptoms appear after an incubation period of around 2–14 days. The duration from the onset of symptoms to death has ranged from 6 to 41 days. However, this duration is dependent on both the age of the patient and the status of their immune system [
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Patients over 70 years of age seem to be more susceptible to this virus, probably as a result of a weaker immune system [
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 infection has been associated with many symptoms and clinical signs. However, based on hospitalised data, patients mainly exhibited symptoms of acute respiratory distress syndrome, associated with pyrexia, cough, fever and fatigue [
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Additionally, one study found that approximately 80% of patients reported being asymptomatic or with mild symptoms (
 <italic>n</italic> = 19). The remaining 20% of cases, however, were more critical and severe [
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. COVID-19 has shown similar clinical presentations to that of its predecessors; however, in contrast to SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, COVID-19 seems to have a lower fatality rate [
 <xref rid="B3-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Despite there being limited information regarding the innate immune response of patients with COVID-19, most studies have shown that patients often develop lymphopenia [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A recent study investigating 99 patient cases in Wuhan demonstrated an increase in neutrophils (38%), lymphopenia (35%), increased IL-6 (52%) as well as an increase in C- reactive protein in 84% of cases [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Moreover, this increase in neutrophils and a decrease in lymphocytes have proven to directly correlate with both disease severity and fatality [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In addition, patients who had severe SARS-CoV-2 infection also presented with high levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-7, IL-10, IL-2, G-CSF, MCP-1, MIP-1A and TNFα. These findings correlate with the clinical profile of SARS-CoV-1 and MERS-CoV, thus suggesting that lymphopenia and the presence of a cytokine storm contributed to the pathogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B17-nutrients-12-02573" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
