<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">In this study, the reduction of ferric ion (Fe
 <sup>3+</sup>) to ferrous ion (Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>) was measured by the methanolic and aqueous extracts of spices by the intensity of the resultant Prussian blue color complex which absorbs at 700 nm. The presence of antioxidants in the methanol and aqueous extracts of the spices were able to convert the oxidized form of Fe
 <sup>3+</sup> into Fe
 <sup>2+</sup>. The higher absorbance at high concentration indicates the strong reducing capacity. Results of this study showed that all spices' extracts exhibited a noticeable concentration-dependent reducing power though reducing power was differed between spices and extraction solvents used. In most cases, methanol extracts had stronger ferric reducing antioxidant power than the aqueous extracts. Interestingly methanol and aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>L. adoensis</italic> with absorbances of 0.98 and 0.72, respectively possessed more pronounced reducing capacity than that of BHT (absorbance, 0.543) and ascorbic acid (absorbance, 0.542) at 1000 μg/mL. The findings of reducing capacity indicate that the noticeable ferric reducing power of the extracts of the tested spices appear to be due to the presence of polyphenols in the extracts, which may exert their action by breaking free radical chain by donating a hydrogen atom (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Duh et al., 1999</xref>). In our research, correlation analysis between total phenolic content of aqueous extracts and ferric reducing capacity was performed and a strong positive correlation (r
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.942, 
 <italic>P</italic> = .017) was observed. However, the correlation between total phenolic content of methanol extracts and reducing power was relatively lower (r
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.620, 
 <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05). Correlation coefficient value of higher than 0.61 and lower than 0.9715 is considered as the high positive correlation (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Thaipong et al., 2006</xref>).
</p>
