<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The group of Chiralt [
 <xref rid="B156-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B159-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">160</xref>] has also intensively worked toward the incorporation of antimicrobial essential oils in starch-based materials for their use as preservative coatings or packaging systems. Moreover, they have also introduced proteins into starch [
 <xref rid="B161-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">161</xref>], such as lactoferrin and lysozyme, as efficient antioxidant/antimicrobial systems [
 <xref rid="B162-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">162</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>]. In this sense, the co-encapsulation of herb extracts and lysozyme into such polysaccharides as starch, chitosan, and alginate has been demonstrated to produce more stability and durability during storage [
 <xref rid="B164-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">164</xref>]. Besides this, these particles were more effective against Gram-positive 
 <italic class="italic">B. subtilis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Micrococcus luteus</italic> bacteria and Gram-negative 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Serratia marcescens</italic> bacteria. Starch was also modified with octenyl succinic anhydride for microencapsulation by electrospray, in combination with gum Arabic and nutmeg oleoresin [
 <xref rid="B165-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">165</xref>]. They exhibit excellent antioxidant activity and a high retention of phenolic and flavonoid content after 60 days of storage as well as antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and Gram-positive 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus cereus</italic> bacteria. This modification of starch was also used to stabilize emulsions of nisin and thymol (2-isopropyl-5-methylphenol) (an isomer of carvacrol) cantaloupe juice [
 <xref rid="B166-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">166</xref>]. The addition of modified starch to the juice increases its capacity to retain nisin and thymol over the storage period and to inhibit the growth of Gram-positive 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium.
</p>
