<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several widely distributed African medicinal plants with long history in therapeutic use, are employed in the management of different infectious diseases 
 <bold>(</bold>
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref>–
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>
 <bold>)</bold> and many of them are being repurposed for COVID-19 by herbal firms and local healthcare providers in Africa. Some of such plants e.g 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> plant species including 
 <italic>Artemisia abrotanum</italic> L. (Asteracea), 
 <italic>Artemisia caruifolia</italic> Buch. -Ham. ex Roxb (Asteracea), 
 <italic>Artemisia pontica L.</italic> (Asteracea), 
 <italic>Artemisia herba-alba</italic> Asso (Compositae)
 <italic>, Artemisia absinthium</italic> L. (Asteracea), 
 <italic>Artemisia afra</italic> Jacq (Asteraceae) significantly inhibits CYP3A4 (
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">Lazaridi, 2014</xref>). Aqueous infusions (3.3 mg/L) of 
 <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> displays significant reduction in the CYP3A4 activity (
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">Lazaridi, 2014</xref>). Many of the plants applied in TAM accumulate bioactive polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) such as linoleic 
 <bold>(75)</bold>, linolenic 
 <bold>(74)</bold>, docosahexaenic acid 
 <bold>(67)</bold> which have been reported to have profound inhibitory effect on CYP3A4. Linoleic 
 <bold>(75)</bold> and linolenic acid 
 <bold>(74)</bold> are the most common acids found in plants of the 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> family. 
 <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> is the main active component of the claimed anti-COVID-19 herbal formulation popularly called COVID organics by Madagascar. In another study, 75, 52 and 5% of CYP3A4 were respectively inhibited by100 μg/mL grapefruit oil, Eucalyptol 
 <bold>(77)</bold> and menthol 
 <bold>(65)</bold> (
 <xref rid="B290" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Lim, 2008</xref>). Curcumin 
 <bold>(72)</bold> (40 µM), 6-gingerol 
 <bold>(79)</bold> (100 µM), citral 
 <bold>(78)</bold> (250 µM), d-limonene 
 <bold>(64)</bold> (400 µM), β-caryophyllene 
 <bold>(66)</bold> (500 µM), 1,8-cineole 
 <bold>(77)</bold> (1 mM), myrcene (1 mM) shows inhibitory effect on CYP3A4; piperine 
 <bold>(76)</bold> has been shown to enhance bioavailability (
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">Lutgen, 2016</xref>). These bioactive plant metabolites which have demonstrated antiviral properties have been reported in several plants used in TAM for the symptomatic treatment of COVID-19 in Nigeria (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). This means the co-administration of these herbal medicines with orthodox drugs used in COVID-19 management could result in herb-drug interaction that potentially may be hepatotoxic. However, this area of study has not received adequate scientific attention, particularly by 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments and should be of research interest in future.
</p>
