<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">
   <italic>Streptococcus agalactiae</italic> (
   <italic>S. agalactiae</italic>) is a contagious pathogen of bovine mastitis. It has financial implications for the dairy cattle industry in certain areas of the world. Since antimicrobial resistance increases in dairy farms, natural antimicrobials from herbal origins and nanoparticles have been given more attention as an alternative therapy. Hence, this study reported the antimicrobial and antibiofilm potentials of cinnamon oil, silver nanoparticles (AgNPs), and their combination against multidrug-resistant (MDR) 
   <italic>S. agalactiae</italic> recovered from clinical bovine mastitis in Egypt.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par2">Our findings revealed that 73% (146/200) of the examined milk samples collected from dairy cows with clinical mastitis were infected with 
   <italic>Streptococci</italic> species. Of these, 9.59% (14/146) were identified as 
   <italic>S. agalactiae</italic> and categorized as MDR. 
   <italic>S. agalactiae</italic> isolates expressed four virulence genes (
   <italic>Hyl</italic>, 
   <italic>cylE</italic>, 
   <italic>scpB</italic>, and 
   <italic>lmb)</italic> and demonstrated an ability to produce biofilms. Cinnamon oil showed high antimicrobial (MICs ≤0.063 μg /mL) and antibiofilm (MBIC
   <sub>50</sub> = 4 μg/mL) potentials against planktonic and biofilms of S. agalactiae isolates, respectively. However, AgNPs showed reasonable antimicrobial (MICs ≤16 μg/mL) and relatively low antibiofilm (MBIC
   <sub>50</sub> = 64 μg/mL) activities against screened isolates. Synergistic antimicrobial or additive antibiofilm interactions of cinnamon oil combined with AgNPs were reported for the first time. Scanning electron microscope (SEM) analysis revealed that biofilms of 
   <italic>S. agalactiae</italic> isolates treated with cinnamon oil were more seriously damaged than observed in AgNPs cinnamon oil combination. Moreover, reverse transcriptase quantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR) showed that cinnamon oil exerted a remarkable down-regulation of pili biosynthesis genes (
   <italic>pilA</italic> and 
   <italic>pilB</italic>) and their regulator (
   <italic>rogB</italic>) against 
   <italic>S. agalactiae</italic> biofilms, meanwhile the AgNPs cinnamon oil combination demonstrated a lower efficacy.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par3">This is an in vitro preliminary approach that documented the antibiofilm potential of cinnamon oil and the inhibitory activity of cinnamon oil and its combination with AgNPs against MDR 
   <italic>S. agalactiae</italic> recovered from clinical mastitis. Further in vivo studies should be carried out in animal models to provide evidence of concept for implementing these alternative candidates in the treatment of dairy farms infected by streptococcal mastitis in the future.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Supplementary Information</title>
  <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12917-021-02842-9.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
