<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We performed the in vitro antibiotic-containing culture of 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic> to decontaminate DNA sequences other than 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic>. Micropropagation and tissue culture of 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> species have been documented for 
 <italic>M. glomerate</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and 
 <italic>M. micrantha</italic> [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Both exogenous and endogenous microbes have been noted as the greatest challenge in the micropropagation of 
 <italic>M. glomerate</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The same case is with 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic>. Eed et al. show that incorporating antibiotics into the in vitro culture may offer a solution to produce aseptic 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic> plantlets [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Since fungicides are highly toxic for plants [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], this study only utilized antibiotics to inhibit bacterial growth in micropropagation. The survival rate of explants increased to 65% with 1 g·L
 <sup>−1</sup> CTX treatment. Similarly, the survival rate was also increased to 50% under the treatment of 0.6 g·L
 <sup>−1</sup> TIM. Among the viable plantlets, the germination rate was above 80% in both treatments. During the rooting phase, the rooting rate with the treatment of 0.5 g·L
 <sup>−1</sup> CTX was sharply decreased to 55% in comparison to the 100% rooting rate under the treatment of 0.3 g·L
 <sup>−1</sup> TIM. CTX was observed to have toxic effects on the root growth of 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic>. Similar results have been reported for orange [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and tobacco [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. It is of note that the rooting ability was recovered after the nonrooting plantlets were transferred to TIM-containing media. Though the latent or exogenous microbes reappeared on a few cultures (~5%), most plantlets were microbial-free during large-scale propagation and maintenance. These results indicated that antibiotics were able to inhibit the growth of bacteria in the long term [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Overall, CTX showed more effectiveness at the initial cultivation of 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic> to control endophytes than TIM, but it had an inhibitory effect on rooting. In contrast, TIM did not affect the rooting of 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic>, which has also been demonstrated in tobacco [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and tomato [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. As for fungi, they may be eliminated by chance in culture in batches. Previous studies have shown that culturing multiple explants represents an effective way to produce fungal endophyte-free explants for 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> plants [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01665" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In line with this, a batch of aseptic 
 <italic>M. cordata</italic> was obtained for genome sequencing.
</p>
