<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Self-emulsifying formulations are isotropic mixtures of an active drug compound in a combination of lipids, surfactants, and water soluble co-solvents that produce ultrafine emulsions upon gentle agitation in aqueous phase, such as the upper GI lumen content (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fatouros et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kale and Patravale, 2008</xref>). Generally, self-emulsifying formulations are categorized as self-emulsifying (SEDDS), self-microemulsifying (SMEDDS) and self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery systems (SNEDDSs). SEDDS, SMEDDS, and SNEDDS can be differentiated basically according to their size of globules upon aqueous dispersion (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pouton, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pouton and Porter, 2008</xref>). A lipid formulation classification system (LFCS) based on the composition was developed which categorized the LBF into four different types (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pouton, 2000</xref>). The LFCS explains the formation of different types of self-emulsifying formulations in a very simple way based on their types and compositions. Briefly, Type I formulations represent 100% pure oil (surfactant free) as component. Types II and IIIA systems contain water insoluble surfactants (HLB &lt; 10) with different % oil in the formulation (Type II contain 60–80% oil and Type IIIA contain 40–60% oil). Type IIIB formulations contain water soluble surfactant and oil (20–50% oil), whereas Type IV formulations contain only water soluble surfactant/cosolvent without oil. In board terms, the Type II and/or Type IIIA formulations spontaneously forms SEDDS emulsions (translucent) with a droplet size ranging from 250 nm to 1.0 μm. SMEDDS refers to the formulations which form transparent microemulsions (oil-in-water/water-in-oil) with a particle diameter of 50 nm or less, belong to Type IIIB and or Type IV. On the other hand, SNEDDS is a relatively newer term representing the droplet size between 20 and 200 nm, provides also transparent appearance. The drug encapsulated as liquid dosage forms can be in a thermodynamically and kinetically stable form as SNEDDS (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kang et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Elgart et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
