<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is therefore essential for any study using chemical data extracted from herbarium materials to test for potential age effects on results in order to verify interpretations (Jafari et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). Only few studies to date have systematically tested the stability of different compound classes in historical herbarium samples. An early study by Eloff (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>) showed no sample age effect on antibacterial activity of herbarium samples of 
 <italic class="italic">Combretum erythophyllum</italic> (Burch.) Sond. and 
 <italic class="italic">Helichrysum pedunculatum</italic> Hilliard &amp; B.L. Burtt over almost 100 years and only minor differences were observed in chemical composition of flavonoids and terpenoids using thin layer chromatography (TLC). Using proton nuclear magnetic resonance (
 <sup class="sup">1H</sup>NMR) spectroscopic metabolite screening, Jafari et al. (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>) found no significant difference in metabolite profiles of recently dried and up to 25 year old fungi specimens. Cook et al. (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) found no age effect on toxic diterpenoid alkaloid composition of 
 <italic class="italic">Delphinium occidentale</italic> S. Watson from up to 100 year old herbarium specimens and Yilmaz et al. (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) found no significant degradation of quinine alkaloids in 50–150 years old historical Cinchonae bark samples. Likewise, a study by Zangerl and Berenbaum (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>) found no sampling age effect on furanocoumarins in the phototoxic invasive 
 <italic class="italic">Pastinaca sativa</italic> L. over 150 years. Consequently, these previous studies support the idea that herbarium specimens provide a significant untapped resource of chemical data in addition to data on distribution and morphological traits over time and space.
</p>
