<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Viola pilosa</italic> Blume, 
 <italic>Diospyros lotus</italic> L., 
 <italic>Morchella esculenta</italic> Fr., 
 <italic>Trillium govanianum</italic> Wall. Ex D. Don are the most important medicinal species produced in Pakistan [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The knowledge of medicinal species has mostly been transmitted orally from generation to generation [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Cultural practices and local biodiversity are the driving factors of medicinal species are utilization [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Ethnomedicinal research can serve as the basis for the development of new natural remedies for native plant species [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In Pakistan, local market systems named “Pansar” specifically deal with medicinal species, including the export of important quantities of plants [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The utilization of plants as medication varies from 4 to 20% in various nations, and around 2500 species are traded globally [
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In Pakistan alone, about 50,000 Ayurvedic specialists, tabibs (experts of Unani medicine), and many unregistered health experts are working in far-flung mountainous and urban areas making common use of around 200 plant species in herbal medications [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Botanical gardens, universities, and the National Council for Tibb, Hamdard, and Qarshi industries help to control and develop the herbal industry in Pakistan. There are over 4000 registered manufacturers of herbal marketable products in the country [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-09-01001" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
