<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par61">
 <italic>Asarum</italic> is a sciophyte that grows in habitats with reduced sunlight. Volatile oil is an essential component of its extracts that have importance as antifungal, antibacterial, antidepressant, and anxiolytic effects. Despite its medicinal importance and availability, only a limited knowledge exists about the effect of light conditions on the biosynthesis of volatile oil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Hence, it is important to understand if the 
 <italic>Asarum</italic> volatile oil components’ are affected by growing this plant in full sunlight conditions. Recent work has shown that the composition of volatile oil detected through LC-MS was different under different light conditions but the total volatile oil content did not significantly differ among the 
 <italic>Asarum</italic> plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Our results demonstrated that the individual percent content of each of the four components showed the positive effect of full sunlight conditions as compared to reduced light intensities. To understand the effect of light on the phenylpropanoid pathway, we searched for DEGs that were significantly enriched under the tested conditions. The established phenylpropanoid pathway has shown that coniferyl aldehyde is converted into coniferyl alcohol by the reaction of CAD which is an important step for the subsequent formation of methyleugenol, safrole, and myristicin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Two CADs were highly expressed in full sunlight conditions; one in full to 50% and one in full to 28% sunlight conditions. Therefore, the higher accumulation of these three components in the full sunlight conditions suggests that higher light intensities affect the volatile oil formation by increasing the CAD expression. Alternatively, the coniferyl alcohol can also be converted to lignin by the action of peroxidases. Therefore, the upregulation of CADs in 
 <italic>Asarum</italic> leaves grown under higher light intensities (full sunlight) would lead to higher lignin content. In this regard, the upregulation of a peroxidase responsible for the lignin formation suggested that under higher light intensities, higher lignin content is produced in the 
 <italic>Asarum</italic> leaves. This observation is similar with those of heliophytes where it is known that leaf lignin content increases with the increasing light intensities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Once, the methyleugenol is formed, it can further be converted into safrole and then into myristicin. The formation of safrole is under the control of cytochrome p450s (specifically CYP719As) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. We found the upregulation of two CYP719As in higher light intensity (50%) to lower light intensity (12%) (Additional Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>) which may explain the higher safrole content and subsequently myristicin content in high light intensity. The fourth major component i.e. toluene is synthesized from orcinol by the action of orcinol-OMTs in rose. However, very little is known about the biosynthesis of orcinol, which is hydroxylated in position 3 and 5 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Some studies have reported that orcinol is biosynthesized by the monolignol biosynthetic pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. A recent study on 
 <italic>Rhododendron dauricum</italic> L. demonstrated that orcinol is produced from tetraketide non-enzymatically by decarboxylative aldol condensation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. In our results, no OMT was differentially regulated between full sunlight and 50% or 28% light conditions. However, two OMTs (one protein L-isoaspartyl methyltransferase (PIMT) and one trans-resveratrol di-O-methyltransferase (ROMT)) were differentially regulated between full and 12% sunlight conditions (Additional Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>). PIMT was downregulated while the ROMT was upregulated. ROMT is implicated in stilbene pathway where it catalyses the biosynthesis of pterostilbene from resveratrol in grapevine and our KEGG pathway mapping was also in agreement with this study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Based on the percent content observations, it is found that somehow light affects toluene content but the pathway and the genes involved in this increase needs specific studies or a different approach. Altogether, these results propose that the light treatment had a positive effect on the contents of the four volatile oil component. 
</p>
