<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is well-known that UV radiation with wavelengths in the 220–280 nm range is capable of inhibiting microbial growth by inducing the formation of DNA thymine dimers. Indeed, UV light has been used for years for the decontamination of water, air and surfaces. However, the contribution of UV radiation to the antimicrobial effect of plasmas obtained at atmospheric pressure is controversial. Thus, although some researchers hypothesize that UV-C radiation present in plasma plays an important inactivating role (Boudam et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Eto et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Muranyi et al., 
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>), most authors (Laroussi and Leipold, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>; Deng et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Dobrynin et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Joshi et al., 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Miao and Yun, 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Reineke et al., 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) believe that UV radiations are not generated at the most effective wavelengths or are absorbed by the gas molecules themselves (Reineke et al., 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) and, therefore, are not involved in microbial inactivation (Patil et al., 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Surowsky et al., 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Indeed, Reineke et al. (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) compared the effectiveness of different plasmas for the inactivation of 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus atrophaeus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus subtilis</italic> spores and found that, although plasmas containing oxygen and nitrogen emitted four times more UV radiation than pure argon plasmas, the greatest lethal effect was achieved when pure argon was used as the working gas. These authors suggested that the antimicrobial effect was determined by reactive species of oxygen and nitrogen generated in the pure gas, and especially by hydroxyl radicals. Other authors have also tested the contribution of UV light by exposing 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> cells (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Gweon et al., 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus cereus</italic> (van Bokhorst-van de Veen et al., 
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">B. subtilis</italic> spores (Hong et al., 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) to the action of plasma by intercalating between the plasma generation point and the treatment medium a lithium fluoride filter or a fused silica quartz plate transparent to UV light, which allows cell/spore exposure to the radiation potentially emitted by the plasma source but avoids contact with chemical reactive species. These studies demonstrated that the contribution of UV light to microbial inactivation was negligible, compared to that observed for direct exposition to plasma. In addition, exposure of 
 <italic class="italic">B. cereus</italic> vegetative cells to nitrogen plasma has been shown to result in a transcriptional response in which the expression of genes involved in UV damage repair (
 <italic class="italic">uvrA, uvrB</italic>) was unaffected, while various genes involved in the response to oxidative stress, such as those encoding nitric oxide dioxygenase, as well as membrane-associated enzymes that catalyze oxidation-reduction reactions, were overexpressed (Mols et al., 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Finally, it has also been shown that microorganisms exhibiting variability in resistance to UV light exhibit a similar tolerance against NTAP. For instance, although 
 <italic class="italic">B. cereus</italic> spores were more sensitive to UV light than spores of 
 <italic class="italic">Geobacillus stearothermophilus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">B. atrophaeus</italic>, a given NTAP treatment produced a similar degree of inactivation for the three species (van Bokhorst-van de Veen et al., 
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), suggesting that the mechanism of inactivation through both technologies was different.
</p>
