<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Results from this study revealed that appropriate dosage of EOM improves rumen degradability and microbial activity. Cinnamaldehyde consisting EOM has been known to bind to feed proteins and inhibit the amino acid decarboxylase in 
 <italic class="italic">Enterobacter aerogenes</italic> by disturbing energy metabolism of bacterial cells [
 <xref rid="b21-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. However, NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>-N significantly increased in response to supplementation of the high dose of EOM. Ammonia nitrogen is an end product generated by microbial fermentation of protein sources in the feed. In the previous studies, the NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>-N was not affected by the addition of BEO [
 <xref rid="b9-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="b22-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] and, Benchaar et al [
 <xref rid="b2-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>] did not observe any significant changes in NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>-N concentrations when EOs or EOCs were added to substrates. Furthermore, Busquet et al [
 <xref rid="b6-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] reported that the addition of eugenol and cinnamaldehyde to substrates at over doses of 300 mg/L, decreased NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>-N concentrations. Considering that our dosage level of EOM 0.2 was 30 mg/L, it is postulated that the dosage level of EOM in this study might be too low to modulate microbial degradative action on protein sources. Newbold et al [
 <xref rid="b23-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] reported that defaunation of protozoa significantly decreased the rumen NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>-N concentration (−26%, p&lt;0.001), indicating that, in this study, the increase of relative fold change of ciliate protozoa with an increase in the level of EOM supplementation might be linked with a higher concentration of NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>-N in EOM treatments than those in CON.
</p>
