<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In present study, an increased IVDMD and IVNDFD were observed in groups treated with EOM after 24-h incubation (
 <xref rid="t3-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). Regarding with IVDMD, Benchaar et al [
 <xref rid="b2-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>] observed a significant decrease, when diets were supplemented with carvacrol (400 mg/L) and eugenol (800 mg/L) (p&lt;0.05), but other EO (cinnamon leaf oil, clove leaf oil, sweet orange oil, oregano oil, and thyme oil) and EOC (cinnamaldehyde and thymol) had no effect on IVDMD in an 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> batch culture system after 24 h incubation. Castillejos et al [
 <xref rid="b9-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] reported that IVDMD was not changed by supplementation of EOM containing thymol, limonene, and guaiacol in an 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> continuous culture system. Benchaar et al [
 <xref rid="b2-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>], Castillejos et al [
 <xref rid="b7-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], and Fraser et al [
 <xref rid="b10-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] observed a decrease in IVNDFD, and Benchaar et al [
 <xref rid="b2-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>] explained that fibrolytic bacteria might be sensitive to high concentrations of phenolic compounds in EO thereby fiber digestibility might be impaired by EO supplementation. 
 <italic class="italic">Fibrobacter succinogenes</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus flavefaciens</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus albus</italic> are the bacteria constituting 33.0%, 2.6%, and 46.0%, respectively, of the rumen fibrolytic bacteria [
 <xref rid="b24-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="b25-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Rumen ciliate protozoa have been known to have fibrolytic activity [
 <xref rid="b23-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], and the fungi in the rumen have also been considered to produce fibrolytic enzymes [
 <xref rid="b26-ajas-18-0652" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. In the present study, EOM 0.1 significantly increased the fold change of 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus albus</italic> (p = 0.005) and increased that of 
 <italic class="italic">Fibrobacter succinogenes</italic> in a quadratic manner (p = 0.047). EOM 0.2 significantly increased the fold change of ciliate protozoa (p&lt;0.001), 
 <italic class="italic">Butyrivibrio fibrisolvens</italic> (p&lt;0.001), fungi (p = 0.001), and 
 <italic class="italic">Ruminococcus flavefaciens</italic> (p&lt;0.001). Thus, the EOM used in this study may promote fibrolytic bacterial, protozoa, and fungal growth by unknown synergistic effect between chemical compounds and the main EO in the newly developed EOM, thereby improving ruminal degradability.
</p>
