<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <bold class="bold">Antigenotoxic evidence for ginger and its phytochemical (Gingerol):</bold> Despite the common and local consumption of ginger as a food condiment, some studies analyze its protective effects against the damage produced by genotoxic substances. The main evidence that suggests its antigenotoxic potential has emerged due to its antioxidant capacity. One of the first studies was the investigation performed by Odunola (2003) [
 <xref rid="B108-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>], who evaluated the modulatory effect of the aqueous extracts of some food condiments (garlic, ginger, sconio, and cloves) on the clastogenic effects of sodium arsenite in mouse bone marrow cells using the micronucleus assay. The results were brief and confirmed that a pre-treatment of mice for seven days with extracts of the condiments orally administered before the oral dose of sodium arsenite (2.5 mg/kg) markedly reduced the number of MNPE of the bone marrow. The degree of reduction of the clastogenic effect of arsenite was as follows: Ginger &gt; garlic &gt; cloves &gt; sconio. His conclusion was that this reduction of arsenite-induced clastogenicity by aqueous extracts of the condiments might be partially due to the antioxidant properties of their chemical constituents. Later, Bidinotto et al. [
 <xref rid="B109-nutrients-10-01954" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>] evaluated the chemoprotective effect of a ginger extract (GE) on the DNA damage induced by N-butyl-N-(4-hydroxibutyl) nitrosamine (BBN)/N-methyl-N-nitrosourea (MNU) in Swiss mice using the comet assay as well as the same technique that was used in the previous study.The animals were fed for 18 weeks with diets containing ginger extract (1% and 2%) and applied four intraperitoneal injections of MNU and a continuous treatment of BBN. The results were that the GE is not a genotoxic agent and does not reduce or alter the levels of DNA damage induced by the BBN/MNU treatment during the exposure.
</p>
