<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Elemental composition of 12 commercially available tilapia samples in U.S. marketplace was analyzed. Among the main elements studied, K had the highest concentration followed by P, Na, Ca, Mg. Previous study has shown that higher concentration of Na than K in the diet can significantly increase the risk of cardiovascular disease [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Concentration of Na was lower than K in all the tilapia fillets samples of the present study demonstrating that these products from marketplace are good choice of a meal for a healthy diet. Total concentrations of As, Cd and Hg were measured and compared to food safety standards showing that the studied fish products do not pose health risks associated with heavy metal exposures. Cadmium concentration in all the samples were below detection limits which agrees with previous research that found only trace amounts of Cd in tissues of aquatic organisms [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. In nature, As exists in both organic (i.e. arsenobetaine and arsenocholine) and inorganic forms, however in fish tissue it is present mostly in organic forms which are less toxic than the inorganic species [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Tilapia fillet total As (organic and inorganic) concentration was significantly lower(
 <italic class="italic">p&gt;0</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">05</italic>). than USEPA limit of 1.3 mg kg
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> (wet weight) in freshwater fish for human health protection [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Mercury is one of the most toxic heavy metals in the environment. Methylmercury (MeHg) is a contaminant in fish that can pose risks to humans. High MeHg exposures can have severely adverse effects on the central nervous system, particularly the developing brain of a fetus [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. However, instead of harm, epidemiological studies have consistently found that increasing Hg exposures from maternal consumption of ocean fish during pregnancy result in substantial maternal health benefits and improved neurological outcomes in their children [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Clearly, it is not the increased Hg exposures that were responsible for these positive health outcomes. Instead, the improved neurological development, motor abilities, verbal intelligence, perception, social behavior, and diminished hyperactivity appear to be due to improved maternal intakes of nutrients such as omega-3 fatty acids and Se which are abundant in ocean fish [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>].
</p>
