<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There were no significant differences in the FCR, weight gain, HSI, VSI, hepatic and plasma GPx activity, or in the intestinal microvilli length of fish from the different treatment groups. Similar results were observed in studies on Crucian carp (
 <italic class="italic">Carassius auratus gibelio</italic>), juvenile grouper (
 <italic class="italic">Epinephelus malabaricus)</italic> and rainbow trout (
 <italic class="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss)</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. However, as we hypothesized, feeding the organic form of Se led to a significant increase in Se concentrations observed in kidney, plasma and fillets of the fish. This appears to be due to differences in the absorption, bioaccumulation and bioavailability of different species of Se (organic and inorganic) [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Selenomethionine (SeMet), an organic form of Se that was used in this study, is readily absorbed by erythrocytes through the same active mechanism that incorporates methionine (Met), the more abundant sulfur analogue. Since Met and SeMet are incorporated into cellular proteins for repeated protein synthesis cycles until they are eventually degraded several weeks to several months later, organic Se fed in this form tends to be retained for extended periods of time. In contrast, sodium selenite, an inorganic form of Se, is digestively absorbed and rapidly incorporated into Sec. Since Sec cannot be reused in protein synthesis but must instead be actively degraded into inorganic metabolites which are readily excreted when sufficient Se is available, dietary Se provided in the inorganic form is retained to lesser extents in the muscles and is excreted in higher concentrations than organic Se. Because Met and SeMet are immediately incorporated into tissues with high levels of protein synthesis such as skeletal muscles, liver, and kidney, these tissues accumulate greater amounts of Se [
 <xref rid="pone.0217043.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Since no significant differences in GPX activity were noted between the two treatment groups, this confirms that the diets were Se-replete.
</p>
