<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015" class="p">Nutritional components generally analysed are carbohydrates, proteins, fat, fibers, ash, vitamins, minerals and dry matter. Carbohydrates hold a special place in human nutrition providing the largest single source of energy in the diet and satisfying instinctual desire for sweetness (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brand-Miller, 2002</xref>). A high carbohydrate content is a major source of readily available energy (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Assogbadjo et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bamidele et al., 2015</xref>). Proteins are fundamental elements for metabolism of enzymes, hormones and many other molecules essential for life. Proteins are composed of 20 amino acids of which nine are essential and need to be provided through the diet (histidine, isoleucine, leucine, lysine, methionine, phenylalanine, threonine, tryptophan and valine). In early childhood a number of amino acids, which are not essential in adults, cannot be formed in adequate amounts. These are conditionally essential, because of the limited ability of their endogenous formation relative to the magnitude of demand (arginine, cysteine, glycine, glutamine, histidine, proline and tyrosine) (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jackson, 2002</xref>). There may be disease situations during adult life whereby a particular amino acid, or group of amino acids, becomes conditionally essential (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jackson, 2002</xref>). Some tree food species are promising as sources of dietary protein and amino acid supplement for domestic and industrial use (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Djenontin et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Igwenyi and Akubugwo, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lohlum, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ayessou et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Otori and Mann, 2014</xref>). Fats are a major source of energy and are the essential fuel for the brain and growing fetus (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stubbs et al., 2018</xref>). They enhance flavour and palatability of food and make an important contribution to health containing essential fatty acids that cannot be synthesized in the body and are furthermore required for a range of metabolic and physiological processes to maintain the structural and functional integrity of cell membranes (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mann and Skeaff, 2002</xref>). High content of fat make certain oils from native trees a good alternative or supplement to conventional oil (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bazongo et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Niyi, 2014</xref>). Fiber has many health benefits and can reduce diabetes (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bazongo et al., 2014</xref>) and high blood cholesterol (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2000</xref>). Ash content is obtained by burning away of organic materials and gives a measure of the contents inorganic minerals (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Adubiaro et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Amoo et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ayessou et al., 2014</xref>). High content of dry matter in food is an advantage for high shelve-life because it prevents microbial spoilage and pest attack during storage (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Magaia et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Honfo et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
