<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The link between nutrition, the gut microbiota and health has been expounded in the multitude of studies published in recent years. Long-term dietary habits appear to have the most profound influence on the quality of the gut microbiota and hence its efficacy to the human body. In this regard, healthy eating patterns with adequate fruits and vegetables, ensuring a rich source of dietary fibre, along with healthy fats (MUFAs and PUFAs) and a trend towards more plant-derived proteins should help promote gut microbiota diversity and functionality enabling it to effectively serve its host. But as countries become more industrialised and range of choice expands, including foods available for consumption, consumers tend to eat for taste-satisfaction and/or convenience at the cost of nutritional value in many instances. Furthermore, not everyone responds effectively to dietary interventions aimed at improving health. The consequence of this has been an alarming surge in non-communicable diseases, including cancer and metabolic-related diseases. Understanding the specific role of the gut microbiota in the diet-health sequence has enabled scientists and nutritionists to further comprehend how diet specifically impacts health at the individual level and why dietary interventions do not always serve everyone equally. Thus, modification of the gut microbiota through diet, probiotics and prebiotics may offer viable opportunities for preventing many of these ‘Western-associated’ diseases, particularly in the case of metabolic-related diseases for which microbiota quality and quantity can be an essential aspect. Indeed, Part II of this review looks at the efficacy of such interventions in terms of over/under nutrition. We also explore opportunities for optimising health at different life stages (elderly in nursing homes, during pregnancy, physically active individuals and those in high stress environments) through improved diet and interventions. In this regard, microbiome testing at the individual level has a significant role to play in interpreting how an individual responds to dietary components and what interventions should be undertaken to improve those responses for a healthier outcome, thus underpinning the very goal of precision nutrition. In Part II of this review, we also look at specific examples of how the microbiota is already being used as a biomarker to predict responsiveness to specific dietary constituents and highlight further research which is necessary to make precision nutrition through the microbiome a reality.</p>
