<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among the various alternatives of biomass-derived fuels, biodiesel is the most suitable for compression-ignition (diesel) engines [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Earlier, vegetable oils without transesterification were tested in this type of engines, but due to their higher viscosity they were not compatible for such operation [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. While transesterification solved the problem of viscosity, debates on “food vs. fuel” obstruct the utilization of vegetable oil feed stocks for biodiesel production [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The oils obtained from oleaginous microbes can substitute the vegetable oils for biodiesel production. The microbial oils comprise an intracellular product of different kind of oleaginous microorganisms such as bacteria, yeasts, algae, and fungi [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Among the different classes of microorganisms, yeasts are considered to be best suitable for lipid production, which can be used as feed stock for the production of biodiesel [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Oleaginous yeasts present various positive characteristics such as independency from weather conditions, high lipid productivity and the ability to utilize a wide range of inexpensive and renewable waste substrates derived from agricultural and industrial practices, which makes them an excellent choice for lipid production and the substitution of oily crops [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The majority of oleaginous yeasts demonstrate a preference to utilize glucose over other carbon sources that might be present and will not shift to the other sugars until glucose is fully utilized [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. This type of microorganisms have a carbon catabolite repression (CCR) mechanism that suppresses the utilization of other sugars when glucose is present and is responsible for the utilization of sugars in a sequential manner, which in turn is expressed as a delay in the growth when the microorganism is grown on a mixture of sugars [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. To permit a financially sustainable commercial application of oleaginous yeasts within the biofuel market, their cultivation must be supported by inexpensive raw materials such as non-edible lignocellulosic feedstocks. The hydrolysates obtained from various non-edible lignocellulosic feedstocks often contain a mixture of pentoses and hexoses [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. It is therefore economically advantageous for any process to incorporate the use of components in the lignocellulosic hydrolysates in a simultaneous manner. Unfortunately, co-utilization of various sugars by such microorganisms is rarely observed. However, certain oleaginous yeasts have the ability to utilize a mixture of sugar sources simultaneously. Oleaginous yeasts belonging to the 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodosporidium</italic> genera have been extensively studied for the simultaneous utilization of mixtures of sugars derived from lignocellulosic biomass [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. For this purpose, various strains belonging to the 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodosporidium</italic> genus have been grown on different types of non-edible lignocellulosic biomass such as rice straw, wheat straw, corn powder, cassava, Jerusalem artichoke, sugarcane, sweet sorghum, waste molasses, soy whey, and glycerol, a byproduct from biodiesel industries [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-03052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>].
</p>
