<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-20" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stability studies</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stability results are summarized in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>. Niosome size was not changed significantly during 3 months at 4 °C, a finding that confirmed physical stability of niosomal formulation in the above-mentioned condition as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>. Nonetheless, size of vesicles significantly was increased during storage time at 40 °C with RH of 70% (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, the results also showed that increasing the Chol content from 30 to 50 molar ratios enhances stability at 4 °C during 3 months. Furthermore, it has been revealed that smaller vesicles are thermodynamically unstable (
  <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">27</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Size distribution changes of niosomal myrtle essential oil during 3 months storage at different temperatures. (F1), S/T 40:Chol (70:30 molar ratio); (F2), S/T 40:Chol (60:40 molar ratio); (F3), S/T 40:Chol (50:50 molar ratio); (F4), S/T 60:Chol (70:30 molar ratio); (F5), S/T 60:Chol (60:40 molar ratio); (F6), S/T 60:Chol (50:50 molar ratio).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="RPS-13-250-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="T3" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Assessment of niosomal myrtle essential oil physical stability</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="RPS-13-250-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, therefore, relative stability of nMEO during 3 months storage at 4 °C is likely to be associated with large vesicle size of all prepared nMEO.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The maximum and minimum mean size changes, during 3 months storage was for F2 formulation stored at 40 °C with RH of 70%, and F6 formulation stored at 4 °C (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>), respectively. Thus, F6 formulation was considered as an optimum formulation because of good stability during storage and high EE%.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Size distribution changes of F6 formulation during storage at 4 °C as an indicator of physical stability of vesicles. (F6), S/T 60:Chol (50:50 molar ratio).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="RPS-13-250-g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
