<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Today’s consumers are becoming more aware of the link between diet and health. For instance, the Mediterranean diet possesses a plethora of bioactive phytochemicals, e.g., polyphenols and melatonin [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>], which can contribute to its beneficial effects against chronic-degenerative disorders, including cancer, cardiovascular diseases and diabetes [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. This trend is leading to increasing demand for the use of natural ingredients as food supplements and preservatives. In addition, an increasing number of microorganisms that are not only antibiotic resistant, but are more tolerant to existing preservative techniques is of worldwide concern [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Plant derived extracts that have biological activities, such as antimicrobial, antidiabetic or antihypertensive effects, have the potential to fulfill the need for safe natural preservatives [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Therefore, much emphasis has been put on the investigation of plant derived natural sources of antimicrobials, compounds that could potentially replace chemical preservatives and synthetic antimicrobial ingredients [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-22-02145" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
