<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Recreationists, including hikers, are known to contribute through their activities in the countryside to the spread and dispersal of invasive pests and diseases, including in woodland and forests. Thus, understanding how best to engage and communicate with such groups to encourage positive biosecurity behaviours is crucial for resilient treescapes. More broadly, for those concerned about biosecurity, recreationists and visitors to countryside areas can play an important role, not only in helping to avoid the introduction and spread of pests and pathogens, but also in ongoing risk mitigation and surveillance.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Principles for stakeholder engagement to encourage behavioural change emphasise the need to design engagement campaigns using the values and motivations of importance to the target group in order to effectively frame the issue. Further research is needed into the values and attitudes of hikers towards the environment, trees, diseases and good practice in the countryside; this will help to inform the design of biosecurity campaigns in GB and elsewhere. Linked to this point, engagement campaigns should place more emphasis on information exchange, learning from recreationists about their own experiences, concerns and observations. This reflects IPPC guidance on Pest Risk Communication which stresses that ‘
   <italic>pest risk communication is used to enable mutual understanding and dialogue among all stakeholders about plant health issues</italic>’ ([
   <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], P5).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Communicators need to use trusted information sources for communicating with hikers and other recreationists about biosecurity. It is well established that using trusted sources for communicating with the public about environmental challenges is important [
   <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It is important to note that information on its own is unlikely to lead to behaviour change [
   <xref rid="ETLS-4-531C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Successful biosecurity campaigns combined equipment with information provision.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Thus far, there has been a lack of evaluation of outreach and engagement programmes designed to encourage behaviour change. There is an urgent need to increase understanding of the effectiveness of such campaigns by combining on the ground activities with before and after studies of behaviours, ideally observed rather than self-reported. Further, principles of stakeholder engagement as described in many publications should be applied and tested with regard to biosecurity engagement campaigns.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
