<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, we turned our attention on the synthesis of novel 2- or 4-substituted 13α-oestrone derivatives. First ring A halogenations and then Pd-catalysed C–P cross-coupling reactions were carried out
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>. Hirao reaction is widely used for the synthesis of arylphosphonates from aryl halides
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>. Variations of the reaction have been described under traditional thermal conditions or microwave-irradiation
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20–22</sup>
 </xref>. Dialkyl phosphites are usually used as the reagents, Pd(PPh
 <sub>3</sub>)
 <sub>4</sub> as the catalyst and Et
 <sub>3</sub>N as the base. Our certain novel halo and phosphono 13α-oestrone derivatives displayed outstanding inhibitory activities against enzymes (steroid sulfatase, STS and 17β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 1, 17β-HSD1) involved in oestrogen biosynthesis. Concerning oestrogen-dependent diseases, the suppression of local oestrogen production might serve as an effective therapy. This strategy might be intensified by the inhibition of polypeptides transporting organic anions (OATPs), which are able to transport oestrone-3-sulfate (E1S) into cells
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref>. The desulphation of E1S and the stereospecific reduction of E1 result in E2 with a marked cell proliferative potential. Certain OATPs, known as E1S transporters, are overexpressed, among others, in breast and ovarian tumours. It is of note that both 2-bromo- and 4-bromo-13α-oestrone derivatives (
 <bold>5</bold> and 
 <bold>6</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>), synthesised recently, exerted outstanding 17β-HSD1 inhibition (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = ∼ 1 µM). Compound 
 <bold>6</bold>, however, displayed dual STS and 17β-HSD1 inhibition. Additionally, 3-hydroxy-2-phosphonate 
 <bold>7</bold> proved to be dual 17β-HSD1 and OATP2B1 inhibitor with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 1–2 µM, whereas its 3-benzyloxy counterpart (
 <bold>8</bold>) exhibited selective OATP2B1 inhibition with IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.2 µM (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0003">Figure 3</xref>)
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>.
</p>
