<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> protein hydrolysates show antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B27-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE)-inhibitory activity [
 <xref rid="B28-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] and immunomodulatory effects [
 <xref rid="B29-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> has starch (1–4%) as a reserve polysaccharide. Furthermore, 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> has water-soluble and insoluble cellulose (38–52%) corresponding to structural polysaccharides with a major component called Ulvan. Ulvans are sulphated heteropolysaccharides that contribute to the strength of the cell wall and give flexibility to 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic>, preventing 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> desiccation for tides. Ulvan is up to 30% 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> dry weight and contains mainly sulfonic acids, sulphated 
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-rhamnose, xylose and glucose. This polysaccharide and its oligosaccharides have anti-viral, anti-tumour, anti-coagulant, anti-lipidique, hepato protective, immuno-stimulating, anti-depressant and anti-anxiolytic activities [
 <xref rid="B26-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], and are increasingly requested for pharmaceutical and food applications. In addition, Ulvans are thermos reversible gels, with industrial applications in the chemical, pharmaceutical, biomedical and agricultural areas [
 <xref rid="B26-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The commercial application of these gels is not yet as developed as other algal hydrocolloids [
 <xref rid="B31-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. However, interesting recent applications were reported with a composite material made of zinc oxide and calcium carbonate capped with 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> polysaccharides for burn treatments [
 <xref rid="B32-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Ulva</italic> carbohydrates can also be a carbon source for microbial production of biomaterials and building blocks to produce a range of chemicals and intermediates, such as organic acids, alcohols and biomaterials, but this market is still emerging [
 <xref rid="B31-marinedrugs-17-00357" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>].
</p>
