<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>50 adults zebrafish (
 <italic>Danio rerio</italic>) wild-type short-fin strain of both sexes (ratio: 50:50 male: Female, 3–4 month-old, and 3–4 cm-long) were purchased from a specialized commercial supplier (Pet Product S.R.L., Bucharest, Romania). The zebrafish were acclimatized in the experimental room for at least 14 days. Fish were sorted in groups of 10 fish in 24 L thermostated (26 ± 1 °C) tanks, kept under water filtration and aeration (7.2 mg O
 <sub>2</sub>/L) using Tetra
 <italic>tec</italic>
 <sup>®</sup> air pumps (Tetra, Melle, Germany). Animals were maintained on 14/10 h light/dark cycle, and were fed twice a day with Norwin Norvitall flake (Norwin, Gadstrup, Denmark). In behavioral studies, acclimatized zebrafish were randomly assigned to the control, the Sco (100 µM), and three TEO treatment groups (25, 150, and 300 µL/L). The essential oil [
 <xref rid="B43-antioxidants-09-01083" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-antioxidants-09-01083" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and the Sco [
 <xref rid="B45-antioxidants-09-01083" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] doses were selected according to previous studies. TEO (25, 150, and 300 µL/L) was diluted with 1% Tween-80 solution and was administered to zebrafish by immersion for 1 h, once daily for 13 days, while Sco (100 µM) was administered 30 min before each behavioral tests. The control group was immersed only in unchlorinated water with a 1% Tween-80 solution. All experiments (as outlined in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antioxidants-09-01083-f001">Figure 1</xref>) were carried out following scrutiny by the Ethics Committee on Animal Research of the Alexandru Ioan Cuza University of Iasi, Faculty of Biology (Iasi, Romania) under license no. 02/30.06.2020 and fully complied with the Directive 2010/63/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 September 2010 on the safety of animals. The health status and the well-being of all animals involved in the research have been tested regularly during the behavioral tests. No procedures have caused serious pain or long-lasting damage to the zebrafish, and no experimental subject has died during the experimental procedures (fish housing and behavioral tests).
</p>
