<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">The genetic diversity of the BMSB populations was determined by analysing the mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) cytochrome c oxidase subunit I (COI) and cytochrome c oxidase subunit II (COII). The two markers were chosen due to their fairly high variability and large number of sequences previously reported. Partial sequence of the COI (657 bp) and COII (518 bp) genes were amplified using the genomic DNA as a template. The LCO1490 (5′-GGTCAACAAATCATAAAGATATTGG-3′) and HCO2198 (5′-TAAACTTCAGGGTGACCAAAAAATCA-3′) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] primer pairs were used for amplification of the COI region. Similarly, the HhalysCO2F2 (5′-TAACCCAAGATGCAAATTCT-3) and HhalysCO2R2 (5′-CCATATATAATTCCTGGACGA-3′) primer pairs were used for amplification of the COII region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The PCR reagents (reaction volume of 20 μl) for COI and COII were the same except the primers, comprising of 4.4 μl sterile deionized water, 10.0 μl 2X GoTaq® Green Master Mix (Promega), 1.0 μl of 5 μM Forward primer, 1.0 μl of 5 μM Reserve primer, 0.6 μl of 50 mM MgCl2, 1.0 μl of 10 μg/μl BSA. Thermocycling conditions for both reactions comprised of an initial denaturation step of 94 °C for 5 mins, followed by 40 cycles of denaturation at 94 °C for 15 s, annealing at 50 °C for 30 s, and extension at 72 °C for 45 s, followed by a final extension phase at 72 °C for 7 min. All reactions were performed using a Veriti 96-well thermal cycler (Life Technologies). In this study, 463 specimens were used for COI and COII sequencing. The amplified DNA fragments in the final PCR product was evaluated on 1% agarose gel against a 100 bp DNA ladder (Invitrogen™) in TAE buffer stained with SYBR safe (Life Technologies) and visualised using a Gel Doc Software system (BioRad, Hercules, CA, the USA). The resulting product was diluted 5-fold with sterile water, and sent for Sanger sequencing Macrogen (Soul, South Korea) using the amplification primers in both directions. The quality of the Sanger sequencing dataset was manually examined and analysed in Geneious software (Biomatters, Auckland, New Zealand) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The resulting quality-filtered COI and COII gene sequences for each haplotype were submitted to GenBank under the accession numbers, MT517228 - MT517274 for COI and MT490838 - MT490860 for COII. All the metadata for each specimen and their sequences were submitted into BOLD under project code BMSB. The BOLD processed IDs for each specimen are listed in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. All the sequences were used to create a dataset in BOLD, under the DOI: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5883/DS-BMSB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">dx.doi.org/10.5883/DS-BMSB</ext-link>.
</p>
