<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is believed that the bioactivities of fish oils are chiefly due to the effect of PUFAs. The epidemiological studies show a significant improvement of asthma symptoms in patients receiving fish oil supplements rich in DHA and EPA [
 <xref rid="B6-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The use of omega-3 fatty acids in fish oil capsules has been associated with a reduction in plasma triglyceride concentration, leading to the decreased incidence of hyperlipidemia [
 <xref rid="B7-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The PUFA supplementation can diminish the risks of cardiovascular diseases such as thrombosis, high blood pressure, and low high-density-lipoprotein cholesterol [
 <xref rid="B8-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The meta-analysis studies have shown that fish oil consumption and dietary omega-3 PUFAs decrease the risk factor of type 2 diabetes mellitus via enhanced insulin sensitivity [
 <xref rid="B9-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The consumption of fish oil containing a high level of PUFAs can play a role in cancer prevention and therapy [
 <xref rid="B10-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The anticancer effect of omega-3 PUFAs is ascribed to the capability of downregulating proinflammatory eicosanoid synthesis from cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) [
 <xref rid="B11-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. The PUFAs from fish oils or cod liver oils can also be employed with a high level of safety as natural antibacterial and anti-infectious agents [
 <xref rid="B12-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Intravenous lipid emulsions are a component of parenteral nutrition used as a resource for essential fatty acids for supplying energy to patients. Soybean oil is the traditional source of lipid emulsions. However, a high percentage of omega-6 PUFAs in soybean oil contributes to the immunosuppressive effect [
 <xref rid="B13-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Recently, fish oil has been used to replace soybean oil in lipid emulsions to reduce the possible risk of inflammatory complications [
 <xref rid="B14-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>].
</p>
