<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">Furthermore, 
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">Negera &amp; Washe (2019)</xref> evaluated AF degradation abilities of some selected natural food spices including garlic, ginger, black cumin, clove, sacred basil, lemon grass, thyme, fenugreek and lemon, traditionally used by the Ethiopian community for food flavoring and preservation. Electrochemical and LC-MS/MS methods were used to investigate aflatoxin degradation efficacy of the spice extracts by determining the toxin in extract-treated and non-treated samples. The results revealed that garlic had maximum AFB
 <sub>1</sub> degradation activity followed by lemon and the other dietary spices during 1-hour exposure to AFB
 <sub>1</sub> standard at 25 °C. The results also showed that the possible mechanism of AFB
 <sub>1</sub> degradation is through chemical transformation of AFB
 <sub>1</sub> parent compound to another compound by the plant extracts. 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Iram et al. (2015)</xref> investigated the ability of 
 <italic>Corymbia citriodora</italic> plant extract to detoxify AFB
 <sub>1</sub> and AFB
 <sub>2</sub> both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in</italic> v
 <italic>ivo</italic>. They observed that the leaf extracts had maximum detoxification at pH 8 and 30 °C temperature after 72 h of incubation. 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Iram et al. (2016)</xref> demonstrated that 
 <italic>Trachyspermum. ammi</italic> seed extracts can be used for the development of biologically safe herbal additives in food and feed. 
 <xref rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr">Ponzilacqua et al. (2019)</xref> evaluated degradation capabilities of aqueous plant extracts of 
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis, Origanum vulgare, Psidium cattleianum</italic> and 
 <italic>Passifora alata</italic> against AFB
 <sub>1</sub>, with 
 <italic>R.</italic>
 <italic>officinalis</italic> extract exhibiting the highest degradation percentage of AFB
 <sub>1</sub> (range: 49.0–60.3%) at 24–48 h, followed by 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> with (range of 30.7%–38.3%) after 48 h of incubation.
</p>
