<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bioinformatic surveys suggest that a number of genetic systems analogous to 
 <italic>Podospora anserina nwd2/het-S</italic> exist in fungal genomes; gene clusters comprising a gene encoding an NLR and one or several genes encoding predicted cell death execution proteins [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). These systems can be classified based on the sequence of the predicted amyloid motif, shared between the NLR and the execution proteins and have been grouped so far into three superfamilies termed HRAM (for 
 <underline>H</underline>ET-s 
 <underline>r</underline>elated 
 <underline>a</underline>myloid 
 <underline>m</underline>otifs), PP (
 <underline>p</underline>seudo-
 <underline>p</underline>alindrome) and sigma [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Although the evidence is yet indirect, the sigma motif is thought to be responsible for infectious propagation of a cytoplasmic element termed σ, identified in the fungus 
 <italic>Nectria haematococca</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The PP-motif in turn was functionally characterized as amyloid signalling motif as part of a study – by heterologous expression in 
 <italic>P. anserina –</italic> of a three-gene cluster from the fungus 
 <italic>Chaetomium globosum</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The PP-motif stands out among fungal amyloid signalling motifs because it shows homology to the RHIM motif involved in amyloid necrosome assembly in mammals [
 <xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. As we shall see, recent studies have confirmed these bioinformatic predictions and support the existence of other amyloid signalosomes in fungi and also in filamentous bacteria.
</p>
