<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Nomenclatural remarks</italic>. Fries (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">1822</xref>) described the anamorphic genus 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic> and distinguished three species. Later, Donk (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">1962</xref>) designeted the first species, 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>cocos</italic> (Schwein.) Fr. (syn. 
 <italic>Sclerotium cocos</italic> Schwein.) as the generic type of 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic>. The teleomorphic genus 
 <italic>Wolfiporia</italic> was typified with 
 <italic>Poria cocos</italic> F. A. Wolf by Ryvarden and Gilbertson (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>), which was a species derived from 
 <italic>Sclerotium cocos</italic> Schwein., hence it was cited as a basionym by Wolf (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">1922</xref>). Therefore, both 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic> and 
 <italic>Wolfiporia</italic> are typified with 
 <italic>Sclerotium cocos</italic> Schwein., thus these genera are considered as synonyms. Based on the changes in Art. 59 of the International Code of Nomenclature for algae, fungi, and plants (ICN; Turland et al., 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), all legitimate fungal names are treated equally for the purposes of establishing priority, regardless of the life history stage of the type (Art. F.8.1). In the case that the sexually typified generic name does not have priority it is recommended that it can either be formally conserved (e.g., Braun, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), or included on a list of protected names (Rossman, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The generic names 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic> and 
 <italic>Wolfiporia</italic> are both listed by Kirk et al. (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) for protection as a result of changes in Art. 59. However, the earlier name 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic> is sanctioned by Fries (ICN, Art. F.3.1) and well represents the economically important stage of the generic type. For this reason, currently we consider that it is unnecessary to conserve the name 
 <italic>Wolfiporia</italic> over 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic>. Consequently, based on nomenclatural priority, the use of the earlier and sanctioned generic name 
 <italic>Pachyma</italic> is recommended over 
 <italic>Wolfiporia</italic>.
</p>
