<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In recent years, natural antioxidants have gained importance for their prophylactic and therapeutic potential for many diseases, during which the search for medicinal plants with antioxidant properties has intensified in recent years [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Natural antioxidants are molecules that protect the organism from cellular damage resulting from excess free radicals responsible for inducing oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Oxidative stress is characterized by the imbalance between the production of oxidizing substances and endogenous antioxidants, and it may cause the oxidation of biomolecules such as nucleic acids, proteins and lipids [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. In particular, phenolic compounds have been shown to be effective agents in scavenging reactive species responsible for inducing oxidative stress. In concordance with chemical studies, quercetin was identified in the three extracts, which has been noted in the literature for its antioxidant activities [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>], and anticancer [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>], neuroprotection [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], hepatoprotection [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], and antiparasitic [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-plants-07-00110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] properties. Among the 
 <italic class="italic">P. matricarioides</italic> extracts, higher antioxidant activity was observed in the PmC extract, which also displayed the higher concentration of quercetin according to the chemical profile as shown in the quantitative map. Thus, it is likely that better antioxidant capacity may depend on quercetin concentration and locality collection area.
</p>
