<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">The following protocols were used to conduct the interviews: 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par28">All interviews took place with the same interviewer;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par29">There was a difference of 3 months from one interview to another for all participants;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par30">The participants were informed that the interviews should be carried out individually, avoiding other people nearby. However, this was not always possible, as there were times when other people appeared during the interview. The fact that a third person remained in the same room as the interviewer and interviewee during the interview was considered as presence of third party and interference by third party if this person at any time intervened (trying to assist the informant);</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par31">Participants were approached at their homes. There were some cases where the participants were found at the neighbors’ house or working next to their residence and asked to be interviewed in these places; thus, two types of environments were obtained: closed space, inside residences, and open space, in which the interview took place outside the residence, such as the footpath or the balcony of the house;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par32">Priority was given to the place where the participant felt most comfortable and away from areas of greatest activity. However, some participants performed certain activities at the time of the interview. Factors we considered as potential interview interference included the participant having the television on, using the cell phone or simultaneously performing some domestic activity. Unforeseen factors that could also influence were recorded during the interview.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par33">The participant was informed that the interviewer would record their response in writing.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
