<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this context, Bruyere and coworkers tested this oxyprenylated coumarin in vitro as growth inhibitory agents of a panel composed of six human cancer cell lines and found that it was weakly active on OE21 (human esophageal carcinoma) and LoVo (human colorectal adenocarcinoma) cell lines with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 79 µM and 82 µM, respectively [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Two years later, in 2013, Valiahdi and coworkers investigated the cytotoxic effects of individual phytochemicals isolated from 
 <italic>Ferula</italic> spp. against a panel of three human cancer cell lines, namely ovarian carcinoma (CH1), lung cancer (A549), and melanoma (SK-MEL-28) using the (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5 diphenyltetrazolium b bromide) (MTT) assay [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. 7-Isopentenyloxycoumarin however was found to exert only a very modest effect with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value &gt; 250 µM. One year later, Haghighi and coworkers assayed the cytotoxic effect of this secondary metabolite on 5637 cells, a transitional cell carcinoma cell line (bladder cancer) using the same test with human dermal fibroblast (HDF) as the “normal” cell line [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The MTT assay was performed in both cell lines to record the cytotoxic activity of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin in the concentration range 10–100 µg/mL for three consecutive days. This oxyprenylated coumarin exhibited a time- and dose-dependent effect. IC
 <sub>50</sub> values for 5637 cells were 76, 76, and 65 μg/mL after 24, 48, and 72 h of treatments, respectively. In the same concentration range and times, 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin did not show an appreciable cytotoxic effect against HDF cells. Gaining further insights into its mechanism of action, microscopic observation on 5637 cells revealed an extensive cytoplasmic granulation and cell death. 4′,6-Diamidin-2-phenylindole (DAPI) staining and alkaline comet assay showed that at a concentration of 65 μg/mL, a high condensation of chromatin and nuclear fragmentation occurred in more than 89% of treated cancer cells. Furthermore, 43% of the latter exhibited DNA damage, while HDF cells were practically not affected. The increase of caspase 3 activity was about 2.5-fold higher in cancer cells in respect to normal ones, suggesting that 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin could behave as a proapoptotic agent. Finally, at the same concentration mentioned above, 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin induced an arrest of the cycle in 5637 cells in the G2/M phase after 24 h treatment. In the same year, Rezaee and coworkers investigated the antigenotoxic properties of this phytochemical on human lymphocytes under oxidative stress conditions using the comet assay [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. 7-Isopentenyloxycoumarin did not show appreciable effects on cell viability even at high concentrations. Isolated lymphocytes were treated with H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> at a concentration of 25 µM and were found to induce 45% DNA damage. The effect of the oxyprenylated coumarin was revealed by its incubation with cells with and without H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> in the concentration range 10–200 μM. Under these conditions, 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin exhibited a dose-dependent reduction in DNA damage (0.88–8%). Quite interestingly, the parent coumarin umbelliferone recorded a significantly less effect (3.05–22.4%), thus suggesting that the addition of the 3,3-dimethylallyl side chain may play a pivotal role in the mechanism of action underlying the observed effects, allowing 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin to selectively trigger a specific biomolecular target. When assayed on LoVo cells in the concentration range 0.01–100 μM, 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin showed a moderate growth inhibitory effect (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 30 μM), as pointed out in 2017 by Bisi and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In the same study it was revealed that this phytochemical has a capacity to revert multidrug resistance equal to verapamil when assayed at a concentration of 2.5 μM in the same cancer cell line. One year later, Kafi and coworkers found that 7-isopentenyoxycoumarin was cytotoxic against K562 (human myelogeneous leukemia) cells in the concentration range 10–40 μM and that the same could modulate myeloid cell leukemia type-1 (Mcl-1) gene expression by hormesis in the same concentration range [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Finally, Marquez Duarte da Cruz and coworkers studied the mechanism of action of the in vitro and in vivo (Ehrlich ascites carcinoma in mice) anticancer activity of 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-05923" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. First, its toxicity was evaluated: this coumarin did not provide an appreciable level of hemolysis on mice peripheral blood erythrocytes at a concentration of 2000 µg/mL and no deaths were observed in parallel in an in vivo acute non-clinical toxicity assay (LD
 <sub>50</sub> = 1000 mg/kg). 7-Isopentenyloxycoumarin was also shown not to be genotoxic when assayed in the peripheral blood micronucleus test. No statistically significant differences were recorded with the control group of untreated cells. Accomplishing in vivo assays and applying a concentration range 25–50 mg/kg, 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin was able to reduce tumor volume and weight, both by about 50%. The same percentage of reduction was observed for the total viable cancer cells with respect to the controls. For what concerns the mechanism of action, it was found that the same led to a reduction of microvessel density around the tumor mass (24–58%) and, although only at the concentration of 50 mg/kg, to a decrease (45%) of the release of chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 2 (CCL2). Thus, it was hypothesized that 7-isopentenyloxycoumarin could reduce tumor growth and development by the inhibition of angiogenesis and CCL2 release in the tumor microenvironment.
</p>
