<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Sufficient aqueous solubility is one of the essential requirements for oral administration of a drug. Limited solubility can lead to insufficient dissolution and further reduce the bioavailability of a drug.
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref> As a result, a variety of effort has been made to enhance the oral bioavailability of poorly water soluble drugs through lipid based emulsion systems, specifically the self-emulsifying drug delivery system (SEDDS).
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref> SEDDSs are defined as homogeneous mixtures of natural or synthetic oils, surfactants, and co-surfactants that easily form emulsion upon mild agitation and generate a high surface area of interactions between the SEDDS formulation and the gastrointestinal (GI) fluid.
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref> Moreover, SEDDS has been identified as a prominent technology for drug delivery, because the formulations have great solubilization capacity and a tiny droplet size, which could improve permeation across the GI membrane. In present, SEDDS is usually prepared as a liquid solution or encapsulated in soft gelatin capsules; however, these preparations have some imperfections, including sensitivity to temperature and humidity, and high production cost.
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref> Moreover, liquid and capsules are less convenient to the patient than the solid dosage form, and incompatibility problems can occur between the soft gelatin shell and the drug formulation.
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref> Transformation of the liquid SEDDS into the solid dosage form using specific techniques, such as spray drying, may maintain the advantages of SEDDS but avoid the disadvantages of liquid SEDDS mentioned above. Spray drying is the most commonly used method to prepare a solid formulation. First, the sample is prepared by mixing an optimized ratio of ingredients (oil, surfactants, and co-surfactants), the drug, and a suitable solid carrier. Afterwards, the liquid solution (suspension) is sprayed into a heated air chamber to evaporate the volatile fraction (organic solvent or water) contained in the sample,
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref> hence the term, spray drying. This process is executed under the optimized operation conditions, such as inlet/outlet temperature, aspiration, and feed rate. In addition, spray drying may solve the stability problems associated with traditional emulsions during storage. The outer film coating and packaging in spray drying has shown improved photostability in various photosensitive drugs.
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>
</p>
