<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Oral administration of methanol extract of Rn at 200 mg/kg body weight in adult male Wistar rats for 30 days reduced the levels of total cholesterol, triglycerides and phospholipids in the liver of diabetic rats to a level like that of non-diabetic control. Further, the extract also reduced the level of low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (LDL-C) and very-low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (VLDL-C) in the diabetic rats apart from improving the levels of HDL-C, thereby exhibiting hypolipidemic activity in diabetic rats. More importantly, the plant did not exhibit any hypoglycemic activity in normal rats indicating that it was non-toxic to normal rats [
 <xref rid="B63-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Impaired lipoprotein and lipid metabolism are a characteristic feature of type II diabetes. Pathological changes include increased hepatic secretion and impaired clearance of VLDL [
 <xref rid="B71-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. One of the key players in lipid metabolism is insulin, which helps in the storage of triacylglycerols (TAG) and reduces the generation of VLDL by declining the level of non-esterified fatty acids in circulation. Similar to 
 <italic>Rn</italic> extract, oral administration of rhinacanthin-rich extract and RnC significantly normalized the water and food intake in diabetic rats, along with the bodyweight, without causing any significant changes in the normal rats. It also decreased the hyperglycemic levels and destruction of beta cells in the pancreas and increased the serum insulin gradually in diabetic rats. The elevated levels of aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) along with blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and creatinine in diabetic rats were significantly reduced by the extract treatment indicating the normalization of the liver as well as kidneys functioning in diabetic rats [
 <xref rid="B72-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Similar results were also reported by Rao et al. 2013, where the key markers of liver functioning were normalized in diabetic rats upon treatment with the plant extract [
 <xref rid="B73-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Further, RnC also modulated the levels of fasting blood glucose (FBG) and glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) in diabetic rats. HbA1c is a form of hemoglobin that is in bonding with sugar moiety and is formed when there is an excessive circulation of glucose in the bloodstream. Moreover, RnC could also reduce the insulin resistance index, modulate antioxidant enzymes, and prevent the shrinking of the islet of Langerhans in diabetic rats [
 <xref rid="B74-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. The reported health benefits of the plant extract against diabetic condition could probably be mediated by the activity of cytosolic and mitochondrial enzymes. The level of cytosolic enzymes like glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PDH), glutamate dehydrogenase (GDH) and mitochondrial enzyme succinate dehydrogenase (SDH) is reduced in individuals with diabetes, where G6PDH plays a vital role in antioxidant defense against oxidative stress by the production of NADPH [
 <xref rid="B75-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] while GDH and SDH are involved in insulin secretion [
 <xref rid="B76-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Administration of 
 <italic>Rn</italic> extract significantly restored the levels of these enzymes, thereby ameliorating the diabetic conditions in diabetic rats [
 <xref rid="B73-nutrients-12-03776" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
