<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> invasions generate environmental, social and economic benefits as well as harm (
 <xref rid="PLU027C13" ref-type="bibr">Chikuni 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2004
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C33" ref-type="bibr">Geesing 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2004
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C95" ref-type="bibr">Wise 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
 </xref>). This has led to contentious issues surrounding the genus (
 <xref rid="PLU027C73" ref-type="bibr">Richardson 1998
  <italic>b</italic>
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C88" ref-type="bibr">van Wilgen and Richardson 2014</xref>). Some advocates promote it as a ‘wonder plant’ while others call for its eradication, or contrast its positive and negative aspects, e.g. ‘Boon or bane’ (
 <xref rid="PLU027C82" ref-type="bibr">Tiwari 1999</xref>), ‘Pest or providence, weed or wonder tree?’ (
 <xref rid="PLU027C58" ref-type="bibr">Pasiecznik 1999</xref>), ‘Invasive weed or valuable forest resource?’ (
 <xref rid="PLU027C59" ref-type="bibr">Pasiecznik 2002</xref>). Contrasting views, contradictory perceptions and unclear policies are limiting options for constructive dialogue between different parties. This is exacerbated by problems in identifying and differentiating morphologically similar species, and by a general lack of knowledge on the distribution, scale of invasion, benefits, impacts and effective management approaches. Furthermore, many different approaches for managing 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> have been tried in different situations, without a thorough evaluation of the relative effectiveness of the methods. The Food and Agricultural Organization has called for a sound, unbiased global overview of 
 <italic>Prosopis</italic> to act as a prerequisite for the holistic management of the genus (
 <xref rid="PLU027C30" ref-type="bibr">FAO 2006</xref>). Such reviews have been useful for guiding and prioritizing management and improving knowledge in other groups of woody invasive plants (
 <xref rid="PLU027C74" ref-type="bibr">Richardson and Rejmánek 2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="PLU027C75" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C39" ref-type="bibr">Kull 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU027C93" ref-type="bibr">Wilson 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2011
 </xref>).
</p>
