<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Beta-sitosterol was isolated from the roots of 
 <italic>B. pilosa</italic> which was subjected molecular docking. The docking analysis was followed by the protocol of Sastry et al. (2013) [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and explained in detail in our previous studies [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Protein data bank was used to derive the 3D structures of the subsequent proteins: cyclooxygenase (COX)-1 (PDB ID: 2OYE) [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], cyclooxygenase (COX)-2 (PDB ID: 6COX) [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], serotonin transporter (PDB ID: 5I6X) [
 <xref rid="B54-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], potassium channel (PDB ID: 4UUJ) [
 <xref rid="B55-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], PDE4 complexed with inhibitor (PDB ID: 4WCU) [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], bromodomain of human BRD4 (PDB ID: 3U5J) [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], 
 <italic>V. cholerae</italic> MARTX toxin and (PDB ID: 3CJB) [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], and bromodomain of human BRD4 in complex with midazolam (PDB ID: 3U5K) [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-25-04737" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The molecular docking analysis was assessed by Schrodinger Maestro version 11.1 and the amino acid residues of the active sites of each receptor were given as follows: for 2OYE receptor, the amino acid residues were Val116, Arg120, Glu524, Leu531, Ala527, Gly526, Trp387, Met522, Leu384, Tyr385, Ser530, Val349, Leu352, Ile523, Ser353, Phe518, Tyr355, and Leu93; for 6COX receptor, the amino acid residues were Trp387, Tyr385, Gly526, Ala527, Leu384, Met522, Leu352, Phe518, Ala516, Gln192, Arg513, Ser353, Tyr355, Val116, Arg120, Leu531, Leu359, Val349, Val523, and Ser530; for 5I6X receptor, the amino acid residues were Val501, Phe335, Gly338, Ser336, Asp98, Ala96, Tyr95, Tyr176, Ser438, Ser439, Ile172, Ala169, Gly442, and Phe341; for 4UUJ receptor, the amino acid residues were Val93, Arg89, and Leu86; for 4WCU receptor, the amino acid residues were Phe432, Met273, Thr271, Asp318, Leu319, Tyr159, Trp332, Asn321, Thr333, Ile336, Phe340, Met337, Gln433, Gln369, Met357, Ile376, Phe372, and Leu436; for 3U5J receptor, the amino acid residues were Pro82, Trp81, Leu92, Met149, Ile146, Leu94, Asn140, and Phe83; for 3CJB receptor, the amino acid residues were Gly158, Leu16, Val159, Gly13, Gly15, Ser14, Gly302, Lys336, Tyr306, Met305, Glu214, Lys213, Thr303, Asp157, Gly301, Lys18, Gly156, and Asp154; and for 3U5K receptor, the amino acid residues were Asn140, Leu94, Leu92, Met149, Ile146, Trp81, Pro82, Val87, and Phe83.
</p>
