<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because relatively few studies have examined effects of multiple invaders on native plants, whether such relationships are largely additive, or sub- or super-additive is still not fully understood (
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Braga 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2018
 </xref>). We find evidence consistent with the possibility of super-additive effects (
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Braga 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2018
 </xref>), but only in some experimental contexts. The interaction only in the presence of activated carbon, combined with the lack of AMF colonization in any experimental treatment, suggests that the experimental interaction between 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> and 
 <italic>Lumbricus terrestris</italic> was not due to an indirect effect of allelochemicals on AMF (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, arrow 2), contrary to indirect effects of 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> allelochemical via AMF in other systems (
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Hale 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2016
 </xref>). Our experimental plants may have lacked AMF colonization because they were large healthy rhizomes at the beginning of the experiment, though this is speculative. Although 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> has not been reported in the field to have facultative AMF association (
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Soudzilovskaia 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2020
 </xref>), the ability to ‘cut off’ mycorrhizal partners is well-described and common in many plant species (
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Johnson 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 1997
 </xref>). In the field, 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic> cover was lowest at sites that had both greater soil nitrogen and 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> present, and the presence of earthworms reduces soil nitrogen content in the field and increases leaf nitrogen content in the experiment. If earthworms speed up nutrient cycling (
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Costello and Lamberti 2009</xref>), there might be less nitrogen in the soil and more within plant tissues. This increase in nutrients within the plant might reduce some of the harmful effects 
 <italic>Alliaria petiolata</italic> has on 
 <italic>Podophyllum peltatum</italic>, though our survey data suggest that such effects are likely weak. In addition, like others before us, we found no evidence for a correlation between earthworms and garlic mustard in the field (
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Zelles 2012</xref>), [however, see 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Nuzzo 
  <italic>et al</italic>. (2009)
 </xref>], inconsistent with an ‘invasion meltdown’ hypothesis of these two invaders facilitating one another (
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Simberloff and Von Holle 1999</xref>).
</p>
