<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.1.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.1. 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> L., commonly called rosemary, is a Mediterranean shrubby herb and widely spread in European, American, and Asian countries. It is a common spice used worldwide for culinary, medicinal, and commercial uses, including the fragrance and food industries [
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>]. The leaves of rosemary (fresh or dries) are used for their characteristic aroma in cooking or consumed in small amounts as herbal tea, while rosemary extracts are regularly used for their natural antioxidant active proprieties to improve the shelf life of perishable foods. Recently, rosemary extracts (E392) have been approved as a safe and effective natural antioxidant for food preservation by the European Union [
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phytochemical studies have revealed that leaves contain 0.5% to 2.5% volatile oil. The major components of rosemary oil include monoterpene hydrocarbons (alpha and beta-pinene), camphene, limonene, camphor (10% to 20%), borneol, cineole, linalool, and verbinol. Rosemary contains a widespread variety of volatile and aromatic components. Flavonoids in the plant consist of diosmetin, diosmin, genkwanin, luteolin, hispidulin, and apigenin [
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>–
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>]. Additionally, terpenoid components from rosemary consist of the triterpenes oleanolic and ursolic acid and the diterpene carnosol. Phenols in rosemary comprise caffeic, chlorogenic, labiatic, neochlorogenic, and rosmarinic acids. Rosemary covers high amounts of salicylates [
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>–
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modern pharmacological studies have indicated that rosemary and its constituents, especially caffeic acid derivatives such as rosmarinic acid, have various traditional uses in ethnomedicine including analgesic, anti-inflammatory, anticarcinogenic, antirheumatic, spasmolytic, antihepatotoxic, atherosclerotic, carminative, and choleretic applications [
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>–
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>], protection against UV and gamma radiation, and amelioration of stress [
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The powdered leaves are used as an effective natural flea and tick repellent. Activity against certain bacteria including 
  <span class="italic">Staphylcoccus aureus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus albus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Vibrio cholerae</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Corynebacterium</span> has been observed. One study found that rosemary oil is most active against “meat spoiling” Gram-negative (
  <span class="italic">Pseudomonas</span>) and Gram-positive (
  <span class="italic">Lactobacillus</span>) bacteria [
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though rosemary oil is used safely as a food flavoring spice and whole leaves are used as a potherb for seasoning, ingestion of great quantities can be associated with toxicity characterized by stomach and intestinal irritation and kidney damage. While rosemary oil is irritating to rabbit skin, it is not usually considered to be a sensitizer for human skin [
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bioactive compounds such as flavonoids, diterpenes, phenols, and triterpenes from plant sources have been traditionally extracted by a conventional solid-liquid extraction. Nevertheless, this extraction technique presents several disadvantages, mainly because it is an arduous, time-consuming process that requires a high consumption of solvents, and in some cases provides low recovery. For that reason, in last years, new promising extraction methods are arising, which introduce some form of additional energy in order to facilitate the transfer of solutes from the sample to solvent in a faster process [
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. Thus, microwave-assisted extraction [
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>] and/or ultrasound-assisted ethanol, acetone, or 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-hexane extraction represent alternatives to the conventional method, improving the speed and efficiency of the extraction process and reducing the consumption of solvents [
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">57</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have revealed that the rosemary extract may have analgesic and anti-inflammatory effects [
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">58</a>–
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>]. Therefore, data have shown that the ethanolic extract of rosemary inhibited acetic acid-induced pain in mice with an ED50 of 108.84 mg/kg
  <span class="sup">−1</span> [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. Furthermore, the extract inhibited the time mice spent licking and shaking induced by formalin injections. Nevertheless, the extract did not display any anti-inflammatory activity as evaluated by uric acid induced-hind limb edema in rats [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>]. In an experiment conducted by Emami et al. [
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>], the effects of 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> extract and its major constituent, carnosol, on plasma corticosterone levels and activity of the enzymes cyclooxygenase types 1 and 2 (COX1 and COX2) reduced pain in phase 2 of the formalin test, which was not inhibited by naloxone and/or memantine. In addition, pretreatment of the animals with 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> extract and/or carnosol reduced the formalin-induced inflammation. Moreover, the extract and carnosol did not affect plasma corticosterone levels compared with the control group. Interestingly, both the extract and carnosol inhibited COX1 and COX2 activities. Going one step further, one can conclude that 
  <span class="italic">R. officinalis</span> extract and carnosol suppress pain and inflammation induced by formalin injection, which may be due to inhibition of the activity of COX1 and COX2 enzymes.
 </p>
</sec>
