<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.12.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.12.1. 
  <span class="italic">Hyptis pectinata</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Hyptis pectinata</span> L. Poit. is present very common in gardens, and it is frequently used as tea (decoctions or infusions) and mouthwash to treat inflammation due to being considered a natural antiphlogistic. In Brazilian folk medicine, the infusion of the fresh leaves is used to treat inflammations, bacterial infections, pain, gastrointestinal disorders, skin infections, nasal congestion, fever, cramps, inflammation, orofacial painful conditions and wound healing [
  <a rid="B222" ref-type="bibr" href="#B222">222</a>], fungal infections, and HIV.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also, the plant has cytotoxicity and insecticide properties [
  <a rid="B223" ref-type="bibr" href="#B223">223</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> has an important neurogenic and inflammatory orofacial antinociceptive effects, without interference in the motor performance. The mechanism is currently unknown but seems to be related to vanilloid and glutamate receptors. The opioid system seems unlikely to participate in the antinociception caused by the extract [
  <a rid="B224" ref-type="bibr" href="#B224">224</a>]. The local application of dental gel based on 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> has anti-inflammatory effect and also prevents alveolar bone resorption and weight loss in animals with periodontitis [
  <a rid="B223" ref-type="bibr" href="#B223">223</a>]. The healing effect of 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> suggests that this plant may have antileishmanial action [
  <a rid="B219" ref-type="bibr" href="#B219">219</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aqueous extract of 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> possesses antiedematogenic properties in the carrageenan-induced paw edema model. The association of the aqueous extract of 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> leaves at 200 mg/kg with intraoperative laser therapy can stimulate liver regeneration and cause a reduction in liver mitochondrial respiratory function without altering its phosphorylative activity [
  <a rid="B225" ref-type="bibr" href="#B225">225</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antinociceptive effects of 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> can be seen in the volatile oil [
  <a rid="B226" ref-type="bibr" href="#B226">226</a>]. The major constituents of oil are 1,8-cineole (12.46%), 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene (20.51%), and 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-pinene (13.54%). 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-Pinene may be considered a partial agonist of 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>-opioid receptors [
  <a rid="B227" ref-type="bibr" href="#B227">227</a>]. Franco et al. [
  <a rid="B228" ref-type="bibr" href="#B228">228</a>] suggested that the essential oils have both peripheral and central analgesic actions without opioid system influence, although the central activity was more discrete. GC-MS analysis showed that 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene (40.90%) and caryophyllene oxides (30.05%) were the main compounds present in the oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2011, Raymundo published the results that 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> essential oil shows peripheral and central antinociceptive effects, likely mediated by opioid and cholinergic receptors, and anti-inflammatory activity through the inhibition of nitric oxide and PGE2 production [
  <a rid="B229" ref-type="bibr" href="#B229">229</a>]. The involvement of the opioid system in the antinociceptive activity of 
  <span class="italic">H. pectinata</span> essential oil was evaluated in the hot-plate model by pretreating mice with an opioid antagonist, naloxone. The results suggest that naloxone reversed the antinociceptive activity of the essential oil. The antinociceptive effects were observed in other tests like acetic acid or hot-plate [
  <a rid="B230" ref-type="bibr" href="#B230">230</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
