<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.17.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.17.1. 
  <span class="italic">Leonurus cardiaca</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Leonurus cardiaca</span> L. is a perennial herb widespread in Europe, throughout the plains and hills, as well as in East Asia to the Himalayas and eastern Siberia, Northern Africa, and North America [
  <a rid="B283" ref-type="bibr" href="#B283">283</a>]. The common name of 
  <span class="italic">L. cardiaca</span> is motherwort, but it is also known as throw-wort, lion's ear, or lion's tail. For centuries, motherwort extract has been used as a medicinal plant to treat cardiac and vascular diseases, especially tachycardia associated with anxiety, tension, and stress, and also for hypertension to reduce the risk of thrombosis to inhibit artery calcification formation [
  <a rid="B284" ref-type="bibr" href="#B284">284</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ethanolic extract has been prepared by adding 96% ethanol over aerial parts of the plants for 24–36 hours. The supernatant was collected and concentrated by vacuum distillation at a temperature of 50°C. The extract was completely dried under sterile conditions using an autoclave at temperatures lower than 50°C.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the aerial parts of 
  <span class="italic">L. cardiaca</span>, many compounds were identified: terpene compounds: monoterpenes (iridoids: leonuride, ajugoside, galiridoside, and reptoside) [
  <a rid="B285" ref-type="bibr" href="#B285">285</a>], diterpenes (of clerodane, furanolabdane, and labdane types) [
  <a rid="B286" ref-type="bibr" href="#B286">286</a>], triterpenes (ursolic acid, oleanolic acids, corosolic acid, euscaphic acid, and ilelatifol D) [
  <a rid="B287" ref-type="bibr" href="#B287">287</a>], nitrogen-containing compounds (leonurine, stachydrine, and amine choline), and phenylpropanoids (lavandulifolioside), as well as flavonoids, phenolic acids, volatile oils, sterols (
  <span class="italic">β</span>-sitosterol and stigmasterol), and tannins. The phenolic compounds comprise phenylpropanoid glycosides such as lavandulifolioside (arabinoside) [
  <a rid="B288" ref-type="bibr" href="#B288">288</a>], phenolic acids such as chlorogenic, rosmarinic, caffeic, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-coumaric, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-hydroxybenzoic, vanillic, and ferulic acids, and phenolic glycoside [
  <a rid="B289" ref-type="bibr" href="#B289">289</a>]. The volatile oils mainly contain sesquiterpenes such as germacrene D, epicedrol, 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-humulene, and spathulenol and monoterpenes such as 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene and dehydro-1,8 cineole [
  <a rid="B290" ref-type="bibr" href="#B290">290</a>, 
  <a rid="B291" ref-type="bibr" href="#B291">291</a>]. Of these, ursolic acid proved a stronger anti-inflammatory activity than indomethacin and acetylsalicylic acid, and furanolabdane-type diterpenes inhibited abdominal cramps more effectively than the parallel-given aspirin or acetaminophen.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pharmacological studies have established that 
  <span class="italic">L. cardiaca</span> possesses additional antimicrobial [
  <a rid="B286" ref-type="bibr" href="#B286">286</a>, 
  <a rid="B292" ref-type="bibr" href="#B292">292</a>], antioxidant [
  <a rid="B289" ref-type="bibr" href="#B289">289</a>, 
  <a rid="B293" ref-type="bibr" href="#B293">293</a>], anti-inflammatory [
  <a rid="B294" ref-type="bibr" href="#B294">294</a>, 
  <a rid="B295" ref-type="bibr" href="#B295">295</a>], antinociceptive [
  <a rid="B296" ref-type="bibr" href="#B296">296</a>], neuroprotective [
  <a rid="B297" ref-type="bibr" href="#B297">297</a>], sedative [
  <a rid="B298" ref-type="bibr" href="#B298">298</a>], and even anticancer effects [
  <a rid="B299" ref-type="bibr" href="#B299">299</a>]. The findings obtained by Rezaee-Asl and coworkers, using the 
  <span class="italic">formalin</span>, 
  <span class="italic">tail flick</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">hot-plate</span> tests, assess that central and peripheral mechanisms are involved in the antinociceptive activity of the motherwort extract. According to the tail flick test of this study, 
  <span class="italic">L. cardiaca</span> extract only at the maximum dose (500 mg/kg) could alleviate the pain in all times of tail flick test, whereas the lower doses (125 and 250 mg/kg) reduced only late pain. The formalin test showed that the 
  <span class="italic">L. cardiaca</span> extract at a dose of 500 mg/kg and 250 mg/kg was more effective in the first and second phases, suggesting peripheral and central antinociceptive mechanism. The second phase of the formalin test is related to a peripheral inflammatory process [
  <a rid="B296" ref-type="bibr" href="#B296">296</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a conclusion, the studies concerning the analgesic activity of 
  <span class="italic">L. cardiaca</span> extract afford a justification for the use of this plant in pain and inflammatory disorders. Further research should be accomplished for the isolation of new phytochemicals and to fully understand the antinociceptive mechanism exhibited by the plant extract.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As undesirable effects, one can mention the potential to increase the risk of bleeding due to its antithrombotic and antiplatelet effects, and the synergistic sedative effect when associated with benzodiazepines, which may result in coma [
  <a rid="B300" ref-type="bibr" href="#B300">300</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
