<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.5.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5.1. 
  <span class="italic">Satureja hortensis</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Satureja hortensis</span> L., also known as summer savory (culinary herbs), is an annual aromatic plant with origin in the Mediterranean region and wide distribution in the Mediterranean Sea region, Black Sea, Central and Southern Europe, Asia Minor, and Siberia, but nowadays cultivated worldwide [
  <a rid="B126" ref-type="bibr" href="#B126">126</a>]. The floral parts and leaves from the plant are used as aromatic spice. It is also used in medicinal purposes as decoctions, plasters, and compresses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main constituents of the plant were carvacrol, 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-cymene, 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-terpinene, and myrcene. The only notable sesquiterpene is 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-bisabolene [
  <a rid="B126" ref-type="bibr" href="#B126">126</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the biological activity, extracts from 
  <span class="italic">S. hortensis</span> are covering a large spectrum of pathological conditions [
  <a rid="B127" ref-type="bibr" href="#B127">127</a>–
  <a rid="B132" ref-type="bibr" href="#B132">132</a>]: antimicrobial activity, antioxidant activity, cytotoxic activity, insecticidal activity, fumigant toxicity, insect repellant activity, antinociceptive and analgesic activity, antileishmanial activity, genotoxic activity, anti-inflammatory activity, effects on immune system, effects on productive performance, acaricidal activity, antidiarrheal activity, relaxant effect (antispasmoidal activity), antigenotoxic activity, antihepatoma activity, contact toxicity and persistence, effect on vitality and healthiness of cereals, molluscicidal activity, larvicidal activity, antihelmintic activity, inhibition on blood platelet adhesion, aggregation and secretion, effect on rhinosinusitis, amyloid beta protein aggregation inhibitory activity, and matrix metalloproteinase inhibitory activity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concerning the analgesic activity, 
  <span class="italic">S. hortensis</span> extracts (hydroalcoholic extract, polyphenolic fraction, and essential oil of the aerial parts of the herb) were evaluated by use of tail flick, formalin, and acetic acid-induced writhing tests in mice. Results showed that, in the light tail flick test, neither the essential oil nor the extracts could exert any significant effect. The hydroalcoholic extract (2000 mg/kg, p.o.) and the essential oil (200 mg/kg, p.o.) inhibited the mice writhing responses caused by acetic acid. In the formalin test, hydroalcoholic extract (500–2000 mg/kg, p.o.), polyphenolic fraction (250–1000 mg/kg, p.o.), and the essential oil (50–200 mg/kg, p.o.) showed analgesic activity, and pretreatment with naloxone (1 mg/kg, i.p.) or caffeine (20 mg/kg, i.p.) failed to reverse this antinociceptive activity. Authors suggested that antinociceptive effect could be due to the involvement of opioid and adenosine receptors in the antinociception mediation [
  <a rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" href="#B133">133</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
