<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.6.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6.3. 
  <span class="italic">Stachys inflata</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A hydroalcoholic extract of 
  <span class="italic">Stachys inflata</span> Benth., one of the 
  <span class="italic">Stachys</span> species from Iran, induced antinociception and anti-inflammatory effects in two well-characterized inflammatory models in rats: carrageenan-induced paw edema and formalin-induced paw licking [
  <a rid="B151" ref-type="bibr" href="#B151">151</a>]. Intraperitoneal injection of the hydroalcoholic extract of the aerial parts from nonflowering stems of 
  <span class="italic">S. inflata</span>, 60 min before induction of inflammation, was capable of attenuating both early and delayed phases of carrageenan-induced inflammation with a dose-related inhibition over the dose range of 50–200 mg/kg. Compared to a standard nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug, indomethacin, the hydroalcoholic extract of 
  <span class="italic">S. inflata</span> inhibited the inflammation more effectively than indomethacin. Moreover, all three doses of the extract significantly inhibited the pain associated with the second phase (inflammatory component) of the formalin test, but with no effect against the first phase (0–5 min).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The obtained data suggest that the anti-inflammatory activity of hydroalcoholic extract of 
  <span class="italic">S. inflata</span> may be related to the inhibition of the release or synthesis of cyclooxygenase products and polymorphonuclear leukocytes accumulation determined by myeloperoxidase activity. The effects of 
  <span class="italic">S. inflata</span> extracts (200 mg/kg) on inflammation and myeloperoxidase activity were confirmed by histological examination where the extract considerably reduced the morphological injury and neutrophil infiltration in a carrageenan-induced model of local inflammation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results presented in this study are taken as the basis for further investigation on the exact mode of action of individual constituents of the extract. Several components quantified in 
  <span class="italic">Stachys</span> extracts demonstrated 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> anti-inflammatory and antinociceptive activity in carrageenan-induced hind paw edema and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-benzoquinone-induced abdominal constriction tests [
  <a rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100">100</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
