<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Identification of Secondary Metabolites</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The identification of secondary metabolites from essential oils was achieved by gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry and from aqueous or alcoholic extracts by liquid chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry. Due to the high selectivity and sensitivity, mass spectrometry coupled to separation techniques such as gas chromatography and liquid chromatography represents a valuable technique for the qualitative and quantitative analysis of chemical substances present in essential oils and plant extracts.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The determination of the chemical composition belonging to essential oils for the following 14 species of the Lamiaceae family of plants: 
  <span class="italic">Hyptis pectinata</span> [
  <a rid="B357" ref-type="bibr" href="#B357">357</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</span> [
  <a rid="B349" ref-type="bibr" href="#B349">349</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Lavandula officinalis</span> [
  <a rid="B356" ref-type="bibr" href="#B356">356</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Leonurus cardiaca</span> [
  <a rid="B290" ref-type="bibr" href="#B290">290</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Lamium purpureum</span> [
  <a rid="B357" ref-type="bibr" href="#B357">357</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Melissa officinalis</span> [
  <a rid="B358" ref-type="bibr" href="#B358">358</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Mentha spicata</span> [
  <a rid="B359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B359">359</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Marrubium vulgare</span> [
  <a rid="B360" ref-type="bibr" href="#B360">360</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span> [
  <a rid="B361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B361">361</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Ocimum basilicum</span> [
  <a rid="B362" ref-type="bibr" href="#B362">362</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</span> [
  <a rid="B363" ref-type="bibr" href="#B363">363</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Salvia officinalis</span> [
  <a rid="B364" ref-type="bibr" href="#B364">364</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Satureja hortensis</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</span> [
  <a rid="B365" ref-type="bibr" href="#B365">365</a>], included in most of the scientific articles follow the same steps: (i) collection of flowering aerial parts and drying of the plant material, (ii) hydrodistillation of the dried plant material using a Clevenger apparatus for 1 to 5 hours, (iii) drying the essential oil using anhydrous sodium sulfate (Na
  <sub>2</sub>SO
  <sub>4</sub>), storing the essential oil in the dark at 4°C, i.v. injection of 0.1–1 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>l of the essential oil in the capillary column of a gas chromatograph, and separation of the chemical compounds, (v) ionization and detection of each volatile substance in a mass spectrometer, and (vi) identification of the components performed based on their retention indices established in relation with a series of 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes (C
  <sub>8</sub>–C
  <sub>32</sub>) and based on the mass spectra stored in NIST 21, NIST 107, Wiley spectral libraries, or reported in scientific articles.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The volatile substances isolated from the 14 species of plants and analyzed by gas chromatography coupled with mass spectrometry are presented for each of the essential oils in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab1" href="#tab1">Table 1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical compounds identified by LC-ESI-MS in extracts prepared for the 9 species of plants that are included in the Lamiaceae family are also presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yalçin and the collaborators showed, using HPLC-ESI-MS, that the 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-butanol extract of 
  <span class="italic">Lamium garganicum</span> subsp. 
  <span class="italic">Laevigatum</span>, which was previously shown to possess anti-inflammatory and antinociceptive activity, contains nine iridoid glycosides [
  <a rid="B366" ref-type="bibr" href="#B366">366</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The decoction prepared from 
  <span class="italic">Melissa officinalis</span> dry leaves was filtered through a Whatman no. 4 filter paper, frozen and lyophilized. The phenolic compounds were separated and analyzed by HPLC coupled with an ESI-triple quadrupole-ion trap mass spectrometer using the negative-ion mode. The identification of the phenolic compounds was carried out based on the comparison of their retention time, UV-Vis, and mass spectra with those obtained from solutions prepared with standard substances. For the compounds for which no standard substance was available, the identification was performed based on the scientific literature [
  <a rid="B367" ref-type="bibr" href="#B367">367</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the UHPLC-ESI-MS data reported by Martina Cirlini et al. [
  <a rid="B368" ref-type="bibr" href="#B368">368</a>], the methanolic extract of 
  <span class="italic">Mentha spicata</span> contains 88% of rosmarinic acid derivatives when calculating the amount of rosmarinic acid derivatives as percentage of the total amount of detected phenols. For the salvianolic acids, a percentage of 5.6% of the total amount of detected phenols was calculated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taamalli and collaborators reported the analyses of the methanolic extract of 
  <span class="italic">Mentha pulegium</span> performed using an UPLC-ESI-QTOF mass spectrometer coupled with a liquid chromatograph and detected metabolites from the following groups: hydroxybenzoic acids, hydroxycinnamic acids, flavanols, flavones, flavanones, flavonols, organic acids, nucleosides, amino acids, and fatty acids [
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>]. In the methanolic extract of 
  <span class="italic">Mentha pulegium</span>, the authors identified a very high amount of gallocatechin.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of the plant 
  <span class="italic">Marrubium vulgare</span>, Amessis-Ouchemoukh Nadia and collaborators prepared the methanolic extract and analyzed it using an UHPLC-ESI-QTOF instrument. The mass spectra were acquired in the negative-ion mode and showed the presence of the metabolites presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a> [
  <a rid="B369" ref-type="bibr" href="#B369">369</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anna Vallverdú-Queralt et al. identified the phenolic compounds present in the ethanolic acidified extract of 
  <span class="italic">Origanum vulgare</span> (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>) [
  <a rid="B370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B370">370</a>]. After the first extraction with a hydroalcoholic solvent, the extracted plant material was centrifuged, dried, ground, and stored. An aliquot of 1 g of extracted and dried plant material was subjected to extraction, 3 times, with 5 mL of 50% aqueous ethanol containing 0.1% formic acid. All the supernatants were combined, and the organic solvent was evaporated under nitrogen flow. The dried residue was dissolved in 0.1% formic acid and subjected to solid-phase extraction using mixed-mode anion-exchange cartridges in order to reduce potential interferences from plant extracts. For accurate mass measurement, the separation and mass spectrometric analyses were performed using a LC-ESI-LTQ-Orbitrap mass spectrometer operated in negative-ion mode. The quantification of the compounds identified was performed using a triple-quadrupole mass spectrometer.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pandey and Kumar performed extraction of dried leaves of 
  <span class="italic">Ocimum basilicum</span> using 80% aqueous methanol [
  <a rid="B371" ref-type="bibr" href="#B371">371</a>]. A liquid chromatograph coupled to an ESI-Q-TOF mass spectrometer was used for the identification of the compounds, and the results are summarized in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
