<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many researchers have reported the biomedical applications of herbal medicines [
 <xref rid="B346-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">346</xref>,
 <xref rid="B347-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">347</xref>,
 <xref rid="B348-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">348</xref>,
 <xref rid="B349-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">349</xref>,
 <xref rid="B350-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">350</xref>,
 <xref rid="B351-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">351</xref>,
 <xref rid="B352-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">352</xref>,
 <xref rid="B353-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">353</xref>,
 <xref rid="B354-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">354</xref>,
 <xref rid="B355-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">355</xref>,
 <xref rid="B356-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">356</xref>,
 <xref rid="B357-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">357</xref>,
 <xref rid="B358-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">358</xref>,
 <xref rid="B359-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">359</xref>,
 <xref rid="B360-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">360</xref>,
 <xref rid="B361-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">361</xref>,
 <xref rid="B362-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">362</xref>,
 <xref rid="B363-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">363</xref>,
 <xref rid="B364-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">364</xref>,
 <xref rid="B365-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">365</xref>]. Antibiotics and other chemical antimicrobial agents including metal oxide and metal nanoparticles can inhibit bacteria growth but also lead to ROS generation and other side effects. On the other hand, herbal medicines such as clove, portulaca, tribulus, eryngium, cinnamon, turmeric, ginger, thyme, pennyroyal, mint, fennel, chamomile, burdock, eucalyptus, primrose, lemon balm, mallows, and garlic can eliminate bacteria by acting as a free radical scavenger. The antibacterial activity of these herbal medicines is different toward various kinds of bacteria and different kind of extract and essential oil of these herbal medicines [
 <xref rid="B73-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B366-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">366</xref>]. In this light, it was exhibited [
 <xref rid="B34-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B367-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">367</xref>] that the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of these herbal medicines such as the essential oil of thyme towards various bacteria is in the range of 50–400 ppm for 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>P. mirabilis</italic>, 
 <italic>S. typhimurium</italic>, 
 <italic>P. vulgaris</italic>, 
 <italic>Y. enterocolitica</italic>, 
 <italic>S. marcescens</italic>, 
 <italic>B. licheniformis</italic>, 
 <italic>P. putida</italic>, 
 <italic>S. flava</italic>, 
 <italic>P. fluorescens</italic>, 
 <italic>L. innocua</italic>, 
 <italic>Micrococcus spp</italic>., 
 <italic>and B. thuringiensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B34-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B367-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">367</xref>]. However, some other studies [
 <xref rid="B368-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">368</xref>,
 <xref rid="B369-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">369</xref>,
 <xref rid="B370-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">370</xref>,
 <xref rid="B371-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">371</xref>,
 <xref rid="B372-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">372</xref>,
 <xref rid="B373-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">373</xref>,
 <xref rid="B374-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">374</xref>,
 <xref rid="B375-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">375</xref>,
 <xref rid="B376-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">376</xref>] evaluated positive aspects and restrictions of nanofibrous dressings with a great surface area and capacity to release antibiotics, herbal medicine, and antibacterial agents locally into the wound in order to the treatment of infection. It is worth noting that herbal medicines can act as direct antioxidants by blocking ROS generation and therefore can inhibit the planned cell death pathways. Thus, based on the lower concentration of ROS, the defense mechanism is started before the apoptosis pathway is prompted by glutamate. The presence of phenolic compounds in the extract or essential oil of these herbal medicines often demonstrates the potent antioxidant and antimicrobial properties. Therefore, herbal medicines are often preferred due to their less toxic and side effect-free nature compared to synthetic antimicrobial agents. Based on the high antimicrobial and antioxidant ability of these herbal medicines, they can be beneficial for healing all types of wounds. Herbal medicines also show a high antimicrobial potential at a lower price. Bioavailability is the primary essential measure for assessing the health benefits of herbal medicine for humans. In current years, the idea that natural remedies are more secure in comparison with prescription medications has acquired traction and contributed to a massive rise in phytopharmaceutical applications [
 <xref rid="B377-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">377</xref>]. The bioavailability of these herbal medicinal products varies in blood, plasma, or tissue [
 <xref rid="B378-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>]. The bioavailability of these herbal medicinal products such as thyme [
 <xref rid="B379-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">379</xref>], eucalyptus [
 <xref rid="B380-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">380</xref>], turmeric [
 <xref rid="B381-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">381</xref>], mint [
 <xref rid="B378-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>], garlic [
 <xref rid="B382-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">382</xref>], ginger [
 <xref rid="B377-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">377</xref>], cinnamon [
 <xref rid="B377-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">377</xref>], and clove [
 <xref rid="B377-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">377</xref>] was recorded in earlier research. These studies significantly lead to the precise scientific evaluation of the numerous remarks regarding the herbal products, which are progressively marketed with curative remarks throughout the world [
 <xref rid="B378-antioxidants-09-01309" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>]. Therefore, the replacement of chemical antimicrobial agents with these herbal antimicrobial agents is a perfect solution due to their performance as an antimicrobial agent and also their radical scavenger ability. Herbal materials have created a novel exciting field in all sciences, especially in medicine, for future studies due to their unique properties. Their medicinal applications have already led to the development of new medical productions. Considering the decisive role of antimicrobial drugs in human life, these new fields in the drug industry have become increasingly more acceptable. However, designing new antimicrobial drugs free from side effects will not only create a new area of study but can also help meet the expanding human needs. Hence, this review suggests the use of herbal antimicrobial agents instead of synthetic ones due to their dual activity. In this paper, antioxidant, antimicrobial, and antiviral properties of individual herbs have been described comprehensively. Use of a combination of these herbs is also widespread in traditional medicine practice. Therefore, future research can focus on the characterization of the active component and the effect of herb–herb combinations for future therapeutic advancements and pharmaceutical product development. These materials shows high antiviral activity; therefore, these biomaterials are suggested for use against the COVID-19 virus. Therefore, these materials can be suggested to improve drug delivery (Covid-19), cancer therapy, infection, and acceleration of the healing rate, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antioxidants-09-01309-f005">Figure 5</xref>.
</p>
