<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With other respects of Gram-negative bacteria, essential oils inhibited the growth of ESBL producing 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa and E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>K. pneumoniae</italic> isolate of an infected wound. Bactericidal activity of essential oils was remarkable and pronounced inhibitory effect on references and drug-resistant bacteria. This insight into the application of essential oils on wound can improve healing. On the other hand, doses, types, and bacteria species determine the effectiveness of oils. These findings agreeing with essential oils can reduce biofilm formation and multiplication and inhibit inflammatory edema formation and leucocyte chemotaxis around the wound [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. There were several determinants of acquired resistance to conventional drugs. In line with this, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> developed resistance genes to many available and affordable antibiotics [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. These are associated with spontaneous mutations that interfere with drug-target binding and compromise prodrug activation or cause over expression of the target [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Other studies showed that there were intrinsic genes, acquired antibiotic resistance (expressed new trait), and caused the genetic change. The genetic changes can confer resistance to antibiotics by altering the target site of the drug, enzymatical inactivation of the drug, and preventing the drug from accessing the target sites. Those factors compromised all or third-generation cephalosporins and penicillin classes [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Overall, those factors contributed to resisted amoxicillin, tetracycline, piperacillin, ofloxacin, and oxacillin [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
