<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antimicrobial tests</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> was investigated for its antibacterial and antifungal activities. The antibacterial activity was examined against the growth of four reference bacterial strains obtained from the American Type Culture Collection (ATCC); 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (ATCC 25923), 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> (ATCC 25922) and 
  <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span> (ATCC 27853) as well as against the growth of a diagnostically-confirmed Methicillin Resistant 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span> (MRSA) clinical isolates. The antifungal activity of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil was examined against the growth of a diagnostically-confirmed 
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> clinical isolate. The antimicrobial activities of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> oil used in this study were determined by using broth micro-dilution method as described previously by Wikler 2007 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> was dissolved in 5 % Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) at a concentration of 132 mg/ml. The prepared oil solution was filter-sterilized and then was serially micro-diluted (2 folds) 11 times in sterile nutrient broth. The dilution processes were carried out under aseptic conditions in 96 well plates. In the micro-wells that were assigned to evaluate the antibacterial activities of the oil, the concentration of this oil ranged from 0.129 to 66 mg/ml. While the concentrations of this oil in the micro-wells assigned to evaluate their antifungal activities ranged from 0.065 to 55 mg/ml. In these plates, micro-well number 11 contained essential oils-free nutrient broth, which was used as a positive control for microbial growth. On the other hand, micro-well number 12 contained essential oils-free nutrient broth that was left un-inoculated with any of the test microbes. This well was used as a negative control for microbial growth. Micro-wells numbers 1 to 11 were inoculated aseptically with the test microbes. At the time of inoculation, the final concentrations of microbial cells were about 5 × 10
  <span class="sup">5</span> and 0.5–2.5 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> colony-forming unit (CFU)/ml for the tested bacterial pathogens and 
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span>, respectively. Each of the included microbes in this study was examined in duplicate for being inhibited by the obtained 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All of the inoculated plates were incubated at 35 °C. The incubation period lasted for about 18 h for those plates inoculated with the test bacterial strains and for about 48 h for those plates inoculated with 
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span>. The lowest concentration of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil, at which no visible microbial growth in that micro-well was observed, and was considered as the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) of the examined 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil.
 </p>
</sec>
