<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oils are highly valuable natural products and most of them are phytogenic compounds and had been used since ancient times in cosmetics, food and medicine due to their aromatic odor as well as their therapeutic effect [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemically, most of the essential oils are mixtures of hydrocarbon compounds (C
  <sub>5</sub>H
  <sub>8</sub>)
  <sub>n</sub> with their oxygenated, hydrogenated and dehydrogenated derivatives and most of them are monoterpenoids and sesquiterpenoids. There are about 3000 species of plants containing essential oils, from which 10 % are commercially important and used in perfumes, cosmetics and medicines or used as food and drugs preservatives and flavoring agents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therapeutically, essential oils have been approved for their antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral, anthelmintic, local anaesthetic, antispasmodic, carminative, expectorant, antimutagenic and many other therapeutic effects [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]
  <span class="italic">.</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is well known that plant biodiversity is greatly affected by geographic location. The Holy Land, especially, West Bank-Palestine, is considered one of the richest areas in plant biodiversity. This may be due to its special climate and topo-geographic terrains. In fact, this location is covered with thousands of plant species. Since ancient time, Jericho was highly advanced in the field of agriculture and horticulture, where peas, lentils, barley and wheat were cultivated. For centuries, thyme was considered one of the most used herbs in the Palestinian folkloric food and medicine. The genus 
  <span class="italic">Thymus</span> (Lamiaceae family) is known in several Mediterranean and other countries as food and a spice and is employed for the treatment of several diseases including cough, cancer and many fungal skin infections [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Thymus bovei</span> Benth. is a native species of the eastern Mediterranean regions. It is an aromatic, perennial herbaceous plant and is considered one of the most important 
  <span class="italic">Thymus</span> species for culinary and medicinal purposes. In the West Asian and North African regions, this herb has been utilized for treatment of various skin and blood infections as well as other infectious diseases. In the Palestinian folk medicine 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> has been used as anthelmintic, expectorant, antispasmodic, antiseptic as well as for treatment of injuries, upper respiratory system inflammations and anorexia [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To the best of our knowledge, there are no previous reports on the chemical composition and biological activity of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil originating from this area. The aim of this study was to characterize the composition of the essential oil of wild-growing 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> from the city of Jericho in Palestine. The goal was also to test the anthelmintic, antioxidant, antifungal and antibacterial activities of the analyzed essential oil as a potentially new source of biologically active natural products, especially that this plant has been used in the Palestinian folk medicine from ancient times as anthelmintic, anti-inflammatory and as antiseptic.
 </p>
</sec>
