<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multi-antibiotic resistance is becoming one of the major global concerns. 
  <span class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Klebsiella pneumonia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> and many other 
  <span class="italic">ß-</span>lactamase inhibitors have become a major clinical problem. Increased attention has been focused on the usage of natural antimicrobial agents, especially from plant origins, due to their safety and efficacy as well as the fact that the majority of essential oils are classified as Generally Recognized As Safe (GRAS) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In fact, natural products are used intensively as food preservatives, nutraceuticals as well as potential drugs for the treatment and prevention of various diseases and conditions including: cancer, cardiovascular disorders, aging and many others. For these reasons, in recent decades, worldwide studies have been conducted for the characterization, utilization and extraction of biological and pharmacological active compounds from plant origins [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of our phytochemical analysis showed consistent differences in the content of Palestinian 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> when compared with the only study which was conducted on the similar species by Tepe et al. 2011. Trans-geraniol, α-citral and β-citral were identified as major components of the Palestinian 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil while the major components of the Turkish 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil were carvacrol, p-cymene and thymol. This may be due to the differences between the two geographic and topographic areas, which may greatly affect their constituents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, these differences in the chemical composition may explain the differences in the antimicrobial activities. In fact, our 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> showed higher activity than the corresponding Turkish species, which were 0.5 and 31.25 for 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>, and 0.25 and 31.25 for 
  <span class="italic">Candida albicans</span> respectively, which means that our studied species had more powerful antibacterial activity against studied microbial species than the Turkish 
  <span class="italic">Thymus</span> species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, our results are in agreement with the literature with regards to the antimicrobial effects of these compounds which were reported in a study conducted by Pattnaik et al. 1996. In this study citral, linalool, geraniol, menthol and cineole were tested against eighteen bacterial strains and twelve fungal strains. The results showed that geraniol and citral are the active constituents in the aromatic plants with strong antibacterial and antifungal potentials [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another study performed by Singh et al. 2012, found that geraniol and terpineol, the major components of geranium oil, were active against Gram-positive and Gram-negative pathogenic bacteria. Antifungal activity was also observed against yeast, 
  <span class="italic">Dermatophytes</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Aspergillus</span> species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, citral isomers such as trans-citral and cis-citral and geraniol were found to have potential antioxidant activity compared to Trolox standard, in studies performed by Choi et al. 2000 and Francesco et al., 2016 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our study the free radical scavenging activity in comparison with Trolox standard for 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil was higher than 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> from Turkish origins which may again be caused by differences in the chemical compositions between the two species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In fact, geraniol is an alcoholic monoterpenoid and is commercially used in flavors and fragrances. In addition to its aromatic odor, geraniol is known to exhibit insecticidal and repellent properties and is used as a natural pest control agent exhibiting low toxicity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Accordingly, conducting research studies in order to discover other therapeutic agents is a striving challenge. Again, herbals are currently considered the most important door to be addressed. 
  <span class="italic">Thymus bovei</span>, is extensively used as anthelmintic herb in the Palestinian heritage and folk medicine. Accordingly, it was extremely important to investigate the efficacy of its essential oil as an anthelmintic agent by comparing it with piperazine citrate.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anthelmintic activity of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> was tested in comparison with piperazine citrate. The obtained results showed significant potency for 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> against worms, which is supposed to be due to the presence of high content of geraniol in this plant species. In addition, these results showed a concentration dependent effect, since the time of paralysis and death decreased as the concentration of geraniol in the extract increased. These finding are in accordance with the literature, since plants with high geraniol content exhibited anthelmintic activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further pharmacological and toxicological examination of 
  <span class="italic">T. bovei</span> essential oil are needed to explore its synergistic effects with first line antibiotics, especially against bacteria that have developed resistance, as well as to study its safety.
 </p>
</sec>
