<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Therefore, in recent years, cotton growers in China’s Xinjiang region have begun to spray defoliants using plant protection unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Compared with traditional mechanical and artificial pesticide application, use of UAVs is labor and time-saving, with the same significant effect on defoliation and ripening of cotton, but no significant effect on yield and quality
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. With the introduction of UAVs, cotton cultivation has become more mechanized and technological. Pesticides sprayed by plant protection UAVs show high levels of safety and cause little harm to the human body. The UAVs produce a low-altitude and low-volume flight spray. The airflow generated by the propeller causes the pesticide mist to flow through the cotton plant from top to bottom with strong penetration, less drift, and uniform spray
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, the coverage rate of pesticide formulations is higher and more efficient than that using more traditional methods
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. At the same time, UAVs can reduce land pollution caused by pesticides and improve pesticide utilization rates. The spray efficiency and effectiveness of plant protection UAVs are significantly better than those of boom-type sprayers, but there are few pesticide formulations suitable for plant protection UAVs. The low-altitude, small-volume spray produced by plant protection UAVs imposes stricter requirements on pesticide formulations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. Defoliants currently registered in China are mainly suspension concentrates, water-dispersible granules and wettable powders, which are not suitable for spraying using plant protection UAVs. This lack of pesticide formulations suitable for UAVs is the biggest obstacle in the development of UAV application. Ultra-low-volume pesticide sprays, with high-boiling-point oil solvent as carrier, have low volatility and strong adhesion. Compared with conventional pesticide formulations, they provide special advantages, such as high levels of coverage and better efficacy, making them ideal for plant protection UAVs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
