<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Allium sativum</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Allium sativum</span> L. belongs to the genus 
  <span class="italic">Allium</span>. The family Alliaceae has around 780 species based on new internal transcribed spacer (ITR) region of nuclear ribosomal DNA classification [
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>,
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>]. It is widely dispersed over the warm-temperate and temperate zones of the northern hemisphere. Today, it is grown in a number of countries and the leading producers are India, China and Korea [
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>]. It is rich in c-glutamylcysteine and other sulfur-containing compounds giving a characteristic flavor. However, additional constituents of garlic include a wide range of primary and secondary non-sulfur biomolecules, such as steroidal glycosides, essential oil, flavonoids, anthocyanins, lectins, prostaglandins, fructan, pectin, adenosine, vitamins B1, B2, B6, C and E, biotin, nicotinic acid, fatty acids, glycolipids, phospholipids and essential amino acids [
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71–81</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">A. sativum</span> extract has demonstrated radioprotective effects in mice and was found to be effective in significantly reducing the micronuclei frequencies induced by radiation [
  <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">82</a>]. A dose-dependent effect was evaluated on the frequencies of damaged cells and chromosomal aberrations, and it was recommended that administration of the extract for 30 days is vital for mitigating the clastogenic effects of genotoxicants [
  <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">83</a>]. Recent investigations showed that aged garlic is superior to fresh garlic as far as antiglycation and antioxidant activities are concerned [
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">84</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
