<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Allium cepa</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Allium cepa</span>, belonging to the family Liliaceae that occurs worldwide, is a bulbous plant. India, China and the US are the leading producer [
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">57</a>,
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">58</a>]. Traditionally, it is used for the treatment of stomach ache, throat infection and hepatitis, and has properties such as antioxidant, antihyperglycemic, antihypertentive and anti-asthamatic [
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">59–61</a>]. Among the many phyto-active constituents documented, the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">A. cepa</span> contains compounds such as 3-1,8-cineole, L-linalool and camphordare and has been thoroughly investigated. Besides this, the onion bulb contains Kaempferol, β-sitosterol, ferulic acid, myritic acid and prostaglandins. Flavonoids and tannins are also present in 
  <span class="italic">A. cepa</span>. Quercetin, quercetin 4-glucoside, taxifolin, taxifolin 7-glucoside and phenylalanine have been isolated from the bulb. The major sulfur compounds are dimethyl trisulfide, propenyl propyl disulfide, dipropyl disulfide, propenylmethyldisulfide and methyl propyl trisulfide dipropyle trisulfide. Onion contains active compounds such as allyl propyl disulfide along with other active sulfur-containing compounds [
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62–66</a>]. Radiation protection and antioxidative effects of onion extract were studied in albino rats. Biochemical parameters were assessed such as alanine aminotransferase, superoxide dismutase and catalase in liver, kidney and heart. It was concluded that onion extract has significant radioprotective activity [
  <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
