<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Coriandrum sativum</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Coriandrum sativum</span> L. belongs to the family Umbelliferae (Apiaceae), commonly called as coriander. It is widely cultivated in the Middle East, Latin America, Africa and Asia [
  <a rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" href="#B108">108</a>]. Seeds as well as leaves have been used for flavoring food since ancient times [
  <a rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" href="#B109">109</a>]. Phytochemical constituents of 
  <span class="italic">C. sativum</span> seeds showed the presence of polyphenols (rutin, caffeic acid derivatives, ferulic acid, galic acid and chlorogenic acid), flavonoids (quercetin and isoquercetin) and β-carotenoids. Seeds of coriander mainly contain essential oils; however, leaves contain caffeic acid and flavonoids apart from volatile oils [
  <a rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110">110</a>,
  <a rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" href="#B111">111</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The radio protective effect of coriander seeds against whole-body γ-irradiation was studied in rats. Treatment with coriander seed extract was effective in preventing radiation-induced biochemical changes in serum and significantly improved the antioxidant status in liver and kidney of rats. It is suggested that scavenging of free radicals was a possible mechanism of protection [
  <a rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112">112</a>]. Ethanol extract of 
  <span class="italic">C. sativum</span> was effective against Ultraviolet B (UVB)-induced skin photoaging 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> and 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span>. Thinner epidermal layers and denser dermal collagen fibers was observed in treated mice, which also had lower MMP-1 levels and higher procollagen type I levels, thus suggesting the ability of 
  <span class="italic">C. sativum</span> extract to prevent UVB-induced skin photoaging [
  <a rid="B113" ref-type="bibr" href="#B113">113</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
