<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Root-rot is a world-wide soil-borne disease, which can seriously damage many crops and medicinal plants and limit the continuous development of agriculture. 
 <italic class="italic">P. notoginseng</italic> root-rot can occur in one- or two-year growth of 
 <italic class="italic">P. notoginseng</italic>, whereas the occurrence rate of 
 <italic class="italic">P. notoginseng</italic> older than two years is more severe [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Chemical fungicides are a double-edged sword which guaranteed the agricultural development but also bring serious pollution and harm to ecology and environment or human health [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Flutriafol and hymexazol are economically important agricultural chemicals, which are able to control several diseases affecting a wide range of crops. However, their high mobility potential in the soil makes them problematic fungicides. Indeed, flutriafol is a potentially toxic chemical fungicide, which may disrupt fertility in women and affect the endocrine system [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. In contrast to chemical fungicides, botanical fungicides are wanted in agriculture. In consequence, it is very urgent to look for new compounds from natural material to develop new kinds of high efficiency, low toxicity fungicides. In the study, the results showed that 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oxysporum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">solani</italic> have strong pathogenicity to 
 <italic class="italic">P. notoginseng</italic>. After infection for a period of time, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">notoginseng</italic> appears the disease symptoms with yellowing of leaves and rot of roots (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-00213-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). By comparing the potency of the methanol extracts with roots, stems, and leaves from 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">annua</italic>, it was found that the extracts from 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> with different methanol concentrations have various antifungal activities. The antifungal effect of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">annua</italic> leaves extracted by pure methanol is the strongest (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-00213-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). When the methanol concentration reached 100%, the antifungal activity on various fungi is the most significant. At the same time, when the extraction method is the same, the antifungal activity of leaves extract is the best, while the effect of roots is the worst. Some studies showed that the ethanol extract from 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> could inhibit mycelium growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Cytospora chrysosperma</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Guignardia laricina</italic>, and its inhibition rates are 100% and 91.74%, respectively [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Therefore, an effort was made to know what kinds of substances in 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">annua</italic> leaves are active. Then solvents with different polarity were used for fractionation and antifungal evaluation. The results reveal that 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> EO is the most active, whereas the inhibitory effects of water soluble substances are negligible (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-00213-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>). By comparing the potency of different fractions, it might infer that EO is responsible for the major antifungal activity of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">annua</italic>. According to the others’ studies, the antifungal activity of 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> EO was evaluated against economically important foliar and soil borne fungal pathogens of tomato, which has revealed that 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> EO is active against 
 <italic class="italic">Sclerotinia sclerotiorum, Botrytis cinerea</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Phytophthorainfestans</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Verticillim dahliae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. They also have suggested that 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> EO could be used as potential antifungal agents to treat or prevent the pathogenic fungi.
</p>
