<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the previous study, EOs from either 
 <italic class="italic">Alpinia officinarum</italic> Hance and 
 <italic class="italic">Amomum tsao-ko</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">Zingiberaceae</italic>) are found to have a good inhibition against the 
 <italic class="italic">F. oxysporum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">F. solani</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">C. destrutans</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], and the EOs of 
 <italic class="italic">Alpinia Katsumadai</italic> Hayata and 
 <italic class="italic">Zingiber officinal</italic> Roscoe also have significant reductions in the mycelium growth of the pathogen in vitro [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. This is corroborated by our findings. The results uncover that the main ingredients are camphor, camphene, germacrene D, and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-caryophyllene (
 <xref rid="molecules-24-00213-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>), which accounted for 42.35% of the total EO. Perazzo et al. has extracted EO from 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> and identified 25 compounds including camphor (43.5%), macrocarbene D (16.0%), 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-pinocarveol (11.0%), and herb-cymene (9.0%) [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. The EO in the analysis revealed a great variability both in the qualitative and quantitative composition. Chemical profile is generally influenced by the harvesting season, fertilizer, and the pH of soils, the choice and stage of drying conditions, the geographic location, chemotype or subspecies, and choice of part plant or genotype or extraction method [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Some study showed that the yield and main components of the EOs extracted from 
 <italic class="italic">A. annua</italic> are varied at different flowering stages. The highest amounts of the main components were recorded in the full flowering stage, which main compounds are artemisia ketone (28.30–37.15%), camphor (18.00–23.30%), and 1,8-cineole (9.00–10.39%) [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-24-00213" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Then, the MIC values against 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oxysporum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">solani</italic> were determined with the 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">annua</italic> EO and the main compounds (
 <xref rid="molecules-24-00213-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). The results prove that the pathogenic fungi show a high sensibility to 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">annua</italic> EO and the main compounds, with MIC ranging from 0.09 to 0.37 mg/mL.
</p>
