<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cannabis oil galenic preparations were delivered for cannabinoids determination to our laboratory between 2017 and 2019 and account for 8,201 samples. However, after the initial data collection and laboratory analysis, samples were excluded on the basis of 1) the absence, in the detailed sheet, of pharmaceutical-grade 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> varieties; 2) the use of pharmaceutical-grade 
 <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> varieties diverse from Bedrocan, Bediol, Bedrolite, and FM2; and 3) a nonstandardized preparation method. Consequently, this study was limited to 4,774 samples standardized for both pharmaceutical-grade cannabis varieties and the extraction methods. Preparation methods are mainly based on maceration of vegetable materials in olive oil at high temperature, at about 100°C or more [Methods A (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Romano and Hazekamp, 2013</xref>) and B (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Citti et al., 2016</xref>)]. Both of them do not require a preliminary decarboxylation of the vegetal matrix. A preliminary decarboxylation step is performed with Method C [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Società Italiana Farmacisti Preparatori (SIFAP), 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Casiraghi et al., 2018</xref>] or Method D (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Calvi et al., 2018</xref>). All these methods were used by pharmacists, based on medical prescriptions, to obtained cannabis oils by different varieties of medicinal grade plant material: the Dutch Bedrocan, Bediol, Bedrolite, and the Italian FM2. After decarboxylation, where planned, the cannabis decoctions in oil were mainly carried out with a weight-to-volume ratio between plant material and oil of 1:10 (usually 5 g in 50 ml) (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Baratta et al., 2019</xref>). Mainly, pharmacopeia grade olive oil, usually virgin or refined according to the European Pharmacopoeia (Ph. Eur.), was used as extraction solvent. This oil can minimize the formation of large amounts of aldehydes and ketones that can also influence the digestibility of the macerated oil (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Pavlovic et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
