<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">In vitro</italic> laboratory experiments may have more relevance to post-harvest interventions than pre-harvest mediations due to the complexity of the poultry GIT that cannot easily be modeled in a laboratory environment (
 <xref rid="B310" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">White et al., 1997</xref>). For instance, in a series of benchtop studies orange oil was found to be inhibitory to 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni, C. coli, L. monocytogenes, Salmonella</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas</italic> (
 <xref rid="B220" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">O’Bryan et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nannapaneni et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chalova et al., 2010</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nannapaneni et al. (2009)</xref> tested seven orange oil fractions on 3 
 <italic class="italic">Arcobacter</italic> strains and 21 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> strains, including 14 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> strains, four of which were isolated from poultry. When viewed on disk diffusion agar, cold pressed (CP) terpeneless Valencia orange oil produced the largest zones of inhibition (in mm) of 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> including those isolated in poultry, whereas other orange oil fractions produced more limited zones of inhibition. Valencia orange oil was also reported to be inhibitory toward 
 <italic class="italic">C. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Arcobacter</italic>. 
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kurekci et al. (2013)</xref> found tea tree oil at a concentration of 0.001% to be inhibitory against two strains of 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> on nutrient agar. Wild carrot oil, when used in agar plates as an antimicrobial against 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> spp. including a multidrug-resistant strain, 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> 99T403, exhibited a minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of 125 to 500 μg/mL depending on the species or strain (
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi et al., 2007</xref>). Isoeugenol and E-methyl isoeugenol are extracts of carrot oil and when tested against 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> resulted in an MIC of 125 μg/mL (
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi et al., 2007</xref>). Thymol, in a concentration of 0.25 μmol/mL, reduced 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. coli</italic> by 5 logs CFU/mL in Bolton broth from an initial concentration of 7 log CFU/mL (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Anderson et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carocho et al., 2014</xref>). An EO extract from 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum minutiflorum</italic>, composed primarily of carvacrol and 
 <italic class="italic">p-</italic>cymene, has been shown to be effective in inhibiting 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> in concentrations as low as 12.5 μg/mL on Mueller-Hinton agar (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aslim and Yucel, 2008</xref>). However, these MICs were strain-specific, as of the 12 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> strains tested, only 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> 118d was inhibited at the concentration of 12.5 μg/mL, while 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> 113k, 7d, and 9a required 700 μg/mL to be inhibited (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aslim and Yucel, 2008</xref>). Cinnamon, clove, thyme, and bay leaf oils were found to be bacteriostatic at a concentration of 0.075% against 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni, S.</italic> Enteritidis
 <italic class="italic">, E. coli, Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> when tested in tryptic soy broth (TSB) (
 <xref rid="B267" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Smith-Palmer et al., 1998</xref>).
</p>
