<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The use of EOs in the post-harvest environment has focused on their bactericidal activity within carcasses washes and finished products (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Calo et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dima and Dima, 2015</xref>). A 0.5% 50:50 mixture of thyme oil and orange oil was used in a marinade for chicken wings dip-inoculated with 10
 <sup class="sup">7</sup> CFU/mL of a nalidixic acid resistant strain of 
 <italic class="italic">C. coli</italic> (
 <xref rid="B278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thanissery and Smith, 2014</xref>). While cross-contamination events were observed via the marinade, 
 <italic class="italic">C. coli</italic> concentrations on treated wings were reduced by 3.0 log CFU/mL, as determined through plating of rinsates. Skinless chicken breasts experimentally infected with 5 × 10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> CFU/g of 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> were subjected to stinkwort (0.2%; 
 <italic class="italic">Inula graveolens</italic>), bay leaf (0.6%; 
 <italic class="italic">Laurus nobilis</italic>), mastic tree (0.6%; 
 <italic class="italic">Pistacia lentiscus</italic>), and winter savory (0.6%; 
 <italic class="italic">Atureja gontana</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Djenane et al., 2012</xref>). After 8 days of refrigerated storage under microaerophilic conditions, greater than 5 log CFU/g reductions of 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> were observed compared to the control inoculated with 5 × 10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> CFU/g. Sensory analysis indicated these EOs improved or did not impact the odor of the refrigerated samples according to a six member trained panel. Within 60 s, 0.06% linalool oil reduced 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> on 2 cm × 2 cm pieces of cabbage leaf and chicken skin by greater than 5 log CFU and 2 log CFU, respectively (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fisher and Phillips, 2006</xref>). Cold pressed Valencia orange oil has also been shown to reduce 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> UAF 244 on retail chicken thighs and legs (
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nannapaneni et al., 2009</xref>). Chicken thighs and legs were dipped in a 0.8% saline solution containing 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> CFU/mL 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> UAF 244 for 5 min and then submerged for 2 min in 20% (v/v) Valencia orange oil or 20% (v/v) limonene. The samples were then rinsed and plated. Across both types of chicken pieces, 1.5 to 2 log CFU/mL reductions were observed, compared to the control. Treatments with limonene resulted in reductions without detectable recovery of viable bacterial cells, although the limit of detection was not provided by the authors. Moreover, while taste panels have found concentrations of orange oil up to 0.1% to be acceptable in milk, chicken patties and marinades, a 20% part dip has not been investigated for impacts on sensory characteristics (
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jo et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fisher and Phillips, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B244" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rimini et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
