<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We had also hypothesized that, due to incongruent evolutionary history, native herbivore abundance would be depressed within invaded patches. The Coleoptera were not correlated with presence of 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic>, but herbivorous Hemiptera were more abundant within the invaded plots. Given the low levels of herbivory seen on 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> (Morrison, Lubchansky, Mauck, McCartney, &amp; Dunn, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Sanders, Belote, &amp; Weltzin, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>) and the general lack of understory forest vegetation in reference plots, it is likely the invaded habitats provided favorable near‐ground microhabitat conditions for invertebrates, including herbivores, without providing increased palatable plant biomass for native insects. The δ
 <sup>13</sup>C values of sampled spiders in our study area similarly reflect dietary avoidance of 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> by herbivorous prey insects, which include the abundant planthoppers and leafhoppers found in the study area. In our study area, spiders collected in plots dominated by 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> exhibited δ
 <sup>13</sup>C values near −26‰, while the C
 <sub>4</sub>
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> carbon ratios are generally between −13 and −15‰ (Bradford et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Considering a potential stepwise increase of 0.5‰ per trophic level, it is unlikely that potential prey in this invaded habitat, including detritus‐based Diptera and phytophagous Hemiptera, are utilizing the invasive species. If so, spider δ
 <sup>13</sup>C values should be much closer to that of C
 <sub>4</sub> plants. Given the relative abundance of flies deriving from detrital food webs in invaded plots, it is likely that the spider community in our study area is largely supported by the detritivores (Hyodo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; McNabb, Halaj, &amp; Wise, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Miyashita, Takada, &amp; Shimazaki, 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). These fly larvae are likely feeding on the litter and root systems of the surrounding C
 <sub>3</sub> trees due to the paucity of other understory plant species both within and adjacent to invaded plots. The few taxa found to utilize 
 <italic>M. vimineum</italic> in the southeastern U.S. (Bradford et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36752-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) are not likely to be ingested by 
 <italic>L. venusta</italic> and are too large to be captured by most forest web‐building spiders in the mid‐Atlantic U.S. The primary producers supporting the food web in this invaded habitat are the less abundant C
 <sub>3</sub> species, indicating the importance of native vegetation in providing energy for resident herbivorous and predatory insect communities.
</p>
