<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec4.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Chemical Composition Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chromatographic spectra of different essential oils from different Moroccan regions revealed the same qualitative chemical composition with some quantitative differences. 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-spathulenol is the most abundant compound and represents 15% of the essential oil from Berkane region. trans-Caryophyllene oxide prevails in essential oils from all regions with an average rate of 14%. Ar-curcumene is found to represent 14% of the essential oils from Beni Mellal and Agadir regions and 11% of those from other regions. Neral represents 10% of the essential oil from Agadir region and 6% to 8% of those from other regions. cis-Verbenol represents nearly 8% of the essential oil from Agadir region and 4% to 6% of other essential oils. Paracymene was only present in the essential oil from Agadir region at 0.02%. 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-muurolene was only found at 0.04% in the essential oils from Beni Mellal and Demnate regions. 8-Cedren-13-ol was not found in the essential oil from Agadir and represented 0.01 to 0.05% of the essential oils from other regions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The major molecules dominating the chemical composition of essential oils are caryophyllene oxide, 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-spathulenol, Ar-curcumene, neral, and cis-verbenol (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab2" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>). Other products such as 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, isoledene, elemene, 1.8-cineole, copaene, and nerol are also present with variable ratios. Unlikely, limonene and 6-methyl-5-hepten-2-one, which are compounds constantly found in
   <span class="italic"> A. citriodora</span> essential oils distilled in Morocco at proportions of 14% for the first and 3% for the second, are present in the studied essential oils in the present work at very low averaging rates of 0.02% to 0.5%. In fact, the compositions of the essential oils depend on the operating (drying, extraction methods) and on the harvest and the storage conditions [
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>, 
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chemical composition analysis of our essential oil was dominated mainly by Ar-curcumene (12.32%), caryophyllene oxide (13.68%), and spathulenol (12.38%). Other compounds were reported in the essential oil of Argentina which is rich in ketones (myrcenone 36.50%, 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-thujone 13.10%), while limonene is only at 6.87% [
   <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>]. The essential oil from Turkey contains citrals ranging from 17.90% to 27.10% and limonene of 16% [
   <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>]. The major compounds of the essential oil of
   <span class="italic"> A. citriodora</span> from Portugal were geranial (26.80% to 38.30%), neral (20.80% to 29.60%), and limonene (5.70% to 20.60%) [
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main compounds found in the present investigation were different quantitatively and qualitatively from those reported in the literature. The average rate of limonene and geranial was 17% and 9%, respectively, in different essential oils distilled from
   <span class="italic"> A. citriodora</span> grown in Morocco (leaves of
   <span class="italic"> A. citriodora</span> harvested in May period), whereas the amount of the monoterpene (limonene) is only 0.52% and the terpene aldehyde (geranial) is not detected in the present study. However, the rates of sesquiterpenes (
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, Ar-curcumene, 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-elemene, etc.), terpene oxides (caryophyllene oxide), some monoterpene alcohols (cis-verbenol), and sesquiterpene alcohols (spathulenol) were higher in the present studied essential oils [
   <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>]. It is interesting to note that limonene, 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene, p-cymene, linalool, citral, 
   <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene, and 1.8-cineole are common compounds of essential oils of
   <span class="italic"> Lippia</span> sp. and thought to be responsible for specific biological effects and properties attributed to the genus
   <span class="italic"> Aloysia</span> [
   <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. Cytotoxicity against P815, MCF7, VERO, and PBMCs Cell Lines</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the essential oils cytotoxicity ranking [
   <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>], the five essential oils studied marked very high cytotoxic effect against P815 (BE essential oil is the most cytotoxic with IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 6.60 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml) and high to moderate activity against MCF7 and VERO cell lines (DE essential oil is the most cytotoxic with IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 34.72 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml and 32.90 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>g/ml, resp.). To the best of our knowledge, there is no previous report about the cytotoxic activity of
   <span class="italic"> A. citriodora</span> essential oil. However, the cytotoxic effect of
   <span class="italic"> Lippia alba</span>, with its main constituent citral on HeLa and VERO cell lines was reported [
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>]. The interesting cytotoxicity toward cell lines could be due to the main compounds in the essential oil. Literature reports the induction of apoptosis by citrals (neral and geranial) in chronic lymphoid leukemia by activation of caspase-3 [
   <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>, 
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>]. Moreover, it has also been demonstrated that 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene and caryophyllene oxide were also reported to induce apoptosis in tumor cells and exert analgesic, anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, antifungal, and sedative activities [
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. Furthermore, 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-elemene and spathulenol were reported as having anticancer activities on human glioblastoma and on MCF7 cancer cell lines [
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>–
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>]. Interestingly, no cytotoxic effect of
   <span class="italic"> A. citriodora</span> essential oil studied here was observed on Human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Antibacterial Effect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MIC values (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tab4" href="#tab4">Table 4</a>) showed that the MA and BM essential oils were the most active against
   <span class="italic"> E. coli</span> and BM and DE were the most active against
   <span class="italic"> S. aureus</span>. In contrast, AG and BE were the least effective on
   <span class="italic"> E. coli</span> and on
   <span class="italic"> S. aureus</span>, respectively. All the five tested essential oils showed no activity against
   <span class="italic"> P. aeruginosa</span>. Other studies have shown that this bacterial strain is naturally resistant to other essential oils. The CMB/MIC ratio (2.14 for
   <span class="italic"> E. coli</span> and 2.02 for
   <span class="italic"> S. aureus</span>) permitted to qualify the five studied essential oils as bactericidal [
   <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>]. Interestingly, it was observable that cytotoxic and antibacterial activities of essential oils were different; for example, MA presented the moderate cytotoxicity but a very strong antibacterial activity. This may be explained by qualitative and quantitative variability of chemical compounds identified in these essential oils and their differential molecular mechanisms.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, the first site of action of essential oils on the bacterial cells is the membranes. This is directly related to the hydrophobicity of the essential oils components. This property ensures and facilitates permeability of membrane phospholipids bilayer to these molecules. The result is a destabilization of the plasma membrane structure and a change in its permeability to ions, protons, and other cellular components [
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>–
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>]. In addition to the induced membrane alterations, such molecules can cross the lipid bilayer and interact with intracytoplasmic targets [
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>]. Given the molecular diversity of the essential oils, it appears more likely that their antibacterial activity results from the combination of several mechanisms, acting synergistically on different cellular targets [
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>]. In fact, among the dominant molecules in the five studied essential oils, caryophyllene and 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-caryophyllene oxide have antibacterial and antifungal activities [
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>]. Oxygenates (caryophyllene oxide, 1.8-cineole, etc.) have
   <span class="italic"> in vitro</span> antibacterial activity [
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>]; citral (neral and geranial) has a strong antibacterial effect [
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>]. The interaction between p-cymene, ‎
   <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene, and the phenolic compounds could exhibt an antibacterial activity [
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>]. Furthermore, the essential oils showing high antibacterial activity are phenol and cinnamic aldehyde rich oils (thymol, carvacrol, and eugenol) as in the essential oils of
   <span class="italic"> Thymus vulgaris</span>,
   <span class="italic"> Origanum compactum</span>,
   <span class="italic"> Satureja montana</span>,
   <span class="italic"> Eugenia caryophyllata</span>, and
   <span class="italic"> Cinnamomum zeylanicum</span> [
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>]. However, antimicrobial effectiveness of an essential oil is due to the nature and content of these various constituents that may act synergistically; the effect of minor compounds is not always negligible. Synergism between constituents can cause a much more pronounced effect than the expected activity of the major compounds [
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
