<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0205">Heavy metal contamination in medicinal plants is an increasing concern [
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The anthropogenic release of heavy metals into the environment by mining, manufacturing, agriculture, and smelting is the major cause of heavy metal entry into the food chain and plant constituents. Certain heavy metals are essential for fundamental biological processes. However, when in excess heavy metals may induce substantial detrimental effects both as cellular and organismal level. For instance, copper works as a cofactor in numerous cellular reactions including metabolic pathways; however, in excess it can cause toxicity and may exhibit carcinogenic activities [
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Likewise, lead is a highly poisonous metal, affecting almost every organ and tissue in the human body including brain, kidneys and liver. By mimicking calcium, lead can cross the blood–brain barrier and degrades the myelin sheaths of neurons, reduces their numbers, interferes with neurotransmission routes and decreases neuronal growth. In the human body, lead inhibits porphobilinogen synthase and ferrochelatase, resulting in ineffective heme synthesis causing anemia [
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The role of arsenic in humans is not well understood; however, excess intake of arsenic has detrimental effects on human health [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Zinc is an important micronutrient for many biochemical metabolisms in the plants. It is required for the optimum crop growth and is taken in divalent form by the plants. Zinc deficiency causes the gastrointestinal, central nervous, epidermal, immune, skeletal, and reproductive disorders. Zinc supplement can reduce episode of malaria, prevalence of pneumonia and diarrhea [
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Iron is an important component or molecule of hemoglobin in red blood cells that carry oxygen from our lungs to transport it throughout our body. A lack of red blood cells is called “iron deficiency anemia” which is dangerous for the human body [
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The soil has been drastically polluted and becomes reservoir of metal contents because of excessive use of synthetic fertilizers and industrial discharge to the agricultural land and other intentional or unintentional hazardous activities by human. These heavy metals in turn transferred to human and other animals by consumption of plants parts which store metal contents. Consequently, heavy metals enter to the ecosystem and lead to elevated bioaccumulation and storage in plants, animal and human.
</p>
