<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kilaru et al. (2015)</xref> carried out a complete transcriptomic analysis targeting pathways related to oil metabolism in mesocarp and seeds from avocado cv. Hass at five different developmental stages (from 125 to 230 g FW ~ 4 to 12.5% oil content) and compared with that of oil rich monocot (palm oil) and dicots (rapeseed and castor) tissues in order to identify tissue and species specific regulation of TAG biosynthesis supposed to be considered a highly conserved process in plants. Avocado mesocarp presented about 45, 34, 9, 5, 4, and 3% (average of five developmental stages) of the transcripts to be genes involved in glycolysis and plastidial fatty acid biosynthesis, pentose phosphate pathway, sucrose degradation, phospholipid, and TAG assembly and plastid transporters, respectively (
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kilaru et al., 2015</xref>). It was noted that across the five developmental stages of the mesocarp, the abundance of genes involved in glycolysis for the generation of pyruvate and further fatty acid synthesis was striking as the genes involved in the acyl group synthesis in the plastid in contrast to the abundance levels of genes involved in phospholipid and TAG assembly remained pretty constant among the different developmental stages of the mesocarp. 
 <xref rid="ref126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vergara-Pulgar et al. (2019)</xref> has recently reported a strong expression of transcripts related to fatty acid and TAG biosynthesis at the start of the developmental process of Hass avocado (150 DAFS and 240 DAFS) but downregulation for later stages of 300 DAFS and 390 DAFs, respectively, which support previous reports that most of the lipid content in avocado is produced during the first half of fruit development, then the processes are reduced but not culminated. Same authors have recently reported oleosin to be differentially expressed in the mesocarp between 240 DAFS and 390 DAFS possibly having a role as lipid storage stabilizer. Previously, 
 <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Horn et al. (2013)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gidda et al. (2013)</xref> reported two new lipid droplet associated proteins (LDAP1 and LDAP2) in avocado mesocarp. 
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kilaru et al. (2015)</xref> found higher expression of these proteins during the five evaluated developmental stages in avocado mesocarp. These proteins are supposed to bind and stabilize lipid particles in avocado mesocarp. Recently, 
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ge et al. (2019)</xref> reported a histological analysis of lipid droplets in avocado mesocarp during fruit development (from 65 days after pollination, DAP to 125 DAP for the avocado variety Guitenda N°2, 
 <italic class="italic">Persea americana</italic> var. guatemalensis). Small lipid droplets of 2 μm of diameter were present throughout the periphery of the cells from 65 to 105 DAP. But at 125 DAP (harvest date corresponding to 11.12% total fatty acids based on dry mass), larger lipid droplets of 10–25 μm occupying the volume of most of the cell were observed.
</p>
