<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6389899</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">39236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-39236-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>WRINKLED1</italic> transcription factor orchestrates the regulation of carbon partitioning for C18:1 (oleic acid) accumulation in Siberian apricot kernel</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Shuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>Yiting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shui</surname><given-names>Lanya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><address><email>niujun5555@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0373 6302</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.428986.9</institution-id><institution>Hainan Key Laboratory for Sustainable Utilization of Tropical Bioresource, Institute of Tropical Agriculture and Forestry, </institution><institution>Hainan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Haikou, Hainan 570228 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>25</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>2693</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">WRINKLED1 (WRI1), an APETALA2 (AP2)-type transcription factor, has been shown to be required for the regulation of carbon partitioning into fatty acid (FA) synthesis in plant seeds. To our knowledge, the regulatory network of WRI1 remains unknown in <italic>Prunus sibirica</italic> kernel (PSK), a novel woody biodiesel feedstock in China. In this study, based on the transcriptional data from developing oilseeds of multiple plant species, we identified 161 <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes using weighted gene co-expression network analysis (WGCNA). The major portion of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes was characterized to be involved in carbon partitioning and FA biosynthesis. Additionally, we detected the temporal patterns for oil content and FA compositions in developing PSK from two different germplasms (AS-85 and AS-86). The major differences between the two germplasms are higher contents of oil and C18:1 in AS-85 than in AS-86 at a mature stage. Thus, AS-85 and AS-86 are desirable materials to explore the molecular and metabolic mechanisms of oil accumulation in Siberian apricot. Expression analysis in developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86 indicated that the expression level of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>sibirica WRI1</italic> (PsWRI1) was closely correlated to accumulative rate of oil. Also, the comparison of expression profiles in developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86 displayed that the <italic>pPK</italic>, <italic>E1-&#x003b1;</italic>, <italic>E2</italic>, <italic>TAL</italic>, <italic>BC</italic>, <italic>MCMT</italic>, <italic>BS</italic>, <italic>SAD</italic> and <italic>FAD2</italic> have a high correlation with <italic>PsWRI1</italic>. Transient expression showed that Pro<sub>SAD</sub>- and Pro<sub>BS</sub>-driving GUS expression showed no substantial difference between AS-85 and AS-86, while the expression level of Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-85 driving GUS was significantly higher than that of Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-86 driving GUS. Additionally, transient co-transformation with <italic>PsWRI1</italic> revealed that Pro<sub>SAD</sub>, Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub> and Pro<sub>BS</sub> activity could be specifically up-regulated by PsWRI1. This regulatory mechanism of PsWRI1 may create a steep concentration difference, thereby facilitating carbon flux into C18:1 accumulation in developing PSK. Overall, all our findings imply a versatile mechanism of WRI1 to optimize carbon allocation for oil accumulation, which can provide reference for researching the woody biodiesel plants.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (National Science Foundation of China)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31700586</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Siberian apricot (<italic>Prunus sibirica</italic> L.) belongs to the Rosaceae family. In China, the total area of Siberian apricot is approximately 1.7 million ha<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> and the annual harvest of seeds is nearly 192,500 tons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. In the previous study, we have found that Siberian apricot kernel (PSK) had a high oil content (over 50%) which mainly comprised C18:1 (oleic acid) and C18:2 (linoleic acid)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Moreover, according to the investigation of biodiesel fuel properties, such as cold filter plugging point, cetane number, oxidative stability and flash point, the PSK oil has been determined to be suitable for biodiesel production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Thus, Siberian apricot has become a more critical component of woody oilseed species.</p><p id="Par3">Generally, seed development is a highly controlled developmental program that can be divided into three main steps: morphogenesis, maturation and late maturation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Several studies have reported that the accumulation of storage compounds (including protein, starch and lipid) usually occurs during the maturation stage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Presently, plant seeds store lipid mainly in the form of triacylglycerol (TAG) that could be degraded to provide carbon and energy during germination and early seedling growth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Additionally, plant-derived oils are a major food for humans, and are an important source of margarines, salad oils, lubricants and biodiesel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. For these reasons, the accumulative metabolism of plant oil has been subjected to intensive studies, and hundreds of oil-related genes have been identified to be involved in a series of enzymatic reactions occurring in several subcellular organelles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Also, recent studies in Siberian apricot provide details on the very large number of regulatory enzymes, transcription factors (TFs) and microRNAs (miRNAs) responsible for oil biosynthesis and accumulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">The main source of carbon for oil biosynthesis in heterotrophic tissues is sucrose, which could be converted to acetyl-CoA by glycolysis, pentose phosphate pathway (PPP) and pyruvate dehydrogenase complex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The acetyl-CoA is the main precursor for malonyl-CoA destined to <italic>de novo</italic> fatty acid (FA) biosynthesis in plastid<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Also, <italic>de novo</italic> FA synthesis requires stoichiometric amounts of ATP, NADPH, and NADH for each sequential addition of an acetyl unit to the growing chain of FA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. The generated FAs (C16 or 18) can be further elongated, desaturated or otherwise modified in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), and then they can participate in TAG assembly for storage oil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. All these findings indicate that oil biosynthesis as a part of the seed maturation process is a highly controlled developmental program. Indeed, previous studies in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> delineated a complex network of TFs that control a series of gene expressions for oil biosynthesis, for example ABSCISIC ACID INSENSITIVE3 and 4 (ABI3 and 4)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, LEAFY COTYLEDON1 and 2 (LEC1 and 2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, FUSCA3 (FUS3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, and WRINKLED1 (WRI1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Importantly, a loss-of-function mutation, <italic>WRI1</italic>, in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> causes an approximately 80% reduction in oil content compared with the wild type<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. WRI1, an APETALA2 (AP2)-type transcription factor, can activate genes via binding to the conserved AW-box, [CnTnG](n)7[CG] (n represents any nucleotide)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. In various plant species, it has been proved that WRI1 expression is pivotal in directing the carbon flux from glycolysis into FA biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Despite an increasing body of physiological, biochemical, genetic and molecular data in model plants, the regulatory role of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>sibirica WRI1</italic> (PsWRI1) in oil accumulation of PSK remains unclear.</p><p id="Par5">Recently, advances in molecular and sequencing technology have made transcription patterns during oilseed development to become an effective choice for the identification of genes involved in oil biosynthesis and accumulation, such as Siberian apricot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, oil palm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and castor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Based on those transcriptomic data, the analysis of gene co-expression network has been feasible to identify functional module. Weighted gene co-expression network analysis (WGCNA), one of the most useful gene co-expression network based approaches, allows a global interpretation of gene expression data by constructing gene networks based on similarities in expression profiles among samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. These coexpressed genes are likely to be functionally related, and may participate in similar biological processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Therefore, the analysis of gene co-expression network has been conducted to reconstruct regulatory pathways, discover novel candidate genes, and identify key modulators<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">To infer the biological roles of WRI1 in oil plants, we took advantage of 22 publicly available transcriptome databases derived from Siberian apricot, oil palm, castor, rapeseed and burning bush to study the coexpression genes with WRI1. Also, Gene Ontology (GO) and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) were used to categorize the functions of WRI1-coexpressed genes. Furthermore, two different germplasms (AS-85 and AS-86) of Siberian apricot were used as experimental materials, and their oil contents and FA compositions were first detected at different developing stages. Subsequently, according to the WGCNA results, we conducted comparative expression analysis of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> and its coexpressed genes using quantitative reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR). Several <italic>PsWRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes were selected for promoter cloned and transient expression analysis. Also, co-transformation with <italic>PsWRI1</italic> was performed to verify whether the activity of the selected <italic>PsWRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes was specifically regulated by PsWRI1. This work can provide novel insights into the function of PsWRI1 in Siberian apricot for increasing oil production in seeds.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Co-expression network analysis of <italic>WRI1</italic> gene</title><p id="Par7">Based on previous transcriptome data from developing oilseeds of Siberian apricot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, oil palm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, castor, rapeseed and burning bush<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, we screened and obtained 4011 shared genes with the same TAIR numbers, all of which expressed among the above species (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Thus, these genes may be considered to be constitutively transcribed in the 5 oilseeds. Subsequently, we attempted to establish the coexpression network using the R package of WGCNA. The WGCNA software is a comprehensive collection of R functions for performing various aspects of weighted correlation network analysis, including functions for network construction, module detection, gene selection, calculations of topological properties, data simulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. By using a convenient one-step network construction of WGCNA, we extracted and ranked the 161 genes whose transcriptional levels most tightly correlated with <italic>WRI1</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S2</xref>), implying that these <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes may be under the same metabolic pathways.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Functional classification of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes</title><p id="Par8">A better understanding of the functions of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes will help us identify the biological function of WRI1. We performed KEGG and GO clustering, and found a high correlation among <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Such an enrichment indicates that <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes are at least partially biologically connected in developing oilseeds. By KEGG analysis, support for this view came from a finding of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes enriched in FA biosynthesis and pyruvate metabolism in developing oilseeds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Also consistent with this result, <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes were characterized to be credibly implicated in &#x0201c;GO.0008610 lipid biosynthetic process&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;GO.0044255 cellular lipid metabolic process&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;GO.0006629 lipid metabolic process&#x0201d; with low false discovery rate (FDR), indicating a reliable enrichment of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes in these biological processes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b,c</xref>). Intriguingly, KEGG analysis showed that some <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes function in biotin metabolism (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Together, our functional enrichment highlights multiple functions for WRI1 in carbon partitioning and FA biosynthesis, desaturation or other modifications.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Functional clustering analysis of <italic>WRI1</italic>-corelated genes. (<bold>a</bold>) KEGG analysis of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes. (<bold>b</bold>) GO analysis of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes. These data labels on the histograms represent the FDR values. (<bold>c</bold>) Visual enrichment analysis by Metascape. The detailed results have been shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e608"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Dynamic changes of oil content and FA compositions in developing PSK</title><p id="Par9">In general, high oil content in oil plants is considered to be the vital metric for commercial development. The previous study has indicated that the accumulative pattern of PSK oil showed a sigmoid pattern during development stage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Thus, the PSK samples of AS-85 and AS-86 at 4, 6, 8 and 10 weeks after anthesis (WAA) were selected as the experimental materials for comparative analysis. We characterized a gradual increase of PSK oil contents from 1.35 to 52.25&#x02009;g/100&#x02009;g and 1.81 to 42.79&#x02009;g/100&#x02009;g in AS-85 and AS-86, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Importantly, the oil increase of AS-85 (22.57&#x02009;g) showed a higher accumulation than that of AS-86 (12.71&#x02009;g) during 4&#x02013;6 WAA, which ultimately led to the significant difference in total oil content between AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). By using GC-MS analysis, eight species of FAs were detected both in AS-85 and AS-86 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), as previously reported in PSK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Among those FAs, C18:1 (oleic acid) and C18:2 (linoleic acid) represented the major compositions in PSK oil, and showed a remarkable elevation at 4&#x02013;8 WAA (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Importantly, a major difference between the two germplasms was that C18:1 content was higher in AS-85 than in AS-86 at the last stage (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Together, the significant differences in the oil and C18:1 content between AS-85 and AS-86 indicate that the two germplasms would be desirable materials to explore the molecular and metabolic mechanisms of oil accumulation in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>sibirica</italic>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The PSK oil content by Soxhlet method at different development period. Data are means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE of three separate measurements.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e655"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Changes in the FA composition by GC-MS during PSK development.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="4">AS-85 (g/100&#x02009;g)</th><th colspan="4">AS-86 (g/100&#x02009;g)</th></tr><tr><th>4 WAA</th><th>6 WAA</th><th>8 WAA</th><th>10 WAA</th><th>4 WAA</th><th>6 WAA</th><th>8 WAA</th><th>10 WAA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>C16:0</td><td>0.270&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.029</td><td>1.200&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.022</td><td>1.833&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.050</td><td>2.017&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.055</td><td>0.354&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006</td><td>0.784&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.010</td><td>2.076&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.031</td><td>1.897&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.021</td></tr><tr><td>C16:1</td><td>0.013&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td><td>0.218&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.015</td><td>0.281&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002</td><td>0.337&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.093&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.012</td><td>0.344&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.014</td><td>0.314&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.007</td></tr><tr><td>C18:0</td><td>0.033&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.010</td><td>0.231&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006</td><td>0.486&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.034</td><td>0.523&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.031</td><td>0.076&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td><td>0.166&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.016</td><td>0.505&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008</td><td>0.453&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td>C18:1</td><td>0.198&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.013</td><td>12.773&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.616</td><td>31.351&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.647</td><td>35.912&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.519</td><td>0.229&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.012</td><td>7.152&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.879</td><td>23.810&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.218</td><td>26.987&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.298</td></tr><tr><td>C18:2</td><td>0.786&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.032</td><td>9.387&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.087</td><td>13.526&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.180</td><td>13.319&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.330</td><td>1.002&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.023</td><td>6.221&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.001</td><td>13.123&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.111</td><td>12.988&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008</td></tr><tr><td>C18:3</td><td>0.046&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004</td><td>0.066&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.010</td><td>0.050&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.013</td><td>0.031&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004</td><td>0.122&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.019</td><td>0.061&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.023</td><td>0.068&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006</td><td>0.087&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003</td></tr><tr><td>C20:0</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.026&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002</td><td>0.059&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.013</td><td>0.044&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008</td><td>0.024&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.009</td><td>0.023&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008</td><td>0.032&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.002</td><td>0.033&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004</td></tr><tr><td>C20:1</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.021&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.006</td><td>0.049&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003</td><td>0.047&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>0.025&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.005</td><td>0.030&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td><td>0.033&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.007</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Early expression of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> gene contributing to oil accumulation in developing PSK</title><p id="Par10">To investigate whether the <italic>WRI1</italic> (AT3G54320) expression has any influence on PSK oil accumulation, the expression pattern of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> gene during PSK development was analyzed by using qRT-PCR in AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Expression data in AS-85 and AS-86 indicated that <italic>PsWRI1</italic> gene displayed a similarly bell-shaped pattern of expression (a maximal level at 6 WAA) during PSK development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Intriguingly, the most striking difference with regard to the temporal pattern of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> expression was a higher transcription at 4 WAA in AS-85 than in AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). However, the expression levels for <italic>PsWRI1</italic> gene at other periods showed no substantial difference between AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Our data imply, as noted above for a higher accumulative rate of oil in 4&#x02013;6 WAA of AS-85 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), that the expression level of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> was closely correlated to accumulative rate of oil in PSK development.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The qRT-PCR analysis of <italic>WRI1</italic> and its coexpression genes in developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86. The ghecyclophilin and ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme were used as internal controls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, and the expression data of AS-85 at 4 WAA served as control. The relative expression levels were calculated as log<sub>2</sub>((1&#x02009;+&#x02009;E1)<sup>&#x025b3;Ct1(Control-Sample)</sup>/(1&#x02009;+&#x02009;E2)<sup>&#x025b3;Ct2(Control-Sample)</sup>), E1: PCR efficiency of target-gene primer; E2: PCR efficiency of reference-gene primer; &#x025b3;Ct1: the difference of Ct value between control and sample in experimental group; the difference of Ct value between control and sample in reference group. The significance of differences were analyzed using Duncan method (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). Abbreviations: BC, biotin carboxylase; BS, biotin synthase; EAR1, enoyl-ACP reductase 1; FAD2, fatty acid desaturase 2; HAD, hydroxyacyl-ACP dehydrase; KAR, ketoacyl-ACP reductase; KAS, ketoacyl-ACP synthase; LPCAT, acyl-CoA: lysophosphatidylcholine acyltransferase; MCMT, malonyl-CoA: ACP malonyltransferase; PEPCK, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase; pPK, plastidial pyruvate kinase; SAD, stearoyl-ACP desaturase; TAL, transaldolase; WRI1, WRINKLED1.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1003"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><italic>PsWRI1</italic>-mediated output of carbon flux in glycolysis during PSK development</title><p id="Par11">The pyruvate required for oil biosynthesis is mostly from glycolysis, in which pyruvate kinase (PK) catalyzes the last conversion of phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP) to pyruvate in both cytosol (cPK) and plastid (pPK; AT5G52920)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Aside from glycolysis, PEP also can be generated by PEP carboxykinase (PEPCK; AT4G37870)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Our coexpression analysis characterized a coordinated expression of <italic>pPK</italic> and <italic>PEPCK</italic> with <italic>WRI</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). However, qRT-PCR showed that only <italic>pPK</italic> had a consistent trend of the relative expression with <italic>WRI</italic> (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) in developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86, whereas <italic>PEPCK</italic> displayed a gradual increase and decrease in AS-85 and AS-86, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">Transaldolase (TAL; AT1G12230) is important for the balance of metabolites in the PPP, and is responsible for the generation of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate (GAP) for plastidial glycolysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. In this study, the expression levels of plastidial TAL were comparable to that of PsWRI1 (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), and showed a correlation with oil synthesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Our results imply that PsWRI1 may play a major role in regulation of plastidial PPP for high rates of FA synthesis in PSK development.</p><p id="Par13">To our knowledge, plastidial pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (PDC), including E1-&#x003b1;, E1-&#x003b2;, E2, and E3 subunit, is thought to be implicated in the conversion of pyruvate to acetyl-CoA for <italic>de novo</italic> FA biosynthesis in plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Coexpression analysis characterized E1-&#x003b1; (AT1G01090) and E2 (AT1G34430) subunit with <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), and indeed a highly correlated temporal expression pattern (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) was identified by qRT-PCR in developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Also, we observed the higher expression levels for <italic>E1-&#x003b1;</italic> and <italic>E2</italic> in AS-85 than in AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). These results suggest, as noted for <italic>pPK</italic>, that PsWRI1 may be responsible for output rather than input in carbon flux to generate more carbon source for acetyl-CoA biosynthesis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><italic>PsWRI1</italic>-mediated input of carbon flux in FA biosynthesis during PSK development</title><p id="Par14">A multi-subunit acetyl-CoA carboxylase (ACC) complex, including biotin carboxylase (BC; AT5G35360), biotin carboxyl carrier protein (BCCP) and carboxyltransferase (CT), catalyzes the carboxylation of acetyl-CoA to malonyl-CoA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Subsequently, malonyl-CoA is transferred to malonyl-ACP by malonyl-CoA: ACP malonyltransferase (MCMT; AT2G30200) to provide two-carbon unit at each step of elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. There are four reactions of condensation, reduction, dehydration and reduction occurring in each synthesized cycle, which is catalyzed by a series of regulatory enzymes, including ketoacyl-ACP reductase (KAR; AT1G24360), hydroxyacyl-ACP dehydrase (HAD; AT5G10160), enoyl-ACP reductase (EAR; AT2G05990), ketoacyl-ACP Synthase (KAS; AT5G46290)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. An intriguing observation was that most of enzymes (BC, MCMT, HAD, KASI, EAR1 and KAR) were identified as <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes in the present work (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>), implying a wide involvement of WRI1 targets in FA biosynthesis. In developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86, the temporal expression of <italic>BC</italic> and <italic>MCMT</italic> closely matched the pattern of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), which may reflect a major contribution of PsWRI1 in developing PSK by controlling influx of acetyl-CoA to FA biosynthesis. However, the other FA synthases showed a coordinated down-expression in developing PSK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). As expected, most enzymes involved in FA biosynthesis showed a higher expression level in AS-85 than in AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Biotin biosynthesis</title><p id="Par15">It was intriguing that <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes were characterized to be credibly implicated in biotin biosynthesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Furthermore, biotin synthase (BS; AT2G43360) that catalyzes the conversion of dethiobiotin to biotin has been identified with a consistent trend of the relative expression with <italic>PsWRI1</italic> gene (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) in developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In addition, the expression levels of <italic>BS</italic> gene were higher in AS-85, especially at 4WAA, relative to AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). These results suggest that PsWRI1 appears to be intimately involved in the transcriptional regulation of <italic>BS</italic> gene.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>The C18:1 biosynthesis in developing PSK</title><p id="Par16">After 7 elongation cycles, some produced 16:0-ACP are released from the FA biosynthesis, whereas others are elongated to 18:0-ACP by KASII and efficiently desaturated to 18:1-ACP by a stearoyl-ACP desaturase (SAD; AT2G43710)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. One <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed gene was identified as a homologous gene of <italic>SAD</italic>, which exhibited a similarly bell-shaped expression pattern (a maximal level at 6 WAA; <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) in developing PSK of AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Compared with AS-86, AS-85 had a higher expression of <italic>SAD</italic> gene (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), which could explain the faster increasing trend of C18:1 (oleic acid) content in AS-85 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Thus, we consider that the close correlation between <italic>PsWRI1</italic> and <italic>SAD</italic> expression in developing PSK suggests the regulatory role of PsWRI1 in C18:1 accumulation, leading to an ongoing outflow of FA to monounsaturated FA.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Limiting factor with regard to the synthesis of polyunsaturated FAs in developing PSK</title><p id="Par17">The synthesized FAs should be exported from the plastid to ER for further esterification or modification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. For the synthesis of polyunsaturated FAs, the C18:1 must be esterified by acyl-CoA: lysophosphatidylcholine acyltransferase (LPCAT; AT1G12640) to phosphatidylcholine (PC) pool in ER, and then desaturated by FA desaturase 2 (FAD2; AT3G12120) in PC pool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Comparative analysis of expression profiles between AS-85 and AS-86 indicated that <italic>FAD2</italic> gene showed an expression relation with <italic>PsWRI1</italic> (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), and had a higher level in AS-85 than in AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Unexpectedly, there was no obvious difference in C18:2 accumulation between AS-85 and AS-86 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Considering the important role of LPCAT1 in transport of newly synthesized FAs to PC for further desaturation in developing PSK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, we detected the expression level of <italic>LPCAT1</italic> gene that was not the WRI1-coexpressed genes in this study. Interestingly, the expression levels for <italic>LPCAT1</italic> displayed a similar profile during PSK development between AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). These comparisons strongly suggest LPCAT-mediated FA flux rather than transcriptional regulation of FAD2 as a major factor associated with the accumulation of polyunsaturated FAs in PSK development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Transient expression of promoter-GUS in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic></title><p id="Par18">Among these detected genes, only <italic>PEPCK</italic> showed a different expression pattern between AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Also, the involvement of WR11 in <italic>BS</italic> transcriptional regulation remains unclear, and SAD has an important role in C18:1 accumulation. Thus, the three gene promoters were cloned from AS-85 and AS-86, and named as Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-85, Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-86, Pro<sub>BS</sub>-AS-85, Pro<sub>BS</sub>-AS-86, Pro<sub>SAD</sub>-AS-85 and Pro<sub>SAD</sub>-AS-86, respectively. Motif analysis indicated that Pro<sub>SAD</sub> and Pro<sub>BS</sub> had the same <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements between AS-85 and AS-86 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). However, in contrast to Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-86, Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-85 specifically contained the binding sites of calmodulin-binding transcription activator 3 (VCGCGB, &#x02212;241), ABA INSENSITIVE 3 (CATGCA, &#x02212;319 and &#x02212;317) and Dof-type zinc finger transcription factor (TAAAG, &#x02212;585 and &#x02212;590) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). To investigate whether the promoter has any influence on gene expression, transient expression carrying promoter-GUS chimeric vectors were performed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Expectedly, we observed that Pro<sub>SAD</sub>- and Pro<sub>BS</sub>-driving GUS expression showed no substantial difference between AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). However, the expression level for GUS was significant higher in Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-85/GUS than in Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-86/GUS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), indicating that the promoter differences could result in the PEPCK expression difference.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparative analysis of GUS transcription by the <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transient expression system in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>. Pro<sub>(name)</sub>/GUS means GUS transcription driven by the gene promoter. Also, Pro<sub>(name)</sub>/GUS was co-transformed with 35&#x02009;S/PsWRI1 and 35&#x02009;S/Em (control), respectively. The transcript level of GUS was determined by qRT-PCR using the actin and ubiquitin as an endogenous reference. The significance of differences were analyzed using Duncan method (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1359"/></fig></p><p id="Par19">WRI1 activates genes via binding to AW-box target sites containing the sequence [CnTnG](n)7[CG], where n represents any nucleotide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. To explore whether the activity of Pro<sub>SAD,</sub> Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub> and Pro<sub>BS</sub> was specifically regulated by PsWRI1, we constructed <italic>PsWRI1</italic> plant expression vector (35&#x02009;S/PsWRI1) as effector, and meanwhile various promoter-GUS chimeric vectors were used as reporters. Transient co-transformation of <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> indicated that Pro<sub>SAD</sub>-, Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>- and Pro<sub>BS</sub>-driving GUS expression was significantly increased compared with the control (35&#x02009;S/Em Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>/GUS) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), suggesting that Pro<sub>SAD,</sub> Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub> and Pro<sub>BS</sub> activity could be specifically up-regulated by PsWRI1. Indeed, characterization of <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements revealed that the Pro<sub>SAD,</sub> Pro<sub>BS</sub> and Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub> sequences had the core binding <italic>cis</italic>-element of WRI1 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par20">Despite many TFs such as ABI3, LEC1, LEC2 and FUS3 were identified to be responsible for oil synthesis and deposition, only <italic>WRI1</italic> gene was highly up-regulated in oil palm compared to date palm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, and its expression has been found to be closely connected to oil accumulation in various plants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. However, the biological role of WRI1 in PSK oil accumulation remains elusive. On the basis of this theory that TF and its direct target genes may have similar expression patterns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, we utilized 22 publicly available transcriptome databases to identify 161 <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes by the R package of WGCNA. Many studies in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> elucidated a number of WRI1-targeted genes encoding enzymes responsible for glycolysis, FA synthesis and TAG assembly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. By KEGG and GO analysis, we characterized most of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes to be implicated to pyruvate metabolism, lipid metabolism and FA modification, whereas no <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes were identified to be involved in TAG assembly. An intriguing observation is that the temporal patterns of gene expression for the enzymes of FA synthesis and for TAG assembly are very different during seed development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Thus, this difference may contribute to low transcriptional correlation of genes in TAG assembly with <italic>WRI1</italic> gene. From this WRI1 regulatory network (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), 14 genes encoding key enzymes implicated in carbon partitioning, FA biosynthesis and desaturation were further investigated in this present work. By the transient expression in <italic>N</italic>. <italic>benthamiana</italic>, Pro<sub>SAD</sub>-, Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>- and Pro<sub>BS</sub>-driving GUS expressions were enhanced when co-transformed with 35&#x02009;S/PsWRI1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), indicating that PsWRI1 could transcriptional regulate SAD, PEPCK and BS expression. Our results demonstrate that WGCNA analysis of <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes is feasible.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Proposed model of PsWRI1 regulation in PSK oil accumulation. Blue arrow lines represent the possible transcription regulation sites of PsWRI1. Abbreviations: BC, biotin carboxylase; BS, biotin synthase; EAR1, enoyl-ACP reductase 1; FAD2, fatty acid desaturase 2; G6P, Glucose-6-phosphate; Glu, glucose; HAD, hydroxyacyl-ACP dehydrase; KAR, ketoacyl-ACP reductase; KAS, ketoacyl-ACP synthase; LPCAT, acyl-CoA: lysophosphatidylcholine acyltransferase; MCMT, malonyl-CoA: ACP malonyltransferase; PEP, phosphoenolpyruvate; PEPCK, phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase; pPK, plastidial pyruvate kinase; PYR, pyruvate; SAD, stearoyl-ACP desaturase; TAL, transaldolase; OAA, oxaloacetate; pPK, plastidial pyruvate kinase; PYR, pyruvate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1519"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">Generally, transformation of foreign gene into plant is highly efficient manner of studying gene function. However, owing to lack of the technology for tissue regeneration in Siberian apricot, we used two different Siberian Apricot germplasms to explore the biological role of WRI1 in PSK oil accumulation. Based on the previous investigation on developing kernel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> and collection of Siberian Apricot germplasms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, the PSKs of AS-85 and AS-86 at 4, 6, 8 and 10 WAA were selected for comparative analysis of oil content, FA composition, and gene expression. A gene expression map of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> indicated many core genes involved in FA synthesis display a bell-shaped pattern of expression during seed development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Indeed, most genes such as <italic>WRI1</italic>, <italic>pPK</italic>, <italic>TAL</italic>, <italic>E1-&#x003b1;</italic>, <italic>E2</italic>, <italic>BC</italic>, <italic>MCMT</italic>, <italic>SAD</italic> and <italic>FAD2</italic> showed a bell-shaped pattern of expression (a maximal level at 6 WAA) during PSK development of AS-85 and AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par22">In previous reports, such as <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, maize<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, rapeseed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> and potato<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, it has been proved that overexpression of <italic>WRI1</italic> could lead to an significant increase in oil content. In this study, <italic>PsWRI1</italic> displayed high expression levels during 4&#x02013;8 WAA both in AS-85 and AS-86, and the <italic>PsWRI1</italic> expression of AS-85 had a higher level than that of AS-86 at 4 WAA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In addition, we observed a major period of oil accumulation of during 4&#x02013;8 WAA, and a higher accumulative rate of oil at 4&#x02013;6 WAA in AS-85, relative to AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Summarily, these results indicated the expression level of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> may be closely related to accumulative rate of PSK oil, suggesting the pivotal role of PsWRI1 central to the oil production.</p><p id="Par23">The PPP is thought to not only provide plants with important substrates for metabolism, but also generate large amounts of reducing power to drive various anabolic processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. In the PPP, TAL is important for the balance of metabolites and is involved in the glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate (GAP) production for glycolysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The carbon source (GAP) and reducing power (NADPH) generated by PPP both could be used for FA biosynthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the expression profile of <italic>TAL</italic> gene displayed a similarly bell-shaped pattern with that of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> gene (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), as has been reported for developing PSK by transcriptome analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Thus, PsWRI1 may be involved in the regulation of PPP to generate reducing power for FA biosynthesis in PSK development. A major flux through glycolysis is expected to provide the large amounts of pyruvate required for high oil synthesis in oilseeds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. As the rate-limiting enzyme, PK catalyzes the last conversion of PEP to pyruvate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Our qRT-PCR imply that pPK may be directly regulated by PsWRI1 in PSK, as was reported in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. In addition, our data implicate transcriptional regulation of pPK rather than of cPK as a major factor associated with the production of pyruvate via glycolysis for FA biosynthesis in PSK development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), which is consistent with our previous conclusion that pPK plays a major role in providing pyruvate for FA synthesis in PSK development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par24">Besides of glycolysis, PEPCK in the presence of oxaloacetate can provide PEP for pyruvate generation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. The qRT-PCR analysis indicated that <italic>PEPCK</italic> showed an up- and down-regulation in AS-85 and AS-86, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In addition, the previous transcriptome analysis in PSK development revealed that <italic>PEPCK</italic> gene displayed an U-shape expression pattern, a minimum value at early-middle development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. One possible reason for the various expression patterns of the <italic>PEPCK</italic> gene is the difference in the promoter sequence. Motif analysis of Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub> indicated Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-85 specifically contained the <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements of calmodulin-binding transcription activator 3 (VCGCGB, &#x02212;241), ABA INSENSITIVE 3 (CATGCA, &#x02212;319 and &#x02212;317) and Dof-type zinc finger transcription factor (TAAAG, &#x02212;585 and &#x02212;590) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). This result, combined with a differential expression of GUS between Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-85/GUS and Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub>-AS-86/GUS (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), implied that other TFs (ABI3) and signal factors (Ca<sup>+</sup>) may regulate the <italic>PEPCK</italic> transcription, leading to different expression pattern in different Siberian Apricot germplasms. As noted for the previous report, PEPCK is mainly involved in amino acid catabolism and dissimilation of organic acids in developing seeds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Thus, we believe that PEPCK may not participate in providing carbon for FA biosynthesis in PSK development.</p><p id="Par25">The acetyl-CoA required for <italic>de novo</italic> FA synthesis is provided by the activity of plastid PDC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The expression pattern of <italic>E1-&#x003b1;</italic> and <italic>E2</italic> showed a high correlation with that of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), a bell-shaped pattern that was consistent with our previous transcriptome studies in developing PSK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. It is interesting to note that pPK and PDC are at the bottom of carbon flux in glycolysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), implying that the PsWRI1 in developing PSK may regulate the output of carbon flux, which is important for achieving high oil yield<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par26">Carboxylation of acetyl-CoA to malonyl-CoA is the first committed step in FA synthesis and is catalyzed by a multisubunit ACC complex, including BC, BCCP and CT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The biotin (vitamin H) has been recognized as a carrier of carbon dioxide, and is the essential cofactor of biotin-dependent carboxylases, such as pyruvate carboxylase, acetyl-CoA carboxylase and ACC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. It is well-known that a series of plastidial proteins (MCMT, HAD, KAS, EAR1 and KAR) are responsible for conversion of malonyl-CoA to FAs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. In agreement with the previous assumption that many genes from FA synthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> are the targets of WRI1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, most of genes involved in FA synthesis were identified as WRI1-coexpressed genes in this study (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Notably, the expression profiles of <italic>BC</italic>, <italic>BS</italic> and <italic>MCMT</italic> closely matched the bell-shaped pattern of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> expression, but <italic>HAD</italic>, <italic>KASI</italic>, <italic>EAR1</italic> and <italic>KAR</italic> showed a gradual down-expression in developing PSK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), similar to our previous transcriptome data in developing PSK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Therefore, there may be an intricate regulatory network at transcriptional and post-transcriptional level controlling FA biosynthesis in developing PSK. The components of this network are largely unknown and, therefore, further investigation will be needed to understand metabolic networks involved in oil biosynthesis and their regulations. The most interesting finding was noted for the involvement of WR11 in <italic>BS</italic> transcriptional regulation, which has not been reported in previous studies. Our results suggested that <italic>PsWRI1</italic> expression could up-regulate BS transcription, which could promote carbon flow from glycolysis into FA biosynthesis.</p><p id="Par27">After <italic>de novo</italic> FA synthesis, the saturated FAs could be further desaturated to monounsaturated and polyunsaturated FAs by SAD and FAD2, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Previous transcriptome study in developing PSK has found the shared expression profiles of <italic>SAD</italic>, <italic>FAD2</italic> and <italic>WRI1</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Indeed, our qRT-PCR confirmed that <italic>SAD</italic> and <italic>FAD2</italic> showed an expression correlation with <italic>PsWRI1</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Transient co-transformation indicated that Pro<sub>SAD</sub> activity could be up-regulated by PsWRI1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Thus, these results lead us to speculate that WRI1 may participate in production of unsaturated FAs by controlling the expression of <italic>SAD</italic> and <italic>FAD2</italic> gene. Also consistent with this inference, expression analysis revealed that <italic>SAD</italic> gene showed a significantly higher expression in AS-85 compared with AS-86 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Combined with our observation on a higher content of C18:1 in AS-85 than that in AS-86 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), we concluded that PsWRI1 has a primary role in promoting C18:1 accumulation in PSK, as was shown in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> that seeds of the <italic>WRI1</italic> mutants showed a 10% reduction in C18:1 content<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. In sharp contrast to the content of C18:1, the content of C18:2 showed no substantial difference between AS-85 and AS-86 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, <italic>FAD2</italic> as the <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed gene showed a significant up-regulation at AS-85, implying that WRI1-mediated transcriptional regulation of FAD2 may not be the limiting factor for C18:2 accumulation in PSK. Given that the LPCAT is responsible for PC-deacylation half of the acyl editing cycle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> and important role of LPCAT1 in PSK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, the expression level of <italic>LPCAT1</italic> gene was analyzed. The similar expression levels of <italic>LPCAT1</italic> gene between AS-85 and AS-86 strongly implicate LPCAT-mediated FA flux with the accumulation of polyunsaturated FAs in developing PSK.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par28">We systematically and comprehensively analyzed the <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes in five oil plants, and identified most coexpressed genes to be involved in carbon partitioning and FA biosynthesis, desaturation or other modifications. From this WRI1 regulatory network, many rate-limiting genes involved in glycolysis, PPP, and FA synthesis and desaturation, such as <italic>pPK</italic>, <italic>TAL</italic>, <italic>E1-&#x003b1;</italic>, <italic>E2</italic>, <italic>BC</italic>, <italic>BS</italic>, <italic>MCMT</italic>, <italic>SAD</italic> and <italic>FAD2</italic>, showed a high expression correlation with <italic>PsWRI1</italic> in developing PSK of AS-85 and As-86. Moreover, the expression level of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> and the accumulative rate of PSK oil were closely related in developing PSK of AS-85 and As-86. This would imply that PsWRI1 could control carbon flow into FA biosynthesis, especially into C18:1 accumulation, by transcriptional regulation of some core genes. Although no definitive answer can be provided at this time, Pro<sub>SAD,</sub> Pro<sub>PEPCK</sub> and Pro<sub>BS</sub> activity was identified to be up-regulated by PsWRI1 using transient co-transformation in <italic>N</italic>. <italic>benthamiana</italic>, indicating the reliability of WGCNA in this study. This study will provide a fundamental basis for in-depth experimental studies of WRI1 function in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>sibirica</italic> for increasing oil production in seeds.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par29">Based on the previous collection of Siberian Apricot germplasms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, the kernels of two germplasms were identified with obvious differences in oil content, and were named AS-85 and AS-86, respectively. AS-85 and AS-86 located at the Beijing Forestry University experimental station, Beijing, China. Flowers with the same anthesis were marked, and then seeds were harvested at 4, 6, 8 and 10 WAA on the basis of our previous investigation on kernel characteristics, oil contents and FA compositions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. The oil content and FA composition should have obvious alteration during the four developmental stages. After removing the sarcocarp, the seeds were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>PSK oil extraction and trans-esterification</title><p id="Par30">The kernels were dried using an oven at 80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 8&#x02013;10&#x02009;h and crushed. Subsequently, the PSK oils were extracted by n-hexane double extraction at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C using a rotary evaporator (LABORTA 4000-efficient, Heidolph, Germany). The oil content was determined by the difference in weight of the dried kernel sample before and after the extraction. The determination was performed in triplicate.</p><p id="Par31">Siberian apricot kernel oils were methylated following a trans-esterification method as Wang (2012) described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The KOH (1 mass % with respect to oil) was dissolved in anhydrous methanol (5.5:1&#x02009;mol ratio of methanol/oil). The methanol-KOH solution was added to the pre-heated PSK oil and stirred at 60&#x02013;65&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h. After cooling and standing, the reaction mixture was separated into two layers. The upper layer, including the resulting methyl esters, was isolated, dried with Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and analyzed by gas chromatography to determine the FA composition.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Fatty acid methyl ester analysis</title><p id="Par32">The qualitative and quantitative analyses of obtained FA methyl esters were performed by GC-MS using the Agilent 6890 equipped with a flame ionization detector (GB/T17377-1998). The following chromatographic conditions were applied: inlet temperature 250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, detector temperature 280&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and injection volume 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;L. The carrier gas was high-purity hydrogen. Peak integration was performed by applying HP3398A software. The determination was run in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Coexpression analysis and functional annotation</title><p id="Par33">To precisely pinpoint <italic>WRI</italic>-coexpressed genes, the raw data were downloaded from NCBI Short Read Archive database, including SRR1564517, SRR1568273, SRR1568275, SRR1568789 and SRR1568805 for Siberian apricot, SRX059258, SRX059259, SRX059260, SRX059261 and SRX059262 for oil palm, SRX090767, SRX090768, SRX090769 and SRX090771 for rapeseed, SRX007402, SRX007403, SRX007404, SRX007405 and SRX007406 for castor, and SRX070806, SRX029139, SRX029140, SRX029141, SRX029142 and SRX029135 for burning bush. Based on assembly results of cDNA library and annotated results against TAIR database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, the homologous TAIR locus with the maximum scorer and minimum E-value (an cut-off of 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>) was assigned to the corresponding gene to sufficiently normalize these genes. Subsequently, the shared genes with the same TAIR number were selected from the above species for coexpression analysis. After removal of the low quality reads (including adapter sequences, reads containing ploy-N, and reads with more than 10% Q&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;20 bases), the clean reads from different transcriptome databases were mapped to the shared genes in different cDNA libraries, respectively. The expression levels of genes were estimated using Fragment Per Kilobase of exon model per Million mapped reads (FPKM) by RSEM software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par34">Using the R package of WGCNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, automatic construction of the gene network and identification of modules were conducted according to the manual (labs.genetics.ucla.edu/horvath/CoexpressionNetwork/Rpackages/WGCNA/#manualInstall). To optimize data and avoid zero value, the values of Log<sub>2</sub>(FPKM&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.001) were used for WGCNA (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Using the data of Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">S1</xref>, the power 9 was selected by pickSoftThreshold analysis to amplify the strong connections between genes and penalize the weaker connections. Then, we used a convenient one-step network construction and module detection, and chose a relatively large minimum module size of 30 and a medium sensitivity (DeepSplit&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) to cluster splitting. The WGCNA package also provides a convenient function for exporting the network to text format<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The WRI1-coexpressed genes were selected with threshold weight&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.1. The GO and KEGG analysis were performed by Blast2GO<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup> and KOBAS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup> software, respectively. The FDR was used for the multiple testing of KEGG and GO enrichment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Also, WRI1-coexpressed genes were analyzed by Metascape (metascape.org/gp/index.html#/main/step1) and statistically enriched using Cytoscape<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Transient expression and co-transformation in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic></title><p id="Par35">The gDNA from AS-85 and AS-86 was extracted using plant genome DNA extraction kit (Bioteke). Total RNA was separately extracted from the mixture using RNeasy Plant Mini Kits (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Three biological repetitions were performed for each RNA extraction. The first-strand cDNA was synthesized by using oligo d(T) primers and reverse transcription System (Promega). The promoters (&#x02212;1 kb upstream of the predicted translation start site) of the <italic>WRI1</italic>-coexpressed genes were cloned. The reverse primers were designed in the 5&#x000b4; sequence based on our previous cDNA library<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>, while the forward primers were designed in conserved region based on the genome information of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>persica</italic>, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>avium</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>mume</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/gdv/">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/gdv/</ext-link>), belonging to the same family Rosaceae with our experimental material. The primer sequences were shown in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>. The promoter sequences were sequenced by Sangon (Guangzhou, China). Applications in the web-based promoter analysis program Motif Matcher (users.soe.ucsc.edu/~kent/improbizer/motifMatcher.html) and PLACE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dna.affrc.go.jp/PLACE/signalup.html">www.dna.affrc.go.jp/PLACE/signalup.html</ext-link>) were used to analyze the <italic>cis</italic>-acting elements. According the ClonExpress&#x000ae; II One Step Cloning Kit (Vazyme), the promoters were inserted into the EcoRI and NcoI sites of vector pCAMBIA1301. The full-length cDNA sequence (<italic>PsWRI1</italic>) was amplified from PSK cDNA by PCR using two gene-specific primers: 5&#x02032;-TCCTCTTCTTCTTCTTGGGTCTCTG-3&#x02032; (forward prime) and 5&#x02032;-CACCCACATCAAATCACAACAAAC-3&#x02032; (reverse primer), and then cloned into pGM-T Vector (TIANGEN). A HindIII-EcoRI fragment from pGM-PsWRI1 containing the <italic>PsWRI1</italic> sequence was linked to the HindIII and EcoRI sites of pGreen0029 vector. For a negative control, empty effector plasmid 35&#x02009;S/Em was constructed by the replacement of <italic>PsWRI1</italic> gene in pGreen0029. These constructs were introduced into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> strain EHA105 via the freezing-thaw. <italic>N</italic>. <italic>benthamiana</italic> was transformed and co-transformed using a standard leaf-disc co-cultivation procedure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Preparation of RNA and qRT-PCR</title><p id="Par36">The amplification primers were designed using PrimerQuest (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idtdna.com/PrimerQuest/Home/Index">www.idtdna.com/PrimerQuest/Home/Index</ext-link>) software with melting temperatures at 62&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and the absence of secondary structures was verified by the UNAFold program (eu.idtdna.com/UNAFold). The qRT-PCR was performed using the SYBR Premix Ex Taq Kit (TaKaRa) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Negative controls consisting of nuclease-free water instead of template, and reverse transcriptase controls prepared by substituting reverse transcriptase for nuclease-free water in the cDNA synthesis step were included in all analyses for each primer pair. Three technical repetitions were performed for qRT-PCR. According to our previous studies, cyclophilin and ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme were used as reference genes in PSK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, actin and ubiquitin were used as reference genes in <italic>N</italic>. <italic>benthamiana</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. The qRT-PCR primer sequences were shown in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>. The relative expression levels were calculated as log<sub>2</sub>((1&#x02009;+&#x02009;E1)<sup>&#x00394;Ct1(Control-Sample)</sup>/(1&#x02009;+&#x02009;E2)<sup>&#x00394;Ct2(Control-Sample)</sup>), E1: PCR efficiency of target-gene primer; E2: PCR efficiency of reference-gene primer; &#x00394;Ct1: the difference of Ct value between control and sample in experimental group; the difference of Ct value between control and sample in reference group. The PCR efficiency (E) was estimated from the data obtained from the exponential phase of each individual amplification plot and the equation (E&#x02009;=&#x02009;10<sup>slope</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. The statistical analysis of expressed data was performed using SPSS software.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec22"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table S1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table S2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_39236_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Table S3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Shuya Deng and Yiting Mai contributed equally.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-019-39236-9.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This study was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31700586) and Hainan University research funded projects (KYQD(ZR)1701).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>J.N. conceived and designed the experiments. S.D. and Y.M. wrote the manuscript and performed the bioinformatics analysis. L.S. conducted the qRT-PCR analysis.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kernel characteristics, oil contents, fatty acid compositions and biodiesel properties in developing Siberian apricot (<italic>Prunus sibirica</italic> L.) seeds</article-title><source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><year>2016</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.05.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis revealed the mechanism of oil dynamic accumulation during developing Siberian apricot (<italic>Prunus sibirica</italic> L.) seed kernels for the development of woody biodiesel</article-title><source>Biotechnol Biofuels</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>29</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13068-015-0213-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25834637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25834637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated mRNA and miRNA transcriptome reveal a cross-talk between developing response and hormone signaling for the seed kernels of <italic>Siberian apricot</italic></article-title><source>Sci. Rep-UK</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>35675</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep35675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of Siberian Apricot (<italic>Prunus sibirica</italic> L.) germplasm variability for biodiesel properties</article-title><source>J. Am. Oil Chem. Soc.</source><year>2012</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1743</fpage><lpage>1747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11746-012-2069-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutin</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Miquel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrated overview of seed development in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> ecotype WS</article-title><source>Plant Physiol. Bioch.</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0981-9428(01)01350-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadegari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant embryogenesis: zygote to seed</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>266</volume><fpage>605</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.266.5185.605</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17793455?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17793455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of de novo fatty acid synthesis in maturing oilseeds of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>448</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2008.12.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chia</surname><given-names>TYP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawsthorne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Storage oil breakdown during embryo development of <italic>Brassica napus</italic> (L.)</article-title><source>J. Exp. Bot.</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1285</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eri129</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15767324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15767324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Napier</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New frontiers in oilseed biotechnology: meeting the global demand for vegetable oils for food, feed, biofuel, and industrial applications</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Biotech.</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2010.11.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21144729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21144729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Libeisson</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid and lipid transport in plant cells</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>145</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2015.10.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26616197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26616197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stymne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical pathways in seed oil synthesis</article-title><source>Curr Opin in Plant Bio.</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>358</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2013.02.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23529069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourgis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative transcriptome and metabolite analysis of oil palm and date palm mesocarp that differ dramatically in carbon partitioning</article-title><source>P. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>12527</fpage><lpage>12532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1106502108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Troncoso-Ponce</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative deep transcriptional profiling of four developing oilseeds</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1014</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04751.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21851431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21851431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bednarek</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and developmental regulation of seed oil production</article-title><source>Prog. Lipid Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plipres.2010.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20102727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated transcriptome sequencing and dynamic analysis reveal carbon source partitioning between terpenoid and oil accumulation in developing <italic>Lindera glauca</italic>fruits</article-title><source>Sci. Rep-UK</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>15017</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep15017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horstman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The BABY BOOM Transcription Factor Activates the LEC1-ABI3-FUS3-LEC2 Network to Induce Somatic Embryogenesis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>848</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.17.00232</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28830937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28830937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary analysis of the <italic>LAFL</italic> genes involved in the land plant seed maturation program</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>439</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00439</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28421087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28421087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luerssen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mis&#x000e9;ra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>FUSCA3</italic> encodes a protein with a conserved <italic>VP1/AB13</italic>-like <italic>B3</italic> domain which is of functional importance for the regulation of seed maturation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>1998</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1998.00259.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9807814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9807814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofvander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potato tuber expression of <italic>Arabidopsis WRINKLED1</italic> increase triacylglycerol and membrane lipids while affecting central carbohydrate metabolism. <italic>Plant</italic></article-title><source>Biotechnology J.</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1883</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Focks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>wrinkled1</italic>: a novel, low-seed-oil mutant of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> with a deficiency in the seed-specific regulation of carbohydrate metabolism</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.118.1.91</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9733529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9733529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An AP2&#x02010;type transcription factor, <italic>WRINKLED1</italic>, of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> binds to the AW&#x02010;box sequence conserved among proximal upstream regions of genes involved in fatty acid synthesis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03967.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19594710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19594710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langfelder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WGCNA: an R package for weighted correlation network analysis</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>559</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-559</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19114008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19114008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene network based on the graphical Gaussian model</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2007</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1614</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.6911207</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17921353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17921353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression-based network biology identifies immune-related functional modules involved in plant defense</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-421</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24888606?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24888606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oldham</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Geschwind</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation and evolution of gene coexpression networks in human and chimpanzee brains</article-title><source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>17973</fpage><lpage>17978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0605938103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amrine</surname><given-names>KCH</given-names></name><name><surname>Blancoulate</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery of Core Biotic Stress Responsive Genes in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> by Weighted Gene Co-Expression Network Analysis</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0118731</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118731</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25730421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25730421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression and manipulation of phosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase 1 identifies a role for malate metabolism in stomatal closure</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>679</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04822.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22007864?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22007864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caillau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into plant transaldolase</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02427.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwender</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shacharhill</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A flux model of glycolysis and the oxidative pentosephosphate pathway in developing <italic>Brassica napus</italic> embryos</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>29442</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M303432200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12759349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikolau</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurtele</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant biotin-containing carboxylases</article-title><source>Arch. Biochem Bioph</source><year>2003</year><volume>414</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-9861(03)00156-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohlrogge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid biosynthesis</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>970</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3870050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7640528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7640528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>a. &#x00026; Somerville, C. Glycerolipid Synthesis: Biochemistry and Regulation</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Plant Physiol. Mol. Biol.</source><year>1991</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pp.42.060191.002343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome wide analysis of fatty acid desaturation and its response to temperature</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1594</fpage><lpage>1605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.16.01907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cernac</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>WRINKLED1</italic> encodes an <italic>AP2/EREB</italic> domain protein involved in the control of storage compound biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2004</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02235.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15500472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide association study dissects the genetic architecture of oil biosynthesis in maize kernels</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2484</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23242369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A gene expression map of Arabidopsis thaliana development</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15806101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leegood</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation and roles of phospho enol pyruvate carboxykinase in plants</article-title><source>Arch Bioch Biophys</source><year>2003</year><volume>414</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-9861(03)00093-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerbling</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Axiotis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Douce</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotin biosynthesis in higher plant cells</article-title><source>Identification of intermediates. Eur. J. Biochem.</source><year>1993</year><volume>217</volume><fpage>479</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1993.tb18267.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8223585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8223585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An AP2-type transcription factor, <italic>WRINKLED1</italic>, of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> binds to the AW-box sequence conserved among proximal upstream regions of genes involved in fatty acid synthesis</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2010</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03967.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hai-Yan</surname><given-names>YU</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao-Hui</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of fatty acid composition of woody biodiesel plants on the fuel properties</article-title><source>J. Fuel Chemist. Technol</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1872-5813(12)60018-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>323</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-323</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21816040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21816040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-throughput functional annotation and data mining with the Blast2GO suite</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>3420</fpage><lpage>3435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18445632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the False Discovery Rate: A Practical and Powerful Approach to Multiple Testing</article-title><source>J. R. Statist. Soc.</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Meta- and Orthogonal Integration of Influenza &#x0201c;OMICs&#x0201d; Data Defines a Role for UBR4 in Virus Budding</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2015</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2015.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26651948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schocher</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shillito</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saul</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Paszkowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Potrykus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-transformation of unlinked foreign genes into plants by firect gene transfer</article-title><source>Bio Technology</source><year>1986</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mccormac</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient co-transformation of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> by two independent T-DNAs, the effect of T-DNA size and implications for genetic separation</article-title><source>Transgenic Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008909203852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11305361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></name><name><surname>Matton</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Crescenzo</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolicoeur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transient expression of antibodies in suspension plant cell suspension cultures is enhanced when co-transformed with the tomato bushy stunt virus p19 viral suppressor of gene silencing</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Progr.</source><year>2011</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1534</fpage><lpage>1543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/btpr.485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selection of reference genes for gene expression studies in Siberian Apricot (<italic>Prunus sibirica</italic> L.) Germplasm using quantitative real-time PCR</article-title><source>Plos One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e103900</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103900</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25105495?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25105495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramakers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruijter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Deprez</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assumption-free analysis of quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) data</article-title><source>Neuroscience Lett.</source><year>2003</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(02)01423-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>