<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par96">Usually, the target compound was enriched by first dimensional separation and purified by last dimensional separation. Multi-dimensional separation can be achieved using the same type separation equipment (LC or GC) or different types of equipment (GC and LC). A novel volatile compound, (2
 <italic>E</italic>,6
 <italic>E</italic>)-2-methyl-6-(4-methylcyclohex-3-enylidene)hept-2-enal (
 <bold>154</bold>), was purified by a three-dimensional prep-GC from wampee essential oil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. Five antioxidant compounds, including two alkaloids [glusodichotomine AK (
 <bold>155</bold>) and glusodichotomine B (
 <bold>156</bold>)] and three flavonoids [tricin (
 <bold>157</bold>), homoeriodictyol (
 <bold>158</bold>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig21" ref-type="fig">21</xref>), and luteolin (
 <bold>3</bold>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)], were separated using a two-dimensional HPLC (RP/HILIC) method from 
 <italic>Arenaria kansuensis</italic> on a RP-C18HCE and a NP-XAmide preparative columns [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. Sciarrone et al. exploited the separation of sesquiterpenes in patchouli essential oil by three dimensional Prep-GC. Patchouli alcohol (
 <bold>111</bold>, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>) (496 μg) was separated in the first dimension on a poly(5% diphenyl/95% dimethylsiloxane) column, and 295 μg of 
 <italic>α</italic>-bulnesene (
 <bold>159</bold>) was from a second column coated with high molecular weight polyethylene glycol as well as 160 μg 
 <italic>α</italic>-guaiene (
 <bold>160</bold>) from the third dimension on an ionic-liquid based column (SLB-IL60) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]. Pantò et al. applied two three-dimensional approaches (GC–GC–GC and LC–GC–GC) to separate the sesquiterpene alcohols [(
 <italic>Z</italic>)-
 <italic>α</italic>-santalol (
 <bold>161</bold>), (
 <italic>Z</italic>)-
 <italic>α</italic>-
 <italic>trans</italic> bergamotol (
 <bold>162</bold>), (
 <italic>Z</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-santalol (
 <bold>163</bold>), 
 <italic>epi</italic>-(
 <italic>Z</italic>)-
 <italic>β</italic>-santalol (
 <bold>164</bold>), 
 <italic>α</italic>-bisabolol (
 <bold>165</bold>), (
 <italic>Z</italic>)-lanceol (
 <bold>166</bold>), and (
 <italic>Z</italic>)-nuciferol (
 <bold>167</bold>)] from the sandalwood essential oil. They found that the first dimensional separation using LC reduced the sample complexity and increased the productivity of low-concentration components [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. 
</p>
