<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the first attempts to explore the bacterial activity of 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> was undertaken by Yildirim et al. [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. These authors used water extracts of Rize tea and young shoot tea against 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and, contrary to most of the studies, no antimicrobial activity was detected in the referred extracts. It should be noted that such absence could be related with the extraction procedure. Many studies in several contexts mention that the extraction procedures highly affect the extracted compounds and consequently the biological activity of the extracts. Several years later, Tsai et al. [
 <xref rid="B59-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] reported the capacity of crude methanolic extracts of green tea to inhibit the growth of several oral pathogens (
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus sanguinis</italic> and 
 <italic>Streptococcus sobrinus</italic>). In 2009, Erol et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] studied the antibacterial activities of various fresh tea leaves and green tea extracts (ethanol, methanol and water extracts) against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Hafnia alvei</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella enteritidis</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> Type 1 and 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic>. Water extracts did not show antibacterial activity for any of the bacteria while ethyl acetate fractions of extracts showed antibacterial activity on 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>B. cereus</italic>. It should be noted that the absence of antimicrobial activity reported for the water extract was in accordance with the findings of Yildirim et al.’s [
 <xref rid="B58-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] studies reinforcing the relevance of the extraction method. Beyond the extraction procedure, the pH value could also influence the activity of the extract. Indeed, Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] proved that the higher the pH value, the worse the antimicrobial activity of tea saponins against Gram-positive bacteria 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and Gram-negative bacteria. Of note, the best pH value was an acidic one, namely pH = 4.8. Dhaouadi et al. [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] reported also the antimicrobial activity of the polyphenols of commercialized green and black Tunisian tea decoctions (green/black tea) against Gram positive 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> and the Gram negative 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>Salmenolla wiam.</italic> The authors noticed that the inhibition zones were proportional to the phenolic content, suggesting the implication of these molecules in the observed activities. Kiran et al. [
 <xref rid="B60-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] also proved the relevance of the tea polyphenols. These authors studied the effect of black tea (
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic>) on virulence traits of clinical isolates of 
 <italic>Shigella dysenteriae</italic> and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>. The tea-treated cultures showed a decrease of the time necessary for bacterial killing. Indeed, crude tea polyphenols of black tea improved (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) phagocytic uptake of tea-adapted 
 <italic>S. dysenteriae</italic> cells in 30 min by 37.68% and phagocytic killing by ten-fold in 3 h. Chan et al. [
 <xref rid="B61-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] studied the antibacterial properties of different brands of green, black and herbal teas of 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> against the Gram positive bacteria 
 <italic>Micrococcus luteus, S. aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>B. cereus</italic>, and Gram negative bacteria 
 <italic>E. coli, Salmonella typhi</italic> and 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. The results showed no inhibitory activity of teas against any of the Gram negative bacteria. However, 
 <italic>M. luteus</italic> and 
 <italic>B. cereus</italic>, were inhibited by black tea and herbal teas and all of the Gram positive were inhibited by green tea, being the best results reported for 
 <italic>M. luteus</italic>. The teas were obtained with hot water which validated the inactivity of 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> reported by previous studies against Gram negative bacteria; however, this study reported activity against Gram positive ones. Similar results were obtained by Orak et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] regarding the activity of white, green and black tea extracts. Also, Arbia et al. [
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] reported antimicrobial activity of aqueous extracts against Gram negative bacteria (
 <italic>Porphyromonas gingivalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Prevotella intermedia</italic>). These somehow contradictory results obtained by several authors regarding the antimicrobial activity of aqueous extracts need further clarification. Abidi et al. [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] also studied the activity of aqueous extracts of 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> against 
 <italic>S. epidermidis</italic>; however, in combination with current antibiotics such as vancomycin, erythromycin, tetracycline, chloramphenicol, ampicillin, ofloxacin, cephalexin and gentamicin. The authors noticed an appreciable synergistic activity between the plant extracts and the tested antibiotics. Granato et al. 2016 [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02178" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] studied the characterization of binary and ternary mixtures of green, white and black tea extracts in vitro antibacterial activity against several microorganisms. The results revealed that black and white teas show the highest antimicrobial effects against 
 <italic>Salmonella Typhimurium</italic>; however, the combination of green/white and green/black teas also showed a significant inhibitory effect depending on the considered serotype.
</p>
