<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">In this study, 
 <italic>Satureja</italic>
 <italic>hortensis</italic> essential oil (SHEO), and a series of heated samples at different temperatures and periods (SHEOx-y) were investigated by GC–MS, HPLC–MS, ATR-FTIR, and TG/DTG/DTA to characterize the heating conditions influence on the chemical composition and thermal behavior. For the SHEO sample, the GC–MS analysis showed that the major constituents of chemical composition were γ-terpinene + α-terpinolene (~ 48%) and carvacrol + 
 <italic>p-</italic>cymene (~ 42%), compounds whose characteristic absorption bands predominate the ATR-FTIR spectrum of the sample. TG curves recorded on air or nitrogen atmosphere show a continuous mass-loss in 50–220 °C range. In contrast, the DTA profile curves suggest that the endothermic processes which take place are complex and involve at least two overlapped mass-loss steps better highlighted on the DTG curves. Based on the obtained results the first degradation step could be due to vaporization mainly of γ-terpinene + α-terpinolene and to a small fraction of carvacrol + 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, while the second step, recorded between 175–220 ºC, could be attributed to vaporization of the remained major fraction of carvacrol and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene. For the SHEOx-y samples, it can be noted that as the temperature and heating time increase, major changes in chemical composition are occurring. In the ATR-FTIR spectra a decrease up to the total absence of the terpinene isomers (γ-terpinene + α-terpinolene) characteristic bands were observed, while those for carvacrol and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene amplified. The TG/DTG/DTA curves showed a decrease in mass-loss values for the 50–175 ºC step and an increase in 175–220 ºC range. For the SHEO175-2.5 and SHEO 190–2.5 samples, only one mass-loss stage was achieved. As the vaporization of γ-terpinene + α-terpinolene from samples progresses, an increase in the activation energy (
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>a</italic>
 </sub>) values with the increase of the samples' thermal stability (T
 <sub>onset</sub>) was observed. Corroborating all the data obtained, the heating of 
 <italic>Satureja</italic>
 <italic>hortensis</italic> essential oil at 190 ºC for two and a half hours lead to the obtaining of carvacrol as the main component. This study demonstrated the importance of analyzing the chemical composition of essential oils after thermal exposure with essential effects on the uses of the essential oils as a natural preservative for the food industry and aromatherapy.
</p>
