<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to understand the biosynthetic potential of the isolates, the detection of genes encoding polyketide synthases and non-ribosomal peptide synthetases, responsible for the synthesis of most biologically active polyketide and peptide compounds, has been broadly used for assessing biosynthetic potential of culturable and non-culturable microorganisms. In this study, at least one antibiotic biosynthetic gene was detected in 27 (representing 50% of tested strains) antagonistic strains. The antimicrobial genes screening results indicated that the presence of 
 <italic>PKS</italic> and 
 <italic>NRPS</italic> encoding genes were widespread in the tested strains. The higher proportions of 
 <italic>PKS II</italic> (38.9 %) and 
 <italic>NRPS</italic> (27.8 %) as well as lower detection rates of 
 <italic>PKS I</italic> (7.4 %) these results were in agreement with the previous study (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2015</xref>). The absence of amplification of 
 <italic>PKS I</italic>, 
 <italic>PKS II</italic>, and 
 <italic>NRPS</italic> genes in some of the tested strains may be due to the absence of these genes, and the amplified primers were not suitable for screening the biosynthetic genes of some tested strains (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Ayuso-Sacido and Genilloud, 2005</xref>). Moreover, we obtained the 
 <italic>PKS</italic> and 
 <italic>NRPS</italic> existent strains with other 
 <italic>PKS I</italic>, 
 <italic>PKS II</italic>, and 
 <italic>NRPS</italic> genes primers (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2009</xref>). 
 <italic>PKS-II</italic> (25.9%) and 
 <italic>NRPS</italic> (24.1%) genes exhibited high positive rates in the members of 
 <italic>Streptomyces</italic>, and this result was in opposition to the study of 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al. (2015)</xref>; they argued that the NRPS genes displayed wide distribution in the members of both 
 <italic>Streptomyces</italic> and rare actinobacteria. Among tested endophytes, strains T3L1C, T3RB033, T3SB005, T3SB037, T4LB045, T4LB049, and T4RB005 displayed remarkable antibacterial activity in the bioactive assay, while 
 <italic>PKS</italic> and 
 <italic>NRPS</italic> genes were negative. According 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Finking and Marahiel (2004)</xref>, the NRPS genes could also influences quorum-sensing of bacteria, though not in the biosynthesis of bioactive secondary metabolites.
</p>
