<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">More complex tapered optical fibre configurations, employing multiple tapers, novel fibres and novel taper geometries, have also been investigated. For example, a double-pass in-line fibre taper MZI was formed in a single mode (Corning SMF28) optical fibre by creating two abrupt tapers using a fusion splicer (arc discharge). The tapers excited cladding modes of the length of fibre separating the two tapers, creating different optical path lengths for higher order modes traveling in the cladding and fundamental core mode travelling in the core (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02294-f012" class="xref">Figure 12</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B70-sensors-19-02294" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. This is similar to the cascaded LPGs described earlier, but in this configuration, there is no control over the modes excited and the channelled spectrum is visible across the entire spectrum. The sensor can be interrogated by monitoring the light transmitted by the gold coating, where the light has traversed the sensing region once, or light reflected by the gold coating, which traverses the sensor twice. The resulting channelled spectrum was analysed to facilitate the measurement of surrounding RI and temperature. The temperature sensitivity arose from the thermo-optic effect and the thermal expansion of the MZI during the temperature change. The double-pass configuration increased the sensitivity compared to the single pass case because of the doubled interaction length between the propagating light and the measurands. The RI sensitivities of the single (measured in transmission without gold film) and double-pass MZIs were found to be 1.63 ± 0.01 × 10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> and 3.05 ± 0.01 × 10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> dBm/RIU, respectively, while the temperature sensitivities of single- and double-pass MZI were found to be 201.9 ± 2.7 and 382.7 ± 5.3 dBm/°C, respectively [
 <xref rid="B70-sensors-19-02294" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>].
</p>
