<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Intercropping fodder plants with medicinal plants, in addition to enhancing productivity, can remarkably reduce the population of weeds, pests and diseases and for naturally meeting of livestock medicinal needs. Two experiments were conducted to evaluate biological yield, essential oil (EO) composition and yield of sweet basil (
  <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L.) treated with N
  <sub>2</sub> fixing bacteria in additive intercropping with forage maize during the 2018 and 2019. Treatments were arranged in factorial split-plot-in time in randomized complete block design with three replications. The factors were 100% chemical fertilizer (N), N
  <sub>2</sub> fixing bacteria (
  <italic>Azospirillum brasilense</italic> and 
  <italic>Azotobacter chroococcum</italic>), integration of N
  <sub>2</sub> fixing bacteria + 50% nitrogen chemical fertilizer and control. The cropping pattern factor included of sole cropping basil and the additive intercropping of maize + 25% basil, maize + 50% basil, maize + 75% basil, and maize + 100% basil. The results indicated that the highest essential oil yield (30.8 kg ha
  <sup>−1</sup>) and essential oil percentage (0.75%) were obtained in sole cropping with 
  <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
  <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> + 50% chemical nitrogen fertilizer application in second harvest in 2019. In both cropping systems, the N
  <sub>2</sub> fixing bacteria application significantly increased fresh and dry yield and land equivalent ratio (LER) as compared to control plants. In both years of experiments could remarkably vary depending on type of treatment. In both years, eight constituents including methyl chavicol (17.24–51.28%), Z-citral (neral) (8.33–24.3%), geranial (10.2–31.3%), (E)-caryophyllene (1.05–5.64%), α-
  <italic>trans</italic>-bergamotene (0.53–1.7%), α-humulene (0.4–1.69%), germacrene-D (0.2–1.88%), and (Z)-α- bisabolene (1.16–3.86%) were the main constituents of EO. The highest content of methyl chavicol was found through sole cropping of sweet basil with nitrogen chemical fertilizer followed by sole cropping of sweet basil with an integration of 
  <italic>A. brasilense</italic> and 
  <italic>A. chroococcum</italic> + 50% nitrogen chemical fertilizer in 2018 and 2019. Intercropping system and N
  <sub>2</sub> fixing bacteria can be effective in reducing chemical fertilizer consumption and environmental pollution and achieving the sustainable agriculture goals.
 </p>
</abstract>
