<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>LPS administration results in multiple pathogenic events including massive polymorphonuclear leukocytes (PMN) infiltration in pulmonary tissue, diffuse intravascular coagulation, and profound pulmonary injury [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Accumulation of infiltered inflammatory cell in pulmonary tissue exacerbates ALI through the release of multiple toxic mediators including ROS, proteases, and proinflammatory cytokines [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Furthermore, recruitment of inflammatory cells contributes to increase of the alveolar-capillary barrier permeability and lung edema. Results of this study were in line with previous research [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], as LPS induced marked pulmonary edema presented by increased lung W/D ratio. The total protein content in the BALF, as another index of epithelial permeability and pulmonary edema [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01620" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], was highly increased in the BALF of mice exposed to LPS. However, EC decreased the lung W/D ratio and the total protein in the BALF, indicating that EC could prohibit the leakage of serous fluid into the lung tissue and attenuate the development of pulmonary edema. Additionally, LDH, as a marker of tissue injury, was increased in BALF upon LPS administration compared with the control group, which was inhibited by EC pretreatment. Inflammatory cell infiltration in the lungs, mainly neutrophil, was noted through increased total and differential cell counts. These biochemical observations were supported by the histopathological examination of the lung, which revealed excessive inflammatory changes such as pulmonary edema, alveolar distortion, and inflammatory cell infiltration lung of LPS-challenged mice. On the other hand, EC attenuated pulmonary edema and inhibited the infiltration of inflammatory cells, as well as restraining the alveolar structural damage. The remarkable attenuation of the biochemical parameters of ALI was parallel to the observed improvement of the histology of the lung in EC-pretreated animals. These findings demonstrated the protective effect of EC on ALI induced by LPS and the ability of EC to prohibit inflammatory cell sequestration and migration into the lung tissue.
</p>
