<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a study carried out by Carramiñana et al., the effect of savory (
 <italic>Satureja montana)</italic> EO [0.25, 0.5, 1, and 2.5 μl/g (v/w)] against inoculated 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> serovar 4b (10
 <sup>4</sup> CFU/g) in minced pork meat stored at 4°C for up to 7 days was investigated. Furthermore, they utilized thyme (
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> F) and rosemary (
 <italic>R. officinalis</italic>) as reference ingredients. They found that just 
 <italic>S. montana</italic> and 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> F EOs efficiently inhibited the growth of 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in pork, while 
 <italic>R. officinalis</italic> had no remarkable antimicrobial effect. They indicated that the low antimicrobial effect of 
 <italic>R. officinalis</italic> EO could be attributed to the absence of carvacrol and thymol in this EO (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>). Similarly, Bukvički et al. (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>) studied the effect of 
 <italic>Satureja horvatii</italic> EO (0.16–20 mg/ml) on 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> (10
 <sup>7</sup> CFU/ml) in pork meat medium stored at 4 and 25°C for 3 days. They also indicated that two concentrations of 10 and 20 mg/ml 
 <italic>S. horvatii</italic> EO led to a 100 inhibition of 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> regardless of the incubation temperature, while no inhibition was observed at the lowest concentrations of 
 <italic>S. horvatii</italic> EO (0.16 and 0.32 mg/ml). GC-MS analysis of 
 <italic>S. horvatii</italic> EO showed that the main components of this EO included 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene (33.14%), thymol (26.11%), thymol methyl ether (15.08%), γ-terpinene (4.05%), α-pinene (4.26%), and α-terpinene (4.02%) (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>). It has been reported that the high antimicrobial potential of 
 <italic>Satureja</italic> oil is related to the considerable amount of oxygenated monoterpenes thymol and thymol methyl ether compounds (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>). Selected publications on the major compounds of various EOs and their anti-
 <italic>Listeria</italic> activity in meat and poultry products are summarized in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.
</p>
