<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Firouzi et al. studied the effect of oregano and nutmeg EOs (1, 2, and 3 μl/g) on 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in ready-to-cook Iranian barbecued chicken that was inoculated with 6–7 log CFU/g of this pathogen and stored at 3, 8, and 20°C for 72 h. They reported that nutmeg with a MIC value of 0.20 μl/ml was more effective against 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> than oregano EO with a MIC value of 0.26 μl/ml. Furthermore, MBC values of 0.50 and 0.54 μl/ml were obtained against 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> by nutmeg and oregano EOs, respectively. They also found that there were no significant differences among all EO-treated and control Iranian barbecued chickens in 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> growth during 72 h of storage at any of the three temperatures (3, 8, and 20°C) (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Furthermore, the effect of 
 <italic>N,O</italic>-carboxymethyl chitosan, oregano EO, and their combination on 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in raw chicken meat filets that were inoculated with low (10
 <sup>3</sup> CFU/g) and high (10
 <sup>5</sup> CFU/g) counts of bacteria and stored at 4°C for 14 days was studied by Khanjari et al. Their results showed that 
 <italic>N,O</italic>-carboxymethyl chitosan exerted a significantly stronger antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> when compared to oregano EO. They found that 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> was completely inhibited by the combination of 
 <italic>N,O</italic>-carboxymethyl chitosan and oregano EO in the samples with low and high inoculation levels at days of 2 and 4 of storage, respectively (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). Similarly, Pavli et al. found that incorporation of oregano EO into sodium alginate edible films in ham slices led to a 1.5-log CFU/g decrease in population of 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> at the end of the storage (40 days) at 8 and 12°C and an approximately 2.5-log CFU/g reduction at 4°C. They finally indicated that a significant reduction or absence of 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> was achieved in ham slices by application of high hydrostatic pressure and edible film containing oregano EO, together (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). Additionally, the combination effect of packaging atmosphere, oregano EO, and cold temperature on inhibition of 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> Scott A in RTE smoked turkey meat was studied by Mahgoub et al. They found that inhibition of 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in RTE smoked turkey under MAP and MAP with oregano EO (MAPEO) was increased when compared to VP during the shelf life of the product. They stated that 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> can be efficiently controlled by a combination of MAP and oregano EO, especially when it is difficult to keep constant temperature during transportation and retail display (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>). The antimicrobial activity of oregano EO has been previously confirmed, and it has been utilized to control 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in meat and meat products (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>–
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>). The composition of oregano EO is a mixture of volatile terpenes, including α-terpinene, 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, carvacrol, and thymol, that participate in antimicrobial properties of this EO, and the latter two compounds are the most important due to their activities on the membranes of bacteria (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>). Furthermore, it has been reported that 
 <italic>Z. multiflora</italic> Boiss EO, which mainly contains thymol and carvacrol, had antimicrobial activities against 
 <italic>L. monocytogenes</italic> in meat and meat products, indicating the importance of these two components in the antimicrobial activities of the EOs (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>).
</p>
