<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">El-Nemr et al. (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1990</xref>) determined crude protein in fully ripened Egyptian pomegranate fruits obtained from the local market. The analysis discovered that seeds, but not juice, contain protein and that 13.2% of the constituents measured in the dry seeds were unidentified proteins (El-Nemr et al., 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1990</xref>). Al-Maiman and Ahmad (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>) studied total protein amounts in seeds of Saudi Arabian pomegranate “Taifi.” Fully-ripe fruits contained 4.06% of protein in the seeds (Al-Maiman and Ahmad, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>). Elfalleh et al. (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) studied proteins in the seeds of two Tunisian commercial pomegranate cultivars. Seed storage protein content was 167.8 ± 8.9 mg/g dry weight, which constitutes 16.9% of the seeds' dry weight. Globulins (62.4 mg/g) and albumins (54.1 mg/g) are its major fractions, followed by glutelins (33.2 mg/g) and prolamins (18.1 mg/g). No significant difference in the content of albumins and glutelins was found between the cultivars (Elfalleh et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Elfalleh et al. (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) studied storage proteins in seeds of mature pomegranate fruits of eight different Tunisian cultivars from five Tunisian regions. The authors reported that the seeds contain 16.8% proteins (per dry weight). The pomegranate seeds accumulated mainly globulins (43%) and albumins (32%). Glutelins constituted 16% and prolamins only 9% of the proteins found. Significant differences between the cultivars in the total amount of storage proteins, ranging from 15.4% in “Beldi” to 20.1% in “Rafrafi” was found, as well as differences for each fraction's content (Elfalleh et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Zang (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) determined protein content in pomegranate seeds oil originating from Xinjiang. The average content of crude protein in pomegranate seeds was 14.3%, in which glutelins and residual protein constituted more than 80% of total protein content, and the contents of globulins, albumins, and prolamins were lower (Zang, 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
