<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plants are subjected to a wide range of abiotic and biotic stresses and have evolved various molecular defense mechanisms. Antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) are a part of plants’ innate immunity [
 <xref rid="B1-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. A wide range of plant AMPs have been described and grouped into families: thionins, defensins, hevein-like, knottin-type, lipid transfer proteins, α-hairpinins, snakins, cyclotides, and some unclassified peptides [
 <xref rid="B2-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Most AMPs are cationic, cysteine-rich molecules, stabilized by disulfide bonds. Thionins were the first plant AMPs to be described. Balls et al. first crystallized thionins in 1942 [
 <xref rid="B3-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and Okada et al. described them as a “lethal toxic substance for brewing yeast” in 1970 [
 <xref rid="B4-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Thionins are small (~5 kDa) cationic peptides divided into five classes based on the number of cysteine residues and charge. Thionins with eight cysteine residues are divided into classes I and II, and thionins with six cysteine residues into classes III, IV, and V. The sequences and secondary structures of thionins are highly conserved. The secondary structures of thionins generate a “β1-α1-α2-β2-random coil” motif with the N-terminus forming the first β-sheet [
 <xref rid="B5-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The spatial structure of thionins has shown a distinct capital Greek gamma letter “
 <italic>Γ</italic>” shape. The vertical arm consists of two antiparallel α-helices, and the horizontal arm contains a coil in an extended conformation and a short antiparallel β-sheet. Thionins typically have an amphipathic character with hydrophobic residues located on the outer surface of the two α-helices. Hydrophilic residues are situated on the undersurface of the “
 <italic>Γ</italic>” and at the outer surface of the corner of the “
 <italic>Γ</italic>”, as well as on the inner surface of the molecule, where positively charged residues are concentrated [
 <xref rid="B4-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Thionins have been found in monocots (
 <italic>Poaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>Liliaceae</italic>) and dicots (
 <italic>Santalaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Ranunculaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Viscaceae</italic>, 
 <italic>Brassicaceae</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B3-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Thionins are considered plant toxins because of their toxic properties against a wide range of prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms, as well as mammalian cells [
 <xref rid="B8-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
