<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">TB is caused by various strains of 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, commonly affects the lungs, and is transferrable from person to person through the air. Mtb is an intra-cellular parasite normally residing in the human macrophages, where its survival and growth depends on complex networks of the attenuation of macrophage activity by the Mtb bacilli. Mtb has not only developed a number of mechanisms to evade onslaught from such host macrophage immune responses as reactive oxygen and nitrogen species, but it has also evolved a metabolism that has allowed it to survive in this very specialized niche environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. It has become evident that one of the mechanisms to arrest the progression of Mtb into full-blown infection is a multi-targeted approach [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The key question which arises is, “Can a single plant extract be used to screen multiple targets as a means of identifying novel synergistic anti-infective properties?” Medicinal plants have been used for the treatment of several diseases and the plant extract identified for analysis was that from 
 <italic>Pelargonium sidoides,</italic> as this plant has a 200 year documented history of ethnobotanical use in the treatment of tuberculosis and other infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. This includes well documented reports in literatures that suggest the medicinal properties and efficacy of 
 <italic>P. sidoides</italic> against 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> and other bacterial infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]
 <italic>.</italic> The mechanisms and targets of this anti-tubercular activity are, however, not defined. The aqueous-ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>P. sidoides</italic> (EP® 7630) roots have been used to treat bacterial infections, as well as to induce the production of the pro-inflammatory cytokines TNF-α and IL-6 in human blood human immune cells, alleviating symptoms associated with acute bronchitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This extract is licensed in Germany as herbal medicine for the treatment of upper respiratory tract infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].
</p>
