<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) was defined as the lowest concentration at which 90% of growth was inhibited (corresponding to the lowest concentration of no visible growth in the well) compared with vehicle control, as previously reported [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and the IC
 <sub>50</sub> was defined as the lowest concentration at which 50% of growth was inhibited. As there is no standard method described in the CLSI (Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute) guidelines for growing and evaluating the MIC of 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>gingivalis</italic>, we followed previously described methods with some modifications [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Briefly, the bacterial culture previously incubated for 48 hours was standardized to a final concentration of 10
 <sup>6</sup> CFU/mL in sBHI using a Cytation 3 multimode plate reader (Biotek®, Winooski, VT) by change in optical density (OD
 <sub>600</sub> nm), and confirmed by colony plate counts. Assays with plant extracts and controls were performed in 96-well flat-bottom non-tissue culture treated plates (Falcon® 35–3075, Corning, NY). All extracts were tested at a range concentration of 2–256 μg/mL or 1–128 μg/mL via serial dilution. An untreated growth control, vehicle (DMSO) control (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0239316.s001">S1 Fig</xref>), and antibiotic control (tetracycline) were included. Plates were incubated in anaerobic conditions at 37°C for 72 hours. All experiments were performed in triplicate and repeated one time on a separate day to confirm the accuracy of the results. Growth inhibition was determined by change in OD from the start of incubation to the final time point (72 hours). Growth inhibition was calculated with the following formula: (1−(Δ
 <italic>ODtest</italic>/Δ
 <italic>ODvehicle</italic>))*100 [
 <xref rid="pone.0239316.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The mean and standard error of triplicates for each treatment were calculated using Microsoft Excel.
</p>
