<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this context, we would like to highlight a factor overlooked until now: the influence of metabolic detoxification by the insects, which may underlie the greater toxicity of full essential oils relative to their main components. Insects have evolved alongside plant defenses like natural terpenes, so they have developed mechanisms to deal with them to some extent (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rosenthal and Berenbaum, 2012</xref>). There is evidence that insect metabolism can alter the actual concentration of these toxicants, as demonstrated for the essential oils from 
 <italic class="italic">M. verticillata</italic>, eucalyptus (
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus cinerea</italic>) and orange (
 <italic class="italic">Citrus sinensis</italic>) as fumigants against 
 <italic class="italic">M. domestica</italic> (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi and Palacios, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi and Palacios, 2015</xref>). In these cases, the essential oils were more active than the most abundant (and most toxic) terpene, and it was shown that 
 <italic class="italic">M. domestica</italic> absorbed most of the component terpenes, proportionally to their relative contribution to the essential oils. The metabolization of the major terpene by cytochrome P450 was also demonstrated in each case, by using piperonyl butoxide (PBO) to inhibit the oxidizing system (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jones, 1998</xref>). In other words, the insect absorbs most of the terpenes offered, but preferentially metabolizes the terpene with the highest concentration in the mixture. The metabolic process could yield a product even more toxic to the insect than the original terpene, thus enhancing its toxicity (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi et al., 2012</xref>), but would more often diminish the toxicity of that terpene (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi and Palacios, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rossi and Palacios, 2015</xref>).
</p>
