<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">The census of breeding sacred ibises' sites took advantage of the long-term initiative “Garzaie-Italia” that has been monitoring the heronries in Italy since 1972
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. The active heronries monitored throughout northern Italy increased in number from 40 in 1972 to 301 in 2019
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>, and unpublished data in the “Garzaie-Italia” archive. The number of nests of each breeding species was estimated from ground observations and from aerial surveys by small drones, depending on the site characteristics and observability, during repeated visits to each colony from March to July, i.e. during the period of peak occupation by each species. According to the methods adopted for the other species that bred in the heronries, the counts of sacred ibis nests aimed to assess the “number of nests during the period of peak occupation” in order to obtain estimates that could be comparable among years. The counts included all visible nests without checking its contents. The count of sacred ibis nests presented additional difficulties, compared to the nest of the other waterbirds. Sacred ibis nests were often packed in communal platforms comprising from 2 to several nests, and their precise number was difficult to assess from the ground. Since 2017, an increasing number of cases of active nests were observed as late as September, but these nests were not included in the counts, because it could not be ascertained whether they were replacements of lost ones or new late breeding attempts. Several juvenile or adult individuals of sacred ibises were often observed roaming around the nest platforms, but they were not quantified, because they were apparently non-breeding. A precise count of sacred ibis nests could be performed only in 90% of cases, therefore we managed missing counts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup> using the program TRIM (TRends and Indices in Monitoring data). TRIM allows for missing counts in the time series and produces unbiased yearly indices and standard errors using Poisson regression
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, we excluded heronries data collected in the period from 1972 to 1989, because the first report of a nesting sacred ibis concerns a pair breeding in 1989
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>, while no other heronries were occupied by sacred ibises before 1989
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
