<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The high flavonoid content of dark chocolate cocoa has proven to be an effective cardioprotective agent [
 <xref rid="B133-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>] by acting as an effective anti-inflammatory agent, by inhibiting NF-kb, by acting as an antihypertensive agent by increasing the bioactivity of nitric oxide, displaying antiatherogenic activity by decreasing triglyceride concentration, and by decreasing insulin resistance and increasing platelet reactivity [
 <xref rid="B134-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Dihydro-quercetin (DHQ), a dihydroxyflavone used in animal models, proved to be effective against cardiac dysfunction by decreasing the generation of ROS and lipid peroxidation and increasing the biological function of antioxidant enzyme. The PI3K/Akt pathway activation is found to have protective effects [
 <xref rid="B135-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Clinical trials on oxerutin showed that it is quite active in treatment of chronic venous hypertension [
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. Interestingly, there are no detected toxicities or side effects of oxerutin clinical trilas results [
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. Different studies and clinical trials showed that a mixture of flavonoids like diosmin, troxerutin, RutinS hesperidin, quercetin, etc., enhance the veins function, soothe the capillary permeability, and increase the lymphatic and hemorrhoidal drainage [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Thus, flavonoids are useful in control of piles and hemorrhoid diseases. Diosmin that is the flavone glycoside of diosmetin effectively control various types of blood vessel disease like hemorrhoids, bleeding from gums and eyes, etc. [
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. It enhances blood flow inside the body.
</p>
