<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0034">In, 
 <italic>Porphyridium</italic> another imperative unicellular microalga, each cell is encapsulated in a sulphated polysaccharides. The capsule outside the cell is dissolved in a growth medium to form exopolysaccharides. These complex sugars are composed of glucuronic acid (10%), galactose (22%), glucose (24%), xylose (38%) and other saccharides such as rhamnose, mannose and arabinose in minute concentration (
 <xref rid="bib0058" ref-type="bibr">Geresh et al., 2002</xref>). The exopolysaccharides are compatible with the human body and are biodegradable and plays vital role in manufacturing of various medicines, cosmetics and food derivatives. A study carried out by 
 <xref rid="bib0187" ref-type="bibr">Pujol et al. (2002)</xref>, revealed identification of various sulfated polysachharides from marine algae and animal resorviors and act as potential inhibitors of human and animal viral infections. A study by 
 <xref rid="bib0161" ref-type="bibr">Nagle et al. (2020)</xref>, suggested strong antiviral bioactivity of sulfated polysaccharides isolated from marine red algae. Sulfated polysaccharides are multifarious class of macromolecules and have diverse clinical relevance (
 <xref rid="bib0201" ref-type="bibr">Seedevi et al., 2013</xref>). They have been found to be broadly distributed in animals, plants and algae found in the saline soil. A report by 
 <xref rid="bib0101" ref-type="bibr">Karthik et al. (2014)</xref>, revealed their presence in the marine saline soil is an indication of an adaptation process which might have established during application. The two chief constituents responsible for the antiviral bioactivity of sulfated polysaccharides are chondroitin sulfate and heparin (
 <xref rid="bib0059" ref-type="bibr">Ghosh et al., 2009</xref>). The exopolysaccharides of Porphyridium have been elucidated to be potent against several virus viz. retrovirus (
 <xref rid="bib0222" ref-type="bibr">Talyshinsky et al., 2002</xref>), and HSV-1 and HSV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib0161" ref-type="bibr">Nagle et al., 2020</xref>) etc. Therefore, these biocompatible compounds were suggested to be employed in coating materials of various sanitary items for COVID-19 deterrence.
</p>
