<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The yeast-to-hyphal transition of 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> is linked to a number of properties, which is important for its interactions with the host. These properties include adhesion to epithelial and endothelial cells, primary and intercellular invasion via induced endocytosis, active penetration and escape of the phagocytes and immune evasion [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. This transition plays a fundamental role in the virulence and pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. According to the above information, it is important to assess whether the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">B. morelensis</italic> has the ability to inhibit the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. For this reason, the inhibition of germ tube was evaluated which obtained an CL
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> of 1.4 mg/mL. It is noteworthy that this the first study about examining the effect of the 
 <italic class="italic">B. morelensis</italic> essential oil on the inhibition of the germ tube of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>. This potential pharmacological target is important since the essential oil is acting on an important process in the morpho-transformation of 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Furthermore, this essential oil also might act at the level of the synthesis occurring at the activation of glucan synthase, which is associated with the extensive synthesis of cell wall during the formation of hyphae [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. This characteristic could suggest a new antifungal which is more selective towards the infecting yeast than towards the host cells [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-22-02095" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] so we can’t ignore this pathway inhibition of 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>.
</p>
