<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Objective:</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Lonchocarpus sericeus</italic> stembark decoction has been extensively employed in folkloric medicine in many parts of Nigeria as a remedy for pain as well as inflammation. The plant was studied for its anti-inflammatory as well as analgesic potency using standard biological models.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Materials and Methods:</title>
  <p>The stembark of 
   <italic>L. sericeus </italic>was evaluated for anti-inflammatory properties using egg albumin and xylene-induced oedema models. The pain-relieving property was evaluated using acetic acid-induced writhing and thermally-induced pain models. Median lethal dose determination (intraperitoneal LD
   <sub>50</sub>), quantification of some phytochemicals as well as phytochemical screening were also performed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p>The LD
   <sub>50</sub> of stembark extract of 
   <italic>L. sericeus </italic>was found to be 3,100 mg/kg (i. p). The crude extract and fractions (310-930 mg/kg) effectively reduced oedema caused by egg albumin and xylene and exhibited high analgesic properties in inhibiting pain induced by acetic acid and heat. These reductions were dose-dependent and statistically significant (p&lt;0.05-0.001) when compared to distilled water and similar to prototype drugs employed. Quantitative determinations of some bio-active constituents of the plant showed a higher flavonoid content (0.52±0.02 mg/100 g) compared to alkaloids (0.36±0.02 mg/100 g) and flavonoids (0.49±0.03 mg/100 g). Phytochemical screening of the stembark showed the presence of alkaloids, cardiac glycosides, flavonoids terpenes, tannins and saponins. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion:</title>
  <p>These results imply that the stembark extract of 
   <italic>L. sericeus </italic> possesses anti-inflammatory and analgesic potency and these data validate its wide use in folkloric medicine for inflammation and pain management.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
