<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The exposure of inoculated and edible-coated fruits to simulated gastrointestinal fluids was done as previously described [
 <xref rid="B26-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-foods-08-00057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Ten grams of fruit was transferred to a sterile Stomacher bag (Interscience, Saint Nom, France) and 6 ml of artificial saliva (KCl (89.6 g/L); KSCN (20 g/L); NaH2PO4 (88.8 g/L); Na2SO4 (57 g/L); NaCl (175.3 g/L); NaHCO3 (84.7 g/L); urea (25 g/L); 290 mg of α-amylase; 15 mg of uric acid; 25 mg mucin, pH 6.8 ± 0.2) was added. The fruit was homogenized for 30 sec in a Stomacher (IUL Instruments, Barcelona, Spain) and the incubation was done for 5 min, 37 °C, 60 rpm. After this time interval sampling was done to determine the viability as described above, and an artificial gastric fluid (1.884 mL NaCl (175.3 g/L); 0.36 mL NaH2PO4 (88.8 g/L); 1.104 mL KCl (89.6 g/L); 2.16 mL CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·2H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O (22.2 g/L); 1.2 mL NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>Cl (30.6 g/L); 0.09 mL HCl 37% (w/w); 1.2 mL glucose (65 g/L); 1.2 mL glucuronic acid (2 g/L); 0.408 mL urea (25 g/L); 1.2 mL glucosamine hydrochloride (33 g/L); 0.12 g bovine serum albumin; 0.3 g pepsin; 30 mL mucin (12 g/L), pH 2.5 or pH 1.5) was added to the previous saliva mixture. Incubation continued for 2 h, at 37 °C and a slight agitation (60 rpm). Simulation of the gut environment was achieved by the addition of an artificial intestinal fluid (pH 6.5) to the gastric medium. The intestinal fluid composition includes 2.4 mL NaCl (175.3 g/L); 2.4 mL NaHCO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> (84.7 g/L); 0.6 mL KH
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>PO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> (8 g/L); 0.378 mL KCl (89.6 g/L); 0.6 mL MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (5 g/L); 0.0108 mL HCl 37% (w/w); 0.24 mL urea (25 g/L); 0.54 mL CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·2H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O (22.2 g/L); 0.06 g BSA; 0.54 g pancreatin; 0.09 g lipase and bile solution is made of 1.2 mL NaCl (175.3 g/L); NaHCO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> (84.7 g/L); 0.168 mL KCl (89.6 g/L); 0.006 mL HCl 37% (w/w); 0.4 mL urea (25 g/L); 0.4 mL CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>·2H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O (22.2 g/L); 0.072 g BSA; 1.2 g bile (0.6 g porcine bile, 0.6 g bovine bile). The intestinal challenge lasted 2 h at 37 °C, 60 rpm. Three independent experiments were performed. The viability in the gastric and intestinal challenge was determined after 1 and 2 h of exposure.
</p>
