<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It has been noted that the failure of biocontrol might be due to the focus on simple predator-prey relationships and the disregard of more complex interactions in the invaded community 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Pearson1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In a natural ecosystem, herbivory and competition are two of the most common biotic stressors that plants encounter 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Boege1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Schdler1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, and both play important roles in shaping the structure and dynamics of the community 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Doyle1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>; this is true for both the invasive plants and the invaded community 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Doyle1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. It is well known that both herbivory and competition from native competitors in the invaded community can negatively affect invasive plants and reduce their growth and fitness 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-FerreroSerrano1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Sheppard1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Inter-specific competition and herbivory can have synergistic effects on the performance of the attacked invasive host plant 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Turner1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Crawley1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> and, as a result, release native neighbours from competition 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Newingham1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, thus limiting invasive success in the invaded community and facilitating the restoration of the native community 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Levine1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. However, only few studies have revealed the independent 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Suwa1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and antagonistic 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Schdler1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0062608-Callaway1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> interactive effects of herbivory and competition on invasive plants. We predicted that the antagonistic interactive effect between herbivory and competition could induce the compensatory growth of invasive plants and weaken the effect of herbivory on invasive plants, which would release invasive plants from the naeighbouring competitors and result in the failure of herbivory to control invasive plants. Obviously, an understanding of the interactive effect of herbivory and competition on the performance of invasive plants and the structure and dynamics of the invaded community is important to predict the effectiveness of biological agents on the invasive plants in an invaded community.
</p>
