<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0070">The literature review demonstrated that polyphenols have been investigated for their potential antiviral efficiency against SARS-CoV-2 in molecular modeling studies, cell-free polyphenol–protein interaction studies, and in cell-based virus infection studies (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Chojnacka 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Paraiso 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). Convincing data shows that polyphenols such as epigallocatechin gallate, resveratrol, and curcumin are prime candidates for preclinical and clinical trials. As a cautionary note, the efficacy of tested polyphenols against human viral disease 
 <italic>in silico</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> screening methods are not validated. Potential regulation of COVID-19 intensity by polyphenols controlling ACE2 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> has been suggested (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Horne and Vohl, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Manoharan 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>) but very few studies have been performed to examine the antiviral activity of polyphenols against SARS-CoV-2 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. Pudilan Xiaoyan Oral Liquid (PDL), a traditional Chinese medicine containing four herbs and more than 180 ingredients, showed potent anti-SARSCoV-2 activity in infected hACE2 mice (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Deng 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). It has also been stated that a nebulized formula of quercetin and N-acetylcysteine substantially relieved the respiratory symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 in a patient treated with hydroxychloroquine and antibiotics (
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Schettig 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2020
 </xref>). This reinforces the value of more clinical trials to determine the potential of polyphenol-based nutraceuticals as an adjuvant or key treatment for COVID-19. High-throughput screening methods will speed the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> development of lead candidates by reducing the number of polyphenol libraries. Screening of polyphenol-rich plant extracts is an alternative, commonly used method, but it has the drawback that extracts contain a multitude of natural products with inherent difficulties of not being able to reliably distinguish active concepts and the potential for pharmacological antagonism. These problems can be solved by integrating classical bioassay-guided fractionation with machine learning approaches that expose the identity of bioactive natural products in extracts without the need for homogeneity purification. In our view, the above hybrid method aims to accelerate research because many antiviral 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments can be conducted without the treatment of live viruses and because the identification of polyphenols (and other natural products) has been made simpler over the past few years thanks to developments in plant metabolism and ever-growing natural product databases such as phenol-explorer (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Rothwell 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>), knapsack (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Shinbo 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006
 </xref>), and the global natural product social networking database (
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Wang 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>).(
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Palamara et al 2005</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Ryu et al, 2010</xref>)
</p>
