<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a recent study, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al. (2018b)</xref> reported that 
 <italic>Ajuga bracteosa</italic> (a high-valued medicinal plant) accumulated higher levels of monoterpene hydrocarbons, which could be potentially used as essential oil-based medicine against human viruses. These hydrocarbons included limonene (3.4%), α-pinene (5.3%), camphene (4.45%), α-thujone (9.4%), 1,8-cineole (14.3%), borneol (11.4%), camphor (12.2%), and nerol (9.2) in the shoots raised 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> in response to the application of TDZ (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2018a</xref>). Similarly, the supplementation of TDZ into the MS media produced a substantial amount of monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes through shoot cultures in the medicinally potent plant 
 <italic>Lallemantia Iberica</italic> (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Pourebad et al., 2015</xref>). The higher production of the important terpene volatiles (candidate anti-SARS-CoV-2 metabolites) in the regenerated shoots can be attributed to the different attributes of shoot cultures, such as the juvenile stage of the differentiated shoots, as the monoterpenes biosynthesis is directly linked to the young and immature shoot with higher metabolic potential (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bassolino et al., 2015</xref>). Biosynthesis of terpene metabolites generally takes place in epidermal cells of shoot or leaf and is stored in special glandular structures called leaf trichomes (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2018a</xref>). In another study, compared with callus cultures, the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> raised shoot cultures in medicinally important plants 
 <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> were found to accumulate higher levels of monoterpenes hydrocarbons (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Gounaris, 2010</xref>). As the growth and development during 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> shoot cultures are highly influenced by the effects of different plant growth regulators, the biosynthesis of terpenes could be correlated to 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> growth and development. The ontogenetic changes in the shoots as a result of plant cell growth and the accelerated but controlled secondary metabolism during 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures are other important reasons which influence and regulate the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2019a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Khan M. A. et al., 2020</xref>). Apart from micro-propagated plantlets many other 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures are also serving as useful sources of different medicinally important secondary metabolites (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).
</p>
