<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">The rate of delivery of much simpler and easy to fabricate matrix-type transdermal patches is usually controlled by skin permeation (Prausnitz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2004</xref>). These systems comprise drug in the hydrophilic or lipophilic matrix (Valenta and Auner 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2004</xref>). The current study focuses on developing a matrix-type transdermal patch of lamotrigine, a relatively new anti-epileptic agent which is not structurally related to compounds of this class but has pharmacological action similar to phenytoin (Leach et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">1986</xref>). It is a weak base with pKa of 5.5 and molecular weight 256.09. The octanol/water partition coefficient is 1.19. The low water solubility of lamotrigine, i.e., 1 g/L presents a challenge in designing formulation (Levy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2002</xref>; Rambeck and Wolf 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">1993</xref>). Lamotrigine is used alone or in combination with other anticonvulsants for treating both partial and generalized seizures. It is conventionally available as immediate-release and extended-release tablet dosage forms. The co-administration of other anti-convulsants and dosing recommendations for lamotrigine are variable and, to optimize treatment, therapeutic drug monitoring is recommended as lamotrigine linear pharmacokinetics which can be significantly affected by co-administration of other AEDs. The elimination rate of lamotrigine is increased due to enzyme-inducing drugs, such as phenytoin, carbamazepine, phenobarbital, and primidone, and prolonged by administration of valproic acid (Yuen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">1992</xref>; Gidal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2000</xref>; Anderson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2002</xref>).
</p>
