<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">Seed longevity is described as the period over which a seed remains viable and capable of germination [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The length of time during which seeds maintain their viability and vigor is a trait of interest not only for crop species within breeding programs and food security, but also for describing natural populations’ dynamics and assess persistence potential [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Seed longevity is strongly variable, ranging from just a few months in soybean [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], to more than 2000 years in 
 <italic>Phoenix dactylifera</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In species with orthodox seeds, viable seeds may enter dormancy, a temporal suppression of germination under favorable conditions, thanks to their ability to tolerate considerable desiccation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The slow pace of seed viability loss in orthodox species hinders the study and characterization of species’ seed longevity under natural conditions. Due to those difficulties, ex situ aging tests are used to estimate seed longevity and vigor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Genetic factors have a key influence on seed persistence and because of this, the survival of seeds experiencing moisture and temperature stress in the laboratory is thought to be a good predictor of their potential persistence in the environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In fact, similar molecular events were found to accompany artificial and natural seed aging processes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Long et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] successfully predicted species seed persistence in the field with the species ranking of the days taken for seed viability to decline by 50% in an artificial aging test. A faster viability decay under artificial aging conditions is linked to a germination depression with time [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. There are different proposed approaches to estimate and contrast seed longevity by generating an atmosphere that speeds up the aging process: accelerated aging and controlled deterioration. Controlled deterioration tests were first developed to identify low vigor seeds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and consist of subjecting to high temperatures (around 40–45 °C) prearranged high seed moisture content (from 18 to 24%) for 24 to 96 h [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In contrast, accelerated aging (AA) tests consist of exposing seeds to high temperatures around 40–45 °C over water, generating an atmosphere with high relative humidity (RH). The AA test was first developed by Delouche and Baskin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] to estimate the longevity of seeds stored in a warehouse, as the decline in germination following AA is proportional to the initial physiological potential of the seed lot. Seed lots with high vigor should be able to withstand these stress conditions and will deteriorate at a slower rate than lots with poorer vigor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The AA test is preferable for a rapid method as it does not require initial seed moisture control and equilibration, which may suppose extra time and offers similar results to the controlled deterioration test [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].
</p>
