<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>People with diabetes are at higher risk to develop complications with a corona virus infections. The recent data from the 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) also confirms that diabetes, along with advanced age and/or presence of cardiovascular conditions, obesity, is a major risk factor for an adverse outcome. Similarly, Diabetes was also a major contributor to MERS-CoV disease severity and mortality (Iacobellis, 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Patients who have diabetes are often have associated with the weakened immune response, both concerning cytokine profile as well as changes in immune responses together with T-cell and macrophage activation. Weaker glycemic control harms several aspects of the immune response by a viral infection and in addition to the risk of potential bacterial secondary infection in the lungs. According to studies, the coronavirus predominantly infects human by allowing the cells to enter through the ACE-2 receptor. Spike proteins of coronavirus usually bind to the ACE receptors in the lungs. ACE-2 is a peptidase enzyme and a membrane glycoprotein, mainly expressed in epithelial cells of the lungs, intestine, kidney and blood vessels to regulate the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS). This enzyme is the main component that converts Ang-I to Ang-II (Das et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) and angiotensin-I (Ang-I) to peptides, angiotensin (1–7) and angiotensin (1–9), separately. Angiotensin (1–7) is responsible for the anti-inflammatory and antioxidant role (Das et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Human dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP4) was identified as a functional receptor for the spike protein of the SARS CoV-2 viral entry. DPP4 enzyme is a type II transmembrane glycoprotein, expressed ubiquitously in many tissues, including the immune cells. DPP4 degrades incretins such as glucagon like peptide 1 (GLP-1) and glucose-dependent insulinotropic polypeptide, ultimately leading to reduced insulin secretion and abnormal visceral adipose tissue metabolism (Iacobellis, 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The renin–angiotensin–aldosterone system (RAAS) component ACE2 and DPP4 are proteins dysregulated in diabetes (Cuschieri &amp; Grech, 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Valencia et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The entry of SARS-CoV-2 within the host cell triggers an inflammatory response, recruitment of T helper cells with the production of interferon gamma leading to a cytokine storm. Hence, considering the cellular mechanisms triggered by SARS-CoV-2 and the pathophysiology of diabetes, individuals with diabetes are more susceptible to a cytokine storm with potential organ damage if infected by COVID-19 (Iacobellis, 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). ACE-2 is also expressed in the pancreas. So, the entry of the coronavirus into the pancreatic islets may cause an acute beta-cell dysfunction with a resultant acute hyperglycemic state. Hence, individuals with diabetes are vulnerable to COVID-19 infection leading to an uncontrolled hyperglycemic status (Cuschieri &amp; Grech, 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Valencia et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). To summarize, potential mechanisms that may increase the susceptibility for COVID-19 in patients with DM includes higher affinity cellular binding and efficient virus entry, decreased viral clearance, diminished T cell function, increased susceptibility to hyperinflammation and cytokine storm syndrome, presence of cardiovascular diseases (Muniyappa &amp; Gubbi, 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Liu et al., have successfully crystallized the main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>)/chymotrypsin-like protease (3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>) from COVID-19 has been structured and repositioned in the Protein Data Bank (PDB) (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Quimque et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). This protease represents a potential target for the inhibition of corona virus for entry and replication. In this study, the binding affinity of mentioned ligands to main protease (6LU7), spike protein with ACE2 receptor (6M0J), RdRp (6M71) and MERS-CoV with hDPP4 receptor (4L72) proteases was examined and compared with existing anti-viral drugs like remdesivir, hydroxychloroquine and favipiravir. 
</p>
