<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the current study, first, we searched the literature for the mention of the chemical constituents of 
 <italic>C. fistula</italic> leaf extracts through mass spectrometry techniques. There are around 12 different major molecules in the leaf extract of 
 <italic>C. fistula.</italic>(
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>) Most of these phytoconstituents are flavonoids, and many of them have medicinal values including antimicrobial activities.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>p</italic>-Coumaric acid is a phenolic acid of the hydroxycinnamic acid family that shows 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> antiviral activity against hepatitis C virus at the initial stage and antileishmanial activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>
 </sup> Syringaresinol is a furofuran-type lignin and shows antileishmanial activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>
 </sup> Myricetin belongs to the flavonoid class of polyphenolic compounds that possesses antioxidant and is known for its nutraceutical values.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>
 </sup> Myricetin exhibits antibacterial activity against Gram-negative bacteria and antiviral activity, acting as a strong inhibitor of reverse transcription of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and Rauscher murine leukemia virus (RLV).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>
 </sup> Proanthocyanidins, recognized as condensed tannins, are a class of flavonoids present as an active compound in medicinal plants and occur as polymers of different oligomeric forms.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, proanthocyanidins are known for their antibacterial, antiviral, and antileishmanial activities.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref>
 </sup> It has been reported that flavonoids are a potential candidate for leishmanicidal drugs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>L. donovani</italic> contain many significant enzymes, which are considered as potential drug targets for the development of new therapeutic molecules. We have selected four key drug targets of 
 <italic>L. donovani</italic> for molecular docking studies against the abundant phytochemicals of leaf extract. 
 <italic>Ld</italic>PTR1 is an NADPH-dependent short-chain reductase responsible for the retrieval of pterins in the protozoan parasite 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic>. This enzyme acts as a metabolic bypass for drugs targeting dihydrofolate reductase.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>
 </sup> The 
 <italic>Ld</italic>TR enzyme follows thiol-redox metabolism to keep trypanothione in its reduced form. This antioxidant property of 
 <italic>Ld</italic>TR is essential for the survival of 
 <italic>L. donovani.</italic>(
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23">23</xref>)
 <italic>Ld</italic>SMT is required for the biosynthesis of ergosterol, the major membrane sterol in 
 <italic>L. donovani</italic>, responsible for parasite virulence, and highly conserved protein among 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> species.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>Ld</italic>NH are conserved phylogenetic markers and important enzymes for the replication of DNA of the parasites.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26">26</xref>
 </sup> We have selected these enzymes for molecular docking with major constituents of 
 <italic>C. fistula</italic> for predicting the possible antileishmanial activity of these molecules. In silico approaches have been effectively used to predict protein structures and protein–ligand interactions. Molecular docking is a computational method used to speculate the preferred orientation of ligands (organic molecules) with the proteins. Accordingly, nature provides a huge diversity and an alternative source of valuable chemical structures for biological screening test against pathogens. We further tested our hypothesis through different antileishmanial and cytotoxicity assays on promastigotes, amastigotes, and human THP-1-derived macrophages.
</p>
