<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">Our study found that elevated nitrogen altered the competitive relationship between the weak invader 
 <italic>G. quadriradiata</italic> and the two non-invasive plant species. It indicates that elevated nitrogen deposition may strongly influence the invasion processes of weak invaders as well as vigorous invasive plants in natural ecosystem. We should be especially cautious of the expansion of weak invasive plants in response to elevated nitrogen deposition in the context of global change. The results showed that the competitive interactions between 
 <italic>G. quadriradiata</italic> and the non-invasive plant species were not altered by light treatment but by nitrogen enrichment. In the Control and Shade treatments, when we planted the weak invader together with the two non-invasive species, no competitive advantage was exhibited. However, in the treatments with elevated nitrogen (N and N+Shade), the weak invader obtained a considerable advantage and outcompeted the non-invasive plants (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The shade treatment suppressed the growth of both the invader and non-invasive species, especially in pots with elevated nitrogen (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, it did not change the competitive pattern between 
 <italic>G. quadriradiata</italic> and the non-invasive species. The results indicate that initially weak invasive plants can become more vigorous under elevated nitrogen deposition associated with global change. As suggested by numerous studies, the invasion of vigorous invasive plants can usually be accelerated by elevated nitrogen
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Such vigorous invasive plants are commonly characterized by a conspicuous and strong competitive ability with respect to resources
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. However, 
 <italic>G. quadriradiata</italic> is not a vigorous, but rather weak, competitor under ambient conditions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Although 
 <italic>G. quadriradiata</italic> is a worldwide invasive plant in farmland, it is generally considered to be a relatively weak invader or weed due to its lack of high competitive and colonizing ability in natural communities which is usually characterized by relatively low soil nitrogen resource and high competition from close relatives. Thus, our results suggest that competition relationships between some originally weak exotic species and their competitors can be changed by elevated nitrogen. Such changes of competition outcome caused by nitrogen resource were also occasionally reported by some researchers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. This suggests that necessary attention should be paid to the expansion of invasive plants which are weak under low nitrogen but powerful under rich nitrogen conditions in the context of global change.
</p>
