<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In order to evaluate the possible effects of ingested NP, there are several factors that should be taken into account: (A) NP dimensions: several studies reported as the size of food mNP might alter their uptake from intestinal cells[
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>-
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. The smaller the mNP, the faster and easier will be its passage through the mucous layer and its passage into the mucosa either by transcellular or paracellular transport; (B) Core material: it could determine whether NPs remain intact or partially digested by the intestinal fluids. An important concern is in fact the propensity of NPs to be dissolved and release heavy metals, which in turn affects NP toxicity. In this sense, AgNP, ZnONP and CuONP are regarded as the most dangerous food nanoparticles[
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. NP core composition also determines the chemical reactivity, substance adsorption on NP surface, and possibly the epithelial translocation route[
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]; (C) Aggregation/agglomeration state: NPs can arrive into the gut as single entities or in clusters (agglomerates or aggregates[
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]). This feature depends on the NP composition, but also on the physiochemical properties of the environment. It has been reported that the degree of aggregation/agglomeration of SiO2-, Ag- and aluminium-NPs can change in artificial mouth, gastric and intestinal conditions[
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>-
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. At the same time, this factor also affects NP uptake and toxicity, as demonstrated by McCracken et al[
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] and Albanese et al[
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]; (D) Gastrointestinal environment and food: Physiochemical features of food, beverages, and the gut are important factors that influence NP stability, size, surface composition and aggregation/agglomeration state[
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Wang et al[
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>] and Cao et al[
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] demonstrated a higher oxidative stress-related toxicity exerted by ZnONP when associated with Vitamin C and palmitic oil, respectively; on the contrary the presence of flavonoids or quercetin seems to protect against AgNP toxicity[
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>].
</p>
