<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to Tomberlin and Sheppard, the number of matings is proportional to the intensity of illumination in the range of 400–700 nm, and when the intensity of illumination is greater than 200 μ mol m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>s
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, the mating rate reaches 75%. However, at less than 63 μ mol m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>s
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, no mating behavior was observed [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. In addition, the number of matings gradually decreases with time between 8:00–17:00, particularly before 15:00. Tomberlin and Sheppard achieved the highest mating rate with irradiation with an iodine tungsten lamp at a power of 500 W and an illumination intensity of 135 μ mol m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>s
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> under a temperature of 22 °C and a relative humidity of 60–70% The adult longevity (females: approximately 8–9 days; males: approximately 6–7 days) and hatching period of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> are affected by morphological, biological, ecological factors, and environmental stress. Therefore, the density of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> in the wild is low. In the 1970s, to promote resource utilization and large-scale production of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>, Sheppard and Tomberlin started systematic research on the artificial breeding of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>. They determined the ecological factors that affect mating and spawning and identified and summarized the that affect the survival rate of larvae and the development of the pupa prophase [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. There were no significant effects of artificial feeding on the development and survival of pre-pupal 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>. However, the number of adults bred under fodder feeding was significantly lower than under natural feeding, and there were differences in the proportions of males and females. Therefore, to increase mating rates under artificial feeding, it is necessary to achieve the proportions observed in nature [
 <xref rid="B74-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. When peanut bran was used to feed the larvae, the effective conversion rate was 28.9%, this information was valuable for the standardization, scale expansion, and industrialization of the artificial breeding of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B75-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>]. With the successful development of scientific, large-scale breeding of the 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic>, the production of insect protein and oil has become possible [
 <xref rid="B76-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. Furthermore, organic wastes have been recycled and treated in an environmentally friendly way [
 <xref rid="B78-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>].
</p>
