<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the first experiment, the seeds of two landraces of cumin were planted in the experiment site of College of Aburaihan, University of Tehran, during two successive years (2014 and 2015). Each landrace was planted in 2 m
 <sup>2</sup> plots in a sandy-clay soil. The soil was well drained, with pH of 7.2. Recommended crop management practices were implemented to raise the crops to desirable growth stages. Plots were kept weed-, pest-, and disease-free until harvesting time. Chemical characters including the content of catalase, ascorbate peroxidase, protein, proline, essential oil, and its composition of two landraces of cumin were measured. It is worth noting that catalase and ascorbate peroxidase play an important role in the maturity of plant tissues and their high activities affect somatic embryogenesis [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Each essential oil is made up of numerous different organic molecules and some of these including terpenic hydrocarbons, alcohols, and phenols existing in the essential oil are among the genetic properties affecting somatic embryogenesis [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In order to measure chemical characteristics of two landraces of cumin, leaf tissue samples were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. Protein and proline contents of the leaves were measured according to Bradford and Bates et al. [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], respectively. The activities of antioxidant enzymes including catalase and ascorbate peroxidase were estimated as described by Beers and Sizer [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and Nakano and Asada [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The essential oil of the ripened seeds was extracted by the Clevenger apparatus, using the hydrodistillation method. The dried powdered seeds of cumin (40 g) were placed in a distillation apparatus with 400 mL of distilled water and hydrodistilled for three hours. Then, the essential oils were stored in glass vials at 5°C until the essential oil compositions' analysis. The analysis of essential oil composition was performed by GC-MS analysis (a combined analytical method to identify different substances within a sample): Varian CP-3800 GC (gas chromatography) coupled with Varian 4000 (ion trap) MS (mass spectrometry) equipped with a capillary VF-5 fused silica column (30 m × 0.25 mm i.d., film thickness: 0.25 
 <italic>μ</italic>m). Helium was used as the carrier gas at the constant flow of 1.0 ml min
 <sup>−1</sup>, with split ratio of 1/50. Mass spectra were taken at 70 Ev and Mass range was from 
 <italic>m</italic>/
 <italic>z</italic> 35–400 a.m.u. The oven temperature was held at 60°C for 1 min and then programmed to 250°C at a rate of 3°C min
 <sup>−1</sup> and held for 10 min. The injector and detector (FID) temperatures were kept at 250 and 280°C, respectively. The essential oil compositions were identified by calculation of their retention indices under temperature-programmed conditions for n-alkanes (C6–C24) and the oil on a VF-5 column under the same chromatographic conditions. The compounds were identified by comparison of their mass spectra with those of the internal reference mass spectra library (Wiley 7) or with authentic compounds and confirmed by comparison of their retention indices with authentic compounds or with those reported in the literature. For quantification purposes, relative area percentages obtained by FID were used without the use of correction factors.
</p>
