<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Numerous terpene recovery techniques have been developed by solvent-based or solvent-less. Essential oils are usually hydro-distillated extracts from the trichomes of cannabis containing mostly terpenes or terpenoids. Although most of the constituents remain intact during distillation, a few monoterpenes may undergo chemical changes or are quite often lost due to the nature of the distillation process [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The other possible technique is steam distillation by passing dry steam through the inflorescences of the cannabis whereby the terpenes are volatilized, condensed, and collected [
 <xref rid="B84-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Moreover, the microwave-assisted extraction (MAE) can enrich bioactive compounds. The MAE treatment using high irradiation power and relatively long extraction times significantly increased the content of CBD in the essential oil with considerably high yield when compared with the conventional hydro-distillation techniques [
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. In Canada, for instance, the commercial production of the extract is achieved by either solvent extraction such as butane or supercritical fluid (SFE) with the restriction on product purity of no solvent contaminants [
 <xref rid="B87-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. The later technique is known to give superior performance in terpene recovery [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. SFE has recently become a much-preferred method for terpene recovery, largely because it allows using lower temperatures, leading to less deterioration of the thermally labile components and is free from organic solvents [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. A supercritical fluid is the substance at a temperature and pressure above its critical points, with no boundary between the liquid and gas stage. At these points, the fluid is low in viscosity with high diffusion properties to dissolve chemical molecules from the plant matrix. Carbon dioxide (CO
 <sub>2</sub>) is generally used because it is nonflammable, relatively inexpensive, and non-toxic. Large amounts of terpene ingredients were recovered from this method (i.e., up to 50%, 20% and 10% of caryophyllene, humulene and limonene, respectively, can be recovered compared to the conventional methods) [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. 
</p>
