<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_IJPDDR388 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?FILEfx2 jpg ?><?FILEfx3 jpg ?><?FILEfx4 jpg ?><?FILEfx5 jpg ?><?FILEfx6 jpg ?><?FILEfx7 jpg ?><?FILEfx8 jpg ?><?FILEfx9 jpg ?><?FILEfx10 jpg ?><?FILEfx11 jpg ?><?FILEfx12 jpg ?><?FILEfx13 jpg ?><?FILEfx14 jpg ?><?FILEfx15 jpg ?><?FILEfx16 jpg ?><?FILEfx17 jpg ?><?FILEfx18 jpg ?><?FILEfx19 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Parasitol Drugs Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Parasitol Drugs Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal for Parasitology: Drugs and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2211-3207</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7902805</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2211-3207(21)00003-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpddr.2021.01.002</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Special issue articles on 'Anaerobic Protozoan Pathogens: Drugs, Resistance and New Developments'</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A review study on the anti-<italic>trichomonas</italic> activities of medicinal plants</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>Nooshin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Ommi</surname><given-names>Davood</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Kheyri</surname><given-names>Parya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Khamesipour</surname><given-names>Faham</given-names></name><email>faham.khamesipour@yahoo.com</email><email>F.Khamesipour@shirazu.ac.ir</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Setzer</surname><given-names>William N.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Benchimol</surname><given-names>Marlene</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>School of Medicine, Bam University of Medical Sciences, Bam, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Functional Neurosurgery Research Center, Shohada Tajrish Neurosurgical Center of Excellence, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Young Researchers and Elite Club, Shahrekord Branch, Islamic Azad University, Shahrekord, Iran</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Chemistry, University of Alabama in Huntsville, Huntsville, AL, 35899, USA</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Universidade do Grande Rio (UNIGRANRIO) and UFRJ (Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>faham.khamesipour@yahoo.com</email><email>F.Khamesipour@shirazu.ac.ir</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>104</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of Australian Society for Parasitology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>The parasitic diseases represent the most important health risk, especially in underdeveloped countries where they have a deep impact on public health. Trichomoniasis is a prevalent non-viral sexually transmitted disease, and a significant amount of new cases are identified each year globally. Furthermore, the infection is linked with serious concerns such as pregnancy outcomes, infertility, predisposition to cervical and prostate cancer, and increased transmission and acquisition of HIV. The therapy is restricted, adverse effects are often observed, and resistance to the drugs is emerging. Based on this, a new treatment for trichomoniasis is necessary. Natural products represent a rich source of bioactive compounds, and even today, they are used in the search for new drugs. Additionally, natural products provide a wide variety of leadership structures that can be used by the pharmaceutical industry as a template in the development of new drugs that are more effective and have fewer or no undesirable side effects compared to current treatments.</p><p>This review focuses on the medicinal plants that possess anti-trichomonal activity <italic>in vitro</italic> or <italic>in vivo</italic>. An electronic database search was carried out covering the last three decades, i.e., 1990&#x02013;2020. The literature search revealed that almost a dozen isolated phytoconstituents are being explored globally for their anti-trichomonal activity. Simultaneously, many countries have their own traditional or folk medicine for trichomoniasis that utilizes their native plants, as a whole, or even extracts. This review focuses mainly on the human parasite <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>. However, at some points mention is also made to <italic>Tritrichomonas foetus</italic> that causes trichomoniasis in animals of high veterinary and economical interest. We will focus on the plants and plant-based compounds and their anti-trichomonal activity. The literature search highlighted that there are abundant compounds that possess anti-trichomonal activity; however, in-depth <italic>in-vivo</italic> evaluation of compounds and their clinical evaluation has not been undertaken. There is a critical need for new anti-trichomonal compounds, and focused research on phytoconstituents can provide the way forward.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><alt-text id="alttext0010">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Trichomoniasis</kwd><kwd>Anti- <italic>trichomonas</italic> activity</kwd><kwd>Medicinal plants</kwd><kwd>Natural products</kwd><kwd>Compounds</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><sec id="sec1.1"><label>1.1</label><title>Trichomonads and trichomoniasis pathogenesis</title><p id="p0010">Trichomonads are anaerobic flagellated protists infecting many vertebrate and invertebrate species, fit into the large and diverse groups of Trichomonadea and Tritrichomonadea (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Trichomonas species and their infection site in the host.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0015">Five species of trichomonads infect humans. They are <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis,</italic> found in the urogenital tract; <italic>Trichomonas tenax,</italic> localized in the oral cavity; <italic>Pentatrichomonas hominis; Tetratrichomonas</italic> sp<italic>,</italic> in the respiratory tract of humans (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2019</xref>) and digestive tract of several animals (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Cepicka et al., 2006</xref>). and <italic>Dientamoeba fragilis</italic>, both found in the digestive tract (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Maritz et al., 2014</xref>). <italic>P. hominis</italic> and <italic>D. fragilis</italic> cause gastrointestinal symptoms like abdominal pain and diarrhea, and infect domestic animals like cats and farm mammals, demonstrating non-human selectivity and zoonotic origin. Additionally, trichomonad species causing infections in birds and animals, and thus having veterinary importance, are <italic>Trichomonas gallinae</italic>, <italic>Tetratrichomonas gallinarum</italic>, and <italic>Histomonas meleagridis</italic>, and <italic>Tritrichomonas foetus</italic> (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Amin et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">The only species with well-established pathogenic potential in humans is <italic>T. vaginalis.</italic> Trichomoniasis is the most common non-viral sexually transmitted urogenital infection that affects both men and women. Caused by flagellated protozoan parasite <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>, it mainly affects women's vagina, showing clinical symptoms like vaginal discharge, often yellow or green, vulvovaginal irritation, and dysuria. Men with trichomoniasis may not show any clinical signs; however, the urethra is the most common infection site, causing urethral irritation, discharge, or mild burning after urination or ejaculation and swelling of the prostate gland (<xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">Rein, 2020</xref>). Humans are the only host for the <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> parasite existing only in trophozoite form that uses adhesion proteins to bind to squamous epithelial cells. Soluble and membrane-associated enzymes having phospholipase A activity cause lysis of nucleated cells, resulting in microulcerations and microscopic hemorrhages of the vaginal wall and exocervix. Although humoral and cell-mediated immune-inflammatory responses are generated, repeated, and persistent infection occurs, indicating non-protective immunity (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Meites and Workowski, 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">Pulmonary trichomoniasis, an opportunistic infection caused by <italic>T. tenax,</italic> is generally harmless; however, it may become serious in patients with poor oral hygiene. Periodontal diseases like gingivitis and periodontitis, resulting from disruption of the host&#x02013;oral microbiome homeostasis, often trigger <italic>T. tenax</italic> infection. The flagellate can adhere to epithelial cells and produce diverse enzymes that cause periodontal breakdown (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Bisson et al., 2019</xref>). It is generally observed as a mixed infection with chronic purulent or necrotic lung diseases, such as lung abscess or bronchiectasis (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Hersh, 1985</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">Treatment of trichomoniasis, for the last several decades, involves 5&#x02032;-nitroimidazoles, e.g., metronidazole, tinidazole, ornidazole, and nimorazole. Metronidazole low-dose vaginal preparations are not effective for trichomoniasis; hence high-dose vaginal suppositories are used. The male partner(s) should also be treated simultaneously, even if asymptomatic. Metronidazole or tinidazole 2&#x000a0;g orally as a single dose of metronidazole 500&#x000a0;mg orally twice daily for seven days is the treatment option. Based on the observations of a multicentre, open-label, randomized controlled trial in women positive for <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> infection, 7-days low dose metronidazole is recommended as a primary treatment (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Kissinger et al., 2018</xref>). Single-dose is less effective and is associated with side effects than the 1-week treatment, and it is preferred because of patient compliance and lower cost of therapy (<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Se&#x000f1;a et al., 2014</xref>). <italic>T. tenax</italic> is morphologically close to <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> and is sensitive to anti-parasitic treatment with tinidazole (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Kurnatowska and Kurnatowski, 1999</xref>) as <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Butt and Tirmizi, 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><label>1.2</label><title>Challenges to the effective management of trichomoniasis</title><p id="p0035">Although curable, trichomoniasis and its treatment are often challenging because of the drug's side effects. Generally, adverse effects include nausea, vomiting, constipation, cramping, and metallic taste. Other adverse effects include peripheral neuropathy, seizures, fatigue, dizziness, headache, and leukopenia (<xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">Wendel and Workowski, 2007</xref>). Additionally, trichomonas is increasingly associated with other health complications like pelvic inflammatory disease and cervical cancer. Preterm births, low birth weights, stillbirth, neonatal death, sexual transmission, and acquisition of HIV infection are strongly associated with trichomoniasis (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Hirt et al., 2011</xref>). HIV-positive women may require multiple doses of metronidazole because of changes in vaginal ecology, interference of impaired immunity with single-dose treatment, and interaction of antiretroviral drugs with metronidazole (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Kissinger and Adamski, 2013</xref>). In men's case, <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> infections are also associated with chronic prostatitis leading to aggressive prostate cancers, as observed from increased Prostate-Specific Antigen levels (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Langston et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Suitcliffe et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p id="p0040">Even though the single metronidazole therapy has a failure rate of only 10%, these figures are significant due to the large number of patients suffering from trichomoniasis. Although oral 5-nitroimidazoles such as metronidazole and tinidazole exhibit high cure rates, trichomonas infection can still be highly persistent and recurrent (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Dunne et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Se&#x000f1;a et al., 2014</xref>). One of the major reasons for this is the drug resistance to metronidazole or cross-resistance to other 5-nitroimidazoles or, in some cases, multiple drug resistance (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Dunne et al., 2003</xref>). Additionally, in certain cases, metronidazole-associated allergy may cause urticaria, facial edema, and anaphylactic shock. It may result in therapy failure as well (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Mehriardestani et al., 2017</xref>). Drug resistance to metronidazole or the whole 5-nitroimidazole family is fairly common, which eventually exposes the lack of drugs available in the armamentarium to treat trichomonas infection. Given the population density that suffers from trichomonas infection and lack of drugs, there is an urgent need to discover safe and efficacious drugs to treat trichomonosis.</p><p id="p0045">On a different but serious note, trichomonads are evolving and losing strict host specificity; <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>-like isolates from cases of epidemic avian trichomoniasis exemplify the importance to create awareness of potential human-to-bird transfer and evolution and origins of these pathogens (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Maritz et al., 2014</xref>). Cross infection of parasites between pigs and cattle has also been observed (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2017</xref>). Trichomonad parasites, which were known to infect animals, are now causing infection to humans as well. Although rare, human tritrichomoniasis caused by <italic>T. foetus</italic> has been reported as opportunistic infections in immunocompromised or immunosuppressed individuals (<xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki et al., 2016</xref>). <italic>T. foetus</italic> is also found in the stomach, caecum, and nasal cavity of pigs without apparent clinical significance (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Mueller et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0050">This report's objective was to collate the literature on activity against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> of isolated natural products and whole plant products. Several reviews have analyzed medicinal plants' efficacy and safety, their extracts, or isolated plant constituents for treating <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> infection. However, the results of systematic reviews are not consistent, and the methodological quality of systematic reviews is unknown. No overview focused on the efficacy and safety of several plant species. This study aimed to summarize the evidence from reviews and systematic reviews that evaluated the effectiveness of various plants and their isolated constituents in treating trichomonas infection and critically assessing the evidence's quality.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Review question</title><p id="p0055">This systematic review aimed to look at the evidence across the scientific literature for the efficacy of various plants to treat <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> infection.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Search strategy</title><p id="p0060">The protocol of this qualitative synthesis of the current literature is performed according to the recommendations of the PRISMA Statement [<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Moher et al., 2015</xref>] with the relative flow diagram shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. US National Library of Medicine (PubMed), ScienceDirect&#x000ae; and Scopus&#x000ae; trademark of Elsevier, Google Scholar, Wiley Interscience, Taylor, and Francis Group were searched combining the terms (&#x0201c;<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> infection&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;trichomoniasis&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;anti-trichomonal&#x0201d;) and (&#x0201c;natural treatment&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;plant therapy&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;cure&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;plant extract&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;medicinal plant&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;herb&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;herbal medicine&#x0201d;). We chose all the full-text articles published in the English language only evaluating anti- <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> medicinal plants using the keywords mentioned above. Several articles were found to end tracking citations from other publications or directly access the journals' website.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Quality assessment and article selection</title><p id="p0065">All the articles identified in the databases mentioned above were evaluated independently by two reviewers. After reviewing the titles, abstracts, and full texts of the articles, unrelated studies were excluded from the review. The remaining articles were investigated using quality assessment checklists.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Inclusion criteria</title><p id="p0070">All the study articles evaluating the <italic>in-vitro</italic> and <italic>in-vivo</italic> effects of medicinal herbs on <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>, published between 2000 and 2020.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p id="p0075">All the articles with studies shown outside the determined period and articles on parasite species other than <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Data extraction</title><p id="p0080">Essential data with the scientific name of plants, type of herbal extracts, used parts of the plants, extract concentrations, and killing or growth-inhibitory effects were obtained from the selected articles and recorded.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Search results</title><p id="p0085">At first, nine possibly relevant records were retrieved. After screening titles and abstracts, 20 records were excluded, and the remaining 79 records were considered potentially eligible for full-text screening. Lastly, 55 reviews were included in this overview (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Flow chart describing the study design process.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0090">Drugs from medicinal plants have proven to be effective, cost-effective, well-tolerated, and with fewer side effects than synthetic drugs. It has prompted scientists globally to screen medicinal plants for the effective treatment of trichomoniasis. Medicinal plants are a huge source of compounds with a diverse structural range. Some of the plants/phytopharmaceuticals are reported to possess anti-<italic>Trichomonas</italic> activity. The largest number of plants reported showing anti-<italic>Trichomonas</italic> activity belong to the <italic>Asteracea, Lamiaceae,</italic> and <italic>Myrtaceae</italic> families of plants. The majority of active phytopharmaceuticals were found to fall under the categories of terpenes, &#x003b2;-glycosides, saponins, essential oils, and alkaloids (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Mehriardestani et al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Description of included systematic reviews on isolated compounds</title><sec id="sec3.2.1"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Isolated natural product- alkaloid berberine</title><p id="p0095">Berberine is a nonbasic and quaternary benzylisoquinoline alkaloid, isolated from plants with a long history of medicinal use in the traditional medicine system.<fig id="undfig2"><alt-text id="alttext0015">Image 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx2"/></fig></p><p id="p0100">Berberine has been isolated from various plant families (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Kaneda et al., 1990</xref>; <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Neag et al., 2018</xref>), as given in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Various plant families and species containing berberine alkaloids, having the potential for antitrichomonal activity.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plant family</th><th>Genera</th><th>Examples of plant species</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Annonaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Annickia, Coelocline, Rollinia, Xylopia,</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>A. chlorantha (Oliv.) Setten and Maas, A.pilosa (Exell) Setten and Maas, R. pilocarpa Loefgr., C. polycarpa, R. mucosa (Jacq.) Baill., X. macrocarpa, X. polycarpa (DC.) Oliv.</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Berberidaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Berberis, Caulophyllum, Jeffersonia, Mahonia, Nandina, Sinopodophyllum</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>B. aristata DC., B. aquifolium Pursh, B. heterophylla Juss. ex Poir., B. beaniana C.K. Schneid., B. asiatica Roxb., B. croatica Horvat, B. thunbergii DC., B. vulgaris</italic> L.<italic>, B. pseudumbellata R. Parker</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Menispermaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Coscinium, Tinospora</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>C. fenestratum Colebr., T. cordifolia (Willd.) Miers</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Papaveraceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Argemone, Bocconia, Chelidonium, Corydalis, Eschscholzia, Glaucium, Hunnemannia, Macleaya, Papaver,</italic> and <italic>Sanguinaria</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>A. alba F. Lestib., A. Mexicana</italic> L.<italic>, A. hispidu, A. munita Durand and Hilg., B. frutescens</italic> L.<italic>, Chelidonium majus</italic> L.<italic>, Corydalis solida (L.) Clairv., Corydalis turtschaninovii Besser, E. californica Cham., G. corniculatum (L.) Rudolph, P. rhoeas</italic> L.<italic>,</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ranunculaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Coptis, Hydrastis,</italic> and <italic>Xanthorhiza</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>C. chinensis Franch., C. japonica (Thunb.) Makino, C. rhizome, H. Canadensis</italic> L.<italic>, X. simplicissima Marshall</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rutaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Evodia, Phellodendron,</italic> and <italic>Zanthoxyllum</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>E. meliaefolia, P. amurense Rupr., P. chinense C.K. Schneid., P. lavallei Dode, Z. quinduense</italic></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0105">However, the genus <italic>Berberis</italic> is the best potential berberine source (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Imenshahidi and Hosseinzadeh, 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0110">Berberine is often administered in a salt form for several clinical applications like anti-bacterial, anti-fungal, anti-inflammatory, anti-malarial, antioxidant, and analgesic activities (<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Pund et al., 2014a</xref>). Exposure of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> to berberine sulfate caused deformity in the shape of the organism. Autophagic vacuoles were formed and increased in number, leading to the plasma membrane's rupture, thus exhibiting anti-trichomonal activity (<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Kaneda et al., 1990</xref>). Berberine hydrochloride intravaginal therapy had shown significant improvement in bacterial vaginosis patients' clinical symptoms as observed from a reduction in oxidative stress in vaginal discharge and apoptosis of vaginal epithelial cells. The activities of superoxide dismutase and catalase were noted as reduced levels of malondialdehyde and hydrogen peroxide (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2019</xref>). However, the exact infection cause of vaginitis was not identified in these patients. <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Soffar et al. (2001)</xref> suggested berberine sulfate as a safe alternative to metronidazole, having comparable potency and applicability in metronidazole resistant cases.</p><p id="p0115">Considering berberine as one of the important constituents of plant <italic>Argemone mexicana</italic>, very recently, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Elizondo-Luevano et al. (2020)</xref> compared the anti-trichomonal effect of methanolic extract of leaves and stem of the plant with pristine berberine and metronidazole as a standard control. The IC<sub>50</sub> values of stem and leaf extracts of <italic>Argemone mexicana</italic> against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> were 70.8 and 67.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively. Although the values observed were not comparable to that of metronidazole, IC<sub>50</sub> 0.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, they were comparable to pure berberine of IC<sub>50</sub> 40.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.2"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Isolated natural product- polyphenol curcumin</title><p id="p0120">Curcumin is a polyphenol extracted from the Indian spice turmeric, <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>, a rhizomatous perennial plant.<fig id="undfig3"><alt-text id="alttext0020">Image 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx3"/></fig></p><p id="p0125">In Indian food, it is traditionally used for food coloring and has been investigated for its biological research outcomes over the past years (<xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Wachter et al., 2014</xref>). Its diverse therapeutic activity encompasses anti-inflammatory, anti-cancer, antioxidant, immunomodulatory action, and anti-infective (<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Pund et al., 2016</xref>). Curcumin is an effective anti-infective agent against various parasites, e.g., <italic>Giardia lamblia</italic> (<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Perez-Arriaga et al., 2006</xref>)<italic>, Eimeria tenella</italic> sporozoites (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Khalafalla et al., 2011</xref>)<italic>, Plasmodium</italic> spp. (<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Mimche and Taramelli 2011</xref>)<italic>, Cryptosporidium parvum</italic> (<xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Shahiduzzaman et al., 2009</xref>)<italic>, Leishmania amazonensis,</italic> and <italic>L. mexicana</italic> (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Koide et al., 2002</xref>)<italic>, Trypanosoma brucei</italic> (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Changtam et al., 2010</xref>)<italic>, Schistosoma mansoni</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Allam, 2009</xref>), and HIV (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Jordan and Drew 1996</xref>)<italic>.</italic> Various studies suggest the <italic>in-vitro</italic> therapeutic utility and efficacy of curcumin in trichomoniasis. <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Wacther et al. (2014)</xref> studied the effectiveness of curcumin in various concentrations against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>. The group also studied the efficacy of curcumin in metronidazole-resistant strains of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Wachter et al., 2014</xref>). Curcumin eradicated 100% <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> cells at the concentration of 400&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL in 24&#x000a0;h. The EC<sub>50</sub> ranged from 73.0 to 105.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, while the EC<sub>90</sub> from 164.9 to 216.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL. Although in comparison to metronidazole, curcumin was found to be effective at a higher concentration, curcumin is well tolerated without any side effects in contrast to metronidazole. The safety of curcumin is well established and demonstrated. However, these concentrations are very high, even to a natural compound that the authors presented without toxicity. As demonstrated by <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Cos et al. (2006)</xref>, endpoints, such as IC50, higher than 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for extract and 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M for isolated compounds, should not be considered promising.</p><p id="p0130">A systematic meta-analysis was carried out to study the safety of curcumin (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Chainani, 2003</xref>). This meta-analysis included various research articles, book chapters, <italic>in-vitro</italic> studies, human trials from 1966 to 2003. The metanalysis reported that curcumin is a well-tolerated compound and is safe in at least six human clinical trials. Moreover, curcumin can be administered topically, which will further reduce the likelihood of side effects associated with metronidazole's oral administration. Thus, curcumin holds a promise as a potential anti-trichomoniasis candidate of plant origin. However, the poor aqueous solubility of curcumin limits its widespread therapeutic utilization. To overcome the poor aqueous solubility (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Carapina da Silva et al., 2019</xref>) synthesized 21 monocarbonyl analogs of curcumin that possessed anti-protozoal activity. Out of these 21 compounds, three derivates, 1,5-diphenylpenta-1,4-dien-3-one, 1,5-bis(2-chlorophenyl) penta-1,4-dien-3-one, and 2,6-bis(2-chlorobenzylidene) cyclohexanone, were found to have comparable anti-trichomoniasis activity as that of metronidazole. All the three derivates eradicated <italic>T. vaginalis in vitro</italic>. Additionally, 1,5-bis(2-chlorophenyl) penta-1,4-dien-3-one was found to have higher selectivity as well (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Carapina da Silva et al., 2019</xref>). However, two reports suggest a contradictory effect of curcumin on <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Muelas-Serrano et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Raether and Seidenath, 1984</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.3"><label>3.2.3</label><title>Isolated natural product &#x02013; polyphenol resveratrol</title><p id="p0135">Resveratrol is a dietary non-flavonoid polyphenolic phytoalexin, present in grapes' skin and exhibits a broad range of biological activities that potentially underlie its antioxidant anti-inflammatory, and anti-carcinogenic efficacy (<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Pund et al., 2014b</xref>).<fig id="undfig4"><alt-text id="alttext0025">Image 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx4"/></fig></p><p id="p0140">In a mechanistic study, <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Mallo et al. (2013)</xref> explored the <italic>in-vitro</italic> antitrichomonal effect and mechanism of action of resveratrol on <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> trophozoites. At concentrations between 25 and 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, resveratrol inhibited the growth of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> trophozoites. The lower dose of 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M exerted a cytostatic effect, whereas higher doses exerted killing effects. Resveratrol, at a high dose, upregulated gene expression of the hydrogenosomal enzyme pyruvate-ferredoxin oxidoreductase. At doses lower than 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M but more than 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, overexpression of heat shock protein 70, a protective protein found in the hydrogenosome of <italic>T. vaginalis,</italic> was observed. The results demonstrated that resveratrol exerts its deleterious effects as anti-trichomonas via hydrogenosomal dysfunction and metabolic alteration (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Mallo et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.4"><label>3.2.4</label><title>Isolated natural product- anthraquinone emodin</title><p id="p0145">Emodin, a derived anthraquinone, is extracted from roots and barks of various plants like <italic>Rheum palmatum, Aloe vera, Polygonum multiflorum,</italic> and <italic>Polygonum cuspidatum.</italic> Emodin shows fundamental therapeutic properties, such as antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anti-bacterial, and anti-viral (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2020</xref>).<fig id="undfig5"><alt-text id="alttext0030">Image 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx5"/></fig></p><p id="p0150"><xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (1993)</xref> studied <italic>in-vivo</italic> efficacy of emodin in two types of experimental infections, namely that caused by subcutaneous injection of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> in BALB/c mice and the one due to intravaginal inoculation of the parasites in mice. The appearance of subcutaneous abscess induced by injection of trichomonads was delayed by emodin treatment. An oral administration also cured the trichomonal abscesses, indicating good absorption of emodin anthraquinone. Oral treatment with emodin significantly decreased the number of trichomonads in the vagina as well. This activity's criteria were determined according to living trichomonads in isolated vagina obtained from the treated mice.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.5"><label>3.2.5</label><title>Isolated natural product-flavonoid quercetin and quercitrin</title><p id="p0155"><fig id="undfig6"><alt-text id="alttext0035">Image 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx6"/></fig><fig id="undfig7"><alt-text id="alttext0040">Image 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx7"/></fig></p><p id="p0160"><xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Omisore et al. (2005)</xref> studied the anti-trichomonas activity of <italic>Dorstenia barteri</italic>, and <italic>Dorstenia convexa</italic> extracts, and some isolated components from <italic>D. barteri</italic> against <italic>T. gallinarum</italic> and compared with quercetin and quercitrin. Quercetin was found to be most potent, followed by quercitrin. Minimum lethal concentrations were found to be 0.121., 0.244, 0.244, 0.73, and 0.98&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL for quercetin, quercitrin, bartericin B, bartericin A, and stigmasterol, respectively, and for 6,8-diprenyleridictyol, isobavachalcone, and dorsmanin F, similar activity was noted i.e., 31.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL. In the same study, researchers studied minimum lethal concentrations for the extract of leaves and twigs of both the <italic>Dorstenia</italic> species. Extracts were prepared using a 1:1 organic solvent mixture of dichloromethane and methanol. At 24&#x000a0;h exposure, minimum lethal concentrations were found to be 15.625 and 15.625 &#x003bc;/mL for extracts of leaves and twig of <italic>D. barteri,</italic> whereas leaf and twig extract of <italic>D. convexa</italic> exhibited much higher minimum lethal concentrations as 125 and 437.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively.</p><p id="p0165"><xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Naemi et al. (2014)</xref> have reported anti-trichomonas activity of the plant <italic>Rheum ribes</italic> L. extracts<italic>,</italic> which contains quercetin, and derivatives of quercetin like 5-desoxyquercetin, quercetin 3-<italic>O</italic>-rhamnoside, quercetin 3-<italic>O</italic>-galactoside, and quercetin 3-<italic>O</italic>-rutinoside. Aqueous and organic extracts of flowers, leaves, and stem showed <italic>in-vitro</italic> antitrichomonal activity against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at a 125&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL concentration.</p><p id="p0170"><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Brandelli et al. (2013)</xref> showed remarkable anti-trichomonas activity of ten different plants traditionally used by the Mby&#x000e1;-Guarani indigenous group in Brazil. Researchers studied extracts of leaves of <italic>Aloe arborescens</italic> Mill., aerial parts of <italic>Bidens pilosa</italic> L., aerial parts of <italic>Rhipsalis baccifera</italic> (Sol.) Stearn, barks of <italic>Luehea divaricate</italic> Mart<italic>.</italic>, roots of <italic>Trichilia</italic> sp., leaves of <italic>Campomanesia xanthocarpa</italic> Mart. ex O. Berg, leaves of <italic>Coix lacryma-jobi</italic> Lin., leaves of <italic>Citrus limonium</italic>, leaves of <italic>Citrus reticulate</italic> Blanco, and <italic>Verbena</italic> sp leaves. The anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity was attributed to flavonoids, namely quercetin, quercitrin, myricetin, and rutin.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.6"><label>3.2.6</label><title>Isolated natural product- alkaloid lycorine</title><p id="p0175">Lycorine is the most common Amaryllidaceae phenanthridine ring-type alkaloid present in Amaryllidaceae family plants and has been considered a promising anti-proliferative agent.<fig id="undfig8"><alt-text id="alttext0045">Image 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx8"/></fig></p><p id="p0180">This natural alkaloid has immense therapeutic potential as it has shown high specificity in a very low concentration against several cancers both <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> and against various drug-resistant cancer cells (<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Roy et al., 2018</xref>). Recently, lycorine showed anti-viral activity against the Zika virus <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>). <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Giordani et al. (2011)</xref> studied the cytotoxicity of lycorine against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> covering a very broad range of concentrations from 2.5 to 1000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M. Cell cycle analysis and observations of ultrastructural alterations in the parasitic cell were analyzed by flow cytometry and transmission electron microscopy, respectively, after treatment with 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M lycorine for 6 and 24&#x000a0;h. Significant changes occurred, including disruption in the trophozoite's original shape and a few depressions on its surface. Although apoptotic blebs were not seen, the nucleus looked abnormal in shape, e.g., elongated or split. Several cytoplasmic vacuoles resembling an autophagic process were observed. Randomly spread hydrogenosomes were also seen within the parasite cells. Fragments of the endoplasmic reticulum were seen in close contact with abnormal hydrogenosomes, indicative of autophagy. Lycorine arrested the T. vaginalis cell cycle at the G2/M phase of the cell cycle, although no apoptosis hallmarks, such as apoptotic bodies, were observed. Consequently, the underlying mechanism of action fails to fulfill the criteria for apoptosis completely. However, some similarities to paraptotic cell death were observed (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Giordani et al., 2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.7"><label>3.2.7</label><title>Isolated natural product alkaloid candimine</title><p id="p0185">Candimine, an alkaloid from the bulbs of <italic>Hippeastrum morelianum</italic>, was found to be cytotoxic for the parasite <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Giordani et al., 2010a</xref>). An ultrastructural study of the parasite in the presence of candimine revealed striking morphological alterations, although the cell membrane remained intact in all parasites observed. After treatment with 1 for 6 and 24&#x000a0;h, modifications in size, shape, and intracellular localization of hydrogenosomes. The hydrogenosomes presented signs of autophagy. Besides, candimine caused arrest of the <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> cell cycle, altered morphologic and ultrastructural features, but did not induce the formation of apoptotic bodies, left the cell membrane intact, and did not cause exposure of phosphatidylserine residues nor DNA fragmentation. Thus, candimine-induced cell death in <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> fails to fulfill apoptosis criteria and instead exhibits features like paraptosis.</p><p id="p0190">The same group (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Giordani et al., 2010b</xref>) studied the effects of both lycorine and candimine alkaloids on the <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> NTPDase and ecto-5&#x02032;-nucleotidase activities. When both alkaloids were added directly to the reaction mixture, no effect on ATP, ADP, or AMP hydrolysis could be observed. In contrast, <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> NTPDase, and ecto-5&#x02032;-nucleotidase activities were significantly inhibited by candimine and lycorine after 24&#x000a0;h treatment. Expressive inhibition by lycorine and candimine on this enzymatic cascade in <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> modulates the extracellular ATP and adenosine levels. The accumulation of extracellular nucleotides, mainly the cytotoxic and proinflammatory ATP due to alkaloids inhibition, plus the ATP originated from host cells, associated to reduced concentrations of the immune-modulatory adenosine, might contribute to an increased susceptibility of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> to host immune response in the presence of lycorine and candimine (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Giordani et al., 2010b</xref>). The fact that ecto-nucleotidases have an external location are implicated in parasite survival and are widely distributed among different eukaryotic human pathogens make them interesting targets for the development of antimicrobial agents. This study claimed a new pharmacological potential of two Amaryllidaceae alkaloids, lycorine, and candimine against <italic>T. vaginalis.</italic></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.8"><label>3.2.8</label><title>Isolated natural product- monoterpenoid geraniol</title><p id="p0195"><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Dai et al. (2016)</xref> studied the essential oil of <italic>Amomum tsao-ko</italic> Crevost and Lemari&#x000e9;, which belongs to the family Zingiberaceae, and its primary constituent geraniol, for anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity.<fig id="undfig9"><alt-text id="alttext0050">Image 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="fx9"/></fig></p><p id="p0200">It is a spice used in Chinese cuisine and is also part of the Chinese Traditional Medicine. <italic>A. tsai-ko</italic> is effective for the treatment of stomach disorders and throat infection (and exhibits a wide range of biological activities, such as antimicrobial, antioxidant, and cytotoxic activities, as well as lipid-lowering effects). Geraniol is a widely used fragrance ingredient and is the main component of <italic>A. tsao-ko</italic> essential oil, constituting approximately 14%. Geraniol has antimicrobial activity, insecticidal, and antitumor activity (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2011</xref>). Both <italic>A. tsao-ko</italic> essential oil and geraniol showed <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-<italic>T. vaginalis</italic> activity against two different parasite isolates. <italic>A. tsao-ko</italic> essential oil was found to be 4-8-fold more effective than that of geraniol; however, it was 10-fold less active than metronidazole, 20-fold less than ornidazole. <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Dai et al. (2016)</xref> further explored the mechanism of activity of <italic>A. tsao-ko</italic> essential oil and geraniol against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> using direct visualization with transmission electron microscopy. Several morphological changes were observed in the treated cells, such as many vacuoles, disappearance of ribosomes, dilation of rough endoplasmic reticulum, and dissolving nuclei. The leakage of cytoplasmic contents was also observed.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.9"><label>3.2.9</label><title>Isolated plant compounds- &#x003b2;-glycosides</title><p id="p0205"><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Arthan et al. (2008)</xref> isolated various &#x003b2;-glucosides and their corresponding aglycone part from various Thai plants (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>&#x003b2;-Glucosides and their corresponding aglycone part from various Thai plants isolated for anti-trichomonas activity (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Arthan et al., 2008</xref>).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plant and part of the plant</th><th>&#x003b2;-glucosides</th><th>Aglycone</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Thai rosewood seeds</td><td align="left">dalcochinin-8&#x02032;-<italic>O</italic>-&#x003b2;-D-glucoside</td><td align="left">Dalcochinin</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Solanum torvum</italic> Sw. fruits</td><td align="left">torvoside A,<break/>torvoside H</td><td align="left">26-degluco-torvoside A 26-degluco-torvoside H</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Plumeria obtusa</italic><break/>L. flowers</td><td align="left">Plumieride coumarate glucoside</td><td align="left">13-<italic>O</italic>-coumarylplumieride aglycone</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Gonocaryum subrostratum</italic><break/>Pierre leaves</td><td align="left">Gonocaryoside A, kingiside</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ligustrum confusum</italic> Decne. leaves</td><td align="left">Ligustaloside A</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0210">Among these 11 compounds tested, kingiside, gonocaryoside A, plumieride coumarate glucoside, and torvoside A were the most potent anti-trichomonal with MIC of 6.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M. Although these compounds were 125-fold less effective than metronidazole (MIC 0.05&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M), they were found to be safe and not toxic on Vero, KB, and MCF-7&#x000a0;cell lines at the concentrations tested.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.10"><label>3.2.10</label><title>Isolated plant product- diterpenoids and triterpenoids</title><p id="p0215"><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Loyola et al. (2001)</xref> isolated diterpenoids, namely 9,12-cyclomulin-13-ol or 13&#x003b2;-hydroxyazorellane,13&#x003b1;-hydroxyazorellane, azorellanol, mulinolic acid, and mulin-11,13-dien-20-oic acid from the aerial parts of <italic>Azorella yareta</italic> Hauman. All the compounds showed anti-trichomonal activity <italic>in vitro</italic>; however, it was very low, as observed from very high LC<sub>50</sub> values, 40&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;120&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, which is almost ten times higher than of metronidazole (LC<sub>50</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M).</p><p id="p0220">Betulinic acid and ursolic acid were isolated from barks of <italic>Platanus acerifolia</italic>, and <italic>Malus domestica</italic> peels, respectively (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Innocente et al., 2014</xref>), and semisynthetic derivatives of both were prepared. Compounds obtained from betulinic acid presented better activity than those from ursolic acid. Piperazine derivatized from betulinic acid presented a minimum inhibitory concentration of 91.2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, revealing these compounds' high potential as trichomonacidal agents.</p><p id="p0225">A pentacyclic triterpenoid, hederagenin isolated from <italic>Cussonia holstii</italic> is a traditional African medicinal product that was found to display antitrichomonal activity with an IC<sub>50</sub> of 2.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2003</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.11"><label>3.2.11</label><title>Isolated plant product- saponins</title><p id="p0230"><xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Rocha et al. (2012)</xref> successfully demonstrated saponins' activity from <italic>Quillaja</italic>, <italic>Passiflora</italic>, and <italic>Ilex</italic> species on <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>. Saponins were extracted from the leaves of <italic>Passiflora alata</italic> Curtis (passion fruit), <italic>Quillaja brasiliensis</italic> Mart. (soap tree), and <italic>Ilex paraguariensis</italic> A. St.-Hil. (mat&#x000e9;).</p><p id="p0235">Saponins from <italic>Sapindus mukorossi</italic> showed anti-<italic>Trichomonas</italic> activity at a 10-fold lower concentration than required for effective spermicidal activity against human spermatozoa, thus suggesting the potential of these saponins for the development of a safe spermicidal and microbicide for human use (<xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Tiwari et al., 2008</xref>). <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Jain et al. (2014)</xref> combined a synthetic spermicide with a natural saponin trichomonacide for safe, prophylactic contraception. This study's anti-trichomonal saponins were a fully standardized mixture of six sapindosides (sapindosides A, B, C, D, and mukurozisaponins E1 and Y1), with sapindoside B as the major constituent. They were isolated from the fruit pericarp of <italic>Sapindus mukorossi</italic> Gaerth (family Sapindaceae) by <italic>n</italic>-butanol extraction of its ethanolic extract. The combination of saponin with synthetic spermicide resulted in lowering the anti-trichomonal MIC of synthetic spermicide from 285&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL to 32.8285&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL.</p><p id="p0240"><xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Damke et al. (2013)</xref> evaluated the anti-trichomonas activity of a purified sample of saponins and hydroalcoholic and butanolic extract of dried pericarps of <italic>Sapindus fruits saponaria.</italic> MIC for saponins was four-fold less than for hydroalcoholic extract and two-fold less than butanolic extract.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2.12"><label>3.2.12</label><title>Aromatic plant extracts and essential oils</title><p id="p0245">Essential oils are the natural, volatile, aromatic, complex secondary metabolites produced in aromatic plants and are characterized by strong aroma (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bakkali et al., 2008</xref>). Such aromatic plants generally grow in warm and tropical countries. Essential oils are known to possess medicinal properties, e.g., virucidal, fungicidal, antiseptic, and bactericidal. Some of the essential oils like those from <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> (peppermint), <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Yousefi et al., 2013</xref>) <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Mahboubi, 2018</xref>), and <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> (lavender) (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Moon et al., 2006</xref>) possess anti-trichomonal properties. All four belong to the aromatic plants of the Lamiaceae or Labiatae family. Hydro-alcoholic extracts of <italic>M. piperita</italic> and <italic>S. officinalis</italic> were found to have anti-trichomonal activity comparable to metronidazole. However, <italic>S. officinalis</italic> was found to have higher potency than <italic>M. piperita</italic> (<xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Yousefi et al., 2013</xref>). From the same family, <italic>Mentha crispa</italic> has been evaluated for its efficacy as anti-trichomonal activity in a clinical trial (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Moraes et al., 2012</xref>). In a randomized, double-blind, and controlled clinical trial, 60 female patients were administered orally with 90% of the patients administered with <italic>M. crispa</italic> was found to have recovered from trichomoniasis while 96.6% recovered using secnidazole [statistically not significantly different (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.6120)]. However, the secnidazole group's adverse events were statistically significantly higher than the <italic>M. crispa</italic> group (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0006). <italic>Mentha crispa</italic> exhibited comparable therapeutic efficacy as that of secnidazole with significantly lower side effects (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Moraes et al., 2012</xref>). In another <italic>in-vitro</italic> study, the efficiency of <italic>Mentha longifolia</italic> extract was compared with that of aqueous extract of <italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> against a clinical strain of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Niyyati et al., 2015</xref>). Aqueous extract of <italic>Mentha longifolia</italic> reduced the number of live <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> in a time- and concentration-dependent manner and exhibited a MIC of 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL and 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL at the end of 24&#x000a0;h and 48&#x000a0;h, respectively. In contrast, an extract of <italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> inhibited only 73.7% and 86.9% of live parasites at a 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL concentration at the end of 24&#x000a0;h and 48&#x000a0;h, respectively. <italic>Mentha longifolia</italic> extract seems to possess higher potency towards <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> than <italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Niyyati et al., 2015</xref>). Further, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Aslani et al. (2019)</xref> evaluated a vaginal cream for anti-trichomonal activity containing a combination of <italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic>, <italic>Viola odorata,</italic> and <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> extracts. A cream preparation containing 2.5&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic>, 0.06&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>V. odorata</italic>, and 1&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>M. piperita</italic> was found to inhibit 100% growth of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at the end of 24&#x000a0;h. <italic>Z. multiflora</italic> is another flowering plant of the Lamiaceae family that has been reported to possess anti-trichomonal properties. <italic>Z. multiflora</italic> contains oxygenated sesquiterpenes (1.6&#x02013;5.7%), monoterpene hydrocarbons (3.6&#x02013;24.5%), thymol, carvacrol and linalool, and <italic>p</italic>-cymene (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Mahboubi, 2018</xref>). <italic>Z. multiflora</italic> essential oil at a concentration of 0.1&#x02013;0.0004% was found to inhibit clinical isolates of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at 1&#x000a0;h (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Abdollahy et al., 2004</xref>). Efficiency of <italic>Z. multiflora</italic> vaginal cream, 0.1%, as compared with metronidazole in 54 non-pregnant women. 88.9% of patients were treated in the metronidazole group than 51.9% of the <italic>Z. multiflora</italic> group. A group of 48.1% of patients treated with metronidazole showed adverse effects compared to none of the patients treated with <italic>Z. multiflora</italic>. The authors concluded that though the clinical success was low in <italic>Z. multiflora-</italic>treated patients, still the patients of this group exhibited greater improvement in clinical symptoms (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abdali et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0250">Essential oils from <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> and <italic>Lavandula intermedia</italic> were evaluated for their anti-trichomonal properties (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Moon et al., 2006</xref>). It was found that both the lavender essential oils can eradicate <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>, even at a concentration below 1% (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Moon et al., 2006</xref>).</p><p id="p0255">Black seed or black cumin or <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L., which belongs to the Ranunculaceae, has a widespread culinary and traditional medicinal usage in the Mediterranean and Indian subcontinent. <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> L. seeds have been reported to possess antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, anti-fungal, anti-infective, and anti-parasitic properties. The effect of aqueous extract of <italic>N. sativa</italic> was compared with metronidazole on the growth and motility of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Tonkal, 2009</xref>). Aqueous extract of <italic>N. sativa</italic> was found to possess a remarkable effect on the growth of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>. To further elucidate the mechanism and understand the effect of fatty acids of <italic>N. sativa,</italic>
<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud et al. (2016)</xref> undertook a study to compare the efficacy of <italic>N. sativa</italic> oil, aqueous extract, and alcoholic extract of <italic>N. sativa</italic> on <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>. It was found that <italic>N. sativa</italic> oil at a concentration of 2&#x000a0;mg/mL, and alcoholic extract at a concentration of 10&#x000a0;mg/mL, exhibited similar activity as that of metronidazole (50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL) after 24&#x000a0;h. The aqueous extract was found to have less effect on <italic>T. vaginalis.</italic> This difference in the activity was attributed to the fatty acids present in <italic>N. sativa</italic> oil and those extracted in the alcoholic extract of <italic>N. sativa</italic>. The lowest anti-trichomonal activity of aqueous extract of <italic>N. sativa</italic> was ascribed to the absence of major fatty acids, viz., oleic acid, and linoleic acid, in the aqueous extract. Remarkably, the fatty acids tridecanoic acid and palmitoleic acid were found only in the oil of <italic>N. sativa.</italic> The authors proposed a possible mechanism of action that suggests the cell membrane of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> as the main target. It is presumed that fatty acids in the oil and alcoholic extract may interact with the cell membranes, resulting in transient or permanent variable size pores. This formation of pores results in leakage, reduced nutrient uptake, or cellular respiration inhibition in <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud et al., 2016</xref>). Thus, oil and alcoholic extract of <italic>N. sativa</italic> are potentially bioactive against <italic>T. vaginalis.</italic></p><p id="p0260">Rosemary, an age-old globally used herb known to strengthen brain and memory activity, was found to possess antitrichomonal activity when the extract, rather than an essential oil, was used (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Saeidi et al., 2019</xref>). Rosemary essential oil essentially contains camphor, 1,8-cineole, verbenone, borneol, and &#x003b1;-pinene. In the same line, essential oil from <italic>Artemisia sieberi</italic> was effective both <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> in an infected pigeon model against <italic>Trichomonas gallinae</italic> (<xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Youssefi et al., 2017</xref>). <italic>Pistacia lentiscus mastic</italic> and <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> oil are known for their anti-bacterial, anti-fungal, anti-viral, and anti-protozoal effects were compared for anti-trichomonal activity (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Ezz Eldin and Badawy, 2015</xref>). Amongst the two, <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> oil was found to be more potent as compared to <italic>Pistacia lentiscus mastic</italic> oil. The minimum lethal dose of the <italic>Pistacia lentiscus mastic</italic> oil was found to be 15&#x000a0;mg/mL after 24&#x000a0;h incubation, 10&#x000a0;mg/mL after 48&#x000a0;h, and 5&#x000a0;mg/mL after 96&#x000a0;h, while the minimal lethal concentration of <italic>O. basilicum oil</italic> was 30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL after 24&#x000a0;h incubation, 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL after 48&#x000a0;h and 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL after 96&#x000a0;h. The essential oils disrupt the cellular membrane or cause extensive vacuolization of cytoplasm, resulting in eradicating the parasite <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Mehriardestani et al., 2017</xref>). These essential oils need to be screened and clinically evaluated further for their anti-trichomonal activity. <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">van Vuuren and Naidoo (2010)</xref> also tested essential oils from <italic>Croton gratissimus</italic> and <italic>Tarchonanthus</italic>. However, they were found to be ineffective against <italic>T vaginalis.</italic></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Extracts of the whole plant or plant parts</title><sec id="sec3.3.1"><label>3.3.1</label><title>Eucalyptus</title><p id="p0265">One such plant that has been found to possess potential anti-trichomonas activity is <italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic>; growth-inhibitory activity against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> has been reported for the extract of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Mehriardestani et al., 2017</xref>). <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> or the River Red Gun tree belongs to the genus <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> and family Myrtaceae. <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> trees are well known for their adaptability and ability to grow fast. Consequently, <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> is one of the widely grown plants globally. Of the 800 species in the <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> genus, <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> is one the most grown. Being a native of Australia and Tasmania, <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> is a widely used medicinal plant in Aboriginal society and Australia's traditional medicinal system (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aleksic Sabo and Knezevic, 2019</xref>). The medicinal application of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> ranges from treating gastrointestinal disorders, e.g., diarrhea, colic, and dysentery, to respiratory diseases such as colds, coughs, laryngitis, and sore throat (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aleksic Sabo and Knezevic, 2019</xref>). It has also been traditionally used to arrest bleeding and joint pain. However, it is used as a folk medicine globally. Smoked leaves of <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> are used to alleviate respiratory issues in Sudan, while its decoction is used for treating coughs and colds in Zimbabwe. Nigerian people use its stem for oral hygiene. The medicinal properties of <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> are attributed to its chemical constituents. <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> is rich in essential oils ~0.4%, primarily 1,8-cineole (~77%). Other major constituents are cuminal, phellandrene, aromadendrene (or aromadendral), valerylaldehyde, geraniol, cymene, and phellandral. The leaves also contain a considerable quantity of tannins (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Ghasemian et al., 2019</xref>). <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> has been proven to possess a diverse range of medicinal properties such as anti-bacterial, anti-fungal, anti-viral, and anti-protozoal. The first reported anti-trichomonas activity of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> was by Mahdi and co-workers (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Mahdi et al., 2006</xref>). This group reported that an aqueous extract of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> leaves (at a concentration of 500&#x000a0;mg/mL) at pH 5.35 resulted in eradicating <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at the end of 24&#x000a0;h (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Mahdi et al., 2006</xref>). Later, a couple of other groups further confirmed this finding in independent research. <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Hassani et al. (2013)</xref> evaluated five different types of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> extract on <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Hassani et al., 2013</xref>). The group evaluated total extract, diethyl ether, chloroform, ethyl acetate, and water fractions of <italic>E. camaldulensis in vitro.</italic> The growth-inhibitory activity was found with all the extracts. The potency of all the extracts for the growth inhibition of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> can be ranked as ethyl acetate extract&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;crude extract&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;diethyl ether extract&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;water extract. Ethyl acetate extract exhibited 100% growth inhibition of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at a concentration of 12.5&#x000a0;mg/mL at the end of 24&#x000a0;h, while the water extract exhibited 80% growth inhibition at a concentration of 50&#x000a0;mg/mL at the end of 24&#x000a0;h (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Hassani et al., 2013</xref>). Around the same time, the findings of another group further strengthened these results. <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Youse et al. (2012)</xref> compared alcoholic and water extracts of <italic>Echinophora platyloba, Stachys lavandulifolia</italic>, and <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> for <italic>in-vitro</italic> activity against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (<xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Youse et al., 2012</xref>)<italic>.</italic> Out of the three plant extracts, only the extracts of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> exhibited <italic>in-vitro</italic> activity against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>. Based on these findings, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Aslani et al. (2019)</xref> developed a vaginal cream containing extract of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> along with extract of <italic>Viola odorata</italic> and <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Aslani et al., 2019</xref>). A cream formulation containing 2.5&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic>, 0.06&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>V. odorata</italic>, and 1&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>M. piperita</italic> was found to inhibit 100% growth of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at the end of 24&#x000a0;h<italic>.</italic> While the formulation containing 1.25&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic>, 0.03&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>V. odorata</italic>, and 0.5&#x000a0;mg/mL of <italic>M. piperita</italic> exhibited only 92% of growth inhibition at the end (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Ghasemian et al., 2019</xref>) of 24&#x000a0;h.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3.2"><label>3.3.2</label><title>American plants</title><p id="p0270">In a very exhaustive experiment, <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Muelas-Serrano et al. (2000)</xref> systematically explored the anti-trichomonas activity of various aqueous and organic extracts of different parts of more than 40 South American plants belonging to 20 different families known for their immunomodulatory, anti-inflammatory, and anti-protozoal effects (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Cytocidal and cytostatic activities against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> strain JH31A no. 4 were evaluated concerning control cultures. <italic>Mikania cordifolia</italic> (Linnaeus f.) Willdenow and <italic>Neurolaena lobata</italic> (L.) R. Br. from the Asteraceae and <italic>Scutia buxifolia</italic> Reiss from the Ramnaceae were the most active extracts amongst all the plants examined.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Various Central and South American plants and their extracts assayed for <italic>in vitro</italic> anti-trichomonas activity by <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Muelas-Serrano et al. (2000)</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0075">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plant family</th><th>Name of the plant, part of the plant used, and type of extract</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Acanthaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Ruellia tuberosa</italic> L., Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Annonaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Annona reticulata</italic> L. Leaf Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Annona reticulala</italic> L. Seed Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Rollinia emarginata</italic> Schlecht Aerial parts Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Araceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Philodendron bipinnatifidum</italic> Schott. Aerial parts, Aqueous, Methanolic, Methanol-insol., Butanolic, and Butanol-insol.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Asteraceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Baccharis trimera</italic> (Less.) DC. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Mikania cordifolia</italic> (L.) Willd. Leaf, Aqueous, Methanol-insol., Methanolic, Butanolic, Butanol-insol.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Neurolaena lobata</italic> (L.) R. Br. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tagetes lucida</italic> Cav. Aerial parts, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tithonia diversifolia</italic> Hemsl. Gray. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tridax procumbens</italic> L. Aerial parts, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Bignoniaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Crescentia cujete</italic> L. Fruit, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Jacaranda mimosifolia</italic> D. Don. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Tecoma stans</italic> HBK Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Bursera simarouba</italic> (l.) Sarg. Bark, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caprifoliaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Sambucus mexicana</italic> Presl. ex A. DC Aerial parts, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Euphorbiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Croton guatemalensis</italic> Losty. Bark, Aqueous, Methanol-insol., Methanolic, Butanolic, Butanol-insol.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hydrophyllaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Wigandia caracassana</italic> HBK Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Leguminosae</td><td align="left"><italic>Cassia occidentalis</italic> L. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Erythrina crista-galli</italic> L. Leaf, and Bark, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Gliricidia sepium</italic> (Jacq.) Steud. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Mimosa tenuiflora</italic> (Willd.) Poiret Bark, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Prosopis affinis</italic> Griseb. Bark, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lythraceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Heimia salicifolia</italic> Link and Otto Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Malpighiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Byrsonima crassifolia</italic> (L.) HBK Bark, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Moraceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Cecropia obtusifolia</italic> Bertolini Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Cecropia pachystachya</italic> Mart. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Myrtaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Psidium guajava</italic> L. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Phlebodium aureum</italic> (L.) John Smith Rhizome, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Polypodiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Pontederiaceae Eichornia</italic> crassipes (Martius) Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ramnaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Scutia buxifolia</italic> Reiss. Bark, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Sapindaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Allophylus edulis</italic> (St. Hil.) Radlk. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Chrysophyllum cainito</italic> L. Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Manilkara achras</italic> (Mill.) Fosberg Bark, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Smilacaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Smilax lundellii</italic> Killip and Morton Root, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Solanaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Brunfelsia australis</italic> Benth. Root, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Nicotiana glauca</italic> Graham Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Solanum</italic> nigrecens Mart. And Gal Leaf, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Solanum pylcomayense Morong. Aerial parts, Aqueous</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sterculiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Chiranthodendron pentdactilon</italic> Larr. Fruit Aqueous, Methanol-insol., Methanolic, Butanolic, Butanol-insol.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zingiberaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. Rhizome, Aqueous</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0275">The Brazilian Caatinga is a tropical semiarid vegetation biome with a climate characterized by elevated temperatures and reduced precipitation. <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Frasson et al. (2012)</xref> studied the anti-trichomonas activity of 44 aqueous extracts of 23 Brazilian plants belonging to 14 different families used in folk medicine found in the Caatinga desert (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Plant species from the Brazilian Caatinga region and part of the plant used for screening anti-trichomonas activity by <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Frasson et al. (2012)</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0080">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Family</th><th>Name of the plant</th><th>Part of the plant used for testing</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Anacardiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Myracrodruon urundeuva</italic> Alem&#x000e3;o</td><td align="left">Branch, bark, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Apocynaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Allamanda blanchetii</italic> A.DC.</td><td align="left">Branch, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Burseraceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Commiphora leptophloeos</italic> (Mart.) J.B. Gillett</td><td align="left">Branch, bark</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cactaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Melocactus zehntneri</italic> (Britton and Rose) Luetzelb.</td><td align="left">Leaf, root</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Combretaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Buchenavia tetraphylla</italic> (Aubl.)</td><td align="left">Leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Euphorbiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Jatropha mutabilis</italic> (Pohl)</td><td align="left">Branch, root</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Fabaceae-Caes</td><td align="left"><italic>Chamaecrista desvauxii</italic> (Collad.) Killip</td><td align="left">Branch, fruit, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Libidibia ferrea</italic> (Mart.ex Tul.)</td><td align="left">Fruit, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Parkinsonia aculeata</italic> L</td><td align="left">Leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Senna macranthera</italic> (Collad.)</td><td align="left">Fruit</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Senna splendida</italic> (Vogel.)</td><td align="left">Branch</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fabaceae-Mim</td><td align="left"><italic>Anadenanthera colubrina</italic> (Vell.)</td><td align="left">Branch, bark, fruit, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Piptadenia viridiflora</italic> (Kunth)</td><td align="left">Branch, fruit</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Pityrocarpa moniliformis</italic> (Benth.)</td><td align="left">Leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fabaceae-Pap</td><td align="left"><italic>Bauhinia acuruana</italic> Moric.</td><td align="left">Branch, fruit, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Dioclea grandiflora</italic> Mart. ex Benth</td><td align="left">Branch, fruit, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Myroxylon peruiferum</italic> L.f. B&#x000e1;lsamo</td><td align="left">Leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Malpighiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Stigmaphyllon paralias</italic> A. Juss</td><td align="left">Leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Malvaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Sida galheirensis</italic> Ulbr. Malva-veludo</td><td align="left">Branch, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Myrtaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Eugenia brejoensis</italic></td><td align="left">Leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ochnaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Ouratea blanchetiana</italic> Engl.</td><td align="left">Branch, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Polygalaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Polygala boliviensis</italic></td><td align="left">Branch, inflorescence, leaf</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Polygala decumbens</italic> Aubl.</td><td align="left">Root</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0280">Only the extract of roots of <italic>Polygala decumbens</italic> showed a significant effect on the viability of trophozoites. The extract was active against metronidazole-resistant species with MIC 1560 &#x003bc;g/mL.</p><p id="p0285">Recently, <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al. (2020)</xref> studied various extracts of fruits of <italic>Poincianella</italic> (<italic>Caesalpinia</italic>) <italic>microphylla,</italic> a plant found in Brazilian Caatinga. The crude aqueous extract was successively extracted with different ratios of the water-methanol mixture. The main compounds identified were hydrolyzable tannins like gallotanins and ellagitannis. Procyanidin dimer, epicatechin, ellagic acid, and <italic>O</italic>-(digalloyl) quinic acid were also identified. Tannins enriched fractions presented anti-trichomonas activity.</p><p id="p0290">Beas of <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L., (Perla black bean) a staple food in many Latin American countries, are largely consumed because of their high protein content. IC<sub>50</sub> of acidified water and acetic acid extract of perla black bean for <italic>in-vitro</italic> antitrichomonal activity against <italic>T. vaginalis was</italic> 176.8 and 378.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively, showing the potential of this plant (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Lara-D&#x000ed;az et al., 2009</xref>). <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic>, a European plant, is now naturally adapted to dry summer climates and is now cultivated as an ornamental plant in California and North America's west coast. Ethyl acetate extract of <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> leaves was an effective anti-trichomonacidal with 100% growth inhibition of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Ertabaklar et al., 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3.3"><label>3.3.3</label><title>Mexican plants</title><p id="p0295">In a search for new chemotherapeutic agents for trichomoniasis, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Calzada et al. (2007)</xref> screened crude methanolic extracts of 22 Mexican medicinal plants commonly used for abdominal pain, colic, and vaginal discharge for antitrichomonal activity against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>. In all, 22 plants belonging to 15 different families were assayed. The details of the plants and important experimental findings are shown in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>IC<sub>50</sub> values of various plants methanolic extracts along with their families analyzed by <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Calzada et al. (2007)</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0085">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Plant family</th><th>Name of the plant</th><th>Part of the plant studied</th><th>IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/mL)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Anacardiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Schinus molle</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">790.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Annonaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Annona cherimola</italic> Miller</td><td align="left">Seeds</td><td align="left">270.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Asteraceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Artemisia absinthium</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">708.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Artemisia ludoviciana</italic> Nutt</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">230.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Chrysactinia mexicana</italic> A. Gray</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">105.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Matricaria recutita</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">559.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Caricaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Carica papaya</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Seeds</td><td align="left">5.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Chenopodiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L. Green variety</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">996.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L.<break/>Red variety</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">105.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Chenopodium murale</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">196.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Convolulaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Dichondra argentea</italic> Humb and Bonpl</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">317.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Geraniaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Geranium mexicanum</italic> HB and K.</td><td align="left">Roots</td><td align="left">56.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Fabaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Caesalpinia pulcherrima</italic> (L.) Sw</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">137.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Senna villosa</italic> Mills</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">223.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Lamiaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">126.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">204.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Papaveraceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Bocconia frutescens</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">30.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Arecaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Cocos nucifera</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Husk fibre</td><td align="left">5.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Punicaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Punica granatum</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Exocarpo of fruit</td><td align="left">100.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rutaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Ruta chalepensis</italic> L.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">226.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Schizaeaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Lygodium venustum</italic> Sw</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">60.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Verbenaceae</td><td align="left"><italic>Lippia alba</italic> (Mill.) N.E.Br.</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">227.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Aloysia triphylla</italic> Britton</td><td align="left">Aerial part</td><td align="left">103.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>An overview of several plants and phytochemicals with promising anti-trichomonas activity.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0090">Table 6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Name</th><th>Origen</th><th>Source</th><th>Chemical structure</th><th>Effect</th><th>Remarks</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Polyphenol Curcumin</bold></td><td align="left">polyphenol extracted from the Indian spice turmeric</td><td/><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx10.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0095">Image 9</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left">possessed anti-protozoal activity<break/>two reports are suggesting a contradictory effect of curcumin on <italic>T. vaginalis</italic></td><td align="left">curcumin is a well-tolerated compound and is safe in at least six human clinical trials</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Polyphenol Resveratrol</bold></td><td align="left">dietary non-flavonoid polyphenolic phytoalexin</td><td align="left">skin of grapes</td><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx11.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0100">Image 10</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left">inhibited the growth of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic><break/>cytostatic effect, whereas higher doses exerted killing effects</td><td align="left">Deleterious effects as anti-trichomonal via hydrogenosomal dysfunction and metabolic alteration</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Anthraquinone Emodin</bold></td><td align="left">a derived anthraquinone, <italic>cuspidatum</italic></td><td align="left">is extracted from roots and barks of various plants like <italic>Rheum palmatum, Aloe vera, Polygonum multiflorum,</italic> and <italic>Polygonum</italic></td><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx12.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0105">Image 11</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left">emodin significantly decreased the number of trichomonads in the vagina as well</td><td align="left">cured the trichomonal abscesses, indicating good absorption of emodin anthraquinone.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Flavonoid Quercetin Quercetrin</bold></td><td align="left">Extract of leaves and twigs of both the <italic>Dorstenia</italic> species.<break/>Extracts of flowers, leaves, and stem of <italic>Rheum ribes</italic> L.</td><td align="left"><italic>Dorstenia barteri</italic> and <italic>Dorstenia convexa</italic> extracts and <italic>Rheum ribes</italic> L.</td><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx13.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0110">Image 12</alt-text></inline-graphic><break/><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx14.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0115">Image 13</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left">Quercetin was found to be most potent, followed by quercitrin</td><td align="left">anti-trichomonal activity was attributed to flavonoids, namely quercetin, quercitrin</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Alkaloid lycorine</bold></td><td align="left">Plants of Amaryllidaceae family</td><td/><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx15.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0120">Image 14</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left">arrested the <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> cell cycle at the G2/M phase of the cell cycle</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Alkaloid Candimine</bold></td><td align="left">bulbs of <italic>Hippeastrum morelianum</italic></td><td/><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx16.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0125">Image 15</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left">modifications in size, shape, and intracellular localization of hydrogenosomes</td><td align="left">arrest of the <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> cell cycle; hydrogenosome autophagy</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Alkaloid lycorine-Candimine</bold></td><td/><td/><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx17.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0130">Image 16</alt-text></inline-graphic><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx18.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0135">Image 17</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left"><italic>T. vaginalis</italic> NTPDase and ecto-5&#x02032;-nucleotidase activities were significantly inhibited by candimine and lycorine</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Monoterpenoid geraniol</bold></td><td align="left">oil of <italic>Amomum tsao-ko</italic></td><td align="left">a spice used in Chinese cuisine and is also part of the Chinese Traditional Medicine</td><td align="left"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx19.gif"><alt-text id="alttext0140">Image 18</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="left">10-fold less active than metronidazole</td><td align="left">Cell and organelles damage,<break/>Intense morphological changes</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>&#x003b2; glycosides</bold></td><td align="left">Thai plants</td><td align="left">Seeds, flowers, leaves, fruits</td><td/><td align="left">125-fold less effective than metronidazole</td><td align="left">potent anti-trichomonal with MIC of 6.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Diterpenoids and triterpenoids</bold></td><td align="left">barks of <italic>Platanus acerifolia</italic> and <italic>Malus domestica</italic></td><td align="left">peels</td><td align="left">Betulinic acid and ursolic acid</td><td align="left">betulinic acid presented better activity than those from ursolic acid</td><td align="left">betulinic acid: better activity than ursolic acid.<break/>Piperazine derivatized from betulinic acid: high trichomonacidal agents.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Saponins</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Passiflora alata;</italic><break/><italic>Quillaja brasiliensis;</italic><break/><italic>Ilex paraguariensis;</italic><break/><italic>Sapindus mukorossi</italic></td><td align="left">Leaves; fruit pericarp of <italic>Sapindus mukorossi</italic></td><td/><td align="left">MIC for saponins was four-fold</td><td align="left">The combination of saponin with synthetic spermicide resulted in lowering the anti-trichomonal MIC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Essential oils</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> and <italic>Lavandula intermedia</italic></td><td/><td align="left"><italic>M. piperita</italic> and <italic>S. officinalis:</italic> anti-trichomonas activity</td><td align="left">Comparable to metronidazole<break/><italic>S. officinalis</italic> was found to have higher potency as compared to <italic>M. piperita</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> and <italic>Lavandula intermedia</italic> were evaluated for their anti-trichomonal properties</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Eucalyptus</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic></td><td align="left">aqueous extract of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> leaves</td><td/><td align="left">eradication of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at the end of 24&#x000a0;h</td><td align="left">vaginal cream containing extract of <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> along with extract of <italic>Viola odorata</italic> and <italic>Mentha piperita</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>American plants</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Mikania cordifolia</italic><break/><italic>Neurolaena lobata</italic></td><td align="left">Asteraceae and <italic>Scutia buxifolia</italic> Reiss from the Ramnaceae</td><td/><td align="left">The most active extracts amongst all the plants examined</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Brazilian Caatinga region</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Polygala decumbens</italic> 0 &#x003bc;g/mL.</td><td align="left">roots</td><td/><td align="left">Significant effect on the viability of trophozoites.</td><td align="left">The extract was active against metronidazole-resistant species with MIC 156</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>California</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Arbutus unedo</italic></td><td align="left">ornamental plant</td><td/><td align="left">effective anti-trichomonacidal</td><td align="left">100% growth inhibition of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> at 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Mexican plants</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Carica papaya</italic> and <italic>Cocos nucifera</italic>,</td><td/><td/><td align="left">anti-trichomonas effect</td><td align="left">less effective than metronidazole</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>African plants</bold></td><td align="left"><italic>Cussonia</italic> species (Araliaceae)</td><td align="left">Methanolic extract of leaves</td><td/><td align="left">Anti-trichomonas activity against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic></td><td align="left">MIC in the range of 0.8&#x02013;1.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0300">As observed in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, <italic>Carica papaya</italic> and <italic>Cocos nucifera</italic>, showed the best anti-trichomonas activity with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 5.6 and 5.8&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, respectively. Moderate activity was observed with the species <italic>Bocconia frutescens</italic>, <italic>Geranium mexicanum</italic>, and <italic>Lygodium venustum</italic> with IC<sub>50</sub> values 30.9&#x02013;60.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL. The rest of the plants are considered ineffective as the IC<sub>50</sub> values were considerably greater than 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL. Although effective anti-trichomonal, all plants were still very less effective than metronidazole with 0.037&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL.</p><p id="p0305">Extract of peels of pomegranate fruits; <italic>Punica granatum</italic> were also tested by <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">El-Sherbiny and El Sherbiny (2011)</xref> for <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-<italic>T. vaginalis</italic> activity. In this study, the authors also determined the <italic>in-vivo</italic> anti-trichomonal activity of <italic>Commiphora molmol</italic> (Engl.) Engl. ex Tschirch (Mirazid) in metronidazole and tinidazole resistant females, and the dose was two capsules (600&#x000a0;mg) for six to eight successive days on an empty stomach. Both these plants showed promising effects.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3.4"><label>3.3.4</label><title>African plants</title><p id="p0310">On similar lines, scientists from South Africa (<xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">van Vuuren and Naidoo, 2010</xref>) investigated several plants indigenous or introduced to southern Africa and are used by ethnic rural populations to treat infections related to the urogenital tract <italic>Aloe ferox</italic> Mill. leaves<italic>, Bowiea volubilis</italic> bulb<italic>, Bowiea volubilis</italic> Harv. leaves <italic>Carpobrotus edulis</italic> (L.) L. Bolus leaves <italic>Cassia occidentalis</italic> N&#x000e1;ves leaves <italic>Cassia occidentalis</italic> N&#x000e1;ves seeds <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> (L.) G. Don leaves, <italic>Cissus quadrangulis</italic> leaves, <italic>Croton gratissimus</italic> Burch. leaves, <italic>Euclea natalensis</italic> A. DC. leaves, <italic>Hypericum aethiopicum</italic> Thunb. roots, <italic>Hypericum aethiopicum</italic> Thunb leaves <italic>Polygala fruticosa</italic> P.J. Bergius leaves, <italic>Psidium guajava</italic> L. leaves<italic>, Sansevieria aethiopica</italic> Thunb. leaves<italic>, Scabiosa columbaria</italic> L. roots, leaves<italic>, Strelitzia reginae</italic> Aiton leaves<italic>, Syzygium cordatum</italic> Hochst<italic>., Tarchonanthus camphoratus</italic> L. leaves<italic>, Terminalia sericea</italic> Burch. ex DC. leaves<italic>, Typha capensis</italic> (Rohrb.) NE Br. leaves<italic>,</italic> Essential oil of <italic>Croton gratissimus</italic> Burch.<italic>,</italic> and <italic>Tarchonanthus camphoratus</italic> L. Aqueous extracts of these plants were not as effective as observed from their high MIC values. In organic extracts prepared using dichloromethane and methanol (1:1), only three plants' meaningful activity leaves extract of <italic>Psidium guajava</italic> L.<italic>, Strelitzia reginae</italic> Aiton<italic>,</italic> and <italic>Tarchonanthus camphoratus</italic> L<italic>.</italic> Later, in 2013, the same group (<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Naidoo et al., 2013</xref>) extensively studied several plants used individually or in combination for the treatment of sexually transmitted diseases in rural northern Maputaland, KwaZulu-Natal was explored. Plants were selected based on their applications and use in traditional medicine. Aqueous and organic extract of the following plants were studied for cytotoxicity and antimicrobial activity against various pathogens including <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>. <italic>Albizia adianthifolia</italic> (Schumach.) W. Wight<italic>, Aloe marlothii</italic> Berger<italic>, Bidens pilosa</italic> L.<italic>, Carica papaya</italic> L.<italic>, Clematis brachiate, Euphorbia hypericifolia</italic> Boiss.<italic>, Hypoxis hemerocallidea</italic> Fisch. and C.A. Mey<italic>., Kigelia Africana</italic> (Lam.) Benth.<italic>, Musa acuminate, Ozoroa engleri</italic> R. Fern. and A. Fern<italic>., Peltophorum africanum</italic> Sond.<italic>, Ranunculus multifidus</italic> Forssk<italic>., Sarcophyte sanguinea</italic> Sparrm<italic>., Sclerocarya birrea</italic> (A. Rich.) Hochst.<italic>, Senecio serratuloides</italic> DC.<italic>, Syzygium cordatum</italic> Hochst<italic>, Tabernaemontana elegans</italic> Stapf<italic>, Trichilia dregeana</italic> Sond.<italic>,</italic> and <italic>Ximenia caffra</italic> Sond<italic>.</italic> In this study, aqueous extracts were ineffective, as seen from their high MIC values (&#x0003e;16&#x000a0;mg/mL) whereas organic extracts exhibited MIC from 2 to 12&#x000a0;mg/mL.</p><p id="p0315"><italic>Cussonia</italic> species (Araliaceae) are used in African traditional medicine to treat pain, inflammation, gastro-intestinal disorders, malaria, and sexually transmitted diseases. Methanolic extract of leaves of 13 <italic>Cussonia</italic> species was tested for <italic>in vitro</italic> anti-trichomonas activity against <italic>T. vaginalis,</italic> and MIC was found to be in the range of 0.8&#x02013;1.3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">De Villiers et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Concluding remarks</title><p id="p0320">Trichomoniasis is considered a re-emerging disease, and drug resistance against metronidazole or 5-nitro imidazole family, the first-line drug for treating trichomoniasis, is on the rise. Lack of alternative treatment options for trichomoniasis is a serious clinical threat, and there is a critical need to have alternative drugs for its management. Traditional/folk medicines that are in practice in various countries have carved out the pathway for anti-trichomonal drug research. Whole-plant extracts and phytoconstituents form a major part of these traditional anti-trichomonal medicines. Negligible adverse events are one of the major benefits of using plant-based medicines. Much research has been carried out on such phytoconstituents or extracts, and their therapeutic utility has been established. However, most of this research is sparse and is mostly limited to <italic>in-vitro</italic> studies. These studies have revealed several promising phytoconstituents or plant extracts that need to be evaluated in experimental models and clinical settings. Many potential phytochemicals have been evaluated for them <italic>in-vitro</italic> anti-trichomonas activity but have not been explored subsequently. It is desired that further research should focus on the clinical efficacy of these phytoconstituents or plant extracts. Concerted efforts are needed to take these potential phytoconstituents/plants for therapeutic usage.</p><p id="p0325">Our overview indicates that several plants and phytochemicals have promising anti-trichomonas activity (<xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p><p id="p0330">However, considering the limited quality of included evidence and heterogeneity of different studies, more well-design studies are required to further confirm the conclusion. We recommend that future studies focus on the intensity and treatment duration of selected plant material or isolated phytoconstituents and pay more attention to safety profiles. Moreover, a better understanding of the selected active constituents' mechanism of action is needed to help researchers and clinical professionals pursue further studies. Structure-activity relationship studies will also help identify the essential structural features of the selected molecule.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0335">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper. All authors have seen and approved the final version of the manuscript and warrant that the article hasn't received prior publication and isn't under consideration for publication elsewhere.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdali</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahed</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amooee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarshenas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabatabaee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bekhradi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of vaginal <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> cream and oral metronidazole Pill on results of treatments for vaginal infections, including trichomoniasis and bacterial vaginosis in women of reproductive age</article-title><source>BioMed Res. Int.</source><volume>683640</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/683640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdollahy</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziaei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabankhani</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azadbakht</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of essential oils of <italic>Artemisia aucheri</italic> Boiss, <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss and <italic>Myrtus communis</italic> on <italic>trichomonas vaginalis</italic>. Iran</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Res.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>35</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aleksic Sabo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knezevic</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of Eucalyptus camaldulensis Dehn. plant extracts and essential oils: a review</article-title><source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><volume>132</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.02.051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allam</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunomodulatory effects of curcumin treatment on murine schistosomiasis mansoni</article-title><source>Immunobiology</source><volume>214</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19249123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilic</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebhart</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trichomonads in birds--a review</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><volume>141</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24476968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arthan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sithiprom</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Limmatvatirat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavalitshewinkoon-Petmitr</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Svasti</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitory effects of Thai plants beta-glycosides on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>103</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18463895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aslani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asghari</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darani</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghanadian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design, formulation, and physicochemical evaluation of vaginal cream containing <italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis, Viola odorata</italic>, and <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> extracts for Prevention and Treatment of Trichomoniasis</article-title><source>Int. J. Prev. Med.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>179</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijpvm.IJPVM_525_17</pub-id><comment>eCollection 2019</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32133097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakkali</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Averbeck</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Idaomar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological effects of essential oils--a review. Food and chemical toxicology: an international journal published for the Brit</article-title><source>Ind. Biol. Res. Assoc.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>475</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bisson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dridi</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machouart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the role of Trichomonas tenax in the etiopathogenesis of human periodontitis: a systematic review</article-title><source>PloS One</source><volume>14</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0226266</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandelli</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remarkable anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity of plants traditionally used by the Mby&#x000e1;-Guarani indigenous group in Brazil</article-title><source>BioMed Res. Int.</source><volume>826370</volume><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tirmizi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous metronidazole, liquid tinidazole, and intra-vaginal boric acid to cure trichomonas in a patient with gastric bypass surgery</article-title><source>Int. J. STD AIDS</source><volume>29</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956462417750711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29393008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calzada</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x000e9;pez-Mulia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapia-Contreras</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Mexican medicinal plant used to treat trichomoniasis on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> trophozoites</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>113</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17628366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carapina da Silva</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>das Neves</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di&#x000e9; Alves</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sena-Lopes</surname><given-names>&#x000c2;.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borsuk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Pereira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-parasitic activity of synthetic curcumin monocarbonyl analogues against <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>111</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30594049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cepicka</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hampl</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flegr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New evolutionary lineages, unexpected diversity, and host specificity in the parabasalid genus Tetratrichomonas</article-title><source>Mol. Phylogenet. Evol.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2006.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chainani-Wu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Safety and anti-inflammatory activity of curcumin: a component of tumeric (<italic>Curcuma longa</italic>)</article-title><source>J. Alternative Compl. Med.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Changtam</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Koning</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajid</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suksamrarn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcuminoid analogs with potent activity against <italic>Trypanosoma</italic> and <italic>Leishmania</italic> species</article-title><source>Eur. J. Med. Chem.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20004045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-viral activity of lycorine against Zika virus <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Virology</source><volume>546</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32452420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlietinck</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berghe</surname><given-names>D.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-infective potential of natural products: how to develop a stronger in vitro 'proof-of-concept</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.04.003</pub-id><comment>106(</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>J.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pharmacology, toxicology and therapeutic potential of anthraquinone derivative emodin</article-title><source>Chin. J. Nat. Med.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32503734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> properties of the oil of <italic>Amomum tsao-ko</italic> and its major component, geraniol</article-title><source>Pharm. Biol.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25963227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damke</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuzuki</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chassot</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortez</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>I.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesquita</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>da-Silva</surname><given-names>V.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Svidzinski</surname><given-names>T.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Consolaro</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spermicidal and anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity of Brazilian <italic>Sapindus saponaria</italic></article-title><source>BMC Compl. Alternative Med.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>196</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-13-196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Villiers</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Vuuren</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Zyl</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Wyk</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and antimalarial activity of Cussonia species (Araliaceae)</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>129</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20298772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetratrichomonas in pyopneumothorax</article-title><source>Am. J. Emerg. Med.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1215</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajem.2019.03.029</pub-id><comment>e1-1215.e4</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunne</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Upcroft</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Donoghue</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Upcroft</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug resistance in the sexually transmitted protozoan <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>Cell Res.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12974614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elizondo-Luevano</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verde-Star</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Horta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro-R&#x000ed;os</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch&#x000e1;vez-Montes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In Vitro</italic> effect of methanolic extract of <italic>Argemone mexicana</italic> against <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>Kor. J. Parasitol.</source><volume>58</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>145</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Sherbiny</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>El Sherbiny</surname><given-names>E.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Effect of <italic>Commiphora molmol</italic> (Myrrh) in treatment of trichomoniasis vaginalis infection</article-title><source>Iran. Red Crescent Med. J.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22737515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ertabaklar</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiv&#x000e7;ak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mert</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozensoy T&#x000f6;z</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> activity of <italic>Arbutus unedo</italic> leaf extracts against <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> trophozoites</article-title><source>Turk. Parazitoloji Derg.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>265</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ezz Eldin</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Badawy</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity of <italic>Pistacia lentiscus</italic> mastic and <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> essential oil</article-title><source>J. Parasit. Dis.: Off. Organ Ind. Soc. Parasitol.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>473</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frasson</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva Trentin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordani</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First report of anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity of the medicinal plant <italic>Polygala decumbens</italic> from the Brazilian semi-arid region, Caatinga</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>110</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2581</fpage><lpage>2587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22205352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghasemian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eslami</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasanvand</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozorgi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-abodi</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> properties for use in the eradication of infections</article-title><source>Comp. Immunol. Microbiol. Infect. Dis.</source><volume>65</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31300120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giordani</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira Pde</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weizenmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosemberg</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonorino</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Carli</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogo</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuanazzi</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candimine-induced cell death of the amitochondriate parasite <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>J. Nat. Prod.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>2019</fpage><lpage>2023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np100449g</pub-id><comment>73</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giordani</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weizenmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosemberg</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonorino</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Carli</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogo</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuanazzi</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lycorine induces cell death in the amitochondriate parasite, <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>, via an alternative non-apoptotic death pathway</article-title><source>Phytochemistry (Oxf.)</source><volume>72</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>650</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giordani</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weizenmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosemberg</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Carli</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogo</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuanazzi</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> nucleoside triphosphate diphosphohydrolase and ecto-5'-nucleotidase activities are inhibited by lycorine and candimine</article-title><source>Parasitol. Int.</source><volume>59</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.parint.2010.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20176129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asghari</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousefi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazemian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafieiean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darani</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of different extracts of <italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> parasite in culture medium</article-title><source>Adv. Biomed. Res.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2277-9175.114187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24516847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Puyvelde</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosselaers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Kimpe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antitrichomonas <italic>in vitro</italic> activity of <italic>Cussonia holstii</italic></article-title><source>Engl. Nat. Prod. Res.</source><volume>17</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12713125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hersh</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary trichomoniasis and <italic>Trichomonas tenax</italic></article-title><source>J. Med. Microbiol.</source><volume>20</volume><year>1985</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3894667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Miguel</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakjang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappelli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta-Serrano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiori</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mottram</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> pathobiology new insights from the genome sequence</article-title><source>Adv. Parasitol.</source><volume>77</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22137583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imenshahidi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseinzadeh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Berberis vulgaris</italic> and berberine: an update review</article-title><source>Phytother Res.: PTR</source><volume>30</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1745</fpage><lpage>1764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27528198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Innocente</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frasson</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>B.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnoatto</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity from triterpenoid derivatives</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>113</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>2933</fpage><lpage>2940</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24880238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushwaha</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maikhuri</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining a synthetic spermicide with a natural trichomonacide for safe, prophylactic contraception</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod. (Oxf.)</source><volume>29</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>252</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Curcumin--a natural herb with anti-HIV activity</article-title><source>J. Natl. Med. Assoc.</source><volume>88</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8691490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaneda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of berberine, a plant alkaloid, on the growth of anaerobic protozoa in axenic culture</article-title><source>Tokai J. Exp. Clin. Med.</source><volume>15</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2131648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khalafalla</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahiduzzaman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyachenko</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desouky</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alber</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daugschies</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of curcumin (diferuloylmethane) on <italic>Eimeria tenella</italic> sporozoites <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>108</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>879</fpage><lpage>886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21057813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>So</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geraniol inhibits prostate cancer growth by targeting cell cycle and apoptosis pathways</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source><volume>407</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21371438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kissinger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trichomoniasis and HIV interactions: a review</article-title><source>Sex. Transm. Infect.</source><volume>89</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23605851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kissinger</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzny</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mena</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lillis</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwebke</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchamps</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Augostini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Secor</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-dose versus 7-day-dose metronidazole for the treatment of trichomoniasis in women: an open-label, randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30297322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koide</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nose</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogihara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leishmanicidal effect of curcumin <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Biol. Pharm. Bull.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11824543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurnatowska</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurnatowski</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rzesistkowica jamy ustnej powik&#x00142;ana grzybica (trichomonosomycosis) [Trichomonosomycosis of the oral cavity]</article-title><source>Wiad. Parazytol.</source><volume>45</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16886453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langston</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alderete</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nevin</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakpahan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marzo</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaydos</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaacs</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>W.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokoll</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenilman</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Platz</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> infection and prostate-specific antigen concentration: insights into prostate involvement and prostate disease risk</article-title><source>Prostate</source><volume>79</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1622</fpage><lpage>1628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31376187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lara-D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gayt&#x000e1;n-Ramos</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000e1;valos-Balderas</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos-Guzm&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mata-C&#x000e1;rdenas</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas-Villarreal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa-Quintana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Reyes</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno-Cuevas</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological and toxicological effects of Perla black bean (Phaseolus vulgaris L.) extracts: <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> studies</article-title><source>Basic Clin. Pharmacol. Toxicol.</source><volume>104</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19053992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loyola</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f3;rquez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Araya</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neira</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagua</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>San-Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diterpenoids from <italic>Azorella yareta</italic> and their trichomonicidal activities</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><volume>56</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11219811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Berberine exhibits antioxidative effects and reduces apoptosis of the vaginal epithelium in bacterial vaginosis</article-title><source>Exp. Ther. Med.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>2122</fpage><lpage>2130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31410167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahboubi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potency of <italic>Zataria multiflora</italic> Boiss in treatment of vaginal infections</article-title><source>Infect. [online].</source><volume>22</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>83</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdi</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gany</surname><given-names>Z.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharief</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative drugs against <italic>trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>EMHJ &#x02013; East. Mediterr. Health J.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17333809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>M.A.E.F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aminou</surname><given-names>H.A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are the fatty acids responsible for the higher effect of oil and alcoholic extract of Nigella sativa over its aqueous extract on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> trophozoites?</article-title><source>J. Parasit. Dis.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12639-014-0479-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27065592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leiro</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogenosome metabolism is the key target for anti-parasitic activity of resveratrol against <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><volume>57</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>2476</fpage><lpage>2484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23478970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehriardestani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliahmadi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toliat</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants and their isolated compounds showing anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>- activity</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>88</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28178618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maritz</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlton</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the importance of zoonotic trichomonads for human health?</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol.</source><volume>30</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24951156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meites</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Workowski</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Trichomonas vaginalis</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prober</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Principles and Practice of Pediatric Infectious Diseases</source><year>2018</year><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>1364</fpage><lpage>1366</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slootmaker</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grear</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Salvo</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiser</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shwiff</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-species transmission potential between wild pigs, livestock, poultry, wildlife, and humans: implications for disease risk management in North America</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>7821</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-07336-z</pub-id><comment>10</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28798293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mimche</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taramelli D</surname><given-names>V.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant-based immunomodulator curcumin as a potential candidate for the development of an adjunctive therapy for cerebral malaria</article-title><source>Malar. J.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>Suppl. 1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>S10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21411011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamseer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghersi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petticrew</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shekelle</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prisma-P Group</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic review and meta-analysis protocols (PRISMA-P) 2015 statement</article-title><source>Syst. Rev.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2046-4053-4-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25554246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-parasitic activity of two Lavandula essential oils against <italic>Giardia duodenalis, Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> and <italic>Hexamita inflata</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>99</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16741725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>M.E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>G.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezerra</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fechine</surname><given-names>F.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pontes</surname><given-names>A.v.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezerra</surname><given-names>F.A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of the <italic>Mentha crispa</italic> in the treatment of women with <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> infection</article-title><source>Arch. Gynecol. Obstet.</source><volume>286</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00404-012-2251-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22350328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muelas-Serrano</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogal</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escario</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f3;mez-Barrio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> screening of american plant extracts on <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> and <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>71</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10904152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin-Adeline</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;lapeta</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High prevalence of <italic>Tritrichomonas foetus</italic> 'bovine genotype' in faecal samples from domestic pigs at a farm where bovine trichomonosis has not been reported for over 30 years</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>212</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2015.08.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naemi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asghari</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousofi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousefi</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of essential oil and anti-trichomonas activity of leaf, stem, and flower of <italic>Rheum ribes L</italic>. extracts</article-title><source>Avicenna J. Phytomed.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25050317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naidoo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zyl</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wet</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants traditionally used individually and in combination to treat sexually transmitted infections in northern Maputaland, South Africa: antimicrobial activity and cytotoxicity</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>149</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23880127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neag</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mocan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Echeverr&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bocsan</surname><given-names>C.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cri&#x0015f;an</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzoianu</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Berberine: botanical occurrence, traditional uses, extraction methods, and relevance in cardiovascular, metabolic, hepatic, and renal disorders</article-title><source>Front. Pharmacol.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>557</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30186157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niyyati</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joneidi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamalinejad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haghighi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In Vitro</italic> activity of <italic>Mentha longifolia</italic> leaves and <italic>Pimpinella anisum</italic> seeds against a clinical strain of <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>Intern. J. Mol. Clin. Microbiol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>509</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omisore</surname><given-names>N.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adewunmi</surname><given-names>C.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwalewa</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngadjui</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adenowo</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abegaz</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojewole</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watchueng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antitrichomonal and anti-oxidant activities of <italic>Dorstenia barteri</italic> and <italic>Dorstenia convexa</italic></article-title><source>Braz. J. Med. Biol. Res.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1087</fpage><lpage>1094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16007280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Arriaga</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendoza-Maga&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cort&#x000e9;s-Z&#x000e1;rate</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corona-Rivera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobadilla-Morales</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troyo-Sanrom&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez-Herrera</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytotoxic effect of curcumin on <italic>Giardia lamblia</italic> trophozoites</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><volume>98</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16678115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pund</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borade</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasve</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvement of anti-inflammatory and anti-angiogenic activity of berberine by novel rapid dissolving nanoemulsifying technique</article-title><source>Phytomed.: Intern. J. Phyto. Phytopharmacol.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>314</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pund</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patravale</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Improving bioavailability of nutraceuticals by nanoemulsification</chapter-title><source>Nutraceuticals Nanotechnology in the Agri-Food Industry</source><edition>fourth ed.</edition><year>2016</year><publisher-name>Elsevier Inc London</publisher-name><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>534</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pund</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>More</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid based nanoemulsifying resveratrol for improved physicochemical characteristics, in vitro cytotoxicity and in vivo antiangiogenic efficacy</article-title><source>Colloids Surf. B Biointerfaces</source><volume>120</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24905685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raether</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidenath</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ketoconazole and other potent antimycotic azoles exhibit pronounced activity against <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi, Plasmodium berghei</italic> and <italic>Entamoeba histolytica in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Z. Parasitenkd.</source><volume>70</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6320547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref77"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rein</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Trichomoniasis</chapter-title><source>Hunter's Tropical Medicine and Emerging Infectious Diseases</source><year>2020</year><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>733</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Brum Vieira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnoatto</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity of saponins from Quillaja, Passiflora, and Ilex species</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>110</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>2551</fpage><lpage>2556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22218924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref79"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lycorine: a prospective natural lead for anticancer drug discovery</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>107</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30114645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saeidi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forgani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javadian</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javadian</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> plant extract on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> parasites and <italic>Candida albicans</italic> under laboratory conditions: an experimental study</article-title><source>Gene Cell Tissue</source><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5812/gct.92867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref81"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Se&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistent and recurrent <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> infections: epidemiology, treatment and management considerations</article-title><source>Exp. Rev. Anti-Inf. Ther.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>685</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref82"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahiduzzaman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyachenko</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalafalla</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desouky</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daugschies</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of curcumin on <italic>Cryptosporidium parvum in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>105</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1155</fpage><lpage>1161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19557435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref83"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>L.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigo</surname><given-names>G.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carollo</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trentin</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrolyzable tannins from <italic>Poincianella (Caesalpinia) microphylla</italic> fruits: metabolite profiling and anti-<italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> activity</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>134</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>109236</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32517934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref84"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soffar</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Metwali</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Aziz</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>el-Wakil</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the effect of a plant alkaloid (berberine derived from <italic>Berberis aristata</italic>) on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis in vitro</italic></article-title><source>J. Egypt. Soc. Parasitol.</source><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2001</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref85"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannucci</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alderete</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaydos</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenilman</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marzo</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Platz</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasma antibodies against <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> and subsequent risk of prostate cancer</article-title><comment>2006 May</comment><source>Cancer Epidemiol. Biomark. Prev.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-05-0781</pub-id><comment>PMID: 16702374</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref86"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osuka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawahata</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of a human isolate of <italic>Tritrichomonas foetus</italic> (cattle/swine genotype) infected by a zoonotic opportunistic infection</article-title><source>J. Vet. Med. Sci.</source><volume>78</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26685985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref87"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-Trichomonas activity of <italic>Sapindus saponins</italic>, a candidate for development as microbicidal contraceptive</article-title><source>J. Antimicrob. Chemother.</source><volume>62</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18544604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref88"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tonkal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antitrichomonal effect of <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> aqueous extract and wheat germ agglutinin</article-title><source>JKAU Med. Sci.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref89"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naidoo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An antimicrobial investigation of plants used traditionally in southern Africa to treat sexually transmitted infections</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>130</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20561928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref90"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wachter</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Syrowatka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Obwaller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walochnik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> efficacy of curcumin on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>Wien Klin. Wochenschr.</source><volume>126</volume><issue>Suppl. 1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>S32</fpage><lpage>S36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24619489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref91"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antitrichomonal action of emodin in mice</article-title><source>J. Ethnopharmacol.</source><volume>40</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8133650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref92"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Workowski</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trichomoniasis: challenges to appropriate management</article-title><source>Clin. Infect. Dis.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>Suppl. 3</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>S123</fpage><lpage>S129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/511425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17342665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref93"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youse</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazemian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sereshti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahmanikhoh</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadinia</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafaian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maghsoodi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darani</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of <italic>Echinophora platyloba, Stachys lavandulifolia</italic>, and <italic>Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> plants on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> growth <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Adv. Biomed. Res.</source><volume>1</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>79</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2277-9175.102987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23326809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref94"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousefi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taghipur</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arefkhah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimian</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davoudian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafeiean</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Darani</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In-vitro</italic> effect of <italic>Menthe piperita</italic> and <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> extracts on <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>J. Isfahan Med. Sch.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>241</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref95"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youssefi</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abouhosseini Tabari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghadamnia</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> activity of <italic>Artemisia sieberi</italic> against <italic>Trichomonas gallinae</italic>. Iran</article-title><source>J. Vet. Res.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0340">We thank Prof. Michael Wink, Pharmaceutical Biology, Heidelberg, Germany, and Prof. Vincenzo De Feo, Department of Pharmacy, University of Salerno, Salerno, Italy, for assistance and comments that greatly improved the manuscript.</p></ack></back></article>