<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2662-7671</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7433056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-020-03051-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The toxicity assessment of extract of <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. seeds in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>Xiangzhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Yanyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Nianxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xinkui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Jiarui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Yonggang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Peng</given-names></name><address><email>tanpengtcm@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.24695.3c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1431 9176</institution-id><institution>School of Chinese Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Beijing University of Chinese Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>No. 11, Bei San Huan Dong Lu, Chaoyang District, Beijing, 100029 China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>256</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. is a medicinal herb extensively used in traditional Chinese medicine (TCM). So far, relevant reports on the toxicity of <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. seeds (PHS) are hardly available. Especially, we still know little about the in vivo mechanism for PHS toxicity. This study aims to evaluate the toxicity effects of PHS in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (<italic>C. elegans</italic>), investigate the possible mechanism of the toxicity effects of PHS, and provide reference for the pharmacological research of PHS.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">In the present study, the <italic>C. elegans</italic> was exposed to 0.25, 0.50, 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS in nematode growth medium (NGM) at 22&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in the presence of food. Lethality, lifespan, growth, reproduction, and locomotion behavior assays were performed to evaluate the toxicity effects of PHS in <italic>C. elegans</italic>. We then determined the mechanism of the toxicity effect of PHS by quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR), acetylcholinesterase (AChE) activity assay, and oxidative stress resistance assays. The main components of PHS were detected by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Compared with the control group, the lethality of <italic>C. elegans</italic> was significantly increased when they were exposed to the ethanol extract of PHS at 0.25, 0.50 and 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), and the mean lifespan was significantly decreased (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). We also observed that PHS exposure could induce the toxicity on body length, brood size, and locomotion behavior.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Our study shows that the ethanol extract of PHS exerts obvious toxic effects on <italic>C. elegans</italic>, which would provide new ideas and methods for the biological evaluation of the toxicity of Chinese medicinal materials.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L.</kwd><kwd><italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></kwd><kwd>Toxicity</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>National Chinese Medicine Standardization Project</institution></funding-source><award-id>ZYBZH-Y-HUB-20</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Peng</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Fundamental Research Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</institution></funding-source><award-id>2020-JYB-ZDGG-042</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par15"><italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. is widely distributed in the Central Asia, North Africa and Middle East [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It is a common medicinal material in traditional Chinese medicine for the treatment of cough, diabetes, depression, hypertension, jaundice, Parkinson&#x02019;s and Alzheimer&#x02019;s diseases, and many other human ailments. It has a variety of biological activities, including anti-cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], anti-inflammatory, antibacterial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], anti-depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], antioxidant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>],cholinesterase and monoamine oxidase inhibitory activities, antitumor, anti-hypertension, anticoagulant, antidiabetic, antimicrobial, insecticidal, antiparasidal, anti-leishmaniasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">PHS has long been known to possess hypothermic and remarkably hallucinogenic properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The main chemical constituents of PHS are alkaloids, flavonoids and anthraquinones. Harmaline and harmine are the two main alkaloidal constituents in PHS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], which can accumulate in dry seeds at 4.3 and 5.6% (w/w). Harmaline and harmine are primary toxic alkaloids in the PHS. The toxicity of harmaline is almost twice than harmine and in moderate doses causes tremors and clonic convulsions, but with no increase in spinal reflex excitability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Peganumine B showed potential inhibitory activity against both AChE and BChE respectively. Peganumine C, peganumine D, and peganumine I were found to have selective inhibitory activity against AChE respectively. Peganumine G and peganumine H showed significant cytotoxicity against a ZR-75-1 cell line respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Beta-carboline alkaloids may result in toxic effects, namely visual and auditory hallucinations, locomotor ataxia, nausea, vomiting, confusion and agitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. So far, relevant reports on the toxicity of PHS are hardly available. At present, there are few studies on the toxic mechanism of PHS. Therefore, the present study aims to evaluate the toxicity effects of PHS by <italic>C. elegans.</italic> Harmine could ameliorate impaired memory by enhancement of cholinergic neurotransmission via inhibiting the activity of acetylcholinesterase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Harmaline and harmine could effectively ameliorate memory deficits in scopolamine-induced mice, both of them exhibited an enhancement in cholinergic function by inhibiting AChE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par17"><italic>C. elegans</italic> is a common nematode living in the soil. <italic>C. elegans</italic> can provide a useful toxicity test system that is best suitable for interrogating in vivo problems. <italic>C. elegans</italic> has been used in many biological researches, such as genomics, cell biology, neuroscience and aging. The <italic>C. elegans</italic> is characterized by short life cycle, compact genome, stereotypical development, ease of propagation and small size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], which serves as a remarkable advantage in the toxicity study of TCM.</p><p id="Par18">In this study, the <italic>C. elegans</italic> system was used to evaluate the toxicity of PHS ethanol extract in vivo. In addition, we also explored the possible mechanism of PHS toxicity to <italic>C. elegans</italic>. Our data here will help understand the possible mechanisms of PHS toxicity and in turn confirms that the <italic>C. elegans</italic> is an effectual model when used for assessing adverse effects of Chinese medicinal materials.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials</title><p id="Par19">The PHS (Voucher specimen number:14032101) were purchased from Shenzhou Pharmacy and then authenticated by Hongliang Zhang, Xinjiang medical university. The content of harmaline was 96.76&#x02009;mg/g and the content of harmine was 98.05&#x02009;mg/g. The reference material has been deposited in the School of Chinese Pharmacy, Beijing University of Chinese Medicine.</p><p id="Par20">Alkaloids are the main chemical components in PHS, alkaloids could be extracted by the ethanol fraction. After crushing the raw products of PHS, adding 10 times of 95% ethanol ultrasound (540&#x02009;W, 40&#x02009;kHz) ultrasonic extraction twice, each time for 1&#x02009;h, the filtrate was dried after filtration, and the ethanol extract of the raw products of PHS was obtained and preserved at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Deionized water is used to mix the required concentration.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Chemicals and reagents</title><p id="Par21">Agar powder, tryptone, 1,1-diphenyl-2-trinitrophenylhydrazine (DPPH), glutathione and 2&#x02032;,7&#x02032;-Dichlorofluorescein were purchased from Solarbio Co. (Beijing, China). Cholesterol, paraquat and Vitamin C (Vc) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO). Methanol was purchased from Merck KGaA (Germany). Biowest Agarose was purchased from wobisen technology co. (Beijing, China). All the other chemicals were standard commercial products of analytical-reagent grade.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Strain preparation and culture methods</title><p id="Par22">We used wild-type N2 (Bristol) in this study, obtained from the Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology. <italic>C. elegans</italic> were stored in the NGM, which was cultured at 22&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and seeded with <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> OP50 (<italic>E. coli</italic> OP50) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Under aseptic condition, 100 spawning <italic>C. elegans</italic> were selected on a new culture medium covered with <italic>E.coli</italic> OP50, and all the <italic>C. elegans</italic> were picked out after laying eggs for 2&#x02009;h. The spawning plate was cultured in an aseptic biochemical incubator (LRH-250, Shanghai China) at 22&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for a specific period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Lethality and lifespan assays</title><p id="Par23">We chose 0.25, 0.50, 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL as the exposure concentration of PHS. These specific drug concentrations were based on previous experimental research, Tan Lab, unpublished data. Thirty <italic>C. elegans</italic> at L4 stage were added to NGM of PHS ethanol extract of 0.5, 1.0 and 2.5&#x02009;mg/mL, and cultured at 22&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The number of deaths of <italic>C. elegans</italic> was observed and recorded every 24&#x02009;h. In order to eliminate the mixture of the tested <italic>C. elegans</italic> and its newly produced larvae, the live <italic>C. elegans</italic> were picked out every 24&#x02009;h on a new culture plate containing the same drug concentration until all the <italic>C. elegans</italic> died. The mortality standard of <italic>C. elegans</italic> is that the worm itself is incapacitated and does not react to touching many times. Three groups of parallel tests were performed for each drug concentration.</p><p id="Par24">Thirty <italic>C. elegans</italic> were cultured on normal NGM after 24&#x02009;h exposure to ethanol extract from different concentrations of PHS. The number of deaths of <italic>C. elegans</italic> was observed and recorded every 24&#x02009;h. When the survival number of <italic>C. elegans</italic> was 15, the test days were recorded, that is the Mean lifespan.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Growth and reproduction assays</title><p id="Par25">According to previous literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], the <italic>C. elegans</italic> was treated at 50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min after exposure to ethanol extract from PHS of different concentrations for 24&#x02009;h, observed and photographed under stereoscopic microscope (Nikon, Japan), and measured the length of <italic>C. elegans</italic> by Image J software (Bethesda, MD, USA). Thirty <italic>C. elegans</italic> were measured in each concentration group.</p><p id="Par26">Thirty <italic>C. elegans</italic> exposed to different concentrations of PHS ethanol extract for 24&#x02009;h were selected into the normal NGM, one in each medium, and transferred the medium every 12&#x02009;h until the end of the spawning period of <italic>C. elegans</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Record the number of all offspring that it hatches as an indicator of the number of offspring.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Locomotion behavior assay</title><p id="Par27">Evaluation of locomotion behavior through endpoints of head thrash and body bend [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Added 60&#x02009;&#x003bc;L&#x02009;M9 to the medium which without <italic>E. coli</italic> OP50. Picked thirty <italic>C. elegans</italic> exposed to different concentrations of PHS ethanol extract for 24&#x02009;h into the NGM. After 1&#x02009;min recovery, the number of head thrash of <italic>C. elegans</italic> in 1&#x02009;min was recorded. Head thrash of <italic>C. elegans</italic> was defined swing from one side to the other and then back.</p><p id="Par28">Thirty <italic>C. elegans</italic> exposed to different concentrations of PHS ethanol extract for 24&#x02009;h were placed on the NGM without <italic>E.coli</italic> OP50, and their body bend times within 20&#x02009;s were counted. Body bend was counted as a change in the direction of the part of <italic>C. elegans</italic> corresponding to the posterior bulb of the pharynx along the y-axis, assuming that nematode was traveling along the x-axis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>AChE activity assay</title><p id="Par29">The <italic>C. elegans</italic> were collected into a 15&#x02009;mL centrifuge tube. Centrifuged at 500&#x02009;rpm for 15&#x02009;min. Discarded the supernatant and wash 3 times with M9 buffer. Rinsed once with double distilled water, then transfer into a 1.5&#x02009;mL centrifuge tube. Centrifuged at 3000&#x02009;rpm for 10&#x02009;min, discard the supernatant, stored at &#x02212;&#x02009;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for determination of AChE activity. AChE activity was measured by the Ellman method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]: at m(<italic>C. elegans</italic>): V (PBS buffer) ratio of 1: 5, added pre-chilled PBS buffer (0.1&#x02009;mol/L, pH&#x02009;7. 4), homogenized in a glass homogenizer under low temperature environment. Centrifuged at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C,12000&#x02009;rpm for 20&#x02009;min, then took the supernatant for testing. The Bradford method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] was used to determine the protein quality. Bovine serum albumin as a standard to calculate the specific activity of AChE.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Heat stress resistance assay</title><p id="Par30">The <italic>C. elegans</italic> synchronized in the L4 stage was placed in NGM containing drugs of different mass concentrations, 3 NGM per group, 10 <italic>C. elegans</italic> per NGM, and control group was set up. In the drug-administered group, <italic>C. elegans</italic> was treated with drug for 24&#x02009;h and placed in a 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C incubator at the same time as the control group. The death number and survival number of <italic>C. elegans</italic> were counted every 12&#x02009;h until all the <italic>C. elegans</italic> died. The death standard is described above [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Survival graphs were according to literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Oxidative stress resistance assay</title><p id="Par31">The <italic>C. elegans</italic> synchronized in the L4 stage was placed in NGM containing different concentrations of drugs, 3 NGM per group, 10 <italic>C. elegans</italic> per NGM, and control group was set up. We measured <italic>C. elegans</italic> survival when exposed to paraquat. After 24&#x02009;h of development, the <italic>C. elegans</italic> were transferred to the NGM containing 50&#x02009;mM paraquat, and the survival number of <italic>C. elegans</italic> was recorded every 2&#x02009;h until all the <italic>C. elegans</italic> died. The death standard is described above [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>qRT-PCR assay</title><p id="Par32">We used TRIzol&#x000ae;Reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific) to extract total <italic>C. elegans</italic> RNA. Using total RNA as template, cDNA was synthesized by invitrogen reverse transcription kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The process of fluorescence quantitative PCR includes design and synthesis of primers, fluorescence quantitative PCR, PCR product agarose electrophoresis (Bio-rad Sub-Cell&#x000ae;Model 192 Cell,USA), preparation of melting curve (ABI PRISM 7500, USA). qRT-PCR was used to determine the relative quantification of the targeted genes in comparison to the reference <italic>GAPDH</italic> gene, and the results were expressed as the relative expression ratio (between targeted gene and internal control <italic>GAPDH</italic>). The designed primers for targeted genes and reference <italic>GAPDH</italic> gene were shown as follows (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primers used for qRT-PCR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Gene</th><th>Forward primer</th><th>Reverse primer</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>GAPDH</italic></td><td>CGTCAAGCTCGTCTCTTGGT</td><td>AGAGGTCACTTCAAGCTCTTTTCT</td></tr><tr><td><italic>tub-1</italic></td><td>GTCATCAAAGTGCGGGAAGC</td><td>ACTGCATACGTGGTTGAGCA</td></tr><tr><td><italic>ctl-2</italic></td><td>ACACTCATTTCCACCGCCTT</td><td>TCCCAGAATTGACGGGGTTG</td></tr><tr><td><italic>sod-3</italic></td><td>CCACCTGTGCAAACCAGGAT</td><td>CATGGACATAGTCTGGGCGG</td></tr><tr><td><italic>hsp-16.1</italic></td><td>GTCTCGCAGTTCAAGCCAGA</td><td>TCGCTTCCTTCTTTGGTGCT</td></tr><tr><td><italic>hsp-16.2</italic></td><td>TACCACTATTTCCGTCCAGCTCA</td><td>TGTTCTCCTTGGATTGATAGCGTA</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>DPPH-scavenging capacity assay</title><p id="Par33">Using Vc as a control, the antioxidant activity of PHS was studied by DPPH method, and their half-inhibitory concentration values (IC<sub>50</sub>) were calculated. The absorbance of PHS at 517&#x02009;nm was measured by UV&#x02013;visible spectrophotometer (Hitachi, Japan) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The percentage of free radical scavenging activity is determined by the difference in absorbance of DPPH between the control and the sample.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Analysis of the main chemical components in raw-processed PHS</title><p id="Par34">HPLC system (Waters, USA) was used to analyze the chemical composition of PHS. The separation was carried out on an Agilent SB-C<sub>18</sub> column (4.6&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;150&#x02009;mm, 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) and the mobile phase consisted of methanol (A) and 0.5% ammonium acetate (B). The isocratic elution conditions were 47% (A) and the column temperature was set at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with a flow rate of 1.0&#x02009;mL/min. The detection wavelength was set to 325&#x02009;nm. The injection volume was 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;L. Comparing the HPLC retention time and all target peaks to the peak hold time of the standard, we determined the major components of the prepared PHS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par35">All experiments were repeated 3 times in parallel, and the data were expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation. Data were analyzed by SPSS 16.0 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA) and GraphPad Prism 5 (Prism, GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). Differences between groups were analyzed by <italic>t</italic> test. <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Effects of PHS exposure on lethality and lifespan of <italic>C. elegans</italic></title><p id="Par36">The analysis method of lethality of <italic>C. elegans</italic> is simple, and the experimental period is short and effective. Lethality is the basis for the analysis of toxicological toxicity using <italic>C. elegans.</italic> Lifespan is an important indicator of the long-term effects of specific toxicants. We assessed prolonged exposure to PHS in <italic>C. elegans</italic> L4 stage to young adults. After prolonged exposure to the examined concentrations of PHS, compared with the control group, the lethality of <italic>C. elegans</italic> was significantly increased by ethanol extract of PHS at 0.25, 0.50, and 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Prolonged exposure to 0.25, 0.50 and 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS significantly reduced the lifespan of <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Effects of PHS exposure on lethality <bold>b</bold> Effects of PHS exposure on lifespan <bold>c</bold> Effects of PHS exposure on body length <bold>d</bold> Effects of PHS exposure on brood size <bold>e</bold> Effects of PHS exposure on head thrash <bold>f</bold> Effects of PHS exposure on body bend Exposures were performed from L4-larvae to young adult. PHS, seeds of <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L.. <italic>C.elegans</italic> L4-larvae to young adults were exposed to PHS. *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001. The &#x0201c;control&#x0201d; is normal N2 worms</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3051_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Effects of PHS exposure on development and reproduction of <italic>C. elegans</italic></title><p id="Par37">The evaluation indexes of development of <italic>C. elegans</italic> include three aspects: body length, body width and abnormal development. Changes of body length reflect the growth rate and physiological state of <italic>C. elegans</italic>. In this study, we chose body length as a development evaluation indicator. Prolonged exposure to 0.25&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS did not obviously influence the body length of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, but prolonged exposure to 0.50, 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS significantly reduced the body length of <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c)<italic>.</italic></p><p id="Par38">The evaluation indexes of reproduction of <italic>C. elegans</italic> include three aspects: generation time, brood size and number of eggs in the uterus. The generation time is used primarily to investigate the reproductive speed of <italic>C. elegans</italic>. Brood size is mainly used to investigate the reproductive ability of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, and the number of eggs in the uterus can simultaneously examine the reproductive capacity and the physiological function of the ovipositor. In this study, we chose brood size as a reproduction evaluation indicator. We observed that prolonged exposure to 0.25, 0.50&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS did not significantly influence the brood size of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, but prolonged exposure to 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS significantly reduced the brood size of <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d)<italic>.</italic></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Effects of PHS exposure on locomotion behavior of <italic>C. elegans</italic></title><p id="Par39">Evaluation indexes of locomotion behavior of <italic>C. elegans</italic> include four aspects: head thrash, body bend, basic movement and locomotion rate. Locomotion behavior, as an index reflecting the basic function of the nervous system, has been widely used in the analysis of neurotoxicity. In this study, we chose head thrash and body bend as locomotion behaviors evaluation indicator. Prolonged exposure to all the examined concentrations of PHS significantly decreased head thrash of <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e). Prolonged exposure to 0.25&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS did not significantly influence the body bend of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, but prolonged exposure to 0.50, 1.00&#x02009;g/mL of PHS significantly decreased the body bend of <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>f)<italic>.</italic></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Effects of PHS exposure on AChE activity of <italic>C. elegans</italic></title><p id="Par40"><italic>C. elegans</italic> is a model animal with simple central nervous system, which is similar to vertebrates in neurophysiology. <italic>C. elegans</italic> can be used to estimate the harmful effects of toxic substances on the biological nervous system. AChE activity is a classic indicator of neurotoxicity. AChE plays an important role in the process of biological nerve conduction. In cholinergic synapses, AChE can degrade acetylcholine and stop the excitatory effect of neurotransmitters on the post-synaptic membrane, thus ensuring the normal transmission of nerve signals in the body. Prolonged exposure to 0.25&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS did not significantly influence the AChE activity of <italic>C. elegans</italic>. But prolonged exposure to 0.50, 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS significantly decreased the AChE activity of <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This result implied that prolonged exposure to PHS may damage the nervous system of <italic>C. elegans</italic>.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Effects of prolonged exposure to PHS on AChE activity of <italic>C. elegans.</italic> Exposures were performed from L4 stage to young adult. PHS, seeds of <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L.. <italic>C.elegans</italic> L4 stage to young adults were exposed to PHS. *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3051_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Heat stress resistance property of PHS in <italic>C. elegans</italic></title><p id="Par41">Heat stress is the sum of non-specific responses produced by an animal when it is stimulated by high temperatures that exceed its body&#x02019;s ability to regulate temperature. Too high temperature disrupts the normal heat balance of the organism, and the body will produce a series of complex physiological and psychological changes to deal with this change. Heat stress is a commonly used experiment in aging research. To investigate whether PHS has a stress resistance property, <italic>C. elegans</italic> pretreated with 0.25, 0.50, and 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS ethanol extract for 24&#x02009;h were further exposed to 35&#x02009;&#x000b0;C.</p><p id="Par42">Compared with the control group, the lifespan of PHS with different concentrations was significantly longer than that of the control group, which indicated that PHS could significantly improve the heat resistance of <italic>C. elegans</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Heat-stress resistance of PHS-treated <italic>C. elegans</italic>
<bold>b</bold> Oxidative stress resistance of PHS-treated <italic>C. elegans</italic>
<bold>c</bold>, <bold>d</bold> Expression patterns of genes required for development in control and PHS exposed nematodes. The results were expressed as the relative expression ratio between the targeted gene and the reference <italic>GAPDH</italic> gene. Exposures were performed from L4-larvae to young adult. PHS, seeds of <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L.. <italic>C.elegans</italic> L4-larvae to young adults were exposed to PHS. **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3051_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Oxidative stress resistance property of PHS in <italic>C. elegans</italic></title><p id="Par43">Oxidative stress is a negative effect of free radicals in the body and is considered to be an important factor leading to aging and disease. Paraquat is a strong oxidant commonly used in oxidative stress experiments. After paraquat enters the <italic>C. elegans</italic>, a series of biochemical reactions produce superoxide anions that are harmful to the cells, and the superoxide anions are further converted into active oxygen clusters such as hydrogen peroxide and hydroxyl radicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">In this experiment, each experimental group was treated with 50&#x02009;mM paraquat. Compared with the control group, PHS significantly prolonged the lifespan of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, indicating that PHS has certain antioxidant capacity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Effect of PHS on related gene expressions in <italic>C. elegans</italic></title><p id="Par45">Gene expression is an effective indicator for evaluating the effects of foreign compounds, and the specific toxic effects of foreign compounds can be determined according to the characteristics of target genes. <italic>Hsp-l6.l</italic> and <italic>hsp-l6.2</italic> are heat shock protein genes. <italic>Sod-3</italic> is the superoxide dismutase gene. <italic>Ctl-2</italic> is the catalase gene. <italic>Tub-1</italic> is a gene related to longevity regulation.</p><p id="Par46">After exposed to 0.25 and 0.50&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS ethanol extract for 24&#x02009;h, we observed that 0.25&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS significantly increased the expression levels of <italic>ctl-2</italic>, <italic>hsp-16.1</italic> and <italic>hsp-16.2</italic> genes, and decreased the expression levels of <italic>sod-3</italic> and <italic>tub-1</italic>. And 0.50&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS significantly increased the expression levels of <italic>hsp-16.1</italic> gene, and decreased the expression levels of <italic>hsp-16.2</italic>, <italic>ctl-2</italic>, <italic>sod-3</italic> and <italic>tub-1</italic>genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, d).</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Determination of IC<sub>50</sub> values</title><p id="Par47">The DPPH method is a commonly used method to evaluate and screen the antioxidant activity of substances in vitro. It has the advantages of simple operation, high sensitivity and good reproducibility. IC<sub>50</sub> is the antioxidant concentration when the DPPH concentration drops to 50%. The lower the IC<sub>50</sub>, the stronger the free radical scavenging ability of the antioxidant; the higher the IC<sub>50</sub>, the weaker the scavenging activity.</p><p id="Par48">The 50% radical scavenging activity (IC<sub>50</sub>) of Vc is 0.005&#x02009;mg/mL (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). The 50% radical scavenging activity (IC<sub>50</sub>) of PHS is 0.087&#x02009;mg/mL (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> The radical scavenging activity of Vc <bold>b</bold> The radical scavenging activity of PHS</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3051_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Identification of the main chemical components in raw-processed PHS</title><p id="Par49">The content of alkaloids in PHS is 4 to 6%, which is mainly alkaloids such as harmaline, harmine. Harmaline and harmine are not only the main chemical constituents but also the main active constituents.</p><p id="Par50">Using the HPLC, we identified the main chemical components in the concentrated PHS solution (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). The content of harmaline was 96.76&#x02009;mg/g and the content of harmine was 98.05&#x02009;mg/g.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Chemical components in PHS analyzed by HPLC.1, harmaline; 2, harmine</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3051_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par51">PHS has been used as a folk medicine for a long time in both oriental and western counties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. In this study, we conducted a comprehensive assessment of PHS toxicity using <italic>C. elegans</italic>. We evaluated the PHS toxicity of L4 stage for prolonged exposure. This period was chosed to coincide with the developmental stage when the number of germ cells reached its maximum, but before the embryonic membrane became impermeable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par52">We proposed a hypothesis to explain the underlying mechanism of PHS toxicity: the toxicity of PHS may be attributed to its combinational effects on nervous system and Insulin/IGF-1 signaling pathway. Our data showed that prolonged exposure to PHS could be toxic to the lifespan (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b), development (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c), reproduction (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d) and locomotion behavior (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e, f) of <italic>C. elegans</italic>. This may be closely related to the neurotoxicity of PHS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The changes in the behavior of <italic>C. elegans</italic> are mainly controlled by a variety of neurons and their mutual nerve conduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Acetylcholine is closely related to many behaviors of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, and locomotion behavior is the most important acetylcholine-related behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Metrifonate and haloxon can lead to the loss of kinetism by inhibiting the activity of AChE in <italic>C. elegans</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Harmaline and harmol showed good inhibitory activities against AChE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The AChE activity of control <italic>C. elegans</italic> was 30.61&#x02009;U/mg pro and exposure to 1.00&#x02009;mg/mL of PHS was 12.36&#x02009;U/mg pro. Our data showed PHS could obviously decrease the AChE activity of <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</p><p id="Par53">In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, <italic>daf-2</italic>, <italic>tub-1</italic>, <italic>ctl-2</italic>, <italic>hsp-16.1</italic>, <italic>hsp-16.2</italic> are required for Insulin/IGF-1 signaling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In <italic>C. elegans</italic>, this pathway plays a key role in the regulation of development, metabolism and aging, and is the most detailed life-regulating pathway in current research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. We found the expression change of these genes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, d), it may be related to the reduced lifespan of <italic>C. elegans.</italic></p><p id="Par54">Previous studies have indicated PHS possess certain antioxidant activity. Beta-carbolines (harmaline and harmine) may prevent dopamine-induced mitochondrial damage and PC12 cell death through a scavenging action on reactive oxygen species and inhibition of monoamine oxidase and thiol oxidation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The beta-carboline alkaloids have a significant protective effect against H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and paraquat oxidative agents in yeast cells, that their ability to scavenge hydroxyl radicals contributes to their antimutagenic and antigenotoxic effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Aqueous extract of <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> could prevent symptoms and reduced oxidative stress markers in rats with Parkinson&#x02019;s disease induced by 6-hydroxydopamine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Our data also suggest that pretreatment with PHS induced resistance properties in <italic>C. elegans</italic> against damage from both heat-stress (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a) and oxidative stress (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d). Our data further support the protective effects of PHS on animals. The mechanism to protects against heat resistance needs further study.</p><p id="Par55">Our study indicates the potential adverse effects of PHS in <italic>C. elegans</italic> after long-term exposure. These results lay the foundation for further study of the pharmacological mechanism of PHS, and contribute to the reasonable application of PHS on clinical practice. At least according to our data, the duration and dose should be carefully considered before using the drug. At the same time, it is also possible to design and consider strategies such as modulation of the process to reduce the possible adverse effects of PHS.</p><p id="Par56">In summary, with the PHS as a sample, our study provide evidence to illustrate the application value of the system in the evaluation of the toxicity of Chinese medicinal materials. After long-term exposure, PHS had a variety of toxic effects in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, which may be the result of a combination of the nervous system and Insulin/IGF-1 signaling pathway. In the future, the detection of the beneficial or adverse effects of specific chemical constituents in PHS will help us further understand and control the toxicity formation and clinical use of this drug.</p><p id="Par57">Previous studies have shown that <italic>C. elegans</italic> can be used for toxicity assessment of metal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], organic contaminants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], pharmaceutical compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] or specific components extracted from plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In the present study, our data further suggests that <italic>C. elegans</italic> can be utilized to toxicity assessment of Chinese medicinal materials. Therefore, <italic>C. elegans</italic> can be used to estimate the beneficial effects and adverse reactions of Chinese medicinal materials. We first evaluated the toxicity of PHS using <italic>C. elegans</italic>. Since most Chinese medicinal materials still lack detailed toxicity data, <italic>C. elegans</italic> will be a fast and systematic system for assessing the toxicity of Chinese medicinal materials.</p><p id="Par58">However, <italic>C. elegans</italic> is largely different from the human species and lack organs such as heart, kidney, lung, etc. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] Therefore <italic>C. elegans</italic> cannot completely replace traditional animal toxicology experiments such as rats. In the prepared PHS solution, there may be various chemical components. We only studied the toxicity of ethanol extract on <italic>C. elegans</italic> which means that our data may not fully reflect the biological effects of PHS prepared by other extraction methods. The toxicological effects of PHS and related toxicological mechanisms are rarely documented. For these reasons, extensive pharmacological and chemical experiments, as well as human metabolism, should be the focus of future research.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par59">Our study fully evaluated the toxicity effects of PHS on <italic>C. elegans</italic>, investigated the possible mechanism of the toxicity effects of PHS, and provided pharmacological research paradigm for the study of traditional medicine toxicity. The results will be helpful in understanding the probable toxicity effects of PHS and its underlying mechanism. In addition, the results provided new ideas and methods for the biological evaluation of the toxicity of Chinese medicinal materials.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AChE</term><def><p id="Par5">Acetylcholinesterase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>C. elegans</italic></term><def><p id="Par6"><italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>E. coli</italic> OP50</term><def><p id="Par7"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> OP50</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HPLC</term><def><p id="Par8">High performance liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IC<sub>50</sub></term><def><p id="Par9">Half-inhibitory concentration values</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NGM</term><def><p id="Par10">Nematode growth medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PHS</term><def><p id="Par11"><italic>Peganum harmala</italic> L. seeds</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qRT-PCR</term><def><p id="Par12">Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCM</term><def><p id="Par13">Traditional Chinese medicine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Vc</term><def><p id="Par14">Vitamin C</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are thankful to Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology for technical assistance.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>PT and YGL were in charge of study design and coordination, material support for obtained funding. XZM, XZ, YYY, YLZ, JG, NXK performed the experiments and statistical analysis. XZM wrote the manuscript. XKL, JRW corrected the final version of the manuscript. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Chinese Medicine Standardization Project (ZYBZH-Y-HUB-20) and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (2020-JYB-ZDGG-042), it supplied the reagents, herbs and instruments. Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology supplied <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> and technology.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par60">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par61">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par62">The authors declare that there are no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmoudian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jalilpour</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Salehian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity of Peganum harmala: review and a case report</article-title><source>Iranian J Pharmacol Therapeutics</source><year>2002</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jahaniani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebrahimi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahbar-Roshandel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Xanthomicrol is the main cytotoxic component of Dracocephalum kotschyii and a potential anti-cancer agent</article-title><source>Phytochemistry (Amsterdam)</source><year>2005</year><volume>66</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>1592</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zitterl-Eglseer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasnain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of peganum harmala or its &#x003b2; -carboline alkaloids on certain antibiotic resistant strains of bacteria and protozoa from poultry</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1533</fpage><lpage>1538</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18814210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18814210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farzin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidepressant-like effect of harmane and other &#x003b2;-carbolines in the mouse forced swim test</article-title><source>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16183262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of Harmalol and Harmaline on MPTP neurotoxicity in the mouse and dopamine-induced damage of brain mitochondria and PC12 cells</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>75</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10899927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10899927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on traditional uses, phytochemistry, pharmacology, pharmacokinetics and toxicology of the genus Peganum</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2017</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28359849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28359849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Ansari</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matlin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Four flavonoid glycosides from Peganum harmala</article-title><source>Phytochemistry.</source><year>1997</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9014375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9014375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Asgarpanah J. Chemistry, pharmacology and medicinal properties of Peganum harmala L. Afr J Pharm Pharmacol. 2012;6(22):1573&#x02013;80.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neil</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Merck index</source><year>1996</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang Y, Cheng X, Liu W, et al. Peganumine B-I and two enantiomers, new alkaloids from the seeds of Peganum harmala Linn and its potential cytotoxicity and cholinesterases inhibitory activities. Rsc Adv. 2016;6(19):15976&#x02013;87.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frison</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Favretto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zancanaro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A case of &#x003b2;-carboline alkaloid intoxication following ingestion of Peganum harmala seed extract</article-title><source>Forensic Sci Int</source><year>2008</year><volume>179</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>43</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of harmine, an acetylcholinesterase inhibitor, on spatial learning and memory of APP/PS1 transgenic mice and scopolamine-induced memory impairment mice</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>768</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26526348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26526348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analogous &#x003b2;-Carboline Alkaloids Harmaline and Harmine Ameliorate Scopolamine-Induced Cognition Dysfunction by Attenuating Acetylcholinesterase Activity, Oxidative Stress, and Inflammation in Mice</article-title><source>Frontiers Pharmacol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>346</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Luke</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modeling molecular and cellular aspects of human disease using the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Pediatr Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>65</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of Caenorhabditis-Elegans</article-title><source>Genetics.</source><year>1974</year><volume>77</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><?supplied-pmid 4366476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4366476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of developmental stage, salts and food presence on various end points using Caenorhabditis Elegans for aquatic toxicity testing</article-title><source>Environ Toxicol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>14</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2139</fpage><lpage>2147</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuerzenbaum</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single and double metallothionein knockout in the nematode C. elegans reveals cadmium dependent and independent toxic effects on life history traits</article-title><source>Environ Pollut</source><year>2007</year><volume>145</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17141712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17141712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pre-treatment with mild UV irradiation suppresses reproductive toxicity induced by subsequent cadmium exposure in nematodes</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol Environ Saf</source><year>2010</year><volume>73</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20045190?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20045190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellman</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtney</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A new and rapid colorimetric determination of Acetylcholinesterase activity</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>1961</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><?supplied-pmid 13726518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13726518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1976</year><volume>72</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><?supplied-pmid 942051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Beneficial effects of wheat gluten hydrolysate to extend lifespan and induce stress resistance in nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e74553</fpage><?supplied-pmid 24040279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24040279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and neuroprotective effects of Dictyophora indusiata polysaccharide in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2016</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27647012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27647012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandrasekar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhusudhana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determination of DPPH free radical scavenging activity by reversed-phase HPLC: a sensitive screening method for polyherbal formulations</article-title><source>J Pharm Biomed Anal</source><year>2006</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>460</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16297590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16297590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Boveris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroperoxide metabolism in mammalian organs</article-title><source>Physiol Rev</source><year>1979</year><volume>59</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><?supplied-pmid 37532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>MRS</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal properties of <italic>Foeniculum vulgare</italic> mill in traditional iranian medicine and modern phytotherapy</article-title><source>Chin J Integr Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>79</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Epstein HF, Shakes DC. Caenorhabditis elegans : modern biological analysis of an organism. San Diego: Acadmeic Press, Inc. 1995. p. 58.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The structure of the nervous system of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc B Biol Sci</source><year>1986</year><volume>314</volume><issue>1165</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acetylcholine</article-title><source>WormBook</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opperman</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nematode acetylcholinesterases: molecular forms and their potential role in nematode behavior</article-title><source>Parasitol Today</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>406</fpage><?supplied-pmid 15463554?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15463554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acetylcholinesterase inhibitive activity-guided isolation of two new alkaloids from seeds of Peganum nigellastrum Bunge by an in vitro TLC-bioautographic assay</article-title><source>Arch Pharm Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>32</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1245</fpage><lpage>1251</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19784581?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19784581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue-specific activities of C. elegans DAF-16 in the regulation of lifespan</article-title><source>Cell.</source><year>2003</year><volume>115</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14622602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14622602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braeckman</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanfleteren</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic control of longevity in C. elegans</article-title><source>Exp Gerontol</source><year>2007</year><volume>42</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16829009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeira</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant properties of &#x003b2;-carboline alkaloids are related to their antimutagenic and antigenotoxic activities</article-title><source>Mutagenesis.</source><year>2007</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17545209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17545209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roughani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Peganum Harmala L. extract reduces oxidative stress and improves symptoms in 6-Hydroxydopamine-induced Parkinson&#x02019;s disease in rats</article-title><source>Iran J Pharm Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27610168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27610168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000f6;ss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Henschel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haitzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toxicity of cadmium to Caenorhabditis elegans (Nematoda) in whole sediment and pore water&#x02014;the ambiguous role of organic matter</article-title><source>Environ Toxicol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2794</fpage><lpage>2801</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11764163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11764163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu-Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Silver nanoparticle behavior, uptake, and toxicity in\r, <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>\r, : effects of natural organic matter</article-title><source>Environ Sci Technol</source><year>2014</year><volume>48</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3486</fpage><lpage>3495</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24568198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24568198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dengg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meel</surname><given-names>JCAV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caenorhabditis elegans as model system for rapid toxicity assessment of pharmaceutical compounds</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Toxicol Methods</source><year>2004</year><volume>50</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15519907?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15519907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luciana</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorge</surname><given-names>FSF</given-names></name><name><surname>Anne</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Caenorhabditis elegans as a model to screen plant extracts and compounds as natural anthelmintics for veterinary use</article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2011</year><volume>182</volume><issue>2&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21680095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-specific transcriptional regulation of the major sperm protein in Caenorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1982</year><volume>93</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7128929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7128929</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>