<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Serum samples from the immunized mice were used in immunoassays (indirect ELISA) for the quantification of total IgG, IgG1 and IgG2a anti-rCP40 antibodies. Polystyrene 96-well plates (Maxisorp-Nunc) were coated with 100 μL of a bicarbonate-carbonate buffer (pH 9.8) containing 0.1 μg/well of rCP40 protein. Plates were incubated for 18 h at 4 °C and washed 3 times with PBS-T (PBS 1X, pH 7.4, 0.1% Tween 20). The plates were then incubated with 200 μL/well of 5% skim milk in PBS for 2 h at 37 °C, for blocking purposes. A three-step wash was then performed. All serum samples obtained from mice were diluted in PBS (v/v 1:50), and 100 μL of each diluted sample was added to the plates in duplicate. Plates were incubated for 1 h at 37 °C. After washing three times with PBS-T, 100 μL/well of anti-mouse IgG conjugated to horseradish peroxidase (Sigma-Aldrich) was added (1: 5,000 in PBS-T) to the plates in order to detect total IgG prior to the revelation step. In plates designated for the detection of IgG1 and IgG2a, 100 μL/well of either goat anti-mouse IgG1 (1: 5,000 in PBS-T) or goat anti-mouse IgG2a (1: 2,000 in PBS-T) was added. The plates were incubated at 37 °C for 1 h and then washed three times with PBS-T, subsequent to which 100 μL/well of anti-goat IgG conjugated to horseradish peroxidase (Sigma-Aldrich) was added (1: 5,000 in PBS-T). The plates were re-incubated for 1 h at 37 °C and then washed five times with PBS-T. The reaction was developed by the addition of 100 μL/well of the substrate-chromogen solution [
 <italic>o</italic>-phenylenediamine dihydrochloride; OPD tablets (Sigma-Aldrich) in 0.4 mg/mL phosphate-citrate buffer containing 0.04% of 30% hydrogen peroxide, pH = 5.0] and incubation at room temperature in the dark for 15 min, and it was stopped by the addition of 50 μL/well of H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> solution (4N). Optical density (OD) was determined using a microtiter-plate reader (Microplate Reader Mindray MR–96A) set at 492 nm.
</p>
