<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Holt and Hochberg, (
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>) outlined several explanations as to why postrelease adaptation of a target species may be weak in the context of biocontrol. First, the invasive species may lack genetic variation for defence traits. This scenario seems unlikely for 
 <italic>L. salicaria</italic>, which exhibits genetic variation across a broad range of traits in its introduced range (R. Colautti, 
 <italic>pers. comm</italic>.), including vigour, herbivore tolerance (Quiram, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), reproductive and vegetative size, and flowering phenology (Colautti &amp; Barrett, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Another possibility, that selection on defence is weak, seems unlikely given the clear impacts of herbivory on biomass and flowering revealed by our study. A more likely explanation for our findings is that fluctuating or variable selection for plant defence across populations, which is common in nature (Agrawal, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), weakens net selection on these traits (Cullen, Proost, &amp; Volenberg, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Muola et al., 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Many studies have demonstrated that herbivore damage in both the native and introduced ranges of 
 <italic>L. salicaria</italic> varies spatially and temporally (Boag &amp; Eckert, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Denoth &amp; Myers, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Hovick &amp; Carson, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Lehndal et al., 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Quiram, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; St. Louis et al., 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Given sufficient gene flow, variable selection within and among populations could explain the lack of evidence for population divergence in our study. Future studies should examine the degree to which the underlying genetic covariance structure, gene flow, variable intra‐ and inter‐population selection, and phenotypic plasticity contribute to the lack of population divergence in response to biocontrol observed in our field study.
</p>
