<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study offers several important insights into the trajectory and impacts of the 
 <italic>Neogalerucella</italic> spp. biocontrol programme on the management of 
 <italic>L. salicaria</italic> that were not previously evident due to a lack of large‐scale, long‐term studies under natural conditions. First, biocontrol has a strong impact on plant performance: defoliation by the biocontrol was an important predictor of annual fluctuations in plant biomass, and plants in our common garden took years to flower, compared to plants from the same populations grown in the greenhouse, which generally flowered within 3–4 months (M. Stastny, pers. obs.). This finding echoes other reports of the impacts of 
 <italic>Neogalerucella</italic> spp. feeding on 
 <italic>L. salicaria</italic> growth and phenology in field observations (e.g. Schat &amp; Blossey, 
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Yet, in spite of the impacts of herbivory on plant performance, we also observed an impressive ability of 
 <italic>L. salicaria</italic> to tolerate biocontrol and persist, often with marked seasonal fluctuations in growth patterns. For example, it was not unusual for a plant's above‐ground portion to go missing for an entire growing season, only to reappear the following year. In these cases, the plant was clearly maintaining below‐ground biomass following a severe bout of herbivory, but at the expense of stem, leaf and flower production. In a study of impacts of herbivory on carbon storage in the short lived perennial 
 <italic>Rorippa palustris</italic>, Sosnova and Klimesova, (
 <xref rid="eva13053-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>) demonstrated that the timing of herbivory predicted whether plants would allocate to annual reproduction or reserve storage for regrowth the following spring, which could also explain why some of our plants disappeared temporarily. Overall, our study highlights what is impossible to establish from prerelease studies of biocontrol—that under heavy biocontrol pressure in a natural setting, plants sourced from a range of populations are heavily impacted by herbivory, and that this has long‐term, year‐over‐year impacts on fitness‐associated traits.
</p>
