<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">EOs from the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia</italic> demonstrated antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effects. 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia dracunculus</italic> (tarragon) has been used for the treatment of pain and gastrointestinal disturbances in Iranian traditional medicine [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Maham et al. [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] evaluated both central and peripheral antinociceptive activity of tarragon EO in various experimental models. It was found that the EO possesses a potent antinociceptive effect. Similarly, another EO from 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia ludoviciana</italic> was also reported to possess antinociceptive activity, which was partially mediated by the opioid system [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. The aerial parts of 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia herba-alba</italic> are widely used to treat inflammatory disorders (colds, coughing, bronchitis, diarrhea) are infectious diseases (skin diseases, scabies, syphilis). Recent studies showed that appropriate doses of 
 <italic class="italic">A. herba-alba</italic> EO displayed both antifungal and anti-inflammatory activities. Thus, the findings justified and reinforced the use of this plant in traditional medicine [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Abu-Darwish et al. [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] characterized the chemical composition of 
 <italic class="italic">A. herba-alba</italic> EO from South Jordan and found that regular monoterpenes were predominant (39.3%) and the principal components were α- and β-thujone (27.7%). 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia judaica L.</italic> is a medicinal and aromatic plant growing in the valley bottoms of desert areas. Abu-Darwish et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-23-01061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] studied the chemical composition and biological activities of 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia judaica</italic> EO. They found that 
 <italic class="italic">A. judaica</italic> EO had antifungal and anti-inflammatory activities. For 
 <italic class="italic">A. judaica</italic> EO constituents, oxygenated monoterpenes are a representative group of constituents (68.7%) in the oil with piperitone (30.4%), camphor (16.1%), and ethyl cinnamate (11.0%) as the main compounds.
</p>
