<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In
 <italic class="italic"> R. carthamoides</italic> essential oil from roots of soil-grown plants aplotaxene (27%), nardosina-1(10),11-diene (21%), dauca-4(11),8-diene (10%), petasitene (4.3%), and
 <italic class="italic"> trans</italic>-
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-bergamotene (4.2%) were the major components which were not detected in the hairy roots essential oil. Aplotaxene has also previously been found to dominate in essential oil from
 <italic class="italic"> R. carthamoides</italic> roots and rhizomes by Havlik et al. [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. In addition, nardosina-1(10),11-diene and dauca-4(11),8-diene, petasitene, and
 <italic class="italic"> trans</italic>-
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-bergamotene were found for the first time in the
 <italic class="italic"> Rhaponticum carthamoides</italic> root essential oil in the present study. In contrast, Geszprych and Weglarz [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] found geraniol (17–18.3%), 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-caryophyllene (14.12–16.53%), and linalool (8.88–12.07%) to be main compounds in the essential oil of roots and rhizomes of
 <italic class="italic"> R. carthamoides</italic>. However, geraniol and linalool were not identified in the HR and SGR essential oils examined in the present work. The differences between the chemical compositions of the essential oils obtained in this study and those of others may be attributable to environmental factors (geographical, climatic, and seasonal), development stage, genetic variability, and the conditions of in vitro cultures [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Additionally, individual variability and chemotype exist within the same plant species, resulting in the differences in chemical compositions of the raw materials [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>].
</p>
