<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The tangerine essential oil caused statistically significant effects to the brain in different brain regions. It increased brain-wave sub band of beta wave power but decreased the alpha wave power [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This study shows the vigilance effect of undiluted tangerine oil. Beta wave power is observed when awake, especially active thinking, focused, high alert for mid beta wave power and fast idle and musing for low beta wave power [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Alpha wave power is observed during several states of mind or activities. Slow alpha wave power correlated with relaxed state, eyes close condition, calm state, and resting state. Fast alpha wave power correlated with idling state. The reduction of this brain wave power suggests a brain functional shift to a more alert state of mind of beta [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Limonene is a major component in tangerine oil detected by GC-MS. Another study found that autonomic nervous system was increased by (+)-limonene, which was observed by the increase of sympathetic activity parameters [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Sowndhararajan et al. also reported beta wave power increase by (+)-limonene inhalation [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The increase of alertness by tangerine oil or limonene might be because of several underlying brain processes and the psychological basis. Brainstem–thalamo–cortical pathways, suprachiasmatic nucleus—circadian rhythm, hypothalamo–pituitary–adrenal axis and limbic system, as well as the metabolic system and substrates need to be further investigated to explain the underlying mechanisms of these volatile fragrances [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The vigilance effect of tangerine oil is similar to rosemary oil. Previous study suggested that volatile organic in 
 <italic>Chrysanthemum indicum</italic>, 1,8-cineole, can increase the low beta at several sites, excluding frontal, parietal and occipital. By contrast, only frontal is detected in the present study [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In the case of mid beta wave of 15–20 Hz with high significance in active thinking and high alertness, Kim M. has shown that mid beta wave was increased during inhalation of (+)-α-pinene and terpinolene, which is correlated to decreased mid beta, indicating relaxation and reducing stress [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In addition, the effect of essential oil of 
 <italic>Inula helenium</italic> root decreases the mid beta but only in the parietal region [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Each region of the brain is responsible for different functions from homeostatic functions to higher functions. In this study, we divided electrodes into four groups representing frontal, centro-temporal, parietal, and occipital regions. The frontal area is responsible for many important cognitive functions such as working memory, calculation, motivation, and executive function. This brain region collaborates with other brain areas in other deep nuclei to do these elaborative functions. The alteration of brain activities in this brain area may correlate with the mentioned duties. The temporal lobe and central area of the brain are responsible for limbic system-related function, motor function and sensory function. The parietal region is responsible for associative function, and the occipital lobe is responsible for vision. Previous studies showed increased slow alpha in different regions. Neroli and grapefruit oils influenced activity in the occipital region, which indicates relaxation state and helps to reduce cortical deactivation [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The mixing of bergamot and lavender leads to the increase of relative fast and slow alpha waves in the prefrontal region, which is also helping to relax [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Orchid oil increased the parietal region activity [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Low beta is decreased during inhalation of (+)-α-pinene, which is specific in male subjects. The increase in beta wave has also been correlated with an enhanced drowsy state [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The decrease of fast alpha wave power was observed during resting and concentration period of mind. The other studies also showed the different results. When the subjects were exposure to agarwood incense, the fast alpha wave was significantly increased and increased during inhalation of (+)-α-pinene and (+)-β-pinene [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Moreover, the present study showed an emotional state after inhalation of the undiluted oil, which happens in the same way as brain wave power. The visual analog score of orchid oil inhalation also showed higher scores in elegance and freshness [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-04865" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
