<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Metabarcoding has become an effective method for molecular‐based biomonitoring programs and biosurveillance for invasive alien species (IAS; Makiola et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). This molecular technique involves high‐throughput sequencing (HTS), which facilitates the identification of multiple species using environmental DNA (eDNA) extracted from complex ecological samples (Creer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Taberlet et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Incorporating HTS into biosurveillance programs is advantageous as it can provide results faster than conventional identification methods, thereby allowing for early detection of species of concern, including IAS (Ruppert et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). The ability to obtain results fast, the existence of curated DNA reference libraries (Nilsson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Quast et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Ratnasingham &amp; Hebert, 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>), and the continued drop in the cost of HTS platforms have contributed to metabarcoding's rise in popularity in environmental monitoring (Cristescu, 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; de Kerdrel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Furthermore, as DNA reference libraries with associated morphological species identifications continue to grow, the time, effort, and resources that would otherwise be put toward morphological identification of specimens can be saved through the use of molecular identification methods. This is significant since the number of taxonomists available to conduct species identifications is declining. Reference libraries, therefore, provide a permanent repository of traditional taxonomic expertise that can be used with the appropriate molecular identification tools as needed (Cristescu, 
 <xref rid="ece37139-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).
</p>
