<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">In Europe, the introduction of the crayfish plague, 
 <italic>Aphanomyces astaci</italic>, from North America has decimated many indigenous crayfish species, which are much more susceptible to this pathogen than North American species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. Although sensitive to this plague, 
 <italic>A. leptodactylus</italic> is interestingly clustered together with two North American species that are known carriers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, 
 <italic>P. leniusculus</italic> was responsible for four recorded mass mortalities of the indigenous 
 <italic>Austropotamobius pallipes</italic> in France
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. This clustering likely results from the shared evolutionary history between 
 <italic>A. leptodactylus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. leniusculus</italic>, both belonging to the family 
 <italic>Astacidae</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. A phylogenetic signal such as this could outweigh the importance of other trait dissimilarities between species during clustering, which might be the case with crayfish plague resistance. In the Netherlands, 
 <italic>A. leptodactylus</italic> was found almost exclusively in fast flowing and brackish to saline waters, even though it is also adapted to lentic habitats
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Astacus leptodactylus</italic> only occurs near North American species at a few locations and is mainly found in water types where those species are absent. It could be excluded from many water types by presence of plague carriers, while its high salinity tolerance allows it to survive where the other species cannot. Similarly, 
 <italic>C. destructor</italic>, despite possessing several beneficial invasive traits is susceptible to the crayfish plague which might prevent successful establishment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. With the growing presence of crayfish from North America, it seems likely that plague resistance is mandatory to reach the final full invasive stage in the Netherlands.
</p>
