<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">Though a lot of work has been done with native antigens but most significant results were obtained after the discovery of Bm86 molecules from 
 <italic>R. microplus</italic> and development and commercialization of Bm86-based vaccines as TickGARD/Gavac against 
 <italic>R. microplus</italic> infestations on cattle (
 <xref rid="bib229" ref-type="bibr">Willadsen et al., 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">de la Fuente et al., 2007</xref>). On the similar line, protective efficacy of homologue of Bm86 gene in 
 <italic>Hyalomma</italic> species was studied. For example; 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">de Vos et al. (2001)</xref> identified a homologue of Bm86 in 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic> and reported 50 % protection against 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic> by limited immunization trial. Subsequently, 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Ebrahimi et al. (2012)</xref> successfully established the presence of cross-reactive epitopes between Bm86 and HAO3 antigens of 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib189" ref-type="bibr">Said et al. (2012a)</xref> cloned and characterized the Hd86 antigen from 
 <italic>H. scupense</italic>, an ortholog of the Bm86 gene and reported very low intra-specific diversity in amino acid sequences of Hd86 of different isolates of 
 <italic>H. scupense</italic> of Tunisia and a 59.1 % protection against the nymphal stage of 
 <italic>H. scupense</italic> and no protection against adults was reported (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Galai et al., 2012</xref>). To explain the variation in results, 
 <xref rid="bib188" ref-type="bibr">Said et al. (2013)</xref> determined the expression profile of Hd86 in different stages and demonstrated a significant reduction (p &lt; 0.001) in the number of transcripts level during the feeding period and particularly after moulting to adults (12.78 and 9.25 fold in unfed males and unfed females) respectively. Lower Hd86 mRNA levels in adult ticks may result in lower protein levels in immunized animals. Concurrently, 
 <xref rid="bib190" ref-type="bibr">Said et al. (2012b)</xref> studied Bm86 ortholog in four different 
 <italic>Hyalomma</italic> species, viz., 
 <italic>H. marginatum</italic> (Hm86), 
 <italic>H. excavatum</italic> (He86), 
 <italic>H. dromedarii</italic> (Hdr86) and 
 <italic>H. scupense</italic> (Hd86-A1) and suggested that Hd86-A1 vaccine candidate might be more appropriate to target 
 <italic>Hyalomma</italic> tick species in contrast to Bm86 commercial vaccines. 
 <xref rid="bib115" ref-type="bibr">Kopp et al. (2010)</xref> raised series of monoclonal antibodies against synthetic peptides of BD86, a Bm86 homologue of 
 <italic>R. decoloratus</italic> and detected strong signal of one of the antibodies (mAbs 12.1) in immunohistochemical analyses with the gut of four species of ticks including 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic>. But no further progress was reported to exploit the observation. Further, Haa86, a Bm86 homologue of 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic> was generated and tested against homologous challenge infestations. The protective efficacy was variable from 47- 60% against larvae and 40–80% against adults (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Azhahianambi et al., 2009a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2009b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Jeyabal et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2012a</xref>). Recently five antigens namely; Subolesin (SUB), Calreticulin (CRT), Cathepsin-L like cysteine protease (CathL), Ferritin 2 (FER2) and Tropomyosin (TPM) ortholog of 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic> were selected based on their established role in tick physiology and metabolism in different tick species. A very low level of variation of 0.6–2.4 %, 0.3–1.8 %, 0.3 to 6.4, 0.1–0.6% and 0.1–1.3 % in the deduced amino acid sequences of various field isolates of 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic> was observed in SUB, CRT, CathL, FER2 and TPM genes, respectively. Similarly, the amino acid sequence identity for the same genes in other ticks species was 77.4–99.3 %, 85.1–99.7 %, 57.5–89.5 %, 80.1–90.9 % and 98.8–99.9 % against reference 
 <italic>H. anatolicum</italic> IVRI II strain (
 <xref rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib139" ref-type="bibr">Manjunathachar et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
