<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">Following transcriptomic analysis of SUB, CRT, CathL, FER2 and TPM genes revealed that amongst all the life stages except in eggs and frustrated females, the differences in fold change in expression (FCE) of SUB gene was not significant (p &gt; 0.05). In eggs and in frustrated females (tick released on animal but not allowed them to feed for 24 h), relative expression of SUB gene was significantly (p &lt; 0.05) higher than in engorged larvae, nymphs, females and in unfed males. The differences in FCE of CRT gene were not significant (p &gt; 0.05) in all the life stages except in fed males and in between engorged larvae and females. The FCE of CathL gene was (p &lt; 0.001) highest in frustrated females followed by unfed females than in all other stages while differences in FCE were not significant (p &gt; 0.05) among all the other stages except in between eggs and larvae. Similarly, in FER2, only statistically significant (p &lt; 0.01) low FCE was recorded in eggs. Unlike FER2, the FCE of TPM gene was significantly (p &lt; 0.001) higher in fed larvae, nymphs, females, males and in the unfed adult stage (P &lt; 0.01) (
 <xref rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib139" ref-type="bibr">Manjunathachar et al., 2019</xref>). The functional properties of the genes were studied by RNA interference (RNAi) technology and following immunization of animals with recombinant proteins, SUB, TPM, FER2, CRT and CathL, 65.4%, 63.7%, 51.7 %, 41.3% and 30.2%, respectively, protection against larvae was observed. However, against adults, the TPM and FER2 proteins were more effective (
 <xref rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib139" ref-type="bibr">Manjunathachar et al., 2019</xref>). The results of different immunization studies clearly indicated that the majority of the experiments were conducted using the homologous challenge system and the protective efficacy of the antigens was variable. Further, it is emphasized that a multi-antigenic vaccine involving multi-targets is the suitable option for getting significant cross-protection against heterologous challenge (
 <xref rid="bib199" ref-type="bibr">Schetters and Jansen, 2015</xref>, PCT/EP2014/056248).
</p>
