<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alien invasive species refer to non-native species that migrate from their place of origin to a new ecological environment via natural or human-made means. They can reproduce in nature, resulting in damage to local biodiversity and impacts on the local ecological environment [
 <xref rid="B1-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. China suffers significantly from alien invasive species, and the annual economic loss caused by invasive species is as high as USD 119.876 billion [
 <xref rid="B2-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. To effectively prevent the harm caused by invasive species, it is essential to study their geographical distribution. The distribution of invasive species is affected by the interaction among species, the ability of species migration, climate, soil, hydrology, topography, and other factors, among which temperature is a critical factor [
 <xref rid="B3-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The relevant report of the United Nations Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) shows that, during the past 100 years, against the background of global warming, the global average surface temperature has increased by 0.85 °C, and the earth’s surface temperature will continue to show an upward trend in the future [
 <xref rid="B4-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In the context of future global warming, the temperature in China will rise by 1.6 to 5.0 °C [
 <xref rid="B6-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Many studies have shown that sustained climate warming may increase the tolerance of invasive species and expand their habitable areas, and they may form larger populations [
 <xref rid="B7-insects-12-00092" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Therefore, studying the potential geographical distribution pattern of invasive species in the context of future climate change has important theoretical and practical significance for putting forward reasonable and effective biodiversity conservation measures.
</p>
