<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dermatophytosis is one of the most common infections, affecting 20 to 25% of the world population. Among the most prevalent causative agents related to this infection, 
 <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic> species have been reported as responsible for infecting keratinized tissues such as nails, hairs, and skin [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Despite the great efforts in developing antifungal treatments, there is still a current necessity for treatments with high efficacy and low toxicity. Moreover, the opportunity of using plant-based materials for medical purposes is gaining attention among research groups [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Essential oils (EOs) are complex mixtures of natural compounds obtained mainly from herbs and spices [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. EOs have been used as an alternative therapeutic system to conventional drugs in view of their antinociceptive effects, antioxidant, antibacterial, and antifungal activity [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. For instance, Oregano essential oil (OEO) is extracted from Oregano (
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> L.), which has been recognized as one of the most important medicinal plants highly reputed as an efficient remedy for infectious diseases. OEO is mainly composed of carvacrol (57.4–69.6%), thymol (30.3–42.8%), cymene (17.7–51.3%), and terpinene (2.63–6.15%) [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. These bioactive compounds have strong antibacterial, antifungal, antiparasitic, cytotoxic, and antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, the high volatility, sensitivity, and relatively low stability of EOs may minimize their performance when intended for use as pharmaceutical agents [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-02880" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
