<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Arils are a rich source of sugars. Studies obtained from different countries have shown that the composition of sugars among pomegranate varieties might differ. Analyses of the sugars in pomegranate aril juice from 29 worldwide varieties grown in Israel and 19 cultivars from Spain have shown that fructose and glucose were the major sugars found in the arils, while sucrose and maltose were detected in lesser amounts. In some varieties, these two former sugars are the only sugars that were detected (Melgarejo et al., 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; Dafny-Yalin et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). In many studies the levels of fructose were similar to those of glucose in pomegranate juices, and both varied in different varieties by a factor of up to two-fold ranging from 4.2 to 8.5 g/100 g (Kalaycioglu and Erim, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>; Amir et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). In 76 Turkish varieties glucose levels showed a range of 4.2–8.3 g/100 g juice (Caliskan and Bayazit, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Forty Spanish varieties showed a range of 5.5–7.8 g/100 g (Melgarejo et al., 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>), 29 Israeli varieties showed a range of 4.8–6.6 g/100 g (Tzulker et al., 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>), and 30 Tunisian varieties showed a range of 5.7–8.5 g/100 g (Hasnaoui et al., 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). In addition to the main fructose and glucose sugars, some other sugars (arabinose, sucrose, and maltose) were also detected in several varieties at a relatively negligible level (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Examination of 30 Tunisian varieties that showed low concentrations of arabinose and sucrose (9- and 23-fold lower than glucose, respectively; Hasnaoui et al., 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Determination of sugar contents in 6 Spanish varieties has shown that they all contain maltose and sucrose, but possess 45- and 70-fold lower quantities of glucose, respectively (Legua et al., 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Sucrose was also found in an about 33-fold lower quantity than glucose in 6 Turkish varieties (Ozgen et al., 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) and an up to 13-fold lower quantity in 53 out of 76 varieties (Caliskan and Bayazit, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Maltose was only detected in one of 29 Israeli varieties (Dafny-Yalin et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
