<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The signification of β-amino acids has led to an increase in the number of synthetic methods for the preparation of that class of compounds [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Special attention has been paid to β-amino acid-based drug research in the field of medicinal chemistry (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00438-f002">Figure 2</xref>). Over the past decade, β-amino acid moiety has been successfully used in the design of bioactive ligands and novel biomaterials [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Usually, they are incorporated into β-peptides or other β-amino acid-containing oligomers, which may serve as promising tools in medicinal chemistry due to their enhanced biological stability, especially in the case of common proteolytic enzymes, arising from the lack of any interaction between them and in vivo enzymes [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. A large number of β-amino acids, e.g., β-amino acid with a pyrrolidine core, has been used as building blocks in the development of novel peptides exhibiting antimicrobial activities or being selective inhibitors of the TNF-α converting enzyme [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It is known that combinations of two or more biologically active compounds may provide to obtain new molecules with potential strengthened biological activities. Taking into consideration, Venepally et al. have designed and obtained heterocyclic-fatty acid hybrid molecules that exhibited anticancer and antimicrobial activities [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The biological analysis of fatty acid 3,4-dihydropyrimidinones (DHPM-fatty acids) obtained by Treptow et al. demonstrated that these types of compounds present antiproliferative activities on glioma cell lines (C6 rat and 
 <italic>U-</italic>138-MG human) [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. β-Amino acids are now of scientific interest due to their application in the synthesis of peptide mimetics and certain new biologically active substances. They are a constituent of some toxins and a special class of pore-forming lipopeptides, which exhibit antibacterial and antifungal activity. Peptidomimetics containing β-amino acids represent one of the strategies in developing therapeutic candidates with increased oral bioavailability and metabolic degradation resistance. Consequently, β-amino acids are potential inducers of secondary structures, and even single β-amino acid residues stabilize discrete conformations in cyclic peptides [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. When incorporated into the peptide sequence to improve proteolytic stability, highly functionalized cyclic β-amino acid moieties may have a significant impact on drug design [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
