<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the future looks bright, significant issues remain before the full potential of medicinal mushrooms can be reached. Specifically, during our review of the literature, we identified several significant gaps and areas for future research and development. In the first, there is an urgent need to identify the structures and mechanisms of action for active ingredients in many extracts and formulations from medicinal mushrooms. More rigorous chemical analyses as well as understanding the in vivo pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of individual compounds are needed to fill this gap of knowledge. The second promising area of study is to identify the genes and metabolic pathways involved in producing these immunomodulators in medicinal mushrooms. As shown above, aside from the few FIPs where the specific encoding genes have been identified, we have little information about the genes and how they are regulated in producing the other types of mushroom immunomodulators. While the availability of high through-put technologies and genome sequences are facilitating the discoveries, experimental investigations are needed in order to confirm and identify the conditions for increased productions of these compounds. Fortunately, gene editing technologies and -omics tools are becoming increasingly accessible to the broader life sciences communities. In the third, most immunomodulators described above exist in low quantities in medicinal mushrooms and their extractions can take a long time and be costly. For efficient production, it is very important to develop alternative approaches, e.g., by cloning and expressing the relevant biosynthesis genes in alternative hosts, using industrial fermentations, and developing efficient extraction and purification protocols from such commercial cell cultures. Lastly, the potential interactions between immunomodulators from mushrooms and other medicines, foods, and food supplements need to be critically analyzed in order to establish guidelines for safe and effective use of immunomodulators from medicinal mushrooms [
 <xref rid="B197-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. Indeed, at present, safety data about many medicinal mushroom products are not available from controlled clinical trials and associated negative side effects have been reported in several cases for certain types of usages of medicinal mushroom products [
 <xref rid="B198-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>,
 <xref rid="B199-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>]. There is also a cultural difference between Oriental and Western cultures about the use of medicinal mushrooms [
 <xref rid="B197-jof-06-00269" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>], presenting both a challenge and an opportunity for researchers and policy makers on the broad implications of these products on human health.
</p>
