<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a study by Lagha-Benamrouche et al. [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>], the antioxidant potentials of the peels and leaves of seven orange varieties obtained from Algeria were investigated by linoleic acid and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-carotene oxidation assays. The presence of phenolic compounds was also investigated. 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> cv. Bigarade was found to have the highest phenol level. The antioxidant activity assay was in accordance with the phytochemical findings. 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> displayed the highest action on slowing down the rate of linoleic acid and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-carotene oxidation [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. An antioxidant study was performed on the 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> fruits on different ripening stages. According to the outcome obtained from DPPH free radical-scavenging and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-carotene/linoleic acid systems, the antioxidant activity was found to be varied related to the amount of the phenolic components [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>]. Another antioxidant activity study revealed that during dehydration, different air-drying temperature affected the antioxidant effect of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> by-products, including peel and pulp remaining after juice extraction [
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> peel and juice were suggested as a new potential source of natural antioxidants; although, they were found to be less effective than butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT), butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA), and ascorbic acid, used as antioxidant standards [
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>]. Anti-inflammatory activity of the flavonoid-type compounds of Korean 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic>, namely, nobiletin, naringin, and hesperidin was investigated. Inhibition of proinflammatory mediators by blocking nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-ƘB) and mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling in lipopolysaccharide- (LPS-) stimulated RAW 264.7 macrophages was assessed [
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. The flavonoids were found to have the capacity to suppress the mRNA and protein expression of COX-2 and iNOS, by clarifying their anti-inflammatory action [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. A polymethoxy flavonoid-rich 
 <italic class="italic">C. aurantium</italic> extract was shown to have a protective effect on alcohol-induced liver injury in an animal study via AMPK and Nrf2-related signal regulation [
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>].
</p>
