<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the last several years, 
 <italic>T. polium</italic> has been tested and was considered to be a plant rich in antibacterial compounds [
 <xref rid="B56-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. In fact, it exerts antibacterial activities against Gram-negative and positive bacteria [
 <xref rid="B54-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Many research groups [
 <xref rid="B59-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] obtained the same result and demonstrated that the aspect, constituents, and architecture of the membranes of Gram-negative bacteria makes them more susceptible to the bioactive compounds present in methanolic extract. This finding could be explained by their hydrophilic outer membranes, composed of a single layer of peptidoglycan thatinvariably contains a unique component; lipopolysaccharide, which, in addition to proteins and phospholipids, makes the membranes more permeable for any antibacterial compound [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Therefore, the Gram-negative strains are more sensitive than Gram-positive bacteria. The antibacterial effect of the 
 <italic>Teucrium</italic> species has been widely demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In fact, Stanković et al. [
 <xref rid="B67-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] studied the antimicrobial activity of seven taxa of the genus 
 <italic>Teucrium</italic> and they used several solvents (21 extracts). The result indicated that the plant extract showed greater potential for antibacterial than antifungal activity. Darabpour et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] demonstrated that the 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> species were sensitive against 
 <italic>T. polium</italic> extract. The S. 
 <italic>aureus</italic> MDR was found to be one of the most resistant microorganisms against 
 <italic>T. polium</italic> leaves methanol extract [
 <xref rid="B68-plants-09-01418" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
