<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0415">There is evidence that the sesquiterpenoids found in AR have pharmacological properties of improving gastrointestinal function, anti-tumor and anti-inflammatory, so the presence of these compounds may be a key indicator of the quality of the extract (
 <xref rid="bib126" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2012</xref>). The processing of AR also influenced the physicochemical properties and absorption of polyacetylenes. The extraction efficiencies of atractylodin and (4E, 6E, 12E)-tetradecatriene-8, 10-diyne-1, 3-diyl diacetate from AR were decreased when the rhizomes were stir-fried with bran compared to crude rhizomes (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2013</xref>). However, the processing of AR could increase the absorption of atractylodin. Stirfrying of AR with wheat bran could promote and accelerate the absorption of (4E, 6E, 12E)-tetradecatrinen-8,10-diyne-1, 3-diyl diacetate and its concentration was highest in the spleen, possibly increasing the spleen-tonifying effect according to the traditional theory (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Kim, 2016</xref>). Stability is another concerning issue as the occurrences of bioactive polyacetylenes can be changed under certain circumstances, like drying of the rhizomes under the sun. Atractylodin, atractylodinol, and acetylatractylodinol were reported to have 1-cis isomers, (1Z)-atractylodin, (1Z)-atractylodinol, and (1Z)- acetylatractylodinol. The proportions of those cis isomers were less than trans isomers as the cis isomers could be formed during the drying process of the AR under the sun. For example, (1E)-acetylatractylodinol is rapidly isomerized to (1Z)-acetylatractylodinol. On the one hand, the stabilities of 1-cis isomers were weaker than those of 1-trans isomers: (1Z)-acetylatractylodinol more expeditiously disappeared in n-hexane solution compared to (1E)-acetylatractylodinol dissolved in same solvent in the freezer. On the other hand, 1-cis isomer of atractylodin was relatively increased up to a similar ratio with its parent compound, atractylodin, in freezer storage, indicating that atractylodin was considerably unstable than its isomer and different from those two polyacetylenes, (1E)-atractylodinol and (1Z)-atractylodinol, which showed the same degree of instability (
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Resch et al., 2001</xref>).
</p>
