<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0420">According to the TCM theory, genuine (Dao-di) herb is a high-quality medicine produced from specific areas, with a long history of traditional use and excellent efficacy (
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>). Mao Cangzhu is considered a fine-quality good beginning from Hongjing Tao in the Northern and Southern Dynasties (386–589 A.D.). It has been used for more than 1500 years and it is found in Maoshan in Jiangsu Province. Cangzhu always takes Maoshan as geo-authentic habitats. The volatile oil components of AR vary considerably and are distributed continuously. According to the composition of the volatile oil of AR, it can be divided into two chemical types. One is represented by “Hubei Cangzhu”, which is mainly found in Hubei, Anhui, Shaanxi, Southern Henan and other places. The total amount of the volatile oil in Hubei type (HBA) is high, and mainly composed of hinesol and β-cineole, with or without very small amounts of atractylone and atractylodin. The other type, Maoshan type (MA), is mainly represented in Maoshan, Jiangsu Province, including Jiangsu, Shandong, Hebei and northern Henan. Its total volatile oil is low, and mainly composed of atractylone and atractylodin. In the volatile oil, atractylone, hinesol,β-eudesmol,atractylodin showed a specific ratio. In MA, their ratio is 0.70–2.00: 0.04–0.35: 0.09–0.40: 1 (
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2008</xref>). These results showed that 91% of the measured values are in this range. The clustering results of HPLC fingerprint of the water extract of AR were similar to those of the volatile components. The main components of “white frost” in AR are citronellol and β-cineole. The content of these two components in Mao Cangzhu is much higher than that in unfamous-region AR. The content of atractylone, which is the main component of the cinnabar point of Mao Cangzhu, is 25.92% of the total volatile oil of AR. The average content of atractylone in other production areas is only 0.69% of the total volatile oil, but this component was detected in some samples (
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2002</xref>). Thus, atractylone is essential in reflecting the genuine characteristics of AR, suggesting that the efficacy of AR is more similar to that of AM. The strong ability of AR in drying dampness and strengthening the spleen is the reason why it has become a genuine medicine compared with the AR from other places of origin. Generally, phenotypic variation is a product of both genetic and environmental variation (
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">O'Reilly-Wapstra et al., 2013</xref>). The qualities of AR samples are closely associated with their habitat, and the contents of curative components in AR vary considerably based on geographical factors. However, it remains unclear whether the geographical variations are based on genetic or environmental factors. At the colony levels, as a genuine medicinal material of AR, the phenotype (volatile oil) of AR has obvious differentiation, but at the same time, its genetic differentiation is not significant. It can be seen that the larger phenotypic variation and the smaller genetic variation of AR are inconsistent, and the correlation between them is poor. All of these suggest that in addition to genetic factors, the environment is even a very important factor in the formation of herbal medicine of AR. Japanese scholars also confirmed this point by transplanting AR. 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Takeda et al. (1996)</xref> found that the volatile oil composition of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>, 
 <italic>A. chinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>A. koreana</italic> was closer to that of 2–3 years after it was transplanted to Nanjing Institute of Botany. The climate of Maoshan area is characterized by high temperatures, short dry season and sufficient rainfall. The unique ratio of volatile oil of AR may be the result of the specific metabolism of AR caused by a specific environment. The meteorological conditions in October have the greatest impact on the volatile oil components. The annual average and the meteorological conditions in February and September have a greater impact on the volatile oil components. High temperature is the limiting factor for the growth and development of AR, while several meteorological factors related to temperature in Maoshan area are the highest in the whole distribution area (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Guo, 2005</xref>). The formation of AR has an obvious adverse effect. Some studies have reported that the activation of phytohormones such as jasmonic acid and abscisic acid through symbiosis with several endophytes induces the production of the essential oil compounds in 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib136" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al. (2009)</xref> found that soil acidity stimulated the accumulation of essential oils in 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>, particularly β-eudesmol, by influencing the concentrations of phytohormones such as abscisic acid. These results suggested that the contents of essential oil compounds in 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> could vary depending on environmental factors such as biological and abiotic stresses. In contrast, 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Takeda et al. (1996)</xref> suggested that the contents of essential oil compounds are influenced largely by genetic factors based on a comparative study of the essential oil compounds between wild and cultivated 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic>. To examine genotype-environment (G × E) interaction and the effects of environmental factors, 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">Tsusaka et al. (2019)</xref> cultivated six clones in different years and different locations (Hokkaido, Ibaraki), and determined contents of β-eudesmol, hinesol, atractylon, and atractylodin in the clones. Subsequently, genetic variances, environmental variances, and G × E interaction variance based on the compound contents were evaluated. It is demonstrated that the contents of β-eudesmol, hinesol, atractylon, and atractylodin in 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> are influenced mainly by genetic factors. In addition, these essential oil compounds could be selected regardless of rhizome yields in the course of 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> cultivar development. Consequently, 
 <italic>A. lancea</italic> cultivars with high yields and high contents of the essential oil compounds could be developed and a further investigation on the effects of environment factors on the compound contents is a must.
</p>
