<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cloning, expression, and purification through Ni-Sepharose and resource S cation exchange chromatography yielded an active dimeric FIV-RT, which was then used for screening of anti-FIV-RT agents. The inhibition studies revealed that the extracts from 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> showed strong inhibitory activity against FIV-RT with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.80±0.16 and 1.22±0.20 μg/mL for 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> D-EtOH and 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> D-Hex, respectively. 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> is classified as a medicinal mushroom and has been used in traditional medicine for the prophylaxis and treatment of various diseases such as gastric disorder, diabetes mellitus, cancers, cardiovascular, and viral infection diseases [
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The water/ethanol extract of 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> showed anti-herpes simplex virus (HSV) type 1 activity in infected Vero cells [
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The extract showed the IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 3.82 and 12.29 μg/mL in the plaque reduction and HSV-1/blue assays, respectively [
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The 5 μg/mL rate of 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> extract could protect the infected cells from HSV-induced cytodestruction. The best protective effect was observed when 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> extracts were added before or within 1 h after HSV infection [
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The mechanism of anti-HSV was found to be at the initial stage of viral infection by inhibiting membrane fusion between HSV and Vero cells. In addition, 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> extract showed anti-hepatitis C virus, human influenza viruses A and B, and human immunodeficiency virus type 1 activity in cell-based assays [
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Chemical analysis of the methanol extract of 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> revealed that it contains protocatechuic acid which has been shown to have antioxidant, antibacterial, antiviral, and immune regulating activities [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Moreover, Tian 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] stated that polysaccharides from 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> (IOPs) could act as a broad-spectrum antiviral drug against feline calicivirus, feline herpesvirus 1, feline influenza virus H3N2 and H5N6, feline panleukopenia virus, and feline infectious peritonitis virus by blocking viral binding/absorption and replication. From these studies, the bioactive compounds responsible for anti-FIV-RT activity in 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> extract might be protocatechuic acid or IOPs. The solvents and methods used to obtain the extracts from mushrooms could affect the chemical constituents in the extracts [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Therefore, it is mandatory that further studies will be performed to clarify whether these compounds or other specific components are responsible for anti-FIV-RT property of 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic>.
</p>
