<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="app1-microorganisms-08-01619">
  <title>Supplementary Materials</title>
  <p>The following Supplementary Materials are available online at 
   <uri xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/8/10/1619/s1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.mdpi.com/2076-2607/8/10/1619/s1</uri>, S1. Map showing the geographic location of the sampling sites in the barrier island of Schiermonnikoog, The Netherlands. S2. Data of the plant traits, intensity of mycorrhizal colonization and plant litter mass from each of the sampling sites. S3. Details of the soil physicochemical methodology. S4. Table showing the values of soil physicochemical parameters. S5. Boxplots displaying the richness of the Bacterial Amplicon Sequence Variants (ASVs) comparing communities (panel A) and elevations (panel B-D). S6. Boxplots displaying the Shannon diversity index of the Bacterial Amplicon Sequence Variants (ASVs) comparing communities (panel A) and elevations (panel B-D). S7. Boxplots displaying the Faith phylogenetic diversity index of the Bacterial Amplicon Sequence Variants (ASVs) comparing communities (panel A) and elevations (panel B–D). S8. Principal coordinate analysis based on unweighted Unifrac and Bray-Curtis dissimilarity distances of the composition of bacterial communities from the root endosphere, rhizosphere and bulk soil (upper panel). In the lower panel, the table is showing the one-way permutational multivariate analysis of variance with the influence of elevation and community type on the variation in bacterial composition S9. Principal component analysis (PCA) showing the variation among sites in terms of soil physicochemical parameters and plant traits and environmental factors. S10. Potential functional differences among elevations in each type of community. S11. Barplots showing the relative abundance of the potential bacterial functions that showed a tendency to be higher in high or low elevation sites.
  </p>
 </app>
</app-group>
