<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Redox homeostasis of human body cells, including skin cells, is important for intracellular metabolism, which determines the proper functioning of the organism. The redox balance depends on the amount of free radicals produced and the cell’s antioxidant capacity to counteract their cellular activity [
 <xref rid="B23-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, as a result of disorders of cell metabolism, as well as the action of environmental factors such as UV radiation, there is a disruption of cell redox balance and the development of disease states, including cancer [
 <xref rid="B24-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This situation is usually accompanied by overproduction of highly reactive oxygen species (ROS), which act as short-term signaling molecules and stimulate the production of additional mediators, including lipid peroxidation products [
 <xref rid="B25-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Lipid peroxidation products play an important causal role in the initiation and development of diseases [
 <xref rid="B26-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Skin epidermis subtracts unique mixture of lipids (mainly ceramide, cholesterol, and other fatty acids) that forms natural permeability barrier. Free radicals such as superoxide radicals, hydroxyl radicals, and singled oxygen disrupts the natural defense of the skin by reacting with skin lipids, which leaves skin exposed to negative environment. Antioxidants such as polyphenolic compounds scavenge free radicals by inhibiting the initiation or propagation of oxidative chain reactions and can protect organism against serious diseases including cancer [
 <xref rid="B27-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Essential oils of aromatic medical plants are the source of the bioactive compounds that may protect skin cells due to their anti-inflammatory, antibacterial and antioxidant properties [
 <xref rid="B28-antioxidants-10-00053" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
