<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, yam contains dietary fiber, which plays a vital role in the digestive system of humans as well as animals. Adequate intake of fiber increases water holding capacity, aids in regular bowel movement, fecal bulkiness and less intestinal transit. It also promotes beneficial physiological effects such as reduction of blood sugar and cholesterol level, trapping of toxic substances and encourages the growth of natural microbial flora in the gut [
 <xref rid="B94-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. The crude fiber reported in different species of yam ranged between 0.17% and 18.2% with the minimum and maximum concentrations being recorded in 
 <italic>D. cayenensis</italic> and 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic>, respectively. Several dietary fiber constituents such as hemicelluloses, cellulose, lignin and pectins have been reported in yam. Abara et al. [
 <xref rid="B98-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] examined the dietary fiber components of four raw and cooked 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species (
 <italic>D. alata</italic>, 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic>, 
 <italic>D. cayenensis</italic> and 
 <italic>D. rotundata</italic>) using detergent system analysis and reported low levels of fiber components ranging from 0.08%–0.27% (lignin), 0.80%–1.13% (cellulose) and 0.15%–0.28% (hemicelluloses). Interestingly, no significant difference in dietary fiber was observed between the raw and cooked yams, irrespective of their species. Among the species investigated, 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic> had the highest cellulose and hemicelluloses while lignin was higher in 
 <italic>D. alata</italic>. A recent study investigated cell wall carbohydrates of 43 genotypes from five yam species (
 <italic>D. rotundata</italic>, 
 <italic>D. alata</italic>, 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic>, 
 <italic>D. cayenensis</italic> and 
 <italic>D. dumetorum</italic>) using detergent system analysis and recorded the highest cell wall carbohydrate in 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic> at 2.1%, 3.2% and 1.1% for hemicelluloses, cellulose and lignin, respectively [
 <xref rid="B99-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. The discrepancies of the values in the two studies may be attributed to genotypic variations as highlighted by Otegbayo et al. [
 <xref rid="B99-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. In line with this fact, Shajeela et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] observed a higher crude lipid content in 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic> when compared to the other nine 
 <italic>Dioscorea</italic> species investigated. Among the two varieties of 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic> tubers studied by these authors, 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic> var 
 <italic>dukhumensis</italic> (7.42 g/100 g) was reported to contain higher crude lipid than the variety 
 <italic>oppositifolia</italic> (4.40 g/100 g). This trend was also observed for crude protein, with 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic> var 
 <italic>dukhumensis</italic> having higher crude protein content of 13.42 g/100 g compared to 8.44 g/100 g recorded for 
 <italic>D. oppositifolia</italic> var 
 <italic>oppositifolia</italic> [
 <xref rid="B51-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. This is in agreement with an earlier study by Arinathan et al. [
 <xref rid="B100-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. 
</p>
