<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Actinomyces had served as the sources of novel antibiotic and bioactive molecule candidates with application in many fields (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Ramesh and Mathivanan, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Genilloud et al., 2011</xref>). Today, the exploitation of actinomycetes with bioactive metabolites from unexplored or extreme ecosystems may be an efficient way to satisfy the everlasting demand for novel natural products, which have antimicrobial and therapeutic properties to combat human and plant pathogens (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Intra et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Ouyang et al., 2011</xref>). During the last decades, the research of actinomycetes in several alpine habitats has gained some remarkable results. For example, the study in the high Arctic permafrost of Spitsbergen has shown that there is a high diversity of actinobacterial communities in this alpine soil and many of the phylotypes identified may represent novel, uncultured species, which might be the sources of genetic diversity and ultimately novel bioactive compounds (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Hansen et al., 2007</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Ivanova et al. (2009)</xref> presented that a large amount of trehalose and glycerol as cryopreservation additives produced by 
 <italic>Streptomyces</italic> spp. from the permafrost in Spitsbergen could be a reason for the strains to survive in cold and dry conditions. Further studies revealed that production of a range of bioactive metabolites including antibiotics, trehalose, lipase and pigment by actinobacteria from alpine cold habitats, could be a strategy for the strains in response to harsh environmental conditions (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Fong et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Dillon et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Babalola et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Ivanova et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Sivalingam et al., 2019</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Malviya et al. (2009)</xref> documented that some 
 <italic>Streptomyces</italic> isolates from alpine zones of Pindari glacier region in Indian Himalaya exhibited strong antifungal properties. These findings provide evidence that a wide diversity of Actinobacteria can survive in alpine environments, and most of which could yield bioactive compounds. In addition, as pivotal participants in the biogeochemical cycles, actinobacteria were known to possess diverse physiology and metabolic flexibility to survive in unfavorable environments (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Shivlata and Satyanarayana, 2015</xref>). Thus exploring the phylogenetic and physiological diversity patterns of alpine actinomycetes may provide an opportunity for selecting strains that are under environmental pressures, which may drive adaptions that produce unique biosynthetic or hydrolytic capabilities.
</p>
