<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Greenhouse results provided insight into the potential mechanisms through which AC may increase the relative abundance of native plant growth. A number of positive and negative interactions occur among plant roots, soils and soil organisms that can affect plant growth (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU072F6">6</xref>). Because AC binds organic molecules we suggest that AC is likely to decrease plant–soil communication and subsequent interactions. Therefore, we suggest that the decrease in plant growth caused by AC was more likely to be caused by decreases in positive plant–soil interactions (i.e. E, F and J in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU072F6">6</xref>) than by increases in negative plant–soil interactions (i.e. B, C, G, I and K in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU072F6">6</xref>). Results from our sterilization experiment in the greenhouse indicated that AC effects were only realized in live soils. Thus, AC did not appear to affect plant growth by suppressing facilitation or self-promotion (i.e. A and D in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="PLU072F6">6</xref>). The most likely potential mechanisms remaining are suppression of symbioses, suppression of pathogen defence and suppression of increased nutrient cycling (
 <xref rid="PLU072C21" ref-type="bibr">Hawkes 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2005
 </xref>). Results from our current and previous field experiments suggest that AC does not increase nutrient availability (
 <xref rid="PLU072C28" ref-type="bibr">Kulmatiski and Beard 2006</xref>). Therefore, we suggest that the most likely mechanisms through which AC affects plant growth is by suppressing (i) the development of symbiotic relationships between plants and soil organisms (
 <xref rid="PLU072C10" ref-type="bibr">Callaway and Aschehoug 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU072C34" ref-type="bibr">Mangla 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2008
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU072C48" ref-type="bibr">Weißhuhn and Prati 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU072C49" ref-type="bibr">Wurst and Van Beersum 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU072C27" ref-type="bibr">Kulmatiski 2011</xref>) or (ii) the pathogen defence (
 <xref rid="PLU072C46" ref-type="bibr">Van der Putten 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU072C4" ref-type="bibr">Bais 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2004
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU072C36" ref-type="bibr">Orians and Ward 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU072C16" ref-type="bibr">Doornbos 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>). Future experiments would be needed to distinguish the importance of these two mechanisms. 
</p>
