<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The antioxidant capacity of feeds and milk was determined using the oxygen radical absorbance capacity (ORAC) method based on the fluorescence decay rate of a probe in the presence of a radical oxygen species as compared with that of a reference standard, Trolox (6-hydroxy-2,5,7,8-tetramethylchroman-2-carboxylic acid, Sigma-Aldrich, Steinheim, Germany). The hydrophilic and lipophilic fractions of the milk samples (5 g) or feed sample (5 g of finely powdered feed) were extracted according to Prior et al. [
 <xref rid="B22-animals-09-00283" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] to evaluate the lipophilic (L-ORAC) and hydrophilic (H-ORAC) ORAC. Measurements of L-ORAC and H-ORAC in the samples were performed separately, and the total antioxidant capacity (TAC) was calculated by summing the L-ORAC and H-ORAC values, as described by Wu et al. [
 <xref rid="B23-animals-09-00283" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. The ORAC assays were carried out on a FLUOstar OPTIMA microplate fluorescence reader (BMG LABTECH, Offenburg, Germany) set at an excitation wavelength of 485 nm and an emission wavelength of 520 nm. The procedure was based on the method of Zulueta et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-animals-09-00283" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] with slight modifications. Briefly, 2,20-azobis (2-methylpropionamide) dihydrochloride (AAPH; Sigma-Aldrich) was used as peroxyl radical generator, Trolox was used as a reference antioxidant standard, and fluorescein was used as a fluorescent probe. A 100 µL volume of diluted sample, blank or Trolox calibration solution (10–80 µmol) was mixed with 1 mL of fluorescein (80 nM). Then, 200 µL of each mixture was placed in a well of the microplate. The microplate was placed in the reader and pre-incubated for 20 min at 37 °C. To each well, 60 µL of AAPH was automatically added to initiate the reaction and the fluorescence was recorded every 1.9 min. All the reaction mixtures were prepared in duplicate, and at least three independent assays were performed for each sample. The final ORAC values were calculated by using a linear regression equation (Y = a + bX) to describe the relationship between the Trolox concentration (Y, 10–80 µM Trolox) and the net area under the fluorescence decay curve (X). The data were expressed as µmol Trolox equivalents (TE) per g of sample by applying the following formula:
 <disp-formula class="disp-formula">ORAC (μmol TE) = [CTrolox (AUCSample − AUCBlank) k] / (AUCTrolox − AUCBlank)</disp-formula> where, CTrolox is the concentration of Trolox, k is the sample dilution factor, and AUC is the area below the fluorescence decay curve of the sample, the blank, and Trolox, respectively, calculated by applying the following formula [
 <xref rid="B25-animals-09-00283" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] 
 <disp-formula class="disp-formula">AUC = 0.5 + f1 / f0 + … fi / f0,</disp-formula> where, f1 is the initial fluorescence reading at t = 0 min and fi is the fluorescence reading at time = i. The net AUC for each sample was obtained by subtracting the AUC of the corresponding blank from that of the sample.
</p>
