<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In an attempt to investigate the molecular basis of terpene biosynthesis in 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic>, an RNA-seq approach was employed to sequence the stem transcriptome from high and low oil-yielding trees. After transcriptome assembly, the total number, N50 length and mean length of 
 <italic class="italic">de novo</italic> assembled transcipts and unigenes of 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic> were much higher than those recently reported in other non-model plants including 
 <italic class="italic">Carya illinoinensis</italic> (Mo et al., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">Kandelia obovata</italic> (Hong et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">Kalopanax septemlobus</italic> (Han et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia officinalis</italic> (Ali et al., 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>), and 
 <italic class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia</italic> (Bustos-Segura et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>), suggesting high accuracy and reliability of the sequencing data. Numerous annotated unigenes (61.9%) were found to be distributed in the Fabaceae family, which was reasonable since 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic> belongs to the Caesalpinioideae subfamily that is included in the Fabaceae family. Both GO and KEGG enrichment analysis of DEGs in H10 and H12 compared to L4 and L6 revealed that the terpene biosynthesis process and the plant hormone signal transduction pathway may play roles in determining the terpene variation in 
 <italic class="italic">S. glabra</italic>. However, even plants belonging to the same type (low- or high-producing type) exhibited enormous differences in gene expression profiles (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">2A</xref>). These DEGs between H10 and H12 or between L4 and L6 may be accountable for the difference in the ratio of different terpene compounds (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1A</xref>).
</p>
