<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Six wild-type (
 <italic>n</italic> = 6) 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> isolated, according to National Mastitis Council procedure [
 <xref rid="B40-antibiotics-10-00222" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], from subclinical mastitis Holstein cows were used. The protocol followed the Guide for the Care and Use of Agricultural Animals in Agricultural Research and Teaching (Federation of Animal Science Societies—FASS) and was approved by the Institutional Committee (CICUAL) of the Faculty of Veterinary Sciences, National University of La Plata, Buenos Aires, Argentina (47.3.15J). The strains were identified phenotypically as a Gram-positive, catalase-positive, β-hemolytic, Voges Proskauer-positive fermentation of trehalose, mannitol, and maltose. The isolates are part of the strains collection of our Laboratory (Laboratorio de Estudios Farmacológicos y Toxicológicos -LEFyT- Faculty of Veterinary Sciences, UNLP). Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) of EO were established by broth microdilution method in 96-well polystyrene microplates (Becton Dickinson
 <sup>®</sup>). Mueller Hinton Broth (MHB) culture medium was used with the addition of 0.5% of Tween 80. This surfactant enhanced the dissolution of the EO in the aqueous culture medium. MICs and MBCs were evaluated at 3 different pH to emulate extracellular and intracellular (inside cytosol or phagolysosome) conditions where 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> was internalized (7.4, 6.5, and 5.0, respectively). This pH adjustment of the medium was carried out by addition of HCl to the broth. The range of essential oil concentrations evaluated was 50 to 0.09 µL/mL, and each plate was inoculated with a final bacterial concentration of 5 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> CFU/mL and incubated at 35 °C for 18–24 h. MIC was established as the lowest concentration inhibiting bacterial growth. Positive (without antimicrobials) and negative controls (without antimicrobials and inoculums) with MHB containing 0.5% Tween 80 were performed. Every determination for each strain was evaluated at the different 3 pH conditions by triplicate. For quality control, 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> ATCC 29213
 <sup>®</sup> was used, and the susceptibility to erythromycin was checked for this strain by the control procedure [
 <xref rid="B26-antibiotics-10-00222" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
