<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">There was no significant drip loss after 24 h for LL muscle of lambs fed T3 diets and this was in agreement with Yarali et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>] who suggested that this could be due to the fat thickness of the carcasses. A study has demonstrated that the carcasses of high and medium dietary energy groups had a low percentage of evaporation loss due to the improved fatness of their carcasses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>]. In contrast, feeding animals with oil-source diets decreased drip loss in the 
 <italic class="italic">semimembranosus</italic> muscle because of a decline in protein oxidation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>]. However, this study showed that dietary corn has an effect on the cooking loss of lamb meat with the loss being the highest for the SS muscles in 10% corn. Cooking loss was affected by corn supply, which reduced the LL muscle of this parameter for both 5% corn and 10% corn (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). This is favorable since meat with lower water-holding capacity will lose water resulting in a higher cooking loss. The results are in agreement with Yarali et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>] who showed that the various ways of cooking and muscle sections produced different values in different studies. The cooking loss (mean 26.55%) in this study was within a reasonable range. Previous research has shown the potential of using alternative feed ingredients without degrading carcass characteristics and meat quality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. This could explain why PKC has no effect on the meat quality of lambs and that the variations among treatments may be due to the inclusion of corn in the diet. The study by Fadil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>] noted that higher cooking loss was observed in the meat of kids fed a low-energy diet while other studies suggest that a more acceptable reason was related to the pH of the meat [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>]. In this study, shear force decreased significantly in 5% corn and 10% corn compared with the control group although still remaining within the acceptable limits of 3.26 kg/cm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> or less in terms of tenderness of the meat [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. The increase in the body weight of animals fed on corn diets led to a reduction in the tenderness of the meat, especially in 5% corn and 10% corn. The study has stated that shear-force values decreased as weight increased [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. Another study by Yarali et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>] note that the maximum shear force value was derived from the 
 <italic class="italic">M. semitendinosus</italic> muscle, while the 
 <italic class="italic">M. longissimus dorsal</italic> muscle offered the most tender meat. In this study, the mean pH values were from 5.63 to 6.74 at 24 h post mortem. These results are on par with the findings of [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>] and within the acceptable range of lambs meat. Lambs fed on 5% corn had higher pH in the ST and SS muscles, according to [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>] the pH of meat from 5.4–5.5 is characterized as normal and has the highest desirable eating properties. Previous study has done by [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>] reported the meat’s tenderness was greater when pH rises from 5.5 to 6.0. A possible explanation could be the lower proteolytic activity at intermediate levels of pH (5.8 to 6.3) as it is outside the pH optima for two separate enzyme systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>]. The pH is negatively correlated to cooking loss [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>], thus changes in pH loss values observed at 24 h in the ST and SS muscles justify the decline in cooking loss of lambs fed 5% corn. In this study, the selected muscles reflected different responses to meat color with regard to dietary treatments as these authors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>] repoert that diet contain on polyphenols could effect on meat color by effecting on myoglobin. The inclusion corn increased the L* of the SS and LL muscles for Dorper lambs. The obtained data agrees with Juarez et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>] who reported that higher L* was attributed to the slaughter weight of the Merino sheep breed. This finding shows significant negative correlation between the L* value of the meat and the pH of the muscle. However, because there were no differences in the a* color of the other muscles it is difficult to determine that diets supplemented with PKC were solely responsible for the improved stability of meat color [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>]. Lambs in this study had an alert in b* of the ST muscle but had no significant values for the SS and LL muscles. These results are similar to a study conducted by [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. The treatment differences in color appear to be due to variations in muscular myoglobin contents or in the fat content of the carcasses. As such, an increase in intramuscular fat might lead to reduced myoglobin and sarcoplasmic protein concentrations in the meat, inducing differences in the meat color [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>].
</p>
