<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="s2001">
  <title>Purpose</title>
  <p>The management of pain and inflammation with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and opioid analgesics are currently encountering severe adverse reactions. To overcome these problems, herbal remedies may offer new alternative medicines. 
   <italic>Hygrophila schulli</italic> is a medicinal plant traditionally used for the treatment of pain and inflammation-related disorders; yet, these claims are not scientifically validated. Hence, this study was aimed to validate the traditional use of 
   <italic>Hygrophila schulli</italic> leaves as anti-inflammatory and analgesic remedy.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>In vitro anti-hyaluronidase assay and in vivo carrageenan-induced hind paw oedema model were used to evaluate the anti-inflammatory property of ethanolic leaf extract of 
   <italic>Hygrophila schulli</italic>. Tail immersion and acetic acid-induced writhing tests were performed to determine the central and peripheral analgesic activity of the leaf extract, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The ethanolic leaf extract exhibited significant anti-hyaluronidase activity (
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) and significant inhibition of carrageenan-induced paw oedema (
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) compared to untreated controls. Similarly, the extract significantly prolonged the reaction time of mice (
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) for the hot-water stimuli. Furthermore, an oral dose of the extract showed significant inhibition (
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01) of acetic acid-induced abdominal contractions of mice. Besides, the ethanolic leaf extract did not cause any obvious sign of acute toxicity at a single oral dose of 2 g/kg.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2004">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>The findings of this study may partially support the acclaimed traditional use of 
   <italic>Hygrophila schulli</italic> leaves for the treatment of pain and inflammatory conditions.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
