<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Head space-solid phase microextraction (HS–SPME) was conducted according to Zielińska et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-01969" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] with slight modifications. Briefly, 100 mg of dry 
 <italic>E. senticosus</italic> fruits were placed in a 15 mL sealed vial and extracted using a fiber coated with 50/30 µm divinylbenzene–carboxen–polydimethylsiloxane (DVB/CAR/PDMS; Supelco, Bellefonte, PE, USA). The 2-undecanone–2 mg/mL in water (Merck, Poland) was used as an internal standard. Equilibration was performed at 60 °C for 15 min, the fiber exposition time was 15 min, and the thermal desorption was 3 min at 250 °C directly in the gas chromatography (GC) injection port. All analyses were performed in triplicate. The gas chromatography (GC) analysis was performed using Agilent 7890B GC coupled with a 7000GC/TQ system mass spectrometer (Agilent Technologies, Paolo Alto, CA, USA). Separation was carried out on an HP-5 MS column; 30m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 µm (J&amp;W, Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA) at a constant helium flow of 1 mL/min. The injector temperature was set at 250 °C and the sample was applied in a split mode (70:1). The temperature program was 50 °C for 1 min, followed by 5 °C/min to 120 °C, 8 °C/min to 200 °C, then to 250 °C in 16 °C/min and held isothermal for 2 min. The MS source, transfer line, and quadrupole temperature were set at 230 °C, 320 °C, and 150 °C, respectively. The mass spectra were collected in a scan mode from 
 <italic>m/z</italic> 30–400 and the ionization voltage was 70 eV. Data acquisition was performed using Agilent MassHunter Workstation software (version B.08.00). The identification of the compounds was based on a comparison of fragmentation patterns with the NIST17 mass spectra library and they were matched with retention index (RI) obtained by calculation relative to the n-alkane standard (C8–C20; Merc, Poland). The quantitative analysis (expressed as percentages of each compound) was carried out by peak area normalization measurements without a correction factor.
</p>
