<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effect of drought stress on the oil percentage in almond kernels and on its composition is not clear since the results of different studies undertaken in this field are ambiguous. However, studies in other species reported that water stress appears to promote tocopherol synthesis [
 <xref rid="B51-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. In almond there was no obvious relationship between almond tocopherol content and the degree of water deficiency [
 <xref rid="B54-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>], since little variation in kernel oil tocopherols was observed under moderate water stress, except for the more severe deficit of 70% SDI (sustained deficit irrigation) which for all components, except γ-tocopherol, had higher values than the control. In this study, the minor tocopherol homologues appeared to be slightly more responsive to deficit irrigation than the main homologue, α-tocopherol, but their small proportion had little impact on the amount of the total tocopherol content [
 <xref rid="B54-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. In the “Nonpareil” almond cultivar, the highest accumulation rate of α-tocopherol takes place during the period from 74 to 94 days after anthesis [
 <xref rid="B44-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>], indicating that the critical period to add nutrient and water to ensure normal accumulation of these chemical compounds is during this period. Tocopherol concentration has been reported to be affected by drought stress in olive oil [
 <xref rid="B55-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>], but not in 
 <italic class="italic">Brassica napus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B56-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>], by temperature in soybean [
 <xref rid="B57-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>], and by a combination of both in shea butter (
 <italic class="italic">Vitellaria paradoxa</italic> C.F. Gaertn.) [
 <xref rid="B50-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. In olive oil, the total tocopherols and α-tocopherol were highly influenced by the crop-year rainfalls, with the highest concentration from olives harvested during the driest year [
 <xref rid="B58-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. The increase in tocopherol content might contribute to the prevention of plant oxidative damage in drought conditions [
 <xref rid="B59-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-antioxidants-07-00006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>].
</p>
