<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par75">To conclude, acknowledging the expansion of tobacco tree in the Northern Mediterranean coast, bees were placed in the center of this study, since along with other wild insects have been recorded feeding on its plentiful nectar. Therefore, the fundamental question was raised: do tobacco alkaloids, which have been defined as potent insecticides, penetrate in the foraging organisms? To answer this question, a novel method was developed to be able to quantify the tobacco tree alkaloids in the flower extracts and bees, and then a feeding bioassay in bees was performed. The proposed analytical methodology succeeded to detail the alkaloid content of the extracts and to provide qualitative and quantitative definition of the alkaloids residues in bees. The feeding bioassay provided indications of low to medium toxicity of the extracts but more importantly defined the alkaloid content of the dead bees, though in nature consumption by other organisms, is sparingly documented, focused to bee-eater birds (Coraciiformes: Meropidae) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. The impacts of 
 <italic>Nicotiana</italic> alkaloids in honeybees were explicitly summarized by Stevenson et al. (2017) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], identifying foraging repellent and attractive impacts depending on concentration a null impact on the survival of adult bees, which agrees with present findings, but also a reduced larvae survival rate both in vivo and in vitro. On the other hand, it a chemoprotective impact on the reduction in 
 <italic>Crithidia bombi</italic> infection was also reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. These facts in cross consideration with present findings advocate on the role and significance of the reported phenomenon on honeybee’s population dynamics. After all, Neov et al. (2019) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] argued in favor of the role of feeding disorder in the beehives health status, also recognizing the significant impacts of neonicotinoids, agrochemicals defined as pyridine alkaloids. The role and significance of invasive alien species as honeybees feed sources has been stressed by Donkersley et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] that identified a primary pollen source in the form of the invasive 
 <italic>Himalayan balsam</italic>, providing a previous report that advocates the primary role of 
 <italic>Nicotiana glauca</italic> as a honeybee feed source in arid Mediterranean habitats, especially through seasons with scarce flowering. On the contrary, the most important aspect not to be neglected is the transfer of such compounds in the beehive by forager honeybees and potentially to apiculture products, exemplified by honey. Such transfer though remains to be proven. Alkaloids in honey, such as pyrrolizidine based molecules (e.g., echimidine), are intensively studied in terms of residual prevalence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>] and some of the members display carcinogenic, hepatotoxic and other toxic pharmacological activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Despite their toxicity, the European Commission has not yet established their MRLs.
</p>
