<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par74">In this context, HILIC was implemented. The latter additionally exhibited superior performance compared to RP, C18 chromatography (for C18 chromatography see chromatogram in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S6), improving the separation between the isomers especially for ( ±)-nicotine and (
 <italic>R,S</italic>)-anatabine, furnishing better chromatographic peak shapes for the majority of analytes, which is depicted in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. With regard to the mobile phase selection, the trademark of low water content under HILIC conditions was verified in this study as well. Compared to previous work [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], the elution order of common analytes was verified, however in the present work the inclusion of more analytes, that in the HILIC mode were expected to elute early (such as scopoletin and myosmine), led to a decrease of the flow rate, selection of a column with larger film thickness; hence, enhancing the separation, though increasing the retention. Apart from the work of Taujenis and coworkers, a 2006 report showed also how the HILIC conditions employing low water amounts, favor the resolution and chromatographic performance of other alkaloids based on xanthine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. In previous studies, HILIC mode conditions were reported successful in separating low resolution isomers of dansyl amino acids and nicotine enantiomers analogs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. A recent LC coupled to high resolution mass spectrometry (HRMS) research work also demonstrated the importance and optimum performance of HILIC in the separation of nortropane alkaloids (calystegines) in tomato-based products [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. A clear advantage of this analytical work (and related works on alkaloids separation using HILIC) seems to be the distinct separation of anabasine and nicotine, whose structural-chromatographic differentiation is still a challenging topic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>].
</p>
