<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> contains many phytochemical compounds namely, lactones, terpenoids (e.g., 
 <italic>trans</italic>-thujone, γ-terpinene, 1,4-terpeniol, myrcene, bornyl acetate, cadinene camphene, 
 <italic>trans</italic>-sabinyl acetate, guaiazulene, chamazulene, camphor, and linalool), essential oils, organic acids, resins, tannins, and phenols [
 <xref rid="B9-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. It also contains flavonoids (e.g., quercitin), flavonoid glycosides such as isorhamnetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-rhamnose glucoside, isoquercitrin, quercitin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-D-glucoside, quercetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-rhamnoglucoside, and isorhamnetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, and phenolic acids (coumaric, syringic, salicylic, chlorogenic, and vanillic acids) which contribute to free radical scavenging mechanism [
 <xref rid="B10-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition, Ahamad et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] reported that methanolic 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> extract contains isoflavone glycosides that are characterized as 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> isoflavonyl glucosyl diester and bis-isoflavonyl dirhamnoside. Previous studies documented that 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> essential oils are rich in myrcene, 
 <italic>trans</italic>-thujone, 
 <italic>cis</italic>-epoxyocimene, 
 <italic>cis</italic>-chrysanthenyl acetate, and 
 <italic>trans</italic>-sabinyl acetate are the most common compounds found in [
 <xref rid="B12-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The medicinal efficacy of wormwood is often based on its bioactive ingredient in the dimeric guaianolides absinthins, as it is used more effectively than other 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> species as it contains approximately 0.2% of absinthin [
 <xref rid="B14-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In addition, fresh wormwood is considered the best source of azulene, yielding between 40 and 70 mg % of azulene [
 <xref rid="B16-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="antibiotics-09-00353-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the main active constituents isolated from 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic>. 
</p>
