<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the second half of the 19th century, a simple experimental idea would introduce a new hypothesis about the bounding mechanism of cells (
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tanford, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lombard, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stillwell, 2016</xref>). In 1855, Carl von Nägeli and Karl Cramer reported their observations that plant cells, when placed in hypertonic solution, set by increasing salt or sugar concentrations, would result in the protoplasm shrinking away from the cell wall (
 <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">von Nägeli and Cramer, 1855</xref>). Conversely, when the cell was placed in a hypotonic solution, the cytosol would expand to the point of bursting. They referred to these experiments as plasmolysis studies (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>) and interpreted the results as a demonstration of a pliable barrier, capable of adapting its shape to the surrounding vessel: in this case, the cell wall. Finally, they demonstrated that vacuoles, when isolated from the cell, followed the same behavior, and the volume changes here were reversible. Wilhelm Pfeffer continued these studies and proposed that a skin, or plasma membrane, existed that covered the exposed surface of the protoplasm (
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pfeffer, 1877</xref>). At that time, he suggested this membrane was similar to artificial copper ferrocyanide membranes that had been recently discovered by Moritz Traube (
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Traube, 1867</xref>). These were simple studies, ones that any young student can carry out today, yet the implications of the findings were profound. The results provided evidence that the barrier acted like an invisible skin, selectively allowing for the passage of water in and out of the cell, although limiting the permeability of salts and sugars.
</p>
