<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several digestibility trials have been carried out on different aquaculture fish and shellfish species-fed feeds containing insect meals with 
 <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic> (TM) and 
 <italic class="italic">Hermetia illucens</italic> (HI), which are the most frequently investigated insect species (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00170-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Trials on the use of full fat TM in gilthead seabream (
 <italic class="italic">Sparus aurata</italic>) and seabass (
 <italic class="italic">Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>) aquafeeds were carried out by Piccolo et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] and Gasco et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], respectively. Piccolo et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] recorded lower apparent digestibility coefficients (ADC) of crude protein (CP) and ether extract (EE) for fish fed a diet containing 500 g/kg of TM than those fed low TM level (250 g/kg)- and fishmeal (FM)-based diets. Similar results were also obtained in a rainbow trout (
 <italic class="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) trial where the ADC of protein was significantly lower in a group fed 500 g/kg of dietary TM than in the groups fed diets with 250 g/kg of TM and FM, while the dry matter (DM), organic matter (OM) and EE ADCs were unaffected by TM meal utilization [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The in vivo ADC of European sea bass (
 <italic class="italic">Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>) juvenile diets with an inclusion of 25% of TM, with or without the presence of exogenous enzymes (carbohydrases and proteases), was compared to a FM-based control diet [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The CP ADC of the fish fed the TM diet without the presence of exogenous enzymes was significantly higher than that of the fish fed the FM-based diet [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. On the other hand, the CP and acid detergent fiber digestibility were not improved by digestive enzyme supplementation [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The use of a full-fat TM as a replacement for FM has also been tested in a Pacific white shrimp (
 <italic class="italic">Litopenaeus vannamei</italic>) diet consisting of 84.5% of the reference diet and 15% of TM. The ADC values were 76.1% for CP and 66.5% for energy, while the essential amino acid (EAA) ADCs ranged from 72% to 86%, with methionine representing the first limiting AA. The authors therefore suggested that although methionine should be added as a supplement, TM can be utilized as an alternative protein source for Pacific white shrimp (
 <italic class="italic">Litopenaeus vannamei</italic>) juveniles [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Another insect meal that is being tested more and more frequently in feeds is HI meal, as it is probably the most promising insect for feed purposes, due to its ability to be reared on different organic substrates, thus exalting the circular economy/zero waste principle [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Fresh-water Atlantic salmon (
 <italic class="italic">Salmo salar</italic>)-fed diets containing 60% of HI, in replacement of FM, and a soybean protein concentrate, reduced the ADC of the CP, lipids and all the investigated AAs, although they remained highly digestible and comparable with the digestibility obtained for salmonids fed other alternative protein sources (poultry by-products, wheat gluten or bacterial protein meal) [
 <xref rid="B14-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. The use of an HI meal derived from larvae grown on seaweed, in the diets of sea-water phase Atlantic salmon (
 <italic class="italic">Salmo salar</italic>) (inclusion rates of 4.91, 9.84 and 14.75%), as partial or total replacement of FM, did not affect the ADC of the CP, lipid, AAs, or fatty acids (FA) [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The authors found that the apparent digestibility values of the AAs were comparable with those observed in other fish studies on salmonids (
 <italic class="italic">Salmo salar</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] and European seabass (
 <italic class="italic">Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] fed HI meal and that, except for the methionine and lysine contents, they had an essential and non-essential AA profile close to that of FM. The use of high inclusion levels (40%) of HI defatted meal (CP: 55%), in substitution of FM in rainbow trout (
 <italic class="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) diets, was found to lead to a decrease in DM and CP ADCs, while the EE and gross energy (GE) ADCs were unaffected [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Dumas et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] found comparable results for CP and DM in rainbow trout-fed diets including 20% of HI meal, but lower EE ADC than the ones reported by Renna et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Chitin was hypothesized to be the cause of the low observed EE ADC [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Nevertheless, as higher hydroxyproline and tryptophan ADCs were found 
 <italic class="italic">vs</italic> fish fed control diets containing 20% of FM, Dumas et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-animals-09-00170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] suggested a possible positive effect of chitin on prolidase activity, which is the specific enzyme responsible for hydrolysis and absorption of proline and hydroxyproline in the small intestine.
</p>
