<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Besides basic nutrients, eggs are also a great source of potential nutraceuticals. A total of 550 distinct proteins were identified so far in egg-white and yolk/vitelline membranes and the physiological function of only 20 of them is characterized to date. This remark suggests that the egg probably still encloses many unknown activities that merit further investigations considering the current lack of research assessing the fate of egg proteins along the digestive tract. Such studies could help to better appreciate the in vivo potential of egg proteins and of the resulting hydrolytic peptides, and could be easily apprehended using dynamic gastric models that have been used with other foodstuffs, in food- and pharmaceutically-based research [
 <xref rid="B203-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">203</xref>,
 <xref rid="B204-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">204</xref>]. These in vitro models mimic both the biochemical and mechanical aspects of gastric digestion. They incorporate artificial saliva, compressive forces to disintegrate food, simulate continuous gastric emptying, and gastric secretion that generate pH profiles similar to human stomach. They also include bile salts and intestinal enzymes that act sequentially in a realistic time-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B205-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">205</xref>] and may be improved by adding intestine-like microbiota. This model was already used in a wide range of studies in order to assess the bioaccessibility of nutrients and to study the structural changes of food matrices. It is expected that such an experimental strategy would constitute a promising way to study the impact of egg preparation in the diet (raw versus cooked) on the physiological generation of bioactive peptides, and to better appreciate their biological significance for human health. It is well assumed now that gut health depends on the interplay between host genome, nutrition, and lifestyle that it contributes to normal brain function and mental health [
 <xref rid="B206-nutrients-11-00684" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">206</xref>].
</p>
