<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The team of Dr. McClements also compared the bioaccessibility of β-carotene from predissolved nanoemulsions, a physical mixture with nanoemulsions, and phosphate buffered saline [
 <xref rid="B117-nutrients-11-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>]. They constructed the 
 <italic class="italic">o</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">w</italic> nanoemulsions using corn oil as the lipid core. Measurement of bioaccessibility using a simulated GI model indicated that the β-carotene crystals in PBS had the lowest transport, which they attributed to the small number of mixed micelles that are available for the solubilization of β-carotene. The solubilized β-carotene in nanoemulsions was transferred from the oil droplets into mixed micelles in the lipid digestion step, leading to a bioaccessibility of 69%. The interfacial layer surrounding the oil droplets in nanoemulsions is essential to maintain the long-term stability of nanosystems [
 <xref rid="B118-nutrients-11-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>]. Thus, Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B119-nutrients-11-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">119</xref>] utilized ternary conjugates of covalent polyphenol, protein, and carbohydrate cross-links to stabilize the oil drop surface of β-carotene-loaded nanoemulsions. The nanoparticles that were coated with surface-active chlorogenic acid-lactoferrin-polydextrose had better stability in terms of droplet fusion in the GI tract, and therefore increased β-carotene bioaccessibility. Their interpretation was that this was because the formation of a thick interfacial layer by the conjugates suppressed the ability of lipase to adsorb to the oil droplets. Mun et al. [
 <xref rid="B120-nutrients-11-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>] incorporated β-carotene-loaded nanoemulsions into rice starch hydrogels and then determined the in vitro bioaccessibility in simulated GI tract. The oil droplets were stable in the simulated stomach, but they aggregated in the simulated small intestine. Moreover, when they added β-carotene into the nanoemulsions, the bioaccessibility increased from 1% to 23% due to the formation of mixed micelles in the simulated small intestine fluid. The further incorporation of hydrogels increased the bioaccessibility to about 50%, presumably because the hydrogel matrix protected the oil droplets from coalescence in the gastric phase.
</p>
