<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characterization of the emulsions</div>
 <sec id="sec3-7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Creaming index</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The creaming rate was determined experimentally by the measurement of the creaming index (CI) from Eq.2. The CI values were obtained from the ratio between the total height of cream layer (CC) and the total height of emulsion layer (CT). CC and CT were measured directly into a storage glass flask with the help of a graduate scale.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span xlink:href="PM-13-159-g004.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">pH</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measurements of pH were obtained from the probe inserted directly into the emulsion container at room temperature. The values were obtained using a pre-calibrated pH meter (model PG1800, São Paulo, Brazil). The analysis was performed in triplicate.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conductivity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The conductivity was measured by directly inserting the probe into an emulsion container at room temperature, using a portable conductivity meter [MITE, model CD30] previously calibrated with a standard solution of 0.1 N KCl. The analysis was performed in triplicate.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3-10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CG-FID analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The quantification studies were performed on a Shimadzu Gas Chromatograph (model GC-2010 Plus, Kyoto, Japan) equipped with a capillary column DB-1 dimethylpolysiloxane (30mx 0.25 mm, 0.25 micron), and a flame ionization detector was used to analyze the samples.[
   <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">31</a>] The carrier gas was N
   <sub>2</sub> with a flow of 1.3 ml/min., split 1:100, injector temperature 260°C, detector temperature 280°C, initial column temperature equal to 60ºC heated at a rate of 10°C. min
   <span class="sup">-1</span> up to 92ºC for 3 minutes, followed by a heating rate of 10°C/min up to 120°C and a rate of 20°C/min up to 280°C. The injection volume was 1.0 μl. The calibration curve from a commercial sample of carvacrol [Sigma-Aldrich, Chicago, IL, USA] was obtained by recording the peak areas against the known injected amount contained in the same injected volume (1 ml). The analysis was performed in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
