<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The species 
  <span class="italic">Plectranthus amboinicus</span> Lour, also known as 
  <span class="italic">Plectranthus aromaticus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Coleus aromaticus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Coleus amboinicus</span>, is a herbaceous plant. It is perennial, succulent and aromatic with brittle stems and ovate succulent leaves, an acute apex, toothed edges, and a thick petiole. This species is native to eastern Asia and it is widespread throughout the tropical countries.[
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> is widely used in Brazil in the treatment of diseases such as asthma, superficial mycosis, cancer, constipation, headache, cough, colds, fever, and digestive diseases.[
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">2</a>
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">3</a>
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>] The literature also reports that the essential oil of the 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> acts as an antifungal and antibacterial agent.[
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>] The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">P. amboinicus</span> presents a rich composition in mono and sesquiterpenes. In several studies, the carvacrol is reported to be the major component in a concentration ranging from 40 to 90%.[
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>] Furthermore, other constituents have been reported such as eugenol, methyl chavicol, β-caryophyllene, ρ-cymene, α-humulene, γ-terpinene, and 1.8-cineole.[
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Owing to its technological development, the emulsified systems containing essential oil, remain a challenge due to the volatility and instabilities and solubility of essential oil.[
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>] In this way, the development of emulsions as carriers of essential oils demonstrates several benefits such as the ability to hide unpleasant flavors so they can be administered in a palatable form, and also to improve the oral bioavailability.[
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>] Additionally, emulsions are widely used in cosmetic and pharmaceutical formulations due to excellent topical administration of hydrophilic and lipophilic active ingredients.[
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">16</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study is aimed to produce and evaluate nonionic O/W emulsions based on the essential oil from leaves of 
  <span class="italic">Plectranthus amboinicus</span>. For this proposal the physicochemical and phytochemical characterizations of the essential oil were performed. To produce stable O/W emulsions, the HLB system was used to determine the HLB of the essential oil.
 </p>
</sec>
