<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Authors’ contributions</title>
 <p class="p">HWCA carried out the experiments, analyzed the data and drafted the manuscript. RFSA assisted in the performing of experiments and discussion of results. DMR and DRR assisted in statistical analysis and discussion of results and writing the manuscript. CAAS participated in the design of the study and coordination. GMCT conceived and supervised the study and reviewed the final manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Acknowledgements</title>
  <p id="Par53" class="p">The authors are grateful to State University of Paraiba (UEPB) for teaching qualification, and to Nucleus of Research in Environmental Sciences and Biotechnology (NPCIAMB), Catholic University of Pernambuco, Pernambuco, Brazil, for the use of laboratories.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Competing interests</title>
  <p id="Par54" class="p">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p id="Par55" class="p">The datasets supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Consent for publication</title>
  <p id="Par56" class="p">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p id="Par57" class="p">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Funding</title>
  <p id="Par58" class="p">The study was supported by National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq), Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Level Education Personnel Fellowship (CAPES), Foundation for the Support of Science and Technology of the State of Pernambuco (FACEPE), Brazil.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Publisher’s Note</title>
  <p id="Par59" class="p">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
