<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Our study is the only report so far on the chemical composition and phytotoxicity of 
 <italic>O. acanthium</italic> essential oil. Previously, the chemical composition of essential oils from another 
 <italic>Onopordum</italic> species, 
 <italic>O. arenarium</italic>, was investigated, and in total 29 and 25 compounds were identified from this plant’s flower and stem volatile oils, representing 91.6% and 89.2% of the oil mass, respectively. The oils were found to possess antioxidant activity, which were rich in long-chain hydrocarbons (23.3–36.4%), oxygenated long-chain hydrocarbons (31.5–33.8%), and oxygenated monoterpenes (14.4–6.6%), with palmitic acid being the most abundant constituent (25.5–28.7%)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. As of non-volatile compounds, phytochemical study revealed the presence of flavonoids such as apigenin, luteolin, scutellarein, coumarins such as aesculin and aesculetin, sesquiterpene lactones including derivatives of elemane, germacrane, eudesmane, and guaiane
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. Watanabe et al. (2014) suspected that allelopathy might facilitate the invasion success of 
 <italic>O. acanthium</italic>, therefore bioassay-guided isolation procedure was applied using wheat seeds as test species to investigate the chemicals in the leaves, which was extracted with different solvents; the CH
 <sub>2</sub>Cl
 <sub>2</sub> extract showed the most potent phytotoxic activity, which was then further purified to yield 4 compounds, i.e. two flavonoids, pectolarigenin (1) and scutellarein 4′-methyl ether (2), and two sesquiterpene lactones, elemanolide 11(13)-dehydromelitensin b-hydroxyisobutyrate (3) and acanthiolide (4), among which they found compound 3 (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.794 × 10
 <sup>–4</sup> M) strongly inhibited the growth of wheat coleoptiles and compound 1 (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 1.263 × 10
 <sup>−3</sup> M) showed an intermediate effect
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. To the best of knowledge, this is the first study on the chemical profile and phytotoxicity of this plant’s essential oil. Altogether 60 compounds from flower, leaf and stem oils of 
 <italic>O. acanthium</italic> were identified, which were found to be rich in higher 
 <italic>n</italic>-alkanes.
</p>
