<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Insect vectors, especially mosquitoes, directly transmit human diseases such as filarial fever, malaria, dengue fever, and chikungunya, among others [
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. One of the strategies to control these vectors is to destroy their vectors and intermediate hosts. The use of natural products for the control of insect pests offers an economically viable and ecofriendly approach. In recent years, plants have been identified for their insecticidal or larvicidal properties and used to control insect vectors. Twenty-five plant extracts were screened [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], including 
 <italic>G. morella</italic>, for larvicidal activity against 
 <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> Say. (third instar larvae) at 100-ppm concentration and the larval mortality was evaluated after 24 and 48 h. Their experimental results revealed that hexane and dichloromethane extracts of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> extract were responsible for 100% of the mortality of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic> larvae. Murthy et al. [
 <xref rid="B40-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] investigated the phytochemical composition of the resin/latex of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> and evaluated the larvicidal activity (latex was dissolved in 1 mL of acetone, and different concentrations, namely 37.5, 75, 150, 300, and 600 ppm, were prepared) against the filariasis-causing vector 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>. They reported that 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> resin/latex exhibited toxicity against the treated third instar larvae of 
 <italic>C. quinquefasciatus</italic>, with LC
 <sub>50</sub> and LC
 <sub>90</sub> values of 132.54 and 483.15 ppm, respectively. The bioactive compounds isomorellin (
 <bold>7</bold>), morellic acid (
 <bold>4</bold>), and isomorellic acid (
 <bold>6</bold>) of 
 <italic>G. morella</italic> resin [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-05690" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] might be responsible for the larvicidal activities.
</p>
