<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NanoBEO, consisting of an odorless NDS of α-TFS-SLN loaded with BEO-BF, has been tested on acute and neuropathic pain models confirming the strong antinociceptive and anti-allodynic efficacy previously reported for BEO. In fact, BEO has demonstrated analgesic properties in acute pain models, e.g., the capsaicin test [
 <xref rid="B33-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and early phase of the 0.5% formalin test [
 <xref rid="B38-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], but also in neuropathic pain models, like the partial sciatic nerve ligation [
 <xref rid="B36-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and the spinal nerve ligation [
 <xref rid="B25-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It enhances morphine-induced analgesia and its dose-dependent effect is antagonized by naloxone hydrochloride and methiodide (not crossing the blood-brain barrier), suggesting the involvement of peripheral opioid mechanisms. Quite importantly, BEO is able to modulate the synaptic level of glutamate [
 <xref rid="B41-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], involved in pain transmission and modulation through the pain descending pathway due to metabotropic glutamate receptors [
 <xref rid="B3-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Its analgesic efficacy occurs also via the inhalation route [
 <xref rid="B42-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], but it has been demonstrated not to depend on inhalation [
 <xref rid="B40-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. This is fundamental since patients suffering from dementia frequently present dysfunctional olfaction [
 <xref rid="B43-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and neurofibrillary tangles in the entorhinal cortex [
 <xref rid="B44-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Furthermore, BEO is characterized by anxiolytic effects not superimposable to those of diazepam [
 <xref rid="B45-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and insensitive to flumazenil [
 <xref rid="B16-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], hence devoid of sedation and involving serotonergic transmission [
 <xref rid="B46-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The latter pharmacologic properties are very important for the use in dementia since benzodiazepines can worsen cognitive function bearing an anti-cholinergic burden [
 <xref rid="B47-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Moreover, it is effective also on scratching behavior, one of the behavioral disturbances displayed by patients suffering from dementia. The results obtained testing the nanotechnology BEO delivery system showed stable and reproducible aromatherapy effects. In particular, after two and six months of light exposure, the content in the active ingredients declined by 10% and 18%, respectively with no further degradation at twelve months. In fact, these α-tocopheryl stearate-based SLN contain ferulic acid as an anti-oxidant agent, differently from those previously described (US5250236) devoid of anti-oxidants. Therefore, the prolonged physicochemical stability (up to 12 months) of the phytocomplex titrated in its main components (linalool, linalyl acetate, and limonene) is a remarkable advantage allowing reproducible antinociceptive and anti-itch responses to be measured. This latter property is of primary importance because components of the phytocomplex are implicated in the analgesic action of BEO. In fact, s.c. administration of linalool was demonstrated to reduce licking/biting response to formalin [
 <xref rid="B38-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and to capsaicin [
 <xref rid="B34-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] by means of an opioid receptor-dependent mechanism. Linalool attenuates paclitaxel-induced mechanical allodynia and hyperalgesia [
 <xref rid="B48-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The anti-allodynic effect was also reported in the spinal nerve ligation model [
 <xref rid="B49-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Blockade of the activation of spinal extracellular signal-regulated protein kinase (ERK) occurring during neuropathic pain induction underscores the anti-allodynic effect of linalool [
 <xref rid="B36-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Incidentally, BEO enhances basal and induced autophagy, a process implicated in dementia [
 <xref rid="B50-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and pain [
 <xref rid="B52-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and this has been attributed to limonene [
 <xref rid="B53-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Moreover, β-caryophyllene is a common component of essential oils, among which is BEO, and it is endowed with an antinociceptive effect demonstrated in the capsaicin test, mediated by activation of CB2 receptors [
 <xref rid="B54-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. This NDS has the features to guarantee a significant reduction of the total loss of transepidermal water and a large surface area of the SLN, which allows the prolonged exposure and contact of the loaded BEO with the skin, resulting in an efficient release. Added to this is the possibility to perform double-blind clinical trials, impossible so far because of the strong smell of essential oils used in aromatherapy. The diagnosis and treatment of pain in cognitively impaired patients is a neglected area, from chronic pain in dementia and migraine in aged patients often affected by concurrent cognitive impairment to post-stroke pain. Demented patients receive limited treatment for chronic pain, particularly neuropathic [
 <xref rid="B9-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Novel preventative treatments for migraine like the anti-calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP) monoclonal antibody eptinezumab that can provide rapid and longer-lasting action [
 <xref rid="B55-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] are not studied in these patients. Patients suffering from post-stroke pain are often subjected to cognitive deficits and clinical trials studying the use of the strongest painkillers, i.e., opioids, in this population are very few and not adequately powered and designed [
 <xref rid="B56-pharmaceutics-13-00379" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. This is often due to the lack of use of observational tools for non-communicative patients and this problem is worsened by the current coronavirus pandemic. Therefore, the registered clinical trial NCT04321889 BRAINAID (Bergamot Rehabilitation AgaINst Agitation In Dementia) has been designed to assess the effectiveness of NanoBEO on agitation and pain in severely demented patients to offer a safe tool able to provide relief to this fragile population. It will enroll 134 patients aged ≥65 years with severe dementia (Mini-Mental State Examination [MMSE] &lt;12) who will be randomized to NanoBEO or placebo cream in a 1:1 allocation ratio. The primary endpoint is the assessment of agitation through the Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory (CMAI) over four weeks. The secondary endpoints will be the 4-week follow-up of the effect on agitation and the effect on pain measured with the Mobilization–Observation–Behaviour–Intensity–Dementia (MOBID)-2. This double-blind clinical trial will be the first to assess the efficacy and safety of an engineered essential oil with proven strong analgesic properties in acute and neuropathic pain on agitation. The latter trial can provide the rationale for the safer treatment of BPSD and pain and it can confirm the analgesic properties of BEO in clinic.
</p>
