<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three reviews were published in this special issue. The review article by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.575801" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Hassan et al.</ext-link> discussed the ability of phytogenic additives to modulate rumen microbiome, fermentation kinetics and methanogenesis mediated through diet–microbe-phytochemical interactions. Authors concluded that pure PSM, plant extracts or PSM-rich phytogenic feeds have the ability to modulate rumen microbiota, increase volatile fatty acids and decrease ammonia and methane (CH
 <sub>4</sub>) production. Inhibition of enteric CH
 <sub>4</sub> emission was consistently observed in 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments, while the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> effects varied greatly. The authors emphasized that many factors contribute to this vast variability, including variations of the chemical compositions and dose of the PSM, application methods, dietary composition, physiological stage of animals, feeding conditions, and progressive adaptation of microbes for specific phytochemicals. Moreover, they discussed the effects of production, extraction, processing, and application of phytochemicals on the expected responses. In another review, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.588051" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Sun</ext-link> summarized the effects of glucosinolates present in brassica forages on CH
 <sub>4</sub> emissions from ruminants, and concluded that brassica forages can be used as a useful tool to reduce CH
 <sub>4</sub> emitted per unit of DM intake compared with grass-based forages. The author explained physiological mechanisms in the mitigation of CH
 <sub>4</sub> emissions from ruminants fed brassica forages beyond the direct inhibitory effect on methanogens or fermentation profile changes. Glucosinolates and/or their ruminal microbial breakdown products are absorbed into the blood and then may stimulate the secretion of thyroid hormone causing many changes in rumen physiology including a reduction in ruminal digesta retention time, thereby reducing CH
 <sub>4</sub> emissions In the third review article, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.628445" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Tedeschi et al.</ext-link> reviewed the ecologically relevant phytochemicals including polyphenolics, terpenes antioxidants, alkaloids, flavonoids, condensed tannins and essential oils on ruminant performance, and their sustainable production and utilization to replace antibiotics. They recommended the use of many phytochemicals at the same time to obtain better biological responses in ruminant production.
</p>
