<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effect of phytogenic feed additive supplementation on 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> fermentation was evaluated in 3 research articles. In one experiment, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00550" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Ebeid et al.</ext-link> noted that 
 <italic>Camelina sativa</italic> oil (0, 2, 4, 6, and 8% of dry matter) changed proportions of individual ruminal volatile fatty acids and decreased CH
 <sub>4</sub> production by altering total bacteria, protozoa, and methanogens populations. 
 <italic>Camelina sativa</italic> oil caused a linear decrease in bacterial richness and evenness indices along with Shannon diversity. In another experiment, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.623817" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Ahmed et al.</ext-link> reported that Mootral [a commercial product containing 
 <italic>Allium sativum (</italic>garlic) powder and 
 <italic>Citrus aurantium</italic> (bitter orange) extracts] at 0, 10, and 20% of the substrate altered ruminal microbial community, produced more propionate, and reduce microbial groups associated with CH
 <sub>4</sub> production 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Such effects were reflected as reducing CH
 <sub>4</sub> percentage and CH
 <sub>4</sub>/CO
 <sub>2</sub> ratio in a dose-dependent manner. Moreover, Mootral increased abundances of H
 <sub>2</sub>-consuming groups such as 
 <italic>Prevotellaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>Veillonellaceae</italic> and reduced some H
 <sub>2</sub>-producing bacteria as well as reduced the major CH
 <sub>4</sub>-producing family 
 <italic>Methanobacteriaceae</italic> and increased 
 <italic>Methanomassiliicoccaceae</italic>. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.644738" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Gomaa et al.</ext-link> reported that red osier dogwood extract at 1% of DM in the rumen simulated technique system tended to decrease acetate to propionate ratio and decreased starch disappearance in the barely-based diet, but not in the diet containing dried distillers grains with solubles. Rumen microbiota was not affected by red osier dogwood extract at the phylum level, but was altered at the genus level.
</p>
