<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Worldwide, an estimated 5% of agricultural production losses are caused by various species of spider mites. The carmine spider mite 
 <italic class="italic">Tetranychus cinnabarinus</italic> (Boisduval), in particular, has long been recognized as one of the most notorious of tetranychid mites. This species have been shown to cause serious damage to the quality and yield of many crops, fruits and vegetables grown in the field or in greenhouse all over the world by damaging foliar tissues, reducing photosynthetic activity and even causing leaf abscission when severe infestations occur [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Traditionally, control of these mites has involved the use of synthetic chemical pesticides [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>], however, the intensive use of chemical pesticides, coupled with the high fecundity, short life cycle and arrhenotoky genetics of these mites, have resulted in the rapid evolution of insecticide resistance [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Specifically, carmine spider mites have been reported to have resistance against a number of commonly used pesticides, including dicofol, omethoate, amitraz, pyridaben and fenpropathrin [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The frequent use of these non-selective synthetic pesticides has been shown to have adverse effects on both the environment and human health [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], and also been linked to mortality of beneficial natural enemies of the mites, resulting in a resurgence of mite populations. These problems with increasing levels of resistance to conventional acaricides have led to applications of more frequent and higher doses of insecticides, which further increase the risk to humans and the environment [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Thus, studies examining alternatives to traditional chemical treatments such as botanical acaricides that have lower mammalian and environmental toxicity, are being performed [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-22-01873" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
