<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Up to now, a plenty of studies have confirmed diverse therapeutic potentials of EOs including antifungal, antibacterial, antioxidant, cytotoxic, anti-diabetic, and anti-nociceptive features (
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Additionally, MEO has shown potent antioxidant, anti-mutagenic, antimicrobial, antiviral, and antifungal effects. According to ample evidence, EOs’ therapeutic effects are likely to be associated with their unique components. For instance, the potent antibacterial activity of EOs has mostly been related to the oxygenated terpenoids such as 1,8-cineole, linalool, and α-terpineol. Likewise, α-caryophyllene, a well-known component of MEO and another EOs, has been reported to function effectively as an antiviral (
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). However, several evidences have indicated that environmental factors as well as other ones such as harvesting season, vegetative period of plant, and length of distillation affect the content of EOs chemical compositions (
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
 <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Mahboubi, 
 <italic>et al</italic>. considered 1,8-cineole (36.1%), α-pinene (22.5%), and linalool (8.4%) to be the main constituents of MEO, collected from Iran, whose composition content order is similar to that of the results obtained from present study (
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Contrarily, other studies determined the constituents of MEO have yielded varying results. For example, the main constituents of Turkian MEO include linalool (36.5%) and linalyl acetate (16.3%) whereas Italian samples are comprised of α-pinene and 1,8-cineole (
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Despite having potent therapeutic potentials, EOs are unstable due to evaporation or decomposition even at room temperature (
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). To overcome these problems, several methods are developed to stabilize EOs. Previous studies have shown that solid lipid nanoparticles were capable of reducing rapid evaporation of essential oil (
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Liolios, 
 <italic>et al</italic>. study indicated that encapsulation of carvacrol and thymol in liposome dramatically increased antimicrobial activity (
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Unique features of niosomes including superior chemical and storage stabilities makes them a promising carrier for MEO in topical formulations compared to liposomes. However, different niosomal formulations present various physical properties that influence the EE% of active compounds. Hence, we have analyzed the effects of various molar ratios of different surfactants on features of niosomal formulations in the presence of Chol. We found that vesicle yield was low in the presence of Span 20 and Span 80 which could be due to short alkyl chain (C12) of Span 20 and unsaturated alkyl chain of Span 80 (
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Based on findings of this study, S/T 60 formulations have larger vesicles sizes while S/T 40 formulations have higher EE% which increases with increment of the amount of Chol from 30 to 50 molar ratios (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In line with our results, a previous study has revealed that alkyl chain length and hydrophilic-lipophilic balance (HLB) of used surfactants have a significant effect on size and EE% of formulations (
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Moreover, the length of alkyl chain in turn influences HLB value of the surfactant. Therefore, the higher EE% will be achieved with the higher HLB values of the surfactants (
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Ruckmani, 
 <italic>et al</italic>. showed that a decrease in EE% values was accompanied by increased length of the alkyl chain of surfactants (
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) while Guinedi, 
 <italic>et al</italic>. reported that lower HLB surfactants led to higher EE% (
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).
</p>
