<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0005">In biological sense, oxidative stress is defined as a physiological imbalance between reactive oxygen species (ROS) and the ability of the body to discard free radicals (
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al., 2014</xref>). Free radicals such as hydrogen peroxide can lead to oxidation of lipids and proteins, and even produce damages to the genetic material inside the cells. Nevertheless, this so-called genotoxic effect of free radicals might not influence only the DNA, but also the cellular components related to the function of chromosomes within the living cell (
 <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">López-Romero et al., 2018</xref>). Hence, oxidative stress can be associated, besides ageing, with organ inflammatory diseases – cardiovascular and neurodegenerative diseases, chronic kidney and obstructive pulmonary diseases, as well as diabetes and cancer (
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Liguori et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Kuciel-Lewandowska et al., 2020</xref>). In a healthy organism, the levels of free radicals are under firm control mechanisms, hence, oxidative stress can be annulled by the involvement of antioxidant response mechanisms normally occurring in the cells with the help of enzymatic and nonenzymatic endogenous antioxidants (
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Kuciel-Lewandowska et al., 2020</xref>). However, considering that people nowadays are exposed to excessive environmental pollution, chronic psychological stress and physical exertion, cigarette and alcohol usage, among others, this antioxidant protection might only alleviate the oxidative damage (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Liguori et al., 2018</xref>). Nonetheless, additional protection factors, such as exogenous antioxidants, are required to alternate free radical reactions, cell signals transmission and also the activity of different proteins and genes involved in DNA repair mechanisms (
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Kuciel-Lewandowska et al., 2020</xref>). Exogenous antioxidants (externally supplied through foods or supplements) might be of artificial or natural origin (
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Liguori et al., 2018</xref>). Since the basic knowledge of modern medicine and pharmacy relies on the insights of traditional medicine, it is not surprising that nearly a quarter of pharmaceuticals nowadays are developed using natural sources (
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Pandey and Rizvi, 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Nastić et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, the previous fact justifies the ever-growing scientific interest in ethnobotanical studies.
</p>
