<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When free radicals accumulate within a cell and overpower the buffering effects of oxidants, oxidative stress is the result. Oxidative stress has been established as a major contributor to many pathological conditions and diseases [
 <xref rid="B66-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. By using the antioxidant effects of plants, some disease states can be mitigated. 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> is the most studied species related to oxidative stress. Its petal
 <italic>s</italic> have been investigated in vitro by evaluating the oxidative stress on human vascular endothelial cells (HUVECs) [
 <xref rid="B67-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Pretreatment with petal extracts on H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative stress HUVECs cell models reduced the rate of cell death. In this case, a reduction of hydroperoxide’s concentration, assessed by FOX-1 assays, and an increasing value of ferric reducing antioxidant power (FRAP) in both intra and extracellular fluid were observed. This is further confirmed by in vivo studies by Noroozpour et al., which showed that the hydroalcoholic petal extract of 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> had a protective effect on selenite-induced cataracts in rats [
 <xref rid="B51-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Likewise, Abbasi Larki et al. [
 <xref rid="B68-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] demonstrated that the petal of 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> had a protective effect on permethrin-induced rat models. The pretreatment with this extract showed a greatly reduced inflammatory response of cerulein-induced acute pancreatitis in mice [
 <xref rid="B69-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Mahsa Kamali et al. [
 <xref rid="B70-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] reported that 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> could reduce the rate of teratogenicity induced by the antiepileptic medication lamotrigine in mice. Moreover, a clinical trial of 38 volunteers was carried out to investigate the antioxidant properties of 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> [
 <xref rid="B71-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. All the volunteers were administered 7 mg/kg of 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> flower decoction twice every day for two weeks. The results showed that after 14 days of oral consumption of the flower decoction of 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic>, blood lipid peroxidation levels were reduced (from 24.65 ± 11.33 to 19.05 ± 9.7 nmol/mL), and total antioxidant capacity of blood (from 1.46 ± 0.51 to 1.70 ± 0.36 μmol/mL), as well as total thiol molecules in the blood (from 0.49 ± 0.11 to 0.56 ± 0.12 μmol/mL), was increased [
 <xref rid="B71-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. These findings suggested that 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> could ameliorate the pathological conditions resulted from oxidative stress and could be used as a nutritional supplement.
</p>
