<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="s2001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Although investigations on different pharmacological activities of the experimental plant, 
   <italic>Ficus sur</italic> have been conducted, its folklore use for diuresis has not yet been validated. The current study, therefore, focused on the diuretic activity of aqueous and 80% methanol extracts of 
   <italic>F. sur</italic> Forssk. leaves in rats.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Rats were randomly assigned into eight groups each consisting of six rats. Test groups received either 100 mg/kg, 200 mg/kg, or 400 mg/kg of aqueous or 80% methanol leaves extract. The negative control group and positive control were treated with 2 mL/100 g of distilled water and furosemide (10 mg/kg), respectively. Thereafter urine volume was recorded every hour until the end of the fifth hour, and cumulative urine volume of each rat was measured. Then, diuretic activity, diuretic index, saliuretic index, natriuretic index and carbonic anhydrase inhibition index in each group were calculated, and results were compared among the groups.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The middle (200 mg/kg) and the highest (400 mg/kg) doses of both extracts significantly increased diuresis at the fifth hour (
   <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) compared to the negative control, although the diuretic activity was less than that of the positive control. Regarding electrolyte excretion, all dose levels of both extracts showed significant natriuresis (
   <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) and chloriuresis (
   <italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01) compared to the negative control. Aqueous extract displayed more significant diuretic effect than 80% methanol extract. The aqueous and 80% methanol extracts produced alkaline urine.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2004">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>The crude leaves extracts of 
   <italic>F. sur</italic> increased urinary excretion and concentration of urinary electrolytes in a dose-dependent manner. These findings are in agreement with the traditional claim for use of 
   <italic>F. sur</italic> as diuretic agent.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
