<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">The significant correlation between the BSLT and in vitro growth inhibition of human solid tumor cell lines demonstrated by the National Cancer Institute (NCI, USA) is significant because it shows the value of this bioassay as a pre-screening tool for antitumor drug research
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Hence, we assumed that this method could be used in evaluating essential oil toxicity for predicting cytotoxic concentration range and cytotoxicity validation in cancer cell lines. The toxicity of tested essential oil by comparison to Meyer’s and Clarkson’s toxicity index showed that analyzed essential oil should be considered as toxic/highly toxic with LC
 <sub>50</sub> 60.38 μg/mL in BSLT. 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil showed 100% toxicity in brine shrimp model assay provided by Bogavac et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. Although the essential oil is obtained from the same plant species (
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L.) the difference in LC
 <sub>50</sub> values and % toxicity of the thyme essential oil exists, compared to our study. By comparing the GC–MS analysis of the tested oils, a difference in proportions of monoterpene alcohol and monoterpene hydrocarbon fractions is observed. In contrast to our results, the contribution of monoterpene alcohols (thymol and carvacrol), in EO obtained from Bogavac et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>, is doubled, whereas the contribution of monoterpene hydrocarbons (p-cymene and γ-terpinene) is significantly decreased. The toxicity effect in BSLT of above mentioned EOs can be assumed, regarding the high percentage of thymol and carvacrol. Differences in the LC
 <sub>50</sub> values of essential oils from different species of the genus Thymus in BSLT has also been evaluated. 
 <italic>Thymus serpyllum</italic> L. essential oil showed LC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 37.99 µg/mL
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>, compared to higher LC
 <sub>50</sub> values (60.38 µg/mL) of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil in our study. Toxicity of different extracts of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. is also reported
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Al-Balushi et al. concluded that non polar organic extracts (chloroform and petroleum ether extracts) are toxic against the brine shrimp nauplii, whereas polar fractions are not showing toxic activity (hydroalcoholic extract)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. All in all, the thyme essential oil showed activity in the brine shrimp assay with LC
 <sub>50</sub> values as relevant preliminary toxicity parameter for further toxicity studies.
</p>
