<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Our data demonstrated that 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil inhibited the viability of MCF-7, H460 and MOLT-4 cell lines in a concentration-dependent manner. At the concentrations ranging from 5 to 1000 μg/mL an antiproliferative effect was observed for each cell line MCF-7, H460 and MOLT-4 with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values 52.65 µg/mL, 68.59 µg/mL, 228.78 µg/mL, respectively. Based on the results of the antiproliferative effect of thyme essential oil on the observed cell lines presented in (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a,b), it is obvious that solid tumor cell lines MCF-7 and H460 showed very similar sensitivity to the essential oil. The hematological tumor cell line MOLT-4 is less sensitive to essential oil than solid tumor cell lines MCF-7 and H460, which correlates with the obtained IC
 <sub>50</sub> values. Our research with 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil, native to Bosnia and Herzegovina with its unique chemical composition, contributes to previously published statements on good correlation between BSLT bioassay and cytotoxic activity in human solid tumors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Although, there is a difference in sensitivity of solid and hematological tumor cell line to thyme essential oil, it can be noticed that plateau effect of percentage of inhibition of cell proliferation is observed in concentrations of 500–1000 µg/mL. For all tested cell lines, a high level of inhibition of cell proliferation in the indicated concentrations was approximately 96%. 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil showed moderate cytotoxic activity against MCF-7 and H460 cell lines, compared to weak cytotoxic activity against MOLT-4 cell line, according to a criteria based on NCI and Geran protocols
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Beside our research results, 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil has been observed to significantly inhibit growth of human oral cavity squamous cell carcinoma with IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 369.55 µg/mL
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. Cytotoxicity of thyme essential oil towards head and neck squamous cell lines (HNSCC) was evaluated by standard 2,3-bis [2-methoxy-4-nitro-5-sulfophenyl]-2H-tetrazolium-5-carboxanilide inner salt (XTT) assay, after 72 h incubation. In vitro study performed by Kubatka et al. suggested the proapoptotic potential of 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil, by showing the activation of a mitochondria-induced apoptosis pathway in two independent human breast adenocarcinoma cell lines (MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. All these studies, were conducted with 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil of similar chemical composition to the one used in this study.
</p>
