<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Our GC–MS analysis showed that the most abundant metabolites in thyme essential oil are thymol and p-cymene. Based on previously reported in vivo and in vitro results, both molecules could be possible candidates for lead molecules of cytotoxic activity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. However, the cytotoxic effect of other components present at lower percentages in the essential oil must be considered. From the early reports, thymol has been reported to exert anti-carcinogenic activity through a different mechanism of action on the cancer cells lines. These include oxidative stress and cancer cell death
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>, apoptotic cancer cell death
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup> and antiproliferative effects on cancer cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. Contrary, antioxidant activity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, protective effects
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>, antiapoptotic effects
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, anti-inflammatory/immunomodulatory effects
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> and antigenotoxic effects
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup> may be the key mechanisms of thymol’s anti-carcinogenic activity in normal cells. The interesting observation reported by Oliviero et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup> was that the same treatments with thyme extract that had no effect on viability of normal human epithelial cells, were able to induce necrotic cell death in H460 lung cancer cell line. The growth of A17 triple negative breast carcinoma cells transplanted into Friend leukemia virus B (FVB) syngeneic mice was remarkably inhibited by the ruthenium (II) p-cymen complex throught inhibition of the tumor infiltration of regulatory T cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. The induction of p53 protein expression in MCF-7 cells and reduction of their ability to invade have also been reported for ruthenium (II) p-cymene complexes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. Ferraz et al. demonstrated that p-cymene was cytotoxic to mouse melanoma B16-F10 cell lines, showing IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 20.06 µg/mL
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Carvacrol induced apoptosis via mitochondrial membrane permeabilization in the metastatic breast cancer cell line (MDA-MB-231)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. These data, together with the results obtained by our group, demonstrate that thymol, p-cymene and 
 <italic>T. vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil as a phyto-complex have a potential therapeutic significance and should not be overlooked as possible therapeutics in treating cancer. The benefit of thyme essential oil as a chemotherapeutic of plant origin is reflected in the different mechanism of action on normal cells compared to cancer cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. During the use of thyme oil expectorant, spasmolytic, antioxidant, antimicrobial, invigorating, eupeptic, appetizing and choleretic properties have been manifested
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. When administered in the recommended posology, 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil is recognized as safe
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has stated for thyme oil (for which thymol is a component) that it is Generally Recognized as Safe (GRAS) essential oil
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
