<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Medicinal plants have been widely used for the prevention and/or treatment of various diseases, on the basis that they do not present genotoxic risks when consumed for long time [
 <xref rid="B43-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. In the current study, the antioxidant activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana montevidensis</italic> leaf essential oil was evaluated in vitro, while its potential toxic effect was investigated in vivo using 
 <italic class="italic">D. melanogaster</italic>. In general, the essential oil of the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">L. montevidensis</italic> appeared to be rich in terpenes, (mainly, monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes), which can justify its strong odor [
 <xref rid="B44-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. EOLM showed only small differences in composition compared to data reported in the literature [
 <xref rid="B24-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. For instance, in the study carried out by Bezerra et al. [
 <xref rid="B45-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>], the chemical composition of the essential oil of the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana montevidensis</italic> was β-caryophyllene (34.96%), germacrene D (25.49%), and bicyclogermacrene (9.48%), while in the study by Sousa et al. [
 <xref rid="B24-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>], it was β-caryophyllene (31.5%), germacreno D (27.5%), and bicyclerecyroreno (13.9%). Such differences can be attributed to intrinsic and/or extrinsic factors such as environmental conditions and time and place of leaf collection [
 <xref rid="B46-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. β-caryophyllene (28.15%), one of the major component of 
 <italic class="italic">L. montevidensis</italic> leaf essential oil, is a sesquiterpene present in essential oils of several plants families. Plants species that have this constituent exhibit a variety of pharmacological activities such as anti-inflammatory, antinociceptive, and antioxidant, among others [
 <xref rid="B49-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. 
 <sc class="sc">d</sc>-germacrene (31.27%), the major component found in 
 <italic class="italic">L. montevidensis</italic> leaf essential oil, is a common compound in plants, being considered a precursor for the biosynthesis of many sesquiterpenes [
 <xref rid="B52-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. DPPH is a stable radical, exhibiting a maximum absorbance at 517 nm. Such absorption by the action of antioxidants is taken as a measure of antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B53-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. It has widespread use in the assessment of radical elimination [
 <xref rid="B54-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Here, the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">L. montevidensis</italic> showed very low DPPH scavenging activity, and Fe(II) chelating activity, but demonstrated higher reducing power. The study carried out by Barros et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] demonstrated the antioxidant activity of the aqueous and ethanolic extracts of 
 <italic class="italic">L. montevidensis</italic> against DPPH radical, and its capacity to inhibit lipid peroxidation in rat brain. Our results are in agreement with that of Hossain and Shah [
 <xref rid="B40-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], who found low antioxidant activity for other essential oils. Consistent with this, essential oils rich in monoterpenes (e.g., from 
 <italic class="italic">Cupressus sempervirens</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Phyllostachys nigra</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus globulus,</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Psidium guayava</italic>) have been shown to be ineffective in scavenging DPPH radical [
 <xref rid="B14-medicina-55-00194" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. 
</p>
