<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Thymus sipyleus</italic> was investigated to demonstrate its effectiveness in the treatment of rhinosinusitis, as already used in traditional medicine [
 <xref rid="B70-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Eight bacterial strains—
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MRSA), 
 <italic>S. epidermidis</italic>, 
 <italic>S. pyogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, 
 <italic>M. catarrhalis</italic>, and 
 <italic>H. influenzae</italic>—were analyzed using three different methods. Comparing with ampicillin, clarithromycin, chloramphenicol, and amoxicillin/clavulanic acid (1:1) as positive controls, the agar diffusion method demonstrated that all bacterial strains were susceptible, with a maximum value for 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>; the only exception was 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, however this result is related to the higher resistance of Gram-negative bacteria compared to Gram-positive ones, as previously described [
 <xref rid="B3-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The microdilution method has shown that the EO showed an excellent antimicrobial activity on these species at all the tested concentrations, though the effectiveness was lower than one of the positive controls. The vapor diffusion method has also produced encouraging results, especially by demonstrating good action against MRSA strain. The antimicrobial activity of EOs can be exploited in the treatment of skin injury infections. In fact, the presence of the wound causes the reduction in the primary barrier effect, performed by the skin toward the external environment and, as the most dangerous consequence, an increased risk of exposure to microbial infections [
 <xref rid="B65-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. EOs have been recognized as a valid therapy in injured skin infections for their proven antimicrobial activity against multidrug-resistant skin pathogens; however, at certain concentrations, EOs could be cytotoxic, so the risk-benefit ratio for each one should be previously assessed [
 <xref rid="B77-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Another feature supporting the topical use of EOs is their ability to promote wound healing. This potential was discovered by the French chemist Rene-Maurice Gattefossé about a century ago: an explosion in his laboratory caused a severe burn to his hand, but the immersion in lavender EO provided a quick healing, without infection or scar marks. Since that period, many studies aimed at deepening the biochemical basis of this phenomenon, in order to confirm a possible use of EOs for skin healing. Wound healing is composed by three phases: The first one is the inflammatory phase, which includes bleeding blockage, then vasodilation and immune system recruitment [
 <xref rid="B78-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]; the second phase involves the proliferation of various cell lines, including fibroblast, leading to tissue granulation and angiogenesis [
 <xref rid="B79-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]; finally, in the third phase new collagen fibers are generated and fibroblasts differentiate, bringing the two edges of the wound closer to each other [
 <xref rid="B78-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Costa and co-workers demonstrated that the presence of carvacrol and thymol, the most widespread monoterpenes, is relevant in determining EO tissue repairing activity [
 <xref rid="B75-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. In fact, among their various biological activities, they can modulate all phases of tissue regeneration, especially the first one, because of their great anti-inflammatory action. Moreover, due to their remarkable anti-inflammatory action, sesquiterpenes are also able to promote tissue repair, eventually in synergy with monoterpenes [
 <xref rid="B83-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Recently, Seyed Ahmadi et al. illustrated the biochemical mechanisms that permit wound healing through the topical administration of 
 <italic>Cinnamon verum</italic> EO, using a mice model of wound infected by 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B84-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Besides the proven antimicrobial activity of the EO, also its antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities were found relevant, because the shorter the inflammatory phase lasts, the faster the proliferative process that leads to wound healing begins. Furthermore, the three main biochemical mediators modulated by the EO were identified: IGF1, whose expression was enhanced, leading, among other implications, to an increase of fibroblast cells and proliferation; VEGF and FGF-2, whose biosynthesis and expression were up-regulated, respectively, improving the angiogenesis, which is important in various stages of inflammation and cell proliferation. 
 <italic>Melaleuca alternifolia</italic> was investigated by Edmondson and co-workers to assess its antimicrobial and wound-healing activity [
 <xref rid="B85-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. The volunteers, who had wounds infected with Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA), were medicated for a few days with an EO solution: the antibacterial action of the EO toward this resistant bacterial strain was demonstrated. Moreover, the reduction in size of the wound was found significant according to the analytical method used, thus authors demonstrated that the EO is able to promote the wound healing. Wounds infected with MRSA were also subjected to the treatment with 
 <italic>Anethum graveolens</italic> EO, obtaining many important results [
 <xref rid="B86-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Antimicrobial activity was demonstrated by the significant reduction in bacterial growth. In addition, this EO proved to be able to influence various phases of wound healing. In the inflammatory phase, it increased the expression of p53 and caspase-3, which respectively promote apoptosis and stimulate the proliferation of stem cells to repair tissue [
 <xref rid="B87-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Moreover, this EO up-regulated the expression of Bcl2, an anti-apoptotic agent, as well as VEGF and FGF-2, which have important roles in angiogenesis and epithelial cells proliferation and differentiation [
 <xref rid="B88-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Finally, it influenced the expression of Erα-promoting collagen biosynthesis. These results demonstrated the potential use of 
 <italic>Anethum graveolens</italic> EO in the treatment of infected wounds, due to the healing properties related to the presence of its major compounds, α-phellandrene, p-cymene, and carvone. 
 <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> EO has also proven to have great beneficial effects on wounds. Mori and co-workers demonstrated that the topical application of this EO on wounded mice caused a faster closure of the lesion compared to the untreated and control groups, suggesting its potential use in the initial stages of tissue regeneration [
 <xref rid="B91-pharmaceutics-13-00327" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Moreover, the ELISA analysis showed a significant augmentation of TGF-β levels, which promotes wound contraction through increasing the number of fibroblasts, thus resulting in an intensified collagen production. Finally, it emerges that 
 <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> EO caused a quicker switch from collagen type III to collagen type I. All the cited studies therefore showed that EOs for topical use may constitute, in the close future, the alternative therapy for the treatment of chronic and infected wounds.
</p>
