<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the antimicrobial activity of topical formulations prepared from EO of
 <italic class="italic"> C. martini</italic>, hydrophilic ointment showed the highest potency followed by macrogol blend ointment against all tested bacteria and fungi at every tested concentration. In contrast, there was no activity in macrogol cream ointment, simple ointment, and white petrolatum ointment formulations. From this it is evident that the oil was easily diffused or the bioactive constituents in the formulations was easily released and inhibited the growth of the tested microorganism. Previous study has reported that the efficacy of formulation depends on the nature of bases, in which the release of bioactive compound from the base depends on its affinity for the base than media used for antimicrobial assay and the viscosity of the formulation base [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The results have showed significantly higher activity of
 <italic class="italic"> C. martini</italic> EO formulation in hydrophilic ointment and macrogol blend ointment base. Various reports from previous study have reported superior efficacy in hydrophilic ointment formulation and macrogol blend ointment formulation of other EO [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Moreover, the increased activity of the Hydrophilic ointment formulation can be attributed to the presence of sodium lauryl sulfate, which is used as a surfactant, has biological activity against bacterial and fungal strains, and is also used pharmaceutically as a protective skin cleaner as well as in medicated shampoos [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], while the better antimicrobial activities of the macrogol blend ointment formulation may be due to the fact that polyethylene glycols have an excellent solubility in water and can enhance the diffusion bioactive constituents in to the media which are more hydrophilic [
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. On the other hand, the absence of efficacy of
 <italic class="italic"> C. martini </italic>EO in the remaining three formulation bases, namely, macrogol cream ointment, simple ointment, and white petrolatum ointment base, can be attributed to the lipophilic affinity of the EO for paraffin, which impairs the release of its active constituents into the more hydrophilic agar medium. Moreover, paraffin is much more viscous than
 <italic class="italic"> C. martini </italic>oil and this would further hinder diffusion of the active principle from the oil into agar medium.
</p>
