<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Isoflavonoids have attracted a lot of research attention because of their potent phyto-oestrogenic effects—particularly those of simple isoflavones like genistein and coumestans such as coumestrol. One of the important sources of these compounds are common grazing plants (such as 
 <italic>Trifolium</italic> spp.; Fabaceae). The phyto-oestrogenic effect was first observed in animals that were grazing on these fabaceous plants as their reproductive ability was significantly altered. Isoflavonoids exert oestrogenic activity by mimicking the structure of the steroid hormone oestradiol and binding to the corresponding receptors. Their relative activity is much less than that of oestradiol. Isoflavonoids were of interest as agents combating the negative symptoms of menopause, such as hot flushes, mood swings, sleep disturbance, tiredness, osteoporosis, and cardiovascular problems. These symptoms are currently treated by the administration of oestrogens as hormone replacement therapy. Though efficient in reducing menopausal problems, the use of oestrogens was associated with thromboembolic events and an increased risk of breast and ovarian cancer. It was thought that isoflavonoids might provide a safe alternative for the relief of menopause symptoms, and it was also claimed that they had other beneficial effects including protection against various types of cancer and Alzheimer’s disease. The clinical efficacy of isoflavonoids is still controversial and available data do not support any unequivocal conclusions [
 <xref rid="B144-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Positive effects were observed in only a few studies, such as in osteoporosis [
 <xref rid="B145-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Others such as the prevention of hot flashes failed to show any benefit [
 <xref rid="B146-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>], while in the case of cardiovascular problems and cancer prevention, the results were inconsistent [
 <xref rid="B147-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>,
 <xref rid="B149-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,
 <xref rid="B150-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Since isoflavonoids both stimulate and antagonise the oestrogenic response, this potential for endocrine disruption has sparked debate and health concerns about the risks associated with dietary exposure to isoflavonoids. It was claimed that the frequent consumption of isoflavonoid-containing foods such as soy products might alter the normal levels of testosterone in males and cause infertility, but to date there has been no evidence to prove this claim [
 <xref rid="B151-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>,
 <xref rid="B152-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,
 <xref rid="B153-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. Soy products are widely used in infant formulas, and questions were raised about whether phyto-oestrogens influenced the normal development, growth, and reproduction when consumed at an early age. Again, available studies have not shown these functions to be adversely affected [
 <xref rid="B154-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>].
</p>
