<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">Enrichment analysis of modulated proteins identified the regulation of HIF-1, p53, PI3K-AKT, MAPK, cAMP, Ras, Wnt, NF-kB, IL-17, TNF, and cGMP-PKG signaling pathway which are directly involved to boost immunity. The task of HIF-1α has been reported to be dysregulated in viral infection which is involved to boost the immunity by regulating the task of macrophages, neutrophils, dendritic cells, and lymphocytes during the hypoxic condition [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]; primarily occurs in COVID-19 infection due to improper exchange of O
 <sub>2</sub>/CO
 <sub>2</sub> in lungs [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In the present study, we identified five genes i.e. ALDOA, FLT1, HMOX1, NOS2, and TIMP1 to be modulated related to this pathway. Further, PI3K-AKT functions as a rheostat in orchestrating the differentiation of memory CD8 T cells [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] which further regulate the functioning of multiple chemokines and cytokines [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] from multiple pathways like NF-k B, IL-17, and TNF signaling pathway which were found to be modulated in the present study. Hence, the next approach to boost the immunity by suggested 
 <italic>Kadha</italic> could occur via regulation of PI3K-AKT, NF-kβ, interleukin, and TNF mediated cytokine regulation. Further, in infectious diseases including viral infection MAPK pathway gets targeted by pathogens. Since this pathway is involved in the synthesis of immunomodulatory cytokines like interleukins and TNF-α via the activation of p38 MAPK pathways, modulation of this pathway could play important coordination with an immune response via the promotion of Th1 and Th2 against extracellular infectious agents [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In the present study, the modulation of six proteins i.e. CD14, FLT1, HSPA6, RAC1, RAP1A, TNFRSF1A indicates the regulation of the MAPK pathways. Further, in COVID-19 there is an increase in cell apoptosis and necrosis in lung tissue. As the phytoconstituents were also predicted to modulate the Ras signaling pathway, the suggested herbal tea could also function in multiple cellular tasks including the regulation of cell survival and proliferation [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Additionally, we also identified the multiple pathways (
 <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table S2</xref>) which get modulated in the pathogenesis of multiple infectious (bacterial/viral) and non-infectious diseases (diabetes, obesity, hypertension, etc) in which the immune system is compromised. Hence, the intake of this tea would also add a beneficial effect to maintain daily lifestyle and also improve the immunity system. The main ingredient of golden milk i.e. 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> constitutes curcuminoids as an active biomarker that has been reported to possess anti-inflammatory and anti-viral properties [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Similarly, tulsi (
 <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic>) is also reported for its detoxifying property and protection against infections which would help to clear the body from dead tissue after viral infection. Additionally, it is also reported to possess the anti-viral, anti-inflammatory property which would also help in healing the infected tissues in the lungs [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Likewise, other ingredients of herbal tea i.e. 
 <italic>C. verum</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], 
 <italic>P. nigrum</italic> (composes the piperamides) [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], 
 <italic>Z. officinale</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and 
 <italic>V. vinifera</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] are also reported for their potential antiviral and anti-inflammatory property. Since COVID-19 is associated with viral infection and inflammation of lung tissues, the anti-viral and anti-inflammatory properties of the above medicinal plants may add a beneficial effect against COVID-19.
</p>
