<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0075">Since the Ministry of AYUSH suggested the oral intake of the herbal tea and golden milk, we attempted to identify the probable lead hits to get absorbed from the human intestinal tract in which the majority of the compounds were predicted to be absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract. Based on the Rule of Five, we identified camphoratin D to possess the highest drug-likeness score with the molecular weight of 486.30, 6 hydrogen bond acceptors, 3 hydrogen bond donors, and 3.47 MolLogP; upregulated vitamin D3 receptor. Similarly, camphoratin B was predicted to have the highest human oral bioavailability. However, the single-molecule may not be as effective compared to the advised herbal tea as the amount required to boost the immunity may not be sufficient enough. Hence, intake of the multiple compounds in the form of herbal tea as suggested by AYUSH could be more beneficial rather than a single molecule for boosting the immune system as a prophylactic against COVID-19. Additionally, AYUSH has recommended utilizing the herbal tea in which only hydrophilic compounds may get solubilized. However, in the present study, we identified the combined interactions of all the hydrophilic and hydrophobic bioactives (
 <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig S3</xref>; MolLogP value) suggested in this process. Hence, the study suggests identifying if all the bioactives are extracted in the herbal tea or not via appropriate analytical techniques. However, this process is not required in golden milk as the whole powder is dissolved in the milk to drink. As the present study is a preliminary in-silico study, it is very difficult to predict the exact nature of phytoconstituents. Further, more elaborative biologically guided fractionation and identification of the major bioactives and validation by suitable 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies are required to confirm the findings which are the future scope of the study. One of the major limitations of the present study is neither 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> nor 
 <italic>in-vivo</italic> experimental data are provided to confirm immune-modulatory and anti-viral activities. Further, one caveat of this study could be that we did not measure the anti-covid potential of these formulations in experimental studies to validate the findings from above 
 <italic>in-silico</italic> investigations.
</p>
