<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>In this work, two varieties of 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> (L.) including 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> var. 
  <italic>pyrethrum</italic> (L.) and 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> var. 
  <italic>depressus</italic> (Ball) Maire were evaluated for their mineral and chemical compositions, total phenolic and flavonoid contents, and antimicrobial and antioxidant activities using hydroalcoholic extracts from their different parts (leaves, capitula, roots, and seeds). The phytochemical and mineral compositions were carried out using standard methods. The antioxidant activity was determined using the DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl), ABTS (2,2-azino-bis 3-ethylbenzothiazolin-6-sulfonic acid), and FRAP (ferric reducing antioxidant power) tests. The antimicrobial activity was assayed using the agar diffusion, minimum inhibitory concentration, and minimum bactericidal concentration methods. The results of the chemical analysis showed that both varieties contained interesting mineral and chemical compositions with potentially active compounds; among them, 
  <italic>N</italic>-isobutyl-2,4-heptadiene-6-monoynamide and cinnamic acid were detected in the 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> var. 
  <italic>pyrethrum</italic> (L.) only while thiadiazolo [5,4-d] pyrimidin-7-amine and 
  <italic>N</italic>-isobutyl-2,4-undecadiene-8,10-diynamide compounds were limited to the 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> var. 
  <italic>depressus</italic> (Ball) Maire. In vitro antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of the two varieties demonstrated that the different parts had prominent antioxidant and antimicrobial properties. The principal component analysis (PCA) showed great similarity in the activity of the leaves, capitula, and seeds of both plants and a high difference in roots. 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> var. 
  <italic>pyrethrum</italic> roots were characterized by a high content in phenols and flavonoids and better antibacterial activities compared to 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> var. 
  <italic>depressus</italic> (Ball) Maire roots, which were characterized by better antioxidant activities. From this study, it can be concluded that the two varieties of 
  <italic>Anacyclus pyrethrum</italic> (L.) showed promising mineral and chemical compositions with antioxidant and antimicrobial properties.
 </p>
</abstract>
