<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?OLF?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biodivers Conserv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biodivers Conserv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biodiversity and Conservation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0960-3115</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1572-9710</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7544764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-020-02060-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Indigenous knowledge and rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity conservation in Tanzania: success and failure</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0388-0069</contrib-id><name><surname>Selemani</surname><given-names>Ismail Saidi</given-names></name><address><email>ismal.selemani@sua.ac.tz</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11887.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9428 8105</institution-id><institution>Department of Animal, Aquaculture and Range Sciences, </institution><institution>Sokoine University of Agriculture (SUA), </institution></institution-wrap>P. O. Box 3004, Morogoro, Tanzania </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by Peter Bridgewater.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Springer Nature B.V. 2020</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par4">Tanzania is one of the African countries endowed with diverse rangeland&#x02019;s biological resources hosting 6 out of 25 globally known biodiversity hotspots. Despite, government efforts on biodiversity conservation, the pressures on rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity utilization are growing in line with increasing human population. With little recognition of contribution of local knowledge in biodiversity conservation, the current paper reviewed the potential of available indigenous knowledge in Tanzania and challenges limiting adoption of this vital knowledge on rangeland&#x02019;s biodiversity conservation.&#x000a0;This review established that, the country has rich indigenous knowledge potential for rangeland management and biodiversity conservation. Traditional enclosures and pastoral mobility are among the important indigenous practices used for rehabilitation of degraded rangelands and conservation of fragile ecosystems. The coexistence of local communities with complex ecosystems offers them excellent experiences on rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity conservation. However, increasingly loss of rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity in the country is attributed to ignoring the contribution of local communities which are rich in indigenous knowledge and skills on rangelands management. Among of the challenges hindering the adoption and involvement of indigenous knowledge to conservation are; scientific bias toward pastoral communities, loss of local expertise, poor knowledge inheritance systems, poverty, conflicts and emergence of pandemic diseases. For effective and sustainable utilisation of indigenous knowledge, the following are recommended; fully engagement of local communities in conservation process, empowering local communities to reduce poverty and conflicts, mainstreaming the indigenous knowledge to conservation education, emphasising on livelihoods diversification to reduce reliance on biological resources and promoting studies to document existing indigenous knowledge.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Biodiversity</kwd><kwd>Conservation</kwd><kwd>Ecosystem</kwd><kwd>Indigenous knowledge</kwd><kwd>Rangeland management</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Rangelands are critical areas for biodiversity conservation in terms of genetic materials (Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>) and are sources of livelihoods to many communities living in arid and semi-arid regions; providing feed for both livestock and wildlife, medicinal plants and other diverse ecosystems services (Abule et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2007</xref>). Tanzania rangelands cover more than 74% of total land of 88.6&#x000a0;million hectares (Mwilawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>) comprising about 74% of plants species found in East Africa (Goldman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2011</xref>; Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). Because of their ecological value and socio-economic importance, these rangelands are home to most spectacular wildlife population attracting substantial tourism revenues in the country (Homewood et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2012</xref>; Kidegesho <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2001</xref>). On the other hands, most pastoral communities in Tanzania derive their livelihoods from rangeland resources. Currently, Tanzania is a second country in Africa after Ethiopia with largest livestock population harbouring about 30.5&#x000a0;million cattle, 18.8&#x000a0;million goats and 5.5&#x000a0;million sheep (URT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2017</xref>). Most of these livestock (99%) are managed under traditional pastoralism/or agro-pastoralism in rangelands (Mwilawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>) sharing forage and water resources with wildlife in competitive and facilitative manner (Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2012</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">Besides, heavy utilization pressure on rangeland resources resulting from cultural behaviour of most pastoralists stocking larger herds of livestock than the carrying capacity of land coupled to increasing wildlife population, pastoralists and wildlife managed to coexist and survive environmental stress for long time (Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2012</xref>). The complex pastoral management system involving adaptation of harsh conditions in highly scarce heterogeneity forage and water resources is a results of pastoralists&#x02019; indigenous knowledge and strategies on rangeland management and biodiversity conservation (Godana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>; Saruni <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>). Historically, pastoral communities in Tanzania have relied on the rich indigenous knowledge to manage their environments and maintain resilience (Saruni <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>; Selemani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2012</xref>). Using indigenous and Local Knowledge (ILK), pastoralists manage their lands through locally devised rules, by-laws, principles and code of conducts. Besides global initiatives which encouraging the interface of academia, pastoralism and policy (IUCN <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2016</xref>), this vital local knowledge in East Africa is normally ignored in academic and scientific arena (Saruni <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>; Roba and Oba <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2009</xref>). Nevertheless, little has been documented with regard to the role of indigenous knowledge on rangeland resources management and biodiversity conservation in Tanzania. In this context, the paper first outlines the status and contribution of rangeland resources to communities&#x02019; livelihoods, review existing literature and summarize the usefulness of available indigenous knowledge from different pastoral communities in Tanzania and challenges underpinning adoption of indigenous knowledge in range management.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Status of rangeland resources and biodiversity conservation in Tanzania</title><p id="Par7">Tanzania is one of the African countries endowed with diverse rangeland resources comprising about 74% of total land in the country (Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>; Mwilawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>). These rangelands are situated in a highly varied ecosystem and topographic features ranging from highland zones with an average annual rainfall of 2700&#x000a0;mm (Mwakisunga and Majule <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2012</xref>) and dryland zones with low (less than 600&#x000a0;mm) and unpredictable rainfall (Selemani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2013</xref>). Approximately, about 80% of land in Tanzania is classified as semi-arid receiving relatively lower and unpredictable rainfall (Selemani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). These characteristics rendered most of rangelands worldwide being unsuitable for rain-fed agriculture and hence considered as unproductive (Vetter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2005</xref>). However, in Tanzania rangelands are ideal for livestock grazing and tourism attraction due to their unique flora and fauna resources (Mwilawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>). Vegetation types vary with climatic condition, soil characteristics and management regime mostly dominated with dense bush land and grassland with scattered wood vegetation (Selemani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). Miombo woodlands which cover 90% of forestland in Tanzania are integral parts of rangeland resources providing good and services to rural and urban communities (Lupala et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2015</xref>; Ruvuga et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2020</xref>). Rangelands in Tanzania are known as home to number of wildlife species recognized in the world (Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). It has extensive diversity of species with at least 14,500 known and confirmed species and is among 15 countries globally with the highest number of endemic as well as threatened species and also accounts for more than one-third of total plant species in Africa (VOP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>). The country hosts about 6 out of 25 globally known biodiversity hotspots with a rich spectrum of fauna and flora. Wade et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2001</xref>) reported that, Tanzania is privileged with diverse wildlife, good scenery and unspoiled and attractive environment for tourists making the tourism the second leading foreigner exchange earner in the country after agriculture. About 20% of the African large mammals and nine rare and endangers species of birds are found in Tanzania (Miller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1989</xref>).</p><p id="Par8">Pressures on rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity utilization are growing in line with increasing human population (Kidegesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2007</xref>). The rapid human population growth in Tanzania which results into increased rates of unsustainable consumption of resources and changes in land uses is the underlying cause for biodiversity loss (Kideghesho <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2001</xref>; Selemani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). With current increasing anthropogenic activities such as expansion of crop production and settlements, most rangelands in Tanzania are increasing experiencing some form of exploitation pressures and hence become degraded (Selemani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). On the other hands, overexploitation of rangeland resources is associated with tremendous increase in both wildlife and livestock population resulting into changes in botanical composition (replacing perennial by annual species) and nutritional quality of forage by increasing unpalatable species against palatable one (Selemani and Sangeda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2019</xref>). Increasing bush encroachment and invasive species due to heavy grazing pressure resulting to suppression of herbaceous vegetation production is very common in most Tanzanian rangelands. Lyimo et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2019</xref>) reported some major impacts associated with bush encroachment and invasive species in different parts of country which include but not limited to loss of biodiversity, disappearance of certain species of fauna and flora which in turn resulted to social and economic distress to human livelihoods. Using economic value approach, Kirui (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2016</xref>) concluded that, the annual cost for land degradation due to land use and land cover changes in Tanzania is approximately $ 2.3&#x000a0;billion which is equivalent to 13.7% of the country GDP.</p><p id="Par9">Different strategic efforts to restore degraded rangelands and conserve biological resources have been made with limited capacity. Tanzania government through different policy reform such as Tanzania Livestock Modernization initiatives of 2015 and Tanzania livestock Master Plan of 2017 to 2022 has prioritized rangeland rehabilitation and improvement in the country. The plan is to increase grazing land from 10 to 13% and promoting establishment of improved pasture/fodder production from 0% to at least 5% (URT <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2017</xref>). Despite the promising plans, critical challenges remain, threatening the sustainability of the rangeland and natural resources. The UNDP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2016</xref>) paper highlighted some of the challenges limiting rangeland management and biodiversity conservation which include but not limited to unsustainable harvesting and use of natural resources, unchecked cultivation practices, bush encroachment and invasive species resulted from the impacts of climate change. All of these challenges can seriously undermine the country&#x02019;s efforts toward achievement of sustainable development goals if remains unaddressed.</p><p id="Par10">The current global debate on the potential use of indigenous knowledge on rangeland management and biodiversity conservation has brought attention to researchers and land practitioners. Historically, pastoral communities relied on their indigenous knowledge and experiences to manage their rangeland resources. While, international recognition of indigenous knowledge on rangeland management is gaining momentum, the development and implementation of framework for integrating local communities and ecological methods in some parts of Africa have made limited progress (Roba and Oba <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2009</xref>). According to Saruni (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>), indigenous knowledge is normally ignored in academic research and policy circles. Scientific bias of viewing local pastoralists as one of the agents of environmental degradation has always creates hostility between herders and ecologists (Benjaminsen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2009</xref>). The equilibrium ecological theory that strongly linked the degradation of rangelands by the pastoralists&#x02019; culture of overstocking appears to ignore the potential use of indigenous knowledge possessed by these pastoralists (Roba and Oba <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2009</xref>; Vetter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2005</xref>). With these views, there is scanty information regarding the role and state of indigenous knowledge on rangeland management and biodiversity conservation in Tanzania and elsewhere. The proceeded sections reviewed different sources and summarized the role of indigenous knowledge on rangeland resources management and challenges hindering utilization of indigenous knowledge and practices.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>&#x000a0;Role of indigenous and local knowledge in rangelands</title><p id="Par11">Sustainable rangeland management required weaving of Indigenous and Local Knowledge (ILK), traditional practices and strategies (Teng&#x000f6; et al.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>). Solomon et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2007</xref>) maintained that, any attempt toward improvement of rangeland resources require through understanding of ILK and perceptions of local communities. According to Godana (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>) and Hill et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020</xref>), the ILK are skills, practices and technologies that are integral part of production system in particular culture. In the context of range management, these are specific skills and practices used by specific society for rangeland and natural resources management. Saruni (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>) hold that, indigenous traditional land contained about 80% of global biodiversity of which local people are practicing their Indigenous and Local Knowledge for conserving natural resources and environmental management at large. In Tanzania context, there are more than 100 distinct customary institutions (ethnic groups and tribes, traditional religious groups, women&#x02019;s groups and social groups) each with specific inherited Indigenous and Local Knowledge potential for natural resources management (Lwoga et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2017</xref>). These local organizations are responsible for management and empowering of the indigenous people for better-informed decision with regard to use of ILK. This article cited few key indigenous pastoral communities as representative cases in Tanzania regarding the potential available indigenous skills and practices.</p><sec id="Sec4"><title>&#x000a0;Traditional enclosure and rangeland restoration</title><p id="Par12">Enclosure has emerged as a successful ecological rehabilitation tool for degraded rangelands in arid and semi-arid regions of Africa (Nyberg et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>; Verdoodt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2009</xref>; Wairore et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2015</xref>). Although, Nyberg et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2019</xref>) uphold that enclosures are not only panacea for dry land development, establishment of enclosures has become an important measure to combat land degradation in semi-arid rangelands (Verdoodt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2009</xref>). Tradition reserved land (enclosure) has been used as indigenous practices for many years among pastoral and agro-pastoral communities in Tanzania to provide dry season feeds for livestock and promote environmental conservation (Mwilawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>). These enclosures influence restoration of depleted rangelands by allowing quick vegetation recovery. Angassa et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2010</xref>) reported significant higher herbaceous biomass yield, grass basal cover, species richness and diversity in enclosed land than grazed land in Southern Ethiopia. Similarly, Selemani et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2013</xref>) established significantly higher biomass yield and vegetation cover in the enclosures of North Western Tanzania compared to open land. Given the shrinkage of grazing land in Tanzania, many pastoral communities in the country are shifting from pastoral mobility strategy to enclosure practices. These enclosures are well managed by respective ethnic groups or tribes using devised local rules and regulations (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Different Ethnic groups practicing enclosure in Tanzania</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Local name of enclosure</th><th align="left">Ethnic group</th><th align="left">Regions in Tanzania</th><th align="left">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Ngitili</td><td align="left">Sukuma</td><td align="left">Shinyanga, Simiyu, Tabora, Mwanza, Geita</td><td align="left">Pye-Smith (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2010</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Olopololi/Alalili</td><td align="left">Maasai</td><td align="left">Arusha, Manyara, Tanga, Morogoro</td><td align="left">Goldman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2011</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Milanga</td><td align="left">Gogo</td><td align="left">Dodoma, Singida</td><td align="left">Njau et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Radanenda</td><td align="left">Barbaig</td><td align="left">Manyara, Arusha</td><td align="left">Kilongozi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2004</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par14">In Sukumaland, North-Western part of Tanzania <italic>ngitili</italic> has been proven as one of the successfully traditional management systems for rangeland management and forestry restoration (Kamwenda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2002</xref>). The system is farmer-lead Initiatives evolved from traditional grazing management used by pastoralists and agro-pastoralist as drought coping mechanisms. It involve reserving pasture as standing hay during rainy season and allowed for grazing during the peak of dry season when forage resources are scarce. Historically, <italic>ngitili</italic> evolved in 1980s&#x02019; as pastoralists&#x02019; initiatives in response to acute shortage of forages occurred as a result of increased human population pressure (Barrow and Shah <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>; Selemani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2013</xref>). These ngitili have been practiced for many years as drought coping strategy among sukuma people before abandoned in 1970s&#x02019; as results of ujamaa villagization programme (Pye-Smith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2010</xref>). Ujamaa villagization scheme forced pastoralists to settle in ujamaa villages and abandon their traditional pastoral practices including ngitili management. Disrupting pastoral systems by increasing sedentarisation drives a population boom which strains the fragile ecosystem. In 1980s&#x02019; ngitili practice was revived in response to acute shortage of forage resources (Barrow and Mlenge <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2003</xref>). According to Kamwenda (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2002</xref>) two key powerful institutions are used in management of <italic>ngitili</italic> namely; traditional village guards (<italic>sungusungu</italic>) and village assemblies (<italic>dagashida</italic>). In 1986, the tradition <italic>ngitili</italic> management was reinforced by the government initiative named &#x0201c;Hifadhi Ardhi Shinyanga&#x0201d; (HASHI), the project funded by Norwegian government (Pye-Smith <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2010</xref>) which enabled restoration of approximately 400,000&#x000a0;ha of <italic>ngitili</italic> by 2002 (Barrow and Shah <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). In addition to forage improvement and forestry restoration, <italic>ngitili</italic> in Sukuma land plays significant role in soil conservation and reduction of soil erosion.</p><p id="Par15">In Maasailand, tradition pasture reserves are well known as <italic>Alalili</italic> and are practiced in response to the declined pastoral mobility due to expansion of protected areas and crop production. Historically, Maasai were mobile pastoralists, searching for quality pasture and water and the <italic>Alalili</italic> were only used for sick animals or calves (Goldman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2011</xref>). However, increasing sedentarisation forced Maasai pastoralists to use <italic>Alalili</italic> as important pasture reservation strategy for their livestock. It is adaption mechanism to the effect of climate change and variability (Goldman and Riosmena <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2013</xref>). Mapinduzi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2004</xref>) pointed out that, <italic>Alalili</italic> is one of the powerful Indigenous and Local Knowledge used by Maasai for dry season feed reserves and biodiversity conservation. <italic>Alalili</italic> is normally managed by elders through individual boma, or groups of bomas or entire village (Goldman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2011</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">The Gogo people in the central part of Tanzania have similar practices of conserving forage resources for dry season feeds. Like Alalili in Maasai, <italic>Milanga</italic> is a common indigenous practice in central region of the country. According to Njau et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2013</xref>), Gogo people are among the leading pastoralists with high livestock population in the country and thus are facing with challenge of poor availability and quality of forage. Therefore, tradition reserved pastures (<italic>Milanga</italic>) used by Gogo tribes is a cheap source of dry season feeds for cattle, goats and sheep (Mwilawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>). Similar ILK was noted from the Barbaig tribe, where the council of elders manages pasture reserves known as <italic>Radanenda</italic> for their livestock as drought coping mechanism (Kilongozi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Indigenous and local knowledge on biodiversity conservation</title><p id="Par17">Based on the Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) the term &#x0201c;Biodiversity&#x0201d; refers to variability among living organisms and ecological complexes of which they are integral part of it (CBD <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2001</xref>). The rapid declining in the world biological diversity can be explained by several factors including, habitat destruction, land use changes, overexploitation of biological resources, climate change and invasive species (Rawat and Agrawal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2015</xref>). Degradation of rangelands due to increasing anthropogenic activities results to loss of habitats for several species. Biodiversity loss has several consequences to people since it lowers the capacity of ecosystems to provide good and services to human being. With recognition of the value of biodiversity, the Convention on Biological Diversity emphasizes on achieving three objectives; conservation of biological diversity, sustainable utilization of biological resources and equitable sharing of benefits accrued from utilization of genetic resources (Bennett <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>).</p><p id="Par18">Biodiversity conservation in Tanzania faces many challenges include but not limited to increased crop production, overgrazing, overexploitation of biological resources due to increased human population and climate change. The rapid human demographic growth has resulted into overexploitation of biological resources beyond the capacity of available resources (Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). Agriculture is among the most leading human activities contributing significantly to habitat loss. Newmark (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2008</xref>) cautioned that, the rapid disappearance of habitats in Tanzania if not checked will impact species survival and ecological functioning. Recognizing the important of biodiversity conservation, the government of Tanzania concentrated her conservation efforts to protected areas (National Parks, Game Reserves, Game Controlled Areas, Wildlife Management Areas Conservation Areas and Forest Reserves) which cover only 32.5% of the total land in the country (NAFORMA <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2015</xref>). More than 65% of the total land is unprotected and hence vulnerable to habitats loss due to increasing unchecked human activities (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Nevertheless, most of wildlife species are mobile and hence most of time found outside protected areas exposing themselves into the risk of disappearance. Nelson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2012</xref>) reported that many species of mammals such as elephants, wildebeest and zebra undertake annual migrations outside protected areas based on seasonal availability of forage and water resources. However, the synergies between wildlife and local communities surrounding protected areas and historical coexistence of wildlife and pastoralists is underexplored (Homewood et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2012</xref>). This necessitates the need to explore the contributions of local communities (occupying larger habitats) on biodiversity conservation using their indigenous knowledge.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Land use cover in Tanzania. <italic>Source</italic> NAFORMA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2015</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10531_2020_2060_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">Generally, Indigenous and Local Knowledge in Eastern Africa has been previously ignored and neglected in the management of natural resources and biodiversity conservation (Bruno et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2018</xref>). Recently, it has been realized that, conservation of biodiversity is hardly possible without involving local communities endowed with rich conservation skills and strategies (Carvalho and Frazao-Moreira <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2011</xref>). According to Bruno et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2018</xref>), there is strong relationship between ILK and biodiversity conservation. Tanzania like other African countries has transformed from the fence-and-fine approach to Community Based Conservation (CBC) which embraces the contribution of local communities on biodiversity conservation (Noe and Kangalawe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>). The fundamental concept behind the CBC is to empower local communities using their respective institutions to conserve biological resources in their private or communal lands (Noe and Kangalawe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2015</xref>). With this understanding, both the pastoralists and agro-pastoralists who live adjacent to protected areas have a very long traditional culture and experience of protecting the environment whereby they coexist with nature with little disturbance. For example, in Ngorongoro Conservation Area, Maasai pastoralists have historically managed to coexist with wildlife. This synergy has made the Indigenous Maasai people maintain their cultural heritage and the rest of the biodiversity without harming them. On the contrary, the attempt made in 1974, on removing Maasai pastoralists from Ngorongoro crater resulted into declined of herbivore diversity (Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2012</xref>). It was therefore concluded that, presence of Maasai and their livestock has no detrimental effects to any single wildlife species both in Ngorongoro and Serengeti ecosystem (Nelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>&#x000a0;Proper grazing management</title><p id="Par21">Indigenous and Local Knowledge has cultural significance and play vital roles on management of natural habitats through sustainable use of available resources. Most local pastoralists in Tanzania have ability to identify and assess plant species based on their nutritive values, biomass yield, medicinal plants and plants with impacts on animal performance. For example, Maasai elders play central role in assessment of range suitability for grazing animals (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). These traditional ecological Indigenous and practice enable them to make proper decision on how to conserve their ecosystem. Nevertheless, pastoral mobility and deferred grazing systems are two main strategies adopted by pastoralists to conserve their fragile ecosystems. Adriansen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2005</xref>), described pastoral mobility as a necessary adaptive strategies (particularly in dryland) ensure rangeland health by reducing grazing pressure through migrations to other areas with high quality forage and water resources. Historically most of key pastoralists in Tanzania (Maasai, Sukuma, Gogo and Barbaig) used to practice mobility to various parts of country before draft shift to deferred grazing systems as described above.</p><p id="Par22">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Range condition assessment using Maasai local knowledge</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Range condition</th><th align="left">Ecological attributes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Good range</td><td align="left">Enough pasture, adequate water, good soil, short distance to grazing, less disease incidence and few or no predators.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Average range</td><td align="left">Adequate forage, long distance to water, few diseases, incidences, few predators</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bad range</td><td align="left">Inadequate pasture, acute shortage of water, high disease incidences, many predators</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Source</italic> Kilongozi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2004</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Conservation of key valuable plants in the rangelands</title><p id="Par23">Local communities have long experience on identification of key valuable plant species such as medicinal plants or plants with high economic values in the society. Moshi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2010</xref>), reported that, local people from the North-Western Tanzania have rich culture of traditional herbal plants due to their inter-ethnic interactions with different people such as Rukiga and Banyakole from Uganda and Tutsi and Hutu from Rwanda. Although utilization of medicinal plants is condemned to cause local species extinction (da Silva et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2019</xref>), most elders have Indigenous and Local Knowledge of identifying key plant species required priority for conservation. For example, plants such as <italic>Ageratum conyzoides, Biden pilosa, Boerhavia diffusa, Caparis tomentesa, Combretum collinum</italic> and <italic>Latana camara</italic> have been given conservation priorities by Haya people due to their potential medicinal value (Moshi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2010</xref>). In addition to medicinal plants, some tress species are strictly conserved due to their cultural values in particular society (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). It has been reported that, some tree species such as <italic>Comiphora</italic> species and <italic>Adansonia digitata</italic> are given conservation attention because they are linked with ancestors the beliefs which symbolized the relationship between sky and Earth (Hines and Eckman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1993</xref>).</p><p id="Par24">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Some trees with significant cultural value in Tanzania</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S/N</th><th align="left">Tree species</th><th align="left">Cultural value</th><th align="left">Ethnic groups</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">
<italic>Comiphora ugogoensis</italic>
</td><td align="left">Ritual purposes, dyes</td><td align="left">Gogo, Sukuma</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">
<italic>Ficus sycomonus</italic>
</td><td align="left">Associated with good luck</td><td align="left">Gogo, Zigua, Rangi</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">
<italic>Trichilia emetica</italic>
</td><td align="left">Shades, Ritual, Medicine</td><td align="left">Chaga, Bondei, Zigua</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">
<italic>Grewia bicolar</italic>
</td><td align="left">Used for shades</td><td align="left">Gogo, Luguru, Zaramo</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">
<italic>Euphorbia candelabrium</italic>
</td><td align="left">Expel evil spirits</td><td align="left">Gogo, Chaga</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">
<italic>Ficus thonningii</italic>
</td><td align="left">Provide shades</td><td align="left">Zigua, Fipa, Iraqw</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">
<italic>Bridelia micrantha</italic>
</td><td align="left">Extraction of dyes</td><td align="left">Hehe, Nyamwezi</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">
<italic>Combretum adenogonium</italic>
</td><td align="left">Medicine, shades</td><td align="left">Hehe, Yao, Nyamwezi</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Source</italic> Hines and Eckman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1993</xref>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par25">
.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Challenges hindering adoption of indigenous and local knowledge in Tanzania</title><p id="Par26">Besides, the critical roles play by Indigenous and Local Knowledge and skills on rangeland management and biodiversity conservation in Tanzania, degradation of rangelands and loss of biodiversity is a growing trend (Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). It has been noted that, rangeland biodiversity loss is attributed mainly to human activities resulting into habitat destruction, overexploitation of species, introduction of exotic species and the effects of climate change and variability. The use of ILK and practices on rangeland biodiversity conservation in Tanzania has been constrained by number of factors. This section presented briefly the challenges limiting integration of Indigenous and Local Knowledge with ecological methods used for rangeland management.</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Erosion of indigenous and local knowledge and scientific bias</title><p id="Par27">Indigenous societies are generally aware of the importance of biodiversity conservation through experience and practical skills inherited mainly from elders. However, the Indigenous and Local Knowledge on natural resources management is wide world threatens by growing globalisation. According to Sujarwo et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2014</xref>) indigenous communities are rapidly changing their cultures under the influence of western models. Most young pastoralists in Tanzania are transforming their tradition culture and life styles to western culture. For example, Maasai Morans are currently migrating to towns and cities and become engaged in different activities such as guards and saloon activities. Although, such cultural changes are considered as livelihoods diversification (McCabe et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2014</xref>), they bear the consequences on erosion of ILK important for natural resource management. Disconnection between the young warriors and elders with rich indigenous knowledge, is adversely affecting inheritance of indigenous knowledge. However, in the face of their continuous and alarming erosion rate, ILK is increasing gaining attention in the international arena. For example, among of the objectives of the Intergovernmental Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (IPBES) is to ensure that the best available ILK is incorporated in the national or international frameworks on biodiversity conservation (Teng&#x000f6; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2017</xref>; UNESCO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2019</xref>).</p><p id="Par28">Despite the good will of weaving the Indigenous and Local Knowledge to the conservation initiatives but building synergies between ILK and science remains a challenge. Saruni (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>), uphold that, ILK has been ignored in academic and scientific arena. According to Roba and Oba (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2009</xref>), scientific bias is attributed to academic training of natural scientists whose understandings are influenced exclusively by scientific methods and theories. Besides scientific bias, local communities and individuals partly contribute to their own marginalisation and exclusion from mainstreaming the ILK to rangeland management and biodiversity conservation. The ways of learning, storing and transmitting knowledge have partly contributed to the erosion of Indigenous and Local Knowledge as people often &#x0201c;ring fenced&#x0201d; their expertise or died without transferring it to next generations (Maunganidze <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Land use conflicts and poverty</title><p id="Par29">Overexploitation of natural resources in Tanzania is partly attributed to poverty among pastoral communities. Tanzania is classified among the least developed countries in the world (Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). Homewood et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2012</xref>) described pastoral communities living in Arid and Semi-arid regions as among the poorest groups affected by extreme climatic events. These marginalised groups derived their livelihoods from the harsh environments by extracting natural resources from rangelands. However, increasing human population pressure overwhelmed the ability of local communities to conserve their biological resources using their indigenous knowledge. Increasing environmental scarcity is a driving force for conflicts between different land users (Benjaminsen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2009</xref>). The land use conflicts may results into destruction of natural resources and rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity through burning or improper cultivation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>&#x000a0;Emerging pandemic diseases</title><p id="Par30">Emergence of pandemic diseases such as HIV/AIDS and COVID 19 are undoubtedly affecting all development sectors including natural resources management. Apart from increasing disappearance of labour forces as result of these pandemic diseases, biodiversity conservation is indirectly endangered. The rapid decline in the national economy and household income due to pandemic diseases resulted into reliance on natural resources from rangeland for human survival (Kideghesho et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). With such economic crisis, local people engage in harvesting of rangeland resources such as timbers, charcoal making, and collection of firewood, building materials and fodders for livestock. Besides, the possession of the ILK on biodiversity conservation, the socio-economic demands forces communities to over-utilize these resources beyond the production capacity. In addition to harvesting rangelands&#x02019; goods, the unsustainable harvesting of medicinal plants for treating pandemic diseases has resulted to biodiversity losses. For example, the current outbreak of COVID 19, created huge demand of medicinal plants in Tanzania, that could significantly affect biodiversity conservation. Although, to date, there is no cure for COVID 19, numerous traditional herbs and trees have been used by different ethnic groups for supressing corona virus in Tanzania (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par31">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Some medicinal plants used locally for treating COVID 19 in Tanzania.</p><p><italic>Source</italic> Adopted from Zahabu and Temu (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2020</xref>)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S/N</th><th align="left">Botanical name</th><th align="left">Local name (Ethnic group)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">
<italic>Ocimum suave</italic>
</td><td align="left">Mzumbashi (Sambaa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">
<italic>Asparagus asparagoides</italic>
</td><td align="left">Shungamzinga (Sambaa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">
<italic>Piectranthus barbatus</italic>
</td><td align="left">Ighombo (Chaga)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">
<italic>Vangueria tomentosa</italic>
</td><td align="left">Mvule (Swahili)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">
<italic>Zehnenia scabra</italic>
</td><td align="left">Fuiza</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">
<italic>Senecio syringifolia</italic>
</td><td align="left">Ulenge (Sambaa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">
<italic>Timeria grandfolia</italic>
</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">
<italic>Conyza newii</italic>
</td><td align="left">Ikowe (Chaga)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">
<italic>Clausena anisota</italic>
</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">
<italic>Drymaria cordata</italic>
</td><td align="left">Ugwiashingi (Sambaa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">
<italic>Psidium guajava</italic>
</td><td align="left">Mpera (Swahili)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">
<italic>Rhus natolensis</italic>
</td><td align="left">Mhunguu (Sambaa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">
<italic>Latana camara</italic>
</td><td align="left">Mvuti (Sambaa)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">
<italic>Eucalyptus species</italic>
</td><td align="left">Mkaratusi (Swahili)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">
<italic>Venonia lasiopus</italic>
</td><td align="left">Mhasha (Sambaa)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par32">This review established that, local communities in Tanzania possess useful Indigenous and Local Knowledge potential for rangeland management and biodiversity conservation. The coexistence of local communities with complex ecosystems and diverse living species enabled them to gain experiences on rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity conservation. For example, it has been noted that, the traditional enclosures and pastoral mobility are two important key indigenous practices used by pastoral communities for rehabilitation of degraded rangelands and conservation of fragile ecosystems. Using indigenous knowledge, pastoral communities have ability to identify and classify rangeland conditions into conservation priorities. This includes conservation of endangered species and species with high economic and ecological values in the community. However, increasingly loss of rangelands&#x02019; biodiversity in the country is to the large extent attributed to ignoring the contribution of local communities which are rich in ILK and skills on rangelands management. Little incorporation of ILK to the ecological conservation methods and national managerial frameworks is linked to the negative perceptions pervade among scholars of viewing local pastoral communities as driver of environmental degradation.</p><p id="Par33">With recognition of contribution of indigenous knowledge, Tanzania like other African countries has adopted the Community Based Conservation (CBC) approach that empowers local communities toward conservation of biodiversity using their Indigenous and Local Knowledge and practices. Despite the government initiatives to engage local communities, the utilization of ILK in the country has limited progress. The numbers of challenges have been reported to hinder the adoption and integration of Indigenous and Local Knowledge to management of rangelands and conservation of biological resources. Poor involvement of Indigenous and Local Knowledge to ecological and conservation methods is one the main challenge associated with scientific bias resulted from training of natural scientists based on western scientific methods and theories. Besides, erosion of ILK and skills is partly contributed to the behavioural and cultural changes as results of globalisation. The ways of learning, storing and transmitting knowledge have contributed to the erosion of ILK as people often &#x0201c;ring fenced&#x0201d; their expertise or died without transferring it to next generations. In addition, land scarcity and emerging pandemic diseases exposed local communities to extreme poverty and conflicts which in turn resulted into overexploitation of biological resources.</p><p id="Par34">For effective and sustainable utilisation of Indigenous and Local Knowledge in rangeland&#x02019;s biodiversity conservation a number of issues are recommended as conservation measures. Firstly, local communities should be fully engaged in conservation process from decision making to implementation of targeted plans. This will empower local communities and hence reduce bias and conflicts among rangeland stakeholders. Secondly, studies aiming for documenting existing Indigenous and Local Knowledge and practices should be promoted. Thirdly, the ILK should be mainstreamed to conservation education from lower levels (in secondary schools) to higher levels (university). Lastly, local communities should be empowered to diversify their livelihoods which in turn will reduce reliance on biological resources from rangelands.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>This article belongs to the Topical Collection: Biodiversity appreciation and engagement.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par35">The author declared that, there is no conflict of interest with regard to this article.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abule</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyman</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rangeland evaluation in the Middle Awash Valley of Ethiopia: II. Woody vegetation</article-title><source>J Arid Environ</source><year>2007</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaridenv.2007.01.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adriansen</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pastoral mobility</article-title><source>Nomadic People</source><year>2005</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3167/082279405781826182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angassa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Oba</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Treydte</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Waladji</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of traditional enclosure on diversity of herbaceous vegetation in semi-arid rangelands,&#x00026;nbsp;Southern Ethiopia</article-title><source>Livest Rural Res Dev</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>163</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barrow E, Mlenge W (2003) Trees as key to pastoralist risk management in semi-arid landscapes in Shinyanga, Tanzania and Turkana, Kenya. In: Paper presented at the international conference on rural livelihoods, forests and biodiversity, 19&#x02013;23 May, Bonn, Germany</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barrow E, Shah A (2011) TEEBcase: traditional forest restoration in Tanzania. TEEweb.org</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjaminsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maganga</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The kilosa killings: political ecology of farmer-herder conflicts in Tanzania</article-title><source>Dev Change</source><year>2009</year><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-7660.2009.01558.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bennett B (2004) Integrating biodiversity conservation and sustainable use: lessons learned from ecological networks. IUCN, Gland, Switzerland, and Cambridge, UK, p vi + 55</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>TMR</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e9;dric</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Phanuella</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>d&#x02019;Estaing</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Valery</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nfornkah</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Funwi</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>KBLP</given-names></name><name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jean-Paul</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>WP1</given-names></name><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapfack</surname><given-names>LZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous and local knowledgeas a tool for wildlife conservation in the Dja biosphere reserve, cameroon</article-title><source>Int J Soc Sci Hum Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>156</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frazao-Moreira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of indigenous knowledge in plant resources management and conservation in two protected areas from Tras-Os-Montes</article-title><source>Portugal J Ethno Ethnomed</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-7-36</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CBD (2001) Secretariat of the Convention on Biological Diversity (2001) Assessment and management of alien species that threaten ecosystems, habitats and species. Abstracts of keynote addresses and posters presented at the sixth meeting of the Subsidiary Body on Scientific, Technical and Technological Advice, held in Montreal, Canada, from 12 to 16 March 2001. CBD Technical Paper no. 1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>JLA</given-names></name><name><surname>Feitosa</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous and local knowledgeand conservation priorities of medicinal plants near a protected area in Brazil</article-title><source>Hindawi Evid-Based Complement Altern Med</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/8275084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godana</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of indigenous knowledge in rangeland management in Yebello Woreda Southern Oromia, Ethiopia</article-title><source>Arts Soc Sci J</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4172/2151-6200.1000172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strangers in their own land: maasai and wildlife conservation in Northern Tanzania</article-title><source>Conserv Soc</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0972-4923.79194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Riosmena</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive capacity in Tanzanian Maasailand: changing strategies to cope with drought in fragmented landscapes</article-title><source>Global Environ Change</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>588</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2013.02.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Adem</surname><given-names>&#x000c7;</given-names></name><name><surname>Alangui</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name><surname>Moln&#x000e1;r</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Aumeeruddy-Thomas</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridgewater</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>CYA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Carino</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>da Cunha</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaw</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardison</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kariuki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Karki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyver</surname><given-names>POB</given-names></name><name><surname>Malmer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Masardule</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeboah</surname><given-names>AAO</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pataridze</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rou&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Working with indigenous, local and scientific knowledge in assessments of nature and nature&#x02019;s linkages with people</article-title><source>Curr Opin Environ Sustain</source><year>2020</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cosust.2019.12.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hines DA, Eckman K (1993) Indigenous multipurpose tree of Tanzania. Use and economic benefits for people. FAO, Rome, p 221 p</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Homewood</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trench</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockington</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pastoralist livelihoods and wildlife revenues in East Africa. A case of coexistence?</article-title><source>Pastoralism</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IUCN (2016) Integrating traditional knowledge into red list assessments. In: Workshop paper #9744 presented at the IUCN WCC 2016 on 2 September, Honolulu, Hawai&#x02019;i</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamwenda</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ngitili silvipastoral system in the United Republic of Tanzania</article-title><source>Unasylva</source><year>2002</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kideghesho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rija</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwamende</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Selemani</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging issues and challenges in conservation of biodiversity in the rangelands of Tanzania</article-title><source>Nat Conserv</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/natureconservation.6.5407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kidegesho</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roskaft</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaltenborn</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing conservation attitudes of local people in Western Serengeti, Tanzania</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2213</fpage><lpage>2230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-006-9132-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kideghesho</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitigating the loss of wildlife habitats in Tanzania: current and future strategies</article-title><source>Tanzania J For Nature Conserv</source><year>2001</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kilongozi N, Kengera Z, Leshongo S (2004) The utilization of indigenous and local knowledgein range management and forage plants for improving livestock productivity and food security in the Maasai and Barbaig Communities of KIBAHA. A case Study report. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/3/a0182e/A0182E00.htm#TOC">http://www.fao.org/3/a0182e/A0182E00.htm#TOC</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirui</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nkonya</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzabaev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>von Braun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economics of land degradation and improvement in Tanzania and Malawi</article-title><source>Economics of land degradation and improvement&#x02014;a global assessment for sustainable development</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>648</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupala</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lusambo</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngaga</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Makatta</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The land use cover change in miombo woodlands under community based forest management and its implication to climate change mitigation: a case of Southern Highland Tanzania</article-title><source>Int J For Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>2015</volume><fpage>11</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lwoga ED, Ngulube P, Stilwell C (2017) Indigenous knowledge management practices in indigenous organizations in South Africa and Tanzania. In: Ngulube P (ed) Handbook of research on social, cultural, and educational considerations of indigenous knowledge in developing countries. IGI Global, pp 181&#x02013;201. 10.4018/978-1-5225-0838-0.ch010</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lyimo JG, Kangalawe RYM, Liwenga ET (2019) Status, impact and management of invasive alien species in Tanzania. Tanzania J For Nat Conserv 79(2)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mapinduzi</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Oba</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weladji</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Colman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of indigenous ecological knowledge of the Maasai pastoralists for assessing rangeland biodiversity in Tanzania</article-title><source>Afr J Ecol</source><year>2004</year><volume>41</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2028.2003.00479.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maunganidze</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A moral compass that slipped: indigenous knowledge systems and rural development in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Cogent Soc Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesile</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Telligman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Livelihood diversification through migration among a pastoral people: contrasting case studies of Maasai in Northern Tanzania</article-title><source>Hum Organ</source><year>2014</year><volume>73</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17730/humo.73.4.vkr10nhr65g18400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25745192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwell</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A methodology for analysing rare species distribution patterns utilizing GIS technology</article-title><source>Rare Birds Tanzania Landsc Ecol</source><year>1989</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00126017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moshi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Otieno</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbabazi</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisheit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnomedicine of the Kagera Region, northwestern Tanzania. Part 2: the medicinal plants used in Katoro Ward, Bukoba District Mainen</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-6-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20663166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mwakisunga</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Majule</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of altitude and management on carbon stock quantities in rungwe forest, southern highland of Tanzania</article-title><source>Open J Ecol</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/oje.2012.24025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mwilawa</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Komwihangilo</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusekwa</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation of forage resources for increasing livestock in traditional forage reserves in Tanzania</article-title><source>Afr J Ecol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2028.2008.00934.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NAFORMA (2015) National forestry resources monitoring and assessment of Tanzania Mainland: mmain results. TFS survey report. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/forestry/43612-09cf2f02c20b55c1c00569e679197dcde.pdf">http://www.fao.org/forestry/43612-09cf2f02c20b55c1c00569e679197dcde.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural conservationists? Evaluating the impact of pastoralists land use practices on Tanzania&#x02019;s wildlife economy</article-title><source>Pastoralism</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newmark</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of African protected areas</article-title><source>Front Ecol Environ</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/070003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Njau</surname><given-names>FBC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lwelamira</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyandye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ruminant livestock production and quality of pastures in the communal grazing land of semi-arid central Tanzania</article-title><source>Livest Res Rural Dev.</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>146</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kangalawe</surname><given-names>RYM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wildlife protection, community participation in conservation and (dis) empowerment in Southern Tanzania</article-title><source>Conserv Soc</source><year>2015</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0972-4923.170396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mureithi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muricho</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostwald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enclosures as a land management tool for food security in African drylands</article-title><source>J Land Use Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1747423X.2019.1636147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pye-Smith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Rural revival in Tanzania. How agro-forestry is helping farmers to restore woodlands in Tanzania. ICRAF trees for change</source><year>2010</year><edition>7</edition><publisher-loc>Nairobi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Agroforestry Centre</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rawat</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity: concepts, threats and conservation</article-title><source>Environ Conserv J</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36953/ECJ.2015.16303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roba</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Oba</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of integrating herder knowledge and ecological methods for monitoring rangeland degradation in Northern Kenya</article-title><source>Hum Ecol</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10745-009-9271-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruvuga</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wredle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwakaje</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Selemani</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangeda</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyberd</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kronqvist</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indigenous rangeland and livestock management among pastoralists and agro-pastoralists in Miombo woodland, Eastern Tanzania</article-title><source>Rangeland Ecol Manag</source><year>2020</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rama.2019.11.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saruni</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Indegeneous knowledge systems and rangeland governance in Northern Tanzania</article-title><source>Tanzania J Pop Stud Dev</source><year>2016</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selemani</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Communal rangelands management and challenges underpinning pastoral mobility in Tanzania: a review</article-title><source>Livest Res Rural Dev</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2014</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selemani</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sangeda</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Kideghesho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rija</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal vegetation dynamics: opportunities and constraints behind wildlife migration in Eastern Africa Savanna Ecosystem</article-title><source>Wildlife management&#x02014;failures, successes and prospects</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IntechOpen Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selemani</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eik</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Holand</surname><given-names>&#x000d8;</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c5;dn&#x000f8;y</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mtengeti</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mushi</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of Indigenous and Local Knowledgeand perceptions of pastoral communities on traditional grazing management in north-western Tanzania</article-title><source>Afr J Agric Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>5537</fpage><lpage>5547</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selemani</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eik</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name><surname>Holand</surname><given-names>&#x000d8;</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c5;dn&#x000f8;y</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mtengeti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mushi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of a deferred grazing system on rangeland vegetation in a north-western, semi-arid region of Tanzania</article-title><source>Afr J Range For Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2989/10220119.2013.827739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyman</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smit</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cattle-rangeland management practices and perceptions of pastoralists towards rangeland degradation in the Borona zone of Southern Ethiopia</article-title><source>J Environ Manag</source><year>2007</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2006.01.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sujarwo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Arinasa</surname><given-names>IBK</given-names></name><name><surname>Salomone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fattorin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cultural erosion of balinese indigenous and local knowledgeof food and nutraceutical plants</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>2014</year><volume>68</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12231-014-9288-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teng&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Malmer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Spierenburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Danielsen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmqvist</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Folke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Weaving knowledge systems in IPBES, CBD and beyond&#x02014;lessons learned for sustainability</article-title><source>Curr Opin Environ Sustain</source><year>2017</year><volume>26&#x02013;27</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cosust.2016.12.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNDP (2016) Environmental sustainability, climate change and resilience strategy Paper 1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNESCO (2019) Linking indigenous and scientific knowledge to counter biodiversity erosion. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.unesco.org/news/linking-indigenous-and-scientific-knowledge-counter-biodiversity-erosion">https://en.unesco.org/news/linking-indigenous-and-scientific-knowledge-counter-biodiversity-erosion</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">URT (2017) Tanzania livestock master plan of 2017/2018&#x02013;2021/2022. Government report, p 126</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verdoodt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mureith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Ranst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronosequence analysis of two enclosure management strategies in degraded rangeland of semi-arid Kenya</article-title><source>Agric Ecosyst Environ</source><year>2009</year><volume>129</volume><issue>1&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2008.10.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vetter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rangelands at equilibrium and non-equilibrium: recent development in debate</article-title><source>J Arid Environ</source><year>2005</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaridenv.2004.11.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">VOP (2015) Biodiversity in Tanzania. Biodiversity information exchange platform. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tz.chm-cbd.net/biodiversity">http://tz.chm-cbd.net/biodiversity</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwasanga</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Eagles</surname><given-names>PFJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A history and market of tourism in Tanzania</article-title><source>Tourism Manag</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0261-5177(00)00019-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wairore</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mureithi</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasonga</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of enclosure managementregimes and factors influencing their choiceamong agropastoralists in North-Western Kenya</article-title><source>Pastoralism</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zahabu E, Temu RPC (2020) Types of trees recommended for treatment of Corona Virus. Leaflet, p 4</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>