<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In Algeria, cattle herds cost a heavy price if infected with piroplasmosis, a major tick transmitted disease of livestock in the country [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Another tick-borne disease, tropical bovine theileriosis transmitted by
 <italic class="italic"> Hyalomma scupense</italic> (syn.
 <italic class="italic"> Hyalomma detritum</italic>), is also present in this area. This species has been the most frequently recorded from several surveys conducted in Algeria [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>]. Many approaches have been used for tick management such as biological control using pathogens or predators, pheromone-assisted control, herbal pour-on or dip preparations including green manufactured nanoparticles [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], and vaccination [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Acaricides and repellents are still regarded as the easiest method for control but applications involve several drawbacks like cost, toxicity, waiting times, and acaricide resistance [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. In Algeria, the most widely used means to control cattle ticks are conventional acaricides. Despite of the absence of studies on the chemoresistance of marketed acaricides, Algerian veterinary practitioners have observed resistance to these compounds in recent years. Therefore, it is prudent that effective compounds be discovered and evaluated for their acaricidal potential. In this study, we investigated the effectiveness of various essential oils (EO) against
 <italic class="italic"> H. scupense</italic> obtained from six aromatic plant species:
 <italic class="italic"> Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> Dehnh (river red gum),
 <italic class="italic"> Eucalyptus globulus</italic> Labill (blue gum),
 <italic class="italic"> Lavandula stoechas</italic> L. (lavender),
 <italic class="italic"> Origanum floribundum</italic> Munby (oregano),
 <italic class="italic"> Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> L. (rosemary), and
 <italic class="italic"> Thymus capitatus</italic> L. (thyme).
</p>
