<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The capability to hamper the damage happening to the liver through toxic material is hepatoprotection. Based on results that have been done on animal models and cell lines, it is proven that Kombucha broth has hepatoprotective performance against different environmental contaminants and as we know, many environmental contaminants can lead to hepatotoxicity and also they can cause damaging to the liver [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Several clinical investigations were performed to evaluate the capability of Kombucha to helpfully reduce the physiological alterations [
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] which are because of many hepatotoxicity-causing agents like cadmium chloride, acetaminophen, aflatoxin B1, and tert-butyl hydroperoxide. In an extensive study on mice, Kombucha was introduced as an inhibitor for carbon tetrachloride (CCl
 <sub>4</sub>) activity. As we know, CCl
 <sub>4</sub> is a xenobiotic substance which can lead to the peroxidation of lipids and therefore makes free radicals CCl
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>–</sup> and finally in the normal process destroys the liver [
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. How Kombucha has the ability to induce oxidative stress in Albino mice using chromate (VI) was the main aim of several investigations [
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Indeed, investigations have also accomplished to determine the preservative activities of Kombucha toward thioacetamide-induced hepatotoxicity. Furthermore, it is proven that Kombucha is able to prevent the death of apoptotic cell related to the hepatocytes. Based on histological tests which have been carried out on alloxan-induced diabetes mice, it is accepted that Kombucha can be utilized as a protective liver-kidney agent for rats which have been a diet involving Kombucha broth [
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. So far, some scientists have performed many investigations toward hepatoprotective activities of Kombucha in mice and they concluded that this valuable activity can be supported by the devaluation in the function of alanine transaminase, aspartate transaminase, gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase in the plasma, and the concentrations of the creatinine urea. As a point, it can be mentioned that the antioxidant activity of Kombucha can be enhanced by manipulating several factors like a metabolic pathway, time, and temperature which were previously discussed.
</p>
