<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by the Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) from the Coronaviridae family and declared as a global pandemic by World Health Organization on 11 March 2020. The new strain of SARS-CoV-2 has lesser virulence but more contagious than its predecessors SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV (Vellingiri et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The highly infectious nature of the COVID-19 is due to the molecular evolution that occurred in the genome of SARS-CoV-2 (Andersen et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 is a 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> belonging to the family of enveloped positive single-stranded RNA. SARS-CoV-2 comprises four major structural proteins; among them, spike glycoprotein (S-protein) is an essential protein, involved in the receptor-host selectivity and infection to the host. The S-protein contains the S1 and S2 subunits, S1 subunit functions as the receptor-binding domain, and involved in binding with the host receptor. Whereas the S2 subunit is engaged in the fusion of viral membrane with the host cellular membrane (Lan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Shang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). S-protein selectively recognizes human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor and transmits the virus into the host cell. Intriguingly, the S-protein of SARS-CoV-2 has shown a higher affinity towards the ACE2 receptor compared with SARS-CoV (Lan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Shang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The stronger association of S-protein with ACE2 might be one of the reasons behind the higher infectious efficiency of SARS-CoV-2. Apart from structural proteins, the Main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>) is a non-structural protein and acts as a critical component of the SARS-CoV-2 viral life cycle. M
 <sup>pro</sup> is a cysteine protease involved in the proteolytic maturation of various polypeptides into non-structural proteins, which are involved in replication and transcription (Jin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Thus, the functionalities of M
 <sup>pro</sup>, S-protein and ACE2 receptor grasp attention as potential therapeutic targets against COVID-19.
</p>
