<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flavonoids are natural substances with a phenolic structure, and widely distributed in plants (Galeotti et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Higdon et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). They exhibit the biological activities such as anticancer, anti-inflammatory and antiviral, which are based on their antioxidant properties (Wei et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Zhen et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Madhu et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zhang et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Kuttinath and Rammohan 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Flavonoids are classified into five subtypes according to their structure. Of them, flavones and flavonols with C-2,3-double bonds have been reported to show strong inhibition of NO production (Kim et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Since anti-inflammatory activity of flavonoids is primarily due to their scavenging effect on NO (Nijveldt et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>), it was investigated whether Sb-EE contained luteolin, kaempferol and quercetin which are representative flavonones and flavonols. HPLC analysis revealed that Sb-EE contains these standard flavonoids (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1(D)</xref>). In addition, Sb-EE inhibited the gene expression of 
 <italic>iNOS</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0002">Figure 2(A)</xref>), similar to the results of previous studies that the mechanism of NO inhibition of flavonones and flavonols is dependent to iNOS down-regulation, not to iNOS activity (Kim et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). This suggests that luteolin, quercetin and kaempferol are the active ingredients of Sb-EE. Furthermore, as several high peaks were observed at retention time of 20–30 min (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1(D)</xref>), it is expected that a large number of phytochemicals other than luteolin, kaempferol and quercetin might be contained in Sb-EE. Plants belonging to the genus 
 <italic>Sauropus</italic> have a high content of apigenin which is a powerful NO inhibitor and a natural flavonoid (Bunawan et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Therefore, Sb-EE is also expected to contain apigenin, and eventually these flavonoids are expected to synergistically reduce the NO production and to exhibit anti-inflammatory action.
</p>
