<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The experimental plant materials used in the present study were cultivated under similar conditions in order to exclude possible variability in the metabolite profile due to cultivation factors. However, the VOC profiles of the three 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> and one 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> genotypes varied. The result of Tukey’s test showed that 54 compounds were significantly different among the three examined 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> accessions (ZO45, ZO89, and ZO114) and 30 compounds were significantly different in 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> accession ZO138 (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-metabolites-11-00021">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). The major VOCs detected to be significantly different between 
 <italic>C. amada</italic> and 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> accessions were α-santalene, β-caryophyllene, trans-α-bergamotene, teresantalol, cuparene, β-bisabolene, (
 <italic>E</italic>)-γ-bisabolene, (
 <italic>Z</italic>)-α-bisabolene, and α-funebrene. The VOC profile of accession ZO45 was leading by compounds 1,8-cineole, α-humulene, α-zingiberene, β-sesquiphellandrene, and β-caryophyllene as major ones. The main constituents in the VOC profile of accessions ZO89 and ZO114 were α-zingiberene, (
 <italic>E</italic>)-γ-atlantone (only in ZO89), β-sesquiphellandrene, cuparene, following by 2,4-di-tert-butylphenol, γ-curcumene, and β-caryophyllene. The sesquiterpene 
 <italic>cis</italic>-α-bergamotene was not detected in the volatile profile of accessions ZO45 and ZO89. Our results were inconsistent with those reported in several studies [
 <xref rid="B8-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-metabolites-11-00021" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], whereas myrcene (80.5–88.8%) following by camphor (5.5–17.9%) and 
 <italic>ar</italic>-curcumene (up to 28.1%) were reported as major constituents (in essential oil obtained from the fresh or dry rhizome) characterized for 
 <italic>C. amada</italic>. 
</p>
