<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To facilitate large‐scale production of cheap renewable energy that can be stored cost‐effectively, there is a great demand for catalysts that can efficiently produce dihydrogen from water and are preferably made from earth‐abundant transition metals. The [FeFe]‐hydrogenase ([FeFe]‐H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>ase) enzymes catalyze the reversible reduction of protons at ambient conditions with a low overpotential
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1</xref> It is envisioned that synthetic mimics of the active site of the [FeFe]‐H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>ase enzyme can serve as efficient catalysts for proton reduction in renewable fuel applications.
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">3</xref> Ever since the structure of the active site of the [FeFe]‐H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>ase enzyme was elucidated,
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">7</xref> a large number of synthetic mimics has been developed.
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">11</xref> It has been shown that it is possible to develop mimics that operate at similar and even higher rates than the natural enzyme.
 <xref rid="ejic201900405-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">12</xref> Next to a high rate it is important to develop catalytic systems that operate at a low overpotential, as it is essential to reduce the loss of energy in the overall conversion of electrical energy to chemical energy. Despite intensive investigations, the development of synthetic [FeFe]‐H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>ase mimics that operate at a mild overpotential remains a challenge to be solved.
</p>
