<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Lindera erythrocarpa</italic> is widely distributed in the Republic of Korea, Japan, and China (Sun and Chung, 1988[
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]). 
 <italic>Lindera</italic> species, including 
 <italic>L. strychnifolia</italic>,
 <italic> L. lucida</italic>,
 <italic> L. chunii</italic>, and 
 <italic>L. aggregate</italic> are important medicinal plants. The fruit and leaves of 
 <italic>L. erythrocarpa</italic> are used in folk medicine for treating digestive disorders, thirst, pain, and neuralgia. They are also used as antidotes and diuretics (Hong et al., 2009[
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]; Oh et al., 2005[
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]; Sun and Chung, 1988[
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]). Recently, 
 <italic>L. erythrocarpa</italic> was reported to suppress adipogenesis and melanin synthesis, attenuate obesity, as well as exhibit antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and antifungal activities (Hsieh and Wang, 2013[
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]; Hwang et al., 2007[
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]; Kumar et al., 2010[
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]; Wang et al., 2008[
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]). Essential oils extracted from medicinal and aromatic plants are known to have biological effects, most notably anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, antifungal, and antibacterial activities (Chaieb et al., 2007[
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]; Pinheiro et al., 2011[
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]). These properties are a driving interest in the use of essential oils in the cosmetic, pharmaceutical, and food industries (Chaieb et al., 2007[
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]; Lang and Buchbauer, 2012[
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]; Tumen et al., 2010[
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]). However, the mechanism by which 
 <italic>L. erythrocarpa </italic>essential oil (LEO) exerts its anti-inflammatory effect has not been elucidated. Therefore, in this study, we examined the anti-inflammatory effects of LEO and its constituents on lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-stimulated RAW264.7 cells.
</p>
