<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Taking into account the high interest in plant antioxidants as an emerging challenge for the development of health-promoting compounds, crop protection, and potential biotechnological applications [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-10-00035" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-plants-10-00035" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-00035" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-plants-10-00035" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-plants-10-00035" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-plants-10-00035" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], I am very pleased to introduce this Special Issue, which aims to cover a wide variety of areas, aiming to contribute to the overall knowledge of the molecular mechanism of antioxidant action by multiple points of view on both the producer and the consumer organisms. This issue is dedicated to Prof. Guddadarangavvanahally K. Jayaprakasha (Vegetable and Fruit Improvement Center, Texas A&amp;M University), who has significantly contributed to this Special Issue and unfortunately left us during this year. He embodied humility and empathy and was an inspiration with his dedication to science and ethics to students and colleagues. I remembered him with scientific esteem for his dedication to advancing science and I was honored by his friendship and he was an amazing person, always ready to help anyone in need. Dr. Jay was an unselfish, dedicated, and passionate scientist and made a lasting impact on several students and scientists around the world, according to his supervisor, Dr. Bhimu Patil (Director of Vegetable and Fruit Improvement Center, Texas A&amp;M University). The long-term impact of his research will save lives and forever leave a footprint on the earth. One of the best examples of his impactful research is based on the isolation and characterization of unique and novel health-promoting compounds from fruits and vegetables, in particular 
 <italic>Citrus</italic> and turmeric. This research would advance science to the next level.
</p>
