<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Tanzania is one of the African countries endowed with diverse rangeland resources comprising about 74% of total land in the country (Kideghesho et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>; Mwilawa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>). These rangelands are situated in a highly varied ecosystem and topographic features ranging from highland zones with an average annual rainfall of 2700 mm (Mwakisunga and Majule 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2012</xref>) and dryland zones with low (less than 600 mm) and unpredictable rainfall (Selemani et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2013</xref>). Approximately, about 80% of land in Tanzania is classified as semi-arid receiving relatively lower and unpredictable rainfall (Selemani 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). These characteristics rendered most of rangelands worldwide being unsuitable for rain-fed agriculture and hence considered as unproductive (Vetter 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2005</xref>). However, in Tanzania rangelands are ideal for livestock grazing and tourism attraction due to their unique flora and fauna resources (Mwilawa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2008</xref>). Vegetation types vary with climatic condition, soil characteristics and management regime mostly dominated with dense bush land and grassland with scattered wood vegetation (Selemani 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2014</xref>). Miombo woodlands which cover 90% of forestland in Tanzania are integral parts of rangeland resources providing good and services to rural and urban communities (Lupala et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2015</xref>; Ruvuga et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2020</xref>). Rangelands in Tanzania are known as home to number of wildlife species recognized in the world (Kideghesho et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). It has extensive diversity of species with at least 14,500 known and confirmed species and is among 15 countries globally with the highest number of endemic as well as threatened species and also accounts for more than one-third of total plant species in Africa (VOP 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>). The country hosts about 6 out of 25 globally known biodiversity hotspots with a rich spectrum of fauna and flora. Wade et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2001</xref>) reported that, Tanzania is privileged with diverse wildlife, good scenery and unspoiled and attractive environment for tourists making the tourism the second leading foreigner exchange earner in the country after agriculture. About 20% of the African large mammals and nine rare and endangers species of birds are found in Tanzania (Miller et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1989</xref>).
</p>
