<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A second coronavirus outbreak occurred in March 2012. A beta-coronavirus was responsible for a dramatic pathological condition that included severe respiratory distress with high mortality [
 <xref rid="B39-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Many countries were affected by this virus, the most affected were those of the Middle East such as Egypt, Iran, Jordan, Kuwait, United Arab Emirates, Yemen, and for this reason the virus was called Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV). The spread of this virus, however, soon crossed borders of Middle East and also infected European countries such as Austria, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, and finally some outbreaks also developed in the United States. After about three years, 1075 people infected with MERS-CoV were registered, as well as 404 deaths related to this virus. As documented, taking into account all the emergencies it caused, MERS-CoV has infected 2,494 people in 27 countries and overall resulted in death of at least 858 people until November 2019 [
 <xref rid="B41-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. As previously for SARS, also in this case the origin of the virus was mainly from animals and in this case bats and camels [
 <xref rid="B42-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. To date, there are no antivirals or vaccines approved by FDA for treatment and prevention of MERS-CoV infection. The only possible treatment is constituted by supportive therapy and above all preventing complications in respiratory level. All of these highlights dramatic need for direct-acting antiviral drugs [
 <xref rid="B43-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The latest case of coronavirus, the most serious case, has occurred since late 2019. The International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) named this novel virus as SARS-CoV-2, infectious agent of coronavirus disease (COVID-19). In chronological order, this represents the third largest coronavirus outbreak of the past 20 years, but it is certainly first from the point of view of socio-economic and health impacts. Its diffusion has been remarkable, involving more than 200 countries in the world, for this reason has been declared a global pandemic by the World Health Organization. In late 2019, WHO China Country Office became aware of pneumonia cases of unknown etiology in Wuhan, Hubei. In early January 2020, Chinese national authorities reported a total of 44 patients with pneumonia of unknown etiology to WHO (WHO, 2020). After these first cases in province of Hubei virus spread throughout China causing thousands of deaths and shortly afterwards the virus reached Italy and from here the other European countries. At the time of authoring (2 June 2020), there are 6,194,533 cases confirmed worldwide since the outbreak and 376,320 deaths [
 <xref rid="B45-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. During this epidemic, infected people presented symptoms such as fever, breathing problems, cough, severe acute respiratory syndrome and severe kidney failure [
 <xref rid="B46-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].
</p>
