<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Once again, this virus appears to derive from animal species that are normally able to host it. According to some scientists, at the end of 2019, there would have been a spike mutation, and this would have caused the transmission of the virus to humans [
 <xref rid="B47-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The first management strategy to fight COVID-19 outbreak was mainly based on supportive therapy and treatment of symptoms, in an attempt to prevent respiratory failure [
 <xref rid="B48-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Then, several world research-programs have evaluated different therapeutic solutions to counteract the advance of the virus. In particular, remdesivir was proposed as a promising candidate for treating COVID-19. Remdesivir is a nucleotide analogue prodrug that has shown antiviral efficacy against SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 in both cellular and mouse models [
 <xref rid="B50-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Favipiravir was another antiviral drug involved in clinical trials to evaluate its effectiveness against COVID-2019 [
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Favipiravir is a purine nucleic acid analogue and potent RNA-dependent RNA-polymerase inhibitor (RdRp) approved for use in influenza and is also considered in numerous clinical studies. Favipiravir has been considered for compassionate use in COVID-19 by taking advantage of its mechanism of action that inhibits the RdRp virus and relying on safety data in previous clinical studies. However, the exact efficacy of favipiravir has been not yet confirmed by ad-hoc clinical studies [
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Since the end of 2019, many clinical data have reported mild or severe cytokine storms in most severe patients, and these were the main causes of death. In severe cases there was a sustained reduction in the percentage of lymphocytes compared to mild cases. Furthermore, in severe COVID-19 cases a decrease in CD8 + T cells was reported, while inflammatory cytokines (IL-6, IL-10, IL-2 and interferon-gamma (IFNγ)) increased in peripheral blood. In light of this, cytokine storm treatment has become the target to consider for saving serious patients with COVID-19. As known, interleukin-6 (IL-6) has a key role in cytokine release syndrome. Starting from this assumption, it is possible to imagine a therapy focused on blocking IL-6 signal transduction pathway. This represents the scientific basis justifying the use of drugs capable of blocking the IL-6 receptor (IL-6R) such as Tocilizumab [
 <xref rid="B52-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. At the time of this review (March 2021) there are now several vaccines that are in use. In particular, scientist around the world have worked for designing different types of vaccines, based on different mechanisms of action including a) Inactivated or weakened virus vaccines, which use a form of the virus that has been inactivated or weakened so it doesn’t cause disease, but still generates an immune response; (2) Protein-based vaccines, which use harmless fragments of proteins or protein shells that mimic the COVID-19 virus to safely generate an immune response; (3) Viral vector vaccines, which use a safe virus that cannot cause disease but serves as a platform to produce coronavirus proteins to generate an immune response; 4) RNA and DNA vaccines, a cutting-edge approach that uses genetically engineered RNA or DNA to generate a protein that itself safely prompts an immune response. According to WHO progress and regulatory document about vaccines (16 February 2021), three vaccines present a complete and finalized assessment about their administration to humans, namely BNT162b2/COMIRNATY Tozinameran (INN) (i.e., a nucleoside modified mRNA, from Pfizer (New York, NY, USA)/Biontech (Mainz, Germany)), AZD1222 (i.e., a recombinant ChAdOx1 adenoviral vector encoding the Spike protein antigen of the SARS-CoV-2, from AstraZeneca (Cambrige, UK) /SK Bioscience (Pangyo-ro Bundang-gu Seongnam-S, Korea), and Covishield ChAdOx1_nCoV19 (i.e., a recombinant ChAdOx1 adenoviral vector encoding the Spike protein antigen of the SARS-CoV-2, from Serum Institute of India, (Maharashtra, India).
</p>
