<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37" class="p">A third type of interface that proteins can be exposed to during storage is the oil–water interface. Silicone oil is commonly used as lubricant or coating in prefilled syringes and other pharmaceutical containers. Protein aggregation induced by silicone oil can be a challenge in the development and commercialization of therapeutic protein products (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>), though the use of surfactant can mitigate this aggregation. Proteins can adsorb to the hydrophobic silicone oil–water interface and form a monolayer, which may result in the perturbation of protein structure and conformation (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>). Agitation can significantly enhance silicone-oil–induced protein aggregation, presumably 
 <italic class="italic">via</italic> increasing the area of silicone oil–water interface and accelerating the transport of structurally perturbed proteins from the oil–water interface to bulk solution. Carpenter 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> showed that there is a synergistic effect between silicone oil and agitation in the stimulation of the aggregation of monoclonal antibodies. The stability of monoclonal antibodies in the presence of silicone oil is better correlated with their colloidal stability, rather than their conformational stability (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">73</xref>). Randolph 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> demonstrated that ionic strength can affect the structure and aggregation propensity of antibodies adsorbed to silicone-oil-water interfaces (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">74</xref>). The sensitivity of therapeutic proteins to silicone oils can be studied by a silicone oil spiking study during formulation development. Considering the synergistic effect between agitation and silicone oil in the stimulation of protein aggregation, agitation stress is often applied as part of silicone oil spiking studies to simulate actual storage or transportation conditions. As with the solid/liquid interface, the use of surfactant and optimization of solution pH and ionic strength are important strategies for mitigating silicone-induced adsorption and aggregation, and most commercial formulations for biologics that will be delivered in prefilled syringes contain a surfactant. In the studies cited above by Randolph and Carpenter, surfactant was shown to ameliorate protein–silicone oil adsorption and subsequent protein aggregation. During the development of therapeutic proteins that are highly prone to silicone oil–induced aggregation, silicone oil-free syringes or syringes with other coatings such as Teflon™ can be considered. Additionally, compared with standard silicone coating, a novel cross-linked silicone coating is shown to be able to reduce protein aggregation and particle formation (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">75</xref>).
</p>
