<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Five replicates from each population were haphazardly selected for molecular analysis of the total and active bacterial communities. DNA was extracted from approximately 0.25 g of soil using the MoBio PowerSoil DNA Isolation Kit (Carlsbad, CA) following manufacturer’s instructions. RNA was extracted from an additional 0.5 g of soil following a protocol originally developed by Mettle et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup> and modified as described by Kearns et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Briefly, cells were lysed by vortexing with 0.17 mm glass beads in 700 µl PBL buffer (5 mM Tris-HCl (pH 5.0), 5 mM Na
 <sub>2</sub>EDTA, 0.1% (wt/vol) sodium dodecyl sulfate, and 6% (vol/vol) water-saturated phenol) for 10 min. Following centrifugation, the supernatant was transferred to a new centrifuge tube and the remaining soil and glass beads were resuspended in 700 µl TPM buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 5.0), 1.7% (wt/vol) polyvinylpyrrolidone, and 20 mM MgCl
 <sub>2</sub>) and vortexed at maximum speed for an additional 10 min. Combined supernatant was treated with an equal volume of phenol:choloroform:isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1 v/v/v; pH 5.5) before nucleic acids were precipitated with 100% isopropanol and 3 M sodium acetate and washed with 70% ethanol. The RNA was loaded on an Illustra Autoseq G-50 Spin Column (GE Healthcare, Pittsburgh, PA) containing 500 µl prewashed Q-Sepharose (GE Healthcare). Samples were spun at 650 × 
 <italic>g</italic> and eluted five times with 80 µl of 1.5 M NaCl (pH 5.5). The eluate was again precipitated with 100% isopropanol and 3 M sodium acetate, and washed with 70% ethanol before being eluted into 50 µl di-ethyl pyrocarbonate treated water. Any DNA contamination in the RNA was removed with DNase I (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA) following manufacturer’s instructions and RNA was reverse transcribed to cDNA with random hexamer primers using the Invitrogen Superscript RT III cDNA synthesis kit (Grand Island, NY). cDNA synthesis was checked by amplification with general bacterial primers and products were visualized via gel electrophoresis on an ethidium bromide stained 1.5% agarose gel.
</p>
