<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0095" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MTT assay</div>
 <p id="par0160" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MTT assay was undertaken in order to evaluate the effectiveness of PLEO extracted on cell viability in A549 cells stressed by NiO NPs. First we evaluated the effects of NiO NPs on A549 cells viability. Incubation with 5, 10, 20, 40, 60, 80 and 100 μg/ml for 24 h resulted in a concentration dependent decrease in cell viability, the LC
  <sub>50</sub> was 79.83 ± 0.856 μg/ml (
  <a rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0010">Fig. 2</a>A). Based on these results NiO NPs at submaximal concentrations after 24 h, 80 and 100 μg/ml were selected in this study. Next, we found all concentrations of PLEO used in MTT assay were determined to be non-toxic for A549 cells (
  <a rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0010">Fig. 2</a>B).
  <div id="fig0010" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(A) NiO NPs induced cytotoxicity in A549 cells. Cells were exposed to different concentrations of NiO NPs for 24 h. (B) Effects of PLEO on cell viability. A549 cells were treated with different concentrations of essential oil samples for 24 h also. Triton was used as a negative control. Data represented are mean ± SD of three independent experiments. *
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05; **
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01; ***
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 treatments compared to control.
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0010" class="alt-text">Fig. 2</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="par0165" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, the pre-exposition for 24 h to PLEO (60 and 80 μg/ml) were the best concentrations exhibited protective effect in cell viability reduced by NiO NPs (
  <a rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0015">Fig. 3</a>).
  <div id="fig0015" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Protective effect of PLEO on NiO NPs induced cytotoxicity. A549 cells were treated with different concentrations of essential oil for 24 h followed by NiO NPs for 24 h. Triton was used as a negative control. Data represented are mean ± SD of three independent experiments. ***
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 treatments compared to control; ≠
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05; #
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01; 
     <span class="sup">##</span>
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 compared to NiO NPs.
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0015" class="alt-text">Fig. 3</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="par0170" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main findings of this assay are the LC
  <sub>50</sub> of NiO NPs was 79.83 μg/ml and submaximal concentrations of 80 and 100 μg/ml were selected in this study. Similar results were obtained in previous findings demonstrated a dose dependent reduction of MTT-value in A549 cells treated with NiO NPs [
  <a rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0050">10</a>] or with Ni NPs [
  <a rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0210">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="par0175" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the Natiaonal Cancer Institute (USA), vegetables crude extracts are cytotoxic considered when their IC
  <sub>50</sub> values are less than 30 μg/ml [
  <a rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0215">43</a>]. After a large screening, PLEO (60 and 80 μg/ml) concentrations were selected due to their best actions. Whereas, the concentration of 80 μg/ml has the highest cytoprotective effect on NiO NPs reduced cell viability. In addition on the obtained results, it was not detected toxic effect in this model of human pulmonary cell line exposed to PLEO. The present study agree with the results of Remila et al. (2015) who have demonstrated that pre-trearment of THP-1 cells with 
  <span class="italic">P. lentiscus</span> extracts for 24 h strongly inhibited H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> damage, with maximum protection at 100 μg/ml [
  <a rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0075">15</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
