<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0100" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ROS production</div>
 <p id="par0180" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to investigate the protective effect of PLEO on NiO NPs induced cytotoxicity mediated through ROS generation, A549 cells were treated with the two selected concentrations of the essential oil 24 h previous to NiO NPs. We detected a significant decrease of ROS level in cells treated with the essential oil (
  <a rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0020">Fig. 4</a>, 
  <a rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0025">Fig. 5</a>).
  <div id="fig0020" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(A) Effects of NiO NPs and PLEO on ROS production in A549 cells. Cells were treated with different concentrations for 24 h. H
     <sub>2</sub>O
     <sub>2</sub> was used as a negative control. (B) PLEO attenuates NiO NPs induced ROS generation. A549 cells were treated with different concentrations of essential oils for 24 h followed by NiO NPs for 24 h also. Data represented are mean ± SD of three independent experiments. *
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05; ***
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 treatments compared to control; ≠
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 compared to NiO NPs.
    </p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0020" class="alt-text">Fig. 4</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="fig0025" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Intracellular ROS generation in A549 cells. Images were captured with a fluorescence microscope (OLYMPUS IX73). Effects of NiO NPs (A) and PLEO (B) on ROS production. Cells were treated with different concentrations for 24 h. (C) PLEO attenuate NiO NPs induced ROS generation in dose-dependent manner. A549 cells were treated with different concentrations of essential oil for 24 h followed by NiO NPs for 24 h also.</p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0025" class="alt-text">Fig. 5</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="par0185" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oxidative stress, which is an imbalance between ROS production and the antioxidant systems favouring a ROS excess, has been identified as a common mechanism for cell damage. During oxidative stress, ROS are produced mainly from the mitochondrial electron transport chain. To minimize the damage induced by ROS, free radicals can be transformed to other less toxic molecules, for example, the superoxide anion is enzymatically converted into hydrogen peroxide by superoxide dismutase (SOD) and hydrogen peroxide may be enzymatically converted into water by catalase or glutathione peroxidase enzymes [
  <a rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0220">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="par0190" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nanoparticles have been demonstrated to generate more free radicals and ROS than larger particles, likely due to their higher surface area [
  <a rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0060">12</a>]. NiO NPs have been reported to reduce cell viability and to induce oxidative stress by depletion of glutathione and induction of reactive oxygen species in HEp-2 and MCF-7 cells [
  <a rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0225">45</a>], cell death via apoptotic pathway and ROS generation in HepG2 cells in dose-dependent manner [
  <a rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0160">32</a>], NiO NPs also increased intracellular ROS, apoptosis and necrosis in BEAS-2B and A549 cells [
  <a rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0050">10</a>], Our results confirmed that NiO NPs is toxic to A549 cells.
 </p>
 <p id="par0195" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, we noted that pre-incubation of cells with PLEO led to decrease of ROS generation which is due to the presence of terpinen-4-ol and, probably, to synergistic effect of its components. It has been reported that plant phenols can behave as ROS scavengers, metal chelators and enzyme modulators and prevent lipid peroxidation [
  <a rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0230">46</a>]. In agreement with our data obtained, pre-treatment of THP-1 cells with 
  <span class="italic">P. lentiscus</span> extracts for 24 h strongly inhibited H
  <sub>2</sub>O
  <sub>2</sub> damage [
  <a rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0075">15</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
