<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Strains of the fungus 
 <italic>P. anserina</italic> exist as two genotypes termed 
 <italic>het-s</italic> and 
 <italic>het-S</italic> and the strains of these genotypes are incompatible, meaning that cell fusions between them result in regulated cell death [
 <xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This occurs however only when the 
 <italic>het-</italic>s-encoded protein is in its [Het-s] prion form. When in the soluble state-designated [Het-s*], the protein is inactive in incompatibility. [Het-s*] strains eventually all acquire the [Het-s]-prion state and as mentioned above, cytoplasmic contact between a prion-infected [Het-s*] strain induces rapid and invasive transformation of the [Het-s*] to [Het-s] phenotype. The HET-s protein displays a C-terminal prion-forming domain (PFD or HET-s (218–289)) comprising two 21 amino acid long pseudo-repeats (R1 and R2) adopting a specific β-solenoid amyloid fold, in which each repeat occupies one rung of β-strands [
 <xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Incompatibility is triggered when [Het-s] interacts with HET-S (‘large S’, which is an allelic variant of the same protein differing from HET-s by just a few residues). Incompatibility (
 <italic>i.e</italic>. cell death) occurs because the PFD region induces β-solenoid folding of the corresponding region in HET-S, leading to a conformation change in the N-terminal globular domain of HET-S (termed HeLo), which turns it into a pore-forming toxin by exposing a hydrophobic N-terminal α-helix [
 <xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8–10</xref>]. In HET-s in contrast, amyloid conversion of the PFD does not lead to toxicity. This is because amino acid changes in the N-terminal α-helix region abolish activity of the HeLo domain. As a result, HET-s is a prion while HET-S is not. In a nutshell, in this incompatibility system, the [Het-s] prion acts as an activation switch of HET-S pore-forming activity. Remarkably, the HeLo domain shows homology to other pore-forming domains involved in regulated cell death, both in plants and animals, the four helix bundle domain of the mixed lineage kinase domain-like protein (MLKL) involved in necroptosis execution and coiled coil-related domains found in Nod-like receptors and other plant immune response proteins [
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11–14</xref>].
</p>
