<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">The tomato pinworm 
 <italic>Tuta absoluta</italic> Meyrick (Lepidoptera: Gelechiidae) is currently considered as the most devastating invasive lepidopteran pest of tomato crops worldwide
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Tuta absoluta</italic> is native to South America and is a specialist predator of Solanaceae
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. The destructive effect of these insects is due to the formation of “mines” within the leaves and the formation of galleries in the stems, fruits and flowers, which can result in losses of up to 100% in tomato crops
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Tuta absoluta</italic> was first reported attacking tomato crops in South America in the 1960s. In Europe, the first detection of 
 <italic>T. absoluta</italic> occurred in Spain in 2006 and during the following years this pest was found in North Africa and sub Saharan Africa. More recently 
 <italic>T. absoluta</italic> was detected in India, causing large losses in tomato crops grown in open fields and in greenhouses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Tuta absoluta</italic> is now successfully established in Europe, Africa and Asia, becoming the main invasive pest of tomatoes in these regions. Favourable conditions for the establishment of this pest are due of the absence of natural enemies in these recently invaded regions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> and the abundance of susceptible host plant species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
