<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec27" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some plant extracts, especially essential oils, have been shown to exhibit insecticidal activities. They are potential alternative products for insect pest control since they are biodegradable and environmentally safer than several conventional insecticides
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. Here, we report on the high toxicity of the essential oil of a Neotropical plant, the Negramina 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span>, to the larval stages of key lepidopteran pests (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gemmatalis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span>, including a 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span> strain that is resistant to the Cry1A.105 and Cry2Ab 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> toxins). This high toxicity was associated with induction of necrotic and apoptotic cell death in lepidopteran cells revealed by 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> assays, which were absent from the human monocytic cell line TPH1. We also report that the sublethal exposure to 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> resulted in deficits in reproduction (e.g., egg-laying deterrence and decreased egg viability), larval development (e.g., feeding inhibition) and locomotion (e.g., individual and grouped larvae walking activities).
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our chromatographical analyses revealed the monoterpene β-myrcene (varying from approximately 69% to 80%) and the non-terpenic acyclic ketone 2-undecanone (varying from approximately 8% to 11%) as the major components of the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil obtained from different samples. Although these results are similar to those from previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, they also differed from chemical profiles reported for 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oils extracted from plants collected from other Brazilian regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. These findings confirm the spatio-temporal variations (e.g., temperature, relative humidity, photoperiod, irradiance, genotype, extraction method and agronomic conditions) commonly encountered in the chemical composition of essential oils and that can influence the chemical profile of essential oil extracted from the same plant species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present investigation, the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil exhibited insecticidal toxicity towards the 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gemmatalis</span> and the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span> (including a strain that is resistant to Cry1A.105 and Cry2Ab 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> toxins). Such activity is suggestive of their potential as insect pest control agents, although their potency is lower than that of the oxadiazine indoxacarb. However, the essential oil activity may well be enhanced with the use of adjuvants and with oral exposure in addition to contact, as demonstrated in our feeding bioassays. The activity of 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil was also previously reported for other pest species including the wax moths 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">mellonella</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">grisella</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, the mosquitoes 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">aegypti</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">quinquefasciatus</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> and the cattle tick 
  <span class="italic">R</span>. 
  <span class="italic">microplus</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. These previous investigations have attributed the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil toxicity to the actions of the oil’s major components (i.e., β-myrcene and 2-undecanone). Indeed, both β-myrcene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span> and 2-undecanone
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span> have been previously reported to produce toxic effects across several insect and mite species. However, as some previous investigations suggest that substantial differences on the biological activities of the essential oils derived from subtle differences in oil components
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>, the precise contribution of each 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil component for the insecticidal activities reported here still needs further toxicological investigation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the mode of action of the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil was not addressed in detail here, and as previously described for the C6/36 mosquito cell lines
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, our 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> bioassays with this essential oil induced necrotic and apoptotic cell death on lepidopteran cultured cells. These effects might be derived from the actions of terpenes (e.g., the monoterpene β-myrcene) present in the essential oil. Terpenes generally allow the essential oil to diffuse through the cell membrane, causing not only cell membrane alterations but also uncoupling oxidative phosphorylation and electron transfer inhibition
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. This interference on the composition or tridimensional arrangement of the plasma membrane can alter the basic structure for homeostatic balance and optimal physiological functioning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>, and such damages may ultimately lead to cell death
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. Intriguingly, our results showed that the viability of a human monocytic cell line (TPH1) was not altered by the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oil, which suggests the existence of differential target susceptibilities between vertebrate and insects cells. A recent investigation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> reported that the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oil selectively acts on two lepidopteran moth pests (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">mellonella</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">grisella</span>) without affecting honey bees 
  <span class="italic">Apis mellifera</span>, reinforcing the hypothesis of existing significant differences in the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oil target susceptibility, even between insect species.
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indeed, essential oils with high monoterpene contents have been shown to exert their action on octopamine, tyramine, GABA and TRP channels
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span>. TRP channels are of particular interest as these transmembrane proteins enable individual cells to sense changes in their internal (i.e., osmolarity and fluid flow) and external environment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. It has been demonstrated that the TRPM-dependent Ca
  <span class="sup">2+</span> influx may account for necrotic and apoptotic death in many cell types following changes in the redox state
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>, which would help to explain the cytopathic effects described here for the lepidopteran cells exposed to the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oil. Furthermore, as the TRP channels play a key role in calcium entry in excitable cells (e.g., muscles and neurons), altering the cytosolic free Ca
  <span class="sup">2+</span> concentration and, consequently, the subcellular processes dependent of free Ca
  <span class="sup">2+</span> concentration (e.g., muscle contraction and locomotion)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>, it is reasonable to suggest that the lepidopteran TRP channels were indeed affected by 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s also induced oviposition deterrence and repellence, high feeding inhibition and reduced locomotion in populations of both 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gemmatalis</span>, indicating strong alterations in the sensory mechanisms related to insect taste, smell and locomotion. These sensory traits are critical for multiple animal behaviors such as discriminating safe from noxious foods, detecting toxic odors and selecting sites for egg-laying
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>. The repellence of essential oils are largely linked with monoterpenes and phenolic compounds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>. For instance, repellent actions of 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oils have been reported against adult mosquitoes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> and larvae and adult lepidopteran pests
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, sublethal exposure to monoterpene-rich essential oils reduced feeding and oviposition on 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gemmatalis</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> and caused relevant alteration in important behaviors in other insect species (e.g., deterrent effects on larval feeding and adult oviposition in 
  <span class="italic">Plutella xylostella</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span> and altered walking activities in the maize weevils 
  <span class="italic">Sitophilus zeamais</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, the findings described here not only revealed the potential control of two key lepidopteran pests (
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gemmatalis</span>, including a 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span> that is resistant to Cry1A.105 and Cry2Ab 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> toxins) by the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oil but also showed that this oil induced cell death (i.e., apoptotic and necrotic cells) in insect cells, although not in human cells. Such characteristics demonstrated that the current pest management initiatives will likely benefit from including 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oil as an alternative tool in managing lepidopteran pests, especially in the context of raising concerns regarding the sustainable use and efficacy of 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span>-plants. Further investigations aiming to elucidate the molecular interactions between the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensi</span>s essential oil (and its constituents) and the potential ionic channels (e.g., octopamine, tyramine, GABA and TRP) targeted by these molecules will shed light on the major mode of actions of these plant products on lepidopteran pests.
 </p>
</sec>
