<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The worldwide adoption of genetically modified crop plants expressing toxic proteins of the bacterium 
  <span class="italic">Bacillus thuringiensis</span> (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> toxins) was a response to the economic losses caused by lepidopteran pest species, particularly in maize and soybeans
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. However, despite the importance of genetically modified 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> plants on the integrated management of lepidopteran and coleopteran pests
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, the sustainability of this agricultural practice has been threatened by lack of information about the interaction of 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> toxins (e.g., Cry proteins) with non-target organisms (including other relevant pests such as the phytosuccivorous insect pests) and the rapid evolution of high levels of resistance. Indeed, recent studies described field-evolved 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span>-resistance in the fall armyworm 
  <span class="italic">Spodoptera frugiperda</span> to non-pyramided 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> plants expressing Cry1F, Cry1A. 105, Cry2Ab and Cry1Ab toxins as well as to the dual-gene 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> (i.e., expressing Cry1A.105 and Cry2Ab toxins) maize
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Additionally, cases of cross-resistance between 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> toxins and non-
  <span class="italic">Bt</span> conventional insecticides were reported in the diamondback moth 
  <span class="italic">Plutella xylostella</span> (i.e., pyrethroids and Cry1Ac toxin) and in 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">frugiperda</span> (i.e., organophosphates and Cry1F toxin)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant-derived products such as essential oils are regarded as a complementary alternative for the integrated pest management of insect pests, as long as they are effective and pose lower health and environmental risks than synthetic insecticides
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. However, major threats to these plant-derived insecticides (or bioinsecticides) becoming commercially available are the lack of regulatory priorities and policies favoring their sustainable uses
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, which seem to be a changing pattern scenario
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Neotropical region exhibits a diverse flora that remains largely underexploited as a source of biologically active substances. The aromatic and medicinal Neotropical plant species 
  <span class="italic">Siparuna guianensis</span> Aubl. (Siparunaceae), also commonly referred to as Negramina, ant bush or Capitiú, is a relevant example. This plant species is widespread in South America, including the Brazilian Northeast and Mid-Western regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>, and products derived from its leaves, bark, and flowers have been used in folk medicine
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. However, there are few investigations on the insecticidal activity of the essential oils and their constituents from the leaf, stem, and fruits of 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span>. Only recently, the essential oil of this plant species was explored for pest management with promising results against the mosquitos 
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Culex quinquefasciatus</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, ticks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, and the wax moths 
  <span class="italic">Achroia grisella</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Galleria mellonella</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, the present study aimed at shedding further light on the insecticidal activity of the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil. The chemical constituents of essential oils of 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> were initially identified and subsequently tested on the velvetbean caterpillar 
  <span class="italic">Anticarsia gemmatalis</span> (Hübner), a key soybean pest species, and on 
  <span class="italic">Bt</span>-susceptible and resistant strains of the fall armyworm 
  <span class="italic">Spodoptera frugiperda</span> (J.E. Smith), a key pest species of maize and soybeans. The larvicidal, ovicidal, egg-laying deterrence and repellence properties of the 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">guianensis</span> essential oil were assessed, as was the potential impairment of larval walking activity of both caterpillar species. We also assessed the toxicity of this essential oil on lepidopteran and human cell lines.
 </p>
</sec>
