<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, essential oil from herbal sources demonstrates many disadvantages including poor stability, solubility, and volatility. One of the approaches to remedy such limitations is the application of nano-encapsulation, which is capable of reducing volatility, improving the stability, water solubility, and efficiency of essential oil-based formulations, while still maintaining therapeutic efficiency of the drug [
 <xref rid="B7-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Dendrimer is a spherical, branched, nanoscale material that is more prominent than linear polymers. The dendrimer consists of three parts including core, inner branches, and lateral groups. Among dendrimers, polyamidoamine (PAMAM), a group of branched-chain dendrimers, including amine branching and amide bridging, is the most widely used dendrimer due to its amine functional groups (for even-numbered PAMAMs) and carboxylates (for odd-numbered PAMAMs) that help dissolve dendrimer in polar solvent [
 <xref rid="B12-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. These groups are also very active so it is easy to react to create new structurally diverse substances [
 <xref rid="B14-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. One of the important uses of PAMAM G4.0 (polyamidoamine generation 4) is acting as a carrier system for the transport of biological molecules and drugs for the treatment of cancer diseases [
 <xref rid="B15-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Recently, many studies in using dendrimer in biocide has been proved to be much potential [
 <xref rid="B17-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. For example, Winnicka and co-workers reported the capability of PAMAM dendrimer in increasing the antifungal activity of clotrimazole against different strains of 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> [
 <xref rid="B19-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Later, Winnicka continued to design a mixture containing PAMAM G2.0 and ketoconazole that also dramatically enhances the antifungal action of the drug [
 <xref rid="B20-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In another study, Jose and co-workers employed different generation of PAMAM dendrimer (G1.0–G3.0) as agents to improve water solubility of amphotericin B drug, thereafter enhancing its antifungal action [
 <xref rid="B21-materials-12-01446" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. However, there are not much reports in combining extracted essential oil with dendrimer as carrier system. 
</p>
