<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results revealed that more studies were conducted to evaluate 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> anthelmintic activities of medicinal plants as compared to 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> validation of medicinal plants provides the proof of reliability of these plants against 
 <italic>H. contortus.</italic> In veterinary parasitology several 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> techniques are broadly used for analysis of nematicidal activity of drugs/plant extracts prior to 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> testing (
 <xref rid="B172" ref-type="bibr">Sangster and Gill, 1999</xref>). There are several positive aspects of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> assays prior to 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> including less time consuming, less expensive, need for a smaller number of animals, and permitting the evaluation of the efficacy of different anthelmintic compounds throughout the life cycle of the parasite (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Demeler et al., 2013</xref>). Based on the reliable results obtained from 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> analysis further selection of extract/pure compound for 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> evaluation can be carried-out (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Zips et al., 2005</xref>). 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> studies are mainly conducted to evaluate the mechanism of action of the desired extract/compound, the immune response of the host animal, toxicity levels, as well as the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> effectiveness. Although there are many advantages of 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies, but there are also some shortcomings including more time consuming, expensive, and lower precision and reproducibility (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Lacey et al., 1990</xref>). These limitations should be taken into account and highlight the significance of pharmaceutical/pharmacokinetic studies for the industrial development of new anthelmintic products against 
 <italic>H. contortus</italic>. The research to find effective and natural anthelmintics has been highly inundated with 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies, hence, it is suggested to evaluate the plant extracts/compounds 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> in future.
</p>
