<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As a promising alternative to oil extraction using hexane, enzyme‐assisted aqueous extraction (EAE) has received significant attention recently. The use of enzymes in an aqueous medium allows for oil separation through the hydrolysis of protein and pseudomembranes surrounding the oil bodies (Campbell &amp; Glatz, 
 <xref rid="fsn3936-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). During EAE of soybeans, three distinct fractions are formed: a cream with emulsified oil, a protein and sugar‐rich skim, and a fiber‐rich residual (Campbell et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3936-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). The cream fraction is usually subjected to de‐emulsification to further improve the oil extraction yield (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3936-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The skim fraction (SF) is an aqueous phase that contains a small amount of emulsified oil and soluble saccharides and a significant amount of soybean protein (de Moura et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn3936-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). It was estimated that almost 27 L of SF was produced for every liter of soybean oil extracted (Yao, Wang, &amp; Wang, 
 <xref rid="fsn3936-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Therefore, efficient protein recovery from SF is a crucial and challenging step that impedes the commercial adoption of EAE process. Conventional methods for high‐purity soybean protein extraction are mainly based on their low solubility at average isoelectric point (pH 4.5) (Alibhai, Mondor, Moresoli, Ippersiel, &amp; Lamarche, 
 <xref rid="fsn3936-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). However, since the solubility of hydrolyzed protein was significantly enhanced at acidic pH, isoelectric precipitation only resulted in a total protein recovery of 30% in extracting skim protein from EAE of soybeans (Campbell &amp; Glatz, 
 <xref rid="fsn3936-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
