<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The bactericidal activity of the top-10 most effective growth inhibitors (pure EOs and in combination) of 
 <italic>A. veronii</italic> bv. 
 <italic>sobria</italic> was also investigated. Intriguingly, a different pattern compared to the inhibitory activity (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) was recorded, with blends of Greek oregano with savoury (#8), Greek oregano with savoury and Spanish oregano (#31), and pure Spanish oregano EO (#5) being the most effective. However, this is not surprising considering that carvacrol, a compound highly abundant in these three solutions, is already reported to have lethal effects on several Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria, such as 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> (Murray et al. 1926) Pirie 1940, 
 <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> (Jones et al. 1931) Veron &amp; Chatelain 1973, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (Migula 1895) Castellani &amp; Chalmers 1919, 
 <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> (ex Kauffmann &amp; Edwards 1952) Le Minor &amp; Popoff 1987 [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], and 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Nevertheless, it is worth noticing that the third most fatal EO was pure Spanish oregano with 42.0% carvacrol content and not Greek oregano containing 72.0% carvacrol. This finding suggests that bactericidal activity of EO blends cannot be predicted solely on the basis of carvacrol content. Hence, other minor constituents and their interactions with the major ones, may play an important role in the germicidal behaviour of these EOs. The beneficial antimicrobial activity of members of the Lamiaceae family, and especially of carvacrol-rich MAPs is widely recognized [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Nevertheless, the potential toxic effects of EOs and/or of their chemical components on organisms are dose-dependent [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In this context, it is quite likely that the positive effect of EOs administration on fish applied as anti-bacterial agents against pathogens can be achieved at much lower concentrations than their respective toxicity thresholds. The mechanism of antibacterial action of the EOs’ composition either used alone or when mixed in blends deserves to be studied in more detail in order to elucidate the complexity of concomitant interactions [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-26-02731" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It is worth deciphering why combinations of EOs with a strong individual antimicrobial efficacy, such as Greek oregano or Spanish oregano and savoury, do not actually show synergistic or additive effects when blended, and why -on the other hand- combinations of two or more EOs with individually moderate activity, such as those of wild carrot, rosemary, etc. studied herein, may result in considerably enhanced effects when are combined in blended EOs preparations.
</p>
