<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral infections, including the current COVID-19 pandemic, are often associated with fever, general malaise, pain, and aches (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Of these, fever (98%), cough (76%), dyspnoea (55%), myalgia or fatigue (44%), headache (8%), and haemoptysis (5%) are commonly noted (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). These infections, therefore, even in the milder and non-life threatening forms, can significantly affect the quality of life. Among the various peculiarities of the COVID-19 infection concerns have been raised about the use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), in particular ibuprofen, which at first seemed to worsen the illness, although further studies have disproved this concern (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). As a consequence, several regulatory agencies, including the European Medicines Agency (EMA), at first expressed concerns about its use, as it may deprive patients of an effective treatment for fever and pain with the exception of paracetamol/acetaminophen (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The debate about NSAID safety is still open. At the beginning of the pandemic, ibuprofen was hypothesized to increase the risk of severe adverse events in COVID-19 patients and a link between NSAIDs and angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) 2 receptors upregulation was suggested to be involved (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Further, Micallef et al. (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) reported that some preclinical evidences, such as immunomodulatory effects or antibiotics efficacy reduction, would support a possible link between NSAIDs and complications in COVID-19 patients. However, data about NSAIDs use in COVID-19 is still inconsistent. In fact, some authors suggested that NSAIDs should be avoided in COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) and others reported that NSAID use has been associated with worse outcomes (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). At the same time, other authors highlighted that evidence about the worsening of COVID-19 symptoms by ibuprofen is lacking (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) or only suggested to be prudent in the prescription (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).
</p>
