<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The fact that ENSDs form in the subsurface in hydrocarbon-bearing systems presents a major challenge to study the involved processes 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic>. Epigenetic native sulfur deposits have been accessed by drilling and mining, but even in cases where native sulfur and hydrocarbons were present, such as at the Main Pass 299 dome offshore Louisiana (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kyle, 1999</xref>), it is not clear if the formation process was still ongoing. Moreover, drilling and mining introduce O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and potentially cause contamination with extraneous microbial communities. For these reasons, interpretations of the conditions under which ENSDs formed mainly rely on petrographic or geochemical studies of geologic archives. Unfortunately, it is geochemically difficult to find evidence that O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is involved in sulfide oxidation because this process does not leave obvious geochemical fingerprints. For example, during the oxidation of sulfide to native sulfur, oxygen from O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> reacts with hydrogen to form water, which is added to the pool of ambient water. The distinct isotopic fingerprint of the O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-derived water is diluted to such a degree that it is no longer distinguishable in the original ambient water, nor is it preserved in carbonate minerals that precipitate from this water. Moreover, chemotrophic sulfide-oxidizing bacteria do not synthesize lipid biomarkers of sufficient specificity (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Arning et al., 2008</xref>). It is equally difficult to make a case, or find geochemical proof, that O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> was absent during the formation of an ENSD. Thus, other, more indirect approaches are necessary. For example, at Damon Mound it was shown that the hydrocarbon degradation products differ between the sulfur-barren near surface caprock, which has likely experienced extensive penetration of O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-rich meteoric water, and deeper caprock where native sulfur is present and supply with O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> must have been limited (
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sassen et al., 1988</xref>).
</p>
