<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Production of Fermented Fish Flours</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different types of fermented fish flour used in this study were produced in the field of fermented fish production located in the Artisanal Fishing Port of Cotonou (southern Benin). The production methods used can be described as follows: samples of fresh fishes (
  <span class="italic">Galéoides decadactylus</span>) are scaled and eviscerated. After washing, it was left for 24 h for maturation. During this step, the fish is subjected to a tissue degradation process, under the action of enzymes and microorganisms. After the maturation step, fishes are salted by introducing the salt into the evisceration slot made under the operculum, and also into the gills and over the entire body of the fish. Fishes are now ready to the anaerobic fermentation process which duration is 3 days. After the anaerobic fermentation step, fish’s samples are then rinsed by immersion in brine (0.5%). The fish thus treated are then separated into four (4) parts labelled respectively A, B, C and D. The first three parts of fish (A, B, C) are treated with the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Pimenta racemosa</span> by adjunction at doses of 0.5, 1.0 and 2.0 μL g
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. These doses were chosen because of the strong fragrance of the essential oil. The fourth part of fish’s samples (D) are not treated with the essential oil and is therefore considered as a control. Fishes are set to solar drying for 6 days according to traditional technology. After the solar drying step, fish’s samples are then ground using a conventional mechanical mill, which is found at the fermented fish production sites of the area’s study. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> indicated the technological diagram used for fermented fish flour production.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Process diagram of different fermented fish flours production</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13659_2017_132_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
