<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mild climates are most suitable for the luxuriant growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Tagetes</italic> species. Flowering in these species greatly improves during mild climates in temperatures ranging from 14.5–28.6 °C. However, higher temperatures (26.2–36.4 °C) adversely affect flower production. The species of 
 <italic class="italic">Tagetes</italic> successfully adapted to different soil conditions. However, the most desirable conditions for enhanced production are a deep, fertile, friable soil having good water-holding capacity, being well drained with a pH close to 7.0–7.5. Sandy loam is ideal for the cultivation of 
 <italic class="italic">Tagetes</italic> spp. The crop of 
 <italic class="italic">Tagetes</italic> is suitable for cultivation in the plains, as well as on the hills, as a monocrop or intercrop in orchards/forest aromatic trees or as widely spaced crops such as rose-scented geranium. It is amenable for integration with traditional agricultural or aromatic crops in suitable field rotations. Cool temperatures induce germination, whereas high temperatures encourage profuse vegetative growth and flowering. Direct seeding (2.0–2.5 kg seeds/ha) or transplanting of 100–200-mm-long 30–60-day-old seedlings (0.50–0.75 kg seeds/ha for raising the nursery) with (300–600) × (150–300) mm spacing is practiced. A closer spacing of 300 × (150–300) mm for direct broadcasted or line-sown seeded crops and a wider spacing of (450–600) × 300 mm for transplanted crops are recommended. In less fertile soils, a closer spacing of 300 × 300 mm is suggested. Seeds germinate in 7–10 days [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Young seedlings are susceptible to weed competition. Two to three manual weeding operations are necessary until the crop establishes. Fully grown plants can smother the weeds. Nipping apical buds 50–60 days after seed sowing or 30–45 days after transplanting promotes the growth of branches and produces a crop canopy with a higher proportion of leaves and flowers. The crop can withstand short periods of moisture shortage. Phosphorus and potassium are usually applied basally, while nitrogen is applied in three equal splits upon planting, active vegetative, and flower bud initiation stages. The crop is occasionally affected by wilt (caused by 
 <italic class="italic">Sclerotiana sclerotium</italic>, for which seed treatment with Thiram is suggested), 
 <italic class="italic">S. rolfsii</italic> (seed treatment with Thiram is recommended), little leaf (caused by phytoplasma, for which spraying with 
 <italic class="italic">Streptomycin</italic> is useful), marigold mosaic (caused by virus, infected plants are burnt) diseases, and collar rot (caused by 
 <italic class="italic">S. sclerotium</italic>). Three to five irrigations at depths of 25–30 mm or at 0.5 IW:CPE ratio of irrigation scheduling [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] are sufficient for raising a good crop. The crop responds to applications of 20–30 tons of Farm Yard Manures (FYM), 100–200 kg N, 60 kg P
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>Os, 60 kg K
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O/ha. Wild marigold is harvested manually with sickles during full flowering [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] (4–7 months duration) or seed setting [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] stages 200–300 mm above ground level. Crop duration is short (main 10 days, ratoon 30–60 days) in south India irrespective of whether the crop is planted in rainy (July/September) or winter (December) seasons [
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-23-02847" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. In the rainy seasons, weeds become the major problem for the yield of marigold. If the weeds are not removed in time, great loss occurs in terms of growth and productivity.
</p>
