<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7" class="p">The fouled RO membrane samples were observed by the direct confocal reflection microscopy (CRM)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. Briefly, a confocal laser scanning microscope (LSM880; Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany) equipped with a 40 × /0.80 numerical aperture water immersion objective (Achroplan W; Carl Zeiss) was used to acquire the biofilm images. For live/dead staining, the RO membrane samples were treated for 15 minutes with SYTO9 for live cells and Propidium iodide (PI) for dead cells (Molecular Probes, OR, US) at final concentrations of 5 µM and 15 µM, respectively. The other staining dyes ConA-FITC conjugate (Sigma-Aldrich, MO, USA), FM4-64 (Molecular Probes) and FilmTracer SYPRO Ruby Biofilm Matrix Stain (Molecular Probes) were used to visualize polysaccharides, lipids (plasma membrane) and proteins, respectively, according to the manufacturers’ instructions. The fluorescent dyes-treated RO membrane samples were washed with water once and set in the sample chamber filled with water in order to wash out the non-specific binding dye and residual dye. For non-destructive observation, the fouled membrane samples were visualized using water immersion lens without a coverslip. Reflected light of 514-nm argon laser was used for reflection microscopy. Illumination with 453-, 488- and 514-nm argon lasers was conducted to detect the SYPRO Ruby, SYTO9/ConA-FITC and FM4-64 fluorescence, respectively. The PI fluorescence was detected with a 543 nm He-Ne laser. An MBS T80/R20 filter (Carl Zeiss) was used as the main beam splitter to detect the reflected light. The obtained images were analyzed using the ZEN software (Carl Zeiss) for the three-dimensional image construction. At least six microscopic images at random points on the RO membrane were taken per sample and the representative images are shown. The total amount, biofilm thickness, cell amount, living cell rate, the polysaccharide, lipid and protein amounts were determined based on six to ten independent observations, and the standard deviations are indicated. The amounts of polysaccharides, lipids and proteins were determined based on the ConA-FITC, FM4-64 and SYPRO Ruby fluorescent signals. The cell amount and living cell rate were calculated from the fluorescent signal intensities of SYTO9 and PI. The image analysis of biofilm was performed using Comstat2 program (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.comstat.dk" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.comstat.dk</ext-link>)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
