<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Xanthophylls in DDGS are highly available and are responsible for yolk yellow color. Distillers dried grains with solubles provided 34 mg xanthophyll/kg, more than that from corn [
 <xref rid="B38-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], even though corn contains over three times the amount of xanthophylls (10.62 mg/kg; NRC, [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]). Similarly, Roberson et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] indicated that dietary DDGS could increase yolk color density. In addition, the removal of egg yolk starch through ethanol fermentation raised the various nutrient contents, including xanthophylls [
 <xref rid="B24-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The xanthophyll content of corn and DDGS were 17 and 30 mg/kg as reported by NRC [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] and Roberson et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], respectively. Distillers dried grains with solubles could be considered a natural feeding material that provides xanthophylls for egg-producing hens [
 <xref rid="B39-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Consequently, it can be a cost-effective means of improving yolk and skin colors that are preferred by consumers and enhance the value of egg in some regions. Xanthophylls include lutein, zeaxanthin, and cryptoxanthin, and represent 0.1, 0.2, and 0.03% of egg yolk content, respectively [
 <xref rid="B40-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Lutein plays an important role in preventing age-related macular degeneration [
 <xref rid="B41-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Poultry species cannot synthesize xanthophylls and depend on dietary sources for color [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-animals-09-00150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Therefore, DDGS inclusion in the diet would provide high levels of xanthophylls and increase lutein content in egg yolk. Results of yolk color reported in the present study indicated that the xanthophylls found in DDGS were effectively absorbed and utilized by the hens (
 <xref rid="animals-09-00150-t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>). Farmers can save on the cost of adding artificial pigments to dense yolk color by utilizing DDGS dietary supplementation. 
</p>
