<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well known that chronic inflammation is implicated in the development and progression of many chronic diseases such as autoimmune and neurodegenerative diseases, atherosclerosis, obesity, diabetes, cardiovascular diseases, and cancer. Chronic inflammation represents, nowadays, the most significant cause of death (&gt;50%) worldwide [
 <xref rid="B148-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. Existing biomarkers, which include, but not limited to CRP, IL-1β, IL-6 and TNF-α, IL-8, IL-17, IL-12, IL-23, and CCL5, have been useful for demonstrating that inflammatory activity is involved in the pathogenesis of chronic diseases and mortality risk [
 <xref rid="B148-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>,
 <xref rid="B149-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. Cortisol and anti-inflammatory natural products were shown to provide protections on a number of chronic diseases. The anti-inflammatory activity of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> was reported by several groups. Momeni et al. were among the first to show a potential anti-inflammatory activity of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic>. The authors demonstrated that sumac fruit alcoholic extract significantly reduced the level of mRNA of the pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-18 and IL-1β, in lipopolysaccharide-stimulated synoviocyte extracted from joint and fluid of limb of the 8-month-old healthy calf [
 <xref rid="B122-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. In another study, Gabr 
 <italic>et al</italic>. showed that 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> fruit extract accelerates the healing of induced wounds in Wistar male rats. Indeed, sumac-treated rats at concentrations of 5 mg/mL and 10 mg/mL showed a significant wound healing at day 6 and 10 post-wounding associated with increased deposition of collagen, hydroxyproline, reduction of MMP-8, and MPO enzyme activity. The authors suggest that the improved healing process might be due to the anti-inflammatory activity of sumac fruit extract [
 <xref rid="B61-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Macerated ethanol and ethanol-water fruit extracts of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> were shown to significantly downregulate in vitro, in HaCaT keratinocyte cells, the level of TNF-α- stimulated IL-8 through inhibition of the NFκB signaling pathway [
 <xref rid="B123-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. This study further confirms the potential therapeutic activity of 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> in the treatment of skin inflammation. A large body of evidence points to the role of inflammation in cancer progression. Increased levels of inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-6, IL-8, and TNF-α, are known to promote migration, invasion and metastasis of various types of cancer [
 <xref rid="B150-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>] and inhibition of these pathways represent a promising approach in cancer treatment. Interestingly, 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> ethanolic extract was shown to significantly downregulate IL-5, IL-8, and TNF-α in breast cancer cells [
 <xref rid="B119-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> fruit extract was shown to downregulate NFκB and STAT3 signaling, two major actors that play crucial roles in transmitting signals of inflammatory cytokines to the nucleus [
 <xref rid="B119-antioxidants-10-00073" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Hence, one possible mechanism through which 
 <italic>Rhus coriaria</italic> inhibit breast cancer through its anti-inflammatory activity.
</p>
