<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Plant biodiversity of argan woodlands reflects its biogeographic heterogeneity where Mediterranean, tropical, succulent, and endemics taxa coexist (Msanda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2005</xref>). The current flora results from paleoclimatological, paleoecological, and paleogeographical influences persisting since the Tertiary. In fact, some parts of the west-central of Morroco are considered as a refuge for tertiary flora, particularly for African thermo-xerophile taxons (Médail and Quézel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">1999</xref>; Médail and Diadema 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2009</xref>). On the Atlantic coast, crassulescent and aphyllous taxa are well represented. They include 
 <italic>E. officinarum</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>officinarum</italic>, 
 <italic>A. burchardii</italic> (N. E. Br.) Plowes subsp. 
 <italic>maura</italic> (Maire) Meve &amp; Liede, 
 <italic>Orbea decaisneana</italic> var. 
 <italic>hesperidum</italic> (Maire) Jonkers
 <italic>, Apteranthes joannis</italic> (Maire) Plowes., 
 <italic>A. arborescens</italic> and 
 <italic>A. latifolia</italic>. Macaronesian elements, linked to the Infra Mediterranean belt, are represented by several plants. The most important species are 
 <italic>Davallia canariensis</italic> (L.) Sm., 
 <italic>Asparagus pastorianus</italic> Webb &amp; Berthel., 
 <italic>Bassia tomentosa</italic> (Lowe) Maire &amp; Weiller, 
 <italic>Artemisia reptans</italic> Bush, 
 <italic>Helianthemum canariense</italic> (Jacq.) Pers., 
 <italic>Andryala pinnatifida</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>mogadorensis</italic> (Hook. f.) Greuter, 
 <italic>Sonchus pinnatifidus</italic> (Cav.), 
 <italic>Asteriscus imbricatus</italic> (Cav.) DC. and 
 <italic>Asteriscus schultzii</italic> (Bolle) Pitard &amp; Proust. Médail and Quézel (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">1999</xref>) listed 28 endemic taxa shared between this area and the Canary Island. The presence of Macaronesian taxa highlighted similarities between this region and the Canary Islands (Emberger 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1939</xref>; Peltier 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">1982</xref>; Barbéro et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1982</xref>). Based on these similarities, several authors have identified a Moroccan Macaronesian sector (Peltier 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">1982</xref>; Kim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">1996</xref>). Despite the floristic similarity, the phytogeographical spectra and species’ life attributes, the coastal, and subcoastal Moroccan sector belong to the Mediterranean region and are not considered a Macaronesian sector (Médail and Quézel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">1999</xref>; Msanda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2005</xref>). Vegetation structure would date from the Mio-Pliocene (Quézel and Barbéro 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">1993</xref>), and the idea of a relationship of continuity between the African continent and the Canary Islands must be abandoned (Quézel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2000</xref>). Many species of tropical origin (Mathez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">1973</xref>) are represented in the sector: 
 <italic>Acacia gummifera</italic>, 
 <italic>Commelina rupicola</italic> Font Quer, 
 <italic>Kalanchoё laciniata</italic> (L.) DC. subsp. 
 <italic>faustii</italic> (Font Quer) Maire, 
 <italic>Leptochloa ginae</italic> (Maire), 
 <italic>Andropogon distachyos</italic> L., 
 <italic>Hyparrhenia hirta</italic> (L.) Stapf, 
 <italic>Tricholaena teneriffae</italic> (L. f.) Link and 
 <italic>Enteropogon rupestris</italic> (J. A. Schmidt) A. Chev, these taxa are currently located in residual stations (Benabid and Cuzin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1997</xref>). The presence of tropical taxa highlights the possibility of floristic exchanges between the Mediterranean and Tropical regions, since the Tertiary period. Saharo Arabian taxa representing southern infiltrations are represented by several species; for example 
 <italic>Traganopsis glomerata</italic> Maire &amp; Wilczeck and 
 <italic>Fagonia harpago</italic> Emberger &amp; Maire are two endemics and remarkable species, which appears in some parts of the Anti-Atlas. The area contains 140 endemic species, which have a Mediterranean origin (Médail and Quézel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">1999</xref>): notably 
 <italic>Chamaecytisus mollis</italic> (Cav.) Greuter &amp; Burdet
 <italic>, Genista ifniensis</italic> A. Caballero, 
 <italic>Bupleurum dumosum</italic> Cosson &amp; Balansae, 
 <italic>Hesperolaburnum platycarpum</italic> (Maire) Maire
 <italic>, Lavandula maroccana</italic> Murb., 
 <italic>Sideritis cossoniana</italic> Ball and 
 <italic>Thymus leptobotrys</italic> Murb. However several endemic species are specific to the argan sector, including 
 <italic>E. officinarum</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>officinarum</italic>, 
 <italic>Teucrium tananicum</italic> Maire, 
 <italic>D. draco</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>ajgal</italic>, 
 <italic>O. europaeae</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>maroccana</italic>, 
 <italic>Thymus broussonnetii</italic> Boiss. subsp. 
 <italic>hannonis</italic> (Maire) R. Morales
 <italic>, Teucrium werneri</italic> Emberger, 
 <italic>A. joannis</italic>, 
 <italic>Lavandula rejdali</italic> Upson &amp; Jury, where many species are well represented in rupicolous communities (Médail and Quézel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">1999</xref>).
</p>
