<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To enhance the bioavailability of petroleum hydrocarbons, one promising approach is the application of surfactants (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kleindienst et al., 2015a</xref>), which may enhance dissolution or desorption rates leading to the solubilization or emulsification of petroleum hydrocarbon pollutants (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Varjani and Upasani, 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chen et al. (2007)</xref> found that the adherence of 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus</italic> sp. DQ02 to hydrocarbon increased 44% in the presence of rhamnolipids and that the degradation of 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-hexadecane increased 11.6% compared to treatment in the absence of rhamnolipids. However, some surfactants, such as Corexit 9500, were reported to exhibit adverse impacts on oil-degrading bacteria (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kleindienst et al., 2015b</xref>) because of toxicity of the surfactant toward bacteria or as a result of competition of the surfactant with hydrocarbon substrates (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Laha and Luthy, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2016</xref>). In view of this, the selection of appropriate surfactants is of great importance for pollution remediation and the prevention of secondary pollution. Bioemulsifier-producing bacteria, which have attracted much attention, generally have the following two physiological aspects: (1) the ability to enhance the complexation and solubilization of non-polar substrates, thereby promoting the bioavailability of substrates, and (2) the ability to improve affinity between cell surfaces and oil-water interfaces through metabolism, promoting deformation of the oil-water interface film (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hou et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ayed et al. (2015)</xref> reported that the biosurfactant produced by 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> An6 was an alternative to chemically synthesized surfactants since it showed high solubilization efficiency toward diesel oil (71.54% at 1 g/L) that was better than SDS and Tween 80 and could enhance the diesel oil degradation efficiency of the An6 strain. However, not all the biosurfactants produced by bioemulsifier-producing bacteria can effectively enhance the degradation rate of pollutants (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Inakollu et al., 2004</xref>). Indeed, whether various biosurfactants stimulate or inhibit the bioremediation of pollutants is dependent on the physico-chemical properties of the surfactants, types of pollutants and physiological characteristics of the functional microorganisms (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hua and Wang, 2014</xref>). Therefore, it is necessary to establish a database of petroleum hydrocarbon pollutants and bioemulsifier-producing bacteria which is conducive to the targeted selection of suitable bacteria to treat with petroleum hydrocarbons.
</p>
