<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Edible films and coatings consist of polymeric matrices that are developed with edible polymers (e.g., polysaccharides and proteins). The polymeric matrices are quite thin and are used for the packaging of food products. Said films and coatings are expected to prevent gaseous exchange, microbial spoilage, and loss of moisture and solutes from the food products without compromising their physicochemical and sensorial properties. Additionally, the polymer matrices can be consumed directly along with the packed food products. These polymeric matrices are prepared using edible biopolymers. Most of the biopolymers that are being explored are being obtained either from renewable sources or from the byproducts of the agroindustries. Since most of the biopolymers are obtained from natural sources, they are biodegradable in nature and hence are environment-friendly. The use of these biopolymers has shown significant promise to reduce the usage of nonbiodegradable plastic packaging materials. Further, as these polymers are obtained from natural sources, the food industries have a significant economic advantage. In recent years, the interest in polysaccharide-based edible films and coatings has seen a surge. This can be ascribed to the ease of chemical modification of the polysaccharides, which paves the way for the researchers to easily modulate the properties of the matrices of edible films and coatings. The polysaccharides are broadly categorized as starch and nonstarch polysaccharides. The nonstarch polysaccharides are more hydrophilic than the starch polysaccharides. The aqueous solutions and dispersions of long-chain hydrophilic polysaccharides help to enhance the viscosity of the solutions. The addition of these polysaccharides helps to tailor the hardness, crispness, and adhesiveness of the biopolymer matrices [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-13-00575" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The nonstarch polysaccharides are categorized as cellulose and derivatives (e.g., carboxymethylcellulose, hydroxypropyl cellulose, methylcellulose, hydroxypropyl methylcellulose, microcrystalline cellulose, chitosan, gellan gum), seaweed extracts (e.g., carrageenans, alginates, agar, furcellaran, pectin), microbial fermentation gum (e.g., xanthan gum), exudate gums (e.g., gum arabic, gum tragacanth, gum karaya), and seed gums (e.g., tamarind gum, guar gum, locust bean gum) [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-13-00575" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The current section will discuss in brief some of the polysaccharides that are being explored in recent times by food scientists to develop edible films and coatings. 
</p>
