<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Various molecular components of BJO are believed to contribute to anticancer activity. For example, linoleic acid is reported to inhibit the cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) enzyme that is related to tumor cell invasiveness and angiogenesis [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In addition, oleic acid can induce cancer cell apoptosis and autophagy [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Importantly, many quassinoids from BJO are also well known for exhibiting therapeutic activity to treat bone [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], breast [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], pancreatic [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], lung [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and liver [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] cancers in vitro. For example, Wang et al. found that the quassinoid bruceine D (BD) induced apoptosis of osteosarcoma cells along with inhibiting cancer cell proliferation and migration [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. These inhibitory activities involved BD blocking a cell signaling pathway that was implicated in cancer cell malignancy [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In addition, BD has been found to inhibit hepatocellular carcinoma by inhibiting signaling pathways related to liver carcinogenesis and disease progression [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Quassinoids are typically more potent than fatty acids, with 50% inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) values down to the nanomolar level [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and hence most therapeutic focus has been on quassinoids [
 <xref rid="B38-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-25-05414" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].
</p>
