<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Comparing of other 
 <italic>Echinacea</italic> species, 
 <italic>E. purpurea</italic> is the most able species to adjust to new conditions. It is resistance to heat or cold weather conditions, easy to grow, and flaunt high efficiency
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Numerous scientific researches demonstrated the useful effect of 
 <italic>Echinacea</italic> immunomodulatory functions and human health
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. The doctors explored that the alcohol extract of 
 <italic>Echinacea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus immediately increased phagocytic activity and leads to high production of white blood cells, as well as, various in vitro researches has confirmed the phagocytosis, and antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity effects of 
 <italic>E. purpurea</italic> rhizomata cum radicibus extracts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Decreasing of severity and symptoms of the common cold by using 
 <italic>E. purpurea</italic> extracts was reported in several clinical studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. According to immunological studies, 
 <italic>E. purpurea</italic> enhanced activation of the nonspecific cellular and increased humoral immunity by increasing the activation and production of monocytes, lymphocytes, leukocytes and cytokines
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Based on the studies, the immune‐stimulatory property is the most important property of the species that involves the immune system based on the dose level
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. Although the rhizomata cum radicibus of 
 <italic>E. purpurea</italic> is very beneficial, purple coneflower of the species was known to be useful for the improvement of the various illnesses, such as sore throats, coughs, and snake bite
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Meanwhile, 
 <italic>E. purpurea</italic> has been used to treat viral, bacterial and fungal infections
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup> and the healing of the burns and wounds
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
