<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Biodiversity conservation in Tanzania faces many challenges include but not limited to increased crop production, overgrazing, overexploitation of biological resources due to increased human population and climate change. The rapid human demographic growth has resulted into overexploitation of biological resources beyond the capacity of available resources (Kideghesho et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2013</xref>). Agriculture is among the most leading human activities contributing significantly to habitat loss. Newmark (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2008</xref>) cautioned that, the rapid disappearance of habitats in Tanzania if not checked will impact species survival and ecological functioning. Recognizing the important of biodiversity conservation, the government of Tanzania concentrated her conservation efforts to protected areas (National Parks, Game Reserves, Game Controlled Areas, Wildlife Management Areas Conservation Areas and Forest Reserves) which cover only 32.5% of the total land in the country (NAFORMA 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2015</xref>). More than 65% of the total land is unprotected and hence vulnerable to habitats loss due to increasing unchecked human activities (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Nevertheless, most of wildlife species are mobile and hence most of time found outside protected areas exposing themselves into the risk of disappearance. Nelson (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2012</xref>) reported that many species of mammals such as elephants, wildebeest and zebra undertake annual migrations outside protected areas based on seasonal availability of forage and water resources. However, the synergies between wildlife and local communities surrounding protected areas and historical coexistence of wildlife and pastoralists is underexplored (Homewood et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2012</xref>). This necessitates the need to explore the contributions of local communities (occupying larger habitats) on biodiversity conservation using their indigenous knowledge.
</p>
