<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">Surfactants with diverse properties and low production costs are required to increase the applications of natural SACs, which gives greater incentive to develop surfactants of biological origin produced by microorganisms. Marine microorganisms are ubiquitous in the marine environment as well as extreme environments. The oceans have a relatively narrow range of pH, salinity and temperature while areas such as the volcanic vents face extreme conditions. These microorganisms are known to be metabolically and physiologically adapted to survive under extreme temperature, pressure, pH and salinity conditions (Das et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2010</xref>; Thavasi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">2014</xref>). For example, members of the 
 <italic class="italic">Alcanivorax</italic> genus survive at low to mild hydrostatic pressure in hydrocarbon contaminated environments. The strains 
 <italic class="italic">A. borkumensis</italic> SK2 and 
 <italic class="italic">A. dieselolei</italic> KS 293 have developed different strategies to cope with environmental stress under high pressure. While the respiration and cell integrity is not affected in KS 293 at mild hydrostatic pressure, SK2 activates the production of the osmolyte ectoine to cope with hydrostatic pressure (Scoma et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">2016a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">b</xref>). Marine bacteria secrete large molecules known as exopolysaccharides (EPS) consisting of proteins, polysaccharides, lipids, nucleic acids and uronic acids. EPS enhances the survival of microbial cells under changing environmental conditions through various mechanisms such as, biofilm formation, enhancing substrate adhesion, protection against limited nutrient availability, detoxification of metals and the presence of antibiotics (Harimawan and Ting 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2016</xref>; Pal and Paul 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">2008</xref>).
</p>
