<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0185" class="p">The surfactant-assisted cooperative self-assembly method achieves well-defined active nanomaterial structures and properties by confining the NP self-assembly or growth within nanocompartments such as micelles and emulsions. The interdigitated surfactant or phospholipid bilayer nanostructure provides a water-soluble and biocompatible interface for biomedical applications such as imaging (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fan et al., 2005b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dubertret et al., 2002</xref>) and drug delivery (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kim et al., 2006</xref>). Owing to the confined self-assembly, highly ordered and densely packed NP nanostructures have been produced. The ordered structure results in new collective properties and enhanced charge and energy transport for applications in photocatalysis and nanoelectronic devices. For example, self-assembly enables effective optical coupling of porphyrins, resulting in more enhanced optical absorption when compared with the original porphyrin monomers. The absorption bands also red shift to a more extensive visible light spectrum. The self-assembled porphyrin network facilitates efficient energy transfer among porphyrin molecules and the delocalization of excited state electrons for enhanced photocatalytic hydrogen production under visible light (
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhong et al., 2014a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhong et al., 2014b</xref>). By using multi-compositional NPs as the building block, highly ordered superparticles possess multiple functions that depend on the choice of the initial NPs for a number of interesting applications such as biomedical, photocatalytic, and optic/electric devices (
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lu and Yin, 2012</xref>). For example, self-assembling magnetic iron oxide into superparticles increases the saturation magnetization, while avoiding the superparamagnetic-ferromagnetic transition (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ge et al., 2007</xref>). The monodisperse, highly water-soluble, superparamagnetic, and biocompatible magnetite nanocrystals should find immediate important biomedical applications.
</p>
