<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par90">Nine seed samples from three stages (30, 60 and 90 DAF, with three biological replicates) were snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground to a fine powder. Total RNA samples were extracted using the Total RNA Isolation System (Takara, Japan) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The quality of the resulting RNA was verified by agarose gel electrophoresis using a Nanodrop ND-4301000 spectrophotometer and Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA). After RNA detection, Oligo (dT) was used to isolate mRNA. Mixed with the fragmentation buffer, the mRNA samples were fragmented. Then cDNA was synthesized using the mRNA fragments as templates. Short fragments are purified and resolved with EB buffer for end reparation and single nucleotide A (adenine) addition. After that, the short fragments are connected with adapters and the suitable fragments are selected for the PCR amplification to construct the sample cDNA libraries. The quantification and qualification of the sample cDNA libraries were checked with Agilent 2100 Bioanaylzer and ABI StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR System during the QC steps. Finally, the nine qualified cDNA libraries (HS30d_1, HS30d_2, HS30d_3, HS60d_1, HS60d_2, HS60d_3, HS90d_1, HS90d_2 and HS30d_3) were sequenced using Illumina HiSeq 4000 system at Beijing Genomics Institute Co., Ltd. (Shenzhen, China). Raw data was analyzed through Sickle (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/najoshi/sickle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/najoshi/sickle</ext-link>) and SeqPrep (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jstjohn/Seq-Prep" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/jstjohn/Seq-Prep</ext-link>), low-quality reads (percentage of base with a quality less than 15 greater than 20% in a read), adapter-containing reads and poly-N reads (with more than 5% N base) were removed to get high-quality clean reads. Based on the clean reads, the sequence duplication level and Q20, Q30, GC-content were calculated. Trinity software was used to assemble all of the clean reads from the left.fq and right.fq data, the min_kmer_cov was set as 2 and other parameters was set as their default. And Tgicl software [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] was used to perform clustering and eliminate redundant data in the assembled transcipts to obtain unique genes based on the parameters as followed: − 140 -c -v25 -O′-repeat_stringency 0.95 -minmatch 35 -minscore 35′. All clean reads were uploaded to the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) Sequence Read Archive (SRA) database under accession number SRP148668.
</p>
