<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9" class="p">The genus 
 <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> (Labiatae, Ocimoideae) comprises approximately 150 species worldwide, with over 90 species and 21 variaties distributed in China, primarily in the southwest region. The greatest variety is found in Yunnan Province, with 46 species and 16 varieties. The identification of enmein by Japanese researchers in 1966 as an anti-bacterial and anti-inflammatory agent from 
 <italic class="italic">I. japonica</italic> revealed 
 <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kaurane diterpenoids (or 
 <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kauranoids) to be the characteristic bioactive constituents of the 
 <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> species, a hot research topic in the field of natural product chemistry. In the 1970s, 
 <italic class="italic">I. rubescens</italic> was utilized as tea by residents in Lin County, Jinan City, Henan Province, and was found to be effective for the treatment of esophageal and cardia cancer. Subsequently, a collaborative group was established in 1973 to investigate the anticancer components of 
 <italic class="italic">I. rubescens</italic>, and Han-Dong Sun, et al. were invited to participate in the cooperation team in 1975. In 1976, rubescensin A (oridonin, or Ori) and ponicidin were identified by Han-Dong Sun, et al., and were proven to be the chemical constituent responsible for the bioactivity against esophageal and cardia cancer. The finding was reported simultaneously and independently by Japanese researchers. For over four decades, Han-Dong Sun, et al. have been engaged in the long-term, systematic and in-depth research on diterpenoids isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> species found in abundance in our country, resulting in a series of major research findings. “Research on Diterpenoids and Their Anticancer Bioactivities from 
 <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> Species” is one of the breakthroughs made in the field of natural product chemistry and natural anticancer lead compounds. The systematic and innovative research provides a solid theoretical foundation and scientific basis for the rational utilization of the plant resources of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> in China. The major research findings are as follows:
 <list list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par10" class="p">To date, 79 
    <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> species have been phytochemically investigated by groups around the world, leading to the identification of 1048 diterpenoids, including 42 types of 
    <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kaurane diterpenoids and 28 novel skeleton types. Sun et al. carried out a study on the chemical constituents of 67 
    <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> species and identified 732 diterpenoids (accounting for over 70% of the total amount) therein, including 30 types of 
    <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kaurane diterpenoids and 24 novel skeleton types. From these efforts, a series of lead compounds with potential for further development were identified. The project is remarkably systematic and innovative, which has made the research group a world center for research on the chemical constituents of the 
    <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> species and their bioactivities [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>–
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par11" class="p">Research on the chemical constituents of the 
    <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> species has led to the discovery of a large number of new compounds. For instance, a rare and highly oxygenated 
    <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kaurane C-glycoside, neoadenoloside A, was found from 
    <italic class="italic">I. adenolomus</italic>; two spirolactone 
    <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kauranes with novel scaffolds, neolaxiflorins A and B were isolated from 
    <italic class="italic">I. eriocalyx</italic> var. 
    <italic class="italic">laxiflora,</italic> and a new diterpenoid-based macrolide possessing a unique 10-membered lactone ring was isolated from 
    <italic class="italic">I. ternifolius</italic>. The above findings have provided more diverse frameworks and increased the chemical space for subsequent research on novel chemotherapeutics (Fig. 
    <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>). 
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par12" class="p">Pharmacological studies were performed on eriocalyxin B (EriB) and oridonin isolated from 
    <italic class="italic">I. eriocalyx</italic>, demonstrating that eriocalyxin B and oridonin suppress tumor growth primarily through inhibition of the NF-
    <italic class="italic">к</italic>B signaling pathway, with the direct target identified as the p50 protein; in vivo studies indicated that EriB demonstrated remarkable growth inhibition of the breast cancer cell line MDA-MB-231. Pharicin A, isolated from 
    <italic class="italic">I. pharicus,</italic> can induce mitotic arrest in paclitaxel-resistant cell lines (Jurkat and Raji), implying a different mechanism of action and offering a new approach for overcoming paclitaxel-resistant malignant tumors. Pharicin B, also isolated from 
    <italic class="italic">I. pharicus,</italic> has been shown to stabilize the retinoic acid receptor-a (RAR-a) and synergistically enhances differentiation in several AML cell lines, particularly in some primary acute promyelocytic leukemia (APL) cell lines, when used in combination with ATRA. Furthermore, pharicin B can overcome the resistance in some ATRA-resistant cells. Adenanthin, isolated from 
    <italic class="italic">I. adenanthus,</italic> can induce differentiation of APL cells by directly targeting peroxiredoxins I and II, revealing a new leukemia cell differentiation mechanism. The finding was selected as one of the “Top Ten Progresses in Chinese Science” in 2012 (Fig. 
    <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>). 
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>Sun’s group works closely with pharmacologists at home and abroad to investigate the anticancer properties of diterpenoids isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">Isodon</italic> species, achieving dramatical breakthroughs. With the knowledge that oncotherapy is gradually moving towards target-based and individualized therapy, 
 <italic class="italic">ent</italic>-kaurane diterpenoids have broad prospects in their application as anti-cancer drug candidates. Based on the previous research work, “Donglingcao lozenges” and “Maoexiangchacai tablets” have been successfully developed as antibacterial and anti-inflammatory drugs that are particularly effective for upper respiratory tract infections. After being brought to market, they have proved economically rewarding and have created social benefits for years.
</p>
