<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The chemical composition and biological activity of essential oils isolated from the leaves of 
  <italic class="italic">Siparuna aspera</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Siparuna macrotepala</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Piper leticianum</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Piper augustum</italic> and the rhizome of 
  <italic class="italic">Hedychium coronarium</italic> were evaluated. These species are used medicinally in different ways by the Amazonian communities that live near the Kutukú mountain range. Chemical studies revealed that the main components for the two 
  <italic class="italic">Siparuna</italic> species were germacrene D, bicyclogermacrene, α-pinene, δ-cadinene, δ-elemene, α-copaene and β-caryophyllene; for the two 
  <italic class="italic">Piper</italic> species β-caryophyllene, germacrene D, α-(
  <italic class="italic">E,E</italic>)-farnesene, β-elemene, bicyclogermacrene, δ-cadinene and for 
  <italic class="italic">H. coronarium</italic> 1,8-cineole, β-pinene, α-pinene and α-terpineol. The antioxidant activity of all essential oils was evaluated by 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), 2,2′-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt (ABTS), photochemiluminescence (PCL) quantitative assays, and DPPH and ABTS bioautographic profiles, with different results for each of them. Antimicrobial activity studies were carried out on three yeasts, six Gram positive and four Gram negative bacteria, by means of the disc diffusion method. The essential oil of 
  <italic class="italic">H. coronarium</italic> showed the most relevant results on 
  <italic class="italic">L. grayi</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">K. oxytoca</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">P. augustum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">P. leticianum</italic> on 
  <italic class="italic">S. mutans</italic>. An antibacterial bioautographic test for 
  <italic class="italic">H. coronarium</italic> was also carried out and highlighted the potential activity of terpinen-4-ol and 1,8-cineole.
 </p>
</abstract>
