<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the UN Environment Program World Conservation Monitoring Centre [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], Ecuador belongs to the group of the 17 megadiverse countries in the world, making it an extraordinary reservoir of biodiversity. As a megadiverse country, it must possess “at least 5000 of the world’s plants as endemics” [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Most of the botanical species described in Ecuador have never been studied so far from a phytochemical point of view; this makes the country an unbelievable source of potentially new chemical structures and biologically active compounds. In 2016, two of us (J.R. and G.G.) reported that about 50% of all the phytochemical publications on the Ecuadorian flora referred only to 8 of the 245 botanical families of the native species known in the country [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. For this reason, the authors have been involved for years in the description of specialized (secondary) metabolites contained in the Ecuadorian flora, to contribute to the advance in its phytochemical and phytopharmaceutical knowledge [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Within a project focused on the description of new essential oils (EOs) [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], the aim of this study is to describe a novel chemical profile of an already known EO, distilled from the aerial parts of 
 <italic>Clinopodium taxifolium</italic> (Kunth) Govaerts. 
 <italic>Clinopodium taxifolium</italic> (Kunth) Govaerts is a species belonging to the family Lamiaceae, also known with many synonyms, such as 
 <italic>Gardoquia taxifolia</italic> Kunth, 
 <italic>Satureja andrei</italic> Epling, 
 <italic>Satureja taxifolia</italic> (Kunth) Briq., 
 <italic>Gardoquia glabrata</italic> Kunth, 
 <italic>Thymus taxifolius</italic> Willd. ex Benth, 
 <italic>Satureja glabrata</italic> (Kunth) Briq., 
 <italic>Satureja taxifolia</italic> (Kunth) Briq. and 
 <italic>Satureja lineata</italic> Epling. [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. This plant is also known with the homonym 
 <italic>Clinopodium taxifolium</italic> (Kunth) Harley [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The species is native of the Andean region of Ecuador [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], where it has been described in the provinces of Azuay, Oro y Loja. However, specimens have also been described in Bolivia and Peru [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This plant grows at an altitude of 1500–3000 m above sea level [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and it is known as 
 <italic>Culantrillo de Cerro</italic> or 
 <italic>Polea de Castilla</italic> [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Furthermore, 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic> is used by infusion in folk medicine for treating internal inflammations, flatulence, stomach pain, malaria and cough [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In 2018, one of the authors (G.G.) first published the composition of an EO from this species as a part of a phytochemical study [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-00045" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Afterwards, the authors studied the composition of the EO of a different sample of 
 <italic>C. taxifolium</italic> of different origin, obtaining very different quali-quantitative and general sensory results, compared to that described in 2018. The EO was therefore re-investigated on a statistically significant number of samples, rigorously identified from the botanic point of view and submitted to new biological essays.
</p>
