<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, these in vitro assays for the antifungal activities of these seven essential oils on mycelial growth of two fungi showed that the lemongrass (
 <italic>C.cit</italic>) essential oil was the most effective. The mycelial growth of 
 <italic>A. alternata</italic> was totally inhibited by application of 
 <italic>C.cit</italic> at a moderate concentration, while 
 <italic>S. cucurbitacearum</italic> was completely inhibited at the highest 
 <italic>C.cit</italic> concentration, with fungicidal activity seen in both cases. Only a few studies have investigated lemongrass essential oils and these fungi, with most studies focused on the essential oil activity rather than its composition. Shafique et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] reported total inhibition of 
 <italic>A. alternata</italic> by a 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oil, with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 279.13 µL/L, as also reported by Jie et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In the same year, Guimarães et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] confirmed in vitro fungitoxic activity on 
 <italic>A. alternata</italic>, with the essential oil rich in citral (69.3%) and myrcene (23.8%). For the second fungus here, 
 <italic>S. cucurbitacearum</italic>, Fiori et al. [
 <xref rid="B30-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reported 100% inhibition of mycelial growth and spore germination at a rate of 20 µL 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oil. Seixas et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] reported the same result at 0.25, 0.5, 0.75, 1, and 1.25 mg/mL 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oil. A number of studies have reported these high proportions of the two isomers α-citral and β-citral in 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oils, even when collected from different countries [
 <xref rid="B33-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], as also confirmed by the present study. Brügger et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] reported that in addition to the high proportion of citral, their commercial 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oil showed relevant amounts of nonan-4-ol (6.5%) and camphene (5.2%). These two compounds were completely absent in the 
 <italic>C.cit</italic> essential oil used in the present study. A Brazilian commercial 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oil also indicated a different composition, which was rich in nonterpenes, as especially 4,8-dimethyl-3,7-nonadien-2-one (25.0%), 1-heptadec-1-ynyl-cyclopentanol (9.6%), and 7,7-dimethyl-bicycloheptan-2-ol (8.0%); here, the proportion of citral was less than 37% [
 <xref rid="B39-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The antifungal activity of 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oil has also been reported against other fungi, including 
 <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic>. This activity can be ascribed to the presence of various components such as citral, geraniol, and β-myrcene [
 <xref rid="B37-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. According to some studies, citral and geranol can indeed inhibit the mycelial growth of 
 <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>, 
 <italic>Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</italic>, 
 <italic>Bipolaris</italic> sp. and 
 <italic>A. alternata</italic> [
 <xref rid="B41-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. These major compounds in the 
 <italic>C. citratus</italic> essential oil also have antioxidant and antimicrobial activities [
 <xref rid="B43-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Furthermore, Kurita et al. [
 <xref rid="B44-antibiotics-10-00104" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] defined the fungicidal action of citral as due to its ability to receive electrons from the fungus cell, through charge transfer with an electron donor in the cell, which results in death of the fungus. In previous studies, β-myrcene and geraniol were found in 
 <italic>C.cit</italic> essential oil. These compounds with citral can contributed to inhibit the mycelial growth of 
 <italic>A. alternata</italic> and 
 <italic>S. cucurbitacearum</italic>.
</p>
