<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Extremely large and severe fires, including the 2017 Knysna fires, are often associated with preceding droughts (
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Kraaij et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Quinn, 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">San-Miguel-Ayanz, Moreno &amp; Camia, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr">Williams, 2013</xref>) and the resultant increase in dead fuels (
 <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Keeley, 2009</xref>). The extent and severity to which thicket, normally regarded as a fire-resistant (~poorly ignitable) vegetation (
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Calitz, Potts &amp; Cowling, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Cowling &amp; Potts, 2015</xref>), burnt in the 2017 Knysna fires was attributed to extreme fire weather conditions and to the preceding severe drought (
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Kraaij et al., 2018</xref>). In this study, we confirmed that the drying of fuels as a crude proxy for severe drought effects considerably increased flammability. However, the magnitude of the increase in flammability in response to drying of fuels was consistent across vegetation groups. Flammability, and by implication fire risk, is thus unlikely to increase disproportionately in one vegetation group compared to another under extended drought unless the production of dead fuels due to drought would be disproportionate among the vegetation groups. We concede that the proxy for drought conditions could not realistically simulate all potential effects of drought on fuel modification and flammability, and in particular on the dying off of fuels and resultant increase in litter component. Detailed consideration of this aspect was beyond the scope of this study and warrants further investigation. Given the low moisture contents of dead fuels, the ratio of dead to live fuels are likely to be a useful indicator of fire risk in evergreen shrublands (
 <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Keeley, 2009</xref>). Proxies for this ratio should, therefore, be sought for incorporation into fire danger indices.
</p>
