<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">
 <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> Georgi, belonging to the family Lamiaceae, is a well-known medicinal plant that is widely cultivated in China and other East Asian countries for its significant medicinal value [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Its dried root, 
 <italic>Scutellariae Radix</italic>, is a traditional Chinese medicine and has been applied to treat inflammation, dysentery, and liver and lung problems for thousands of years, which was first recorded in “
 <italic>Sheng Nong’s herbal classic</italic>” (written between 200 and 300 AD) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The authoritative book “
 <italic>Compendium of Materia Medica</italic>”, first published during the Ming Dynasty, reported that 
 <italic>Scutellariae Radix</italic> could be used in the treatment of a wide range of disorders [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Recently, numerous studies have shown that the main bioactive components in 
 <italic>Scutellariae Radix</italic> are flavonoids, which have a wide range of pharmacological activities, including antitumor, hepatoprotective, neuroprotective, antibacterial, and antiviral activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. At the end of 2019, the emergence of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) disease (COVID-19) has investigated large-scale epidemics worldwide and is currently a main public hygiene issue. The discovery of drugs against SARS-CoV-2 is the most promising treatment method for COVID-19. At present, there is no cure. Recently, baicalin and baicalein, two types of natural flavonoids derived from 
 <italic>Scutellariae Radix,</italic> were appraised as the first non-covalent, non-peptidomimetic inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro (3C-like protease) and revealed powerful anti-virus activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cell systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. With the increasing understanding of the pharmacological activity, molecular biology methods have been used to study 
 <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. The genome sequence of this species is available, and the biosynthetic pathways of some flavonoids and related key enzyme genes have been revealed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].
</p>
