<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Five of six analyzed secondary metabolites were detected in all samples of 
 <italic>G. asclepiadea</italic>, and only one (SWZ) which was found in Golija populations but not in Vlasina populations can be considered as a distinctive compound between the two geographic locations. However, this finding should be interpreted with a note that it relates to only one sampling period, and the occurrence of SWZ in earlier developmental stages of the Vlasina population should not be excluded. Although high ontogenetic variability in the content of secondary metabolites has been documented, the same gender-specific compounds were present in the preflowering, flowering, and postflowering stages in 
 <italic>Gentiana pneumonanthe</italic> [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Considering that the full maturity phase at the time of flowering is the period of collection and harvesting of medicinal plants [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], the information regarding the Vlasina populations is important and deserves further research. Gentiopicrin was the most abundant compound in all samples (36.36 ± 7.53 mg/g and 26.98 ± 5.04 mg/g in aboveground parts of Golija and Vlasina populations, respectively; 31.28 ± 6.56 mg/g and 38.96 ± 8.22 mg/g in belowground parts of Golija and Vlasina populations, respectively). It was also a dominant component in belowground parts of the natural populations of 
 <italic>G. asclepiadea</italic> from Hungary (varying from 45 to 68 mg/g depending on the sampling site), and SWM and SWZ were also found in all studied populations [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Gentiopicroside was the dominant iridoid in Caucasian populations of 
 <italic>G. asclepiadea</italic> (about 90 mg/g in herbs and 65 mg/g in roots, respectively), SWM was detected at a lower level (about 1.5 mg/g in herbs and 6 mg/g in roots, respectively), and SWZ was only found in trace amounts in all plant parts [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The content of MGF in the aboveground plant parts found in the populations from Golija (17.62 ± 4.03 mg/g) was very similar to that previously reported for Caucasian populations (17.48 ± 0.33 mg/g), although it was lower in the populations from Vlasina (6.49 ± 1.04 mg/g). However, this xanthone compound was detected in belowground parts of the populations from Vlasina and Golija but not in the populations from Azerbaijan [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Flavonoids ISOOR and ISOV, which are predominantly abundant in aboveground plant parts of gentians, were detected in all plant parts of 
 <italic>G. asclepiadea</italic>, comparable to a previous report [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00140" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
