<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Surfactants are utilized in various bulk commercial products particularly in personal care products and household cleaners. To fulfil their worldwide demand, millions of tonnes of surfactants are annually produced from non-renewable sources such as petrochemicals. Consumption of surfactants is probably greater than 13 million tonnes per year worldwide (Marchant and Banat 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">2012a</xref>). The most widely used synthetic surfactants such as alkyl benzene sulfonates (ABS), are not readily biodegradable thus causing adverse effects on the environment. U.S. detergent manufacturers therefore, replaced ABS with linear alkylbenzene sulfonate (LAS) which showed no adverse impact on the environment and had the same cleaning characteristics (Cowan-Ellsberry et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, diminishing petrochemical stocks have created a drive towards identification of novel renewable bioresources for efficient surfactant production (Foley et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2012</xref>). In recent years researchers have been involved in continued environmental research to source replacements for synthetic surfactants and other bioactives from the marine environment (Kalogerakis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">2015</xref>). Surface-active compounds (SACs) produced by microorganisms offer an ideal sustainable substitute for petrochemical based surfactants. Biologically produced SACs have numerous potential applications in a wide variety of industrial sectors, due to their synthesis from waste and renewable substrates such as, hydrocarbon wastes, crude oil and vegetable oils in addition to being bio-compatible, non-toxic and biodegradable (Banat et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2010</xref>). They are usually classified based on their molecular weight, those surfactant molecules with low molecular weights are known as biosurfactants (BS) whilst those with high molecular weights are known as bioemulsifiers (BE).
</p>
