<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anti-leishmanial activity</div>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This variability in anti-leishmanial activity may be explained by the qualitative and quantitative differences in chemical compositions of each essential oils. Indeed, literature showed that the chemical composition of essential oils and so their biological activities may be affected by the growing seasons. Some factors may be considered as responsible for these variations as temperature, rainfall and humidity which can affect plant metabolism and lead to composition differences [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the pure compounds, 
  <span class="italic">R</span>-(+)-limonene was the most active one (IC
  <sub>50</sub> = 16.59 μg/ml) compared to inactive 
  <span class="italic">S</span>-(-)-limonene, linalool and 1-octanol (IC
  <sub>50</sub> &gt;100μg/ml). It can explain a part of the anti-leishmanial activity but other active compounds still remain to be identified. Kpadonou Kpoviessi et al., 2014 also, showed that 
  <span class="italic">R</span>-(+)-limonene had an antitrypanosomal effect with IC
  <sub>50</sub>=4.24 ±2.27 μg/mL on 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma brucei brucei</span> bloodstream forms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. As well, linalool was shown to have a strong inhibitory activity on 
  <span class="italic">L. amazonensis</span> promastigotes and amastigotes with LD
  <sub>50</sub> of 15.5 ng/ml and 4.3 ng/ml, respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of the compounds present in our volatile oils were already tested for their anti-parasitic activities. Thus, the IC
  <sub>50</sub> of alpha-pinene (55.3μg/mL; 4.1μg/mL), sabinene (126.6μg/mL; 17.7μg/mL), 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-pinene (200.1μg/mL; 54.8μg/mL), 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-phellandrene (32.8μg/mL; 9.2μg/mL), 4-terpineol (335.9μg/mL; 0.02μg/mL) were reported against promastigotes of 
  <span class="italic">L. major</span> and the bloodstream forms of 
  <span class="italic">T. brucei</span> (TC 221), respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
