<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A total of forty-eight growing barrows (Large White × Landrace) with initial body weight (BW) of 29.61 ± 1.02 kg were obtained from a pig farm. All pigs were allocated to one of the four treatment groups based on BW by using a completely random experimental design. Each treatment had twelve replicates with one pig per replicate. The size of individual pen was 2.0 × 1.5 meters. The four treatments consisted of normal protein diet (NPD), reduced-protein, amino acid-supplemented diet (RPD), the same RPD supplemented with 150 mg of chlortetracycline per kg of feed (RPA), and the same RPD supplemented with 250 mg of OEO per kg of feed (RPO). The pigs were fed in two dietary phases as follows: 1) from 30 to 65 kg BW as growing period, and 2) from 66 to 115 kg BW as finishing period. The NPD diet contained 17% and 15.6% crude protein during the growing and finishing stages, respectively. The dietary protein levels in these two stages with one percentage unit lower than the NRC [
 <xref rid="B14-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] nutrient requirement estimates. The RPD diet contained 15% and 13.6% crude protein during growing and finishing stages, respectively. The Lys, Met, Thr, and Trp of all diets were balanced to meet the requirements of growing-finishing pigs [
 <xref rid="B17-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The compositions of feed ingredient and nutrient contents of the experimental diets were shown in 
 <xref rid="animals-08-00159-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. The chlortetracycline was provided by Jinhe Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Hohhot, China). The addition form of OEO is a powder called Phytogen (Meritech Bioengineering Co, Guangzhou, China). The Phytogen contains 90% natural feed grade inert carrier and 10% OEO of Greek Origanum Vulgare subsp. hirtum. The dosage of OEO additives was referenced from our previous studies [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. The detailed chemical components of OEO are presented in our previous study [
 <xref rid="B13-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Throughout the study, all pigs were given free access to water and feed via nipple drinkers and semi-automatic individual feeders, respectively. The temperature of the pig pens was controlled within the range of 18 and 23 °C. 
</p>
