<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Research on this genus has focused on medicinal or ecological aspects. In southwest Queensland and northwest New South Wales, different species of 
 <italic>Trachymene</italic> (
 <italic>T. glaucifolia</italic> (F. Muell.) Benth., 
 <italic>T. cyanantha</italic> Boyland and 
 <italic>T. ochracea</italic> L.A.S. Johnson) seem to be toxic to cattle [
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The only herbarium voucher of them corresponded to 
 <italic>T. glaucifolia</italic> that seems to be directly correlated to a form of “staggers” in sheep and the deformity “bent leg” in lambs [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Further research has correlated the intake of 
 <italic>T. ochracea</italic> with the limb paresis syndrome, included in the first level of the five progressive clinical groups described of the nervous and muscular locomotor disorders that affect sheep throughout Australia [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The genus 
 <italic>Trachymene</italic> has been also reported to show teratogenic compounds that affect the development of an embryo in pregnancy or may cause a birth defect in the child [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. On the other hand, the niche and competitive ability between 
 <italic>T. cyanopetala</italic> (F. Muell.) Benth. and 
 <italic>T. ornata</italic> (Endl.) Druce was evaluated, although little evidence was found under well-watered and water-stressed conditions [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. 
 <italic>Phytophthora caetorum</italic> (Lebert and Cohn) Schroeter is a pathogen fungus that attacks 
 <italic>T. caerulea</italic> R. Grah., the blue lace flower that is field-grown for the cut-flower industry, although the use of hymexazol (35 mg/L) reduced significantly the symptoms [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Another species, 
 <italic>T. pilosa</italic> Sm., has been described as a resistant and key symptomless host of a relative pathogen 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>cinnamomi</italic> Rands. However, under laboratory conditions, this species died [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The resistance of the exine from the mature pollen grains of this species has been estimated [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The regeneration ability of 
 <italic>T. coerulea</italic> Graham under experimental conditions showed that the center of the shoot apex produced fewer mature leaves and fewer embryos from the basal tissues than did the flanks [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Finally, the importance of this genus is clear when species such as 
 <italic>T. cussonii</italic> (Montrouz.) B.L. Burtt have been described as a coral cay endemic plant representative to the conservation of this type of habitat [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-plants-10-00601" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
