<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bone metastasis and concomitant complications are huge challenges for cancer treatment in the clinic. Bone metastases occur in about 70% of patients suffering from advanced breast cancer or prostate cancer and approximately 15–30% of patients with carcinoma of the lung, colon, stomach, bladder, uterus, rectum, thyroid, or kidney (Irelli et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Sun, Han, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0116" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Escaping from the tumor 
 <italic>in-situ</italic>, tumor cells enter circulation through blood vessels and lymph vessels and then travel all over the body to find fertile soil to proliferate (Croucher et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Vinay &amp; KusumDevi, 
 <xref rid="CIT0125" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Chen, Pei, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Ahangar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The special structure and microenvironment of the bone marrow are beneficial for tumor cells to grow (Ahangar et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Tumor cells replicate in the new environment continually, develop into a metastatic tumor, and destroy the bone structure. Patients with bone metastasis suffer from bone pain, pathological fracture, hypercalcemia, spinal cord compression, and other skeletal-related events (Macedo et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Turpin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0121" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Osteogenic metastasis or osteolytic metastasis both could happen. But osteolytic bone metastases account for approximately 80% of cancer bone metastases (Sun, Ge, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0115" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The ‘vicious circle’ occurring in the metastasized bone accelerates the cancer cells’ proliferation and bone destruction at the same time (Santini et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0101" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Turpin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0121" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). BP and denosumab are common medicine in the clinic but have many side effects. BP may cause mandibular osteonecrosis and impair renal function (Sun, Han, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0116" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Denosumab was reported to increase the risk of pancreatitis and endocarditis, erysipelas, and infectious arthritis (Jie et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Some newly developed drugs have not been used clinically due to their hydrophobicity, short half-life, and other disadvantages (Chew &amp; Danti, 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). These undesired effects of systemic drug delivery arise from the uncontrollable ‘space’ and ‘time’ of drug reaction. Delightedly, nanotechnology and nanomaterials provide new strategies to build superior drug delivery systems that make drugs more efficient and secure to the body (Chen, Wang, et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Many kinds of NPs were utilized as drug carriers and targeted destroyed bone areas to treat cancer and inhibit bone resorption, such as polymer NPs, liposomes, and silica NPs. Elaborate decorations with targeting ligands endowed particles the ability to target bone or special expression of cancer cells in the osteolytic microenvironment, optimizing the spatial distribution of drugs. The multifunctional implantable scaffolds or hydrogel materials can load a large number of drugs and release drugs locally in a more sustainable way, showing desired efficiency and minimal side effects and reducing the frequency of medication. In addition, smart drug release systems were designed to release drugs in response to some physical and chemical stimuli. Internal chemical characteristics of the osteolytic environment (low pH and high Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> concentration) and external physical stimuli [near-infrared light (NIR), ultraviolet light, or ultrasound] both can be utilized as triggers of drug release and further optimize the timing of delivery. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref> summarized the work of these optimized drug delivery systems.
</p>
