<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although Nigeria has similar climate with India, reports show that the leaf and rhizome oils from India have varying chemical composition 
 <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Studies on 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> from other regions also confirmed substantial variability in their chemical composition which may be associated with climatic and geographical factors 
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. There were also global variation in the oil composition of rhizomes from different regions, for instance, α-turmerone (45.3%), linalool (14.9%) and β-turmerone (13.5%) were reported as the main constituent compounds in the oil of the fresh rhizome of Malaysian 
 <italic>C. domestica</italic>
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. While α-phellandrene (24.5%), 1,8-cineole (15.9%), 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene (13.2%) and β-pinene (8.9%) were the major ones in found in the leaf oil of the Vietnam species 
 <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. It is however noteworthy that turmerone or its isomers appears to be present in substantial quantity in most species so far reported but the isomeric curlone is being reported here as a constituent of the essential oil of fresh rhizome from Nigeria for the first time. This report therefore confirms that the Nigerian spp. 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> is unique in its chemical composition compare to either 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> from other regions where α-turmerone (20.1%) and ar-turmerone (68.9%) have been reported to be the major constituents of an Iranian 
 <italic>Curcuma</italic> species 
 <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. The constituent(s) of the oil responsible for the observed neuropharmacological effects could not be ascertained in this study. However, α-phellandrene has been reported to possess both antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effect 
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Also, 1,8-cineol which is the major constituent of many essential oils especially, 
 <italic>Eucalyptus globulus</italic>, has been reported to possess CNS inhibitory activity 
 <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, hypotensive activity in rat 
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> and anti-inflammatory activity 
 <xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Moreover, 
 <italic>E. tereticornis</italic> and 
 <italic>E. globulus</italic> essential oils have been reported to contain 60–90% of 1,8-cineole 
 <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref> which have also been shown to possess both analgesic and antiinflammatory activities in animals 
 <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Therefore, the prominent components of the oil in the present study, contributed majorly to the central inhibitory activities observed for the oil. In view of the remarkable potentials displayed by the plant, its use in ethnomedicine should further be harnessed. We do not have data concerning the pharmacokinetic of this oil in systemic circulation in humans; hence it is imperative to carry out further studies to unravel this.
</p>
