<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <p>The volatile compounds from various parts of 
  <span class="italic">Echinops ilicifolius</span> (Compositae) such as flowers, leaves and roots obtained by hydrodistillation (HD) and headspace solid-phase microextraction (HS-SPME) methods were subsequently analysed by GC and GC/MS and compared. Thirty-seven and 20 components of the flower of 
  <span class="italic">E. ilicifolius</span> were characterized, representing 99.7% and 100.0% of the total compositions using the HD and HS-SPME methods, respectively. The major constituents of the hydrodistilled oil were identified as linalool (58.6%), geraniol (17.4%), 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-dodecane (10.9%) and nerol (5.4%), whereas HS-SPME extract was rich in 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-octane (34.0%), 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-decane (25.1%), 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-cymene (11.1%), 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene (5.3%) and 1,8-cineole (5.1%). 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-Hexadecanoic acid (32.3%), linalool (16.4%) and geraniol (8.3%) were the main components among 43 constituents identified in hydrodistilled extract of the leaf, representing 99.5% of the total components detected, whereas 16 compounds representing 99.9% of the HS-SPME method were identified, among which 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-decane (32.6%), 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-cymene (14.0%), 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-octane (10.3%), limonene (9.2%), 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene (9.1%), 1,8-cineole (7.9%) and 
  <span class="italic">α</span>-pinene (5.9%) were the major ones. Among 23 components comprising 91.2% of the total hydrodistilled oil detected, 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-decane (23.1%), 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-dodecane (14.5%), silphiperfol-4,7(14)-diene (11.1%), selin-11-en-4-a-ol (9.5%), 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-hexadecanoic acid (7.8%) and 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-tetradecane (5.3%) were the main constituents in the root of 
  <span class="italic">E. ilicifolius</span>, whereas 1,8-cineole (29.0%), 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-decane (12.6%), 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-octane (12.6%), camphor (12.0%), 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-cymene (9.6%) and 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>-terpinene (5.9%) were the main components among the 20 constituents characterized in HS-SPME extract, representing 99.9% of the total components detected. The antibacterial activity of the flower, leaf and root oils of 
  <span class="italic">E. ilicifolius</span> against six Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria was determined using the MIC method. The growth inhibitory zone (mm) was also measured.
 </p>
</div>
