<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is likely that pathogen amplification by invasive plants has distinct effects on different native species [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The three native species in our experiment showed unique biomass responses to 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>gigantea</italic> inoculation in the absence of 
 <italic>Microstegium</italic> competition. The range of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>gigantea</italic> inoculation effects on biomass, from negative (on 
 <italic>Elymus</italic>) to positive (on 
 <italic>Dichanthelium</italic>) is consistent with the theory that plant-microbe interactions can vary from mutualism to parasitism depending on context, such as environmental conditions and host identity [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. For example, infection with Cucumber mosaic virus increased the biomass and seed weight of one 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> genotype while it reduced the biomass and seed weight of another genotype relative to a mock inoculation control [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Our results suggest that 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>gigantea</italic> could increase aboveground growth for some host species (e.g., through compensatory growth or re-allocation of resources [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]) and suppress the aboveground growth of other species. Studies encompassing a broader range of environmental conditions and host diversity are needed to better predict when 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>gigantea</italic> will have positive, negative, or neutral effects on host biomass and other traits. In studies of soil microbes, the effects of microbial inoculations on plant growth can predict plant species relative abundances in the field [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. However, whether disease-induced changes in growth of plant species, as observed in our study, are sufficient to shift plant community structure is an important area of future research [
 <xref rid="pone.0237894.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].
</p>
