<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Hydrodynamic, physiological, and ecological conditions, along with presence of other colonizers and harmful agents (e.g., antibiotics and antimicrobial nanoparticles), considerably influence the biofilm structure. For example, biofilm structures of 
 <italic class="italic">P. fluorescens</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P. aeruginosa</italic> are significantly affected by nutritional cues, e.g., carbon and iron availability in their surroundings, respectively [
 <xref rid="B41-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. It has been reported that shear forces affect the distribution of microcolonies due to the passage of fluid over the biofilm. At low shear forces, the colonies are formed like a channel, while at high shear forces, the colonies are extended and susceptible to rapid vibrations [
 <xref rid="B42-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. These channels are essential for bacteria to transport the necessary water, nutrients, and oxygen to the bacterial community within the biofilm [
 <xref rid="B43-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. It has been shown that an increasing loading rate applied under a stable shear stress induced the formation of thicker and rougher biofilms [
 <xref rid="B44-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. Detachment is a fundamental process in biofilm development that benefits the bacterial life cycle by allowing planktonic cells to return to the environment and settle new territories [
 <xref rid="B45-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Three different biofilm strategies have been suggested to elucidate biofilm detachment: (i) swarming dispersal, where planktonic cells are freed from a bacterial cluster; (ii) clumping dispersal, where aggregates of microbial cells are separated as clumps; and (iii) surface dispersal, where biofilm matrices move across infected surfaces through shear-mediated transport [
 <xref rid="B46-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Detachment initiation has been proposed to initiate in response to specific endogenous or/and exogenous cues (e.g., a lack of nutrients that causes starvation, or high cell densities) [
 <xref rid="B47-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. The event of detachment is complex and random. In some cases, separation of large masses (cell clusters larger than 1000 μm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) from mature biofilms represents only 10% of the detachment process, yet accounts for more than 60% of the microorganisms detached [
 <xref rid="B48-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. A considerable amount of literature has been published on biofilms, yet the mechanisms of biofilm detachment are poorly understood [
 <xref rid="B49-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-polymers-10-00515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Better understanding of the detachment mechanisms is necessary to accurately evaluate the spatial distribution of the bacterial cells in their environment, their ability to survive, as well as their resistance to biocides.
</p>
