<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0175">The diverse medicinal capabilities of plants lie in the complexities of their secondary metabolism. Although it is very easy to apply herbal medicine as a whole plant crude extract, decoction, tea, the efficacy of plant-based chemical compounds can be realized only if they are applied in their pure forms or in a mixture to form a compound drug. There are innumerable chemical compounds isolated from plants which are the potent antiviral drug (
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Denaro et al., 2020</xref>). This study reviewed a diversity of polyphenolic compounds isolated from different plants for their antiviral activity. As indicated in 
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> , studies have shown the efficacy of hundreds of different compounds against human viruses for their direct anti-viral activity or alleviation of symptoms (Amber et al., 2017a; 
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">Li and Peng 2013</xref>). For instance, important compounds such as natural mixture of polyphenols from almond that include catechin, naringenin-7-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, kaempferol-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside, epicatechin, isorhamnetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-rutinoside, and isorhamnetin-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside has been shown to reduce the HSV DNA accumulation and cytopathic effects by the virus (
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Musarra-Pizzo et al., 2019</xref>). Similarly, Pentagalloylglucose isolated from 
 <italic>Phyllanthus emblica</italic> has been shown to inhibit HSV-induced rearrangements of actin cytoskeleton (
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">Pei et al., 2011</xref>). It has been observed that generally, phytochemicals acts by interference with viral entry via attachment to viral proteins (
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Kesharwani et al., 2017</xref>), inhibits viral replication (
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">Langland et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2005a</xref>), stops transcription (
 <xref rid="bib147" ref-type="bibr">Yarmolinsky et al., 2012</xref>), and expression of viral proteins (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Kuo et al., 2006</xref>).
</p>
