<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lipids Health Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lipids Health Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Lipids in Health and Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1476-511X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5761127</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12944-017-0645-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Protective effects of <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L. leaf essential oil against CCl<sub>4</sub> induced hepatic oxidative damage and renal failure in rats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Bellassoued</surname><given-names>Khaled</given-names></name><address><email>khaledbra3@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ben Hsouna</surname><given-names>Anis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Athmouni</surname><given-names>Khaled</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Pelt</surname><given-names>Jos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Makni Ayadi</surname><given-names>Fatma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rebai</surname><given-names>Tarek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elfeki</surname><given-names>Abdelfattah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2323 5644</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412124.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Life Sciences, Animal Ecophysiology Laboratory, Faculty of sciences, </institution><institution>University of Sfax Tunisia, </institution></institution-wrap>Road of Soukra Km 3.5, BP 1171, PC 3000 Sfax, Tunisia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0445 6355</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417887.5</institution-id><institution>Biotechnology and Plant Improvement Laboratory, </institution><institution>Centre of Biotechnology of Sfax, </institution></institution-wrap>PO Box 1177, Road Sidi Mansour km 6, 3018 Sfax, Tunisia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2323 5644</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412124.0</institution-id><institution>Department of life sciences, Laboratory of Biodiversity and Aquatic Ecosystems, Faculty of sciences, </institution><institution>University of Sfax Tunisia, </institution></institution-wrap>Road of Soukra Km 3.5, BP 1171, PC 3000 Sfax, Tunisia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Laboratory of Clinical Digestive Oncology, Department of Oncology, KU, Leuven, Belgium </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2323 5644</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412124.0</institution-id><institution>Biochemistry Laboratory, CHU Habib Bourguiba of Sfax, Faculty of Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Sfax Tunisia, </institution></institution-wrap>Road Menzel Chaker km 0.5, CP 3029 Sfax Sfax, Tunisia </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2323 5644</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412124.0</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Histology and Embryology, Faculty of Medicine of Sfax, </institution><institution>University of Sfax Tunisia, </institution></institution-wrap>Road Menzel Chaker km 0.5, CP 3029 Sfax, Tunisia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>9</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L. is a flowering plant belonging to the Lamiaceae family. <italic>Mentha</italic> plants constitute one of the main valuable sources of essential oil used in foods and for medicinal purposes.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The present study aimed to investigate the composition and in vitro antioxidant activity of <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> leaf essential oil (MpEO). A single dose of CCl<sub>4</sub> was used to induce oxidative stress in rats, which was demonstrated by a significant rise of serum enzyme markers. MpEO was administrated for 7 consecutive days (5, 15, 40&#x000a0;mg/kg body weight) to <italic>Wistar</italic> rats prior to CCl<sub>4</sub> treatment and the effects on serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), and &#x003b3; -glutamyl transpeptidase (&#x003b3;-GT) levels, as well as the liver and kidney superoxide dismutase (SOD), catalase (CAT) and glutathione peroxidase (GPx) activity and thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS) levels were evaluated. In addition, histopathological examinations of livers and kidneys was performed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The in vitro antioxidant activity of MpEO was lower than that of silymarin. Pretreatment of animals with MpEO at a dose of 5&#x000a0;mg/kg did not have a significant effect on ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, &#x003b3;GT, urea or creatinine levels in CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced stress. Whereas pretreatment with MpEO at doses of 15 and 40&#x000a0;mg/kg prior to CCl<sub>4</sub>, significantly reduced stress parameters (ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, &#x003b3;GT, urea and creatinine) compared to the CCl<sub>4</sub>-only group. Moreover, a significant reduction in hepatic and kidney lipid peroxidation (TBARS) and an increase in antioxidant enzymes SOD, CAT and GPx was also observed after treatment with MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) compared to CCl<sub>4</sub>-treated rats. Furthermore, pretreatment with MpEO at 40&#x000a0;mg/kg can also markedly ameliorate the histopathological hepatic and kidney lesions induced by administration of CCl<sub>4</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">We could demonstrate with this study that MpEO protects liver and kidney from CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced oxidative stress and thus substantiate the beneficial effects attributed traditionally to this plant.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>M. piperita</italic></kwd><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd>Liver</kwd><kwd>Kidney</kwd><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>Histopathological</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par23">Reactive oxygen species (ROSs) are various forms of activated oxygen. A disproportion of the reactive oxygen species and the absence of their scavenge systems in cells lead to oxidative stress and increases the risk of several human chronic diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. ROS contributes to the development of various diseases such as diabetes, atherosclerosis, cancer, neurodegenerative diseases, liver cirrhosis and the aging process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The liver plays a central role in the maintenance of systemic lipid homeostasis and is especially susceptible to ROS damage. CCl<sub>4</sub> is now of greatest concern as an environmental contaminant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. It was reported that CCl<sub>4</sub> was one of the most commonly used toxins in the experimental study of liver diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Abraham et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] showed that the nephrotoxic effects of CCl<sub>4</sub> were also associated with free radical production.</p><p id="Par24">To prevent the damage caused by ROS, living organisms have developed an antioxidant defense system that includes the presence of non-enzymatic antioxidants and enzymes such as catalase (CAT), superoxide dismutase (SOD) and glutathione peroxidase (GPx) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. It has been anticipated that in addition to these natural antioxidants, other synthetic or natural ROS scavengers may reduce the incidence of free radical-mediated diseases. The use of antioxidants in the prevention and cure of various diseases is intensifying, and there is considerable interest in the study of the antioxidant activities of molecules such as plant polyphenolic and carotenoid components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Antioxidants appear to act against disease processes by increasing the levels of endogenous antioxidant enzymes and decreasing lipid peroxidation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">A number of studies showed that various herbal extracts could protect liver and kidney against CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced oxidative stress by inhibiting lipid peroxidation and enhancing antioxidant enzyme activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Silymarin, a flavonolignan mixture of milk thistle (<italic>Silybum marianum</italic>), is one such important herbal hepatoprotective drug. Silymarin exhibits hepatoprotective effects by altering cytoplasmic membrane architecture and, in turn, preventing the penetration of hepatotoxic substances, such as carbon tetrachloride (CCl<sub>4</sub>), thioacetamide and D-galactosamine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">The well-known and widely used peppermint (<italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L.) (Lamiaceae) is a cultivated natural hybrid of <italic>Mentha aquatica</italic> L. (water mint) and <italic>Mentha spicata</italic> L. (spearmint). Although a native genus of the Mediterranean region, it is cultivated all over the world for its use in flavor, fragrance, medicinal, and pharmaceutical applications. Peppermint oil is one of the most widely produced and consumed essential oils [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Besides its uses in food, herbal tea preparations, and confectioneries, the medicinal uses of mint, which date back to ancient times, include carminative, anti-inflammatory, antispasmodic, antiemetic, diaphoretic, analgesic, stimulant, emmenagogue, and anticatharrhal application. It is also used against nausea, bronchitis, flatulence, anorexia, ulcerative colitis, and liver complaints. Mint essential oils are generally used externally for antipruritic, astringent, rubefacient, antiseptic, and antimicrobial purposes, and for treating neuralgia, myalgia, headaches, and migraines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">From the experimental and clinical studies performed on <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> leaf essential oil (MpEO), it seems that most of its pharmacological actions are due to its antioxidant activity which is mainly due to its ability to scavenge free radicals and/or inhibit lipid peroxidation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Antioxidants are substances that delay or prevent the oxidation of inter- or intra-cellular oxidizable substrates from oxidative stress. In this study, we report the chemical composition and antioxidant effects of MpEO in several in vitro systems (DPPH and superoxide scavenging activities). Besides, we are interested in determining the possible protective effects of MpEO against oxidative damage of the liver and kidney following an intraperitoneal administration of CCl<sub>4</sub>, by assessing the oxidative stress profile and some serum biochemical parameters.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par28">Fresh leaves of <italic>M. piperita</italic> L. samples were harvested from the local market at Sfax (Tunisia) (N: 34.4426&#x000b0;, E: 10.4537&#x000b0;) during the vegetative stage in June 2013. The samples were identified and authenticated by a senior botanist, Pr. Ferjani Ben Abdallah, at the Faculty of Science of Sfax, University of Sfax (Tunisia). From 50 individual <italic>M. piperita</italic> L. plants each, a total of 80&#x02013;100 leaves (&#x02248; 12&#x000a0;cm<sup>2</sup> in size) were randomly collected from the base to the apex. The fresh leaves were mixed and immediately dried in the shade away from light at room temperature. After drying, the samples were grounded to a fine powder that was used for the extraction of essential oil.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Essential oil preparation</title><p id="Par29">MpEO was extracted by the steam distillation method. A mass of 3&#x000a0;kg of dry plant material was hydrodistillated for 2&#x000a0;h in a Clevenger-type apparatus. The recovered (0.47%) essential oil was dried with anhydrous Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, and stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><italic>Mentha piperita</italic> essential oil composition</title><p id="Par30">MpEO compositional analysis of the volatile constituents was performed on a Hewlett-Packard gas chromatograph GC: 5890 series II. The fused HP-Innowax capillary column (polyethylene glycol, 30&#x000a0;m, 0.25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m, ID, 0.25&#x000a0;mm film thickness) was directly connected to the mass spectrometer. Nitrogen was used as a carrier gas at a flow rate of 1.2&#x000a0;ml/min. Oven temperature was initially set at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (1&#x000a0;min) and gradually raised to 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (5&#x000a0;min) at 7&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/min. The temperatures of the injection port and detector were maintained at 250 and 280&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, respectively. The mass spectrometer was operated (full scan-mode) in the EI-mode at 70&#x000a0;eV.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Component identification</title><p id="Par31">The essential oil components were identified based on their mass spectra and computer matching with the data available in the Wiley 275 library (Wiley, New York).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>In vitro antioxidant activities test</title><p id="Par32">The antioxidant activity of the MpEO was determined by two methods and compared with the activity of silymarin, a standardized extract of the milk thistle seeds that containes a mixture of flavonolignans. Silymarin has a number of potential mechanisms including chemoprotective effects from environmental toxins and anti-inflammatory activity and is used as a drug.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Measurement of free radical-scavenging action</title><p id="Par33">2,2-Diphenyl picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radicals scavenging activity was assessed according to Blois [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], with a slight modification. Different concentrations of the MpEO and silymarin (5&#x02013;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml) were mixed with 1&#x000a0;ml of 0.1&#x000a0;mM DPPH in ethanol solution and 450&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 50&#x000a0;mM Tris-HCl buffer (pH&#x000a0;7.4) was added. The solution was incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min and the reduction of DPPH free radicals was measured by reading the absorbance at &#x0028e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;517&#x000a0;nm. Silymarin was used as reference standard. The activity is given as % DPPH scavenging and calculated according to the following equation:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{DPPH}\  \mathrm{scavenging}=\left[\left(\mathrm{control}\ \mathrm{OD}-\mathrm{sample}\ \mathrm{OD}\right)/\mathrm{control}\ \mathrm{OD}\right]\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>DPPH scavenging</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>control</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>OD</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>OD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>control</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>OD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par34">The antioxidant activity of MpEO is expressed as IC50, defined as the concentration of MpEO required to cause a 50% decrease in initial DPPH concentration. Each sample was analyzed six times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Scavenging of superoxide anion</title><p id="Par35">The influence of MpEO on the generation of superoxide anion was measured according to the method described by Yen &#x00026; Chen, 1995 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Superoxide anion was generated in a non-enzymatic system and determined by spectrophotometric measurement for the reduction of nitroblue tetrazolium. The reaction mixture, which contained 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of essential oil in ethanol, 800&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 1&#x000a0;M phosphate buffer (pH&#x000a0;7.4), 400&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of distilled water, 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 0.1&#x000a0;M Na<sub>4</sub>EDTA, 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 1.5&#x000a0;mM NBT and 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of 0.12&#x000a0;mM riboflavin was incubated at ambient temperature for 5&#x000a0;min, and the color was read at &#x0028e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;560&#x000a0;nm against blank samples.<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{superoxide}\  \mathrm{anion}\  \mathrm{scavenging}=\left[\left(\mathrm{blank}\ \mathrm{OD}-\mathrm{sample}\ \mathrm{OD}\right)/\mathrm{OD}\ \mathrm{blank}\right]\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>superoxide anion scavenging</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>blank</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>OD</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>sample</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>OD</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>OD</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>blank</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par36">Where blank OD is the absorbance of the control reaction and sample OD is the absorbance in the presence of MpEO. The IC50 was calculated from the plot of the inhibition percentage against the essential oil concentration. Each sample was analyzed six times.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>In vivo antioxidant properties</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Animal</title><p id="Par37">Male <italic>Wistar</italic> rats, weighing about 200&#x02013;220&#x000a0;g, were purchased from the Central Pharmacy of Tunisia (SIPHAT, Tunisia). They were housed at 22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with light/dark periods of 12&#x000a0;h and a minimum relative humidity of 40%. The animals had free access to commercial pellet diet (SICO, Sfax, Tunisia) and water ad libitum. The general guidelines for the use and care of living animals in scientific investigations were followed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The handling of the animals was approved by the Tunisian Ethical Committee for the Care and Use of laboratory animals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Experimental design</title><p id="Par38">After acclimatizing to the laboratory conditions for 1 week, 70 rats were divided into 7 groups of 10 animals and treated for 7&#x000a0;days as follow [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]:</p><p id="Par39">The rats of group 1 served as normal control and received saline orally daily for 7 days and were injected with 1&#x000a0;ml/kg BW of just olive oil (the solvent of CCl<sub>4</sub>) on the 7 day. The rats of group 2 served as CCl<sub>4</sub>-hepato and renotoxicity control and were received saline orally daily for 7 days and were injected with 1&#x000a0;ml/kg BW of CCl<sub>4</sub> and olive oil mixture on the 7 day (a single intraperitoneal injection). The CCl<sub>4</sub> dose was selected according to the reference dose for chronic oral exposure (RFD) as recommended for CCl<sub>4</sub> (CASRN 56&#x02013;23-5) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p><p id="Par40">The rats of group 3 were pretreated orally seven times with a dose of 50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW of reference drug silymarin with an interval of 24&#x000a0;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">The rats of groups 4, 5, 6 and 7 were pretreated orally seven times with doses of 5, 15 and 40&#x000a0;mg MpEO /kg BW, respectively with an interval of 24&#x000a0;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">After pretreatment with either silymarin or MpEO for 7&#x000a0;days, the rats of groups 3, 4, 5 and 6 received a single intraperitoneal injection of CCl<sub>4</sub> (1&#x000a0;ml/kg BW) on the 7&#x000a0;day.</p><p id="Par43">Rats were killed 24 h after vehicle or CCl<sub>4</sub> single injection. The animals in the different groups were killed by cervical decapitation to avoid stress conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Sample collection</title><p id="Par44">Serum was prepared by centrifugation (1500&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic>, 15&#x000a0;min, 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C; Beckman-Coulter, Marseille, France) and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for further biochemical assays. The liver and kidney tissues were immediately removed and dissected over ice-cold glass slides and a part was homogenized (10% <italic>w</italic>/<italic>v</italic>) with an Ultra Turrax homogenizer in ice-cold, 1.15% KCl-0.01&#x000a0;M sodium, potassium phosphate buffer. Homogenates were centrifuged at 10000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 20&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The resulting supernatants were used for immediate lipid peroxidation and protein oxidation determination. Homogenate aliquots were stored at &#x02212;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for further biochemical assays. Other parts of these livers and kidney tissues were fixed in 10% formaldehyde solution and processed for paraffin sectioning and histological studies.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Biochemical assays</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>Biochemical markers in plasma</title><p id="Par45">Plasma levels of aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), &#x003b3;-glutamyl transpeptidase (&#x003b3;-GT), cholesterol (TC), triglycerides (TG), low-density lipoprotein (LDL), high-density lipoprotein (HDL), creatinine and urea rates were measured in plasma samples by standardized enzymatic procedures using commercial kits from (Biolabo, Maizy, France) on an automatic biochemistry analyzer (Vitalab Flexor E, Diamond Diagnostics, Holliston, MA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Protein quantification</title><p id="Par46">Protein content in liver and kidney tissues were determined according to the method of Lowry et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] using bovine serum albumin as a standard.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Lipid peroxidation</title><p id="Par47">Malondialdehyde concentrations (marker for lipid peroxidation) in liver and kidney tissues were determined spectrophotometrically according to Draper &#x00026; Hadley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Briefly, an aliquot of liver and kidney extracts supernatant was mixed with 1&#x000a0;ml of 5% trichloroacetic acid and centrifuged at 2500&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 10&#x000a0;min. One ml of thiobarbituric acid reagent (0.67%) was added to 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of supernatant and heated at 90&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min. The mixture was cooled and the absorbance measured at 532&#x000a0;nm using a spectrophotometer (Jenway UV-6305, Essex, England). The malondialdehyde values were calculated using 1,1,3,3-tetraethoxypropane as standard and expressed as nmol of malondialdehyde/mg of protein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Determination antioxidant enzyme activities in liver and kidney tissue</title><p id="Par48">Catalase (CAT) activity was measured according to Aebi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. A total of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L tissue homogenate (about 1.5&#x000a0;mg proteins) was added to 1&#x000a0;ml phosphate buffer (0.1&#x000a0;M, pH&#x000a0;7) containing 100&#x000a0;mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Rate of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> decomposition was followed by measuring the decrease in absorbance at 240&#x000a0;nm for 1&#x000a0;min. The enzyme activity was calculated using an extinction coefficient of 0.043&#x000a0;mM<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and expressed in international units (I.U.), i.e. in &#x003bc;mol H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> destroyed/min/ mg protein, at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p><p id="Par49">Superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity was estimated according to Beyer and Fridovich [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The reaction mixture contained 50&#x000a0;mM of tissue homogenates in potassium phosphate buffer (pH&#x000a0;7.8), 0.1&#x000a0;mM EDTA, 13&#x000a0;mM L-methionine, 2&#x000a0;mM riboflavin and 75&#x000a0;mM nitro blue tetrazolium (NBT). The developed blue color in the reaction was measured at 560&#x000a0;nm. Units of SOD activity were expressed as the amount of enzyme required to inhibit the reduction of NBT by 50% and the activity was expressed as units/mg of protein, at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Glutathione peroxidase (GPx) activity was measured by the procedure of Flohe and Gunzler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. One milliliter of reaction mixture containing 0.3&#x000a0;ml of phosphate buffer (0.1&#x000a0;M, pH&#x000a0;7.4), 0.2&#x000a0;ml of 2&#x000a0;mM glutathione (GSH), 0.1&#x000a0;ml of sodium azide (10&#x000a0;mM), 0.1&#x000a0;ml of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (1&#x000a0;mM) and 0.3&#x000a0;ml of liver and kidney supernatant were prepared. After incubation at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min, the reaction was terminated by adding 0.5&#x000a0;ml 5% TCA. Tubes were centrifuged at 1500&#x000d7;g for 10&#x000a0;min and the supernatant was collected. To 0.1&#x000a0;ml of this reaction supernatant, 0.2&#x000a0;ml of (0.1&#x000a0;M pH&#x000a0;7.4) and 0.7&#x000a0;mL of 5,5 dithiobis-(2-Nitrobenzoic acid) (DTNB, 0.4&#x000a0;mg/ml) were added. After mixing, absorbance was recorded at 420&#x000a0;nm and the enzyme activity was calculated as &#x003bc;mol of GSH oxidized/min/mg protein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Histopathological studies</title><p id="Par50">At the time of sacrifice, the liver and kidney tissues were removed and fixed in 10% formaldehyde solution and washed. The tissues were dehydrated in increasing gradient of ethanol, finally cleared in toluene and embedded in molten paraffin wax. Sections were cut at 4&#x02013;5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m thickness and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&#x00026;E). The slides were photographed with an Olympus UTU1X-2 camera connected to an Olympus CX41 microscope (Tokyo, Japan).</p><p id="Par51">The histological damage in liver was quantified by measuring the index of tissue large numbers of inflammatory cells such as lymphocytes together with hepatic sinusoidal inflammation, hepatocyte necrosis and devastating liver architecture. Moreover, the histological damage in kidney was quantified by measuring the index of tissue the glomerular and tubular necrosis. To evaluate the severity of lesions, the degree of liver and kidney damage was graded according to a zero to four-point scoring system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], where 0 indicates no damage, I indicates slight damage (1&#x02013;25%), II indicates discrete damage (26&#x02013;50%), III indicates moderate damage (51&#x02013;75%) and IV indicates severe damage (76&#x02013;100%).The tabulation of data and the statistical analysis were made in accordance with the number of animals with established scores. All the parameters were quantified by a single observer who was not aware of the treatment groups.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par52">All values are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SE for continues variables or as median with inter quartile range [25%, 75%] where appropriate. The results were analyzed by One-Way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) followed by Tukey test for multiple comparisons using SPSS for Windows (version. 12) or ANOVA-on-ranks with Dunn&#x02019;s correction. Differences were considered significant at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec22"><title>Chemical constitution of <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L. leaf essential oil</title><p id="Par53">Chemical composition of MpEO was determined by GC/MS analysis. The compounds, their percentages as well as their retention indices are listed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. MpEO is a mixture with 26 compounds representing 98.17% of the total oil composition. The most abundant chemicals categories for MpEO are oxygenated monoterpenes (79.50%), followed by monoterpene hydrocarbons (16.23%) and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (2.44%). The major components of MpEO are menthol (33.59%) and iso-menthone (33.00%). In lower amounts we found a variety of compounds including limonene (8.00%), piperitone (3.20%), 1,8-cineole (2.80%), linalool (2.64%), iso-pulegol (2.40%), caryophyllene (1.95%) and pulegone (1.60%).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chemical composition (%) of leaves essential oil from Tunisian <italic>M.piperita</italic> as identified by GC/MS analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Peak</th><th>Compounds</th><th>Retention Time (min)</th><th>Percentage (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>&#x003b1;-pinene</td><td>4.42</td><td>1.80</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>&#x003b2;-pinene</td><td>6.07</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>Sabinene</td><td>6.42</td><td>0.25</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>Myrcene</td><td>7.81</td><td>1.30</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>Limonene</td><td>8.30</td><td>8.0</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>1,8-cineole</td><td>8.48</td><td>2.80</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>3-octanone</td><td>10.13</td><td>0.45</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>3-octanol</td><td>10.41</td><td>0.53</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Limonene oxide</td><td>13.44</td><td>0.59</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>&#x003b1;-terpineol</td><td>18.62</td><td>0.37</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Linalool</td><td>15.73</td><td>2.64</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>iso-menthone</td><td>15.14</td><td>33.00</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>Menthyl acetate</td><td>16.35</td><td>0.68</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>Iso-pulegol</td><td>16.71</td><td>2.40</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>Isomenthol</td><td>17.29</td><td>0.28</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>Neo-iso-menthol</td><td>17.90</td><td>0.45</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>Menthol</td><td>18.25</td><td>33.59</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>Pulegone</td><td>18.39</td><td>1.6</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>Neryl acetate</td><td>18.45</td><td>0.8</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>Piperitone</td><td>19.09</td><td>3.2</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>Myrtenol</td><td>19.56</td><td>0.55</td></tr><tr><td>22</td><td>Carveol</td><td>19.99</td><td>0.31</td></tr><tr><td>23</td><td>Caryophyllene</td><td>17.33</td><td>1.95</td></tr><tr><td>24</td><td>Caryophyllene oxide</td><td>20.10</td><td>0.11</td></tr><tr><td>25</td><td>Germacrene D</td><td>20.80</td><td>0.11</td></tr><tr><td>26</td><td>&#x00394; &#x02013;Cadinene</td><td>21.92</td><td>0.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="2"/><td>Monoterpene hydrocarbons (%)</td><td>16.23</td></tr><tr><td>Oxygenated monoterpenes (%)</td><td>79.5</td></tr><tr><td>Sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (%)</td><td>2.44</td></tr><tr><td>Total (%)</td><td>98.17</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Essential oil antioxidant activity</title><p id="Par54">The antioxidant activity of MpEO was compared to that of silymarin, a well-known antioxidant, using two different assays, namely DPPH and superoxide oxygen radicals inhibition, the results are reported in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. DPPH showed for MpEO an IC50 value around 3 times higher than the one recorded for silymarin indicating that antioxidant activity of MpEO was lower than that of silymarin.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>MpEO effects and positive controls on the in vitro free radical(DPPH and superoxide)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>MpEO</th><th>Silymarin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>50% scavenging concentration (&#x003bc;g/ml) on DPPH radical</td><td>61.28&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02*</td><td>21.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.13</td></tr><tr><td>50% scavenging concentration (&#x003bc;g/ml) on superoxide anion</td><td>356.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.35*</td><td>39.04&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.02</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are represented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM of six different experiments</p><p>*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 versus silymarin</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Serum biochemical parameters</title><p id="Par55">The results of biochemical indicators of liver and kidney function are summarized in Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. The administration of CCl<sub>4</sub> caused severe hepato and reno-toxicity in the treated rats, as evidenced by the significant elevations of serum ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, &#x003b3;GT, total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL urea and creatinine levels, while HDL level was decreased compared to control animals.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO and their combination MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> on hepatic markers in serum of control and experimental rats</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment and parameters</th><th>AST (U/L)</th><th>ALT (U/L)</th><th>ALP (U/L)</th><th>LDH (U/L)</th><th>&#x003b3;-GT (U/L)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>164.82&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.28</td><td>65.88&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.44</td><td>149.61&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.19</td><td>20.81&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52</td><td>3.17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.39</td></tr><tr><td>CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>524.12&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.11<sup>***</sup></td><td>179.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.39<sup>***</sup></td><td>217.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.55<sup>***</sup></td><td>40.66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.81<sup>***</sup></td><td>5.43&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.21<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td>SL/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>191.15&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.14<sup>###</sup></td><td>87.82&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.61<sup>###</sup></td><td>157.50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.12<sup>##</sup></td><td>28.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.62<sup>###</sup></td><td>3.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>###</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>a</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>479.89&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;36.41</td><td>162.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.18</td><td>202.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.62</td><td>37.75&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.35</td><td>4.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.25</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>b</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>356.82&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;35.77<sup>##</sup></td><td>147.35&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.67<sup>##</sup></td><td>186.74&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.98<sup>#</sup></td><td>34.16&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.35<sup>##</sup></td><td>4.06&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.17<sup>##</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>216.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.26<sup>###</sup></td><td>97.82&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.98<sup>###</sup></td><td>165.96&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.12<sup>###</sup></td><td>31.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.12<sup>###</sup></td><td>3.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.20<sup>###</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup></td><td>160.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.47</td><td>63.08&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.16</td><td>139.77&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.27</td><td>19.89&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.18</td><td>2.81&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.24</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>AST</italic> aspartate aminotransferase, <italic>ALT</italic> alanine aminotransferase, <italic>ALP</italic> alkaline phosphatase, <italic>LDH</italic> lacatate dehydrogenase and <italic>&#x003b3;GT</italic> gamma glutamyl transferase.<sup>a</sup>MpEO(5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>b</sup>MpEO(15&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>c</sup>MpEO(40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), SL: Silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW)</p><p>Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM for eight rats in each group. CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO and MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> treated groups vs control group; ** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, CCl<sub>4</sub> group vs MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> group; <sup>#</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup># #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup># # #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of CCl<sub>4</sub>,MpEO and their combination MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> on lipid profile in serum of control and experimental rats</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment and parameters</th><th>T-Cholesterol (mmol/l)</th><th>T-Triglycerides (mmol/l)</th><th>HDL (mmol/L)</th><th>LDL (mmol/l)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>1.133&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.033</td><td>0.736&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.075</td><td>1.413&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.023</td><td>0.123&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.014</td></tr><tr><td>CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>1.750&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.028<sup>***</sup></td><td>1.743&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.078<sup>***</sup></td><td>0.446&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.074<sup>***</sup></td><td>0.726&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.053<sup>***</sup></td></tr><tr><td>SL/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.966&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.033<sup>###</sup></td><td>1.043&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.012<sup>###</sup></td><td>1.240&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.030<sup>###</sup></td><td>0.176&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.008<sup>###</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>a</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>1.606&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.063</td><td>1.610&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.041</td><td>0.690&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.135</td><td>0.640&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.066</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>b</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>1.376&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.076<sup>##</sup></td><td>1.196&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.039<sup>##</sup></td><td>0.873&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.053<sup>##</sup></td><td>0.253&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.024<sup>##</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>1.033&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.033<sup>###</sup></td><td>1.050&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.010<sup>###</sup></td><td>1.296&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.039<sup>###</sup></td><td>0.186&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.017<sup>###</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup></td><td>1.100&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.115</td><td>0.763&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.069</td><td>1.210&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.106</td><td>0.113&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.006</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>TC</italic> Total cholesterol (mmol/l), <italic>HDL</italic> high density lipoprotein (mmol/l), <italic>TG</italic> triglyceride (mmol/l) and <italic>LDL</italic> low density lipoprotein (mmol/l). <sup>a</sup>MpEO (5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>b</sup>MpEO (15&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>c</sup>MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), SL: Silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW)</p><p>Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM for eight rats in each group. CCl4, MpEO and MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> treated groups vs control group; ** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, CCl<sub>4</sub> group vs MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> group; <sup>#</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup># #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup># # #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effects of CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO and their combination MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> on kidney markers in serum of control and experimental rats</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment</th><th>Urea<break/>(mmol/l)</th><th>Creatinine<break/>(&#x003bc;mol /l)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>7.53&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.59</td><td>11.12&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.30</td></tr><tr><td>CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>15.41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.57**</td><td>12.79&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.15**</td></tr><tr><td>SL/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>8.04&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32<sup># #</sup></td><td>11.19&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.27<sup># #</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>a</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>12.52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32</td><td>11.94&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.47</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>b</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>10.50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.29<sup>#</sup></td><td>11.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.40<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>9.44&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.67<sup># #</sup></td><td>11.39&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.30<sup># #</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup></td><td>7.34&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.38</td><td>11.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.35</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>MpEO(5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>b</sup>MpEO(15&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>c</sup>MpEO(40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), SL: Silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW)</p><p>Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM for ten rats in each group. CCl4, MpEO and MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> treated groups vs control group; ** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, CCl<sub>4</sub> group vs MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub>group; <sup>#</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup># #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup># # #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par56">Pretreatment with the MpEO at doses of 15 or 40&#x000a0;mg/kg significantly reduced levels of ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, &#x003b3;GT, total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL urea and creatinine and increased the level of HDL compared to the CCl<sub>4</sub> group. It is worth noting that the treatment with 5&#x000a0;mg/kg MpEO did not induce any significant changes in the biochemical parameters (ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, &#x003b3;GT, total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL, urea, creatinine or HDL) when compared to the CCl<sub>4</sub> group. Treatment of rats with only MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW) did not result in significant alterations in biochemical parameters compared to control rats.</p><p id="Par57">Pretreatment with silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg), used as positive control, significantly decreased the elevated levels of ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, &#x003b3;GT, total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL urea and creatinine and increased of HDL level as compared to CCl<sub>4</sub> group. Its effect was comparable in reducing of liver and kidney damage induced by CCl<sub>4</sub> with that observed for the highest dose of MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg).</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Effects on lipid peroxidation</title><p id="Par58">TBARS level is widely used as a marker for free radical mediated lipid peroxidation injury. We determined TBARS levels in the liver and kidney tissues of the investigated animals and our results are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a, b</xref>. The levels of TBARS were significantly increased in both liver and kidney tissues of CCl<sub>4</sub>-treated animals when compared to control untreated rats.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Effects of CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO and their combinations MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> on hepatic TBARS of control (Con) and experimental rats. Con, control group; mod, CCl<sub>4</sub>-model group<sub>;</sub> SL/CCl<sub>4</sub>, silymarin 50&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub>; MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> 5&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> 15&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> 40&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; MpEO 40&#x000a0;mg/kg group. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM for ten rats in each group. CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO, MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> treated groups vs control group; *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, CCl<sub>4</sub> group vs (MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub>) group; #<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, ##<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ###<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001. <bold>b</bold>. Effects of CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO and their combinations <strike>(</strike>MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub><strike>)</strike> on kidney TBARS of control (Con) and experimental rats. Con, control group; mod, CCl4-model group<sub>;</sub> SL/CCl<sub>4</sub>, silymarin 50&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub>; MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> 5&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> 15&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl4 group; MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> 40&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl4 group; MpEO 40&#x000a0;mg/kg. Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM for ten rats in each group. CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO, MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> treated groups vs control group; *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, CCl<sub>4</sub> group vs (MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub>) group; #<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, ##<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, ###<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par59">Pre-treatment with the MpEO at doses of 15 and 40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW significantly reduced levels of TBARS in liver and kidney tissues as compared to CCl<sub>4</sub> group. There was a dose effect; treatment with MpEO at 5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW did not induce any significant decrease in the levels of TBARS in liver and kidney as compared to CCl<sub>4</sub> group. When rats were treated with only MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), no significant differences in the TBARS values was observed compared to control rat. Pretreatment with silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) significantly decreased the elevated levels of TBARS in both liver and kidney compared to CCl<sub>4</sub> control. Moreover, the effect of silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) in attenuation of TBARS levels in liver and kidney was comparable with highest dose of MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg).</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Effects on antioxidant enzymes</title><p id="Par60">Results presented in Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref> and <xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref> showed a significant decrease in the levels of CAT, SOD, GPx in liver and kidney in CCl<sub>4</sub>-treated group when compared to control group. The decrease in hepatic and kidney CAT, SOD and GPx levels induced by CCl<sub>4</sub> injection were significantly restored (elevated) in the MpEO and silymarin groups, and this effect was more pronounced with the increase of essential oil concentration. Pretreatment with MpEO at doses of 15 and 40&#x000a0;mg/kg significantly increased levels of hepatic and kidney CAT, SOD and GPx as compared to CCl<sub>4</sub> group. It is worth noting that the treatment with MpEO at a dose 5&#x000a0;mg/kg did not induce any significant increase in the levels of hepatic and kidney CAT, SOD and GPx as compared to CCl<sub>4</sub> group. No significant differences in the values were observed in rats treated with MpEO only (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) compared to control rat values. Moreover, the effect of silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) was comparable in attenuation of levels of hepatic and kidney CAT, SOD and GPx with highest dose of MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg).<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effects of CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO and their combination MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> on the activities of enzymatic antioxidants in liver of control and experimental rats</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment</th><th>SOD<break/>(Units/mg protein)</th><th>CAT<break/>(&#x003bc;mol H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>/min/mg protein)</th><th>GPx<break/>(&#x003bc;mol GSH/min/mg protein)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>16.04&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.11</td><td>14.03&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.29</td><td>7.66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.51</td></tr><tr><td>CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>13.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.50<sup>***</sup></td><td>11.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.37<sup>***</sup></td><td>5.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.25<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td>SL/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>15.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.50<sup>##</sup></td><td>13.48&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.25<sup>###</sup></td><td>7.41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.16<sup>###</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>a</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>13.92&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.40</td><td>11.34&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.41</td><td>5.41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.31</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>b</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>14.98&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.19<sup>#</sup></td><td>12.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32<sup>#</sup></td><td>6.04&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.17<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>15.65&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.44<sup>##</sup></td><td>13.20&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.19<sup>###</sup></td><td>7.26&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22<sup>###</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup></td><td>15.83&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.31</td><td>13.85&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.33</td><td>7.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.33</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>MpEO(5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>b</sup>MpEO (15&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>c</sup>MpEO(40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), SL: Silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW)</p><p>Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM for ten rats in each group. CCl4, MpEO and MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> treated groups vs control group; ** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, CCl<sub>4</sub> group vs MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> group; <sup>#</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup># #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup># # #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Effects of CCl<sub>4</sub>, MpEO and their combination MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> on the activities of enzymatic antioxidants in kidney of control and experimental rats</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Treatment</th><th>SOD<break/>(Units/mg protein)</th><th>CAT<break/>(&#x003bc;mol H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>/min/mg protein)</th><th>GPx<break/>(&#x003bc;mol GSH/min/mg protein)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>15.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22</td><td>12.90&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.15</td><td>5.68&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.27</td></tr><tr><td>CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>12.12&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.50<sup>***</sup></td><td>10.05&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.34<sup>***</sup></td><td>4.06&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.28<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td>SL/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>14.52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.35<sup>##</sup></td><td>12.23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.24<sup>###</sup></td><td>5.56&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14<sup>##</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>a</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>12.92&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.20</td><td>10.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22</td><td>4.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.33</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>b</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>13.69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.10<sup>#</sup></td><td>11.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22<sup>#</sup></td><td>5.10&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.28<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>14.20&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.35<sup>##</sup></td><td>12.04&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.19<sup>###</sup></td><td>5.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>##</sup></td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup></td><td>14.91&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.21</td><td>12.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.33</td><td>5.59&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.27</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>MpEO(5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>b</sup>MpEO(15&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>c</sup>MpEO(40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), SL: Silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW)</p><p>Values are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM for ten rats in each group. CCl4, MpEO and MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> treated groups vs control group; ** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, *** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, CCl<sub>4</sub> group vs MpEO/CCl<sub>4</sub> group; <sup>#</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup># #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup># # #</sup>
<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Histopathological findings</title><p id="Par61">The normal liver architecture was observed in liver histology of control group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Large numbers of inflammatory cells such as lymphocytes together with hepatic sinusoidal inflammation, hepatocyte necrosis and devastating liver architecture were observed in the CCl<sub>4</sub> group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). However, pretreatment with MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg, Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>) can remarkably ameliorate the histopathological hepatic lesions induced by administration of CCl<sub>4</sub>. MpEO 15&#x000a0;mg/kg showed very few inflammatory cells along with prominent nucleolus (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). The highest dose of MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) and silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) significantly attenuated the damaged liver depicting marked focal regenerative changes which are illustrated by presence of actively dividing cells with a prominent nucleolus (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>). In addition, silymarin at the dose of 50&#x000a0;mg/kg has shown to produce hepatoprotection evidenced by area of regeneration and dark nucleus (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). The histological pattern was almost normal in rats treated with MpEO oil alone. By analyzing the histopathological scoring attributed to the liver tissues it is possible to note that the highest dose of MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) or silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) pretreatment just conferred good protection on CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced liver damage (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab8" ref-type="table">8</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Effect of MpEO on CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced liver damage. <bold>a</bold> Control group; (<bold>b</bold>) CCl<sub>4</sub>-model group showing marked inflammatory cells, necrosis and reduced lesions of necrosis; (<bold>c</bold>) Silymarin 50&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; (<bold>d</bold>) MpEO 5&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group (<bold>e</bold>); MpEO 15&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; (<bold>f</bold>) MpEO 40&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; (<bold>g</bold>) MpEO 40&#x000a0;mg/kg group. Hematoxylin/eosin staining; magnification &#x000d7;400. <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Figa_HTML.gif" id="d29e2887"/> : Marked inflammatory cells; <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Figb_HTML.gif" id="d29e2890"/> : Necrosis cells; <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Figc_HTML.gif" id="d29e2893"/> : Reduced lesions of necrosis; <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Figd_HTML.gif" id="d29e2896"/> : Regeneration area; <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Fige_HTML.gif" id="d29e2900"/> : Prominent nucleolus; <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Figf_HTML.gif" id="d29e2903"/> : Mild inflammatory cells</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab8"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Grades of inflammatory cells and cellular necrosis in rat liver</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="9">Pathologic grading of inflammatory cells and cellular necrosis</th></tr><tr><th>Groups</th><th>Zero</th><th>I</th><th>II</th><th>III</th><th>IV</th><th>N</th><th char="&#x000d7;"><italic>P</italic> value vs Control</th><th><italic>P</italic> value vs CCl<sub>4</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>10</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td/></tr><tr><td>CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>***</sup></td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>10</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>SL/CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>###</sup></td><td>8</td><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>a</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>0</td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>10</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</td><td>ns</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>b</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>#</sup></td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>###</sup></td><td>7</td><td>3</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup></td><td>9</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>MpEO (5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>b</sup>MpEO (15&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>c</sup>MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), SL: Silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par62">Kidney sections of normal histological appearance (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>) and the CCl<sub>4</sub> control group showed some nephrotoxic lesions, as evidenced by the glomerular and tubular necrosis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). However, pretreatment with MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3f</xref>) can remarkably ameliorate the histopathological kidney lesions induced by administration of CCl<sub>4</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3f</xref>). In addition, silymarin at the dose of 50&#x000a0;mg/kg has shown to produce renoprotection evidenced by amelioration the histopathological kidney lesions induced by injection of CCl<sub>4</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). The histological pattern in kidney was almost normal in rats treated with MpEO alone. By analyzing the histopathological scoring attributed to the kidney tissues it is possible to note that the highest dose of MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) or silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) pretreatment just conferred good protection on CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced kidney damage (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab9" ref-type="table">9</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Effect of MpEO on CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced kidney damage. <bold>a</bold> Control group; (<bold>b</bold>) CCl<sub>4</sub>-model group showing some nephrotoxic lesions, as evidenced by the glomerular and tubular necrosis; (<bold>c</bold>) Silymarin 50&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; (<bold>d</bold>) MpEO 5&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group (<bold>e</bold>); MpEO 15&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; (<bold>f</bold>) MpEO 40&#x000a0;mg/kg&#x02009;+&#x02009;CCl<sub>4</sub> group; (<bold>g</bold>) MpEO 40&#x000a0;mg/kg group. Hematoxylin/eosin staining; magnification &#x000d7;400. <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Figg_HTML.gif" id="d29e3293"/> : glomerular necrosis; <inline-graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Figh_HTML.gif" id="d29e3296"/> : necrosis in epithelial cells of the proximal tubules</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12944_2017_645_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab9"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Grades of glomerular and epithelial cells of the proximal tubules necrosis in rat kidney</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="9">Pathologic grading of glomerular and epithelial cells of the proximal tubules necrosis</th></tr><tr><th>Groups</th><th>Zero</th><th>I</th><th>II</th><th>III</th><th>IV</th><th>N</th><th char="&#x000d7;"><italic>P</italic> value vs Control</th><th><italic>P</italic> value vs CCl<sub>4</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Control</td><td>10</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td/></tr><tr><td>CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>***</sup></td><td>0</td><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>10</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>SL/CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>###</sup></td><td>8</td><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>a</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub></td><td>0</td><td>2</td><td>5</td><td>3</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</td><td>ns</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>b</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>#</sup></td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup>/CCl<sub>4</sub><sup>###</sup></td><td>7</td><td>3</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td>MpEO<sup>c</sup></td><td>9</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>10</td><td>ns</td><td><italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>MpEO (5&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>b</sup>MpEO (15&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), <sup>c</sup>MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg BW), SL: Silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg BW)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par63">Chemical composition of the essential oil obtained from MpEO was determined by GC-MS analysis. The compounds, their percentages as well as the retention indices are listed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The essential oil is a complex mixture with 26 compounds representing 98.17% of the total oil composition. The major component of the essential oil is menthol (33.59%) followed by iso-menthone (33.00%). In lower amounts we found a variety of compounds including limonene (8.00%), piperitone (3.20%), 1,8-cineole (2.80%), linalool (2.64%), iso-pulegol (2.40%), caryophyllene (1.95%) and pulegone (1.60%). The obtained results are in accordance with previous studies of <italic>M. piperita</italic> oils from Turkey, Spain (Barcelona), Norway and Poland that also had menthone and menthol as their most important components [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. On the other hand, the composition of the essential oil from Iran is totally different, with &#x003b1;-terpinene (19.70%), isomenthone (10.30%), trans-carveol (14.50%), pipertitinone oxide (19.30%) and &#x003b2;-caryophyllene (7.60%) as the major compounds, and also the oil from the Girona region (Spain) is different, where limonene and 1.8-cineole, eucalyptol are the main compounds (33.37% and 30.75%, respectively) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">These studies showed variable chemotypes of <italic>M. piperita</italic> L. extracts with various major oil components. Differences in chemical composition observed for essential oils is likely related to abiotic factors such as soil type and climate specific regions of provenance samples and geographical factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Furthermore, menthol and iso-menthone, found at relatively high concentrations in the MpEO used in the present study, have been reported to exhibit anti-inflammatory activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], making MpEO use a promising candidate against oxidative damage of the liver and kidney following an intraperitoneal administration of CCl<sub>4.</sub> To be noted: working with natural extracts, the antioxidant activity is considered to be primary related to the major active compounds in the essential oil such as menthol and its derivatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However the antioxidant activity could also come from a minor compound interacting in a synergistic or antagonistic way, to create an effective system against free radicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], this has to be realized when evaluating different MpEO preparations.</p><p id="Par65">Liver injury after CCl<sub>4</sub> exposure is characterized by the elevated levels of serum hepatic marker enzymes indicating the cellular leakage and loss of functional integrity of hepatic membrane architecture. High levels of ALT, AST, ALP, LDH and &#x003b3;GT activities are sensitive indicators of liver cell injury and are most helpful in recognizing hepatic diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. CCl<sub>4</sub>-treated rats show increased activities of these enzymes, reflecting damage to the liver cells or changes in the cell membrane permeability leading to leakage of enzymes from cells to the circulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In the present study increased levels of serum hepatic markers suggested that an extensive liver injury was occasioned by CCl<sub>4</sub> due to increased lipid peroxidation which had the ability to cause membrane damage. It is now generally accepted that CCl<sub>4</sub> hepatotoxicity is the result of reductive dehalogenation, which is catalyzed by its specific isoenzyme of cytochrome P450 2E1, and which forms the highly reactive free radical. Hence, the suppression of P450 2E1 could result in reduced levels of reactive metabolites, and thus decreased tissue damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par66">The liver plays a fundamental role in the metabolism of lipids. Injection of CCl<sub>4</sub> caused a significant increase in the triglyceride, total cholesterol, and LDL levels and decrease in HDL level. Increase in the cholesterol levels might be due to the increased esterification of fatty acids, inhibition of fatty acid &#x003b2;-oxidation, and decreased excretion of cellular lipids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. CCl<sub>4</sub> stimulates the transfer of acetate into liver cells (probably by increasing access to acetate) and leads to an increase in cholesterol synthesis. It also increases the synthesis of fatty acids and triglyceride from acetate and enhances lipid esterification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The accumulation of triglyceride in liver might occur due to the inhibition of lysosomal lipase activity and VLDL secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par67">The administration of CCl<sub>4</sub> induced also renal toxicity evidenced by an elevation of serum creatinine and urea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. These pathological changes can also be attributed to damages touching the structural integrity of nephrons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], which is consistent with reports confirming that the level of serum creatinine increases only if at least half of the kidney nephrons are already damaged [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par68">Treatment of rats with MpEO prior to CCl<sub>4</sub> exposure resulted in a dramatically protective effect against acute hepato and renotoxicity and oxidative stress, which was further also confirmed by the hepatic histopathological examinations. The stimulation of hepatic regeneration makes the liver more resistant to damage by the toxin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Treatment with silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) or MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) significantly decreased the elevated levels of ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, &#x003b3;GT, total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL urea and creatinine and increased of HDL level as compared to CCl<sub>4</sub> group. Pharmacological studies have shown that essential oil derived from various plant materials possesses anti-inflammatory activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] Knowing that sesquiterpenes have excellent anti-inflammatory activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], the anti-inflammatory activity of <italic>M. piperita</italic> L. leaf essential oil could be partly explained by the presence of sesquiterpenes, such as spathulenol, cadinene, caryophyllene and caryophyllene oxide. The ethanolic extract of parsley leaves also showed significant anti-inflammatory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] and antioxidant activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] which may contribute to its hepatoprotective action. Furthermore, menthol and iso-menthone, found at relatively high concentrations in the MpEO used in the present study, have been reported to exhibit anti-inflammatory activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par69">In the present study, the two fold increase in the TBARS levels and reduce activity of SOD, CAT and GPx observed in liver and kidney homogenate of CCl<sub>4</sub>-intoxicated rats. Silymarin significantly reversed CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced TBARS levels elevation but values obtained with MpEO at the highest dose was comparable in attenuation of TBARS levels in liver and kidney. Silymarin reversed CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced SOD, CAT and GPx activities decrease but values obtained with MpEO at the highest dose (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) was comparable in attenuation of SOD, CAT and GPx activities in liver and kidney.</p><p id="Par70">These results suggested that MpEO could exert its antioxidant and/or radical scavenging activities thus preventing the formation of the carbon free radicals originated from CCl<sub>4</sub> metabolism as well as ROS and peroxidation products. This hypothesis is supported by the recent findings on the in vitro antiradical and antioxidative activities of MpEO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Previous studies showed that menthol and its derivatives were the major compounds responsible for antioxidant activity of MpEO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par71">In the present study, the rats of group 2 served as CCl<sub>4</sub>-hepato and renotoxicity control and rats of groups 3, 4, 5 and 6 were injected with 1&#x000a0;ml/kg BW of CCl<sub>4</sub> and olive oil mixture on day seven (a single intraperitoneal injection). It has already been shown that a single dose of CCl<sub>4</sub> initiates lipid peroxidation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] that results in the disruption of cellular and organelle membrane integrity and subsequent leakage of cellular contents into the blood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. CCl<sub>4</sub> is further well known to induce fibrosis of the hepatic tissue that may further progress to cirrhosis if the stimuli persists [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Thus, a single CCl<sub>4</sub> injection in mice can be used as an attractive and highly reproducible model of liver regeneration after toxic injury. The first appearance of histological fibrosis and scarring fibers is usually observed after repeated CCl<sub>4</sub> treatment for 2 to 3&#x000a0;weeks, depending on the dosage and mouse strains used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. In the present work, the hepatic histoarchitecture of the CCl<sub>4</sub>-treated rats resulted large numbers of inflammatory cells such as lymphocytes along with hepatic sinusoidal inflammation, hepatocyte necrosis and devastating liver architecture The highest dose of MpEO (40&#x000a0;mg/kg) or silymarin (50&#x000a0;mg/kg) significantly attenuated the damaged liver depicting marked focal regenerative changes which are illustrated by presence of actively dividing cells with a prominent nucleolus. The administration of MpEO reducing the histological alterations in liver provoked by CCl<sub>4</sub> was quite noticeable. In fact, the histological changes seen in the kidney of rats treated with CCl<sub>4</sub> were characterized by some nephrotoxic lesions, as evidenced by the glomerular and tubular necrosis. Our results confirmed previous findings of Ozturk et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>] who had found degenerative changes in kidney of rats exposed to CCl<sub>4</sub>. The results suggest that MpEO treatment prior to CCl<sub>4</sub> intoxication could prevent the CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced alterations in kidney tissues of treated animals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par72">The contents of MpEO not only protect the integrity of plasma membrane but, at the same time, increased the regenerative and reparative capacity of the liver and kidney. These results suggest that the compound present in MpEO has hepatorenal protective effects against CCl<sub>4</sub> induced oxidative stress in rats. Further investigations are essential to elucidate the precise mechanism of active agents of MpEO protection against CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced hepatotoxicity and nephrotoxicity and it has to be tested against other biological parameters.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BHT</term><def><p id="Par5">Butylated hydroxytoluene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAT</term><def><p id="Par6">Catalase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DPPH</term><def><p id="Par7">1-Diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DTNB</term><def><p id="Par8">5,5&#x02032;-Dithio-bis(2-nitrobenzoic acid)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EDTA</term><def><p id="Par9">Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPX</term><def><p id="Par10">Glutathione peroxidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSH</term><def><p id="Par11">Glutathione</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>M. piperita</italic></term><def><p id="Par12">
<italic>Mentha piperita</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MpEO</term><def><p id="Par13"><italic>Mentha piperita</italic> essential oil</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NBT</term><def><p id="Par14">Nitroblue Tetrazolium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p id="Par15">Reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p id="Par16">Standard deviation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOD</term><def><p id="Par17">Superoxide dismutase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBA</term><def><p id="Par18">Thiobarbituric Acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBARS</term><def><p id="Par19">Thiobarbituric acid reactive substances</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBS</term><def><p id="Par20">Tris Buffered Saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCA</term><def><p id="Par21">Trichloroacetic Acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TRIS</term><def><p id="Par22">Trishydroxymethyl aminomethane</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par73">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par74">All data generated or analyzed during this study are included within the article.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>KB, ABH, KA, JvP, FMA, TR and AE designed and wrote the paper. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par75">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par76">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par77">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par78">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional, dietary and postprandial oxidative stress</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2005</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>972</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15867266?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15867266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basaga</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical aspects of free radicals</article-title><source>Biochem Cell Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>989</fpage><lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/o90-146</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2223017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2223017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ATSDR "Agency for Toxic Substance and Diseases Registry". Toxicological profile for carbon tetrachloride, U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service, TP-39/02. Atlanta, CA, 1994.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of salvianic acid a on acute liver injury induced by carbon tetrachloride in rats</article-title><source>Biol Pharm Bull</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/bpb.30.44</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17202657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17202657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilfred</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cathrine</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative damage to the lipids and proteins of the lungs, testis and kidney of rats during carbon tetrachloride intoxication</article-title><source>Clin Chim Acta</source><year>1999</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-8981(99)00140-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10636716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10636716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibfritz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moncol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Telser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free radicals and antioxidants in normal physiological functions and human disease</article-title><source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2006.07.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16978905?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free radicals antioxidants and nutrition</article-title><source>Nutrition</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0899-9007(02)00916-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12361782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatnagar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N-nitrosodiethylamine induced oxidative stress in rat liver</article-title><source>Chem Biol Interact</source><year>2005</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2005.08.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16144695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16144695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shahjahan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabitha</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jainu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shyamala Devi</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of <italic>Solanum trilobatum</italic> against carbon tetrachloride induced hepatic damage in albino rats</article-title><source>Indian J Med Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15489557?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15489557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of novel mechanisms of silymarin on the carbontetrachloride-induced liver fibrosis in mice by nuclear factor-KB bioluminescent imaging-guided transcriptomic analysis</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2012</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1568</fpage><lpage>1575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2012.02.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22386810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22386810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heywood</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Flowering plants of the world</source><year>1979</year><publisher-loc>Oxford, U.K</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Encyclopaedia of herbs and their uses</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>London, U.K</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Dorling Kindersley</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Foster S. Peppermint, <italic>Mentha piperita</italic>, In Botanical Series, American Botanical Council: Austin, Texas, no 306, 1990.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant products as antimicrobial agents</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>1999</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>582</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10515903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatoprotection of tea seed oil (<italic>Camellia oleifera Abel.</italic>) against CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced oxidative damage in rats</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>888</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2006.11.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17188414?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sun Z, Wang H, Wang J, Zhou L, Yang P. Chemical Composition and Anti-Inflammatory, Cytotoxic and Antioxidant Activities of Essential Oil from Leaves of <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> Grown in China, Plos One. 10.1371/journal.pone.0114767, (2014) 1&#x02013;15.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blois</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant determinations by the use of stable free radical</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1958</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>200</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of various tea extracts in relation to their antimutagenicity</article-title><source>J Agr Food Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf00049a007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Council of European Communities. Council instructions about the protection of living animals used in scientific investigations. Off J Euro Commun. 2010; 276:1-33.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mihailovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihailovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uskokovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Aramba&#x00161;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mi&#x00161;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stankovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Katani&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mladenovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soluji&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mati&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatoprotective effects of <italic>Gentiana asclepiadea</italic> L. extracts against carbon tetrachloride induced liver injury in rats</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2012.10.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23146698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23146698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruckner</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Muralidhara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Luthra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oral toxicity of carbon tetrachloride: acute, subacute and subchronic studies in rates</article-title><source>Fundam Appl Toxicol</source><year>1986</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0272-0590(86)90260-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3710021?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3710021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahreen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatoprotective effects of methanol extract of <italic>Carissa opaca</italic> leaves on CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced damage in rat</article-title><source>Complement Altern Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spindler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subchronic toxicity study of peppermint oil in rats</article-title><source>Toxicol letter</source><year>1992</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-4274(92)90024-E</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowry</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosebrough</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein measurement with Folin phenol reagent</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1951</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14907713?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14907713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malondialdehyde determination as index of lipid peroxidation</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1990</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0076-6879(90)86135-I</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalase <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1984</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0076-6879(84)05016-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>JWF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assaying for superoxide dismutase activity: some large consequences of minor changes in conditions</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>1987</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-2697(87)90489-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Floh&#x000e9; L, G&#x000fc;nzler WA. Assays for glutathione peroxidase. Methods Enzymol. 1984;105:114-21.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheuer</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of chronic viral hepatitis: a need for reassessment</article-title><source>J Hepatol</source><year>1991</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-8278(91)90084-O</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1808228?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1808228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of different extraction methods for the analysis of fragrances from <italic>Lavandula</italic> species by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry</article-title><source>J Chromatogr</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9673(02)01445-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohloff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dragland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mordal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of harvest time and drying method on biomass production, essential oil yield, and quality of peppermint (<italic>Mentha&#x000d7;piperita</italic> L.)</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>4143</fpage><lpage>4148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf047998s</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15884852?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15884852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Skalicka-Wozniak K, Walasek M. Preparative separation of menthol and pulegone from peppermint oil (<italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L.) by high-performance counter-current chromatography. Phytochem Lett. 2014;728: 10.1016/j.phytol.06.007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadegarinia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gachkar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Taghizadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alipoor-Astaneh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasooli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical activities of Iranian <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L. and <italic>Myrtus communis</italic> L. essential oils</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1249</fpage><lpage>1255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2006.04.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz Del Castillo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanch</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Herraiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural variability of the enantiomeric composition of bioactive chiral terpenes in <italic>Mentha piperita</italic></article-title><source>J Chromatogr A</source><year>2004</year><volume>1054</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2004.08.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15553135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative chemical composition of the essential oil of <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L. from various geographical sources</article-title><source>Proc Estonian Acad Sci Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>181</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activities of polyphenols from sage (<italic>Salvia officinalis</italic>)</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0308-8146(01)00198-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marimuthu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>De Heluani</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalan</surname><given-names>CAN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and biocidal activities of <italic>Carum nigrum</italic> (seed) essential oil, oleoresin, and their selected components</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf0518610</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16390196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16390196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pradeep</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Victor Raj Mohan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobianand</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Karthikeyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of <italic>Cassia fistula</italic> Linn. On diethylnitrosamine induced hepatocellular damage and oxidative stress in ethanol pretreated rats</article-title><source>Biol Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0716-97602010000100013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21157638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21157638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botsoglou</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taitzoglou</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Botsoglou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavrentiadou</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokoli</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Roubies</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of long-term dietary administration of oregano on the alleviation of carbon tetrachloride-induced oxidative stress in rats</article-title><source>J AgricFood Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>6287</fpage><lpage>6293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf8003652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zangar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytochrome P4502E1 is the primary enzyme responsible for low-dose carbon tetrachloride metabolism in human liver microsomes</article-title><source>Chem Biol Interact</source><year>2000</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-2797(00)00149-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10731522?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms by which dietary fatty acids modulate plasma lipids</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2005</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>2075</fpage><lpage>2078</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16140878?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16140878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Weber LW, Boll M, Stampfl A. Hepatotoxicity and mechanism of action of haloalkanes: carbon tetrachloride as a toxicological model. Crit Rev Toxicol. 2003; 33: 10.1080/713611034.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marimuthu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Adluri</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajagopalan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective role of ferulic acid on carbon tetrachloride-induced hyperlipidemia and histological alterations in experimental rats</article-title><source>J Basic Clin Physiol Pharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jbcpp-2012-0053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23241587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23241587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel Moneim</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Deib</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The possible protective effects of <italic>Physalis peruviana</italic> on carbon tetrachloride-induced nephrotoxicity in male albino rats</article-title><source>Life Sci J</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1038</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Yahya M, Mothana R, Al-Said M, Al-Dosari M, Al-Musayeib N, Al-Sohaibani M, Parvez MK, Rafatullah S. Attenuation of CCl<sub>4</sub>-Induced Oxidative Stress and Hepatonephrotoxicity by Saudi Sidr Honey in Rats, Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine. 2013; 10.1155/2013/569037.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahreen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokhari</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of CCl<sub>4</sub>-induced nephrotoxicity with Sonchus Asper in rat</article-title><source>Food Chem Toxicol</source><year>2010</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>2469</fpage><lpage>2476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2010.06.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20550952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20550952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bhattacharya H, Lun L, Gomez R. Biochemical Effects to Toxicity of CCl<sub>4</sub> on Rosy Barbs (<italic>Puntius conchonius</italic>). Our Nat. 2005;3:20-25.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadasivan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Latha</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasikumar</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajashekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shymal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shine</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatoprotective studies on <italic>Hedyotis Corymbosa</italic> (L.) lam</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmcol</source><year>2006</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2006.01.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Doriguetto</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composition, and Antiinflammatory and antioxidant activities of the volatile oil from the fruit peel of <italic>Garcinia brasiliensis</italic></article-title><source>Chem Biodivers</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbdv.200890022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18293438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18293438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and anti-inflammatory effects of essential oil from <italic>Farfugium japonicum</italic> flower</article-title><source>J Oleo Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5650/jos.57.623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yua</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and antihyperlipidemic activities of polysaccharides from sea cucumber <italic>Apostichopus japonicas</italic></article-title><source>Carbohydr Polym</source><year>2012</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1664</fpage><lpage>1670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.07.047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22944431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22944431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Howiriny</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Sohaibani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Tahir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafatullah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of experimentally-induced gastric ulcers in rats by an ethanolic extract of "parsley" <italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic></article-title><source>Am J Chin Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S0192415X03001405</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14696673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14696673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>PYY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitts</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the dual antioxidant and antibacterial properties of parsley (<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>) and cilantro (<italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic>) extracts</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2005.05.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antioxidant activity of parsley (<italic>Petroselinum crispum</italic>) essential oil and identification of its antioxidant constituents</article-title><source>Food Res Int</source><year>2006</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2006.03.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hafeman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protection against carbon tetrachloride-induced lipid peroxidation in the rat by dietary vitamin E, selenium, and methionine as measured by ethane evolution</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>1977</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><?supplied-pmid 845700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">845700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mccay</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornbrook</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for carbon tetrachloride-induced lipid peroxidation in mouse liver</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>1982</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-2952(82)90189-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7073767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7073767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burk</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship of oxygen and glutathione in protection against carbon tetrachloride-induced hepatic microsomal lipid peroxidation and covalent binding in the rat. Rationale for the use of hyperbaric oxygen to treat carbon tetrachloride ingestion</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1984</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1996</fpage><lpage>2001</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI111621</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6511912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6511912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Recknagel</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Glende</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolak</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of carbon tetrachloride toxicity</article-title><source>Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1989</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0163-7258(89)90050-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2675128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2675128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Recknagel</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new direction in the study of carbon tetrachloride hepatotoxicity</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>1983</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0024-3205(83)90787-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6348456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6348456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brattin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Glende</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Recknagel</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathological mechanisms in carbon tetrachloride hepatotoxicity</article-title><source>J Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>1985</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0748-5514(85)90026-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3915301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3915301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Earle</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Patek</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of yeast and food intake on experimental carbon tetrachloride cirrhosis of the liver in the rat</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1942</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19970649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19970649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Constandinou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Iredale</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling liver fibrosis in rodents</article-title><source>Methods Mol Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16118456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16118456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Munday</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>York</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dare</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Turton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive characterization of serum clinical chemistry parameters and the identification of urinary superoxide dismutase in a carbon tetrachloride-induced model of hepatic fibrosis in the female Hanover Wistar rat</article-title><source>Int J Exp Pathol</source><year>2007</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2613.2007.00543.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17877538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17877538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashiq</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Turton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dare</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><name><surname>York</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Munday</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic investigation of urinary markers of carbon-tetrachloride-induced hepatic fibrosis in the Hanover Wistar rat</article-title><source>Cell Biol Toxicol</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10565-008-9104-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18777138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18777138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauwers</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanuti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>TANABE</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mouse model of carbon tetrachloride induced liver fibrosis: Histopathological changes and expression of CD133 and epidermal growth factor</article-title><source>BMC Gastroenterol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>79</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-230X-10-79</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20618941?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20618941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liedtke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Luedde</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauerbruch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Streetz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tacke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautwein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trebicka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiskirchen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental liver fibrosis research: update on animal models, legal issues and translational aspects</article-title><source>Fibrogenesis Tissue Repair</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1755-1536-6-19</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24274743?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24274743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ucar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vardi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Batcioglu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iinduced nephrotoxicity and protective effect of betaine in Sprague-Dawley rats</article-title><source>Urology</source><year>2003</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0090-4295(03)00255-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12893363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12893363</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>