<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, EOCs’ high volatility, high reactivity and low solubility in water limit their application [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Several strategies have been investigated to improve the use of EOCs, most of them aiming to reduce their volatility and increase their solubility. Among these strategies, the use of encapsulation protocols has been explored [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Among the materials for EOC encapsulation, mesoporous silica particles (MSPs) present several advantages, such as high pore volume for loading molecules, easy chemical functionalization and low toxicity levels [
 <xref rid="B19-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In fact, MSPs have been used for the protection and controlled release of (i) bioactive molecules for the improvement of organoleptic or nutritional properties of foods [
 <xref rid="B20-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] or of (ii) antimicrobial agents to design novel preservatives [
 <xref rid="B18-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Moreover, given the easy chemical modification of the MSPs’ surface, a wide variety of organic moieties have been used as molecular gates (also known as gatekeepers or nanovalves) to develop advanced delivery systems [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. In these systems, the gated materials can ideally show a “zero” payload release, yet the presence of predefined physical, chemical or biochemical stimuli induce pore opening and cargo delivery. This concept has been widely applied to drug delivery [
 <xref rid="B26-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], sensing [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and communication protocols [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Among gating moieties, proteins have been employed as pore-blocking agents in hybrid MSP materials, allowing entrapped cargo release when proteolytic enzymes are present [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, considering the inherent presence of bacterial protease secretion as a potential stimulus for cargo release, studies in the literature aiming to develop protein-capped antimicrobial carriers are still scarce [
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Moreover, protease secretion is a key factor in the virulence of pathogen growth [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], so the greater the pathogen virulence, the larger the protease secretion and therefore the higher the triggering stimulus. Based on the aforementioned premises, the attainment of a protein able to act as a capping moiety is preeminent to develop alternative MSP-based antimicrobial systems. In this scenario, a low-cost, industrially produced and widely studied protein is α-zein, the most abundant protein in corn [
 <xref rid="B44-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Alpha-zein (hereinafter referred to as “zein”) is an approximately 22-kDa prolamin protein with a complex tertiary structure which strongly depends on the solvent, based on nine repeating α-helices, with an elongated proposed shape [
 <xref rid="B47-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Although zein is a widely described protein and it has even been studied as a matrix for the preparation of antibacterial nanocomposites including essential oil-loaded MSPs [
 <xref rid="B48-ijms-22-03795" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], its use specifically as a gatekeeper for MSPs has not been reported yet. However, its own characteristics make zein a viable option to block pores in MSPs and, therefore, to prepare enzyme-responsive particles to protect and actively release EOCs. Furthermore, as the zein protein is a food grade compound, it can be applied for fortification in food systems. Thus, EOCs’ volatility can be reduced through their encapsulation into MSPs, and their active controlled release triggered by proteolytic enzymes can enhance their antimicrobial action, improving EOCs’ bioavailability, with the aim of increasing food safety while extending the shelf life of food.
</p>
