<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phenolic compounds belong to a large family of secondary metabolites and possess different chemical structures and polarities and are differently extracted by various solvents [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The difference in extractive capacities of solvents on phenolic compounds of 
 <italic>P. capitata</italic> is in agreement with the findings of Ohikhena et al. [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and Freitas et al. [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The global trend was a decrease in the total phenol, flavonoid, and flavonol contents with the increase of solvent polarity, particularly with methanol. For this solvent, the extraction yield was significantly and negatively correlated to TPC (
 <italic>r</italic> = 0.877, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), TFC (
 <italic>r</italic> = −0504, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and TFnC (
 <italic>r</italic> = −701, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), while TTC was positively correlated to the extraction yield (
 <italic>r</italic> = 0.572, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) by this solvent (
 <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). This can be justified by the fact that, in methanol extracts, these compounds were surely diluted, due to the high and nonspecific extractive capacity of plant secondary metabolites by methanol, allowing it to extract a large variety of compounds, both polar and nonpolar [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The positive correlation of the yield to TTC indicates that tannins were more efficiently extracted by methanol. Indeed, tannins are polymerized into complex forms of phenolic compounds with increased polarity [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The yield was positively correlated to TFC (
 <italic>r</italic> = 0.868; 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01) and TTC (
 <italic>r</italic> = 0.529; 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) of ethyl acetate extract (
 <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), suggesting that theses extracts mostly contain aglycone flavonoids. It is known that less polar solvents such as ethyl acetate extract preferably extract aglycone flavonoids, while more polar solvents such as alcohol and water better extract glycoside flavonoids [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. These correlations, associated to one of the methanol extractions, may indicate that the total tannins of 
 <italic>P. capitata</italic> are midpolar compounds. However, it is to be noted that many authors recommend solvent mixtures for tannin extraction [
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and this may later be experimented for 
 <italic>P. capitata</italic> tannin extraction, combining, for example, methanol and ethyl acetate in appropriate proportions.
</p>
