<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">The purpose of this study was to investigate the chemical composition and biological activity of the volatile oils (VOs) from the flowers of three buckwheat species, 
  <italic class="italic">Fagopyrum esculentum</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">Fagopyrum tataricum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">Fagopyrum cymosum</italic>. The VOs were obtained from the fresh buckwheat flowers by hydrodistillation, and were analyzed for their chemical composition by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS). Nonanoic acid (7.58%), (
  <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-3-hexen-1-ol (6.52%), and benzothiazole (5.08%) were the major constituents among the 28 identified components which accounted for 92.89% of the total oil of 
  <italic class="italic">F. esculentum</italic>. 2-Pentadecanone (18.61%), eugenol (17.18%), 1,2-benzenedicarboxylic acid, bis(2-methylpropyl) ester (13.19%), and (
  <italic class="italic">E</italic>,
  <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-farnesylacetone (7.15%) were the major compounds among the 14 identified components which accounted for 88.48% of the total oil of 
  <italic class="italic">F. tataricum</italic>. Eugenol (12.22%), (
  <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-3-hexen-1-yl acetate (8.03%), linalool oxide (7.47%), 1-hexanol (7.07%), and benzothiazole (6.72%) were the main compounds of the 20 identified components which accounted for 90.23% of the total oil of 
  <italic class="italic">F. cymosum</italic>. The three VOs were screened to have broad spectrum antibacterial activity with minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) values ranged from 100.0 μg/mL to 800.0 μg/mL against the tested bacteria, and their median inhibitory concentration (IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub>) values were from 68.32 μg/mL to 452.32 μg/mL. 
  <italic class="italic">Xanthomonas vesicatoria</italic> was the most sensitive bacterium. Moreover, the flower VOs of 
  <italic class="italic">F. esculentum</italic>, 
  <italic class="italic">F. tataricum</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">F. cymosum</italic> also exhibited noteworthy antioxidant capacity with the IC
  <sub class="sub">50</sub> value of 354.15 μg/mL, 210.63 μg/mL, and 264.92 μg/mL for the 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radical scavenging assay, and the value of 242.06 μg/mL, 184.13 μg/mL, and 206.11 μg/mL respectively for the β-carotene-linoleic bleaching test. These results suggested the volatile oils of buckwheat flowers could be potential resource of natural antimicrobial and antioxidant agents.
 </p>
</abstract>
