<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Verbascum thapsus</italic> L. (common mullein, 
 <italic>Scrophulariaceae</italic>) is a monocarpic and self‐fertile herbaceous plant with a native distribution range in Europe and Central Asia from the boreal zone to the Mediterranean area (Ansari &amp; Daehler, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Jäger, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Currently, 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> is a common species globally (Ansari &amp; Daehler, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>), largely naturalized in North America and Australia, for example, present in all states of the United States and considered invasive in some areas of California (Pitcairn, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>) and in Hawaii (Starr et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). In New Zealand, the species is listed in the highest category of the New Zealand Naturalised Vascular Plant Checklist as fully naturalized. Common mullein is well adapted to drought stress and typically grows in open anthropogenic sites such as dry, sandy, and calcareous quarries, in ruderal habitats, in gravel beds, along roadsides, and on abandoned lands (Jäger, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The species has a tap root that is associated with arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (Harley &amp; Harley, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>). As shown by Francis and Read (
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>), mycorrhizal fungi can also reduce the relative growth rate of 
 <italic>V. thapsus</italic> by 25% and the survival rate by 33%; thus, AMF does not necessarily promote plant growth. 
 <italic>Verbascum thapsus</italic> produces up to 180,000 seeds per individual creating a huge persistent seedbank (Darlington &amp; Steinbauer, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">1961</xref>; Gross, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">1980</xref>; Kivilaan &amp; Bandurski, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">1981</xref>). Because of its structural and chemical defense mechanisms, particularly owing to extensive hairiness, the plant is not subjected to grazing but regularly predated by the weevil 
 <italic>Gymnetron tetrum</italic> in the native range (Reinartz, 
 <xref rid="ece36894-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">1984</xref>).
</p>
