<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0110" class="p">In oil reservoirs, salinity concentrations range from almost fresh- to salt-saturated water. Even though salinity and pH have been much less examined than temperature, they also have a high impact on microbial communities in oil by affecting growth and limiting bacterial activity. It was found that 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridia</italic> correlated with low salinity of 3.8%, while 
 <italic class="italic">Petrotoga</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Desulfotomaculum</italic> species were mostly found in samples with a higher salinity of 7.2% [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. It was suggested that hydrocarbon-degradation by 
 <italic class="italic">Desulfotomaculum</italic> species may occur even under relatively high salinity conditions [
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The amount of microbes isolated from oil fields decreased with increasing reservoir salinity above 10% [
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Sulfate-reducing bacteria where found to resist wide ranges of salinity from 0 to 17% [
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Manipulating the salinity of the injection water during oil-production to NaCl concentrations above 12% inhibits microbial H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>S production [
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The analysis of two different pits from the La Brea Tar Pits in Los Angeles indicated that site-specific differences in salinity were highly correlated with microbial community structures within the asphalt [
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Salt concentrations in oil reservoirs affected methanogenic oil biodegradation as hydrogenotrophic methanogenesis from CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> with H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> was only measured up to a salt concentration of 9%, 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0490" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>] (
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>).
</p>
