<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fucoidan is a polysaccharide which is naturally found in seaweeds and brown algae [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. It has been reported to possess antioxidant, anticancer, anti-inflammatory, antidiabetic, and immunomodulatory effects [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Fucoidans extracted from the 
 <italic>Sargassum filipendula</italic> and 
 <italic>Laminaria japonica</italic> has been shown to exhibit antioxidant activity greater than vitamin C [
 <xref rid="B102-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. A recent report mentioned that its antioxidant activity is attributed to higher scavenging of nitric oxide than the most widely used synthetic antioxidants, including butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA) and butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. It was identified and isolated from 
 <italic>Fucus distichus</italic> fungus and was investigated to determine its SIRT6 modulation activity and the results depicted a considerable increase in deacetylation activity of SIRT6 [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Researchers have reported that fucoidan showed SIRT6 specific action since it strongly enhanced SIRT6 deacetylation activity as compared with its SIRT1-SIRT3 isoforms deacetaylation activity. Furthermore, fucoidan-riched five microalgal extracts obtained from 
 <italic>Fucus distichu
  <italic>s</italic>
 </italic>, 
 <italic>Fucus vesiculous</italic>, 
 <italic>Cytoseira tamariscofolia</italic>, 
 <italic>Cytoseira nodacaulis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Alaria esculenta</italic> showed significant amplification of SIRT6 activity [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Most importantly, it exhibited dose-dependent SIRT6 stimulating activity [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Fucoidan induced apoptosis in HepG2 liver cancer cells through the upregulation of p53 and p14, as well as the stimulation of caspases activity. It is noteworthy to mention that overexpression of SIRT6 is associated with the induction of apoptosis in cancer cells. Furthermore, gluconeogenesis was inhibited by fucoidan through the stimulation of SIRT6 by p53, which in turn led to an enhanced level of FoxO1 [
 <xref rid="B89-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. It has also been reported that fucoidan provides antidiabetic action by inhibiting α-amylase and α-glucosidase. Moreover, the antidiabetic property of fucoidan is attributed to activate the PI3K/PKB pathway, which regulates insulin production and stimulates GLUT4 translocation [
 <xref rid="B91-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Implications of fucoidan have also been identified in healing inflammation via inhibition of NO production, downregulation of iNOS, COX-2, IL-1 β, TNF-α, NF- κB expression, and regulation of ERK, JNK, MAPK, and Akt pathways [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-ijms-22-04180" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>].
</p>
