<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characterization of Ce-CMEO-NPs Nanoparticles</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The conventional agriculture is quite often characterized by excess application of synthetic mycobiocides, which generally cause environmental pollution, health issues in humans and animals, and develop fungicide-resistant fungi (
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Lucas et al., 2015</a>). Therefore, researchers have given wide attention for discovery of alternatives to hazardous synthetic mycobiocides (
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">George et al., 2016</a>). Several researchers have found that plant-based mycobiocides are better alternatives for synthetic mycobiocides and especially, essential oils are non-toxic, biodegradable, “GRAS” and appropriate for sustainable agriculture (
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">Burt, 2004</a>). However, essential oils are highly volatile and easily degrade on exposure to light, heat, pH, moisture, and oxygen, and thus, deprive their stability and bio-functional properties. To overcome instability of essential oils, nanotechnologists have developed the technique of microencapsulation of essential oils with chitosan, alginates, zein protein, etc. Thus, microencapsulation safeguards the essential oils from degradation and enables its perseverance, and monitored and gradual release (
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">Turasan et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">Bakry et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">Malešević, 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, various concentrations of CMEO were successfully encapsulated with chitosan by the emulsification process (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Ribeiro et al., 2013</a>). The obtained Ce-CMEO-NPs were characterized by FT-IR, SEM, Zeta potential, and size analysis. The 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> release of CMEO from Ce-CMEO-NPs was also investigated in detail. The FT-IR spectra of the (A) chitosan, (B) CMEO, and (C) Ce-CMEO-NPs were detailed in 
  <span class="bold">Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">5</a>
  </span> and revealed the successful encapsulation of essential oil with chitosan. The results depict the characteristic absorption bands of chitosan, CEMO, and Ce-CMEO-NPs. The band attendance at 3427 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> in chitosan, CMEO, and Ce-CMEO-NPs represents O-H vibration, which confirms one of the positive signs for encapsulation of chitosan with CMEO. Furthermore, peaks at 2935, 1407, 1038, and 1607 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> in CMEO and Ce-CMEO-NPs represent the stretching vibrations of C–H, C–N, C–O–C, and N–H, respectively (
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">Gayathri et al., 2015</a>). These results signify the successful encapsulation of Ce-CMEO-NPs (
  <span class="bold">Figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">5B,C</a>
  </span>). The existence of amine groups on the surface of the chitosan is measured as the key to bind to the active functional groups of CMEO. Especially, unique peak at 1607 cm
  <span class="sup">-1</span> is due to the presence of amine group in chitosan, which is considered to be pivotal in bioconjugation and formation of Ce-CMEO-NPs (
  <span class="bold">Figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">5B,C</a>
  </span>). The amino group complexes are having unoccupied coordination points, which act as the binding sites for functional ligands of CMEO constituent molecules like geraniol, geranial, limonene, linalool, and limonene. The bio-active molecules in CMEO are more stabilized due to chitosan conjugation and enhance the effectiveness of the antifungal activity. The morphological feature of Ce-CMEO-NPs was observed by SEM and depicted in 
  <span class="bold">Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">6</a>
  </span>. The microscopic images revealed that the Ce-CMEO-NPs were showing spherical surface morphology. This is because of high thermodynamic and shape stability of Ce-CMEO-NPs. The agglomerated surface morphology of the prepared Ce-CMEO-NPs is due to the electrostatic interaction of chitosan fragments, which are branched biopolymer.
 </p>
 <div id="F5" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Fourier transform infrared (FT-IR) spectra of 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> chitosan, 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span>
    <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> essential oil (CMEO), and 
    <span class="bold">(C)</span> chitosan encapsulated 
    <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> essential oil nanoparticles (Ce-CMEO-NPs).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fphar-09-00610-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="F6" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Scanning electron microscopic (SEM) image of chitosan encapsulated 
    <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> essential oil nanoparticles (Ce-CMEO-NPs) loaded with 700 ppm of 
    <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> essential oil (CMEO) at different magnifications of 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> 10,000×, 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span> 20,000×, 
    <span class="bold">(C)</span> 30,000×, and 
    <span class="bold">(D)</span> 50,000×.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fphar-09-00610-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, stability and size of Ce-CMEO-NPs were determined by Zeta potential and size distribution analysis. We have prepared Ce-CMEO-NPs with various loading concentrations of CMEO (ppm). The obtained Zeta potential values are ranging from 39.3 to 37.2 mV for the corresponding particle size of Ce-CMEO-NPs varying from 455 to 480 nm (
  <span class="bold">Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">2</a>
  </span>). The obtained Zeta potential values above 35 mV confirm that the Ce-CMEO-NPs are highly stable, and the particle size of the Ce-CMEO-NPs is not greatly affected by the CMEO loading.
 </p>
 <div id="T2" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Zeta potential and size of chitosan encapsulated CMEO nanoparticles (Ce-CMEO-NPs) made with different ppm of CMEO.</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 ppm</th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200 ppm</th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300 ppm</th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400 ppm</th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500 ppm</th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">600 ppm</th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">700 ppm</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Particle size (nm)</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">455</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">459</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">464</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">472</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">476</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">480</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeta potential (mV)</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.6</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> cumulative release of CMEO from Ce-CMEO-NPs at pH 7.4 and 1.5 over a period of 48 h is shown in 
  <span class="bold">Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">7</a>
  </span>. It was noticed that the better-sustained release of CMEO at pH 7.4 than pH 1.5. For a period of 48 h, cumulative of 97.94 ± 0.95 and 43.37 ± 2.17% of CMEO was released from Ce-CMEO-NPs at pH 7.4 and pH 1.5, respectively. The reason might be the formation of highly stable bioactive complex of chitosan at acidic pH 1.5 (
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Cojocariu et al., 2012</a>). It is observed that the release of essential oil is stabilized due to the complex formation with chitosan. The volatile alcohols and phenol groups of CMEO will be converted into its more stable complex forms by the chitosan encapsulation process which in turn increases their effective lifetime for fungicidal action by gradual release of antifungal constituents.
 </p>
 <div id="F7" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="italic">In vitro</span> release kinetics of 
    <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> essential oil (CMEO) from chitosan encapsulated 
    <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> essential oil nanoparticles (Ce-CMEO-NPs) in hydroethanolic solution at pH 7.4 and 1.5. Statistical data were analyzed by one-way ANOVA following Tukey’s 
    <span class="italic">post hoc</span> multiple comparison test and columns with different letters were statistically significant within the group of pH 7.4 and 1.5 (
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fphar-09-00610-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
