<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Fusarium graminearum</span> [telemorph Gibberella zeae (Schwein)] is a sporadic plant pathogen, causes Fusarium head blight (FHB) in barley and wheat, stalk rot and Gibberella ear rot in maize, and one of the utmost liable for economic setback in the agriculture and food industry worldwide (
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Dweba et al., 2017</a>). 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> infestation of agriculture commodities fetches the rancidity along with the loss in grain yield and quality, including texture, color, odor, and nutrition (
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">Morgavi et al., 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">Okeke et al., 2015</a>). As well, 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> is a prominent producer of hazardous Fusarium mycotoxins, including deoxynivalenol (DON), nivalenol (NIV), and zearalenone (ZEA), which were reported to cause deleterious health issues in the farm animals and humans, such as nephrotoxic, immunotoxic, neurotoxic, hepatotoxic, genotoxic, reproductive, and developmental defects (
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">Morgavi et al., 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">Venkataramana et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Kalagatur et al., 2017</a>). Besides, International Agency on Research and Cancer (IARC) has confirmed the carcinogenicity of Fusarium mycotoxins and classified into group 3 agents (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">IARC, 1999</a>). Concerning these worries, the European Union (EU), Joint FAO/WHO Expert Committee on Food Additives (JECFA), and various nations have recommended stringent regulatory levels for Fusarium mycotoxins in agricultural and food products (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">JECFA, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">European Commission, 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regrettably, 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> and its risky toxins are coherent contaminants of wide range of agricultural commodities worldwide (
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">Richard et al., 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">Pasquali et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">Tralamazza et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">Ok et al., 2018</a>). Recently, 
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">Beccari et al. (2018)</a> have detected the higher incidence of FHB in Durum wheat samples of central Italy and reported that 22% fungal species were 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span>. In Mediterranean countries of Europe, 
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">Gorczyca et al. (2018)</a> have detected yield loss and contamination of mycotoxins in Durum wheat owed to FHB incidence. In the same way, 
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">Vogelgsang et al. (2017)</a> in Switzerland haev surveyed the incidence of DON and ZEA between 2007 and 2014 in wheat and noticed an overall mean concentration of 607 μg/kg of DON and 39 μg/kg of ZEA. Intolerably, 11% and 7% of wheat samples were surpassed the EU regulatory limits of DON and ZEA, respectively, and found unfit for consumption. Similarly, 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Mallmann et al. (2017)</a> during 2008–2015 in Brazil have measured the prevalence of FHB and detected 73% and 38% of wheat samples, 67% and 41% of barley samples were contaminated with DON and ZEA, respectively. Furthermore, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Kos et al. (2017)</a> in Serbia have noticed 260.1–1388, 260.4–9050, and 252.3–6280 μg/kg of DON in maize samples during 2013, 2014, and 2015, respectively. Likewise, 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">Mudili et al. (2014)</a> and 
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">Ramana et al. (2011)</a> too enlightened the prevalence of 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> in rice, finger millet, and maize grains originated from Southern region of India and perceived 72–94 μg/kg of DON attendance in freshly harvested maize grains.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The status quo apprehensions the insistent incidence of 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> and its toxins in agricultural commodities, and demand effective approaches from microbiologists and food technologists to overcome these problems in agriculture and food industry. However, the application of synthetic fungicides has not been acceptable because of increasing concern on multiple drug resistance, environmental safety, and deleterious health issues in humans and animals. Over the last decade, plant-originated mycobiocides, exclusively essential oils have attained a considerable attention as of its non-toxic and eco-friendly (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">Hyldgaard et al., 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">Kalagatur et al., 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">George et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">Iram et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">Kumar et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">Vanhoutte et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">Muniyandi et al., 2017</a>). In recent times, nanotechnology has provided great assistance to improve the microbiological safety of food and feed matrices. Particularly, nanomaterials of chitosan were found eco-friendly and safe, and their application in food is highly satisfactory by consumer, food industry, and regulatory agencies (
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">Yeung et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">Niaz et al., 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">Siddaiah et al., 2018</a>). Furthermore, essential oils are volatile and lose their stability and bio-functional features on exposure to temperature, light, pH, moisture, and oxygen (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">Jamil et al., 2016</a>). In this context, the encapsulation of essential oils with chitosan by nanotechnology approach was recognized as a finest approach to safeguard the stability and bio-functional features of essential oils (
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">Barreto et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">Yeung et al., 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this context, essential oil obtained from leaves of 
  <span class="italic">Cymbopogon martinii</span> was encapsulated with chitosan and used for reduction of growth and mycotoxins of 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span>. The 
  <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> also known as Indian geranium, motia, and rosha, is a tropical herbaceous grass belong to family Poaceae and extensively distributed subtropical parts of Africa, America, and Asia (
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">Duke, 1993</a>). This plant is a native of India and grows as wild and irrigated crop in Western Ghats found among the states of Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka, Kerala, and Tamil Nadu, and in some parts of North Eastern India (
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">Rao, 2001</a>; 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Gupta et al., 2015</a>). The aerial parts of plant such as leaf, stem, and inflorescence are considered as decent sources for essential oil and profoundly rich in bioactive chemical constituents like caryophyllene, geraniol, geranyl acetate, linalool, myrcene, limonene, humulene, selinenes, etc. (
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">Rao et al., 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Cannon et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">Verma et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Kakaraparthi et al., 2015</a>). 
  <span class="italic">C. martinii</span> essential oil (CMEO) is considered as non-toxic, non-sensitizing and non-irritant, and not reported for any deleterious health effects and recognized as “Generally Regarded as Safe” (GRAS) by the US Food and Drug Administration, and extensively used as antimicrobial, antihelmintic, cosmetic, toiletry, pharmaceutical, preservative, stress revealer, convalescence, insect, and mosquito repellents, and also as an ingredient in herbal tea, non-alcoholic beverages, flavor in tobacco products, traditional and baked foods, and all these features reflect the potency of CMEO in essential oil industry (
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">Kumar et al., 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">Tsai et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Gupta et al., 2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, CMEO was extracted from leaves by hydrodistillation technique and chemical profile was determined by GC-MS analysis. The antifungal activity of CMEO on 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> was determined in terms of minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) and minimum fungicidal concentration (MFC) by micro-well dilution method, and further, it was confirmed by scanning electron microscopic (SEM) observation of macroconidia. The antifungal mechanism of CMEO was revealed by determining the content of intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS), lipid peroxidation, and ergosterol. The chitosan encapsulated CMEO nanoparticles (Ce-CMEO-NPs) were prepared by emulsification technique and characterized by Fourier transform infrared (FT-IR), SEM, Zeta potential and size, and 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> release of essential oil. Finally, 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> antifungal and antimycotoxin activities of CMEO and Ce-CMEO-NPs on 
  <span class="italic">F. graminearum</span> were comparatively evaluated in maize grains.
 </p>
</sec>
