<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The allorecognition role of the 
 <italic>het-s</italic> and 
 <italic>het-S</italic> alleles appears however to be a derived function [
 <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A distinct, evolutionarily more ancient mode of activation of HET-S is dependent on NWD2, the protein encoded by the gene immediately adjacent to 
 <italic>het-S</italic> in the genome. NWD2 encodes a Nod-like receptor (NLR) with a nucleotide-binding and oligomerization domain of the NACHT type and C-terminal WD-repeats (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>). NLRs constitute a diverse family of immune receptors involved in host defence both in plants and animals [
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. NLR homologs also control regulated cell death in the context of non-self recognition in fungi [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17–19</xref>]. NLRs form supramolecular signalosomes (also designated supramolecular organizing centres or SMOCs [
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]) when recognizing specific non-self cues or danger signals. The N-terminus of NWD2 displays a short region termed R0, homologous to the elementary repeats of the HET-S PFD [
 <xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This observation suggested an amyloid signalling process by which specific NLRs would engage cognate downstream cell-death execution proteins by heterotypic amyloid templating. It was found that indeed chimeric variants of NWD2 are able to induce HET-s prionisation in a ligand-dependant manner [
 <xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The interaction between the NWD2 R0 and the HET-s PFD modules can be recapitulated in mammalian cells. These two modules can substitute for the Pyrin domains in the pathway leading to ASC (apoptosis-associated speck-like protein containing a CARD domain) activation by NLRP3 (nucleotide-binding domain leucine-rich repeat and pyrin-containing receptor 3) [
 <xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], stressing the analogy between amyloid signalling and prion-like activation in mammalian NLR-signalosomes. While the exact function of HET-S/NWD2 is currently unclear (in particular the cognate ligand of NWD2 is not known), it is proposed that this gene pair functions in fungal immunity to induce cell death in response to parasites or pathogens. While many open questions remain regarding the biology of the NWD2/HET-S pathway, it can be considered established that fungi possess amyloid NLR-signalosomes [
 <xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The NWD2/HET-S system thus represents, after the mammalian necrosome (assembled through the interaction of the RHIM amyloid motifs), a second example of an amyloid signalosome [
 <xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].
</p>
