<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0007">Considering stimulation of effective bioenergy extraction, the protagonist dealing with bioelectricity production in MFCs is electroactive microbes or mixed consortia, that effectively release electrons from oxidation of organic matter 
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Of course, the bioactivities of the electricity-generating microorganisms (e.g., biofilm forming, electron-transporting characteristics) would directly influence the power-generating efficiency of MFCs [
 <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Due to some inhibitory/antagonistic interactions to be taken place, it was not possible to guarantee that all of natural substances are appropriate sources to be natural RMs. This might also explain why the extracellular metabolites of 
 <italic>Chlorella</italic> with significant redox capacities sometimes could not significantly stimulate the bioelectricity production of MFCs as previously mentioned 
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. If natural extracts exhibited significant redox-mediating capabilities, they may also possibly express toxicity potency to the receptor organisms. Therefore, significant redox capability cannot be the sole screening criterion to select electrochemically active natural RMs for bioenergy applications. For example, as literature mentioned [
 <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], some tea polyphenols owned anti-inflammatory and bacteriostatic effects (e.g., noticeable inhibition on 
 <italic>Typhoid bacillus, Paratyphoid bacillus, Yellow haemolytic staphylococcus, Streptococcus aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>Dysentery bacillus</italic>). Some studies have also shown that tea polyphenols had a strong killing effect on 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> in the oral cavity 
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Therefore, tea polyphenols have also been widely used in industrial preparation of toothpaste. That is, such strong antibacterial effects of components in tea polyphenols may also have negative effects on bacteria in MFCs.
</p>
