<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The EICA research has focused primarily upon trait change within species, although the relative importance of stochastic forces as opposed to selective forces in this process (Keller and Taylor 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">2008</xref>) can provide a major focus to further research in the evolution of invasives. Stochastic events like founder's events can limit genetic variation, which was long assumed to limit the evolutionary potential of invasive species (Lee 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">2002</xref>). However, successive founding events across the landscape may also result in the loss of less successful genotypes and higher mean population and range trait values (Vasemagi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74">2006</xref>), and population bottlenecks that reduce variation may convert epistatic to additive variation for important phenotypic traits, increasing the rate of phenotypic change (Prentis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">2008</xref>). Accurate assessments of genetic variation for traits at high levels of organization such as ranges depend on accurate assessments of population-level and family-level variation, and the necessary nested analyses require common gardens with replication at the individual level as well as the population level (Conner and Hartl 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">2004</xref>). When common garden experiments are paired with molecular techniques, some evaluation of the relative importance of stochastic and selective forces is possible, using both the single-trait quantitative approaches (e.g., comparisons of F
 <sub>ST</sub> and Q
 <sub>ST</sub>) and the quantitative genomic approaches (Beaumont and Balding 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">2004</xref>). Experimental crosses between home- and introduced-range plants may even allow quantitative trait loci (QTL) or genome mapping of traits correlated with invasiveness (Stinchcombe and Hoekstra 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b69">2007</xref>; Prentis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">2008</xref>). Such comparisons of home- and introduced-range plants are also important in addressing the influence of hybridization or changes in ploidy level, both of which are common in invasive populations, upon traits related to invasiveness (Prentis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">2008</xref>; Whitney and Gabler 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75">2008</xref>). Previous studies comparing stochastic and selective influences on invasive evolution (Handley et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">2008</xref>; van Kleunen and Fischer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">2008</xref>) demonstrate that demographic and dispersal events cannot completely account for the evolutionary divergence of invasive plants from their ancestral home-range populations.
</p>
