<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Little has been reported on the antibacterial activity of 
  <span class="italic">Myracrodruon urundeuva</span> essential oil [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. However, studies of other essential oils from the same plant (with different chemical compositions) have been tested against some of the bacteria herein tested. Among these, 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], and 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], were inhibited by such extracts, showing the antimicrobial activity of 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, in this study, the 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> leaf essential oil showed antibacterial activity against all tested strains. Such activity is probably attributable to the terpenoids, since they represented a higher proportion of the constituents in the GC-MS and GC/FID analyses. Similarly, other studies attribute antimicrobial activity to these secondary metabolites due to being abundant constituents in these essential oils [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study presents α-pinene (87.85%) as the major constituent in 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> leaf essential oil. However, it is not known whether α-pinene is chiefly responsible for the bactericidal action of the oil, or if one of the other terpenes promotes such action, since in other studies, the essential oils from 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> leaves have shown different terpene proportions from our results [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. It is important to consider differences in the chemical composition of essential oils extracted from plants of the same species. These differences arise from factors such as geographic variation, climate, soil, planting modes, fertilizers used, time of collection, and the post collection processing and extraction techniques employed [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. It is believed that the 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil’s antibacterial activity is likely conferred by terpenes, since they are abundant in the composition.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some papers support the hypothesis that α-pinene is responsible for the antimicrobial action reported in the present study. In work by Leite et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>], this terpene was isolated and showed antibacterial activity against 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. epidermidis</span>. Other studies that identified α-pinene as a major constituent in the composition of essential oils from plants other than 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> also observed antibacterial activity against Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the current study, we observed 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil’s bactericidal action for all of the bacteria tested: Gram-positive (
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. epidermidis</span>) and Gram-negative (
  <span class="italic">E. coli, P. aeruginosa</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S. enteritidis</span>). The MIC and MBC data show higher antibacterial activity against Gram-positive bacteria than Gram-negative bacteria. This is probably due to the greater complexity of the Gram-negative cell wall [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>], which interferes with any direct action on the pathogen metabolism. Among the five strains tested, 
  <span class="italic">S. epidermidis</span> (MIC = 0.11 mg/mL) was found to be the most sensitive to 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil, showing even higher sensitivity than the other Gram positive bacteria, 
  <span class="italic">S. aureus</span> (MIC = 0.22 mg/mL). For the three Gram-negative bacteria, 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil more strongly inhibited 
  <span class="italic">S. enteritidis</span> (MIC = 0.44 mg/mL) compared to 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> (MIC = 0.88 mg/mL) and 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> (MIC = 7.0 mg/mL). 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> was the least sensitive to the essential oil, possibly due to the ability of 
  <span class="italic">P. aeruginosa</span> to produce biofilm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>], which further complicates direct action of the aromatic oil component against the bacterial cell.
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span>, the literature reports studies that prove the effectiveness of essential oils obtained from other plants [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>]. Although these other plants show similar or higher antibacterial activities than 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span>, one should not underestimate its promising antibacterial effect.
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, some essential oils extracted from other plants exert weaker antimicrobial activity against the bacteria tested herein because of weaker inhibition of bacterial growth, higher MIC values, or a demonstrated bacterial resistance [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>]. These results, when compared with those obtained in the present study, reveal the more promising antibacterial power of 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil, likely because it contains specific active components.
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For HeLa cells, 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> oil shows increasing cytotoxicity over longer exposure times, indicating possible anticancer activity. For the Vero E6 strain, 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> oil cytotoxicity decreased with increasing exposure time, i.e., the greater the exposure time the lower the cytotoxic activity, and the higher the cell viability. This effect was also observed for the HEK-293 line, where cell viability was superior to both Vero strain readings. For the Vero E6 and HEK-293 strains, these results confirm that the essential oil is potentially non-cytotoxic to normal human and mammalian cells in general.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Literature data on 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> essential oil cellular toxicity are still scarce. However, some researchers have evaluated the toxicity of 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> oil, stimulating further research on their use as a source of medicinal products. In the study by Carvalho et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>] its essential oil showed low cytotoxicity for human erythrocytes. Work by Ferreira et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>] highlights the antiproliferative power of the methanolic extract obtained from 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> against HL-60 lines (leukemia) cancer, SF-295 (glioblastoma), HCT-8 (colon), and MDA/MB-435 (melanoma) cells, indicating the possible antitumor effects of 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> extracts.
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the data obtained from these cell toxicity tests, additional in vitro assays are needed and will be conducted in the future, such as cytotoxicity against normal human cells originating from other tissues, and further investigation of its antitumor activity in fibroblasts and other neoplastic cells. Further testing is needed to prove the effectiveness of the oil in vivo so it can be considered pharmacologically viable. Finally, 
  <span class="italic">M. urundeuva</span> oil showed significant antibacterial activity, notable antitumor effectiveness, and very low cell toxicity.
 </p>
</sec>
