<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to justify both phytosanitary measures associated with international trade and domestic biosecurity actions aimed at slowing or preventing the spread of an established pest, under the International Standards for Phytosanitary Measures (ISPM), it is necessary to estimate the 
 <italic>endangered area</italic> and the value of the impacts that might arise if the pest were to spread throughout that range 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-FAO1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Previously, a variety of models have been used to answer questions related to the probability and consequences of an invasion of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>. Techniques applied include niche modelling using programmes such as CLIMEX 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Venette1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> and Genetic Algorithm for Rule-set Production (GARP) 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kluza1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, as well as fine-scale tactical models and maps to address immediate management issues using support vector machines 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Guo1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, rule-based expert elicitation approaches incorporating both climatic and host data 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-USDA1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Magarey1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> and most recently, spatio-temporal, stochastic epidemiological modelling in combination with realistic geographical modelling to estimate spread 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Meentemeyer2" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Despite the importance of understanding the potential geographical range of 
 <italic>P. ramorum</italic>, most studies have modelled its potential effects and spread where it already exists in the United States and Europe 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Sansford1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Venette1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Guo1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kelly1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Meentemeyer3" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Guo2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Vclavik1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Vclavk1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Only two models have explored the potential for disease establishment and outbreaks globally 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Kluza1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0063508-Magarey1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, and neither of these approaches addressed the question of the endangered area in terms of the ISPM framework.
</p>
