<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical composition of 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> Var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil
 </div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The yield of 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil was 0.19% (
  <span class="italic">w</span>/w, on a dry weight basis). Pharmaceutical potentials of herbal medicines are determined by their chemical compositions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. In the present study, a total of 91 compounds were identified from the essential oil, including alcohols, ketones, esters, hydrocarbons, terpenes, aldehydes, acids, and so on. Total ions chromatogram (TIC) of the sample was shown in Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>, and that chemical information of identified compounds was listed in Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>. Alcohols and ketones were major ingredients of the essential oil. This essential oil has highest concentration of dihydro-
  <span class="italic">β</span>-ionol, followed by 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-ionone, (2,6,6-trimethyl-2-hydroxycyclohexylidene) acetic acid lactone and 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>-decalactone. In order to narrow the scope of potential active ingredients, pharmaceutical properties of these compounds were researched. After the preliminary screening, 79 ingredients were reserved for the next step.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In previous reports, Xin et al. characterize the volatiles in flowers of four cultivar groups of sweet osmanthus (Wuhan, China), and that 71 compounds were found in Thunbergii cultivars. 
  <span class="italic">β</span>-ionone, 
  <span class="italic">cis</span>-linalool oxide (furan), trans-linalool oxide (furan) and linalool were the most common volatiles [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Hu et al. identified 52 components from 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil (Xianning, China), and that 1,2-epoxy linalool was the main component. Lei et al. identified 45 compounds in water-soluble essential oil components from 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> flowers (Hangzhou, China), which was rich in linalool oxide, 4-methoxyphenethyl and 4-hydroxyphenethyl alcohol [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Chemical composition of 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil revealed in the present study was generally consistent with other reports, but differed in percentages of individual components. This might because that compounds in 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> flowers varied among different geographical origins and flowering stages [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
