<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical composition of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> Var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil
  </div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The yield of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil was 0.19% (
   <span class="italic">w</span>/w, on a dry weight basis). Pharmaceutical potentials of herbal medicines are determined by their chemical compositions [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. In the present study, a total of 91 compounds were identified from the essential oil, including alcohols, ketones, esters, hydrocarbons, terpenes, aldehydes, acids, and so on. Total ions chromatogram (TIC) of the sample was shown in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>, and that chemical information of identified compounds was listed in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>. Alcohols and ketones were major ingredients of the essential oil. This essential oil has highest concentration of dihydro-
   <span class="italic">β</span>-ionol, followed by 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-ionone, (2,6,6-trimethyl-2-hydroxycyclohexylidene) acetic acid lactone and 
   <span class="italic">γ</span>-decalactone. In order to narrow the scope of potential active ingredients, pharmaceutical properties of these compounds were researched. After the preliminary screening, 79 ingredients were reserved for the next step.
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In previous reports, Xin et al. characterize the volatiles in flowers of four cultivar groups of sweet osmanthus (Wuhan, China), and that 71 compounds were found in Thunbergii cultivars. 
   <span class="italic">β</span>-ionone, 
   <span class="italic">cis</span>-linalool oxide (furan), trans-linalool oxide (furan) and linalool were the most common volatiles [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Hu et al. identified 52 components from 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil (Xianning, China), and that 1,2-epoxy linalool was the main component. Lei et al. identified 45 compounds in water-soluble essential oil components from 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> flowers (Hangzhou, China), which was rich in linalool oxide, 4-methoxyphenethyl and 4-hydroxyphenethyl alcohol [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Chemical composition of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil revealed in the present study was generally consistent with other reports, but differed in percentages of individual components. This might because that compounds in 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> flowers varied among different geographical origins and flowering stages [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Target proteins and related pathways</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Proteins are crucial for herbal medicines to achieve therapeutic effects in vivo. In order to explore potential bioactivities, we collected target proteins for the selected ingredients of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil. A total of 191 target proteins were obtained (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>), including ornithine decarboxylases, adenosine receptors, hydroxyacid oxidases, and so on. It suggested that this essential oil might have various bioactivities. In addition, we excluded ingredients with no hit targets. Only 44 ingredients were reserved for further study (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pathway analysis was applied on target proteins of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil for further interpretation, and the results showed that these proteins were involved in 70 biological pathways (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>), calcium signaling pathway, nitrogen metabolism, pentose and glucuronate interconversions, cytochrome P450, and so on. These pathways were critical in several important biological processes such as signal transduction, drug metabolism and energy metabolism, which indicated that 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil might have various bioactivities.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ingredient-target-pathway network</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An ingredient-target-pathway network was built for 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), consisted of 305 nodes and 879 connections. The nodes included 44 ingredients, 191 target proteins, and 70 pathways. Degree distribution was first investigated as the basic property of a network. Degree values of all nodes were calculated and listed in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>. ⟨
   <span class="italic">k</span>⟩ of the network was 5.76. 
   <span class="italic">P(k)</span> of the network was shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. It is obvious that some nodes had much higher degree values, whereas others only had a few connections. In general, the network exhibited approximate scale-free property and power-law degree distribution, indicating that key nodes played a much more important role in the ingredient-target-pathway network of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil.
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Ingredient-target-pathway network of 
      <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
      <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil. The network consisted of 44 compounds (red nodes), 191 hit targets (yellow nodes), 70 related pathways (green nodes), and 879 connections. Numbers and names of nodes are listed in Additional file 
      <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Degree distribution of the ingredient-target-pathway network. 
      <span class="italic">k</span> represents degree values, and that 
      <span class="italic">P(k)</span> indicates degree distribution
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Main active ingredients of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> Var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil
  </div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As interaction between small molecule and protein plays a critical role in modulating the intrinsic biological processes, the information related to protein targets and small molecule has been highly valued by biomedical and pharmaceutical sciences. Target proteins are often those important ones in the development of specific diseases within the organism. Perturbing their functions by druggable molecules will help to cure the disease or relieve the symptoms [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Therefore, more attention was paid to highly connected ingredients of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil in this study.
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to explore key nodes of the network, degree values of all nodes were ranked in a descending order (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Among all the 44 ingredients, eugenol (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 106) and geraniol (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 96) had most connections with target proteins, and were screened as key ingredients of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil. Eugenol and geraniol were reported to exert multiple pharmacological actions. For instance, eugenol exhibited potential to inhibit ehrlich ascites and solid carcinoma [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Immunomodulatory and anti-inflammatory effects of eugenol were also found in clove extract [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Geraniol in essential oil of plants was reported to modulate DNA synthesis and potentiates 5-fluorouracil efficacy on human colon tumor xenografts [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Experimental evidences showed the therapeutic or preventive effects of geraniol on other different types of cancer, such as breast, lung, pancreatic, and hepatic cancer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. Geraniol could also inhibit prostate cancer growth by targeting cell cycle and apoptosis pathways [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. In addition, geraniol in plant essential oil also exhibited anti-microbial activity against many microorganisms [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>], which might be induced by causing leakage of K
   <span class="sup">+</span> and Mg
   <span class="sup">2+</span> ions from microorganism cells through changes in the compositions of the cell membranes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Degree values (
      <span class="italic">k</span>) of all nodes in the ingredient-target-pathway network, shown in descending order
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potential anti-tumor effect of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> Var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil
  </div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the target proteins of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil, MAPK1 (MK01
   <span class="italic">, k</span> = 33) and MAPK3 (MK03
   <span class="italic">, k</span> = 31) had much higher degree values than others (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). This indicated that the two proteins were associated with most ingredients and pathways in the network. They were considered as hub nodes and had significant impact on bioactivities of the essential oil. MAPK1 and MAPK3 were members of MAPKs family, which played an important role in MAPK/ERK cascade. Once universally activated, this pathway could block apoptosis, whereas the inhibition of MAPK/ERK is closely associated with anti-tumor effect [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. MAPK1 and MAPK3 have been reported to be associated with various types of cancer, such as prostate cancer, colorectal cancer and gastric cancer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few compounds in this essential oil also showed a potential strong tumor-inhibiting activity through some other target proteins. p53 is one of the most intensively studied tumor suppressor proteins, with mutations that lead to loss of wild-type p53 activity frequently detected in many different tumor types [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. In this study, p53 was the target protein of 
   <span class="italic">cis</span>-anethol. It was involved in 15 pathways in the network, which were all closely correlated to tumor progression, such as apoptosis, pancreatic cancer, glioma, and melanoma. This protein, together with the hub proteins MAPK1 and MAPK3, all belong to MAPK signaling pathway (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 12).
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">EGFR is another important protein in relation to tumor development [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. Signaling by EGFR plays a key role in tumorigenesis prompted efforts to target this receptor in anticancer therapy [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. It was the target protein of the selected main active ingredients, geraniol and eugenol. This protein was involved in 18 pathways in the network, most of which were tumor-related, such as ErbB signaling pathway, bladder cancer, endometrial cancer and colorectal cancer.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, pathway analysis showed that several target proteins of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil were involved in many tumor-related pathways (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>), including cytochrome P450 (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 22), non-small cell lung cancer (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 10), prostate cancer (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 8), small cell lung cancer (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 7), VEGF signaling pathway (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 6), prostate thyroid cancer (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 6), Wnt signaling pathway (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 5), tyrosine metabolism (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 4), and so on. These data suggested a potential anti-tumor effect of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil.
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There were also many reports about the anti-tumor effect of 
   <span class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</span>. Compounds isolated from ethyl acetate extract of 
   <span class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">aurantiacus</span> flower could inhibit the growth of human colon cancer cell line HCT-116 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. Pomolic acid, isolated from flowers of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">aurantiacus</span> Makino, could induce apoptosis in SK-OV-3 human ovarian adenocarcinoma cells [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]. These reports were consistent with the assumption that 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil had a potential anti-tumor effect.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potential neuroprotective effect of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> Var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil
  </div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The key pathway node of the network was neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). This pathway was connected with a total of 50 proteins, which meant that more than a quarter of target proteins of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil were involved in it. Neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction contains a collection of receptors and ligands, and is closely related to neurological function and neurodegeneration diseases [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>]. Coincidentally, some target proteins of this essential oil were proved to be enriched in Alzheimer’s disease (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 8, Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>), one of the best known neurodegeneration diseases. Besides, it has been reported that ethanol extract of dried 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> flowers had neuroprotective effect in Wistar rat [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. Extract of this flower was also found to protect D-galactose induced aging in mouse model [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. These data suggested a possible neuroprotection of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The core subnetwork</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to get further understanding of the key pathway in the ingredient-target-pathway network, the nodes associated with neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction were extracted and reorganized as a core subnetwork (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), which contained 8 ingredients, 50 proteins and 150 connections. Degree values of the network were also evaluated as mentioned above. Interestingly, eugenol (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 47) and geraniol (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 46) were also key nodes with much higher degree values, whereas ⟨
   <span class="italic">k</span>⟩ of the network was only 5.08. This result supported the importance of eugenol and geraniol for 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Core subnetwork of 
      <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
      <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil. The network consisted of 59 nodes and 150 connections. Red nodes represent ingredients, yellow nodes indicate target proteins, and that green nodes refers to neuroactive ligand-receptor interaction. Numbers and names of the nodes are listed in Additional file 
      <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eugenol has been reported to protect neuronal cells from excitotoxic and oxidative injury [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Neuroprotective efficacy of eugenol was also found in acrylamide-induced neuropathy in rats [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>]. Geraniol showed a neuroprotective effect in an acrylamide model of neurotoxicity in 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. Additionally, geraniol was reported to be beneficial for the treatment of Parkinson’s disease associated with neuromuscular disability. These reports further confirmed that eugenol and geraniol played an important role in the neuroprotective effect of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pathway-based protein association network</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interrelationships between target proteins have great values in the network pharmacological study of traditional medicines [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>]. In this section, a pathway-based protein association network was constructed for 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil to select key target proteins with strong interaction (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). The network contained 142 nodes and 2102 connections. ⟨
   <span class="italic">k</span>⟩ of the network was 29.61. Degree distribution was evaluated and listed in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. An uneven distribution was observed, as nodes with higher degree values accounted for a larger proportion, demonstrating that most target proteins of this essential oil were involved in common pathways.
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Pathway-based protein association network of 
      <span class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</span> var. 
      <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil. The network consisted of 142 nodes and 2102 connections. Nodes represent target proteins of selected ingredients in 
      <span class="italic">Osmanthus fragrans</span> var. 
      <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil. Connections indicate that two proteins are involved in common pathway. Numbers and names of the nodes are listed in Additional file 
      <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Statistics for the degree distribution of the pathway-based protein association network</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>
        <span class="italic">k</span>
       </th>
       <th>Frequency 
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </th>
       <th>Frequency% 
        <span class="sup">b</span>
       </th>
       <th>
        <span class="italic">k</span>
       </th>
       <th>Frequency</th>
       <th>Frequency%</th>
       <th>
        <span class="italic">k</span>
       </th>
       <th>Frequency</th>
       <th>Frequency%</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>58</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
       <td>24</td>
       <td>4</td>
       <td>2.82</td>
       <td>11</td>
       <td>9</td>
       <td>6.34</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>57</td>
       <td>10</td>
       <td>7.04</td>
       <td>23</td>
       <td>2</td>
       <td>1.41</td>
       <td>10</td>
       <td>12</td>
       <td>8.45</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>55</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
       <td>21</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
       <td>9</td>
       <td>2</td>
       <td>1.41</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>54</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
       <td>20</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
       <td>8</td>
       <td>4</td>
       <td>2.82</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>53</td>
       <td>15</td>
       <td>10.56</td>
       <td>19</td>
       <td>3</td>
       <td>2.11</td>
       <td>7</td>
       <td>5</td>
       <td>3.52</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>49</td>
       <td>24</td>
       <td>16.90</td>
       <td>17</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
       <td>4</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>48</td>
       <td>3</td>
       <td>2.11</td>
       <td>16</td>
       <td>2</td>
       <td>1.41</td>
       <td>3</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>42</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
       <td>15</td>
       <td>2</td>
       <td>1.41</td>
       <td>2</td>
       <td>5</td>
       <td>3.52</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>28</td>
       <td>13</td>
       <td>9.15</td>
       <td>14</td>
       <td>6</td>
       <td>4.23</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.70</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>27</td>
       <td>3</td>
       <td>2.11</td>
       <td>13</td>
       <td>2</td>
       <td>1.41</td>
       <td/>
       <td/>
       <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>26</td>
       <td>3</td>
       <td>2.11</td>
       <td>12</td>
       <td>3</td>
       <td>2.11</td>
       <td/>
       <td/>
       <td/>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>
      <span class="sup">a</span>Number of nodes with a specific degree value; 
      <span class="sup">b</span> Percentage of nodes with a specific degree value in all the nodes
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clustering coefficient (C) represents cohesiveness of neighborhood for a node, ranging from 0 to 1 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. As Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> shown, most nodes of the pathway-based protein association network exhibited high values of C. On the other hand, L of the network was only 2.59. Short average path length and relatively high clustering coefficient suggested that the pathway-based protein association network had small-world property. This property demonstrated that the network was consisted of many small, but highly connected modules which combined in a hierarchical manner, and exhibited as larger, less cohesive units [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>].
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Distribution of clustering coefficient of the pathway-based protein association network. N represents number of nodes with a specific value of clustering coefficient</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to comprehensively evaluate the importance of individual components, three centrality indices, 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">d</span>
   </sub>, 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">b</span>
   </sub> and 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">c</span>
   </sub> were calculated for nodes in the pathway-based protein association network. The top ten nodes with the highest scores of centrality indices were listed in Table 
   <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>. Subsequently, a three-dimensional diagram was drawn based on the centrality indices of all nodes (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>). Obviously, five nodes were outliers in the diagram, including KPCA, EGFR, PP2BA, MAPK1 and MAPK3. Centrality indices reflect the influence of a node on others through the network and how close a node is to others [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. Therefore, these nodes were considered as key proteins in the pathway-based protein association network.
   <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Top ten nodes with the highest values of centrality indices in the pathway-based protein association network</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>No. 
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </th>
       <th>Protein name 
        <span class="sup">b</span>
       </th>
       <th>C
        <sub>d</sub>
        <span class="sup">c</span>
       </th>
       <th>No.</th>
       <th>Protein name</th>
       <th>C
        <sub>b</sub>
        <span class="sup">d</span>
       </th>
       <th>No.</th>
       <th>Protein name</th>
       <th>C
        <sub>c</sub>
        <span class="sup">e</span>
       </th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>175</td>
       <td>EGFR</td>
       <td>0.411</td>
       <td>166</td>
       <td>PGH2</td>
       <td>0.177</td>
       <td>207</td>
       <td>KPCA</td>
       <td>0.500</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>149</td>
       <td>ADRB1</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>234</td>
       <td>PP2BA</td>
       <td>0.109</td>
       <td>126</td>
       <td>MK01</td>
       <td>0.496</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>156</td>
       <td>BKRB2</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>207</td>
       <td>KPCA</td>
       <td>0.093</td>
       <td>232</td>
       <td>MK03</td>
       <td>0.496</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>170</td>
       <td>DRD1</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>252</td>
       <td>HCD2</td>
       <td>0.082</td>
       <td>234</td>
       <td>PP2BA</td>
       <td>0.496</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>194</td>
       <td>ACM3</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>126</td>
       <td>MK01</td>
       <td>0.082</td>
       <td>175</td>
       <td>EGFR</td>
       <td>0.447</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>195</td>
       <td>ACM2</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>232</td>
       <td>MK03</td>
       <td>0.082</td>
       <td>149</td>
       <td>ADRB1</td>
       <td>0.445</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>197</td>
       <td>ACM5</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>175</td>
       <td>EGFR</td>
       <td>0.069</td>
       <td>156</td>
       <td>BKRB2</td>
       <td>0.445</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>198</td>
       <td>ACM1</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>282</td>
       <td>TYRO</td>
       <td>0.049</td>
       <td>170</td>
       <td>DRD1</td>
       <td>0.445</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>209</td>
       <td>5HT2C</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>192</td>
       <td>AOFA</td>
       <td>0.036</td>
       <td>194</td>
       <td>ACM3</td>
       <td>0.445</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>210</td>
       <td>5HT2A</td>
       <td>0.404</td>
       <td>261</td>
       <td>ADH1B</td>
       <td>0.027</td>
       <td>195</td>
       <td>ACM2</td>
       <td>0.445</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>
      <span class="sup">a</span>Number of nodes are listed in Additional file 
      <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>; 
      <span class="sup">b</span> Names of the target proteins are uniformed by Uniprot; 
      <span class="sup">c</span> C
      <sub>d</sub> represents values of degree centrality; 
      <span class="sup">d</span> C
      <sub>b</sub> represents values of betweenness centrality; 
      <span class="sup">e</span> C
      <sub>c</sub> represents values of closeness centrality
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Three-dimensional diagram illustrating centrality indices of nodes in the pathway-based protein association network</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">KPCA, also known as protein kinase C alpha type, is involved in several important processes such as cell proliferation, apoptosis, tumorigenesis, cardiac hypertrophy and angiogenesis. The expression levels of KPCA were reported to be closely related to esophageal carcinoma [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. EGFR is the abbreviation of epidermal growth factor receptor. Mutation in EGFR could induce non-small cell lung cancer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. PP2BA (serine/threonine-protein phosphatase 2B catalytic subunit alpha isoform) has a role in the calmodulin activation of calcineurin, and is considered to be associated with human neurodegenerative disease [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. These reports further supported the assumption that 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil had anti-tumor and neuroprotective effects.
  </p>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous network analysis has revealed that MAPK1 (mitogen-activated protein kinase 1) and MAPK3 (mitogen-activated protein kinase 3) were hub nodes of the ingredient-target-pathway network. Furthermore, they were also screened as key proteins of the pathway-based protein association network. Consistency of the results indicated that the two proteins were not only associated with most ingredients and pathways, but also closely related to other target proteins of the essential oil. These data provided further support for the potential anti-tumor effect of 
   <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
   <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
