<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The essential oil composition was determined by gas-chromatography coupled to mass-spectrometry, and the quantification of individual components was performed by GC-FID, calculating the relative peak average area of three separated injections. A Varian 3800 gas chromatograph (Varian, Palo Alto, CA, USA) was used, equipped with a Factor four VF-5ms column (poly-5% phenyl-95% dimethylsiloxane) of 30 m length, with an internal diameter of 0.25 mm and a film of 0.25 μm, directly coupled to a Varian 4000 mass spectrometer. The carrier gas was helium with a flow of 1 mL/min and a split ratio of 1:50. The analysis starts at 45 °C and reaches 100 °C at a rate of 1 °C per minute, then rises to a temperature of 250 °C at a speed of 5 °C, staying at that temperature for 15 min: the total analysis time was 90 min. The conditions of the mass spectrometer were: ionization energy: 70 eV; emission current: 10 μAmp, scan rate: 1 scan/s, mass range: 35–400 Da, trap temperature: 220 °C, transfer line temperature: 260 °C. The identification of compounds were performed by comparing their arithmetic indices (AI) and the MS fragmentation pattern with those of other known essential oils, with pure compounds and by matching the MS fragmentations patterns and arithmetic indices with mass spectra libraries and with those in the literature [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-01637" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-01637" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. The experimental arithmetic index of each component was determined adding a C
 <sub class="sub">8</sub>-C
 <sub class="sub">32</sub> n-alkanes mixture (Sigma-Aldrich Italy, Milano, Italy) to the essential oil before injection in the GC-MS equipment and analyzing it under the same conditions reported above [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-01637" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. For the quantitative analysis a ThermoQuest GC-Trace gas-chromatograph (ThermoQuest Italia, Rodano, Italy) equipped with a FID detector and the same column above described were used. The operating conditions for gas chromatograph were reported above. FID temperature was 250 °C. The oil percentage composition was performed by the normalization method from the GC peak areas, without using correction factors [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-01637" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] and was the average of three injections.
</p>
