<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">In the present study, the extract and essential oil of 
 <italic>C. cassia</italic> bark, and their major component, (
 <italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde, which were characterized by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry, and the (synthetic) pyrethroid, fenvalerate, were evaluated
 <italic> in vitro</italic> against unfed larvae and nymphs of 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>longicornis</italic>. The larvae and nymphs are important immature stages of 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>longicornis</italic> as they have been implicated as vectors of tick-borne pathogens, including 
 <italic>Rickettsia rickettsii</italic>, the agent of Rocky Mountain spotted fever [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Therefore, they are considered strategic targets in tick control programs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Furthermore, to elucidate their possible detoxification mechanisms, the effects of the essential oil and (
 <italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde [with low 50% lethal concentration (LC
 <sub>50</sub>) values in the
 <italic> in vitro</italic> test] on the biochemical parameters of larvae and nymphs of 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>longicornis</italic> were tested by targeting
 <italic> in vivo</italic> esterase and monooxygenase activity. In ticks, esterase and monooxygenase are common detoxification enzymes against xenobiotic compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Finally, to evaluate their environmental safety, the toxicological effects of the essential oil and (
 <italic>E</italic>)-cinnamaldehyde were evaluated on the following non-target terrestrial invertebrates: 
 <italic>Tenebrio molitor</italic> (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae), a beneficial insect of ecological and nutritional importance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]; and 
 <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic> (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae), a biocontrol agent of aphids, scales and other phytophagous pests [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].
</p>
