<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Microalgae are promising source of generous amount of metabolites with essential health benefits. Continual exploration for novel microalgae species along with isolation of its bioactive compounds are in great demand for diverse applications in various fields and industries as raw material, biomass or high-quality extracts. Despite of the excellent and superior benefits, there are several limitations that should be addressed as well. The significantly high incurring cost of the isolation might result in over-priced products, where it is believed this could be partly subsidised with utilisation of single solvent to generate high extract yield. In addition, it is essentially important to highlight that these are natural extracts with unique composition and varies subject to the season, cultivation condition, as well as the extraction method. Studies are also focusing on extraction of more than one product from a single biomass for a cost-efficient industry. On the other hand, the process of bringing a drug candidate to the market requires extensive pre-clinical testing and clinical trials to determine the safety and efficacy of the drug before it is approved by the FDA and is a very costly and time-consuming process. Hence, not all potential bioactive will eventually reach the market and consumers. Indeed, low yield of bioactive and strenuous and expensive purification steps have been regarded as the main challenge in producing economically viable drugs from microalgae. Therefore, to overcome these issues some of these active compounds are currently expressed in suitable vectors to ease purification and hence reduce the purification and production costs. Efforts on cost reduction by studying effect of different culturing conditions such as light intensity, nutrient availability and harvesting time on the metabolite yield and bioactivity as well as producing high-yield microalgae species via genetic modification approaches are currently pursued to accelerate the commercialization process of some of these bioactives. Meanwhile, advancements in biotechnology applications can help overcome some issues of poor oral bioavailability or instability in the gastrointestinal tract of some microalgae bioactives like peptides and fatty acids. This includes novel approaches using encapsulation technique and nano formulation to improve the solubility and bioavailability of some microalgae derived compounds for treatment of diseases. Furthermore, genetic engineering approaches expressing microalgae metabolites in natural organism for drug delivery have been explored. Nevertheless, more studies especially in in-vivo models and clinical trials are still needed to determine the safety and efficacy of these novel drugs prior to drug approval and commercialization.</p>
