<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A total of 64 herbal plants were documented in Malaysian Herbal Monograph 2015 (See Supplementary Material-
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplementary-material-1">Table A</xref>), which extensively describes their traditional uses and proven pharmacological activities. Such information is also available online in the Globinmed website (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.globinmed.com/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.globinmed.com/</ext-link>), created by Institute for Medical Research under Ministry of Health Malaysia. A bibliographic search was performed in the following databases: PubMed, ScienceDirect, and Scopus, to find any sepsis-related study on each of the 64 herbal plants listed in Malaysian Herbal Monograph 2015. The search terms used were (“scientific name of the plant” or “common name of the plant”) and (“sepsis” or “lipopolysaccharide” or “LPS”) without narrowing or limiting search items, and the last search was performed on 4 March 2020. All publications obtained from the databases with the searching criteria were studied. Herbal plants that have not been tested, either in the form of extracts or compounds isolated from the plants, in any sepsis-related study were excluded. 
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table"> Table 1</xref> summarizes seven Malaysian herbal plants that have been studied for antisepsis properties, evidenced by the therapeutic effect of the extracts or compounds extracted from these plants against sepsis-associated inflammatory responses or conditions in 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or/and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> experimental models. These mainly include LPS- and LPS-/IFN-
 <italic>γ</italic>-induced macrophages (
 <italic>in vitro</italic>) and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>-infected mice, LPS-induced endotoxemia, and CLP-induced polymicrobial sepsis (
 <italic>in vivo</italic>). Besides that, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies that used HMGB-1 or Transforming Growth Factor-Beta-Induced Protein (TGFBIp) as an inducer to induce endothelial barrier dysfunction were also included. This is because endothelial dysfunction plays an important role in the pathogenesis of sepsis leading to multiple organ failure [
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>], and thus, therapeutic agents that effectively inhibit endothelial barrier dysfunction may have beneficial effect in sepsis. It should be noted that active constituents which only demonstrated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> pharmacological effects and lack supporting 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies were not included in 
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> but were briefly discussed under their respective herbal plants below. The anti-inflammatory effects of these active constituents as evidenced by the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> findings alone are not sufficient to support their antisepsis potential.
</p>
