<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Fab1 protein identified in this work is highly conserved among different fungi (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1(a</xref>) 
 <bold>and Fig. S3B</bold>). Originally identified in yeast [
 <xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], this kinase can phosphorylate phosphatidylinositol-3-phosphate (PI-3-P) to phosphatidylinositol 3,5-bisphosphate (PtdIns-3,5-P
 <sub>2</sub>), which is closely linked to cellular stress responses [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. PtdIns-3,5-P
 <sub>2</sub> further regulates vacuole and cellular homeostasis [
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], with reduced levels of PtdIns-3,5-P
 <sub>2</sub> being associated with serious neurodegenerative diseases [
 <xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50–52</xref>]. Notably, this lipid kinase appears to be an increasingly attractive target for drug development, particularly in the fields of cancer and other proliferative diseases, and in suppressing inflammatory and immune responses [
 <xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. As such, Fab1 is necessary for regulating PtdIns-3,5-P
 <sub>2</sub> levels 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, potentially playing essential roles in a wide range of processes. In agreement with previous results [
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], we found that Fab1 localized to the vacuole membrane in 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic>, where it appeared to play a key regulatory role in this fungus. Given the importance of PtdIns(3,5)P
 <sub>2</sub>, loss of 
 <italic>fab1</italic> in 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic> led to significant defects in growth and development, as expected and observed in other organisms [
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54–58</xref>]. Interestingly, 
 <italic>fab1</italic> deletion results in altered cellular morphology without affecting the virulence of 
 <italic>Candia albicans</italic> [
 <xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In this study, we generated evidence that Fab1 was able to impact aflatoxin production, suggesting this gene to be associated with the regulation of 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic> virulence.
</p>
