<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chrysanthemum oil (CHEO) is an aromatic oily liquid extracted from chrysanthemum. A perennial herb, chrysanthemum belongs to the family Asteraceae, and may help avoid different ailments, such as coronary artery disease, hypertension, and arteriosclerosis. This oil has immunomodulatory, antibacterial, anti-inflammatory, and antifungal activities, according to previous research. Few studies have referred to CHEO’s antibacterial function and antibacterial process. Lin et al. prepared chitosan nanofiber (CSNF) with CHEO by electrospinning to eradicate 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, which causes severe deterioration in meat products [
 <xref rid="B278-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">278</xref>]. This oil destroyed the 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> cell membrane, creating the leakage of cellular substances, such as DNA, proteins, and ATP molecules. It also repressed the respiratory metabolism by suppressing the Embden–Meyerhof–Parnas pathway [
 <xref rid="B279-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">279</xref>], and harmed the activity of hexokinase, phosphofructokinase, and pyruvate kinase in 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>. The scanning electron microscope images showed the chitosan and its blends with CHEO nanofibers were continuous, smooth, and well-distributed [
 <xref rid="B280-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">280</xref>]. The inclusion of CHEO into nanofibers enhanced the thickness and moisture content, but decreased the water solubility because of CHEO’s hydrophobic nature. GC–MS analysis showed the release rate of CHEO from the nanofibers, and it was observed that CHEO was released slowly during 15 days of storage at all temperatures (4 °C, 12 °C, 25 °C). Subsequently, as the weather improved, the release rate also rose. The main reason behind the worsening quality of meat during storage was fat oxidation, resulting in a severe loss of flavor and nutritional value. Thiobarbituric acid-reactive substances are commonly used to measure lipid peroxidation products in cells, tissues, and body fluids. It was observed that thiobarbituric acid-reactive substance values of the treated beef samples were lower than untreated after 12 days at 4 °C [
 <xref rid="B281-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">281</xref>,
 <xref rid="B282-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">282</xref>]. The results indicated that CHEO/CSNF could minimize the rate of lipid oxidation and preserve freshness, thus prolonging the shelf-life of beef.
</p>
