<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The next campaign sought to further augment the activity of mononuclear cyclopalladated TSCs by introducing a lipophilic organosilane motif into the backbone TSC structure of the complexes in an attempt to increase their chances of crossing cellular membranes and potentially retain them in the active site of the targeted malaria parasite (DV) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f023">Figure 23</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B90-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. As previously discussed, the strategy of incorporating organosilane motifs into drug molecules is touted for enhancing their lipophilicity and imparting beneficial therapeutic properties such as enhanced tissue penetration and cell permeability. The dichlorobenzene motif and coordinating PTA moieties were retained (
 <bold>91a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>), and one- and three-carbon silyl linkers were appended to the terminal NH
 <sub>2</sub> group of the TSC backbone (
 <bold>92a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>). Two ferrocene-cyclopalladated representatives (
 <bold>93a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>) were included in the study by replacing the dichlorobenzene unit. Like in the previous studies, cyclopalladation greatly enhanced the inhibitory activity of the complexes by an average of ~31-fold relative to the uncoordinated ligands on the NF54 and Dd2 strains. Ferrocenyl complexes 
 <bold>93a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold> active between 1.07 and 1.52 μM were less potent than the dichlorobenzene derivatives, which exhibited activities mainly in the sub-micromolar range (0.29–0.88 μM) against both strains. Most noteworthy, these complexes showed a great improvement in activity compared with the variants devoid of the one- and two-carbon linkers on the terminal carbon from the previous study (
 <bold>88a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>), which were only active at 1.73–2.69 μM on the same parasites. To further illustrate the pharmacological significance of the organosilane moiety, when the authors compared the effectiveness of the silyl complexes (
 <bold>92a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>) to their carbon analogues (
 <bold>91a</bold>,
 <bold>b</bold>), the activity was found to be twice as good with preferential activity towards the resistant strain (Dd2). It is clear from these observations that the incorporation of the organosilane moiety is a practical approach to enhance the therapeutic efficacy of antiplasmodial agents, as also observed elsewhere in other studies.
</p>
