<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>Red imported fire ants are a notorious pest, impacting humans, livestock, pets and wildlife due to their venomous stings and causing billions of dollars in damages annually. Synthetic insecticides are a major tool used to control this pest. There is an ever-increasing public concern about the potential adverse effects of synthetic insecticides. Extensive effort has been made in searching for alternatives. In addition to biological control, physical and cultural practices, and semiochemicals, natural products continue to be one of the most attractive sources of alternatives. Naturally occurring compounds/materials have been successfully used as active ingredients in fire ant baits, contact-based control products, repellants and fumigants. In this article, we summarized the synthetic insecticides that are currently used in managing fire ants, available alternative products in the current USA market, and academic efforts in searching for fire ant natural toxins, repellants and fumigants.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>The invasive red imported fire ant, 
   <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic> Buren (hereafter, fire ants), is a significant threat to public health and a danger to livestock, pets and wildlife due to their venomous stings. The fire ant has invaded many countries and regions and has become a globally significant pest. The current major tool to manage fire ants are synthetic insecticides that are used largely as stomach poisons in bait products or contact insecticides in spray, broadcast, drench, and dust products for area and nest treatments. In addition to these insecticide products, repellants and fumigants can also be useful in some unique scenarios. The ever-increasing public concern about the potential adverse effects of synthetic insecticides on health and the environment has been a driving force for searching for safer alternatives to control fire ants. Tremendous effort has been made in developing biologically-based control for managing fire ants; however, natural products continue to be one of the most attractive sources of safe alternatives to synthetic insecticides. Here, we summarized the synthetic insecticides that are currently used in managing fire ants, available alternative products in the current market, and academic efforts in searching for fire ant natural toxins, repellants and fumigants.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
