<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The potential antagonistic behaviour of fluorescent pseudomonads isolated from soils of birch and Douglas-fir stands, and their potential linkage with tree species susceptible to 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> was investigated by DeLong et al. [
 <xref rid="B261-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>]. It was found that paper birch provides a more favourable environment for these bacteria than Douglas-fir, and fluorescent pseudomonads positively influence the susceptibility of the managed forest stands to 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> root disease. Several isolates of fluorescent bacteria significantly reduced the growth of 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic> in paper birch, Douglas-fir, and paper birch—Douglas-fir mixtures [
 <xref rid="B261-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>]. 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. along with 
 <italic>Bacillus</italic>, 
 <italic>Enterobacter</italic>, 
 <italic>Serratia</italic> spp. and 
 <italic>Rhizobium radiobacter</italic> (formerly 
 <italic>Agrobacterium radiobacter</italic>) were isolated from root-free soils of the boreal mixed wood forest of Ontario and found to be capable of inhibiting the linear growth of 
 <italic>A. solidipes</italic> in vitro [
 <xref rid="B262-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">262</xref>]. Only a few 
 <italic>P. fluorescens</italic> and 
 <italic>Bacillus</italic> isolates were able to prevent in vitro rhizomorph formation of 
 <italic>A. gallica</italic>, indicating their lower ability to suppress the spread of 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> spp. which produce rhizomorphs more consistently. Gram-negative bacteria, especially members of the genus 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> were observed in decaying fruiting bodies of 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic> and 
 <italic>Coprinus comatus</italic> during the period of their maximum development in forest biocenosis. Such bacterial communities may be promising for the targeted search for bacteria with biocontrol potential [
 <xref rid="B263-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">263</xref>]. Native biocontrol bacteria (
 <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus simplex</italic> and two strains of 
 <italic>Erwinia billingiae</italic>) were selected based on their high level of antagonism against the pathogens 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic> and 
 <italic>H. annosum</italic> in Monterey pine seedlings in vitro [
 <xref rid="B264-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">264</xref>]. These rhizobacterial strains reduced the pathogenic effects of 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic> and the presence of 
 <italic>H. annosum</italic>, exerting antibiotic effects on the fungi. Five isolates of rhizospheric actinobacteria belonging to the species 
 <italic>Streptomyces aurantiacogriseus</italic>, 
 <italic>S. setonensis</italic>, 
 <italic>S. kasugaensis</italic> and 
 <italic>S. jumonjinensis</italic> (two isolates), inhibited the rhizomorph production of 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> [
 <xref rid="B265-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">265</xref>]. Actinobacteria also show mutualistic interactions with mycorrhizal fungi along with their antagonism against fungal root pathogens [
 <xref rid="B266-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">266</xref>].
</p>
