<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3-5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Rheological properties</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Rheology and viscosity properties are easy to measure in the food industry and their results can be used to determine properties and behavior of suspensions, solutions and mixtures. Rheological properties of oils can be important in food formulation and also during processing.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">30</a>
  </span>
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>, shows the obtained results from triplicate measurements for shear stress and shear rates of the blended oils at 4°C and 25°C. At both temperatures, all three blended oils showed a linear relationship between the shear stress and shear rate, which meant that these oils have a typical Newtonian behavior. Therefore, the determination viscosity and regression coefficient (R
  <span class="sup">2</span>) was carried out using Newton’s law equation (Eq. 4).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div xlink:href="apb-8-107-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <div class="statement">
    <p> Relation between shear stress and shear rate of blended oils at 4 °C and 25°C.</p>
    <p> Treatments are olive, sesame and linseed oils in three ratios of 65:30:5; 60:30:10; and 55:30:15, respectively.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> The viscosity of the formulated oils remained generally constant at all shear rates within the 90% confidence interval (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>). Thus, this confirmed that these oils followed Newtonian behavior at speeds from 0-100 (1/s). Fresh vegetable oils, due to their long chain molecules, also show Newtonian flow behaviors.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">12</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div xlink:href="apb-8-107-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <div class="statement">
    <p> Relation between Viscosity and Shear Rate of blended oils at 4 °C and 25°C.</p>
    <p> For treatments see 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> As expected, the viscosity of the blended oils at 25°C was significantly lower (p&lt;0.05) than the viscosity measured at 4°C. Increasing the temperature could increase the average speed of the molecules and, because of increasing the frequency of their collisions; the viscosity decreases.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">31</a>
  </span> The viscosity at 4°C was about two- to three-fold the viscosity at 25°C; this is important as amount of energy needed for pumping the oils increased considerably and the level of their heat transfer also changed at different temperatures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Furthermore, it was observed that viscosity had significantly decreased (p&lt;0.05) with increasing linseed oil percent in the mixtures. This can be caused by the high unsaturated fatty acids, specifically, the linolenic acid present in the linseed oil.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"> Oils with a high level of double bonds in their fatty acid chains show lower viscosity levels because of their weak structures.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">32</a>
  </span> Double bonds, due to their space requirements do not allow molecules to be stacked close to each other. Therefore, oils with high amount of unsaturated oils cannot have a rigid and fixed structure and so behave in a more fluid-like way. Thus, there are some negative correlations between the fatty acid composition of some oils and their viscosity.
 </p>
</sec>
