<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">Lemon (
   <italic class="italic">Citrus limon</italic>) is a flowing plant belonging to the 
   <italic class="italic">Rutaceae</italic> family. 
   <italic class="italic">Citrus</italic> plants constitute one of the main valuable sources of essential oil used in foods and medicinal purposes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">In this study, we assessed chemical composition, antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of 
   <italic class="italic">C. limon</italic> essential oil (
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO) with its preservative effect against 
   <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> inoculated in minced beef meat. Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC-MS) was used to identify the major components of the obtained 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO. The antioxidant activities of this 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO were determined according to the β-carotene bleaching assay, as well as by 2.2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical scavenging activity. For antimicrobial activity, agar well diffusion method was used and the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) as well as the minimum fungicidal concentrations (MFCs) were determined. The in situ effect of the 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO was evaluated through physicochemical parameters (pH and thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS), as well as against 
   <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> in minced beef meat model.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">Twenty one components were identified in the 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO and the two dominant compounds were limonene (39.74%) and β-Pinene (25.44%). This 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO displayed an excellent DPPH scavenging ability with an extract concentration providing 50% inhibition (IC
   <sub class="sub">50</sub>) of 15.056 μg/ml and a strong β-carotene bleaching inhibition after 120 min of incubation with an IC
   <sub class="sub">50</sub> of 40.147 μg/ml. The MICs varied from 0.039 to 1.25 mg/ml for Gram positive bacteria and from 0.25 to 2.5 mg/ml for Gram-negative bacteria. The meat preserving potential of 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO was investigated against 
   <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO successfully inhibited development of 
   <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic> in minced beef meat. The application of 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO at a 0.06 and 0.312 mg/g, may open new promising opportunities for the prevention of contamination from and growth of pathogenic bacteria, particularly 
   <italic class="italic">L. monocytogenes</italic>, during minced beef meat storage at 4 °C. Additionally, during storage period, physicochemical values (pH and TBARS) were higher in control meat than treated meat with 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO suggesting an efficient antioxidant activity of 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">It was suggested that the 
   <italic class="italic">Cl</italic>EO may be a new potential source as natural antimicrobial and antioxidant agents applied in food systems and pharmaceutical industry.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
