<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">EOs have largely been employed for their antibacterial, antifungal and insecticidal activities. At present, approximately 3000 EOs are known, 300 of which are commercially important especially for the pharmaceutical, agronomic, food, sanitary, cosmetic and perfume industries. In our study, five medicinal plant EOs were tested for their antibacterial activities using disc diffusion, MIC and MBC methods. Activity against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> isolates was observed only in cases of 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">R. officinalis</italic>, while 
 <italic class="italic">J. communis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Z. officinale</italic> did not show any effects. Of the three oils, 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> showed the highest antibacterial effect on 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> isolates, followed by 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic>. The lowest antibacterial effect was observed with 
 <italic class="italic">R. officinalis</italic> EO. Based on biochemical specificity, the highest antibacterial activity of 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> is due to linalool (39.7%). This alcohol has significant bactericidal and bacteriostatic effects. This finding is in accordance with the report of Pattnaik et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] who demonstrated that linalool has a strong effect against a number of different bacteria and fungi. In addition, other major compounds such as Terpinen-4-ol (11.7%), β-Myrcene (8.6%) and γ-Terpinene (7.6%) increased the antibacterial activity of 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> and may explain the effect of 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic> since these three major compounds exist in both oils. Principally, the antibacterial activity of 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic> could be related to its high content (25.9%) of the monoterpene alcohol, terpinene-4-ol [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. The highest antibacterial effect of 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> compared to 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic> can be explained by the high presence of linalool. Further, the antibacterial property of 
 <italic class="italic">R. officinalis</italic> can be attributed to the presence of 1,8-cineole (47.7%) and camphor (9.6%) [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>], in addition to α-Pinene (11.7%) and β-Pinene (6.3%). It has been shown that 1, 8-cineole produce alterations on the structure of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. enteritidis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. The chemical structure of EOs components affects their precise mode of action and antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B35-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. According to Faleiro et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>] activity of 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic> is owed to the formation of antibacterial substances from their precursors. The precursors of carvacrol and thymol are p-cymene and α-terpinene. Generally, Gram-negative bacteria are known to be less susceptible to EOs due to the presence of lipopolysaccharide in their cell wall [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. However, in this work, 
 <italic class="italic">O. majorana</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">T. zygis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">R. officinalis</italic> EOs demonstrated a very important antibacterial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> UTIs. 
 <italic class="italic">J. communis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Z. officinale</italic> did not show any effect against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> isolates, in accordance with the reports of Sivasothy et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] and Pepeljnjak et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-01161" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], who demonstrated that 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> is the most resistant strain to 
 <italic class="italic">J. communis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Z. officinale</italic> EOs among many Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria.
</p>
