<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In physiological terms, omega 3 PUFAs, especially those which are most relevant in biological terms, i.e., the long-chain PUFAs eicosapentaenoic (EPA) and docosahexaenoic (DHA), have become analogous to micronutrients (intakes of few hundreds mg/day in most populations out of approximately 100 g/day of total fat). Irrefutable evidence shows that an adequate dietary intake of omega 3 from plant foods (linseed, canola, and soybean oils and walnuts), namely alpha-linolenic acid (ALA; 18:3ω3), and from fish (EPA and DHA, respectively) is associated with a significant reduction of coronary risk and sudden death [
 <xref rid="B82-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], especially in the elderly [
 <xref rid="B84-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Dimensionally, data from 17 prospective cohort studies examining the association of dietary EPA and DHA with the risk of various coronary outcomes indicate an 18% risk reduction for any CVD event for those with higher dietary intake of EPA + DHA compared to those with lower intake [
 <xref rid="B85-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Significant reductions of 23%, 19%, and 47% in the risk for fatal coronary events, coronary death, and sudden cardiac death, respectively, were also computed [
 <xref rid="B85-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. These protective actions, which come from observational studies and are mostly associated with fish consumption rather than supplement use, are mechanistically explained by the favorable effects of EPA and DHA on triglyceridemia, on platelet function, blood pressure, and on the lower production of adhesion and proinflammatory proteins by the arterial wall [
 <xref rid="B82-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], in addition to direct antiarrhythmic and antioxidant effects [
 <xref rid="B82-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. The first RCT that investigated the pharmacological use of omega 3 was the GISSI-Prevenzione, in which capsules of omega 3 ethyl esters concentrates (at a dose of 850 mg/day) vs. placebo were administered to subjects with a clinical history of a coronary event. This trial clinically confirmed the cardioprotective effects of EPA and DHA [
 <xref rid="B88-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. The subsequent JELIS RCT studied the use of EPA (1.8 g/d as an ethylester) alone in Japanese patients treated with statins and reported a 19% lower incidence of reinfarction compared with the statin alone group. After these studies, however, no further significant evidence emerged, from controlled trials, in favor of treatment with omega 3 in secondary prevention, with the exception of the REDUCE-IT trial, where 4 g/d of icosapent ethyl significantly reduced cardiovascular events in hypertriglyceridemic, statin-treated patients. In terms of lipid profile, there was a significant reduction in triglycerides (a decrease of 0.5 mmol/L; 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and LDL-cholesterol (a decrease of 0.13 mmol/L; 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Of note, the numbers needed to treat computed from the Bhatt et al. study is 70 [
 <xref rid="B90-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Consequently, on November 14, 2019, the USA Food and Drug Administration approved the use of icosapent ethyl (registered trademark: Vascepa
 <sup>®</sup>) as an adjunct to statin therapy in patients with elevated triglyceride levels.
</p>
