<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is important to underline that the largely negative outcomes of the most recent, i.e., since 2007, trials should not undermine the recommendation to regularly consume fish or plant sources of ALA [
 <xref rid="B108-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Several reasons may, in fact, explain the lack of effect reported by the most recent trials of supplementary fish oil [
 <xref rid="B110-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>], notably: (a) as opposed to the early trials, such as the GISSI-Prevenzione, cardiopathic patients currently receive highly effective multi-drug pharmacological treatments; the effect of adding omega 3 fatty acids “on top” of these treatments is likely very small; (b) the fatty acid profiles of RCT patients have been almost never evaluated: some subjects could benefit more than others from treatment with omega 3 (for example, those with low basal blood levels of these fatty acids) [
 <xref rid="B103-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. From a mere pharmacological viewpoint, this is surprising because, for instance, the Omega 3 Index (%EPA and DHA in erythrocytes, measured with a standardized methodology) is a risk predictor for cardiovascular mortality (CVD). Namely, CVD is 30% lower with an omega 3 index &gt;8% as compared with an omega 3 index of &lt;4% [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. As recently reported by Bittner et al. [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>], a low Omega 3 Index is associated with early-onset coronary atherosclerosis. Ten cohort studies identified a 15% reduction in risk of fatal CHD for each one standard deviation increase in omega 3 index [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. In many trials, omega 3 capsules might have been given to people who did not necessarily need them, and too low of a dose might have administered to people with a very low Omega 3 Index. This resembles running hypertension trials without measuring blood pressure or hyperlipidemia trials without measuring LDL [
 <xref rid="B114-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]; (3) the bioavailability of omega 3 fatty acids administered as ethylesters, as opposed to, e.g., triacylglycerols and phospholipids from fish, is questionable. As reviewed by Schuchardt and Hahn [
 <xref rid="B115-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>], bioavailability heavily depends on the concomitant intake of fat and/or adequate volume of foods, has high inter-individual variability, and so forth. Examples of good bioavailability include omega 3 fatty acids formulated into milk products [
 <xref rid="B116-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>], when eaten with salmon vs. capsules [
 <xref rid="B117-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>], or when administered as krill oil [
 <xref rid="B119-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]—none used in the trials meta-analyzed. Another often overlooked and controversial [
 <xref rid="B120-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>] issue is that fish oil is, by its own nature and be it from diet [
 <xref rid="B121-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>] or supplements [
 <xref rid="B122-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>], prone to oxidation [
 <xref rid="B124-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Physicians should advise patients to store their medications/supplements in the dark and even freeze fish oil capsules to avoid the formation of noxious [
 <xref rid="B125-nutrients-12-03782" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>] peroxides.
</p>
