<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the purpose of pre-clinical studies on animal models, 
 <italic>Primula veris</italic> L. solid herbal extract (PVSHE) effect on myocontractile function was studied [
 <xref rid="B128-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. The extract composition of phenolic compounds was investigated by purifying the compounds using column chromatography. The differential UV spectrophotometry showed the total flavonoids concentration. The obtained compounds were then characterized by NMR. An experiment on adult Wister rats was performed in which they were divided into control group, intact group, and experimental group. They were fed with herbal extract of 
 <italic>Primula veris</italic> L. and second experimental group was administered with comparative drug. Cardiodynamic changes were determined using surgical procedures, while myocardial contraction rate was determined computationally. Enzyme linked immune-sorption assay (ELISA) was used for determination of CHF markers. Polymethoxylated flavonoids acted as Primula L. biological markers. The extract was further processed to obtain polymethoxylated flavonoids, flavonoid aglycons and its glycosides along with its constituents. The presence of flavonoids is the most likely reason for decreased ROS production and suppressed peroxide formation, which lead to its cardio-protective effect. A lower number of animal deaths, low CHF markers, and a higher rate of myocardial contraction and relaxation were evident in the results [
 <xref rid="B128-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Several flavonoids have been characterized through NMR spectroscopy. For example, saturation transfer difference (STD)-NMR showed the binding of luteolin and its glycosylated form to the ATP binding domain of multidrug resistant transporter [
 <xref rid="B129-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. Thus, these flavonoids have anticancer properties. The antioxidant properties of flavonoids can be accessed through 
 <sup>13</sup>C-NMR and QSAR methods [
 <xref rid="B130-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B131-molecules-25-05243" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>].
</p>
