<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the most characteristic components of cajuput EO is 1,8-cineole (eucalyptol), which has a camphor-medical smell. Its content varies from 15–60% [
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-24-02130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. In addition to eucalyptol, the cajuput EO also contains terpenes, such as γ-terpinene, limonene, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, terpinolene, α-pinene, β-pinene, β-caryophyllene, α-humulene, aromadendren, α-selinene, and β-selinene. Moreover, the cajuput EO also contains terpenoids, such as α-terpineol, linalool, terpinen-4-ol, cajeputol, spathulenol, globulol, viridiflorol, and cariophilene oxide. Nevertheless, the main constituents of cajuput EO differ according to the origin of the EO. In Indonesia, EO extracted from 
 <italic class="italic">M. cajuputi</italic> subsp. 
 <italic class="italic">cajuputi</italic> is characterized by a high content of 1,8-cineneol. In Papua New Guinea, there are two chemotypes, 
 <italic class="italic">M. cajuputi</italic> subsp. 
 <italic class="italic">platyphylla</italic>, which differ in composition. Chemotype I contains significant amounts (2-80%) of 1-acetyl-4-methoxy-3,5,5-trimethylcyclohex-3-en-2,5-dione, while the main components of chemotype II are α-pinene, 1.8 -cineole, γ-terpinene, β-cymene, and β-caryophyllene. Furthermore, cajuput EO from Cuba contains mainly viridiflorol (28.2%) and 1.8-cineole (21.3%). In turn, the EO from South India contains (
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-nerolidol (76.58–90.85%), β-caryophyllene (1.52–4.49%), viridiflorol (0.19–2.79%), (
 <italic class="italic">E</italic>)-β-farnesene (≤0.10–2.67%), and α-humulene (0.22–1.03%) [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-24-02130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>], while cajuput EO from North India contains 1.8-cineole (19.9%), β-eudesmol (15.8%), α-eudesmol (11.3%), viridifloral (8.9%), and guaiol (9.0%) [
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-24-02130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>].
</p>
