<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, this approach needs to overcome certain challenges. First, there is an ongoing search for highly productive endophytic fungi for desired plant-derived compounds followed by their strain improvement through epigenetic modulations, mutations, and genetic engineering to make them suitable for industrial applications. Furthermore, we need to elucidate the complete biosynthesis route including all the enzymes and related genes involved through ‘omics’—genomics, transcriptomics, proteomics, and metabolomics—to regulate and manipulate the biosynthesis process for improved productivity [
 <xref rid="B405-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">405</xref>,
 <xref rid="B406-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">406</xref>,
 <xref rid="B407-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">407</xref>]. Alternatively, the identified biosynthetic pathway of the bioactive compounds can be assembled and mimicked in convenient systems, offering an approach to produce target compounds with ease. Second, we need to know more about the roles of host plant–endophyte interactions, requirements of plant niche, and identities of specific signals/elicitors in the synthesis and induction of host-derived natural compounds by endophytes under the OSMAC strategy to overcome the problem of low yield and attenuation, the major challenges for commercial success of this novel approach [
 <xref rid="B406-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">406</xref>,
 <xref rid="B408-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">408</xref>,
 <xref rid="B409-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">409</xref>,
 <xref rid="B410-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">410</xref>]. The reasons for the attenuation of products have been attributed to the lack of apparent signals/molecules arising from host–endophyte and/or endophyte–peer endophytes interactions in axenic monocultures, resulting in the switching off of genes [
 <xref rid="B86-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. However, characterization of the specific nature of assumed activator signals/molecules remains to be done. Third, this area needs collaborations between scientists working in this area and in the pharmaceutical industry for the successful industrial scale production of pharmaceutically valuable compound/leads [
 <xref rid="B411-microorganisms-09-00197" ref-type="bibr">411</xref>]. The pharmaceutical industry must prioritize their endeavors toward the endophyte-dependent biosynthesis of plant-derived natural compounds.
</p>
