<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, egg production was recorded daily; however, feed consumption and egg weight [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] were recorded weekly. Moreover, feed efficiency was calculated by dividing the total feed intake by total egg mass during each period. The feed conversion ratio (FCR) [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] was expressed as kilograms of feed consumed per kilogram of egg produced. Six eggs (per replicate) were randomly selected to determine the traits related to the characteristics of quail eggs at 0, 2, 4, 6, and 8 weeks. Egg length and width were measured with a 0.01 mm digital caliper (Mitutoyo). For Haugh unit measurements six eggs were weighed and then cracked separately. Albumen heights of three near yolk areas were measured with a 0.01 mm digital caliper. The Haugh unit [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] was calculated using egg weight and albumen height data of each 6 egg. Furthermore, the yolk height and width were measured by 0.01 mm digital caliper. For calculation of yolk to albumen ratio as well as yolk and albumen percentages, yolk and albumen were carefully separated from each other and subsequently weighed by 0.001 g digital scale (A&amp;D N92) [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. For color measurements using Roche color fan, eggs were individually broken onto a flat surface and then color was recorded [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Egg shell thickness was measured using a 0.01 mm micrometer at three different points. Average of three points was considered as final thickness of each eggshell. The eggshell percentages were calculated using washed and dried eggshell weights [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. For pH analysis, yolk and albumen were completely mixed with a glass rod prior to measurement separately (pH meter; Hanna 211, Woonsocket, RI, USA) [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-18-02995" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
