<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lachenmeier et al. [
 <xref rid="B61-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] reported that long-term administration of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> leads to some neurotoxic effect due to the presence of thujone and its analogues. Additionally, McGuffin et al. [
 <xref rid="B155-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>] observed that long-duration use of the essential oil obtained from 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> may cause toxicity absinthism-mental disorder in humans with clinical manifestations which include convulsions, sleeplessness, and hallucinations. The adverse side effects may include stomach cramps, brain injury cramps, vertigo, vomiting, nausea, insomnia, restlessness, urine retention, seizures, and tremors [
 <xref rid="B156-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Many toxicity studies were performed with thujone on experimental animals and revealed that it leads to dose-dependent toxic action [
 <xref rid="B61-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The no-effect level (NOEL) has been reported to be in the range between 5 and 12.5 mg/kg body weight/day. Additionally, Juteau et al. [
 <xref rid="B96-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>] indicated that the essential oil obtained from 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> contains high concentrations of thujyl alcohol, thujone, and other terpene-derivatives, which causes neurotoxicity at high concentrations. Thujone is an antagonist of Gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA
 <sub>A</sub>) receptor that displays an epileptic-like convulsion by rapidly regulating the GABA-gated chloride channel [
 <xref rid="B157-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Intraperitoneal injection of thujone causes convulsion in mice and the action was blocked by intraperitoneal injection of diazepam or phenobarbital [
 <xref rid="B143-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Additionally, Rivera et al. [
 <xref rid="B158-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>] demonstrated a remarkable inhibition of the GABA
 <sub>A</sub> receptor recruitment caused by acute stress after intracerebroventricular injection of α-thujone, and this may be because of α-thujone being acted to block the benzodiazepine binding site or other sites of GABA
 <sub>A</sub>. However, the formation of GABA
 <sub>A</sub> receptors is a potential substrate to α-thujone than to other constitutive receptors. β-Thujone derivative (diastereoisomer α-thujone) also displays behavioral action [
 <xref rid="B1-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Consistently, long-term treatment with high doses of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> leads to mild chromosome aberration [
 <xref rid="B159-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> essential oil is avoided in pregnant females, breastfeeding mothers, and individuals with hyperacidity, peptic ulcer patients, and individuals with allergy. Additionally, high dose administration of the plant can cause central nervous system disorders, intestinal cramps, vomiting, dizziness, and headaches. 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> stimulates the remarkable blockage of acetylcholinesterase activity. Thus, this may be the main cause of chronic diarrhea in some situations because of increased acetylcholine concentration required to stimulate muscarinic receptors in the duodenum [
 <xref rid="B160-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antibiotics-09-00353-f003">Figure 3</xref> represented the side effects of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> and its related compounds.
</p>
