<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">The ability to tune and enhance the properties of photoluminescent materials (phosphors) by changing the emission wavelengths, intensity, band-shape, emission quantum yields and excited states lifetime is essential for optimizing the performance of devices and understanding the luminescence mechanisms. A common type of highly efficient luminescent phosphors are rare-earth (RE) doped oxides, such as Eu
 <sup class="sup">3+</sup>:Y
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, Nd
 <sup class="sup">3+</sup>:Y
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>Al
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">12</sub> and Er
 <sup class="sup">3+</sup>:glass
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. For a given host structure, the photoluminescence (PL) and, in particular the color and brightness of the emitted light, can be tailored by changing the nature and the concentration of the RE ion as well as introducing a co-dopant as sensitizer. The incorporation of the same RE in different hosts also produces modifications of PL properties due to the variation of the crystal symmetry and crystal field around the active ion. More recently, efforts have been focused on the active, 
 <italic class="italic">in-situ</italic> control of the emission of luminescent materials as this would represent a real breakthrough in the phosphor technology. Real-time modulation of PL can be realized by altering the local symmetry and the energy levels by the application of an external physical stimulus or field. The strong coupling existing in ferroelectrics between the lattice strain and external variables, such as electric field and mechanical stress, offers a unique opportunity to modify the crystal field around the active ions thus realizing an effective real-time PL tuning, as demonstrated in some recent papers for RE-doped ABO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> ferroelectric perovskites and LiNbO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Although possible correlations between the PL response and parameters such as the remnant polarization and the poling field have been proposed and the occurrence of a field-induced phase transition has been claimed to play an important role
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>, the detailed mechanisms which control the luminescence in ferroelectric materials are not fully understood yet.
</p>
