<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Material and Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiments were performed at the Phytopathology Laboratory of the Gurupi Campus, Federal University of Tocantins (UFT), in the state of Tocantins, Brazil. 
  <span class="italic">C. lunata</span> was initially isolated from the maize leaves derived from the experimental field of UFT with the diseases’ symptoms, and put in a PDA (Potato, Dextrose, Agar) culture environment. 
 </p>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Essential Oil Attainment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the extraction of the oil of 
   <span class="italic">C. citratus</span> (DC.) Stapf, de Candolle and reclassified by Otto Stapf, the hydrodistillation method was used, utilizing the Clevenger device modified in accordance with the methodology described by [
   <a rid="B11-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-medicines-04-00062">11</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Pathogenicity of the Isolates of Curvularia Lunata to Maize Plants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pathogenicity of the fungus 
   <span class="italic">C. lunata</span> was verified through inoculation tests in maize plants. Initially, the seeds of the Traktor (Syngenta
   <span class="sup">®</span>) maize were sowed in seven polyethylene vases (3 L capacity) containing substrate, improved with 10 g of commercial fertilizer NPK (5-25-15) in each vase. There were made three holes, with two seeds added in each. The pruning was necessary when the plants reached two pairs of definitive leaves, which was in approximately 15 days, and then the inoculation could be initiated. There was utilized an entirely casualized design with seven treatments and three repetitions. There were different tested concentrations of conidia, being 10
   <span class="sup">1</span>, 10
   <span class="sup">2</span>, 10
   <span class="sup">3</span>, 10
   <span class="sup">4</span>, 10
   <span class="sup">5</span>, and 10
   <span class="sup">6</span> conidia mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, the concentrations were adjusted with the aid of a Neubauer chamber. The positive control prepared utilized only distilled water with the same volume utilized for the concentrations of the conidia. For the inoculation there was utilized a manual sprayer (500 mL capacity) containing suspension of conidia of 
   <span class="italic">C. lunata</span> derived from cultures incubated for 10 days in BOD (Biochemical Oxygen Demand) at 25 °C. The suspensions were applied until the runoff point on the leaves (10 mL). Following this, the vases were kept for 48 h with humid cotton and closed with plastic bags aiming at providing the humid chamber. From 48 h after the inoculation, the vases were left in a shaded place until the appearance of the first leaf symptoms of the 
   <span class="italic">Curvularia</span> Leaf Spot. When the symptoms were visualized on the inoculated tissue, the fungus was re-isolated and cultivated in PDA environment. Afterwards, the fungus was inoculated again and re-isolated in the PDA environment, aiming at the compliance of all the stages of the Koch’s postulates.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Preparation of the Solutions for Biological Activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the preparation of the essential oil solutions sterilized small glass jars with lids were utilized in order to receive the different concentrations. One supply solution was prepared for the higher concentration utilizing a volumetric flask of 10 mL. On sequence, there was added initially the oil and adjusted the concentration of 50 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> to a volume of 10 mL, next there was added Tween 80 (1 oil: 1 Tween). In laminar flow chamber, the flask was softly agitated and next was inserted the distilled water. After the agitation, there was obtained a homogeneous mixture. Subsequently, there were realized the other dilutions until the concentrations of 2.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 7.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> were obtained. As negative and positive control there were prepared the solutions of methyl-thiophanate (2 mg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) and sterilized distilled water, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Phytoxicity of the Essential Oil (Cymbopogon citratus) to Maize Plants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The phytoxicity test was realized in greenhouse conditions. There were utilized six polyethylene vases filled with half commercial substrate and half soil. There was added 10 g of fertilizer NPK (5-25-15) in each vase. On the maize plantation there were utilized Traktor (Syngenta
   <span class="sup">®</span>) seeds, sowing two for each hole. After sowing, the vases were irrigated daily until the seedlings growth reached four definitive leaves, or 15 days after plantation. Manual sprayers were used for the application of the treatments. There was utilized an entirely casualized design with six treatments and three repetitions, where different concentrations of the 
   <span class="italic">C. citratus</span> oil were tested, being: 2.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 7.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 10 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 50 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The positive control was prepared utilizing only distilled water with the same volume utilized for the concentrations of the oil. Each vase was pulverized with 5 mL of the solutions. The evaluation was made according to the phytotoxicity scale adapted from [
   <a rid="B12-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-medicines-04-00062">12</a>] until the tenth day.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. In Vitro Inhibiton of Curvularia lunata</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aiming at verifying the effect of essential oil upon the mycelial growth of the phytopatogen, there was different concentrations of 
   <span class="italic">C. citratus</span> oil were tested, being: 2.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 7.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 10 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> and 50 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. As negative and positive control there were prepared the solutions of methyl-thiophanate (2 mg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) (one for 
   <span class="italic">C. lunata</span> and the other for 
   <span class="italic">Fusarium</span> sp.) and sterilized distilled water, respectively. There was tested another pathogen in order to verify the efficiency of the proposed fungicide. There was utilized 100 µL from each concentration, distributed on the surface of the culture environment with the aid of a Drigalski spatula. Next, a mycelium-agar disk with 6 mm diameter was put into the center of the plates. The plates were sealed with PVC (Polyvinyl chloride) film, identified and incubated in BOD at 25 °C for 10 days. The evaluations were realized with digital caliper assessing the mycelial diameter of the fungus tracing two orthogonal axes with each other upon the center of the plates resulting in a arithmetic mean and measured every two days (2, 4, 6, 8 and 10 days). 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot6-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Inhibitory Effect to the Germination of Conidia of Curvularia lunata</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the evaluation of the inhibition effect of the 
   <span class="italic">C. citratus</span> essential oil upon the germination of conidia there was used an entirely casualized design, with seven treatments and three repetitions. The treatments were constituted by the following oil concentrations: 0.625; 1.25; 2.5; 5.0, and 7.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, negative control, with methyl-thiophanate (2 mg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) and positive control with distilled/sterilized water. From each oil treatment, there was mixed 100 µL of the oil concentrations and 100 µL of the 
   <span class="italic">C. lunata</span> conidia concentration (10
   <span class="sup">4</span> conidia mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>). The evaluation was made 12 h after the inoculation in optical microscope.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The plates containing the oil solutions were incubated on a humid chamber (trays) at 27 °C for 12 h. After this period the evaluation was made with approximately 200 conidia where they were counted, and the percentage of germination of conidia of inhibition were calculated, adapted from [
   <a rid="B13-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-medicines-04-00062">13</a>,
   <a rid="B14-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-medicines-04-00062">14</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot7-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Chromatographic Analyses of the Essential Oil of Lemongrass</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The qualitative and quantitative analyses of the essential oils were realized by chromatography in gas phase, attached to the mass spectrometry CG-MS. The chromatograph utilized was the model Shimadzu GC-210, equipped with mass selective detector model QP2010 Plus, and was operated in these conditions: capillary column of fused silica TRX-5MS (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm of film thickness); with the following programming of the temperature on the column: 60–240 °C (3 °C min
   <span class="sup">−1</span>); injector temperature: 220 °C; carrier gas helium; and, splitless injection with injected volume of 1 μL of a solution 1:1000 in hexane. For the mass spectrometer (MS), there were utilized the following conditions: impact energy of 70 eV; ion source, and interface temperature: 200 °C. There was injected, at the sample conditions, a homologous series of n-alkanes (C
   <sub>9</sub>H
   <sub>20</sub>… C
   <sub>26</sub>H
   <sub>54</sub>). The obtained specters were compared with the Nist and Wiley 229 Library’s database and the retention rate calculated to each component was compared to the tabulated, according to [
   <a rid="B15-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-medicines-04-00062">15</a>]. The quantification of essential oils compounds levels were obtained with a gas chromatograph equipped with a flame ionization detector (FIT) using a Shimadzu GC-210 device, in the following methodology: capillary column RTX-5MS (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm of film thickness); injector temperature: 220 °C; FIT temperature: 300 °C; with column programming: initial temperature of 60 °C with a heating rate of 3 °C min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> until 240 °C, next, passing to a heating rate of 10 °C min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> until 300 °C, remaining on this temperature for 10 min; drag gas nitrogen (1.18 mL min
   <span class="sup">−1</span>); split rate 1:50; column pressure of 115 KPa, and injected volume of 1 μL in hexane.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot8-medicines-04-00062" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.8. Curative and Preventive Control of Curvularia Leaf Spot on Maize</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There were used plates containing inoculum of seven days of incubation where were added 10 mL of sterilized distilled water for the preparation of the conidia solutions. Utilizing a soft brush, there was realized the detachment of the conidia. This solution was filtered in gauze, and the conidia were counted in the Neubauer chamber. The concentration of 10
   <span class="sup">4</span> conidia mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> was utilized for the biological activities. Following, the vases were kept for 48 h with humid cotton and closed with a plastic bag in order to provide a humid chamber. 48 h after the inoculation, the vases were left in shaded place until the appearance of the first leaf symptoms of 
   <span class="italic">Curvularia</span> Leaf Spot. For the evaluation of the severity of the diseases, there was used a notes scale according to [
   <a rid="B16-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-medicines-04-00062">16</a>], where 0 = healthy plant; 1 = less than 1% of leaf area sick; 3 = 1 to 5% of the leaf area sick; 5 = 6 to 25% of the leaf area sick; 7 = 26 to 50% of the leaf area sick; and, 9 = more than 50% of the leaf area sick.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the preventive effect of the essential oil, an entirely casualized design was used, where different concentrations of the 
   <span class="italic">C. citratus</span> oil were tested, being: 0.625; 1.25; 2.5; 5.0; and 7.5 mg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, and three repetitions. As control, there were utilized water-pulverized plants (positive control) and methyl-thiophanate-pulverized plants at 2 mg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> (negative control). From each treatment, 5 mL was sprayed on the plants and one hour after, the plants were inoculated with 5 mL of the conidia solution (10
   <span class="sup">4</span> conidia mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) of 
   <span class="italic">C. lunata</span>. The evaluation of the severity of the disease was made every two days after inoculation (5 evaluations on total).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For evaluating the curative effect of the essential oil, an entirely casualized design was used, where different concentrations of the 
   <span class="italic">C. citratus</span> oil were tested, being: 0.625; 1.25; 2.5; 5.0; and 7.5 µL mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, and three repetitions. As a control, there were utilized water-pulverized plants (positive control) and methyl-thiophanate-pulverized plants at 2 mg mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span> (negative control). The maize plants were inoculated with 5 mL of the conidia solution (10
   <span class="sup">4</span> conidia mL
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) of 
   <span class="italic">C. lunata</span>, and next the vases were kept for 48 h with humid cotton and closed with plastic bag in order to provide a humid chamber. 48 h after the inoculation, the plants were left in shaded place until the appearance of the first leaf symptoms of 
   <span class="italic">Curvularia</span> Leaf Spot. From each treatment, 5 mL of the already cited oil concentrations was sprayed on the plants after verification of the appearance of the disease, and the evaluation of severity of the disease was made every two days, being realized a total of five evaluations after the application of the oil solutions. With the obtained results in the evaluations, the Area Under Disease Progress Curve (AUDPC) was calculated, according to [
   <a rid="B17-medicines-04-00062" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-medicines-04-00062">17</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
