<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The invasion of 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic> has a number of negative effects [
 <xref rid="B3-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. It is a human nuisance when it aggregates in buildings in autumn and can taint wine when harvested and crushed with grapes. However, most concern so far has been caused by its impact on biodiversity. Due to its predatory and competitive abilities, 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic> may affect many native species, including non-pest aphids and aphidophagous insects. In particular, native ladybirds may suffer from competition for resources and intra-guild predation (IGP) on larvae and eggs ([
 <xref rid="B3-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and references therein). In North America, several studies showed that 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic> has displaced native ladybirds [
 <xref rid="B6-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Similar observations were made in Chile, where it is also invasive [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In Europe, first analyses made a few years after the establishment of 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic> in UK, Belgium and Switzerland suggested that several native ladybird species had started declining [
 <xref rid="B10-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In a risk assessment based on the likelihood that the assessed native species encounters 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic> in the field, the hazard of competition for food, and the IGP hazard, Kenis et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] stated that four European species were particularly at risk, i.e., 
 <italic>Adalia bipunctata</italic> (L.)
 <italic>, Adalia decempunctata</italic> (L.)
 <italic>, Oenopia conglobata</italic> (L.) and 
 <italic>Calvia decemguttata</italic> (L.). These are species that, as 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic>, are found mainly on deciduous trees, are primarily aphidophagous and have immature stages which are highly vulnerable to IGP by 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic>. These studies and others emphasized the need for further field assessments of native ladybirds’ decline in Europe but, since ladybird populations are known to naturally fluctuate from year to year [
 <xref rid="B13-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], it is essential that such assessments are based on long-term studies. Brown and Roy [
 <xref rid="B15-insects-11-00883" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] provided population changes at four sites in England over an 11-year period (2006–2016) following invasion by 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic>. Their survey focused on three plants: lime trees (
 <italic>Tilia</italic> x 
 <italic>europea</italic>), pine (
 <italic>Pinus sylvestris</italic>) and nettle (
 <italic>Urtica dioica</italic>). While 
 <italic>H. axyridis</italic> was over three times more abundant than the second commonest species, it only dominated at the lime sites and only one native species, 
 <italic>A. bipunctata</italic>, significantly declined.
</p>
