<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Among different parts of the walnut tree, the leaf part is the most considered material, confirming its broad application from ancient times traditional folk medicine of some countries. Extracts from walnut leaf were thoroughly evaluated in numerous studies, and their antioxidant content has been determined. Salimi, et al. [
 <xref rid="B165-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">165</xref>] examined some solvents with different polarities including hexane, chloroform, ethyl acetate, methanol and ethanol for the evaluation of the cytotoxicity of walnut leaf extract on human cancer cell lines. Using colorimetric methods, they reported that the obtained methanolic extract presented the highest amount of TPC, TFC, and TCTC (120.28 ± 2.32, 59.44 ± 0.87, and 227.00 ± 4.91 mg/g DE, respectively). In this study, the authors prepared total extract using ethanol from young and mature leaves of walnut. They found that the contents of the phenolic compounds in young leaves were significantly higher than that of their contents in the mature leaves. It has been recommended that walnut leaves with higher phenolic content should preferentially be collected in July and early September [
 <xref rid="B186-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>]. In this study, the TPC of twelve different cultivars of walnut leaves, over eight distinct harvest times (June 1st to September 15th), was studied. Phenolic compound extracts from walnut leaves were prepared using the UAE and RSM methods by Nour, et al. [
 <xref rid="B104-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>]. In this study, they tried to establish the optimum conditions and the maximum predicted TPC, under the optimized conditions of 61% ethanol concentration, 51.28 min extraction time and the 4.96 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">w</italic> liquid-to-solid ratio was 10,125.4 mg GAEs/l, while 2925 mg quercetin equivalents (QEs)/l as maximum TFC was achieved by using ethanol with 67.83% concentration, 
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">w</italic> liquid-to-solid ratio of 4.96 and 49.37 min of extraction time. Under these conditions, the experimental results were close to the predicted values calculated from the polynomial response surface model equation. Evaluating some solvents for the extraction of phenolics from walnut husk showed the high efficiency of the ethanol or methanol. It has been elucidated that among different tested solvents (water, methanol, ethanol, acetone, and benzene), the obtained methanolic extract from walnut leaves contained the highest TPC (94.39 ± 5.63 mg GAEs/g extract) as compared to aqueous extract (27.92 ± 1.40 mg GAEs/g extract) [
 <xref rid="B145-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">145</xref>]. In another study, the antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of the prepared ethanol and water extracts from the leaves of three plants, namely 
 <italic class="italic">P. aphylla</italic>, Persian walnut, and oleander, were evaluated. The results showed that in all assays, the ethanol extracts had the highest amount of total phenolics and flavonoids, as well as highest antioxidant and antimicrobial activities when compared to the water extracts [
 <xref rid="B149-molecules-24-02133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">149</xref>].
</p>
