<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par69">Total RNA from the 6–8 leaves was extracted using Qiagen RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen, USA) following the manufacturer’s protocol and was pooled and considered as one replicate. For each treatment, three replicates were processed separately. The concentration of the RNA was measured by using a NanoPhotometer spectrophotometer (IMPLEN, CA, USA) and the purity was assessed by using RNA Nano 6000 Assay Kit of the Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 system (Agilent Technologies, CA, USA). Sequencing libraries were created using NEB Next Ultra RNA Library Prep Kit (NEB, USA) following manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, the mRNA was purified from 1.5 μg total RNA of each of three replicate using poly-T oligo-attached magnetic beads. Subsequently, the fragmentation buffer was used to break the RNA into short fragments, and the short-fragment RNA was used as a template to synthesize the first strand cDNA with random hexamer primer and M-MuLV Reverse Transcriptase (RNase H
 <sup>−</sup>), followed by buffer, dNTPs (dUTP, dATP, dGTP, and dCTP). Second strand cDNA synthesis was subsequently performed using DNA Polymerase I and RNase H and the double-stranded cDNA was purified using AMPure XP beads (Beckman Coulter, Beverly, USA). The purified double-stranded cDNA was subjected to terminal repair, A tail was added, and the sequencing linker was ligated, and then AMPure XP beads were used for fragment size selection, and finally PCR enrichment was performed to obtain a final cDNA library. Library quality was initially quantified using Qubit 2.0 using the 2100 to test the insert size of the library followed by accurately quantifying the effective concentration of the library (&gt; 2 nM) by q-PCR. Finally, twelve paired-end cDNA libraries with an insert size of 300 bp were constructed for transcriptome sequencing and sequenced on Illumina HiSeq platform (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA, USA) by Novogene, Beijing, China (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.novogene.com/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://en.novogene.com/</ext-link>).
</p>
