<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Millions of people are affected by contagious bacterial diseases throughout the world. These infectious diseases have persistently caused disability and death throughout mankind’s history. According to the World Health Organization (WHO), approximately 50,000 people die from bacterial infectious diseases throughout the world every year [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) is a group of Gram-positive bacteria that are distinct from other strains of 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. MRSA is usually found in hospitals, prisons and nursing homes, where the people with open wounds and deteriorated immune systems are at greater risk of hospital-acquired infections. Although MRSA began as a hospital-acquired infection, it can be found in all communities and livestock. The terms HA-MRSA (healthcare-associated or hospital-acquired MRSA), CA-MRSA (community-associated MRSA) and LA-MRSA (livestock-associated) reflect the MRSA infections in a variety of hosts [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The MRSA displayed resistance against many antibiotics such as methicillin, a semisynthetic β-lactam antibiotic. Generally, the β-lactam mechanisms of resistance of MRSA strains support cross-resistance to all β-lactam antibiotics [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The key mechanism for resistance is the enzyme-catalyzed modification and ultimate destruction of the antibiotic, causing its dynamic efflux from cells and antibiotic target alteration [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Therefore, there is a high demand to develop antibiotics from natural sources based on medical plant extracts in a bid to back up the effectiveness and potency of conventional antibiotics [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Natural products play an important role in drug discovery, as evidenced by over 50% of all modern clinical drugs being of natural product origin [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-01539" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
