<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The plasticization properties and antibacterial activity of lignin are also observed in cellulose-lignin bioplastics. In addition, the addition content of nanoparticles is generally restricted below 3% due to strong inter-molecular hydrogen bonds. Miranda et al. (2015) evaluated the mechanical properties of corn starch bioplastics with lignin serving as a plasticizer and cellulose nanocrystals acting as the reinforcing filler. The outcomes indicated that the incorporation of 1% cellulose nanocrystals and lignin significantly improved the modulus of elasticity and the maximum stress of about 1478% and 256%, respectively, compared to the group without lignin and cellulose [
 <xref rid="B108-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. Ternary PLA-based bioplastics, with dispersed lignin nanoparticles and cellulose nanocrystals were produced by melt extrusion at contents of 1 and 3 wt %. The ternary systems presented higher modulus and strength values than those of binary PLA bioplastics and pure PLA. Furthermore, cellulose nanocrystals and lignin nanoparticles have shown antibacterial activity by reducing the bacterial pathogen multiplication because of the polyphenolic structure [
 <xref rid="B46-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. In addition, cellulose-lignin nanocrystals can function as outstanding fillers for PLA to develop the bioplastics. To improve the thermo-mechanical and rheological properties of PLA biocomposites, cellulose nanocrystals coated with spray-dried lignin were combined. The results found that the lignin-coated cellulose nanocrystals enhanced their interfacial interaction with the PLA biocomposites and promoted the dispersion of cellulose nanocrystals, leading to a significantly improved thermo-mechanical and rheological properties. Nucleating sites at high density were induced by the super compatibility and dispersion of lignin-cellulose nanocrystals in PLA, generating an increase in PLA crystallinity. Adding 0.5 wt % lignin-cellulose nanocrystals to the PLA biocomposites induced a nearly 60% increase of storage modulus compared to pure PLA. This improvement of mechanical properties was derived from a remarkably improved crystallinity of PLA [
 <xref rid="B109-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>].
</p>
