<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Xanthium strumarium</italic> populations stemming from different habitats had higher seed germination potential under benign and adverse environmental conditions (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0241601.g002">2</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0241601.g005">5</xref>). High germination ability of both populations explain their successful naturalization in different habitats. Furthermore, seed germination ability further warrants range expansion ability to the areas facing different types of abiotic stress, including salinity and drought [
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Seed dormancy and germination ability are strongly mediated by environmental conditions prevailing during seed set [
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Seeds of different populations of the same species or even seeds of the same population significantly vary for their seed germination ability [
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. These inter and intra-population variations are explained by the adaptive ability and climate prevailing during seed development [
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Several earlier studies have identified significant variations between different population of the same species for seed germination, growth and fecundity [
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. We report that tested populations stemming from different habitats differed in their seed germination ability (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0241601.g001">1</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0241601.g005">5</xref>), which is owed to their adaptive ability and environmental conditions faced by maternal plants. The genetic diversity within and among populations might be responsible for these differences; however, this claim needs thorough molecular investigations. The tested populations were able to germinate under diverse environments (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0241601.g001">1</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0241601.g005">5</xref>), indicating that both populations have a wide seed germination niche. There are several earlier studies indicating that weed species possess a broad seed germination niche, which help them to adapt stressful and benign environments [
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241601.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
