<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cell migration/proliferation assay for wound healing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The gap closure cell migration/proliferation assay was performed according to a previously described procedure.
  <a rid="b21-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b21-ijn-13-175">21</a>,
  <a rid="b22-ijn-13-175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b22-ijn-13-175">22</a> The assay employs Petri µ-Dishes (35 mm, Ibidi, Giardini, Milan, Italy), which contain a special insert consisting of two cell chambers (growth area: 0.22 cm
  <span class="sup">2</span> each) divided by a septum (500±50 µm in width), intended to simulate a cell-free gap.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fibroblasts were seeded in each chamber at 10
  <span class="sup">5</span> cells/cm
  <span class="sup">2</span> concentration and grown at confluence in standard conditions as previously described. After 24 h, cells reached confluence and the insert was removed displaying two areas of cell substrates divided by the gap. The cell substrates were put in contact with 200 µL of each sample. Nanoparticle suspensions and nanoparticle suspensions containing 5% w/w pull, as described in the section Lipid nanoparticle preparation, diluted with GM in a 1/100 w/w ratio were tested. Cells kept in contact with GM were considered as control. At prefixed times (0 and 48 h), microphotographs were taken to evaluate cell migration in the gap.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As fibroblasts are migrating cells, a Br deoxyuridine test was associated to in vitro wound healing test to identify cells that were in proliferating phase (S-phase) (positively green and blue stained) and filled the gaps.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In particular, this test enabled identification of cell proliferation properties by assessing 5-bromo-2′-deoxyuridine (BrdU) incorporation in DNA synthesis. To this aim, in the last hour of culture, cells were labeled by adding 30 mM BrdU (Sigma-Aldrich) to the medium; then cells were washed with PBS and fixed in 70% ethanol. The incorporation of BrdU was detected by an immunostaining reaction with anti-BrdU antibody (Amersham Bioscience, VWR) as follows: the substrates were washed with PBS and incubated with HCl 2N for 30 min at room temperature. Cells were neutralized in 0.1 M sodium tetraborate (pH 8.5) for 15 min, washed twice for 5 min in PBS, and incubated for 20 min in a blocking solution, consisting of 1% w/v bovine serum albumin (Sigma-Aldrich) and 0.02% w/v Tween 20 (Sigma-Aldrich) in PBS. Cells were then incubated for 1 h with mouse anti-BrdU antibody, diluted 1:100 w/v in blocking solution, washed 3 times (10 min each) with the same solution and then incubated for 30 min in blocking solution containing anti-mouse immunoglobulin G fluorescein isothiocyanate-antibody (1:100 w/v dilution, Sigma-Aldrich). Finally, cell substrates were again extensively washed with PBS, counterstained for DNA with 0.5 mg/mL Hoechst 33258 (Sigma-Aldrich), and mounted in Mowiol (Sigma-Aldrich). Cells characterized by positive BrdU immunofluorescence were counted by using a fluorescence microscope (Zeiss Axiophot, Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany).</p>
</sec>
