<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Genet.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-8021</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7689033</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2020.598714</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcriptional Analysis of Metabolic Pathways and Regulatory Mechanisms of Essential Oil Biosynthesis in the Leaves of <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> (L.) Presl</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Jiexi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1065906/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Beihong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Xiaofang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Haiyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c002"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Zhinong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c003"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1115151/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Jiangxi Provincial Engineering Research Center for Seed-Breeding and Utilization of Camphor Trees, The School of Hydraulic and Ecological Engineering, Nanchang Institute of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Silviculture, Co-Innovation Center of Jiangxi Typical Trees Cultivation and Utilization, College of Forestry, Jiangxi Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanchang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Hongjian Wan, ZheJiang Academy of Agricultural Sciences, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Changjun Ding, Chinese Academy of Forestry, China; Duc Quan Nguyen, The University of Newcastle, Australia</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jiexi Hou, <email>jxhou@cctnit.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Haiyan Zhang, <email>HYZhang@cctnit.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c003">Zhinong Jin, <email>agroking@cctnit.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>This article was submitted to Plant Genomics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Genetics</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>598714</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Hou, Zhang, Zhang, Jin, Zhang and Jin.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hou, Zhang, Zhang, Jin, Zhang and Jin</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The roots, bark, and leaves of <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> are rich in essential oils, which mainly comprised monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes. Although the essential oils obtained from <italic>C. camphora</italic> have been widely used in pharmaceutical, medicinal, perfume, and food industries, the molecular mechanisms underlying terpenoid biosynthesis are poorly understood. To address this lack of knowledge, we performed transcriptome analysis to investigate the key regulatory genes involved in terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>C. camphora</italic>. High-oil-yield trees of linalool type and low-oil-yield trees were used to assemble a <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome of <italic>C. camphora</italic>. A total of 121,285 unigenes were assembled, and the total length, average length, N50, and GC content of unigenes were 87,869,987, 724, 1,063, and 41.1%, respectively. Comparison of the transcriptome profiles of linalool-type <italic>C. camphora</italic> with trees of low oil yield resulted in a total of 3,689 differentially expressed unigenes, among them 31 candidate genes had annotations associated with metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides, including four in the monoterpenoid biosynthesis pathway and three in the terpenoid backbone biosynthesis pathway. Collectively, this genome-wide transcriptome provides a valuable tool for future identification of genes related to essential oil biosynthesis. Additionally, the identification of a cohort of genes in the biosynthetic pathways of terpenoids provides a theoretical basis for metabolic engineering of essential oils in <italic>C. camphora</italic>.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>transcriptional analysis</kwd><kwd>terpenoid biosynthesis</kwd><kwd>chemotypes</kwd><kwd>leaves</kwd><kwd><italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="46"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p>As a member of the Lauraceae family, <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> is an evergreen tree widely distributed around the southern portions of the Yantze River in China, with the largest numbers in Jiangxi, Guangdong, Fujian, Zhejiang, Yunnan, and Sichuan. Many parts of the camphor tree, including roots, stems, leaves, flowers, fruits, and bark, are rich in essential oils that have a wide range of uses in the pest control, spice, cosmetics, and pharmaceutical industries (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2016</xref>). In order to achieve sustainable production, large-scale plantations have been established in China. Under this model, camphor trees are maintained as bushes, and the leaves and twigs are harvested every year for essential oil production. <italic>C. camphora</italic> plantations are characterized by fast growth and high afforestation density, and therefore, they can provide a large number of raw materials for the essential oil industry.</p><p>Essential oils in the camphor tree primarily consist of monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes. Depending on the principal chemical component of their essential oils, camphor trees can be divided into different chemical types, such as linalool, borneol, camphor, cineol, and iso-nerolidol (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2017</xref>). With the gradual improvements in <italic>C. camphora</italic> cultivation and essential oil extraction techniques, use of <italic>C. camphora</italic> as a source of natural linalool, which has long been preferred over its synthetic form for the perfume industry, is becoming more popular. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying the terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>C. camphora</italic> are still poorly understood, which impedes the progress of identifying &#x0201c;superior&#x0201d; <italic>C. camphora</italic> clones that could increase the efficiency of using <italic>C. camphora</italic> for essential oil production.</p><p>The biosynthetic pathway of terpenoids in plants starts with the synthesis of the universal terpenoid precursors isopentenyl diphosphate (IPP) and dimethylallyl diphosphate (DMAPP) through the mevalonate (MVA) or the methylerythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathways. Isoprenyl diphosphate synthases (IDSs) catalyze reactions involving IPP and DMAPP, forming the intermediate phosphate precursors, geranyl diphosphate (GPP), geranylgeranyl diphosphate (GGPP), and farnesyl diphosphate, which are then catalyzed by terpene synthases (TPSs) to form diverse terpenoids (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2012</xref>). The enzymes in the MVA pathway have been shown to be located in cytosol or peroxisomes, whereas all the enzymes involved in the MEP pathway are found in plastids (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Reumann et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Simkin et al., 2011</xref>). In contrast, the localizations of IDSs and TPSs are more diverse and are often at the site of terpenoid biosynthesis (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2012</xref>). Although characterizations of the genes involved in terpenoid biosynthesis have been reported in many plant species, including peppermint, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, conifers, <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic>, and <italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic> (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Battaile and Loomis, 1961</xref>; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Lange and Ghassemian, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Sando et al., 2008a,b</xref>; <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Zulak and Bohlmann, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2012</xref>), many of the enzyme-encoding genes have yet to be elucidated because of the complexity of the terpenoid biosynthesis pathway, especially in the species without a whole-genome sequence.</p><p>In the studies of <italic>C. camphora</italic>, transcriptome analyses for leaves of camphor trees of linalool-, borneol-, camphor-, cineol-, and iso-nerolidol types led to the identification of 424 unigenes in the biosynthetic pathways of terpenoids (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2014</xref>) and transcriptome profiling of linalool and borneol types of <italic>C. camphora</italic> identified three monoterpene synthase genes possibly involved in the biosynthesis of borneol (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). Although these two transcriptome studies have provided valuable insights into the terpenoid biosynthesis pathway, comparisons between only high-oil-yielding individuals could exclude the identification of genes upstream of the biosynthetic pathway of terpenoids. In this study, we used RNA-Seq to identify key enzyme-encoding genes putatively associated with terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>C. camphora</italic>, which may partially determine its essential oil composition. Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) between camphor trees of linalool-type and low-oil-yield camphor trees were identified. In addition to four unigenes in the &#x0201c;monoterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; pathway, this analysis also identified three unigenes in the &#x0201c;terpenoid backbone biosynthesis&#x0201d; pathway. Overall, these results contribute to the general understanding of terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>C. camphora</italic> and provide a theoretical basis for metabolic engineering of terpenoids in this species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2.SS1"><title>Plant Materials</title><p>Mature leaves of linalool-type and low-oil-yield <italic>C. camphora</italic> were harvested from 3-year-old clones grown at the experimental garden of NanChang Institute of Technology, China, in October. The clones were propagated from mother trees through cutting propagation. For each biological replicate (<italic>n</italic> = 3), leaves from at least five tree clones, which were cloned from the same mother tree, were collected and mixed. The three replicates each for the low-oil-yield variety and linalool-type <italic>C. camphora</italic> were termed N- (1&#x02013;3) and LI- (1&#x02013;3) separately. All the samples were harvested and snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and then stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until RNA extraction. Meanwhile, leaves were also collected for oil extraction and chemical component determination.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS2"><title>Essential Oil Extraction and Determination of Essential Oil Yield</title><p>Fresh leaves were harvested and processed for oil extraction immediately after harvesting. Leaf samples were hydrodistilled in a modified Clevenger-type apparatus for 4 h. Extracted essential oils were weighed, and oil yields were calculated using the formula:</p><disp-formula id="S2.Ex1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Essential oil yield (%)</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W1</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>W2</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where W1 is the weight of extracted essential oil, and W2 is the weight of fresh leaves.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS3"><title>Gas Chromatography&#x02013;Mass Spectrometry Analysis</title><p>Analyses of essential oils were performed on a gas chromatography system (Agilent 7890B, United States) equipped with a TG-5MS capillary column (30 m &#x000d7; 0.25-mm internal diameter &#x000d7; 0.25-&#x003bc;m film thickness). Helium with a flow rate of 1 mL/min was used as the carrier gas. The injector was maintained at 220&#x000b0;C. The initial temperature of the column was set at 40&#x000b0;C and increased to 280&#x02013;300&#x000b0;C at a rate of 6.5&#x000b0;C/min. The mass spectrometer was set to scan in the range of 50&#x02013;650 m/z with a scan rate of 0.5 scans/s. Compounds were determined based on their relative retention time and mas spectra data. Details were described in our previous study (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS4"><title>cDNA Library Preparation and RNA Sequencing</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from samples using the RNeasy Plant Mini Kit (Qiagen, United States) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Next, gDNA was removed using DNase I digestion (Qiagen, United States). The integrity of extracted RNA was determined by the RNA Nano 6000 Assay Kit of the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, United States). Extracted RNA was sent to Gene <italic>Denovo</italic> Biotechnology Co. (Guangzhou, China) for cDNA library preparation and sequencing. Up to 1 &#x003bc;g of total RNA from each sample was used for library construction using the NEB #7530 kit for Illumina<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (New England Biolabs, United States), as described by the manufacturer. mRNA was first enriched by oligo(dT) beads and fragmented into small fragments using fragmentation buffer and reverse-transcribed into cDNA with ProtoScript II Reverse Transcriptase and random primers. Second-strand cDNA was synthesized by DNA polymerase I along with RNase H, dNTP, and buffer. Next, cDNA fragments were purified with 1.8 &#x000d7; Agencourt AMPure XP Beads, end-repaired, and ligated to Illumina sequencing adapters after addition of poly(A) tails. Ligated fragments were subjected to size selection by gel electrophoresis and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplified. The resulting cDNA library was sequenced using Illumina HiSeq<sup>TM</sup> 4000.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS5"><title><italic>De novo</italic> Assembly and Functional Annotation</title><p>Raw reads from each sample were filtered by removing reads containing more than 10% of unknown nucleotides, low-quality reads that contained more than 40% of low-quality (<italic>Q</italic> value &#x02264; 20) bases, and adapter sequences according to the Illumina adapter list. Residual ribosome RNA (rRNA) reads were identified by mapping the filtered reads to rRNA, and the identified sequences were then removed. The resulting 87.9 M reads were assembled using short read assembler, Trinity (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Grabherr et al., 2011</xref>), and further clustered to obtain non-redundant unigenes by Corset (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Davidson and Oshlack, 2014</xref>). The completeness of the transcriptomic assembly was assessed using BUSCO (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Simao et al., 2015</xref>) by comparing the 1,440 embryophyta-specific genes to our unigenes. Unigenes were annotated by BLASTx (with an <italic>E</italic>-value threshold of 1e<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>) to the Swiss-Prot protein database (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bairoch and Apweiler, 2000</xref>) and NCBI non-redundant protein (Nr) database (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">O&#x02019;Leary et al., 2016</xref>). Nr annotation results of unigenes were used for Gene Ontology (GO) annotation by Blast2GO software (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Conesa et al., 2005</xref>), and functional classification of unigenes was performed using WEGO software (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Ye et al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS6"><title>Identification of Differentially Expressed Genes</title><p>Expression values of each gene were calculated as reads per kilobase (of exon) per million (RPKM) mapped reads. Biological samples with low and high oil contents were grouped, and comparison was undertaken to identify DEGs between the two experimental groups. Principal component analysis (PCA) was also performed as a quality control. DEGs with a fold change &#x02265; 2 and <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 across the two experimental groups were identified using the edgeR package (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS7"><title>Quantitative Reverse Transcriptase&#x02013;PCR</title><p>Leaves from five randomly selected 3-year-old tree clones of each chemotype were collected for quantitative reverse transcriptase (RT)&#x02013;PCR analysis. Total RNA was extracted and reverse-transcribed into cDNA using the HiScript II Q RT SuperMix for quantitative PCR (qPCR) (Vazyme, China). The PCRs were performed using ChamQTM SYBR<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> qPCR Master Mix (Vazyme, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions on an ABI Step One Plus System with three replicates. Sequences of the gene-specific primers are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. Relative gene expression was calculated using the 2<sup>&#x02013;&#x025b3;&#x025b3;<italic>Ct</italic></sup> method, and <italic>ACTIN</italic> was chosen as the internal reference gene to normalize expression levels.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3.SS1"><title>Chemical Composition of Leaf Essential Oils From <italic>C. camphora</italic> of Different Oil Contents</title><p>In general, there were no major differences in morphology between camphor trees of different chemotypes, and the trees were therefore initially classified by odor alone. Fresh leaves of the six samples were harvested, and the essential oils were obtained by water distillation. The average oil outputs of the samples from linalool- and low-oil-yield chemotypes were 1.3 and 0.3%, respectively. Chemical composition of the extracted essential oils was determined by gas chromatography&#x02013;mass spectrometry (GC-MS). <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> lists the major components detected, 1&#x02013;15 are monoterpenes, and the remaining are sesquiterpenes. In the essential oils of the linalool type, &#x003b2;-linalool was the principal constituent, making up &#x0223c;90% in average. Among the various constituents of the essential oils extracted from the different chemotypes of camphor trees, the major difference was observed for the monoterpene content. Therefore, transcriptome analyses between trees of linalool type and trees with low oil yield were performed to investigate the molecular mechanisms underlying the biosynthesis of monoterpenes.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Chemical composition of the essential oils from leaf extracts of <italic>C. camphora</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-1 (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-2 (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-3 (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI-1(%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI-2(%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LI-3 (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;-Thujene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pinene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phellandrene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Myrcene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sc>D</sc>-Limonene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eucalyptol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Ocimene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;-Linalool</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borneol acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphor</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpineol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citronellol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citral</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caryophyllene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alloaromadendrene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germacrene D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naphthalene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Humulene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000e7;-Elemene</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nerolidol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(&#x02212;)-Spathulenol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nerolidyl acetate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guaiol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Caryophyllene oxide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others and Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><italic>N: C. camphora with low oil yield; LI: C. camphora of linalool type; &#x0201c;&#x02014;&#x0201d; represents a compound not detected or in trace amounts (&#x0003c; 0.1%).</italic></italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S3.SS2"><title><italic>De novo</italic> Assembly of the <italic>C. camphora</italic> Transcriptome</title><p>To construct a genome-wide transcriptome of <italic>C. camphora</italic>, total RNA of the experimental samples was isolated. This pooled total RNA was sequenced and a total of 87.9 M 150 bp paired-end reads remained after raw reads were processed with sequence filtering and quality control (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS2">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). <italic>De novo</italic> assembly was carried out with short reads using Trinity (see section &#x0201c;Materials and Methods&#x0201d;). A total of 121,285 unigenes were assembled with a high N50 value (1063), as well as high values for both the maximum unigene length (15,713) and percentage of mapped reads (&#x0003e;98%), indicating a good assembly quality (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In addition, BUSCO analysis was performed to assess the completeness of the final genome assembly. Based on the 1,440 embryophytic-specfic genes, 79.8% were identified as complete genes, including 76.3% complete and single-copy genes and 3.5% complete and duplicated genes, and 8.8% were identified as fragmented genes, indicating good completeness of the genome assembly (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Statistics for <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of the <italic>C. camphora</italic> transcriptome.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total assembled bases</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.9M</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total no. of unigenes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121,285</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N50 (bp)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,063</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shortest unigene length (bp)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longest unigene length (bp)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,713</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average unigene length (bp)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">724</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mapped reads (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;98%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S3.SS3"><title>Functional Annotation of Unigenes</title><p>Functional annotation of 121,285 <italic>C. camphora</italic> unigenes was performed by comparing unigene sequences to the protein databases Nr and Swissprot with an <italic>E</italic>-value threshold of 1e<sup>&#x02013;5</sup> using BLASTx analysis. This analysis yielded a total of 50,545 annotated genes, with 34,789 unigenes in common between two databases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). A total of 49,295 unigenes had significant hits in the Nr database. Further GO annotation analysis assigned the 49,295 unigenes to three main categories, including biological process, cellular component, and molecular function (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Within the biological process, &#x0201c;metabolic process&#x0201d; was highly represented (29.5%) followed by &#x0201c;cellular process&#x0201d; (24.1%). Within the cellular component, &#x0201c;cell&#x0201d; (23.7%), &#x0201c;cell part&#x0201d; (23.7%), and &#x0201c;organelle&#x0201d; (16.0%) were most represented. Similarly, &#x0201c;catalytic activity&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;binding&#x0201d; were the most dominant terms under molecular function, accounting for 55.4 and 36.1%, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS3">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). To systematically analyze the metabolic pathways of unigene products in cells and predict the function of these unigene products, Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) analysis was performed, and 11,111 unigenes were annotated and classified into 19 metabolic pathways. The category &#x0201c;Global and Overview&#x0201d; included the largest number of unigenes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>), among which &#x0201c;metabolic pathways&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;biosynthesis of secondary metabolites&#x0201d; were dominant, accounting for 40.8 and 22.2%, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS4">Supplementary Table S4</xref>). Additionally, 359 unigenes were placed into the category &#x0201c;metabolism of terpenoids and polyketides,&#x0201d; which included &#x0201c;terpenoid backbone biosynthesis&#x0201d; (32.3%), &#x0201c;monoterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (5.0%), &#x0201c;diterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (13.4%), &#x0201c;sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (5.0%), &#x0201c;carotenoid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (15.3%), &#x0201c;brassinosteroid biosynthesis&#x0201d; (8.9%), &#x0201c;zeatin biosynthesis&#x0201d; (8.4%), and &#x0201c;limonene and pinene degradation&#x0201d; (11.7%) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS4">Supplementary Table S4</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Functional annotation and GO classification of assembled unigenes in <italic>C. camphora</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> Functional annotation of assembled unigenes by BLASTx against Nr and Swissprot databases with an <italic>E</italic>-value threshold of 1e<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>. A total of 34,789 unigenes were commonly annotated in the two databases. <bold>(B)</bold> GO terms of <italic>C. camphora</italic> unigenes determined by Blast2GO fell into the three categories of biological process, cellular component, and molecular function, where metabolic process, cell part, and catalytic activity were the three most prevalent subcategories, respectively. <bold>(C)</bold> KEGG classification of annotated unigenes. The <italic>x-</italic>axis shows the number of unigenes annotated, and the <italic>y</italic> axis shows the KEGG metabolic pathways the unigenes fell into, including organismal system (O), metabolism (M), genetic information processing (G), environmental information processing (E), and cellular processes (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fgene-11-598714-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS4"><title>RNA-Seq Analyses of DEGs Between <italic>C. camphora</italic> Leaves With High and Low Oil Contents</title><p>To get a better understanding of the dynamic processes of terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>C. camphora</italic>, we performed transcriptome analyses of camphor leaves with high and low oil contents based on the oil yield and GC-MS results (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Trimmed reads were mapped to the <italic>de novo</italic> transcriptome assembly of <italic>C. camphora</italic>. PCA demonstrated a good similarity between samples in the high- and low-oil-content groups (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS2">Supplementary Figure S2A</xref>). Similarly, the range of Pearson correlation coefficient between two samples in each experimental group is 0.93&#x02013;0.96 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS2">Supplementary Figure S2B</xref>), also indicating that the samples in the same groups are highly correlated. Further transcriptome analysis identified 3,689 DEGs with <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 and |log2 fold_change| &#x0003e; 2, which comprised 2,120 up-regulated and 1,569 down-regulated unigenes. The GO terms &#x0201c;metabolic process&#x0201d; in the &#x0201c;biological process&#x0201d; category and &#x0201c;catalytic activity&#x0201d; in the &#x0201c;molecular function&#x0201d; category were the two most highly represented within DEGs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS3">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). In accordance with the GO analysis, KEGG enrichment analysis revealed that most of the 3,689 DEGs were in &#x0201c;metabolism&#x0201d; class (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>), which included &#x0201c;biosynthesis of secondary metabolites,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;phenylpropanoid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;monoterpenoid biosynthesis,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;terpenoid backbone biosynthesis,&#x0201d; and other pathways (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS5">Supplementary Table S5</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Transcriptional cascade of DEGs in terpenoid backbone biosynthesis in linalool-type <italic>C. camphora</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> KEGG pathway annotations of DEGs. The <italic>x-</italic>axis indicates the number of unigenes annotated in each corresponding pathway. The five categories of KEGG pathways are divided and color-coded. <bold>(B)</bold> DEGs in terpenoid backbone biosynthesis. The transcriptional cascade of terpenoid backbone biosynthesis is shown in the form of protein-coding enzymes or nodes annotated by KEGG pathway analysis. Enzyme expression patterns are indicated with logRPKM values, and DEGs are in azure. The left three and right three columns represent low oil content type (N) and linalool type (LI), respectively. AACT, acetyl-CoA C-acetyltransferase; DXS, 1-deoxy-<sc>D</sc>-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase; HMGS, hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA synthase; PMK, phosphomevalonate kinase; MVD, mevalonate diphosphate decarboxylase; DXR, 1-deoxy-d-xylulose-5-phosphate reductoisomerase; HDS, hydroxymethylbutenyl 4-diphosphate synthase; HDR, (E)-4-hydroxy-3-methyl-but-2-enyl diphosphate reductase; IDI, isopentenyl-diphosphate delta-isomerase; GPPS, geranyl diphosphate synthase; FPPS, farnesyl pyrophosphate synthase; GGPPS, geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase; LIS, linalool synthase; MNR1, (+)-neomenthol dehydrogenase-like isoform; GerS, geraniol synthase; GerD, (&#x02212;)-germacrene D synthase; CLS, ent-copalyl diphosphate synthase; CYP88D6, cytochrome P450 88D6; GA2OX, Gibberellin 2-beta-dioxygenase. <bold>(C)</bold> qRT-PCR validation of RNA-Seq data. The black bars represent relative gene expression determined by qRT-PCR (left <italic>y</italic>-axis) and the dotted gray bars represent gene expression levels detected by RNA-Seq (right <italic>y-</italic>axis). Standard errors of the three technical replicates of each sample of the qRT-PCR analysis and three biological replicates in the two experimental groups of the RNA-Seq analysis are indicated by error bars.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fgene-11-598714-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS5"><title>Putative Genes Involved in Terpenoid Backbone and Terpenoid Biosynthesis in <italic>C. camphora</italic></title><p>Annotated protein-coding enzymes were mapped into the terpenoid backbone biosynthesis pathway, and gene expression data of each enzyme in the two experimental groups were indicated with logRPKM values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS6">Supplementary Table S6</xref>). Two unigenes encoding key enzymes, <italic>AACT-like</italic> in the MVA pathway and <italic>DXS-like</italic> in the MEP pathway, exhibited a higher expression level in the groups with high oil contents. Because both MVA and MEP pathways generate the precursors IPP and DMAPP for the final production of terpenoids, increased expression of these two genes could explain the higher amount of terpenoids we observed in this group (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Additionally, the <italic>GGPPS-like</italic> gene also had a higher expression level in the leaves of linalool type. Among the DEGs, 14 unigenes were annotated as terpenoid synthase&#x02013;encoding genes, including four in monoterpenoid biosynthesis, four in sesquiterpenoid and triterpenoid biosynthesis, and six in diterpenoid biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS6">Supplementary Table S6</xref>). One <italic>LIS-like</italic> and one <italic>GerS-like</italic> unigene were up-regulated in the monoterpenoid biosynthesis pathway, indicating that increased availability of terpenoid precursors, along with increased levels of monoterpene synthases, might be the reason for the higher oil yield and higher accumulation of linalool and other monoterpenes in the trees of linalool type. Besides monoterpenoid synthases, four sesquiterpenoid synthase unigenes encoding GerD and four diterpenoid synthase unigenes encoding CLS, CYP88D6, GA2OX1, and GA2OX8 were also up-regulated. In general, the upregulation of terpenoid synthase unigenes in the trees of linalool-type <italic>C. camphor</italic> is consistent with their increased accumulation of terpenoids, suggesting that the presence of various terpenoid synthases might be the reason for the occurrence of varied terpenoids in the essential oils of <italic>C. camphora</italic>. To validate the reliability of our RNA-Seq data, four DEGs were chosen for qRT-PCR examination. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>, the expression profiles of these unigenes observed by qRT-PCR are identical to their profiles identified in the RNA-Seq analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic>C. camphora</italic> oils have a wide variety of uses, including ornamental, medicinal, and industrial, which makes understanding the regulation of essential oil biosynthesis in camphor tree highly important (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). Because of earlier unregulated harvesting, many natural sources of camphor trees have been exhausted. In response to this, camphor tree plantations have been established in many countries including China and Japan. These camphor trees are maintained as bushes and are harvested for twigs and leaves before essential oil extraction. Camphor trees can be divided into different chemotypes based on their main terpenoid components. In this study, we identified camphor trees of linalool type and low oil contents without a dominant terpene component. A total of 26 main components were identified by GC-MS. We further demonstrated that the chemical components in the essential oils of <italic>C. camphora</italic> leaf extracts contained mainly monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes with very minor quantities of diterpenes (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, linalool took up &#x0223c;90 of the total essential oil contents in linalool type, indicating that monoterpene levels account for the major difference between the essential oils of different chemotypes.</p><p>Terpenoid biosynthesis and its regulation are extensively documented in many plant species. Despite having high structural diversity, all terpenes are derived from two isomeric basic backbone molecules, IPP and DMAPP, which are synthesized either through the MVA or MEP pathways (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Sacchettini and Poulter, 1997</xref>). Although many members of the Lauraceae family are rich in terpenoids and are economically important tree species, limited studies are available analyzing genes involved in its terpenoid biosynthesis pathway (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>). This study was focused on identifying genes involved in terpenoid biosynthesis and key enzymes involved in the biosynthesis of the backbone IPP and DMAPP molecules in <italic>C. camphora</italic>. A transcriptome of <italic>C. camphora</italic> was also generated to provide a reference for future RNA-Seq&#x02013;based expression profiling of terpenoid biosynthesis. Functional annotation analysis showed significant enrichment in genes associated with &#x0201c;metabolic pathways&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;biosynthesis of secondary metabolites&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). This is consistent with our observation that September&#x02013;November is the time of the year when <italic>C. camphora</italic> harbors the highest oil contents (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2015</xref>), and it is also the harvesting time of our samples. Furthermore, 116 and 18 expressed unigenes were identified to be highly homologous with 49 and 11 known enzymes in the terpenoid backbone biosynthesis and monoterpenoid biosynthesis pathways, respectively.</p><p>By comparing the transcriptome profiles of leaves of linalool and leaves with low oil contents, 3,689 unigenes were identified as DEGs. Among them, expression levels of <italic>AACT-like</italic> and <italic>DXS-like</italic>, catalyzing the first steps toward IPP and DMAPP in the MVA and MEP pathways, were up-regulated in the leaves of linalool type. <italic>DXS</italic> genes are believed to be a significant control point in the MEP pathway (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Wolfertz et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Rohdich et al., 2006</xref>), and manipulation of gene expression levels of <italic>DXS</italic> in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> altered the levels of tocopherols, carotenoids, chlorophylls, abscisic acid, and various other isoprenoids (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Est&#x000e9;vez et al., 2001</xref>). However, the contribution of each pathway to the generation of the common precursors for varied terpenoid biosynthesis is still unknown, because crosstalk between the two pathways has been documented in many species including chamomile, <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, tobacco, and snapdragon (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adam and Zapp, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bick and Lange, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Hemmerlin et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Laule et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2005</xref>). In addition, the expression level of <italic>GGPPS-like</italic> in the &#x0201c;terpenoid backbone biosynthesis&#x0201d; pathway was up-regulated in the comparison, indicating increased supply of precursors for diterpenes biosynthesis. Although the percentage of diterpenes in leaf extracts of linalool-type camphor trees is not high, their oil yield is much higher than trees of low oil yield. Therefore, higher <italic>GGPPS</italic> expression level may simply be correlated with a general increase in oil content. Interestingly, it has been documented that GPP, the precursor for monoterpene, is constitutively and ubiquitously expressed in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Van Schie et al., 2013</xref>), and our results also showed that the level of <italic>GPPS</italic> was indifferent between the groups regardless of different accumulation of monoterpenes.</p><p>Noticeably, <italic>LIS-like</italic> shared a high sequence identity (&#x0003e;99%) with some of the identified linalool synthases in the Lauraceae family. The conserved DDxxD and NSE/DTE motifs for Mg<sup>2+</sup> or Mn<sup>2+</sup> ion binding as well as the predicted D562 active site cleft were all properly distributed in the LIS-like protein (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="FS4">Supplementary Figure S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS7">Supplementary Table S7</xref>). However, caution should be used when assigning protein functions to terpenoid synthase genes predicted based on sequence similarities as it has been reported that point mutations alone were sufficient to significantly change the kinetic activity of a linalool synthase gene in <italic>Cinnamomum osmophloeum</italic> (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2014</xref>). Additionally, alternative splicing has been shown to alter linalool biosynthesis, as reported in <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). Higher levels of monoterpene production could potentially lower production of other terpenes and isoprenoid derivatives due to the competition for common precursors. Indeed, four unigenes in the &#x0201c;carotenoid biosynthesis pathway&#x0201d; and two unigenes in the &#x0201c;steroid biosynthesis pathway&#x0201d; were down-regulated in the comparison (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS6">Supplementary Table S6</xref>). Similar examples can be seen in tobacco plants producing monoterpene where lower levels of &#x003b2;-caryophyllene were detected in the flowers of these plants (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000fc;cker et al., 2004</xref>). Additionally, both transgenic tomato and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants producing a phytoene synthase and the strawberry linalool/nerolidol synthase separately had significant growth retardation due to the severe inhibition of gibberellin biosynthesis (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Fray et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Aharoni et al., 2004</xref>).</p><p>Other genes of interest emerged from this study, which include several members of the WRKY family. <italic>WRKY21-like</italic>, <italic>WRKY47-like</italic>, and <italic>WRKY65-like</italic> were all up-regulated in the leaves with high oil content (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS6">Supplementary Table S6</xref>). WRKY transcription factors have been reported to regulate the expression of genes involved in terpene biosynthesis in many species, including <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, cotton, <italic>Artemisia annua</italic>, <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic>, and others (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Suttipanta et al., 2011</xref>). Moreover, it was suggested that the linalool-type <italic>C. osmophloeum</italic> contains a W-box element (T)(T)TGAC(C/T) in the promoter region of the linalool synthase gene, enabling regulation by WRKY transcription factors (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2014</xref>). Based on these previous studies, we suspect that members of the WRKY family might be involved in the regulation of terpene synthase genes of <italic>C. camphora</italic> and therefore could potentially play critical roles in the quantitative difference of oil contents between different chemotypes.</p><p>All in all, this study identified a cohort of genes in the terpenoid backbone biosynthesis and monoterpenoid biosynthesis pathways that were commonly up-regulated in leaves with high linalool contents compared to leaves with low oil contents. The knowledge obtained from this study could facilitate manipulation of camphor tree essential oil production through metabolic engineering of essential oil biosynthesis. Additional studies should focus on the isolation of monoterpene synthases genes from different chemotypes of <italic>C. camphora</italic>. Additionally, functional analyses are needed to demonstrate the impact of these genes on terpenoid production.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>Raw reads yielded from Illumina sequencing have been uploaded to the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra</ext-link>) and accession numbers for the six samples are as below: N-1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SRR11362618">SRR11362618</ext-link>); N-2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SRR11362617">SRR11362617</ext-link>); N-3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SRR12576812">SRR12576812</ext-link>); LI-1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SRR11362614">SRR11362614</ext-link>); LI-2 527 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SRR11362613">SRR11362613</ext-link>); and LI-3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SRR12576811">SRR12576811</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>HZ, JH, and ZJ designed the experiments. BZ, JZ, XJ, and JH performed the experiments. HZ and JH analyzed the data. JH wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant no. 31560242) and the Jiangxi Provincial Education Department Fund (grant no. GJJ190975).</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We thank HuiJuan Cheng and Yiqun Zhang for their assistance in sample harvesting and essential oil extraction. We would also like to thank Yanbo Wang and reviewers for their help in improving the manuscript.</p></ack><sec id="S9" sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fgene.2020.598714/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fgene.2020.598714/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS1"><label>Supplementary Figure 1</label><caption><p>BUSCO analysis of the final transcriptomic assembly.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS2"><label>Supplementary Figure 2</label><caption><p>Relationship between the samples.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS3"><label>Supplementary Figure 3</label><caption><p>GO enrichment histogram of DEGs.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="FS4"><label>Supplementary Figure 4</label><caption><p>Amino acid sequence alignment of identified LIS-like in <italic>C. camphora</italic> with linalool synthase CoLIS-LL in <italic>C. osmophloeum</italic> (accession number: <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="JX028232">JX028232</ext-link>).</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS1"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><caption><p>Sequences of the gene-specific primers used in quantitative RT-PCR.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS2"><label>Supplementary Table 2</label><caption><p>Raw transcriptomic data.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS3"><label>Supplementary Table 3</label><caption><p>GO enrichment analysis of <italic>C. camphora</italic> unigenes.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS4"><label>Supplementary Table 4</label><caption><p>KEGG enrichment of <italic>C. camphora</italic> unigenes.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS5"><label>Supplementary Table 5</label><caption><p>KEGG enrichment of DEGs.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS6"><label>Supplementary Table 6</label><caption><p>Putative unigenes associated with terpenoid biosynthesis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS7"><label>Supplementary Table 7</label><caption><p>Sequences of putative unigenes associated with terpenoid biosynthesis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>K.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zapp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis of the isoprene units of chamomile sesquiterpenes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>953</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>959</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0031-9422(97)00992-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstappen</surname><given-names>F. W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertea</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sevenier</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Gain and loss of fruit flavor compounds produced by wild and cultivated strawberry species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>3110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3131</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.104.023895</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15522848?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>The SWISS-PROT protein sequence database and its supplement TrEMBL in 2000.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.45</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 10592178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battaile</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1961</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis of terpenes: II. The site and sequence of terpene formation in peppermint.</article-title>
<source><italic>BBA</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>552</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-3002(61)90612-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13865784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bick</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Metabolic cross talk between cytosolic and plastidial pathways of isoprenoid biosynthesis: unidirectional transport of intermediates across the chloroplast envelope membrane.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Biochem. Biophys.</italic></source>
<volume>415</volume>
<fpage>146</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>154</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0003-9861(03)00233-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12831836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L.-A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome analysis and identification of genes related to terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Genomics</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>:<issue>550</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4941-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30041601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30041601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tholl</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Auria</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Biosynthesis and emission of terpenoid volatiles from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>481</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>494</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.007989</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12566586?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>The Litsea genome and the evolution of the laurel family.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<issue>1675</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-15493-5</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 32245969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32245969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Y.-G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.-Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Plant terpenoids: biosynthesis and ecological functions.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Integr. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2007.00395.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Terol</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tal&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>3674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3676</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti610</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16081474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshlack</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Corset: enabling differential gene expression analysis for de novo assembled transcriptomes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Genome Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>15</volume>:<issue>410</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0410-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25063469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25063469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orlova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichelt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The nonmevalonate pathway supports both monoterpene and sesquiterpene formation in snapdragon flowers.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>933</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>938</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0407360102</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15630092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15630092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reindl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>1-Deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate synthase, a limiting enzyme for plastidic isoprenoid biosynthesis in plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>22901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22909</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M100854200</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 11264287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fray</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedden</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Constitutive expression of a fruit phytoene synthase gene in transgenic tomatoes causes dwarfism by redirecting metabolites from the gibberellin pathway.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant J.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>701</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.1995.08050693.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>J. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>652</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21572440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The chemical composition of essential oils from <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> and their insecticidal activity against the stored product pests.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>:<issue>1836</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms17111836</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27827929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27827929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Molecular differentiation of five <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> chemotypes using desorption atmospheric pressure chemical ionization mass spectrometry of raw leaves.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>46579</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep46579</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28425482?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28425482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemmerlin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeffler</surname><given-names>J.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tritsch</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagan</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosdemange-Billiard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Cross-talk between the cytosolic mevalonate and the plastidial methylerythritol phosphate pathways in tobacco bright yellow-2 cells.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biol. Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>278</volume>
<fpage>26666</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26676</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M302526200</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12736259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12736259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>GC&#x000d7;GC-TOFMS Analysis of essential oils composition from leaves, twigs and seeds of Cinnamomum camphora L. Presl and their insecticidal and repellent activities.</article-title>
<source><italic>Molecules</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>423</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules21040423</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27043503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome analysis for leaves of five chemical types in <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Yi chuan</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3724/sp.j.1005.2014.00058</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24846919?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24846919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>B. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghassemian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Genome organization in Arabidopsis thaliana: a survey for genes involved in isoprenoid and chlorophyll metabolism.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Mol. Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>948</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/a:1023005504702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12777052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laule</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000fc;rholz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heifetz</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Crosstalk between cytosolic and plastidial pathways of isoprenoid biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>PNAS</italic></source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>6866</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6871</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1031755100</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12748386?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12748386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.-T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>F.-H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Characterization of S-(+)-linalool synthase from several provenances of <italic>Cinnamomum osmophloeum</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Tree Genet Genomes</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11295-013-0665-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y.-F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Implementation of CsLIS/NES in linalool biosynthesis involves transcript splicing regulation in <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.13080</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28963730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28963730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;cker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hautum</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Plas</surname><given-names>L. H. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Increased and altered fragrance of tobacco plants after metabolic engineering using three monoterpene synthases from lemon.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>134</volume>
<fpage>510</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>519</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.103.030189</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 14718674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14718674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of AaWRKY1, an Artemisia annua transcription factor that regulates the amorpha-4,11-diene synthase gene, a key gene of artemisinin biosynthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>2146</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2161</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcp149</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19880398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide identification and characterization of novel genes involved in terpenoid biosynthesis in <italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Exp. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>2809</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2823</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err466</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22291132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22291132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Phosphorylation of a WRKY transcription factor by two pathogen-responsive MAPKs drives phytoalexin biosynthesis in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>1639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1653</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.084996</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21498677?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21498677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Leary</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>M. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brister</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciufo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McVeigh</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Reference sequence (RefSeq) database at NCBI: current status, taxonomic expansion, and functional annotation.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>D733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D745</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1189</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26553804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26553804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Z.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>K.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>F.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.-L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Content and main compositions analysis of essential oil in branches and leaves of <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> in different months (in Chinese).</article-title>
<source><italic>Guangxi For. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>430</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19692/j.cnki.gfs.2015.04.021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reumann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babujee</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wienkoop</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemsen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonicelli</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Proteome analysis of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaf peroxisomes reveals novel targeting peptides, metabolic pathways, and defense mechanisms.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>3170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3193</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.050989</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17951448?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19910308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohdich</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauw</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feicht</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;hler</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacher</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Isoprenoid biosynthesis in plants &#x02013; 2C-methyl-d-erythritol-4-phosphate synthase (IspC protein) of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>FEBS J.</italic></source>
<volume>273</volume>
<fpage>4446</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4458</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1742-4658.2006.05446.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16972937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16972937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacchettini</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulter</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Creating isoprenoid diversity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Science</italic></source>
<volume>277</volume>
<fpage>1788</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1789</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.277.5333.1788</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 9324768?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9324768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sando</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takaoka</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008a</year>). <article-title>Cloning and characterization of mevalonate pathway genes in a natural rubber producing plant, <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>2049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2060</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.80165</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18685207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18685207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sando</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okumoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzuyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008b</year>). <article-title>Cloning and characterization of the 2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway genes of a natural-rubber producing plant, <italic>Hevea brasiliensis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biosci. Biotechnol. Biochem.</italic></source>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>2903</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2917</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1271/bbb.80387</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18997428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18997428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simao</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kriventseva</surname><given-names>E. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zdobnov</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>BUSCO: assessing genome assembly and annotation completeness with single-copy orthologs.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>3210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv351</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26059717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26059717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simkin</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guirimand</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papon</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Courdavault</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thabet</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginis</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Peroxisomal localisation of the final steps of the mevalonic acid pathway in planta.</article-title>
<source><italic>Planta</italic></source>
<volume>234</volume>:<issue>903</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-011-1444-6</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21655959?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21655959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suttipanta</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattanaik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulshrestha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>The transcription factor CrWRKY1 positively regulates the terpenoid indole alkaloid biosynthesis in <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>2081</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2093</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.181834</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21988879?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21988879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Schie</surname><given-names>C. C. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuurink</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Prenyldiphosphate synthases and gibberellin biosynthesis</article-title>,&#x0201d; in <source><italic>Isoprenoid Synthesis in Plants and Microorganisms: New Concepts and Experimental Approaches</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohmer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>214</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfertz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hnemann</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Rapid regulation of the methylerythritol 4-Phosphate pathway during isoprene synthesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>1939</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1945</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.043737</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15286290?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15286290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.-Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Characterization of GaWRKY1, a cotton transcription factor that regulates the sesquiterpene synthase gene (+)-delta-cadinene synthase-A.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>135</volume>
<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>515</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.104.038612</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15133151?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15133151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A geraniol-synthase gene from <italic>Cinnamomum tenuipilum</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2004.12.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15680985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15680985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>WEGO: a web tool for plotting GO annotations.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>W293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl031</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16845012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Chemical constituents and chemotypes of fresh leaf essential oil of wild species belonging to Sect. Camphor (Trew.) Meissn. in southeastern China.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Essent.</italic></source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>1115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1122</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0972060X.2019.1662331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zulak</surname><given-names>K. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Terpenoid biosynthesis and specialized vascular cells of conifer defense.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Integr. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7909.2010.00910.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20074143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>