<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Bupleurum</italic> plant species are extensively dispersed in the northern hemisphere and are used as one of the oldest phytomedicines in China. Many reports have identified the activity of this herbal plant in the treatment of HCoV-22E9 and other viral infections [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Generally, 
 <italic>Radix bupleuri</italic> (
 <italic>R. bupleuri</italic>) is derived from the dried roots of 
 <italic>Bupleurum</italic> species and used for the treatment of various diseases [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. It has great pharmacologically significant activities, the main ones reported in the literature being: antiviral, anti-inflammatory, anti-tumor, neuro-modulation and immunoregulation [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Approximately 7% of naturally occurring saikosaponins (triterpene saponin glycosides) are present in 
 <italic>R. bupleuri,</italic> which is the main component of this medicinal plant with potent effects. Four types of saikosaponins (SS) are found; SSa, SSb2, SSc and SSd, which are responsible for the most pharmacological activities in this medicinal plant [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The SSa, SSb2 and SSd have potential to inhibit the effects against coronavirus 229E, SARS-CoV and influenza A virus [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Moreover, the mechanism of action of these SS employing antiviral activity interrupts the early stage of viral replication inside the host cells [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. In addition, these SS also attenuate pro-inflammatory cytokines production, inhibiting viral replication through down-regulating NF-kB signaling, caspase 3-dependent virus ribonucleoprotein nuclear export, lung neutrophil and monocytes recruitment in an experimental in vivo mice model [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-09-01244" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
