<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Existing antiviral drugs were used as positive control (Wishart et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) (Drug Bank 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.drugbank.ca/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.drugbank.ca/</ext-link>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4(e–g)</xref>). Remdesivir was originally investigated as a treatment for Ebola virus, but has potential to treat a variety of RNA viruses. Its activity against the coronavirus (CoV) family of viruses, such as SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, was described in 2017 and it is also being investigated as a potential treatment for SARS-CoV-2 infections. Remdesivir was granted an FDA Emergency Use Authorization on 1
 <sup>st</sup> May 2020. Remdesivir is a nucleoside analog used to inhibit the action of RNA polymerase that terminate the RNA transcription (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4(e)</xref>) (Sheahan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Hydroxychloroquine is a racemic mixture consisting of an R and S enantiomer (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4(f)</xref>). It is an aminoquinoline which is commonly prescribed medication in the treatment of uncomplicated malaria, rheumatoid arthritis, chronic discoid lupus erythematosus and systemic lupus erythematosus (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). It was developed during World War II as a derivative of quinacrine and was granted FDA approval in 1955. Since after investigating, it was found that accumulation of hydroxychloroquine raises the pH which thereby prevents the virus particles (corona viruses) from utilizing their activity for fusion and entry into the cell, the FDA revoked an emergency use authorization on 15
 <sup>th</sup> June 2020. Hydroxychloroquine also inhibits terminal glycosylation of ACE2, the receptor that SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 target for cell entry. Favipiravir is a modified pyrazine analog that was initially approved for therapeutic use in resistant cases of influenza (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Figure 4(g)</xref>). Favipiravir has been investigated for the treatment of life-threatening pathogens such as Ebola virus, Lassa virus and now COVID-19. Favipiravir functions as prodrug and undergoes ribosylation and phosphorylation intracellularly to become the active favipiravir-RTP (Favipiravir-ribofuranosyl-5′-triphosphate). Favipiravir-RTP binds to and inhibits RNA dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp), which ultimately prevents viral transcription and replication. The RdRp catalytic domain is expected to be similar for other RNA viruses and hence it contributes to favipiravir’s broad-spectrum coverage (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Sheahan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
</p>
