<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Depending on the variable compositions of the terpenes, different cannabis ‘strains’ elicit different aromas with a greater link to product quality, retail price, and consumer preference [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The terpene compositions of cannabis are a seasonal variable. The alteration in the proportion of terpenoids in cannabis are in accordance with the variety of cannabis, plant part, environmental conditions, maturity, and method of analyses [
 <xref rid="B72-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Different growth stages of the cannabis could give considerable variations in the terpene compositions. The terpene profile of the cannabis at the vegetative stage was considered to have a much lower proportion of monoterpenes than the flowering stage [
 <xref rid="B56-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Aside from the variations and compositions of terpenes among different phenotypes, the modulated molecular or biological functions of the terpenes are effective only when the concentration of the terpene in the full-spectrum cannabis extract is above 0.05% v/w [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. To characterize the aromatic profile of the cannabis of different chemovars, solid phase microextraction (SPME), which is non-destructive and non-invasive, was used to collect the volatiles from the samples [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. This method favors a small sample size, and eliminates the use of organic solvents and more importantly, it allows for the emission of hundreds of volatile compounds from the samples [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-molecules-25-05792" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05792-f007">Figure 7</xref> shows the chromatograms of the volatile compounds diffusing from the floral tissue of 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> var. Northern Light using SPME and a gas chromatography. As many as 51 volatiles were detected in which caryophyllene was dominant, while β-myrcene and limonene were among the major monoterpenes identified. 
</p>
