<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">We are grateful to T. Wagener for providing his field dataset. W.M.L. would like to acknowledge the GEOTRACES program for the North Atlantic aerosol samples. 
  <bold class="bold">Funding:</bold> Support for this research was provided to A.I. by JSPS KAKENHI grant number JP16K00530 and Integrated Research Program for Advancing Climate Models (MEXT). S.M. acknowledges financial support by the Marie-Curie H2020-MSCA-IF-2015 grant ODEON (ID 705652). Part of model data post-processing was carried out on the Dutch national e-infrastructure with the support of the SURF Cooperative. N.M.M., R.A.S., and D.S.H. acknowledge support from DOE DE-SC0006791. This work was supported by grants to J.F.K. (NSF-CLD-1552519), W.M.L. (NSF-OCE-0929919 and NSF-OCE-1034764), and Y.G. (NSF-OPP-0944589). Support to Y.F. is provided by Argonne National Laboratory under the U.S. Department of Energy contract DE-AC02-06CH11357. This paper resulted from the deliberations of United Nations GESAMP Working Group 38, “The Atmospheric Input of Chemicals to the Ocean.” We thank the ICSU Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research, the U.S. NSF, the Global Atmosphere Watch of the World Meteorological Organization, the International Maritime Organization, and the University of East Anglia for their support. 
  <bold class="bold">Author contributions:</bold> This study was initiated by participants in a GESAMP Working Group 38 workshop in 2017 (A.I., S.M., M.K., N.M.M., A.R.B., T.J., M.S., Y.G., R.U.S., M.M.G.P., C.G., A.N., and R.A.D.). A.I. conceived the statistical analysis and analyzed the data. S.M. manipulated model fields to a common format. A.I., S.M., M.K., N.M.M., R.A.S., D.S.H., N.M., and M.S.J. contributed model products. A.R.B., T.J., S.M., S.B., Y.G., R.U.S., C.S.B., W.M.L., A.R.B., C.G., and Y.F. contributed measured data. J.F.K. provided the analysis for dust correction factors for model data. All authors contributed to writing the manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <bold class="bold">Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors.
 </p>
</ack>
