<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Liposomes are spherical bi-layered vesicles having phosphate head of phospholipids, which are hydrophilic and fatty acid tails (lipids), which are hydrophobic. There were many liposomal non-curcuminoids formulations studied recently with β-elemene and furanodiene. Chen et al. explained various formulations including liposomes of β-elemene and zedoary turmeric oil. Their formulation helped prolong the circulation of turmeric oil liposomes, reduce the irritation and improved the efficacy of β-elemene by encapsulating them in PVP-coated liposomes. Moreover, in vivo studies revealed that liposomal β-elemene were distributed in spleen, kidney, and liver in rats after intravenous administration. Another study summarized the recent advances in the liposomal delivery system of β-elemene exhibiting anticancer activity, mainly on lung cancer because of the various benefits such as availability, angiogenesis inhibition, induction of apoptosis, and enhancement of radiosensitivity. It also exhibited chemotherapeutic effects when combined with other anticancer agents and exhibited minimal side effects, such as damage of kidney and liver function. System biology, network pharmacology and clinical trials provided adequate evidence of β-elemene as a potent anti-lung cancer agent. This also proved that the advancement in molecular pharmaceutical technologies provided a broad platform for making it suitable for liposomal-based delivery [
 <xref rid="B122-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">122</xref>]. Furanodiene hold diverse pharmacological activities ranging from high lipophilicity to poor stability. Comparative research by loading furanodiene with biodegradable polylactide-co-glycolide (PLGA) and pegylated PLGA nanoparticles showed improvement in the stability, hydrophilicity and bioavailability of furanodiene, thus facilitating the permeation of furanodiene across Caco-2 cell monolayers [
 <xref rid="B123-biomolecules-09-00013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">123</xref>].
</p>
