<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Crayfish species predicted to become extraregional invaders by Larson &amp; Olden
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup> were 
 <italic>F. virilis, P. acutus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic>, while the species with the highest FI-ISK scores were 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic>, 
 <italic>P. leniusculus</italic> and 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. All of these species currently occur in the Netherlands. 
 <italic>Faxonius virilis</italic>, 
 <italic>P. leniusculus</italic>, and 
 <italic>P. acutus</italic> were first reported in 2004, 2005, and 2007 respectively, giving them roughly the same time frame for their invasions. However, 
 <italic>P. leniusculus</italic> (stage establishment) showed a far smaller geographical distribution compared to both other species (stage spread). This difference between prediction and current invasive status might be caused by the importance given to import for aquaculture in the FI-ISK tool, while this study is focused on the traits of invasion stages that follow after introduction. The other highest risk species, 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic>, are fully invasive in the Netherlands, but differ in their traits and invasiveness trajectory. Although more widely distributed, 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> is most frequently found in small linear lentic waters and slow flowing waters, which 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic> rarely inhabits. This conforms to the difference in aggression between these species; 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic> being more aggressive could lead to competitive exclusion of 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic>. While 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic>’s higher migration capacity should bring advantage over 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> in occupying new areas, the latter’s widespread occurrence suggests that parthenogenetic reproduction might counteract its lower migration capability. While 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic> can theoretically produce more clutches of eggs in a year, it requires individuals from both sexes to do so. In contrast, 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> can potentially reproduce with a single individual to establish a new population, increasing its invasiveness. Although facultative parthenogenesis in 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> has been experimentally confirmed
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>, its frequency of occurrence in wild populations is uncertain. And although not reported in the literature, parthenogenesis cannot be excluded in 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic>. Furthermore, 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic> has been shown to survive Dutch winter temperatures and for 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> a cold climate is part of its native range. This might explain the different distributions of these species in the Netherlands, with 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic> surviving in deeper waters where it can survive winter conditions and 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> being capable of surviving in different water types due to its inherent cold climate tolerance. Ultimately, these two species have a different combination of functional traits leading to alternative strategies that both are successful in becoming fully invasive.
</p>
