<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>National Nosocomial Infection Survey (NNIS) indicated that 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. were the fourth most common cause of nosocomial bloodstream infections during the 1990s. However, in more recent studies, it has been discovered that 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. are the third most frequent nosocomial bloodstream isolates (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Perlroth et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Lohse et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, 
 <italic>Candida</italic> is the third mainstream infection of central-line-associated bloodstream infections (CLABSIs) and the second most prominent reason for catheter-associated urinary tract infections in the United States. 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Lockhart (2014)</xref> Subsequently, the incidence of disseminated candidiasis which broadly refers to the mucosal, cutaneous, and deep-seated organ infection caused by 
 <italic>Candida</italic> genus has increased 15 to 20-fold in the last two decades (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Lockhart, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Pappas et al., 2018</xref>). It has been reported that systemic candidiasis, caused by 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> is one of the major reasons for death in nosocomial as well as opportunistically abysmal fungal infection in patients because of its ability to form a biofilm which decreases the susceptibility of fungal cells toward drug treatment. Consequently, it has been reported each year that up to 50% of systemic candidiasis adults patients and approximately 30% of the young population die due to candidiasis co-related with biofilms. Moreover, there is an estimation of 100 thousand deaths because of the infection initiated by biofilm formation. Approximately, $6500 millions are spent per year in the United States toward its treatment causing a high fiscal impact on the state (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Gulati and Nobile, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr">Silva et al., 2017</xref>). The five most widespread species, 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>, 
 <italic>C. glabrata</italic>, 
 <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic>, 
 <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, and 
 <italic>C. krusei</italic> are the reason behind 92 to 95% of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) cases in the United States, although, distribution of all five species might vary (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Kojic and Darouiche, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">Ten Cate et al., 2009</xref>). According to National Institute of Health (NIH) reports, pathogenic biofilms account for more than 80% of all microbial infections (
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">Ramage et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Perlroth et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">Tsui et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Lohse et al., 2018</xref>), of which 75% cases are of vaginal yeast infection in women once or more than once in their lifetime (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Perlroth et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">Yapar, 2014</xref>).
</p>
