<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lastly, pine nut characterization is important due to health, commercial, and sanitary concerns. However, only a few studies have been carried out analyzing the morphology of 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic>. Morphological variations of pine nut of 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic> were referred to the number of seeds per cone or to the percentage of developed and aborted seeds and the percentage of germination were studied in relation to the year of harvest [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-02057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Likewise, the seed coat composition of pine nut of several phenotypes of 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic> from the central region of Veracruz has shown statistically significant differences in the composition of fatty acids such as the myristic (3.4–9.1%), oleic (36.7–47.2%), and linoleic (32.9–44.5%) acids [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-02057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Besides, the dehulled seeds of 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic> in the United States were a good source of oil (64%), containing high levels of oleic (47%) and linoleic (41%) acids, and only 10% saturated acids [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-02057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. However, the proximal composition, phenolic content and antioxidant activity of pine nut of 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic> remain unknown. In order to implement a program of genetic improvement through the selection and reproduction of trees and provenances in the states of Hidalgo and Chihuahua, Mexico, it is necessary to characterize the desirable characteristics of the pine nut, such as (i) cones with seeds with greater size, (ii) seeds with thin testa, and (iii) seeds with higher nutritional content. The objective of this study was to make a description of morphometry, the proximal composition, the content of phenolic compounds, and the antioxidant capacity of pine nut from five populations of 
 <italic class="italic">P. cembroides</italic>, distributed in the two states above-mentioned.
</p>
