<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many factors can cause liver damage. In addition to physical factors (
 <italic>e.g</italic>., radiation) and biological factors (
 <italic>e.g</italic>., viruses), some chemicals are hepatotoxic. Carbon tetrachloride (CCl
 <sub>4</sub>) is often used in animal experiments to study the effects of substances on liver injury and the related mechanisms of action[
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The causal link between CCl
 <sub>4</sub> and liver diseases has been well established[
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. During the metabolism of CCl
 <sub>4</sub> in the liver, hepatotoxic metabolites and excessive free radicals such as trichloromethyl radical (∙CCl
 <sub>3</sub>) and trichloromethylperoxy radical (∙OOCCl
 <sub>3</sub>) are generated, accompanied by other free radicals (
 <italic>e.g</italic>., O
 <sup>2–</sup> and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>). Consequently, reductants (
 <italic>e.g</italic>., glutathione, GSH) are depleted, and antioxidant enzymes [
 <italic>e.g</italic>., superoxide dismutase (SOD) and catalase (CAT)] are inhibited, inducing oxidative stress[
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Meanwhile, the toxic metabolites and free radicals bind to phospholipid molecules embedded in the membranes of mitochondria, the endoplasmic reticulum, and hepatocytes, which leads to lipid peroxidation and membrane dysfunction or damage[
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, they can also bind with other macromolecules, such as proteins and DNA, and result in cell damage or death. Such a condition may aggravate hypoxia, induce the accumulation of more lipids, facilitate gut leakage and bacterial translocation, promote cytokine release, and increase hepatic iron accumulation, which exacerbates the production of highly reactive radicals[
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Therefore, oxidative stress is a major pathogenic factor for CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-induced liver injury.
</p>
