<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Comparisons of the antioxidant properties of 
 <italic>Echium</italic> species were investigated by Sakineh Abbaszadeh [
 <xref rid="B63-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] who found that hydroalcoholic extracts of 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> seeds yielded potent antioxidant properties. These extracts yielded the highest DPPH and FRAP values when compared to the leaf and stem extract from 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic>, as well as the same extract from 
 <italic>E. italicum</italic>. Leaves of 
 <italic>E. amoenum</italic> showed the highest TPC values (119.50 ± 2.00 mg GAE/g DW), with the seed extract showing the highest TFC values (62.17 ± 3.59 mg QE/g DW). Moreover, Nuraniye and Eruygur [
 <xref rid="B29-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] compared the antioxidant activity of 
 <italic>E. italicum</italic> L., 
 <italic>E. vulgare</italic> L., 
 <italic>E. parviflorum</italic>, and 
 <italic>E. angustifolium</italic> using DPPH assays and by comparing their ferrous ion chelating ability. Generally, root extracts were attributed to having better antioxidant effects than the herb extracts. This is hypothesised to be due to the roots being rich in phenols, such as tannins, anthraquinones, terpenoids, and flavonoids [
 <xref rid="B64-antioxidants-09-00722" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. A higher DPPH scavenging activity (81.43 ± 0.01%) was achieved by the ethanolic root extract of 
 <italic>E. italicum</italic>, whilst a higher iron-chelating activity (48.69 ± 0.04%) was achieved by 
 <italic>E. parviflorum</italic> ethanolic root extracts. During the investigation of the TPC and TFC quantities of these four species, it was shown that the root of 
 <italic>E. angustifolium</italic> obtained the highest TPC and TFC values at 38.86 ± 0.008 mg GAE/g and 56.12 ± 0.01 mg QE/g, respectively. This was followed by the 
 <italic>E. italicum</italic>, 
 <italic>E. vulgare</italic>, and 
 <italic>E. parviflorum</italic> extracts.
</p>
