<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Through its external hydrophilic and internal hydrophobic structure, cyclodextrin can wrap many small molecular drugs to improve the water solubility of insoluble drugs [
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. In fact, different types of cyclodextrins have different intensities of increasing water solubility. Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] prepared oleanolic acid 
 <italic>β</italic>-cyclodextrin inclusion compound by saturated aqueous solution method and measured the drug solubility by HPLC. The result showed that the inclusion compound solubility in water increased by 3.4 times. After adding NaOH to form a salt, solubility increased by 107 times. While the polyvinylpyrrolidone addition cannot improve the saturates solubility and also affect the oleanolic acid activity. Wang [
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] used hydroxypropyl 
 <italic>β</italic>-cyclodextrin to prepare oleanolic acid inclusion compound and established a pharmacokinetic detection method (HPLC-MC) after oral administration of oleanolic acid. Finally, the absolute bioavailability of acid-hydroxypropyl 
 <italic>β</italic>-cyclodextrin inclusion compound in rats was analyzed, and the results showed that the absolute bioavailability was 2.010%, compared with relevant literature reports [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]; oral bioavailability (
 <italic>F</italic> = 0.7%) has been improved to a certain extent. Ren et al. [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] used synthetic long-chain amino 
 <italic>β</italic>-cyclodextrin derivatives tetra-ethylene pentamine-
 <italic>β</italic>-cyclodextrin to prepare oleanolic acid inclusion compounds. It can be concluded that the oleanolic acid water solubility was improved 2100 times. Oprean et al. [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] chose the antitumor activity in vitro of oleanolic acid cyclodextrin inclusion compound as the index and selected 2-hydroxypropyl-b-cyclodextrin as the most suitable inclusion material. Conversely, it is reported that [
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] the interaction strength between oleanolic acid and natural 
 <italic>β</italic>-cyclodextrin derivatives (
 <italic>β</italic>-CDs) is higher than that of the corresponding hydroxypropyl modified 
 <italic>β</italic>-CDs, and the complexation constant of 
 <italic>γ</italic>-CDs is 6 times of 
 <italic>β</italic>-CDs. The oleanolic acid preparation by cyclodextrin inclusion technique can indeed improve the solubility, but the research on its metabolic absorption and bioavailability in vivo is still insufficient.
</p>
