<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Another strategy described in the literature is the incorporation of essential oils into cellulose-based matrices imparting the antimicrobial property that cellulosic material lacks [
 <xref rid="B100-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>]. For instance, Heredia-Herrero et al. developed an antimicrobial plastic film based on the cellulose derivative ethyl cellulose (EC) [
 <xref rid="B101-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>]. This derivative comes from the substitution of some hydroxyl groups of the cellulose backbone with ethyl ether groups. EC is soluble in organic solvents but insoluble in water, non-toxic, versatile, and edible. From EC, it is possible to form tough films that not very flexible; hence, the addition of plasticizers is needed. Common plasticizers, being low-molecular-weight components, have the problem of migration from the polymer matrix, which affects the material’s performance on the desired application. However, what is even more important and relevant to this contribution is that certain plasticizers also lead to serious environmental pollution in addition to affecting human health [
 <xref rid="B102-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>]. The strategy followed by Heredia-Guerrero et al. was the combination of EC with acetoxy-polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS), which interact to form hydrogen bonds, and with a clove essential oil. The EC-based film’s antimicrobial activity was tested against, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> bacteria. The obtained results revealed that biofilm formation by 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> was significantly inhibited due to the presence of the essential oil, with a film inhibition of 44% and 57% after 24 h and 48 h, respectively. In the case of 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>, significant inhibition occurred after 48 h, with 62% of biofilm inhibition [
 <xref rid="B101-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>]. In conclusion, the authors provided the cellulosic films with antimicrobial properties as well as improved their flexibility so that they could have potential application in food packaging.
</p>
