<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recently, we have focused on 
 <italic class="italic">Phania matricarioides</italic> (Spreng.) Griseb. (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01615-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) (Asteraceae or Compositae family), which has been traditionally used for digestive conditions (stomach pain, bad digestion and diarrhea) and dermatological lesions [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">P. matricarioides</italic> is included in a very large and widespread family of flowering plants that grow for ornamental purposes [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], but the family also represents a certain economic importance due to the provision of products such as cooking oils, lettuce, sunflower seeds, artichokes, sweetening agents, coffee substitutes and herbal teas [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. In addition, many species possess medicinal properties, including antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], antiparasitic [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], anticancer [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] and hepatoprotective [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In particular, the antidiarrheal, analgesic, anti-inflammatory and anti-oxidant effects of extracts have been demonstrated and correlated with some active common phytochemicals such as phenolic compounds, tannins, flavonoids, lactonic compounds, triterpenes or steroids, terpenes and organic acids [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-24-01615" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. However, as far as we know, the EO from 
 <italic class="italic">P. matricarioides</italic> has not been chemically characterized, and its biological properties have not been scientifically demonstrated.
</p>
