<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This method is applicable when the protein is crystallized in delivery medium (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). This method was used for membrane protein crystals in an LCP (e.g., monoolein), which can be used as a delivery medium [
 <xref rid="B60-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Lipidic cubic phase is an artificial membrane-mimicking gel-like material that forms spontaneously upon mixing of specific lipids and an aqueous solution [
 <xref rid="B61-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. Membrane proteins can be reconstituted into the lipid bilayer of LCP (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>A–C). By adding the precipitant for crystallization (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>D), the lipid/protein mixture undergoes crystal nucleation and growth [
 <xref rid="B62-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>E). Since LCP is a viscous material suitable for use as a delivery medium, LCP-containing crystals can be directly used for SX experiments at ambient pressure after removing the crystallization solution (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01094-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>E) [
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Meanwhile, in vacuum, the sample delivery using LCP is required to mix shorter chain lipids (e.g., 9.7 MAG or 7.9 MAG) to avoid the transition of the LCP phase to the lamellar crystalline (Lc) phase (see below) [
 <xref rid="B63-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. On the other hand, previous SFX experiments attempted to crystallize phycocyanin (PC) from 
 <italic class="italic">Thermosynechococcus elongatus</italic> in agarose gel for use as a delivery medium [
 <xref rid="B54-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. Due to its size and low diffusion constant, PC did not crystallize in agarose; however, since crystallization of other proteins in agarose gel has already been reported [
 <xref rid="B64-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijms-20-01094" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>], it can be applied as an LCP in SX studies.
</p>
