<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Plant seeds are not merely reproductive organs, they are also carriers of microorganism, particularly, inherent and non-invasive characteristic endophytes in host plant. Therefore, in this study, the endophytic diversity of 
  <italic>Angelica</italic> seeds was studied and compared with endophytes isolated from healthy leaves, stems, roots, and seeds of 
  <italic>A</italic>. 
  <italic>sinensis</italic> using 20 different media. The metabolites of endophytic strains were evaluated with six different methods for their antioxidant activity and the paper disc diffusion method for antimicrobial activities. As a result, 226 endophytes were isolated. Compared with the biodiversity and abundance of uncultured fungi from 
  <italic>Angelica</italic> seed, the result showed that the most frequent endophytic fungi were 
  <italic>Alternaria</italic> sp. as seen in artificial media; moreover, compared with artificial media, the pathogenic fungi, including 
  <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp. and 
  <italic>Pseudallescheria</italic> sp., were not found from the 
  <italic>Angelica</italic> seed, the results suggested it may not be inherent endophytes in plants. In addition, bacteria from seven phyla were identified by high-throughput sequencing, while five phyla of endophytic bacteria were not isolated on artificial media including 
  <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>, 
  <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>, 
  <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, 
  <italic>Microgenomates</italic>, and 
  <italic>Saccharibacteria</italic>. Furthermore, the sample JH-4 mycelium displayed the best antioxidant activity, and the active constituent may be a flavonoid as determined by total phenol and flavonoid content. Moreover, YH-12-1 mycelium had strong inhibitory activity against the five tested strains and the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) against 
  <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and 
  <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> was found to be 25 μg/mL. Our results confirm that plant endophytes are rich in biodiversity and contain important resource of many uncultured microorganisms.
 </p>
</abstract>
