<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> was first recorded by Linnaeus in 1738 and is mostly distributed between approximately 45° N and 40° S in the Americas [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> has been recorded in Beijing, Tianjin, Henan, Hebei, Shandong, Fujian, Sichuan, Yunnan, Hubei, Hunan, Guangdong, Guangxi, Hainan, Taiwan, Hong Kong, and other provinces or cities in China [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> possesses four distinct developmental stages: egg, larva, pupa, and adult. In nature, 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> lays its eggs in dry areas near wet, rotting organisms. Temperature, humidity, and light intensity are the main environmental factors affecting adult mating and egg laying [
 <xref rid="B10-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The incubation time of the eggs is typically 4–14 days and varies with season, region, and temperature [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. According to Kim, there are six instars in the larval phase [
 <xref rid="B38-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], and the larvae range in size from 1.8 mm to 20 mm, with 20-mm larvae being referred to as mature larvae. 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> initiate feeding immediately upon hatching, with consumption rates increasing greatly after the 3rd instar. When the larvae reach the 6th instar, they cease feeding and initiate pupation, subsequently becoming adults. Adult females initiate egg laying approximately 2–3 days after mating, and female fecundity can reach 900 eggs/female [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. The performance and nutrition of the 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> vary with substrate, and substrates rich in protein and oil are more conducive to the accumulation of protein and grease in this insect [
 <xref rid="B40-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>].
</p>
