<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45">In present EP and ChP monographs, TLC analysis is used mostly for TCM identification and adulterants differentiation. It is a simple, rapid method which allows the simultaneous analysis of multiple samples in parallel, but suffers from the limitations such as low separation efficiency, poor reproducibility and poor sensitivity in quantification. Nevertheless, with the development of high-performance TLC (HPTLC) and the introduction of modern instrument that can provide standardized conditions, the performance of TLC has been significantly improved. Up to date, TLC and HPTLC has been successfully applied to the quantitative analysis of active ingredients in a series of herbal drugs including Astragali Radix [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Magnoliae Officinalis Cortex [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and Glycyrrhizae Radix et Rhizoma [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], etc. In addition, TLC-bioautography that combines TLC separation with bioassay provides a supreme method for the screening of bioactive compounds from herbal drugs directly. It can not only show the activity of the herbal drugs but also reveal which components contribute to the activity. Due to the merits of being simple, convenient and requiring no laborious isolation, TLC-bioautography has been widely employed for screening and identification of herbal drugs components with bioactivity such as anti-microbial [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], acetylcholinesterase inhibition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], α- and β-glucosidase inhibition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], free radical scavenging and antioxidation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Actually, ChP has already included TLC-bioautography against 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl radical for the identification of Rehmanniae Radix. Furthermore, coupling of TLC with MS or LC–MS can offer the possibility for on-line identification of the active compound, which enhances the potential of TLC in screening, identification and quantification of active constituents of herbal drugs.
</p>
