<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We analysed secondary plant compounds for 57 of the 
 <italic>P. padus</italic> and 56 of the 
 <italic>P. serotina</italic> plants for which we sampled herbivores in 2012 (see above). Immediately after each herbivore sampling, we harvested five young leaves and five old leaves from each tree, and kept these in separately labelled bags in a Dewar flask with solid CO
 <sub>2</sub> in the field. All samples were ground under liquid nitrogen and freeze-dried. We carried out NMR-analysis as described previously (
 <xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Pimenta et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Kim, Choi &amp; Verpoorte, 2010</xref>). Briefly, extracts in CH
 <sub>3</sub>OH-d4 and KH
 <sub>2</sub>PO
 <sub>4</sub> buffer in D
 <sub>2</sub>O (1:1) were quantitatively analysed for prunasin and amygdalin, using 1H-NMR spectroscopy on a 500 MHz Bruker DMX-500 spectrometer (Bruker, Karlsruhe, Germany). Purity of quantitated 1H-NMR signals was evaluated using several two-dimensional NMR experiments. Correlations were investigated between concentrations of each of the cyanogenic glycosides and herbivore load. We treated generalists (category G, see above) and specialists (categories R, P, M, and O) separately. In view of the high numbers of 
 <italic>Yponomeuta evonymellus</italic> and 
 <italic>Rhopalosiphum padi</italic> on some 
 <italic>P. padus</italic> trees, we log-transformed the specialist herbivore load for 
 <italic>P. padus</italic>. The relative amounts of cyanogenic glycosides were calculated per sample by taking the integrals in buckets 
 <italic>δ</italic>5.92 (for prunasin) and 
 <italic>δ</italic>5.88 + 
 <italic>δ</italic>5.84 (for amygdalin). Correlations were tested with parametric Pearson’s tests for the data on generalists and (in view of the large numbers of samples devoid of specialists) with non-parametric Spearman’s tests for the data on specialists.
</p>
