<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">The Dutch food and consumer product safety authority (NVWA) does not officially register crayfish aquaculture companies and records of crayfish trade and import are not digitally available. To determine which nonindigenous crayfish are present in the Netherlands, a web search was performed (20-06-2018) for crayfish being sold. The search terms ‘aquarium store crayfish’ and ‘buy aquarium crayfish’ were used (in Dutch) in two separate searches on 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.google.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.google.com</ext-link>, resulting in 16 websites offering 19 species of live crayfish in the Netherlands (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> online). Species only sold on a single website were excluded due to lower potential for introduction into the wild. Per genus, the three species available on most websites were selected for further research. For 
 <italic>C. boesemani</italic> several colour morphs were available for sale, which were treated as a single species. Additionally, 
 <italic>C. destructor</italic> was selected since it is a habitat generalist with a widespread native range
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>, and it has already established populations in Europe; Italy and Spain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. The search resulted in a list of ten species: 
 <italic>C. diminitus</italic>, 
 <italic>C. patzcuerensis</italic>, 
 <italic>C. puer</italic>, 
 <italic>C. quadricarinatus</italic>, 
 <italic>C. boesemani</italic>, 
 <italic>C. destructor</italic>, 
 <italic>C. papuanus</italic>, 
 <italic>P. alleni, P. clarkii</italic> and 
 <italic>P. virginalis</italic>. Species with verified sightings in the wild in the Netherlands, 
 <italic>A. leptodactylus</italic>, 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic>, 
 <italic>F. virilis</italic>, 
 <italic>P. leniusculus, P. acutus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. clarkii</italic>, were obtained from a dataset from Stichting European Invertebrate Survey (EIS)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup>. This resulted in a total of fifteen crayfish species for further analysis (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). 
 <italic>Procambarus virginalis</italic> and 
 <italic>C. quadricarinatus</italic> have been reported only once in the Netherlands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> and were for the purpose of this study not considered to occur in the wild.
</p>
