<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0005">Medicinal plants are being used for human health care management in traditional medicine for centuries. High demand in the products from medicinal plants increased the commercial production and formulation of various herbal-based cosmetics and nutritional supplements (
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Ekor. 2014</xref>). Zingiberaceae family has around 52 plant genera and more than 1300 plant species, and also, many of these plant products were in use for various human health benefits (
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Kress et al., 2002</xref>). Some of the Zingiberaceae plants were reported for their therapeutic usage (
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Basak et al., 2010</xref>). Among those, 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> and 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> are the most important medicinal plants, and they have possessed a variety of medicinal values. 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> is an aromatic plant, commonly known as turmeric. In Ayurveda and Siddha, the vegetal root of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> has been used for the production of various pharmaceutical formulations for the different ailments, including wounds, acne, common cold, parasitic infections, urinary tract infection, and liver diseases (
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Chainani-Wu, 2003</xref>). This plant also possesses various important medicinal properties like antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, anti-human immunodeficiency virus properties (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Araújo and Leon, 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Boaz et al., 2011</xref>). Polyphenol curcumin is a vital phytocompound responsible for the pharmacodynamics action of 
 <italic>C. longa</italic> (
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">Sharma et al., 2005</xref>). Mainly, it has potential anti-cancer property against liver, pancreatic, colon, cervical, lung, brain, breast, and bone cancers (
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Maheshwari et al., 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Bar-Sela et al., 2010</xref>).
</p>
