<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">The potential for insects to be included in the formulation of animal feeds is gaining importance thanks to their high protein content and well-balanced amino acid profiles (Rumpold and Schluter 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">2013</xref>; van Huis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2013</xref>; Barroso et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2014</xref>; Henry et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2015</xref>; Barragan-Fonseca et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2017</xref>). Promising results with insect meals have been obtained in carnivorous species including rainbow trout (St-Hilaire et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">2007</xref>; Sealey et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">2011</xref>; Lock et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2016</xref>; Stadtlander et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">2017</xref>). Microalgae have mostly been used for DHA and EPA substitution and as feed supplement rather than as FM substitution, yet their nutritional values are promising for aquaculture feeding with high contents of protein and high protein digestibility (Nakagawa and Montgomery 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2007</xref>; Teimouri et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">2013</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Spirulina platensis</italic> is commonly described as a microalga although it belongs to the cyanobacteria due to several common characteristics such as a prokaryotic structure and peptidoglycan-based cell walls, as opposed to cellulose in algae (Belay et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">1996</xref>; Spolaore et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">2006</xref>; Becker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2007</xref>). Yeast, another micro-organism widely known in animal nutrition to provide high quality nutrients, can also be used as a probiotic and for its immune stimulant properties in the form of yeast cell walls (Ferreira et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ringø et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">2010</xref>; Navarrete and Tovar-Ramrez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">2014</xref>; Broadway et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2015</xref>). Indeed, yeast cell walls have mainly been used in fish nutrition for their immune function enhancement but have not yet been tested as a substitute for FM (Robersten et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">1990</xref>; Jørgensen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">1993</xref>; Gopalakannan and Arul 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2010</xref>; Refstie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2010</xref>; Meena et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
