<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>AKR1B10 (Aldo-Keto Reductase 1B10), which is highly expressed in normal gastrointestinal epithelial tissues, but low or no expression in other normal tissues, is an NADPH-dependent reductase whose function is mainly to catalyze the reduction of various carbonyl compounds. AKR1B10 has also been found to be overexpressed in human non-small cell carcinoma, liver cancer, breast cancer, oral squamous cell carcinoma and pancreatic cancer, and is involved in the occurrence, development and survival of tumor cells through a variety of mechanisms, including cytotoxic reactive carbonyl compounds Detoxification, enhance the migration and proliferation potential of tumor cells, regulate cellular fatty acid synthesis and lipid metabolism, and participate in the acquisition of multidrug resistance in tumor cells. HMCB (7-hydroxy-2-(4-methoxyphenylimino)-2H-chromene-3-carboxylic acid benzylamide) is the most effective AKR1B10 inhibitor currently but does not have a high selectivity. Satoshi et al. took HMCB as a starting material to synthesize a series of coumarin derivatives, which have stronger selectivity and inhibition for AKR1B10. These coumarin derivatives significantly inhibited the migration and proliferation of lung cancer cells, increased the cisplatin sensitivity of cisplatin-resistant lung cancer cells, and inhibited the metastasis and invasion potential of cisplatin-resistant lung cancer cells (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Awale et al. suggested that AKR1B10 may also be related to the tolerance of pancreatic cancer to nutritional deficiency. Human pancreatic cancer cells are resistant to nutritional starvation by switching energy metabolism, allowing them to survive in tumor microenvironments where blood vessels are scarce. Awale synthesized a series of coumarin derivatives based on HMCB structure and evaluated their inhibition against the resistance to nutritional starvation of human pancreatic cancer cells. 7-hydroxy-2-oxo-2H-chromene-3-carboxylic acid (3-phenylpropyl)amide (compound 2c) showed highly selective cytotoxicity on human pancreatic cancer with a PC50 value of 0.44 mM but no toxicity on conventional nutrient-rich media (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).
</p>
