<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47">In this study, we investigated the composition and diversity of endophytic bacterial communities in three medicinal licorices roots using high-throughput sequencing technology, which provides a large amount of data with more accuracy than that obtained in previous studies using traditional technology [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Our study showed no significant differences in the alpha diversity index, which is used to describe the diversity and complexity of the bacterial community, between the interaction effect planting year and species of medicinal licorices (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). However, our results showed the indexes of endophytic bacterial diversity in year 3 were slightly lower than those in year 2 (Supplementary Table S
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>), which, combined with the observation that growth years had a significant impact on the contents of GIA, GTF and LI, and showed an upward trend with the increasing number of growing year (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We speculate that the accumulation of bioactive compounds in roots regulates the endophytic bacterial diversity and that this is mediated via mechanisms that reduce the relative abundance through the antibacterial effects of bioactive compounds or chemical signals that negatively affect growth [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Although the mechanism by which bioactive compounds regulate endophytic bacteria is still unclear, this discovery may form the basis of further in-depth research. In addition, studies have shown that plant organs, rainfall and temperature are the main drivers of endophytic components [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. In this study, climatic conditions, especially rainfall, in year 2 were significantly higher than those in year 3 (Supplementary Table S
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). This difference may change endophytic bacteria diversity, suggesting that these species are likely to be affected by climate changes in the near future.
</p>
