<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50">Although many studies the composition of plant endophytic bacterial communities are based on Illumina MiSeq technology [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], few studies have focused on the influence of planting year and species on the composition of endophytic bacterial communities in 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza</italic>. Our results show that the endophytic bacteria community is affected by the planting year and species of 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza</italic> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), which helps to fill the knowledge gap in this field. Endophytic bacteria exist in plant species as part of the root microbiome. The endophytic bacteria community (species diversity: abundance and relative abundance) in plants is dynamic and affected by abiotic and biological factors, such as soil conditions, biogeography and plant species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. In this study, the content of bioactive compounds in roots was shown to be the driving factor in differences in the composition and distribution of endophytic bacteria community (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>, Supplementary Table S
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>), with the total flavonoid content shown to explain the differences in the composition and distribution of endophytic bacteria community to the greatest extent. Flavonoids, which are a variety of polyphenolic compounds produced in plants by secondary metabolism, can act as a signal of interaction between plants and many microorganisms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. For example, flavonoids can act as chemoattractants and inducers of nodulation (nod) and other genes in rhizobia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. In recent years, a large number of studies including research by Márton Szoboszlay et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] have also shown that flavonoids have an impact on bacterial communities.
</p>
