<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Plant-derived compounds such as cumin, oregano, and extracts of capsaicin, cinnamaldehyde, and carvacrol have been shown to improve the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus, Bifidobacteria</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Enterococcus</italic>, and therefore may indirectly impact pathogen concentrations through competitive exclusion (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kivanç et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jamroz et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manzanilla et al., 2004</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manzanilla et al. (2001)</xref> demonstrated how XT, a mixture of carvacrol, cinnamaldehyde, and capsaicin, increased 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> cecal counts in post-weaning pigs when provided in the feed. However, these interactions are complicated as the addition of 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> has been attributed to an increase in 
 <italic class="italic">Bifidobacterium</italic> (
 <xref rid="B280" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thibodeau et al., 2015</xref>). Further research must be performed to determine if, or which, EOs exhibit antimicrobial qualities against 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> that may also simultaneously support GIT bacteria that are antagonistic to 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic>. While EOs do not appear to operate as substrates for 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> or other probiotics and are therefore not prebiotics, their indirect impacts on the intestinal mucosal layer promote an environment suitable for the growth of “beneficial” bacteria, which in turn, have the potential to reduce 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> concentrations. Other studies found that EOs, including cumin, orange oil, and oregano, have an inhibitory effect on 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. (
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kivanç et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Elgayyar et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Delaquis et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chalova et al., 2010</xref>). As such, there are limitations for the application of EOs to poultry that must be addressed.
</p>
