<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The influence by EOs on the intestine has primarily focused on crypt depth and mucosal thickness (
 <xref rid="B301" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vidanarachchi et al., 2005</xref>). Broiler diets supplemented with 100 mg/kg of 5% carvacrol, 3% cinnamaldehyde, and 2% of capsicum oleoresin exhibited an impact on the jejunal mucosa. A higher jejunal wall villi layer was observed along with an increase in thickness of the mucosa layer, which helps prevent bacterial colonization (
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jamroz et al., 2006</xref>). This is because while the thicker mucosa may potentially entrap more bacteria, a thick mucosal layer may also prevent adhesion to the intestinal villi and subsequent GIT colonization by decreasing the proximity of bacteria to the intestinal binding sites (
 <xref rid="B288" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Turner, 2009</xref>). Broilers supplemented with thymol or garlic powder (1 g/kg) in their diet showed similar effects in the intestinal morphology (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Demir et al., 2005</xref>). However, in pigs, villi length was either decreased or unaffected by supplementation of EOs (
 <xref rid="B209" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Namkung et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nofrarias et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kroismayr et al., 2008</xref>). Prevention of bacterial adhesion would be beneficial for inhibiting 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> but could have deleterious effects on nutrient absorption due to changes within the GIT microbial community. For instance, SCFA producing bacteria, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Bifidobacterium</italic>, have been shown to have positive impacts on nutrient absorption and overall bird health and antimicrobial strategies that prevent their growth could be detrimental. However, EOs have been reported to improve the colonization of bacteria that are non-pathogenic and may benefit the overall health of the microbiota (
 <xref rid="B309" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wenk, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B314" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Windisch and Kroismayr, 2007</xref>).
</p>
