<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Growth rate improvement of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus, Bifidobacteria</italic>, and other probiotic bacteria in avian hosts is viewed as a potential mechanism inhibiting avian colonization of foodborne diseases such as 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> (
 <xref rid="B254" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Santini et al., 2010</xref>). In simulated environments, 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> has been shown to inhibit the colonization of undesired bacteria such as 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chang and Chen, 2000</xref>). Four strains of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> (10
 <sup class="sup">4</sup>/ml) and 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> (10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup>/mL) were added to a simulated chicken digestive system consisting of pH adjusted veronal buffers. Veronal buffer contains 0.15 mM CaCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, 141 mM NaCl, 0.5 mM MgCl
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, 0.1% gelatin, 1.8 mM sodium barbital, and 3.1 mM barbituric acid (Sigma-Aldrich; St. Louis, MO, United States) and was subsequently adjusted to a pH of 4.5, 4.4, 2.6, 6.2, and 6.3 to represent the crop, proventriculus, gizzard, small intestine, and large intestine, respectively. A simulated chicken digestive system was also created by adjusting each veronal buffer with 0.1N HCl or with veronal buffer at pH 9.6 to simulate passage within each intestinal organ. Within individually simulated GIT compartments, and the simulated chicken digestive system as a whole, significant 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> reductions were observed compared to the control with no addition of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic>. In the gizzard, while a reduction from approximately 6 log CFU/mL to approximately 4 log CFU/mL of 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> was observed within 90 min, likely due to the low pH, a 4 log reduction was observed when 6 log CFU/mL of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> was added. These results might in part be due to the ability for 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> to produce bacteriocins that are inhibitory to 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> (
 <xref rid="B193" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Messaoudi et al., 2012</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B275" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stern et al. (2006)</xref> applied purified bacteriocin OR-7, produced by 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus salivarius</italic> NRRL B-30514, to the feed of broilers that were challenged with 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic>. Compared to controls, 6 log CFU/g cecal content reductions were observed independently of the 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> strain utilized.
</p>
