<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Enterococcus</italic> strains, which can produce SCFAs, were tested 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> and were also found to be inhibitory to 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chaveerach et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Allameh et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chaveerach et al. (2004)</xref> cultured five 
 <italic class="italic">Enterococcus</italic> and five 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> strains from healthy chickens and grew them in Mueller-Hinton broth. The broth was subsequently centrifuged, and the supernatant was separated from the bacteria. The supernatant was neutralized to a pH of 6.2 and treated with pronase and catalase to break down bacteriocins and hydrogen peroxide, respectively. Once the supernatants were confirmed to be free of bacteria, they were applied in a well-diffusion agar assay against 10 individual strains of 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic>. The supernatant with the highest bactericidal activity came from a 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> strain labeled P93, which produced a zone of inhibition of 9 to 15 mm and was able to impact the growth of all 10 strains of 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic>. This strain was also grown in co-culture with 
 <italic class="italic">C. jejuni</italic> C2150, each at an initial inoculum of 7 log CFU/mL, and after 48 h, 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> was not isolated from the culture. 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> C2150 was also grown with 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> strain P104, which did not exhibit any antimicrobial effects in the well-diffusion agar, but by 72 h 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> concentrations were approximately 1.5 log CFU/mL lower than the positive control at 7.5 CFU/mL. This study indicates that not only can 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> directly compete for nutrients and colonization niche with 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic>, but some strains can also employ antimicrobials to reduce their population numbers further.
</p>
