<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Functional food is mainly a conventional food, which is consumed as a part of a usual diet. The term functional food was firstly used by Japan in the 1980s to dedicate food products that are fortified with specific constituents with beneficial physiological effects 
 <xref rid="R09" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>. Foods that are marketed under functional category contain added technologically developed ingredients 
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>, and important biologically active compounds 
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>. These foods provide health benefits by mediating specific physiological functions in the body and are marketed and consumed for this value-added property. Reformulation of meat is achieved by the addition of fibres, proteins, polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA), antioxidants, etc. A functional food should possess certain requirements, i.e. it should be derived from a naturally occurring ingredient; consumed as a part of a regular diet and should be involved in the regulation of certain human process such as age delaying, risk prevention from diseases and improvement in immunological abilities 
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>. Sometimes in functional foods, one or more additional ingredients are added, that shows health benefits above and beyond as compared to those of regular foods 
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>. Functional food is widely used in developed countries due to their high shelf life, advanced food technology, health benefits, and known importance. Food nowadays is not only eaten for hunger satisfaction and necessary nutrition but also for preventing nutrition-related disorders and for mental-physical well being of an individual 
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>. Hence, food nutritionist and technologist are targeting to develop functional meat products with great efforts that possess natural antioxidants and antimicrobials, low fat, lesser sodium content, enriched with dietary fibres and ω-3 and ω-6 fatty acids 
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref> as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>.
</p>
