<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY2005 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6607056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(19)35651-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e02005</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e02005</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Production of protein hydrolysate containing antioxidant activity from <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Firmansyah</surname><given-names>Mochamad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abduh</surname><given-names>Muhammad Yusuf</given-names></name><email>yusuf@sith.itb.ac.id</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>School of Life Sciences and Technology, Institut Teknologi Bandung, Jalan Ganesha 10, 40132 Bandung, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Bioscience and Biotechnology Research Center, Institut Teknologi Bandung, Jalan Ganesha 10, 40132 Bandung, Indonesia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>yusuf@sith.itb.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e02005</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Protein hydrolysate is a complex mixture of peptide and amino acids that can be produced from various biomass sources including insects, such as black soldier fly larvae (<italic>Hermetia illicens</italic>) due to its relatively high protein content. This study aimed to investigate the potential of protein hydrolysate from black soldier fly larvae as a bioactive hydrolysate through enzymatic hydrolysis using bromelain. Black soldier fly larvae contain 25.6% protein and 35.5% lipids as determined by a proximate analysis. Experiments for the enzymatic hydrolysis of black soldier fly larvae was designed using a central composite design with three factors particularly enzyme concentration (1&#x02013;5%), pH (6&#x02013;8) and time of hydrolysis (3&#x02013;24 hours). The protein hydrolysate had a yield of 10.70 % (on a weight basis) based on defatted biomass with a productivity of 21 mg/L/batch. The protein concentration varied between 240-310 &#x003bc;g/ml with the degree of hydrolysis varied in the range of 10&#x02013;43%. The protein hydrolysate had a molecular weight in the range of 14&#x02013;25 kDa based on Sodium Dodecyl Sulfate Polyacrylamide Gel Electrophoresis. The amino acid composition of the protein hydrolysate was also determined and mainly consists of lysine (8.0%), leucine (7.7%), and valine (7.2%). The protein hydrolysate may find application as a bioactive hydrolysate with an antioxidant activity of 72.6 in terms of its ability to inhibit free radicals 2,2-diphenyl-2-picryl hydrazyl with IC<sub>50</sub> of 0.84%.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Biochemistry</kwd><kwd>Biotechnology</kwd><kwd>Chemical engineering</kwd><kwd>Black soldier fly larvae</kwd><kwd>Enzymatic hydrolysis</kwd><kwd>Protein hydrolysate</kwd><kwd>Amino acid</kwd><kwd>Antioxidant activity</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Protein hydrolysate is a complex mixture of oligopeptides, peptides, and free amino acids produced from partial or extensive protein hydrolysis process (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Clare and Swaizgood, 2000</xref>). The global protein hydrolysate demand is estimated to increase to 160 kilo tons in 2024 with an economic value of 800 million US dollars (Market Research <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">MarketsandMarkets, 2018</xref>). Several types of protein hydrolysates have special biological activities (bioactive hydrolysates), such as antioxidant activity (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Halim et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>), antihypertensive, antimicrobial and anticoagulants and so on, therefore they are very beneficial and needed in various fields (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">De Castro and Sato, 2015</xref>). The properties of protein hydrolysate depend on the molecular size, amino acid composition, and amino acids sequence that shape their structure (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Putra et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Currently the primary use of protein hydrolysate for human needs is as a raw material in children nutrition products, toiletries, energy drinks, and supplements (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Clemente et&#x000a0;al., 1999</xref>). Protein hydrolysate is also used for other purposes such as mixture of growth mediums in biotechnology-based industries (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Pasupuleti and Demain, 2010</xref>) and as a high-nutritious animal feed mixture (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Mart&#x000ed;nez-Alvarez et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). The main substrate used in the production of protein hydrolysates is still dominated by various types of animal protein sources such as beef, fish, milk, and eggs, as well as plant sources like wheat and soybeans (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Hou et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Animal and plant protein sources that are used as a substrate in the protein hydrolysates production are also used in human dietary needs, which may cause a competition in resources (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Pasupuleti and Demain, 2010</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">Black soldier fly (BSF) belongs to the order of diptera that is not a pathogenic vector for both human and livestock (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). Black soldier fly larvae (BSFL) is known for its ability to convert organic waste into protein and lipid rich biomass (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000fc;ller et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Abduh et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). BSFL is also utilized as a natural controller of house fly population (<italic>M.&#x000a0;domestica</italic>) and flies that are harmful to humans (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Sheppard, 1983</xref>), biomarkers for forensic entomology (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Pujol- Luz et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>), animal and fish feed (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Magalh&#x000e3;es et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>), biological agents in livestock waste management (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Beskin et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>), and being used as a biodiesel substrate (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). BSFL has the potential to be further developed as high-value bioproducts, such as protein hydrolysates. Recent works that report systematic studies on the production of protein hydrolysate from BSFL are still very scarce. Hence, this study aims to investigate the potential valorization of BSFL as a substrate to produce protein hydrolysate.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Materials</title><p id="p0025">Dried BSFL used in this study was obtained from a local BSFL producer, Biomagg&#x000ae; (Depok, Indonesia). The BSFL was fed with residual mixture, vegetable, and bread crumbs. N-hexane was obtained from PT Brataco (Indonesia), bromelain enzyme powder was obtained from PT Bromelain Enzim Indonesia, O-pthyaldyaldehyde was obtained from Sigma Aldrich (Singapore), HCl, NaOH, Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, Commassie Blue - R, 96% ethanol, distill water, Dithiotheritol (DTT) 99%, and sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) were obtained from the chemicals warehouse of School of Life Science and Technology ITB (Bandung, Indonesia).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Proximate analysis of BSFL</title><p id="p0030">Biomass composition of BSFL was determined by proximate analysis out at the Integrated Chemical Laboratory of IPB, Bogor, Indonesia. Determination of total crude protein content was carried out using a standard Kjeldahl method with a total crude protein content calculated as %N and a conversion factor of 6.25. Determination of total crude lipid was carried out using a standard soxhlet extraction method (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">AOAC, 2012</xref>). Determination of total water and ash content was carried out using standard gravimetric method (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">AOAC, 2012</xref>). Determination of total crude carbohydrate content was obtained from the remaining percentage of another biomass component based on <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (1)</xref>. All parameters for determining the proximate content are calculated based on percentage (%) of weight per weight (w/w).<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label>Carbohydrates (%) = (Total biomass) % - (Protein + Lipid + Ash + Water) %</disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Defatting process of BSFL</title><p id="p0035">Separation of lipid component from BSFL biomass was carried out using a Soxhlet extraction method (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abduh et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). N-hexane was used as a solvent with a ratio of 1: 4 of biomass to solvent. The extraction process was carried out for 6 hours at a temperature of 70 &#x000b0;C. The mixture of oil and solvent was separated using a rotary evaporator for 2 hours at a temperature of 60 &#x000b0;C until the n-hexane solvent was completely separated and a pure oil fraction was obtained. The yield (% w/w) of oil was determined based on <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (2)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label>Oil yield (% w/w) = (weight of oil (g)) / (initial sample weight (g)) &#x000d7; 100%</disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Protein hydrolysis of BSFL</title><p id="p0040">Protein hydrolysis of defatted BSFL was carried out using a bromelain enzyme with an activity of 200 CDU/mg according to the procedure suggested by <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Auwal et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref>. A total of 10 grams defatted BSFL was dissolved in 50 ml phosphate buffer solution at different pH and the enzyme was added at different concentrations in a 250 ml erlenmeyer flask. The hydrolysis reaction was carried out in a water bath shaker at a temperature of 50 &#x000b0;C, rotation speed of 150 rpm, and at different time variations according to the conditions in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. The hydrolysis reaction was terminated by heating the sample at a temperature of 90 &#x000b0;C for 10 minutes using a water bath. Remaining BSFL samples were completely hydrolyzed by using 6 M HCl at a temperature of 110 &#x000b0;C for 24 hours to determine the total free amino acid content.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Factors and level for the hydrolysis of defatted BSFL using a face-centered CCD.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Factors</th><th colspan="3">Level<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>-1</th><th>0</th><th>1</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Enzyme concentration, E/S (%)</td><td>1</td><td>3</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>pH</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>time, t (hours)</td><td>3</td><td>13,5</td><td>24</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0045">The mixture of protein hydrolysate from BSFL was separated by centrifugation as suggested by <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Caligiani et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref>. Briefly, each sample was poured into a 15 ml centrifuge tube and centrifuged at 4000 rpm for 30 minutes at 25 &#x000b0;C. The supernatant was separated from the precipitated part and stored in a 20 ml bottle which was tightly closed for further processing. The supernatant obtained was stored in a refrigerator at a temperature of 4 &#x000b0;C for further analysis. Protein hydrolysate from BSFL was dried using a freeze-drying method. Briefly, 35 ml of the supernatant of protein hydrolysate from BSFL was frozen in the freezer until the phase changed into a solid. The solid sample was then placed inside a freeze drier at temperature and pressure of -55 &#x000b0;C and 1500 mTorr, respectively until a constant weight was obtained. Dried protein hydrolysate from BSFL was stored in a refrigerator at a temperature of 4 &#x000b0;C for further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Design of experiments and optimization</title><p id="p0050">Optimization condition of protein hydrolysis was carried out using Minitab 8.0 with a face-centered Central Composite Design (CCD) with the factors and level for the hydrolysis of defatted BSFL are shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>. The data were modelled using a second-order polynomial as shown in equation <xref rid="fd3" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (3)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg" alttext="Equation 3."><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where y is degree of hydrolysis (%), b<sub>0</sub> is a constant value, b<sub>i</sub> is coefficient of each variables, X<sub>1</sub> is enzyme concentration (%), X<sub>2</sub> is pH, and X<sub>3</sub> is hydrolysis time (hours). The regression equation was obtained by backward elimination of non-significant coefficients as suggested by <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abduh et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</xref>. The optimum conditions for the hydrolysis defatted biomass of BSFL were determined using the numerical optimization function available in Minitab 8.0.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Determination of yield and productivity of protein hydrolysate</title><p id="p0055">The yield and productivity of protein hydrolysates in the form of freeze dried powder were calculated using <xref rid="fd4" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (4)</xref> and <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (5)</xref>, respectively based on the following assumptions:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0060">Yield was calculated based on the initial weight of hydrolysis substrate, the defatted dried BSFL</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0065">Productivity was calculated for 1 batch of production processes that is comparable with a duration of about 2 days.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0070">The reaction volume used during the production process of the BSFL protein was 60 ml</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0075">The oil and solvent mixture were completely separated; hence the amount of remaining solvent was calculated as the difference from the initial solvent and the oil produced.</p></list-item></list><disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label>Yield (%) = m<sub>final</sub> (g) / m<sub>initial</sub> (g) &#x000d7; 100%</disp-formula>where m<sub>final</sub> is mass of freeze dried protein hydrolysate from BSFL (gram) and m<sub>initial</sub> is mass of initial defatted BSFL sample.<disp-formula id="fd5"><label>(5)</label>Productivity (g/L/batch) = m<sub>final</sub> (g) / (V<sub>reaction</sub> (mL) &#x000d7; 1 batch)</disp-formula>where m<sub>final</sub> is mass of freeze dried protein hydrolysate and V<sub>reaction</sub> is volume of hydrolysis reaction in Erlenmeyer flask.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Determination of protein concentration</title><p id="p0080">Protein concentration of protein hydrolysate from BSFL was determined using a Bradford method (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Kruger, 2009</xref>). Briefly, 0.1 ml of the protein hydrolysate from BSFL was poured into a cuvet. Each sample was added with 5.0 ml of commassie brilliant blue-G solution. The mixture was incubated for approximately 2 minutes at 25 &#x000b0;C. The sample absorbance was determined using a Shimadzu UV-3101 spectrophotometer instrument at a wavelength of 595 nm. Protein concentration was calculated was based on a BSA standard curve.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Determination of degree of hydrolysis</title><p id="p0085">Degree of hydrolysis (DH) for protein hydrolysate from BSFL was determined based on the method of <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Nielsen et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</xref> and <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Mirzaei et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref> with slight modifications. O-pthyaldyaldehyde (OPA) reagent was always freshly made before used to determine the DH of the sample. Briefly, 7.62 g of sodium tetraborate decahydrate and 20 mg SDS were dissolved in 150 ml of deion water and stirred using a magnetic stirrer until a homogeneous solution was obtained. The mixture was added with 160 mg of 97% O-pthyaldyaldehyde powder which was dissolved in 4 ml of 95% ethanol. The mixture was added with 176 mg 99% of DTT and stirred until homogeneous. The final volume of the OPA reagent mixture was made up to 200 mL by adding deion water. OPA reagent was stored in a dark bottle at 25 &#x000b0;C.</p><p id="p0090">The analysis of DH was carried out by adding 0.4 mL of a protein hydrolysate sample containing 200&#x02013;300 ug/ml of protein with 3.0 mL of OPA reagent to determine the amount of free amino acid in the solution. L-serine amino acid (0.01&#x02013;0.10 mg/ml) was used as a standard solution to make a standard curve. The standard solution and all samples were incubated at 25 &#x000b0;C for 2 minutes. The standard solution and all samples were measured for absorption at a wavelength of 340 nm using a Shimadzu UV-3101 spectrophotometer. Absorption of each sample was converted using the standard linear curve regression equation obtained. The degree of hydrolysis was calculated based on <xref rid="fd6" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (6)</xref>.<disp-formula id="fd6"><label>(6)</label>DH (%) = h1 / h0 &#x000d7; 100%</disp-formula>where DH is Degree of Hydrolysis (%), h<sub>1</sub> is peptide concentration, and h<sub>0</sub>is total amino acid (counted as L-serine).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Determination of amino acid</title><p id="p0095">The composition of amino acid in protein hydrolysate from BSFL was analyzed using a High-Performance Liquid Chromatography (HPLC) at the Integrated Chemical Laboratory of Bogor Agricultural University, Indonesia.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Determination of molecular weight distribution</title><p id="p0100">Molecular weight distribution of protein hydrolysate from BSFL was determined using a Sodium Dodecyl Sulfate Poly Acrylamide-Gel Electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) method (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hall et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Polyacrylamide gel for electrophoresis was made by mixing a solution of acrylamide bis-acrylamide mix 12%, deion water, Tris-Cl buffer 0.5 M pH 6.8 (staking gel), Tris-Cl buffer 1.5 M pH 8.8 (separating gel), SDS, ammonium persulfat, and Temed, respectively. Protein samples and protein hydrolysates were prepared by mixing 50 &#x003bc;L samples with a staining solution containing 2-mercaptoethanol, 2% SDS, and 0.05% bromophenol blue in 62.5 mM Tris/HCl buffer (pH 6.8). The samples were incubated at 90 &#x000b0;C for 10 minutes in a water bath. Electrophoresis was operated using a Biorad SDS-PAGE device at a voltage of 100 V, current of 0.1 A, for 150 minutes at 25 &#x000b0;C. A ladder protein of 14&#x02013;116 kDa was used as a comparison to determine the distribution of protein molecular weight. The electrophoresis gel was stained using a staining solution consisting of commassie brilliant blue R-250, 40% technical grade methanol in a volume basis (v/v), 10% v/v glacial acetic acid, and 50% v/v deion water. The gel coloring process with staining solution was carried out for 12 hours. The colored gel was rinsed and soaked in a destaining solution consist of 10% v/v methanol in deion water. The destaining process was carried out for 12 hours until the protein band in the gel could be clearly seen.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><label>2.11</label><title>Determination of antioxidant activity</title><p id="p0105">Antioxidant activity of protein hydrolysate from BSFL was determined based on the scavenging ability of DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl) free radicals expressed in the form of IC<sub>50</sub> concentrations (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Zieli&#x00144;ska et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). DPPH free radical inhibition activity analysis was carried out at the Chemigreecal Laboratory of the Padjadjaran University (UNPAD), Jatinangor. Briefly, DPPH free radicals were dissolved in methanol and added with samples at several concentrations (0.25&#x02013;1.25% v/v). All samples were incubated for 30 minutes in a dark room and then tested for absorption using a spectrophotometer at a wavelength of 517 nm. The value of free radical inhibition was determined using <xref rid="fd7" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (7)</xref>. The measurement was carried out at least twice and the average values were reported.<disp-formula id="fd7"><label>(7)</label>Free radical inhibition activity (%) = (A<sub>control</sub>- A<sub>sampel</sub>) / A<sub>control</sub> &#x000d7; 100%</disp-formula>where A<sub>control</sub> is the absorbance of control sample at &#x003bb; = 517nm, and A<sub>sample</sub> is the absorbance of the sample at &#x003bb; = 517 nm.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Biomass composition of BSFL</title><p id="p0110">Biomass composition of BSFL was analyzed using a proximate analysis method to determine crude protein, lipid, carbohydrate, fiber, and ash content. BSFL has crude protein and lipid content of 25.6% w/w and 35.5% w/w, respectively. The content of protein, lipid, carbohydrates, fiber, and ash in BSFL depends on the substrate consumed (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000fc;ller et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> cultivated BSFL using a commercial chicken feed substrate and produced BSFL biomass with a protein content up to 39.2% w/w. <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Abduh et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> reported that BSFL has a protein content of 45% w/w when fed with defatted residual Philippine tung seeds (<italic>Reutalis trisperma</italic>) during its cultivation period. The BSFL used in this study has a lower protein content compared to the other studies. It is probably due to the substrate composition used in this study that comprises a mixture of vegetable and plant-based food residues. However, the protein content is still greater than 25% w/w of BSFL used in this study is still classified as a high protein biomass (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Mulder et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0115">The relatively high lipid content in the BSFL (35% w/w) was separated prior to the hydrolysis process was. The lipid component was separated by a Soxhlet extraction method using an n-hexane as a solvent. After the lipid component has been removed, the BSFL protein fraction was doubled to 54, 81% as compared to the initial content (25.6%) as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>. Increased protein content after lipid extraction process was also reported by <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Longvah et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</xref> with a 50% increased of protein content for silkworm prepupae. So that, the hydrolysis process using bromelain enzyme was more effective after the separation of lipid content in BSFL because the non-protein component have been reduced (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Coulen et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Composition of initial BSFL biomass and defatted BSFL.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig.&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Yield and productivity of protein hydrolysate from BSFL</title><p id="p0120">The yield and productivity of protein hydrolysate from BSFL in the form of freeze dried solid was calculated to investigate it's potential to be developed on a larger scale production. As much as 1.07 grams of freeze dried protein hydrolysates from BSFL were obtained from a series of production processes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The yield of freeze dried protein hydrolysates from BSFL reached up to 10.7% w/w and 6.9% w/w based on the defatted BSFL and based on initial non-defatted BSFL, respectively. Similar findings were reported by <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hall et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> which produced solid protein hydrolysates from cricket biomass with yields ranging from 5.2 to 11.7% w/w. The yield of protein hydrolysates varies depending on the hydrolysis conditions performed (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hall et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Based on the experiments conducted in this study, the productivity of protein hydrolysates from BSFL reached up to 21 mg/ml/batch.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram to produce protein hydrolysate from BSFL.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig.&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Effect of enzyme concentration, pH and time on protein concentration of protein hydrolysate from BSFL</title><p id="p0125">Protein concentration of the protein hydrolysate from BSFL was analyzed using a Bradford method. Protein concentration analysis was carried out to determine the range of dissolved protein concentration in the protein hydrolysate which can be used as a reference for determining the degree of hydrolysis using the OPA method. The results of protein hydrolysate concentration obtained from experimental data and regression model are shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table.2</xref>. In general, protein concentration of protein hydrolysate from BSFL varies in the range 240&#x02013;310 &#x003bc;g/mL. The highest protein concentration of protein hydrolysate from BSFL (308.7 &#x003bc;g/mL) were obtained at 3% enzyme concentration, pH 8, and 13.5 hours of hydrolysis time. The lowest concentration (249.1 &#x003bc;g/ml) was obtained under the conditions at 1% enzyme concentration, pH 6, and 24 hours of hydrolysis time. The varying protein concentrations in the protein hydrolysate from BSFL showed that protein concentration was influenced by enzyme concentration, pH and hydrolysis time.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Protein concentration and DH for protein hydrolysate from BSFL of different condition of enzyme, pH, and hydrolysis time'.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Running</th><th colspan="3">Reaction Condition<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Protein Concentration (&#x003bc;g/mL)<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Degree of Hydrolysis (%)<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Enzyme (%)</th><th>pH</th><th>Time (hours)</th><th>Experiment</th><th>Model</th><th>Experiment</th><th>Model</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>24</td><td>244.4</td><td>265.1</td><td>37.7</td><td>35.0</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>307.3</td><td>299.6</td><td>23.4</td><td>23.5</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>3</td><td>247.7</td><td>253.8</td><td>26.5</td><td>28.6</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>307.3</td><td>299.6</td><td>23.4</td><td>23.5</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>293.9</td><td>295.5</td><td>10.6</td><td>16.5</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>323.4</td><td>299.6</td><td>20.9</td><td>23.5</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>24</td><td>256.8</td><td>250.5</td><td>31.3</td><td>32.3</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>1</td><td>8</td><td>3</td><td>290.6</td><td>287.7</td><td>14.6</td><td>14.0</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>1</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>268.2</td><td>292.4</td><td>19.6</td><td>12.3</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>5</td><td>8</td><td>3</td><td>286.8</td><td>281.3</td><td>20.2</td><td>14.3</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>1</td><td>6</td><td>24</td><td>241.5</td><td>237.9</td><td>17.9</td><td>24.3</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>3</td><td>6</td><td>13.5</td><td>282.0</td><td>289.7</td><td>43.7</td><td>31.1</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>307.3</td><td>299.6</td><td>23.4</td><td>23.5</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>5</td><td>8</td><td>24</td><td>300.6</td><td>299.6</td><td>41.2</td><td>38.3</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>3</td><td>263.4</td><td>268.5</td><td>19.7</td><td>21.0</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>307.3</td><td>299.6</td><td>23.4</td><td>23.5</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>3</td><td>8</td><td>13.5</td><td>308.7</td><td>326.7</td><td>19.6</td><td>30.8</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>3</td><td>7</td><td>13.5</td><td>307.3</td><td>299.6</td><td>23.4</td><td>23.5</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>1</td><td>8</td><td>24</td><td>299.6</td><td>284.4</td><td>39.9</td><td>38.1</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>1</td><td>6</td><td>3</td><td>271.0</td><td>262.9</td><td>17.3</td><td>20.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Effect of enzyme concentration, pH, and time on the DH of protein hydrolysate from BSFL</title><p id="p0130">The DH of the protein hydrolysates from BSFL was determined using the OPA method which calculated the ratio of free L-serine amino acids in the sample and total amino acid from extensive hydrolysis. The DH values of the protein hydrolysate from BSFL are shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref> and the coefficients of the regression equation are shown in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>. The profile of enzyme concentration, pH, and hydrolysis time effect on DH is shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Regression model coefficient for predicting of the DH of protein hydrolysate from BSFL.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variable</th><th>Coefficient</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Constant</td><td>389</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>1</sub></td><td>21.6</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>2</sub></td><td>-107.9</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>3</sub></td><td>-3.83</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>1</sub><sup>2</sup></td><td>-2.28</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>2</sub><sup>2</sup></td><td>7.44</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>3</sub><sup>2</sup></td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>1</sub>X<sub>2</sub></td><td>-0.98</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>1</sub>X<sub>3</sub></td><td>-0.001</td></tr><tr><td>X<sub>2</sub>X<sub>3</sub></td><td>0.49</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>X<sub>1</sub>: enzyme concentration (%), X<sub>2</sub>: pH, and X<sub>3</sub>: time (hour).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Surface response from the interaction between variables on the DH with respect to enzyme concentration and pH (A), enzyme concentration and time (B), and pH and time (C).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig.&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="p0135">Protein hydrolysate from BSFL was successfully obtained from a series of production processes, with the DH values varies in the range of 10&#x02013;44%. This finding shows that the DH value is influenced by various factors, including the concentration of enzymes, pH, and hydrolysis time (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Pasupuleti and Demain, 2010</xref>). Hydrolysis conditions of 3% enzyme concentration, pH 6, and hydrolysis time of 13.5 hours had the highest DH value, reaching up to 43.7%. Meanwhile the hydrolysis conditions at an enzyme concentration of 5%, pH 7 and the hydrolysis time of 13.5 hours had the lowest DH value (10.6%).</p><p id="p0140">The optimum conditions for the hydrolysis of protein in BSFL according to the regression model are the enzyme concentration of 3%, pH 8, and hydrolysis time of 24 hour with a DH up to 47.4%. An enzyme concentration of 3% produces the highest DH compared to enzyme concentrations of 1% and 5%. A maximum DH value at 3% enzyme concentration was also reported for the hydrolysis of cricket proteins (<italic>Gryllodes sigillatus</italic>) using alcalase, with a DH up to 52% (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hall et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Likewise, protein hydrolysates from Chinese sturgeon (<italic>Acipenser sinensis</italic>) had the highest DH value which when the hydrolysis was carried out using a 3% concentration of papain enzyme (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Noman et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). As such occurred because the interaction of protein substrate with bromelain had reached its maximum saturation (plateaued state) and the hydrolysis process will not run effectively and efficiently when the enzyme concentration was greater than 3% (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aspmo et&#x000a0;al., 2005</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Molecular weight distribution of protein hydrolysate from BSFL</title><p id="p0145">Molecular weight distribution of protein sample without the addition of enzymes and protein hydrolysate from BSFL was compared using the SDS-PAGE method. The results of the electrophoresis and ladder protein as a comparison are shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>. In general, protein bands and peptides in protein water extract or control sample (A) appear in a molecular size ranges of around 14&#x02013;116 kDa. Meanwhile the protein hydrolysate (B) sample has bands in a molecular size range of about 14&#x02013;45 kDa.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Distribution of molecular weight of protein extract sample without enzyme (A), and protein hydrolysate from BSFL (enzyme concentration of 3%, pH 7, and hydrolysis time of 13.5 hours) (B).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Fig.&#x000a0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="p0150">Protein bands appeared around 116 kDa and 45 kDa were possibly albumin fraction, because this protein fraction are hydrophilic and also water soluble (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Caligiani et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). Protein hydrolysate from BSFL (A) also has a 45 kDa band, but had a thinner appearance as compared to the control sample (B). There is another difference between the control sample (A) and (B), which is the presence of protein band at a molecular weight around 35 kDa that belongs to bromelain. Bromelain itself is a protease with a molecular weight varying from 28 - 33 kDa (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Murachi, 1964</xref>; <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Ketnawa et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). This result occurred because bromelain was added to protein hydrolysate from BSFL as a protease to catalyze the hydrolysis process while bromelain was not added to the control sample without hydrolysis treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Composition of amino acid in the protein hydrolysate from BSFL</title><p id="p0155">Amino acid composition of protein hydrolysate from BSFL was analyzed using HPLC instruments and the results are shown in <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>. The most dominant amino acid in the protein hydrolysate from BSFL was glutamic acid (18.4%). <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Janssen et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> and <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000fc;ller et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> reported that amino acids in BSFL were dominated by glutamic acid. Likewise, in the prepupa of BSF sample, the most dominant amino acid component is also glutamic acid (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Surendra et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). Protein hydrolysate from another insect species such as tropical banded crickets (<italic>Gryllodes sigillatus</italic>) also has glutamic acid as the most dominant amino acid with a composition up to 19% (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hall et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Amino acid composition of protein hydrolysate from BSFL.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#x000a0;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><break/>Amino acids</th><th>This study (Protein hydrolysate from BSFL)</th><th><xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">M&#x000fc;ller et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> (BSFL)</th><th><xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Janssen et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref> (BSFL)</th><th><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Surendra et&#x000a0;al. (2016)</xref> (BSFL Prepupa)</th><th><xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hall et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> (Protein hydrolysate from <italic>G.&#x000a0;sigillatus</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Alanine</td><td>12.1</td><td>6.2</td><td>4.7</td><td>7.9</td><td>16.6</td></tr><tr><td>Arginine*</td><td>3.3</td><td>6.2</td><td>4.6</td><td>6.6</td><td>18.1</td></tr><tr><td>Aspartic acid</td><td>9.7</td><td>10.3</td><td>12.6</td><td>7.8</td><td>0.8</td></tr><tr><td>Glutamic acid</td><td>18.1</td><td>12.2</td><td>12.1</td><td>8.4</td><td>19.9</td></tr><tr><td>Phenylalanine*</td><td>4.2</td><td>6.2</td><td>7.2</td><td>4.4</td><td>2.6</td></tr><tr><td>Glycine</td><td>6.1</td><td>5.4</td><td>3.9</td><td>7.3</td><td>3.7</td></tr><tr><td>Histidine*</td><td>2.7</td><td>4.8</td><td>3.6</td><td>5.0</td><td>3.4</td></tr><tr><td>Isoleucine*</td><td>5.3</td><td>4.8</td><td>5.8</td><td>4.5</td><td>2.6</td></tr><tr><td>Lysine*</td><td>8.0</td><td>7.4</td><td>9.2</td><td>6.5</td><td>3.6</td></tr><tr><td>Leucine*</td><td>7.7</td><td>7.7</td><td>8.0</td><td>6.9</td><td>8.4</td></tr><tr><td>Methionine*</td><td>1.7</td><td>0.6</td><td>2.5</td><td>2.6</td><td>0.6</td></tr><tr><td>Proline</td><td>-</td><td>6.2</td><td>4.34</td><td>6.2</td><td>3.3</td></tr><tr><td>Serine</td><td>4.5</td><td>4.1</td><td>4.0</td><td>4.5</td><td>6.7</td></tr><tr><td>Cysteine</td><td>-</td><td>0.5</td><td>1.33</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.6</td></tr><tr><td>Tyrosine</td><td>4.3</td><td>6.0</td><td>6.3</td><td>7.0</td><td>1.4</td></tr><tr><td>Threonine*</td><td>5.0</td><td>4.5</td><td>4.9</td><td>4.4</td><td>2.6</td></tr><tr><td>Tryptophan*</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>0.7</td></tr><tr><td>Valine*</td><td>7.3</td><td>6.7</td><td>5.6</td><td>7.2</td><td>1.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>* Essential amino acid group.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0160">In this study, protein hydrolysate from BSFL also contains a relatively high amount of alanine (12.1%). This is because the bromelain enzyme used in hydrolysis process of BSFL mostly consisted of L-alanine amino acid (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Murachi, 1964</xref>). The protein hydrolysate from BSFL contains almost all essential amino acid. Hydrophobic amino acids, such as, lysine (8.0%), leucine (7.7%) and valine (7.3%) were the most dominant essential amino acids. High amount of hydrophobic amino acid in a protein hydrolysate, can be a sign of the ability to scavenge or inhibit free radicals (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Saadi et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><label>3.7</label><title>Antioxidant activity of protein hydrolysate from BSFL</title><p id="p0165">According to the DPPH free radical scavenging analysis, both protein hydrolysate from BSFL and control sample had the ability to inhibit DPPH free radical up to 72.6 &#x000b1; 0.41% v/v and 66.3 &#x000b1; 0.40% v/v, respectively at a concentration of 1.25% v/v (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>). The activity of DPPH free radical inhibition is also found in the protein hydrolysate from sea cucumber or stone fish (<italic>Actynopiga lecanora</italic>) which had an inhibitory ability up to 50% at 1,0% v/v sample concentration (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Auwal et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). In addition, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Zieli&#x00144;ska et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> also reported that protein hydrolysates in three types of insects had DPPH* free radical inhibitory activity indicated by IC<sub>50</sub> values. IC<sub>50</sub> values of protein hydrolysate from BSFL and control samples were 0.84 &#x000b1; 0,001% v/v and 0.92 &#x000b1; 0,015% v/v, respectively. It means that protein hydrolysate from BSFL has a higher DPPH free radical inhibition activity then protein hydrolysate from sea cucumber (IC<sub>50</sub> &#x0223c; 1% v/v) reported by Auwal dkk., (2017). In another study, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Zieli&#x00144;ska et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</xref> reported that protein hydrolysate from selected insect, particularly <italic>Schistocerca gregaria, Gryllodes sigillatus</italic>, and larva of <italic>Tenobrio mollitor</italic> have an IC<sub>50</sub> up to 0.004&#x02013;0.010% v/v which were better than the results obtained in this study.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>DPPH free radical inhibition profile of protein hydrolysates from BSFL and control at various concentrations (0&#x02013;1.25% v/v).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig.&#x000a0;5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0170">The antioxidant activity of a protein hydrolysate is the result of various synergistic mechanisms, including the deterrence or inhibition of free radicals, inhibition of lipid peroxidation processes, metal ionization, countering oxidative reactions by oxygen-containing compounds, and electron transfer processes (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et&#x000a0;al., 1996</xref>). The DPPH free radical inhibition activity possessed by protein hydrolysate from BSFL is influenced by the amino acid composition in it. Aromatic amino acids such as phenylalanine, and tyrosine are able to stabilize DPPH free radicals through the mechanism of proton donors to electron-deficient free radicals (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">D&#x000e1;valos et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>). The proton donor process results in propagating termination of free radical reaction (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Auwal et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). In addition, amino acids that have hydrophobic properties played an important role in the process of deterring free radicals (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Saadi et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). This occurs because of the ability of hydrophobic amino acids to increase access of free radicals to related amino acids, thereby reducing access of free radicals in attacking compounds and targeted cells (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Nasri, 2017</xref>). Thus, protein hydrolysate from BSFL has the potential as bioactive hydrolysate with an antioxidant activity based on the amino acid composition and the ability to inhibit DPPH free radicals.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0175">Protein hydrolysate from defatted BSFL that contains 50 % w/w of protein had been successfully synthesized using a bromelain enzyme as a biocatalyst. The DH of protein hydrolysate from BSFL lies in the range of 10&#x02013;48%. The optimum conditions of the hydrolysis process with a DH of 47.4%, occurred at 3% of enzyme concentration, pH 8, and hydrolysis time of 24 hours as suggested by regression model. The protein hydrolysate from BSFL had a yield of 10.7% w/w and a productivity of 21 mg/mL/batch. The protein hydrolysate from BSFL contains high amount of hydrophobic essential amino acid, particularly lysine (8.0%), leucine (7.7%), and valine (7.3%). The protein hydrolysate from BSFL had an antioxidant activity in terms of its ability to scavenge DPPH free radicals up to 77% at 1.25% sample concentration with IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.84% v/v.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0180">Mochamad Firmansyah: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0185">Muhammad Yusuf Abduh: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0190">This work was supported by a research grant from the <funding-source id="gs1">Ministry of Research, Technology, and Higher Education Indonesia</funding-source> (PN-1-23-2018).</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0195">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0200">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abduh</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasrendra</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subroto</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manurung</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heeres</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental modelling studies on the solvent assisted hydraulic pressing of dehulled rubber seeds</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><volume>92</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0020">Abduh, M. Y., Rasrendra, C.B., Subroto, E., Manurung, R., Heeres, H.J. 2016. Experimental modelling studies on the solvent assisted hydraulic pressing of dehulled rubber seeds. Ind. Crops. Prod. 92, 67-76. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indcrop.2016.07.025</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abduh</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadia</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manurung</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Putra</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting the bioconversion of Philippine tung seed by black soldier fly larvae for the production of protein oil-rich biomass</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Asia Pac. Entomol.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>842</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0025">Abduh, M. Y., Nadia, M. H., Manurung, R., Putra, R. E. 2018. Factors affecting the bioconversion of Philippine tung seed by black soldier fly larvae for the production of protein oil-rich biomass. J Asia-Pac. Entomol. 21, 836-842. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aspen.2018.06.007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>AOAC</surname></name></person-group><source>Official Methods of Analysis of AOAC International</source><edition>19th ed.</edition><year>2012</year><comment>Gaithersburg, M.D. USA</comment></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0300">AOAC (2012). Official Methods of Analysis of AOAC International (19th ed.), Gaithersburg, M.D. USA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aspmo</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eijsink</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymatic hydrolysis of Atlantic cod (<italic>Gadus morhua</italic> L.) viscera</article-title><source>Process Biochem.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1957</fpage><lpage>1966</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0030">Aspmo, S. I., Horn, S. J., Eijsink, V. G. 2005. Enzymatic hydrolysis of Atlantic cod (Gadus morhua L.) viscera. Process Biochem. 40, 1957-1966. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procbio.2004.07.011</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auwal</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdul-Hamid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response surface optimisation for the production of antioxidant hydrolysates from stone fish protein using bromelain</article-title><source>Evid. Based Complement Alternat. Med.</source><volume>2017</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0035">Auwal, S. M., Zarei, M., Abdul-Hamid, A., Saari, N. 2017. Response Surface Optimisation for the Production of Antioxidant Hydrolysates from Stone Fish Protein Using Bromelain. Evid. Based Complement Alternat. Med. 2017, 1-10. https://doi.org/10.1155/2017/4765463</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beskin</surname><given-names>K.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holcomb</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammack</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crippen</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knap</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweet</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomberlin</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larval digestion of different manure types by the black soldier fly (Diptera: stratiomyidae) impacts associated volatile emissions</article-title><source>Waste Manag.</source><volume>74</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29397276</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0040">Beskin, K. V., Holcomb, C. D., Cammack, J. A., Crippen, T. L., Knap, A. H., Sweet, S. T.,and Tomberlin, J. K. (2018). Larval digestion of different manure types by the black soldier fly (Diptera: Stratiomyidae) impacts associated volatile emissions. Waste Manag. 74, 213-220. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wasman.2018.01.019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caligiani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marseglia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leni</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldassarre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maistrello</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dossena</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sforza</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composition of black soldier fly prepupae systematic approaches for extraction fractionation of proteins, lipids and chitin</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>105</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29433277</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0045">Caligiani, A., Marseglia, A., Leni, G., Baldassarre, S., Maistrello, L., Dossena, A., Sforza, S. 2018. Composition of black soldier fly prepupae systematic approaches for extraction fractionation of proteins, lipids and chitin. Food Res. Int. 105, 812-820. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2017.12.012</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muramoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nokihara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of designed peptides based on the antioxidative peptide isolated from digests of a soybean protein</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>44</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>2619</fpage><lpage>2623</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0050">Chen, H. M., Muramoto, K., Yamauchi, F., Nokihara, K. 1996. Antioxidant activity of designed peptides based on the antioxidative peptide isolated from digests of a soybean protein. J. Agric. Food Chem. 44, 2619-2623. https://doi.org/10.1021/jf950833m</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaisgood</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactive milk peptides: a prospectus</article-title><source>Int. J. Dairy Sci.</source><volume>83</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>1187</fpage><lpage>1195</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0055">Clare, D. A., Swaisgood, H. E. 2000. Bioactive milk peptides: a prospectus. I. J. Dairy Sci. 83, 1187-1195. https://doi.org/10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(00)74983-6</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vioque</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Vioque</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedroche</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mill&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein quality of chickpea (<italic>Cicer arietinum</italic> L.) protein hydrolysates</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>67</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>274</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0060">Clemente, A., Vioque, J., Sanchez-Vioque, R., Pedroche, J., Bautista, J., Millan, F. 1999. Protein quality of chickpea (Cicer arietinum L.) protein hydrolysates. Food Chem. 67, 269-274. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0308-8146(99)00130-2</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coulen</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruins</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Valorisation of proteins from rubber tree</article-title><source>Waste Biomass Valorization</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1041</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0065">Coulen, S. C., Sanders, J. P., Bruins, M. E. 2017. Valorisation of proteins from rubber tree. Waste Biomass Valorization. 8, 1027-1041. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12649-016-9688-9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000e1;valos</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolome</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Fandino</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant activity of peptides derived from egg white proteins by enzymatic hydrolysis</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Food Prot.</source><volume>67</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>1939</fpage><lpage>1944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15453585</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0070">Davalos, A., Miguel, M., Bartolome, B., Lopez-Fandino, R. 2004. Antioxidant activity of peptides derived from egg white proteins by enzymatic hydrolysis. J. Food Protect 67, 1939-1944. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028X-67.9.1939</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Castro</surname><given-names>R.J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;response surface approach on optimization of hydrolysis parameters for the production of egg white protein hydrolysates with antioxidant activities Biocatal</article-title><source>Agric. Biotechnol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0075">De Castro, R. J. S., Sato, H. H. 2015. A response surface approach on optimization of hydrolysis parameters for the production of egg white protein hydrolysates with antioxidant activities Biocatal. Agric. Biotechnol. 4, 55-62. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcab.2014.07.001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halim</surname><given-names>N.R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azlan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusof</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarbon</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant anticancer activities of enzymatic eel (<italic>Monopterus sp</italic>) protein hydrolysate as influenced by different molecular weight</article-title><source>Biocatal. Agric. Biotechnol.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0085">Halim, N. R. A., Azlan, A., Yusof, H. M., Sarbon, N. M. 2018. Antioxidant anticancer activities of enzymatic eel (Monopterus sp) protein hydrolysate as influenced by different molecular weight. Biocatal. Agric. Biotechnol. 16, 10-16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcab.2018.06.006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>F.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>O.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Haire</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liceaga</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional properties of tropical banded cricket (<italic>Gryllodes sigillatus</italic>) protein hydrolysates</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>224</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28159288</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0090">Hall, F. G., Jones, O. G., O'Haire, M. E., Liceaga, A. M. 2017. Functional properties of tropical banded cricket (Gryllodes sigillatus) protein hydrolysates. Food Chem. 224, 414-422. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.11.138</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein hydrolysates in animal nutrition: industrial production, bioactive peptides, functional significance</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Anim. Sci. Biotechnol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>24</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28286649</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0095">Hou, Y., Wu, Z., Dai, Z., Wang, G., Wu, G. 2017. Protein hydrolysates in animal nutrition: industrial production, bioactive peptides, functional significance. J. Anim. Sci. Biotechnol. 8, 24. https://doi.org/10.1186/s40104-017-0153-9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincken</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Broek</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogliano</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakemond</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen-to-Protein conversion factors for three edible insects: <italic>Tenebrio molitor, Alphitobius di</italic>aperinus, Hermetia illucens</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>65</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2275</fpage><lpage>2278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28252948</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0100">Janssen, R. H., Vincken, J. P., van den Broek, L. A., Fogliano, V., Lakemond, C. M. 2017. Nitrogen-to-Protein Conversion Factors for Three Edible Insects: Tenebrio molitor, Alphitobius diaperinus, Hermetia illucens J. Agric. Food Chem, 65, 2275-2278. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.jafc.7b00471</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ketnawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaiwut</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawdkuen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pineapple wastes: a potential source for bromelain extraction</article-title><source>Food Bioprod. Process.</source><volume>90</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>391</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0105">Ketnawa, S., Chaiwut, P., Rawdkuen, S. 2012. Pineapple wastes: a potential source for bromelain extraction. Food Bioprod. Process. 90, 385-391. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fbp.2011.12.006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The Bradford method for protein quantitation</chapter-title><source>The Protein Protocols Handbook</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Totowa, NJ</publisher-loc><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0305">Kruger, N. J. (2009). The Bradford method for protein quantitation. In The Protein Protocols Handbook (pp. 17-24). Humana Press, Totowa, NJ.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>ur Rehman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic changes of nutrient composition throughout the entire life cycle of black soldier fly</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>12</volume><year>2017</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0182601</object-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0115">Liu, X., Chen, X., Wang, H., Yang, Q., ur Rehman, K., Li, W., Cai, M., Li, Q., Mazza, L., Zhang, J. Yu, Z., 2017. Dynamic changes of nutrient composition throughout the entire life cycle of black soldier fly. PloS One. 12, e0182601. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0182601.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longvah</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangthya</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramulu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient composition protein quality evaluation of eri silkworm (<italic>Samia ricinii</italic>) prepupae pupae</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>128</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25212147</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0120">Longvah, T., Mangthya, K., Ramulu, P. 2011. Nutrient composition protein quality evaluation of eri silkworm (Samia ricinii) prepupae pupae. Food Chem. 128, 400-403. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodchem.2011.03.041.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref22">Marketsandmarket. 2018.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.marketresearch.com/MarketsandMarkets-v3719/Protein-Hydrolysates-Type-Milk-Meat-11745269/" id="intref0010">https://www.marketresearch.com/MarketsandMarkets-v3719/Protein-Hydrolysates-Type-Milk-Meat-11745269/</ext-link>, accessed on 1 September 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Llorens</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliva-Teles</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Black soldier fly (<italic>Hermetia illucens</italic>) pre-pupae meal as a fish meal replacement in diets for European seabass (<italic>Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>)</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><volume>476</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0125">Magalhaes, R., Sanchez-Lopez, A., Leal, R. S., Martinez-Llorens, S., Oliva-Teles, A.,and Peres, H. (2017). Black soldier fly (Hermetia illucens) pre-pupae meal as a fish meal replacement in diets for European seabass (Dicentrarchus labrax). Aquaculture. 476, 79-85. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.aquaculture.2017.04.021.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Alvarez</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chamorro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein hydrolysates from animal processing by-products as a source of bioactive molecules with interest in animal feeding: a review</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>73</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>212</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0130">Martinez-Alvarez, O., Chamorro, S., Brenes, A. 2015. Protein hydrolysates from animal processing by-products as a source of bioactive molecules with interest in animal feeding: a review. Food Res. Int. 73, 204-212. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodres.2015.04.005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirdamadi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehsani</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aminlari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification and identification of antioxidant and ACE-inhibitory peptide from Saccharomyces cerevisiae protein hydrolysate</article-title><source>J Funct. Foods</source><volume>19</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>268</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0315">MirzaeiM., MirdamadiS., EhsaniM.R., AminlariM., &#x00026; Hosseini, E. (2015). Purification and identification of antioxidant and ACE-inhibitory peptide from Saccharomyces cerevisiae protein hydrolysate. J Funct. Foods, 19, 259-268.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulder</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Peet-Schwering</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ree</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Proteins for Food, Feed and Biobased Applications: Biorefining of Protein Containing Biomass. IEA Bioenergy Task 42</chapter-title><year>2016</year></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0320">MulderW., van der Peet-Schwering, C., Hua, N.P., &#x00026; van Ree, R. (2016). Proteins for Food, Feed and Biobased Applications: Biorefining of Protein Containing Biomass. IEA Bioenergy Task 42.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutzeit</surname><given-names>H.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The black soldier fly, <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic>&#x02013;a promising source for sustainable production of proteins, lipids bioactive substances</article-title><source>Z.&#x000a0;Naturforsch. C Biosci.</source><volume>72</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>363</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0135">Muller, A., Wolf, D., Gutzeit, H. O. 2017. The black soldier fly, Hermetia illucens-a promising source for sustainable production of proteins, lipids bioactive substances. Z. Naturforsch C. 72, 351-363. https://doi.org/10.1515/znc-2017-0030.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murachi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amino acid composition of stem bromelain</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><volume>3</volume><year>1964</year><fpage>932</fpage><lpage>934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14214082</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0140">Murachi, T. 1964. Amino acid composition of stem bromelain. Biochemistry, 3, 932-934. https://pubs.acs.org/doi/pdf/10.1021/bi00895a014</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nasri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein hydrolysates biopeptides: production, biological activities, applications in foods health benefits. A review</article-title><source>Adv. Food Nutr. Res.</source><volume>81</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><comment>Academic Press</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28317603</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0145">Nasri, M. 2017. Protein hydrolysates biopeptides: production, biological activities, applications in foods health benefits. A review. In Adv. Food Nutr. Res. 81, 109-159. Academic Press. https://doi.org/10.1016/bs.afnr.2016.10.003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzymatic production of biodiesel from insect fat using methyl acetate as an acyl acceptor: optimization by using response surface methodology</article-title><source>Energy Convers. Manag.</source><volume>158</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0150">Nguyen, H. C., Liang, S. H., Chen, S. S., Su, C. H., Lin, J. H.,and Chien, C. C. 2018. Enzymatic production of biodiesel from insect fat using methyl acetate as an acyl acceptor: Optimization by using response surface methodology. Energy Convers Manag. 158, 168-175. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.enconman.2017.12.068.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dambmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved method for determining food protein degree of hydrolysis</article-title><source>J. Food Sci.</source><volume>66</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>646</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0310">Nielsen, P.M., Petersen, D., &#x00026; Dambmann, C. (2010). Improved method for determining food protein degree of hydrolysis. J. Food Sci., 66(5), 642-646.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>AL-Bukhaiti</surname><given-names>W.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abed</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramadhan</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of enzymatic hydrolysis conditions on the degree of hydrolysis functional properties of protein hydrolysate obtained from Chinese sturgeon (<italic>Acipenser sinensis</italic>) by using papain enzyme</article-title><source>Process Biochem.</source><volume>67</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0155">Noman, A., Xu, Y., AL-Bukhaiti, W. Q., Abed, S. M., Ali, A. H., Ramadhan, A. H., Xia, W. 2018. Influence of enzymatic hydrolysis conditions on the degree of hydrolysis functional properties of protein hydrolysate obtained from Chinese sturgeon (Acipenser sinensis) by using papain enzyme. Process Biochem. 67, 19-28. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procbio.2018.01.009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doelle</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Reilly</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of Diptera: stratiomyidae, genus <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> (L., 1758) using electron microscopy</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Entomol. Zool. Stud.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>152</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0165">Oliveira, F., Doelle, K., List, R., O&#x02019;Reilly, J. R. 2015. Assessment of Diptera: Stratiomyidae, genus Hermetia illucens (L., 1758) using electron microscopy. J. Entomol. Zool. Stud. 3, 147-152.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pujol-Luz</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francez</surname><given-names>P.A.D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ururahy-Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantino</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The black soldier-fly, <italic>Hermetia illucens</italic> (Diptera, stratiomyidae), used to estimate the postmortem interval in a case in amap&#x000e1; state, Brazil</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Forensic Sci.</source><volume>53</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18366584</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0170">Pujol-Luz et&#x000a0;al., 2008 Pujol-Luz, J. R., Francez, P. A. D. C., Ururahy-Rodrigues, A.,and Constantino, R. 2008. The Black Soldier-fly, Hermetia illucens (Diptera, Stratiomyidae), Used to Estimate the Postmortem Interval in a Case in Amapa State, Brazil. J. Forensic Sci. 53, 476-478. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1556-4029.2008.00659.x.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pasupuleti</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>dan Demain</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Protein Hydrolysates in Biotechnology</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Springer Science dan Business Media</publisher-name></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0325">Pasupuleti, V.K., dan Demain, A.L. (Eds.). (2010). Protein Hydrolysates in Biotechnology. Springer Science dan Business Media.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putra</surname><given-names>S.N.K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishak</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarbon</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation characterization of physicochemical properties of golden apple snail (<italic>Pomacea canaliculata</italic>) protein hydrolysate as affected by different proteases</article-title><source>Biocatal. Agri. Biotechnol.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>128</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0180">Putra, S. N. K. M., Ishak, N. H., Sarbon, N. M. 2018. Preparation characterization of physicochemical properties of golden apple snail (Pomacea canaliculata) protein hydrolysate as affected by different proteases. Biocatal. Agri. Biotechnol. 13, 123-128. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bcab.2017.12.002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saadi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anwar</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazali</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent advances in food biopeptides: production, biological functionalities therapeutic applications</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25499177</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0185">Saadi, S., Saari, N., Anwar, F., Hamid, A. A., Ghazali, H. M. 2015. Recent advances in food biopeptides: Production, biological functionalities therapeutic applications. Biotechnol Adv. 33, 80-116. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biotechadv.2014.12.003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>House fly lesser fly control utilizing the black soldier fly in manure management systems for caged laying hens</article-title><source>Environ. Entomol<italic>.</italic></source><volume>12</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>1439</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0190">Sheppard, C. 1983. House fly lesser fly control utilizing the black soldier fly in manure management systems for caged laying hens. Environ. Entomol.12, 1439-1442. https://doi.org/10.1093/ee/12.5.1439.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Surendra</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivier</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomberlin</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanal</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioconversion of organic wastes into biodiesel animal feed via insect farming</article-title><source>Renew. Energy</source><volume>98</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0195">Surendra, K. C., Olivier, R., Tomberlin, J. K., Jha, R., Khanal, S. K. 2016. Bioconversion of organic wastes into biodiesel animal feed via insect farming. Renewable Energy, 98, 197-202.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zieli&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baraniak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kara&#x0015b;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant anti-inflammatory activities of hydrolysates peptide fractions obtained by enzymatic hydrolysis of selected heat-treated edible insects</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><volume>9</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>970</fpage><lpage>975</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="srct0205">Zielinska, E., Baraniak, B., Karas, M. 2017. Antioxidant anti-inflammatory activities of hydrolysates peptide fractions obtained by enzymatic hydrolysis of selected heat-treated edible insects. Nutrients. 9, 970-975. https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9090970.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to acknowledge PT Bromelain Enzyme Indonesia for supplying bromelain enzyme used in this study.</p></ack></back></article>