<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The main components of the 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> essential oils are monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes [
 <xref rid="B222-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">222</xref>]. The biosynthesis of plants is formed in the cytosol of the mevalonic acid pathway, while monoterpenes are formed in the plastids of the methylethritol phosphate pathway [
 <xref rid="B275-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">275</xref>]. However, there may be competition for the phenyl pyrophosphate substrate between mono and sesquiterpenes [
 <xref rid="B276-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">276</xref>]. The involved terpene synthases have been divided into seven sub-families [
 <xref rid="B277-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">277</xref>]. The genes related to the terpenoid biosynthesis began to be extensively studied only in recent years. Among sequenced angiosperm plant genomes, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> has the highest number of terpenoid biosynthetic genes [
 <xref rid="B278-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">278</xref>]. In total, 106 and 113 putative terpene synthase genes were identified in 
 <italic class="italic">E. globulus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">E. grandis</italic>, respectively—approximately four times as many as in 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and twice as many as in 
 <italic class="italic">Vitis vinifera</italic> [
 <xref rid="B279-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">279</xref>]. Most of these genes were found in large (up to 20 genes) genomic clusters. This interesting pattern of clustering of biosynthetic genes for some allelochemicals (e.g., benzoxazinoids, cyanogenic glucosides, terpenoids, and alkaloids) in chromosomes has been found recently [
 <xref rid="B280-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">280</xref>]. Supposedly, it promotes stable inheritance of functional chemical defense pathways in populations [
 <xref rid="B281-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">281</xref>]. About 30 examples of clusters of genes encoding products important for secondary metabolic pathways were reviewed recently [
 <xref rid="B282-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">282</xref>], but only for grass species.
</p>
