<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Each of the types of extracts used also caused an increase in the electrolyte leakage, which disrupted the water-ion balance of radish seedlings (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="plants-09-01549-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Cell membranes are complex and dynamic structures made of lipids and proteins [
 <xref rid="B42-plants-09-01549" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. They are a measure of structural integrity, function stability and an indicator of plant tolerance to stress. Membranes are one of the first structures affected by stress factors. Their mechanism of functioning and physiological role indicate that electrolyte leakage is associated with the loss of K
 <sup>+</sup> ions, mediating the conductivity of cations through the membrane [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-09-01549" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In the conducted studies, it was found that the extract prepared in the form of macerate, irrespective of the radish cultivar, caused the largest inhibitory effect for the leakage of electrolytes. In the wide spectrum of allelochemical compounds, such properties are attributed to phenolic compounds [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-01549" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. These compounds are among the most common synthesized by plants and show a negative effect even at low concentrations. Allelochemical substances can penetrate into the cell membranes and destroy their structural connections or create new modification. For example, phenolic acids can change channels structure in cell membranes and limit the functioning of enzyme proteins, ATP, effect on transport and accumulation of ions between membranes and the water management of the cell. Other compounds, e.g., terpenoids, quinones, p-coumaric acid and ferulic acid cause lipid peroxidation. The cell membranes are often damaged by free radicals, which are formed, among others, by during the oxidative transformation of phenolics [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-09-01549" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-plants-09-01549" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-plants-09-01549" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-plants-09-01549" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
