<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The inclusion of an insect meal from HI larvae as 25 or 50% substitution of the soybean meal proteins had several effects on the small intestine morphometry and enzymatic activity, as well as on the caecal microbial activity. The morphometry changes mainly occurred in the duodenum and jejunum, but there were also some interesting modifications in the ileum. In general, the villi height decreased as the inclusion level of the insect meal increased in the diet, this is in accordance with the decreased nutrient ileal digestibility recorded in the first part of this trial [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The crypt depth was unchanged among the groups, or it tended to decrease (in the jejunum) as the level of the HI increased in the diet. The small intestine is involved in the digestion and absorption of almost all the dietary nutrients [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]: the duodenum digests around 95% of the fats [
 <xref rid="B35-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]; jejunum digests and absorbs fats, starch, and protein [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]; the ileum is mainly involved in water and mineral absorption, but it also digests and absorbs fats, proteins, and starch [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. The morphological studies of the small intestine are often used to assess its functionality and, in general, an increased villi height is indicative of an improved intestinal function [
 <xref rid="B38-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Another important consideration is that the ileal villi in chickens are smaller and lower than those of the previous tracts of the small intestine, as in hens fed corn-soybean based diets, very little amount of nutrients are available beyond the jejunum [
 <xref rid="B39-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. In the present trial, the height of the ileal villi was lower than that of the duodenum, but higher compared to the jejunum for hens fed both the insect diets. The effect of the diets on the intestinal villi height can be affected by the nutrient digestibility of the diets. As recorded in the first part of this trial [
 <xref rid="B12-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], the dry matter digestibility of the SBM and the HI25 diets (75.0% and 70.3%, respectively) in hens was higher (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) than that of the HI50 group (64.3) and the result was mainly attributable to the crude protein digestibility (86.2 vs. 81.1 vs. 76.1%, respectively, for SBM, HI25, and HI50, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). The low nutrient digestibility in the hens fed the insect meal is tied to the chitin, present in the insect exoskeleton [
 <xref rid="B3-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Thus, our hypothesis is that higher availability of nutrients in the duodenum and jejunum of the hens fed the SBM, increased the intestine functionality, improving the villi height. In insect fed hens, the lower nutrient digestibility induced an increased amount of the potential digestible nutrients in the ileum. Yamauchi et al. [
 <xref rid="B42-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] stated that an increased load of nutrients deriving directly from the duodenum to the ileum (both for jejunum dissection or different diets) might stimulate the ileal absorptive function, resulting in a compensatory development of the villi. In general, longer villi are the result of activated cell mitosis in the crypts [
 <xref rid="B43-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]; thus, a larger crypt area indicates a more intensive cell production. In the present trial, the only crypt depth was recorded, and this was unchanged among the groups in the duodenum and ileum tracts. However, the villi height to crypt depth ratio is strongly related to the epithelial cell turnover [
 <xref rid="B44-animals-09-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. In our trial, the cell turnover was higher in the SBM than in the insect meal groups for the duodenum and jejunum, while no differences were observed among the groups in the ileum.
</p>
