<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the in vivo studies, three test doses were determined from the findings of the acute oral toxicity study as per the method described in OECD guideline.
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Accordingly, one-tenth of the safe dose (2000 mg) in the acute oral toxicity test was used as a medium dose (200mg/kg) with half (100 mg/kg) and double (400 mg/kg) of the medium dose considered as a lower and higher dose, respectively. Furthermore, in vivo carrageenan-induced paw oedema model is the most common animal protocol frequently used to determine the anti-inflammatory and anti-oedema properties of natural remedies.
 <xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> This model is principally based on the release of inflammatory mediators.
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> The ethanolic leaf extract of 
 <italic>H. schulli</italic> exhibited significant (
 <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) anti-inflammatory activity against carrageenan-induced hind paw oedema in mice at two-, three-, and four-hours post-carrageenan injection. This anti-inflammatory activity was in a dose-dependent manner. Even though statistically insignificant, the extract has shown suppression of paw oedema formation at the first hour observation time. The anti-inflammatory activity of the extract may be due to the inhibition of the secretion of inflammatory mediators. In line with the present study, previous reports indicated that extract from 
 <italic>H. schulli</italic> seeds showed significant anti-inflammatory activity in carrageenan-induced paw oedema model.
 <xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Moreover, a study by Patra et al (2009) on a similar species reported that chloroform and alcoholic leaf extracts of 
 <italic>Hygrophila spinosa</italic> demonstrated significant (
 <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05) and dose-dependent in vivo anti-inflammatory activity against carrageenan-induced paw oedema to which findings of the current study are consistent.
 <xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
</p>
