<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Postdistillation wastes are obtained after the extraction of essential oils from the raw material of the plants belonging to the 
 <italic>Lamiaceae, Asteraceae, Apiaceae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Pinaceae</italic> families. It seems that using postdistillation wastes is quite a perspective in terms of the extraction of new biologically active substances possessing valuable pharmacological properties. As the amount of essential oil in the aerial parts of the Lamiaceae family representatives is not high (up to 3%), the majority of a plant raw material remains unused after the hydrodistillation (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Gavarić et al., 2015</xref>). This scientific and practical field of using hydrodistilled residue by-products has been expanding rapidly for the species of this family for the last decade (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Gavarić et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Pogačar et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Vovk et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Baranauskienė et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoudi et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Shanaida, 2020</xref>). Nevertheless, HPLC assay revealed the high contents of such valuable polyphenols as rosmarinic acid (52.36–105.8 mg/g) and rutin (11.01–87.11 mg/g) in the dried extract developed from the postdistillation waste material of 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Gavarić et al., 2015</xref>). In another study (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Pogačar et al., 2016</xref>), it was revealed that the extract obtained from the 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> post-hydrodistillation residue was rich in such bioactive phytochemicals as rosmarinic acid and flavone glucuronides. This extract effectively reduced the adhesion of 
 <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> to abiotic surfaces at low concentrations (0.2–12.5 μg/mL) (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Pogačar et al., 2016</xref>). Hydrodistilled residue by-products from 
 <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. leaves were also considered as a valuable source of rosmarinic acid and other polyphenols with noticeable antimicrobial, repellent, and antioxidant effects (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoudi et al., 2020</xref>). Solid residues of 
 <italic>Lavandula</italic> × 
 <italic>intermedia</italic> and 
 <italic>Thymus mastichina</italic> L. after the isolation of the essential oil were found as a source of polyphenols with antioxidant and metal chelating activities (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Sánchez-Vioque et al., 2013</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, there are no studies related to hydrodistilled residue by-product of 
 <italic>M. fistulosa</italic> aerial part.
</p>
