<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">Enzyme-inhibitory assays are a potent tool to assess the significant health benefits of medicinal plants, dietary supplements, and nutraceuticals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Due to the drastic prevalence of several ailments, there is an urgency to address these health hazards, which commonly include Alzheimer’s disease and diabetes. 
 <italic>M. buxifolia</italic> extracts showed prominent inhibitory activity against clinically important enzymes. The methanol extracts of both parts of the plant and the chloroform extract of stems were most active against AChE, while the chloroform extract of stems was the most potent against BChE. Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) is localized at the cholinergic synapses and regulates neurotransmission through rapid hydrolysis of the neurotransmitter acetylcholine into choline and acetate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Inhibition of AChE can increase the levels of acetylcholine, thereby providing symptomatic relief [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. On the other hand, butyrylcholinesterase (BChE) is a serine hydrolase associates with lipid metabolism and indicators of metabolic syndrome such as body mass index, waist–hip ratio, waist circumference, weight, cholesterol, and triglyceride levels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Increased BChE activity may also lead to a greater degradation of acetylcholine, which lowers the inhibitory effect on the production of cytokines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Furthermore, amylase and glucosidase play a vital role in the digestion of carbohydrates. In diabetes and obesity, inhibition of these enzymes is essential to reduce carbohydrate digestion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The stem extracts showed significant tyrosinase- and amylase-inhibitory activity; however, all fours extracts depicted equal activity inhibition of glucosidase activity. The significant enzyme-inhibitory potential of 
 <italic>M. buxifolia</italic> extracts is therapeutically important, which suggests its potential use as promising antidiabetic medicine. Inhibition of α-amylase is an efficacious approach to overcoming postprandial hyperglycemia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Tyrosinase is one of the key enzymes responsible for the biosynthesis of melanin, and its inhibition is considered the best strategy to treat epidermal hyperpigmentation problems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Tyrosinase also causes browning of fruits and vegetables, leading to quicker degradation and deterioration of nutritional value [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The use of tyrosinase inhibitors has attracted great attention in the cosmetic and pharmaceutical industries due to their preventive effects in pigmentation disorders. This scenario demands deliberate action involving the use of enzyme-inhibitory compounds as an effective strategy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].
</p>
