<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Germinated brown rice has proven strong potentials for better glycemic control, correction of dyslipidemia, amelioration of oxidative stress, reduced type 1 tissue plasminogen activator inhibitor (PAI-1), enhanced adiponectin concentration, and increased sodium potassium adenosine triphosphatase and homocysteine thiolactonase activities, which are reviewed in detail in Imam et al. [
 <xref rid="B236-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">236</xref>] and Nelson et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. These effects cannot be attributable to a single individual bioactive compound, but rather to a synergic interaction between all the bioactive compounds induced also by the germination process (i.e., GABA, oryzanol, phenolics, dietary fibers and others), so obtaining a greater functional effect when consumed as a whole food [
 <xref rid="B237-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">237</xref>]. The effects of white rice, brown rice and germinated brown rice in the dietary management of cardiovascular diseases have been recently investigated by Imam et al. [
 <xref rid="B238-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">238</xref>] who highlighted the modulation of the lipid metabolism and oxidative stress in rats. In pregnant rats the exposure to high-fat diet plus germinated brown rice until 4 weeks post-delivery, influenced metabolic outcomes in offspring of rats with underlying epigenetic changes and transcriptional implications, that led to improved glucose homeostasis and reduced the risk of insulin resistance manifestations [
 <xref rid="B239-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">239</xref>]. Germinated brown rice supplied in the diet also reduced obesity complications in high-fat diet induced-obese rats, through the improvement of lipid profiles and reduction of leptin level and white adipose tissue mass [
 <xref rid="B240-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">240</xref>]. Germinated brown rice enhanced insulin levels, insulin receptor, glucose transporters and glucose metabolism in induced-hyperglycemia mice [
 <xref rid="B241-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">241</xref>]. In addition, in human SH-SY5Y cells, a neuro-protective effect by gene modulations has been found to be provided by germinated brown rice extracts [
 <xref rid="B242-nutrients-11-00421" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">242</xref>]. These evidences represent only a preliminary indication on the potential beneficial effects of germinated brown rice, and more research is still required.
</p>
