<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">0.5 mL of 
 <italic class="italic">P. boldus</italic> essential oil (approximatively 400 mg) were chromatographed on a silica gel (20 g) column (70−230 mesh, 60 Å, Merck, Kenilworth, NJ, USA) using cyclohexane, followed by a stepwise gradient solvent system consisting of cyclohexane/ethyl acetate 99:1 to 97:3. A total of 85 fractions (3 mL) were collected and monitored by thin-layer chromatography (TLC). Fractions 65-74 (AS65-74) yielded 120 mg of a pure compound, and the structure was identified as 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-ascaridole. Both samples, that is, essential oil and AS65-74, were found to contain a certain amount of 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-ascaridole when analyzed by GC/MS analysis, but 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H- and 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C-NMR spectral data of AS65-74 showed only signals assigned to 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-ascaridole. The 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>-ascaridole contents in the essential oil sample and AS65-74 were considered to be artifacts produced during the GC-MS analysis [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. 
 <sup class="sup">1</sup>H- NMR and 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C-NMR spectra were recorded on 500 MHz NMR spectrometer (Bruker Avance III 500 MHz, Bruker, Billerica, MA, USA). The chemical shift values are expressed in δ values (ppm), and coupling constants (
 <italic class="italic">J</italic>) are in hertz; tetramethylsilane (TMS) was used as an internal standard. Proton chemical data are reported as follows: chemical shift, multiplicity (s = singlet, d = doublet, dd = doublet of doublets, t = triplet, dt = doublet of triplets, q = quartet, sept = septet, m = multiplet, brs = broad singlet) coupling constant (s), integration. The NMR data were compared with those reported in the literature, allowing it to be identified as 
 <italic class="italic">cis</italic>-ascaridole [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-00879" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>].
</p>
