<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The total yield of nigellothionin NsW2 was the highest, and further experiments were performed using this peptide. NsW2 was tested against some clinical isolates of filamentous fungi from the genus 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and yeasts. The activity level for most of the clinical strains tested was similar, as well as the activity against isolates from the collection. There was no significant difference between clinical isolates and all non-clinical strains. In contrast, NsW2 was active against clinical 
 <italic>A. terreus</italic> 1133, whereas wild strain 
 <italic>A. terreus</italic> 3K showed total resistance to the peptides’ action. 
 <italic>A. terreus</italic> 3K was sensitive to AmB, which is consistent with data on high 
 <italic>A. terreus</italic> polyene resistance. The mode of action of AmB is associated with specific interactions with sterols, particularly ergosterol. The subsequent effects of AmpB include membrane permeabilization and induction of oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The difference between activity of NsW2 toward wild and clinical strains could be explained by the differences in fungal antioxidant defense system. Thionins induce intracellular reactive oxygen species production (H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>), which could be toxic for cells [
 <xref rid="B36-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. This is one of the mechanisms of thionin toxicity against fungi [
 <xref rid="B5-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-antibiotics-10-00166" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In the case of NsW2 sensitivity, the fungal antioxidant system is most likely not capable of scavenging all of the free radicals, which subsequently leads to cell death. In the case of NsW2 resistance, the antioxidant system overcomes thionin-induced oxidative stress. However, the absence of NsW2 activity on non-clinical isolates suggests the presence of an alternative mechanism of nigellothionin action on fungal cells.
</p>
