<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Peppermint and chamomile are medicinal and aromatic plants that have long been grown for their essential oils as valued aromatic agents. They are highly regarded and widely used medicinal plants in traditional medicine and grown for their dry flowers and leaves that are used for herbal teas. Peppermint (
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> L.) is a hybrid mint, a cross between 
 <italic>Mentha aquatica</italic> L. and 
 <italic>Mentha viridis</italic> L. It is a perennial species of the family Lamiaceae cultivated mainly as an annual crop. The content and composition of peppermint essential oil have economic value for producers, processing industries, manufacturers of peppermint-containing products, as well as for consumers [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Literature sources reveal that the dry aerial biomass of peppermint growing in Serbian localities contains approximately 1–2% essential oil, while leaves contain 2–4%, including approximately 40 chemical components in it, the major of which are: menthol, menthone, iso-menthone, limonene, neo-menthol, menthofuran, trans-sabinene hydrate, pulegone, menthyl acetate and β-caryophyllene [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Chamomile (
 <italic>Chamomilla recutita</italic> (L.) Rausch., syn. 
 <italic>Matricaria chamomilla</italic> L.) is a long-known medicinal plant species of the family Asteraceae, which has often been referred to as the “star of medicinal species”. Chamomile flowers grown for drugs have approximately 120 chemical constituents, such as terpenoids and flavonoids, which have anti-inflammatory, antiseptic, stimulating, carminative, spasmolytic, and sedative activity. Chamomile flowers produce blue essential oil whose yield varies from 0.2 to 1.9%, while their leading constituents are α-bisabolol, chamazulene and farnesene [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-01286" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
