<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ab005">
 <p>Owing to extremely high salinity and harsh environmental conditions, T. 
  <italic>articulata</italic> is one of the most abundant wild plants growing in the deserts of Saudi Arabia. Such plants may contain novel compounds to display promising biological activities. Here, in this study, we evaluate the biological activities of methanolic extracts of fresh leaves, dry leaves, stem, and roots of T. 
  <italic>articulata.</italic> The antioxidant activity was determined by 2, 2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) and total phenolic and flavonoid content were determined using standard colorimetric methods. Whereas antimicrobial and ant-proliferative activities were determined by standard well-diffusion and 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT) methods, respectively. Our results demonstrate that all methanolic extracts of T. 
  <italic>articulata</italic> showed antioxidant activity, however, the methanolic extract of dry leaves exhibits promising antioxidant effect with IC₅₀ value 49.08 ± 1.98, which was strongly supported by total phenolic (409.92 ± 6.03 mg GAE/g DW) and flavonoid (177.71 mg QE/g DW) content. Although, antimicrobial activity was also exhibited by all the methanolic extracts, however, methanolic extract of dry leaves exhibits promising antimicrobial activity in Gram-positive bacteria Staphylococcus 
  <italic>epidemidis.</italic> Furthermore
  <italic>,</italic> MTT assay revealed that all methanolic extracts exhibit antiproliferative activity in MCF-7 (breast cancer) and RKO (colorectal cancer) cells with IC₅₀ values ranges from 219 ± 5.112 µg/ml to 253 ± 5.231 µg/ml and 220 ± 4.330 µg/ml to 325 ± 6.213 µg/ml, respectively. However, the most promising antiproliferative effect was displayed by methanolic extract of dry leaves with IC₅₀ values 219 ± 5.112 µg/ml and 220 ± 4.330 µg/ml, respectively
  <italic>.</italic> In summary, these findings provide evidence that T. 
  <italic>articulata</italic> has promising biological activities and can be used for many pharmaceutical activities in the future.
 </p>
</abstract>
