<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Traditional medicine, since the dawn of history, has exploited the knowledge about plants and natural compounds for medical treatments, laying the foundations of modern medicine and pharmacology. The growing interest towards the application of natural compounds, and in particular essential oils (EOs), stems from their potential multi-purpose functional use as antibacterial, antiviral, antifungal, and antioxidant agents [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. The essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">Melaleuca alternifolia,</italic> (Maiden &amp; Betche) Cheel, commonly known as tea tree oil (TTO), is a complex mixture of approximately 100 compounds, produced by the homonymous Australian plant, member of the Myrtaceae family [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. TTO is highly employed in medicine and in the pharmaceutical, food and cosmetic industries due to several biological properties (antimicrobial, antioxidant, antitumor, insecticidal, etc.) [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Currently, the composition of 
 <italic class="italic">M. alternifolia</italic> essential oil (terpinen-4-ol type) is regulated by the International Organization of Standardization (ISO) 2004, that sets the cut off value for the 15 main components of the TTO [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. The composition of 
 <italic class="italic">M. alternifolia</italic> EO is variable and depending to climate, age of leaves, leaf maceration, and duration of distillation [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Generally, the TTO contains numerous monoterpene and sesquiterpene as well as aromatic compounds, which the principal is the terpinen-4-ol (TER), also known for biological activities, especially for anti-bacterial effects [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Nonetheless, it has been acknowledged that EOs show toxic activities when applied to different cell populations, including fibroblasts, epithelial cells, monocytes, and neutrophils [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Only a few data have been reported about spermatozoa and EOs both in humans (
 <italic class="italic">Trachyspermum ammi</italic> [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]; 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus mumbianus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]) and animals (
 <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]). On swine spermatozoa, some studies have already been performed about the effects of 
 <italic class="italic">Thymbra capitata</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> EOs [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-24-01071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>].
</p>
