<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">About 65% of infections are caused by microorganisms developing on top of, rather than within, the free-living planktonic state [
 <xref rid="B71-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>]. Biofilms are an association of microorganisms that are attached to the surface and encased within a self-produced matrix of exopolymeric substances. Biofilms are constituted by microorganisms with an extraordinary degree of organization. The Candida biofilm consists of a heterogeneous structure that is composed of yeast and hyphae cells surrounded by a self-secreted extracellular matrix. The Candida biofilm frequently shows resistance to conventional antifungal drugs such as amphotericin B and fluconazole. During biofilm formation, an increase in the metabolic activity was associated with an increase in antifungal resistance, which was coincident with biofilm maturation [
 <xref rid="B73-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. Biofilm resistance constitutes an important factor in human disease. The biofilm in 
 <italic class="italic">Candida</italic> spp. represents an important virulence factor, and its reduction is very important in combating infections. It is alarming that biofilm formation by Candida species may increase resistance to antifungal therapy and protect the microbial cells from the host immune defenses [
 <xref rid="B74-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. The possibility of essential oils having potential antibiofilm activity has been studied by many authors. Indeed, Agarwal et al. [
 <xref rid="B75-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>] reported the antibiofilm activity of 30 EOs against 
 <italic class="italic">CA</italic>. Four EOs, including eucalyptus, peppermint, ginger grass, and clove, showed 80.87%, 74.16%, 40.46%, and 28.57% biofilm reduction, respectively. Saharkhiz et al. [
 <xref rid="B55-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>] described the inhibition of biofilm formation of 
 <italic class="italic">CA</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. dubliniensis</italic> with 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic> EOs at concentrations of up to 2000 μg/mL. Stringaro et al. [
 <xref rid="B69-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>] reported that 
 <italic class="italic">M. suaveolens</italic> EO was able to reduce biofilm formation by about 80% at concentrations of 780 μg/mL and 1560 μg/mL in sensitive and resistant to fluconazole 
 <italic class="italic">CA</italic> strains. Other authors, such as Busato de Feiria et al. [
 <xref rid="B76-medicines-05-00112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>], observed the antibiofilm activity of three species of 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">M. aquatica</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">M. arvensis,</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">M. piperita</italic>), which were able to inhibit biofilm formation and disrupt the mature biofilm of 
 <italic class="italic">CA MYA-2876</italic>. These EOs inhibited up to 50% of the biofilm formation at concentrations of 31 μg/mL, 25 μg/mL, and 4000 μg/mL. 
</p>
