<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22" class="p">Cheese is one of the major fermented dairy products. Dairy products are an excellent source of high quality protein and milk fat. It is a rich source of fat soluble vitamins and also an important source of minerals such as calcium, phosphorous and concentrated source of energy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">66</xref>]. A study was performed in traditional Mexican cheese (Cotiaj) to investigate the antioxidant activities of peptides produced during the 6 months ripening period. Peptides were characterized by HPLC and results showed that peptides with antioxidant activity were produced during the ripening period of 6 months. 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) free radical scavenging activity of six month old cheese was 98% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>]. Cheddar cheese was prepared using lactobacillus para casei as starter culture and changes in antioxidant characteristics of cheddar was monitored for six months. Different antioxidant assays were used as indicators of antioxidant activity and it was noted that DPPH and superoxide free radical scavenging activities of cheese increased as up to four months of ripening. The increase in antioxidant activities was attributed to the production of water soluble peptides. Antioxidant activity and extent of water soluble peptides were strongly correlated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>]. Antioxidant activity of white brined cheese prepared from overheated milk (90 °C, 10 min) was investigated. Antioxidant activity of water soluble and water insoluble fraction of cheese increased during the ripening period and antioxidant activities were correlated with degree of proteolysis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>]. Effect of phytochemicals on antioxidant characteristics of cheese have been summarized in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab9" ref-type="table" class="xref">9</xref>.
</p>
