<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="BB1" position="float" class="boxed-text">
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Executive summary</title>
 </caption>
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">The enhanced adverse effect of synthetic drugs and antibiotics has paved way toward the utilization of natural products of plant origin unambiguously in recent years.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">The present review explored the protection against cellular damage resulting from radiation of approximately thirty aromatic plant extracts or plant-derived compounds.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">Many aromatic plant extracts or plant products have shown significant radioprotection in different model systems such as 
    <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic>, 
    <italic class="italic">ex vivo</italic> and/or 
    <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">It is a well-known fact that radiation is a powerful cytotoxic agent. Reactive oxygen species such as superoxide anion, singlet oxygen, hydroxyl radical, nitric oxide, hydrogen peroxide and peroxyl radicals generated by ionizing radiation in biologic system causes cellular injury due to lesions in DNA and proteins.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">The radical scavenging and antioxidant properties such as reduction in radiation-induced lipid peroxidation are some of the notable characteristics of aromatic plant extracts studied in various models of radiation damage.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">In most of the studies, it has been shown that while protecting against the detrimental effects of radiation, there is a capacity to significantly increase the survival rates of small animals exposed to radiation. Results of such studies point out possible applications during radiotherapy and could find application in treatment for victims of nuclear plant accidents or leakage, or radiation terrorism.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">Aromatic plants and their products have gained momentum globally during recent times, with wide applications in the herbal drug industry.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">Natural resources such as wastelands and forests could serve as reservoir for the same. With the increasing burden on natural resources, alternatively, introduction of crops through cropping systems could help out to a great extent with checks on activity including chemical composition.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">Plant material utilized as a specific compound or group of compounds should be well standardized, characterized and processed.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p class="p" xmlns="">Also, the scientific community must be encouraged to focus studies on screening more and more aromatic compounds of plant origin for their different bioactivities, including radioprotection, and to explore the molecular mechanisms involved in the same.</p>
  </div>
 </list>
</boxed-text>
