<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza is one of the most important health problems. There is still a need to develop new anti-influenza drugs to ensure the appropriate bioavailability of drugs for treating a broad spectrum of influenza viruses, including seasonal flu and possible pandemic infections. All influenza viruses bear two surface glycoproteins, hemagglutinin and neuraminidase, which are the antigens that define the particular influenza strain. The hemagglutinin is a sialic acid receptor–binding molecule and mediates the entry of the virus into the target cell. Neuraminidase (sialidase) enzymes are glycoside hydrolases that cleave α-ketosidic linkage between the sialic acid (
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylneuraminic) and an adjacent sugar residue to which the newly formed particles are attached. This cleavage enables the virus to be released from the host’s cells. When inhibiting neuraminidase, infection would be limited to one round of replication, rarely enough to cause disease. Neuraminidase may also facilitate viral invasion of the upper airways, possibly by cleaving the sialic acid moieties on the mucin that bathes the airway epithelial cells. The first neuraminidase inhibitors to be designed were DANA (2-deoxy-2,3-didehydro-
 <italic>N</italic>-acetylneuraminic acid) and FANA (2-deoxy-2,3-dehydro-
 <italic>N</italic>-trifluoroacetylneuraminic acid) [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. They served as the lead structures in the development of the new neuraminidase inhibitors known as zanamivir and oseltamivir [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, a mutation of the influenza virus resulted in its resistance to these drugs, which prompted the development of neuraminidase inhibitors containing a β-amino acid moiety for the influenza virus. Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-00438" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] started from the initial 
 <bold>A-87380</bold> (
 <xref rid="molecules-26-00438-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, Compound 
 <bold>1</bold>, (3
 <italic>S</italic>,4
 <italic>S</italic>)-4-amino-1-(
 <italic>tert</italic>-butoxycarbonyl)-pyrrolidine-3-carboxylic acid), belonging to the β
 <sup>2,3</sup>-amino acid heterocyclic derivatives as other compounds presented in 
 <xref rid="molecules-26-00438-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, which acted as a modestly active neuraminidase inhibitor with IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 50 μM. In the chemical structures of biologically active compounds presented below, the β-amino acid moiety is highlighted in blue.
</p>
