<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aside from these structural and phylogenetic aspects, a major blind spot in these studies is the question of the biological role of the identified NLR signalling cascades. This is true for the microbial NLRs involving amyloid motifs but equally for the microbial NLRs in general. In particular, with the exception of a handful of NLRs involved in allorecognition in fungi, for none of these systems are the triggering cues known [
 <xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. While the central connection point (the amyloid signalling motif 
 <italic>per se</italic>) begins to be well defined, both the downstream events (how exactly do HeLo-related proteins bring about membrane damage?) and foremost the upstream activation steps (what are the ligands?) remain for the time being, at best, highly hypothetical. Then, an important knowledge gap resides in the definition of the actual structure of the NLR amyloid signalosomes, notably regarding the actual subunit stoichiometry of these complexes. In addition, what is unclear at present is whether the execution domains (such as HeLo) remain associated to the NLR moiety as a heterotypic amyloid assembly or whether the PFD regions receive the structural template information and then detach from the NLR amyloid hub. Thus, while some structural aspects of amyloid signalling in fungi have been explored in atomic detail [
 <xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], the global structural and biological understanding of these nanomachines is still in its very infancy. Important also is to articulate precisely, the relation of amyloid signalling to prion propagation. While several of the amyloid signalling components from fungi, bacteria and mammals (HELLP, HELLF, BASS and RHIM) could be artificially turned into prions, none of these systems, with the notable exception of [Het-s] (and σ in 
 <italic>Nectria</italic>), occurs as natural prions. Only the latter two behave as infectious entities and cytoplasmic genetic elements transmitted between organisms. This is the very property that ignited in early studies the interest of pioneering scientists such as Janine Beisson.
</p>
