<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the same way, our findings showed that the manure and vegetable compost soils promoted thymol synthesis, whereas potting mix, professional agriculture mixture, and nursery mixture soils were of the thymol/carvacrol chemotype. These variations confirm the influence of the edaphic conditions on the chemical components’ biochemical pathways of oregano plants. Indeed, EO yield and terpenoids synthesis can be influenced by nutrient availability in the soil [
 <xref rid="B40-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. The authors of [
 <xref rid="B43-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] proved the effect of N and P treatments on the main constituents of 
 <italic class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</italic> (Mill.) essential oil (1.8-cineole, borneol, camphor, α-terpineol, myrtenal). The increase in the amount of aluminium, copper, iron, potassium, manganese, phosphorus, and sulphur in soil affected the amount of EO of 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus pulegioides</italic> and the biosynthesis of the main compounds [
 <xref rid="B44-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. The authors of [
 <xref rid="B45-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] found a positive correlation coefficient between N and essential oil contents in Egyptian oregano (
 <italic class="italic">Origanum syriacum</italic> L. var. 
 <italic class="italic">aegyptiacum</italic> Tackh). Nitrogen fertilization seemed to increase the biosynthesis of thymol and carvacrol. However, contrasting results were obtained indicating that organic fertilizers such as compost and manure may present significant influence on the EO chemical composition in medicinal plants [
 <xref rid="B36-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>].
</p>
