<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Moreover, our results highlighted the effect of mycorrhizal inoculation on EO composition and showed that the concentration of carvacrol was higher in inoculated conditions with respect to non-inoculated ones, while the concentrations of thymol decreased with inoculation. Therefore, inoculation may orient biosynthesis towards the preferential formation of a specific constituent leading to a defined chemotype by activating specific enzymes or group of enzymes. Indeed, AMF symbiosis is known to enhance the contents of some secondary metabolites of medicinal plants [
 <xref rid="B39-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] by increasing the density of glandular trichomes [
 <xref rid="B48-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>] and enhancing the phosphorus plant nutrition [
 <xref rid="B23-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Nevertheless, there are contrasting investigations indicating that AMF symbiosis did not have any significant influence on the EO chemical composition in medicinal plants [
 <xref rid="B22-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Besides, after 16 weeks of culture, moderate spontaneous AMF oregano root colonization rates were observed in the agricultural soil (non-sterilized and non-inoculated soil). This is due to the presence of autochthonous AMF spores in the soil. Based on morphological characters, three AMF species were identified in the studied agricultural soil (
 <italic class="italic">Funnelliformis mosseae</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Septoglomus constrictum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Claroideoglomus lamellosum</italic>). Addition of commercial mycorrhizal inoculum in the soil led to significant improvement of colonization rate of 
 <italic class="italic">O. syriacum</italic> roots in comparison with non-inoculated conditions. Nevertheless, in spite of the moderate colonization rate, arbuscular mycorrhizal inoculation significantly increased the shoot biomass of oregano plants but only in non-sterilized soil. It is well know that arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi improve plant growth by (1) exploring a larger volume of soil, (2) enhancing the mineral (phosphate, nitrogen, oligo-elements) and water nutritional state of their hosts, and (3) alleviating biotic and abiotic stresses such as pollution in host plants [
 <xref rid="B49-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Besides, the presence of both AMF, as well as soil microorganisms such as plant growth-promoting rhizobacteria (PGPR) strains in non-sterilized soil may explain this observation [
 <xref rid="B51-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-foods-08-00090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>].
</p>
