<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Allium cepa</italic> L (onion) and 
 <italic>Allium sativalum</italic> L (garlic) (shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-1179551420963106">Figure 1</xref>) are perennial plant of the 
 <italic>Alliaceae</italic> family. They are grown all over the world and are commonly used as spices.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr18-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup> The most active component of fresh 
 <italic>A. sativalum</italic> (garlic) is allicin while 
 <italic>A. cepa</italic> (onion) have a unique combination of 3 compounds; fructans, flavonoids and organo-sulphur compounds.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr19-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> Tannins, flavonoids, sterols and triterpenes are present in all varieties of onion oil but absent in all varieties of garlic oil.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr19-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> Garlic oil have the highest phytochemical content when compared with the juice or dry forms and is thus recommended for medicinal use.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr19-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> They oils from garlic and onion are dominated by sulfur containing compounds.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr20-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 </sup> These organo-sulphur compounds are responsible for their smell and taste.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr19-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> The organo-sulphur compounds have antidiabetic property and antioxidant property.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr21-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr22-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> Wu and Xu,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr23-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> reported that aqueous extract of onion bulb has no α-amylase inhibitory potential but has α- glucosidase inhibitory activity. Their ethanolic extracts have been reported to have alpha amylase inhibitory activity.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr24-1179551420963106" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> It is possible that the α- amylase inhibitory activity of onion and garlic is present in the organo-sulphur containing oils. This study, therefore investigated the α- amylase inhibitory potential of oils from onion (
 <italic>Allium cepa)</italic> and garlic (
 <italic>Allium sativalum</italic>).
</p>
