<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The term niacin (also known as vitamin B3) refers to all molecules with the biological activity of nicotinamide. It functions in the body as a component of Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide Phosphate (NADP) and Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide Phosphate hydrogen (NADPH), which are involved in many metabolic processes, including glycolysis, FA metabolism, and tissue respiration. Its effect on fasting blood lipids is well established and pharmacological doses of niacin have been used for five decades to treat lipid disorders and try to prevent CVD. Indeed, niacin diminishes fasting blood TG concentration, likely by its inhibitory effect on VLDL production in T2D patients [
 <xref rid="B140-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>], as well as LDL-C concentration, and raises HDL-C concentration in hypercholesterolemic patients and in subjects with diabetes and peripheral arterial disease [
 <xref rid="B141-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">141</xref>,
 <xref rid="B142-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">142</xref>]. Nevertheless, its role on postprandial lipemia is still controversial because the only 3 studies dedicated to this topic showed different results. Indeed, in a first study, niacin treatment did not significantly changed CM kinetics in subjects with isolated low HDL-C [
 <xref rid="B143-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">143</xref>] while in a second one, which was performed in normolipidemic men with hypoalphalipoproteinemia, it significantly diminished it [
 <xref rid="B144-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">144</xref>]. In a third study performed in T2D patients, an intermediate effect was observed with a decrease in the postprandial secretion rate of apoB-48-containing particles without a significant change in iAUC of postprandial plasma TG and apoB-48 concentrations [
 <xref rid="B145-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">145</xref>]. The reason for this discrepancy is not known but it might be due to the form of niacin used, i.e., crystalline or another formulation, e.g., extended-release or sustained-release [
 <xref rid="B146-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">146</xref>], as well as to the characteristics of the subjects. Although it has been shown, in lean and obese subjects, that niacin reduces FFA mobilization from adipocytes, perhaps by suppressing lipolysis [
 <xref rid="B147-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">147</xref>], and diminishes the liver formation of TG via noncompetitive inhibition of liver diacylglycerol acyltransferase-2 (DGAT2) [
 <xref rid="B148-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">148</xref>], mechanisms that explain its role on postprandial lipemia have not been elucidated until the results of a recent study that give an idea on the potential mechanism. Indeed, in a study, which was performed in statin-treated T2D subjects, it was observed that extended-release niacin reduced postprandial secretion rate of apoB-48-containing particles [
 <xref rid="B145-nutrients-11-01299" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">145</xref>].
</p>
