<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec24" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The colour and fragrance of the extracted essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower obtained in this study were similar to previous report of Wanzala &amp; Ogoma, [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Previous study done by Chamorro et al., [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>] on the EO from 
  <span class="italic">Tagetes minuta</span> flower showed that β-Ocimene was reported having the highest chemical content of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower and this agrees with our result. However, study done by Shirazi et al., [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>] and Garcia et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>], reported the predominance of dihydrotagetone in the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> which was not found in the GC-MS result of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> in our study. Several studies have shown that the chemical composition of the extracted essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> varied according to the location where it was harvested, the growth stage at which it was harvested and the part of the plant used for the extraction [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The chemical composition from the GC-MS analysis of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> plant grown in Kenya do not reveal some of the compounds present in our result as reported by Kyarimpa et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], as well as those grown in Argentina [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in the chemical constituents of 
  <span class="italic">Tagetes</span> oil has also been allotted to some environmental variables like soil, temperature and the total period of exposure to sunlight [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. The differences in the chemical constituents of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower could be attributed to many factors which could include but not limited to location, stage of cultivation, season of cultivation and part of the plant used. The chemical composition of the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. mimuta</span> flower shows various classes of terpenes ranging from hemiterpenes to sesquiterpenes. Similar study done by Wanzala &amp; Ogoma, [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>] showed that 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> essential oil contains a wide range of secondary metabolites mainly sesquiterpenes and monoterpenes including β-ocimene, camphene and bicyclogermacrene and their report corroborates with our result. At 0.5 mg/mL concentration, the EO was 72% while vitamin C was 76% and the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower displayed lower DPPH radical scavenging activity at various concentrations compared to the vitamin C as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. Our result is similar with the report of Muyima et al., [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>] on inhibitory effect of the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> against DPPH radical. The action implicated in antioxidant activity assay is the capacity of the molecule to release hydrogen atom to a radical which is the key factor that is involved in free radical scavenging activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. This effect is displayed as the colour DPPH• fades away (purple to yellow) in the test solution due to the production of neutral DPPH-H molecule upon absorption of hydrogen atom from an antiradical [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. The sample antioxidant strength is established by the decreased of UV absorption at 517 nm. Study has shown that DPPH method is not an exact radical specie assay but a general radical scavenging strength of an antioxidant compound [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the assumed antioxidant strength of the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower, we used a mono-cation (ABTS radical) and one specific type of specie, the lipid peroxyl radical. The antioxidant activities of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower and vitamin C were concentrations dependent as observed in DPPH Test. However, a lower radical scavenging effect of 70% was displayed by EO on ABTS radical at highest concentration (0.50 mg/mL) while vitamin C had higher effect of 80% compared to the DPPH experiment as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. The IC
  <sub>50</sub> values of 2.76 mg/mL and 1.14 mg/mL for EO flower of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> and vitamin C were obtained from the linear regression equation from the graph. Percentage lipid peroxidation inhibitory activity of the EO was higher than that of vitamin C (standard drug) and the inhibitory effects was dose dependent. The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower exhibited the highest lipid peroxidation inhibitory effect of 71% ± 0.001 at the concentration of 0.5 mg/mL with IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of 3.23 mg/mL while vitamin C displayed lower percentage lipid peroxidation inhibitory effects of 54% ± 0.004 with IC
  <sub>50</sub> value of 4.19 mg/mL as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>. The result implies that the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower possess higher lipid peroxidation properties than vitamin C. Antiradical scavenging action of the essential oils may be credited to the substitution of hydroxyl groups of the aromatic ring systems of the phenolic compounds due to their hydrogen giving capacity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. Our results in this study demonstrate the ability of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower to scavenge three different radicals suggesting it usefulness as a good antioxidant agent for further investigation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MIC values of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> against the test bacteria strains as shown in Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a> displayed that the EO was more active against Gram-negative than Gram-positive bacteria and this report is not in agreement with the report of Senatore et al., [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] and they reported that the MIC value of the EO of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> from UK for Gram-positive bacteria were 6.25–25 μg/mL and 25–50 μg/mL for Gram-negative bacteria. Minimum bactericidal concentration of any test sample is the lowest concentration of antimicrobial agents capable of killing or preventing any visible bacteria growth after twenty four hours of incubation under standardized sets of conditions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. The EO showed MBC value of 0.06 mg/mL for 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> and 
  <span class="italic">E. cloacae</span> while at higher concentration of 0.125 mg/mL, it was bactericidal against 
  <span class="italic">Vibrio</span> spp. and the MBC value for 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">uberis</span> was recorded at 0.5 mg/mL (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). The essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T. minuta</span> flower had greater bactericidal effect against 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">uberis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Vibro</span> spp. and 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">coli</span>. This suggests that the essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">minuta</span> flower may contain some bioactive compounds that could be efficacious in the prevention and treatment of infectious diseases that are linked to these organisms resistant to some antibiotics.
 </p>
</sec>
