<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Antibiotics were the most efficient therapeutic agents against the growth of pathogenic bacteria. Eight of the antibiotics inhibited the growth of all or most of the pathogenic bacterial strains, but most of these products are not authorized for use in aquaculture. We included several antibiotics in our evaluation because we wanted to investigate if the pathogenic circulating strains exhibited patterns of multiple antibiotic resistance, which could be associated with antimicrobial use [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. In our study, the MAR index was on average 0.23, showing some level of resistance to antibiotics. High antibiotic resistance has been found in hatcheries worldwide, as well as higher MAR indexes in hatcheries rather than in shrimp farms [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. For instance, MAR index ranges from 0.21 to 0.38 have been reported for bacteria isolated from shrimp hatcheries [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>], whereas, MAR indexes in shrimp farms range from 0.11 and 0.32 [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The average MAR index determined in this study is low compared to values reported in other shrimp hatcheries. However, all strains were resistant at the same time to penicillin and oxytetracycline, both antibiotics used in human medicine. Similar observations of isolates with higher resistance to antibiotics used in human medicine than those used in aquaculture have been reported by several authors [
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0210478.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Most of the sampled hatcheries are in a region of multiple anthropogenic activities, without wastewater treatment, which could be a source of antibiotic pollution.
</p>
