<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">This novel and highly reliable anti-COVID-19 in vitro assay is based upon the authentic procedures of Chu and coworkers with very slight modifications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The complete procedures were carried out in a specialized biosafety level 3 (BSL-3) laboratory (SARS-CoV-2 is classified as a BSL-3 pathogen by the WHO and FDA) in Hong Kong SAR (China). The assayed SARS-CoV-2 virus, BetaCoV/Hong Kong/VM20001061/2020, was isolated from the fresh nasopharynx aspirate and throat swab of a confirmed fifty-years-aged COVID-19 male patient in Hong Kong using Vero E6 cells (ATCC CRL-1586). Stock virus (10
 <sup>7.25</sup> TCID
 <sub>50</sub>/mL) was prepared after three serial passages in Vero E6 cells in infection media (DMEM supplemented with 4.5 g/L D-glucose, 100 mg/L sodium pyruvate, 2% FBS, 100,000 U/L Penicillin–Streptomycin, and 25 mM HEPES). Following the original procedures in the literature, 
 <bold>CoViTris2020</bold> and 
 <bold>ChloViD2020</bold> compounds were synthesized (starting from gallic acid), purified (&gt; 97% purity), fully characterized, and put in small dark brown glass containers to be ready for the assay [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The pure three reference compounds were purchased from MedChemExpress (remdesivir), Sigma-Aldrich (ivermectin, B
 <sub>1a</sub> form), and Toyama Chemical “Fujifilm group, Japan” (favipiravir). The stocks of the five tested compounds were accurately prepared by dissolving each of them in dimethylsulfoxide “DMSO” (to get a concentration of 100 mM of each of 
 <bold>CoViTris2020</bold>, 
 <bold>ChloViD2020</bold>, remdesivir, ivermectin, and favipiravir). To evaluate the in vitro anti-SARS-CoV-2 activities of the two target new compounds (
 <bold>CoViTris2020</bold> and 
 <bold>ChloViD2020</bold>) in comparison with those of the standard three reference compounds (mentioned above), Vero E6 cells were pretreated with the five compounds diluted in infection media for 1 h prior to infection by SARS-CoV-2 virus at MOI = 0.02. The five tested compounds were maintained with the virus inoculum during the 2-h incubation period. The inoculum was removed after incubation, and the cells were overlaid with infection media containing the diluted test compounds. After 48 h incubation at 37 °C, supernatants were immediately collected to quantify viral loads by TCID
 <sub>50</sub> assay or quantitative real-time RT-PCR (TaqMan™ Fast Virus 1-Step Master Mix) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Viral loads in this assay were fitted in logarithm scale (log
 <sub>10</sub> TCID
 <sub>50</sub>/mL and log
 <sub>10</sub> viral RNA copies/mL), not in linear scale, under increasing concentrations of the tested compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Four-parameter logistic regression (GraphPad Prism) was used to fit the dose–response curves and determine the EC
 <sub>50</sub> of the tested compounds that inhibit SARS-CoV-2 viral replication (CPEIC
 <sub>100</sub> was also determined for each compound). Cytotoxicity of each of the five tested compounds was evaluated in Vero E6 cells using the CellTiter-Glo® Luminescent Cell Viability Assay (Promega) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The detailed values resulted from the previous assays (compound concentrations in μM) are shown in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Final results were represented as the mean ± SD from the triplicate biological experiments. Statistical analysis was performed using SkanIt 4.0 Research Edition software (ThermoFisher Scientific) and Prism V5 software (GraphPad). All reported data were significant at p &lt; 0.05.
</p>
