<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effect of MESM and its partitions on PLA
 <sub>2</sub> activity was determined using the method of Vane (
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">1971</xref>) as modified by Oyekachukwu et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Fresh human blood samples were centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 10 min after which the supernatant (plasma) was discarded. The red cells were thereafter washed three times with equal volume of normal saline and reconstituted as a 40% (v/v) suspension with normal saline. This served as the substrate for PLA
 <sub>2</sub>. Bacterial enzyme preparation was gotten from 
 <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> strain culture. The organism was cultured in MaCconkey agar for 72 h and the culture centrifuged with normal saline at 3000 rpm for 10 min. The bacterial cells settled at the bottom of the centrifuge tube while the enzyme was contained in the supernatant. Aliquots (0.1 mL) of re-suspended erythrocytes (substrate), normal saline (1.2 mL), 2 mM calcium chloride (0.2 mL), 1 mL varying concentration of MESM and partitions (0.1, 0.2, 0.4, 0.6 and 0.8 mg/mL) in 3% Tween 80 (dissolved in normal saline) and 0.2 mL of the enzyme preparation were incubated at 37 °C for 1 h. Control tubes contained 0.1 mL of the erythrocytes, 1.2 mL normal saline, 0.2 mL calcium chloride, 1 mL 3% Tween 80 and 0.2 mL of the enzyme preparation. The blanks contained everything in the test except the enzyme. After incubation, the reaction mixtures were centrifuged at 3000 
 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min and the absorption of the supernatants read against the blank at 418 nm. A known inhibitor of the enzyme (prednisolone; 0.4 mg/mL), was used as the standard control. The percentage inhibition of enzyme activity was calculated relative to control thus: 
 <disp-formula id="M0001">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="IPHB_A_1839510_M0001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="d2e408">
    <mtext>% Enzyme activity </mtext>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mfrac>
     <mrow>
      <mtext>Absorbance of test</mtext>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mtext>Absorbance of control</mtext>
     </mrow>
    </mfrac>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>100</mn>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>
 <disp-formula id="M0002">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="IPHB_A_1839510_M0002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="d2e426">
    <mtext>% inhibition of enzyme activity </mtext>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mn>100</mn>
    <mi mathvariant="normal"> </mi>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mtext> % Enzyme activity</mtext>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
