<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Emulsions are liquid-in-liquid droplets stabilized by surfactant, with size distributions ranging from several nanometers to hundreds of micrometers.
 <xref rid="cit17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref> These materials have traditionally been employed as delivery systems
 <xref rid="cit18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref> in cosmetic,
 <xref rid="cit20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref> food,
 <xref rid="cit21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref> and pharmaceutical industries,
 <xref rid="cit23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref> with more advanced applications including templates for material synthesis
 <xref rid="cit26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref> and nanoscale reactors.
 <xref rid="cit31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref> While these emerging applications showcase the potential versatility of emulsions, liquid droplets remain underdeveloped compared to other soft materials.
 <xref rid="cit11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref> Currently, a challenge in the preparation of emulsions is decoupling the size and surface charge of the materials.
 <xref rid="cit36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref> Furthermore, chemically robust approaches to append functionality to the surface of emulsions are limited in comparison to conventional nanoparticles.
 <xref rid="cit12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref> Surfactants play a critical role in the formation and stabilization of emulsions, directly affecting the size, surface charge, and stability of the droplets (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" class="xref">Fig. 1A</xref>).
 <xref rid="cit40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref> This class of amphiphilic molecules can be composed of small molecules or polymers. They orient at the liquid–liquid interface to reduce interfacial tension between the immiscible emulsion core and bulk phases. Simple surfactants such as phospholipids and poloxamers (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" class="xref">Fig. 1B</xref>) are routinely used for industrial applications, while recently engineered peptide,
 <xref rid="cit42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="cit44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref> polymer,
 <xref rid="cit45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref> and nanoparticle
 <xref rid="cit46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref> surfactants have produced responsive materials
 <xref rid="cit47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref> and sophisticated architectures. Slight changes in surfactant structure can drastically affect the physiochemical properties of the emulsions.
 <xref rid="cit39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref> These subtleties make the systematic alteration of a single characteristic difficult, precluding structure–property relationships. A method that will facilitate the decoupling of size and surface charge is the ability to control surface chemistry after the droplet has been formed.
</p>
