<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">The infection process of most emerging diseases involves two steps: introduction and adoption. Firstly, the infection agent invades a new host (regardless of its origin, environment, or different species), and secondly the agent’s establishment inside the host [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Although, first incidents of pandemics are thousands of years back, the emergence of new epidemics or the re-emergence of known infections, continue as the interaction between humans and animals including their niches increases. There are many reasons for global disease outbreaks, individual movements for example, can spread previously controlled infections in developed countries to others with poor health systems. Microbial adaptation to environmental changes, such as developing resistance to antibiotics—which is a consequence of antibiotics overuse in animal farming and food processing—increases the chances of the emergence of new strains of pathogens. Ecological changes such as deforestation, can also increase the likelihood of indirect contact with different types of insect vectors and mammalian reservoirs. The infection of some diseases can increase during the cold season, like influenza in winter. As well as the ease in the international travel of goods, animals, and humans, made the transmission of diseases or their vectors much easier yet more difficult to control [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Above all, shortage of public health facilities, such as drinkable water, educational programmes and lack of living expense can participate largely in disease outbreak as well as the re-emerging of previously contained contagions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Since the 1940s, the human lifespan has been greatly improved by the introduction into the drug discovery field of naturally produced fungal bioactive molecules, as well as of their semisynthetic derivatives and synthetic analogues inspired by natural products. However, nowadays we simultaneously face a challenging rise in antimicrobial resistance, and a dramatic decrease in drug innovation. The chemical constituents that are responsible for the bioactivities of fungi are mostly terpene derivatives, some of which (monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes) are volatile in their nature. These compounds are overly broad in their pharmacokinetic spectrum, and often inspired structure-based drug design, particularly in oncogenic and contagious diseases. Insightful knowledge of the chemistry, biogenetic and biotechnology associated to them, will fruitfully increase the application of their native producers—mushroom forming fungi [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].
</p>
