<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nowadays, mushrooms are consumed as medicines or as foods in the form of dietary supplements [
 <xref rid="B92-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. The enormous potential of mushroom polysaccharides and terpenoids in the treatment of diabetes has been discussed in this review. However, there are still a lot of limitations and unknowns concerning the use and consumption of mushroom bioactive compounds in diabetic patients. Currently, in contrast to the high number of experimental results, there is a very limited number of clinical trials of several mushroom species that are used as drugs for patients with type 2 diabetes. In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial, the mushroom 
 <italic>Agaricus Blazei Murill</italic> in combination with metformin and gliclazide improved insulin resistance among treated subjects with type 2 diabetes when compared with the placebo group [
 <xref rid="B93-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Other human clinical studies aiming to evaluate the efficacy and safety 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> in patients with confirmed type 2 diabetes with intervention lengths of 4–12 weeks have reported improvements in glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c), fasting plasma glucose, postprandial glucose, insulin, and C-peptide [
 <xref rid="B94-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>], whilst other studies have reported no changes in glucose parameters [
 <xref rid="B95-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Randomized controlled trials aimed to determine the oral hypoglycaemic effect of suspensions of freeze dried and powdered 
 <italic>Pleurotus ostreatus</italic> and 
 <italic>Pleurotus cystidiosus</italic> showed a significant reduction in fasting and postprandial serum glucose levels of healthy volunteers and reduced the postprandial serum glucose levels and increased the serum insulin levels of type 2 diabetic patients [
 <xref rid="B97-jof-07-00058" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. A majority of available clinical trial reports focused on the study of crude mushroom extract or polysaccharide-enriched fractions. So, further exploration of the relevance of pure mushroom compounds and their therapeutic effects in diabetic patients is warranted.
</p>
