<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Generally, the nature of lipid system used in the formation of microparticles can be valuable not only for the improved intestinal absorption, but also for shielding the food active ingredients against acid and enzymatic degradation when they come in contact with gastric fluid (GF). In produced microparticles, the wall materials must tolerate gastric conditions, such as very low pH and enzyme pepsin existing in the stomach. However, upon approaching the small intestine, microparticles are expecting to release efficiently the core active materials [
 <xref rid="B50-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Until now only few studies have extensively investigated the dissolution behavior of orally delivered SLM suitable for food applications. Therefore, only recently, one research concentrated on evaluating dissolution profiles of caffeine (CAF) from several formulations of SLM produced employing different lipids using various updated dissolution media to simulate conditions of the entire gastrointestinal tract (gastric tract and proximal human intestine) [
 <xref rid="B31-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In these dissolution tests, CAF totally dissolved within 5 min both at pH 1.2 (stomach pH) and at pH 6.8 (small intestine pH), indicating high and pH-independent water solubility. It was found, that in the case of bigger particles (&gt;250 μm), SLM composition was crucial for the dissolution behavior of active ingredients, while smaller SLM (100–250 μm) were mostly affected by the dissolution liquid content. A comprehensive review on factors affecting the bioavailability of β-carotene incorporated in solid lipid microcapsules was recently published [
 <xref rid="B77-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The studies cited in this review show that both the simulated gastric medium and the nature of lipid microcapsules affect the bioavailability of β-carotene. A Vitamin-B12 release tests were performed as well on simulated gastric and intestinal system fluids [
 <xref rid="B50-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. SLM formed from vegetable fat and soy bean lecithin gradually released 90% of its encapsulated Vitamin-B12 in gastric fluid after 90 min of the experiment. When release studies were performed in simulated intestinal fluid, from the beginning of the analysis a high amount of vitamin was observed for all formulations. In another study, the survival of encapsulated probiotics was found to be above 75% when evaluated under simulated gastrointestinal conditions. The survival of probiotics was satisfied as well under different stress conditions (low pH, high level of sucrose and NaCl), showing that encapsulation improved their protection compared to the free form [
 <xref rid="B36-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In the case of in vitro release behavior of caramel flavor, the release rate of the resultant particles in the simulated gastric environment was weak; however, the release rate in the simulated intestinal environment increased rapidly within 30 min. Approximately 70% of the core material was released within 120 min [
 <xref rid="B56-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The taste-masking ability of microencapsulated powders was studied in vitro by dissolution of Quercetin-loaded SLM in the simulated salivary medium (pH 6.8). A significantly reduced dissolution rate of microencapsulated Quercetin in the simulated salivary medium in comparison to a non-encapsulated one may propose potentially good taste-masking effectiveness of this type of encapsulation [
 <xref rid="B42-foods-10-00400" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
