<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The current study showed that the area has a substantial diversity of medicinal plants; utilization of medicinal plants and plant-based remedies is abundant in the area. Total of 109 medicinal species, from 64 families were documented for the treatment of 64 various ailments. 
 <italic>Aconitum violaceum, Broussonetia papyrifera, Cedrus deodara, Celtis caucasica, Conandrium arnotaimum,</italic> and 
 <italic>Pinus wallichiana</italic>, were reported for the first time from the study area for the treatment of arthritis, diarrhea, torridity (cooling agent), wound healing, skin allergy, and as antipyretic, respectively. This confirmed our first hypothesis—that plants used especially for medicinal purposes are still highly important in this remote area. The people of the study area are economically very deprived, and their main occupation is agriculture, work as laborers, home-run shops and engaged in livestock rearing. The terrain of Gokand valley is hilly, and most of the villages of the region are cut off from frequent visits to town and inhabitants of the area still depend on the medicinal plants for the basic health requirements. In the surrounding areas of Gokand Valley, i.e., Malakand and Swat, medicinal plants have already been documented in detail; but in current study, medicinal plant species were reported with different uses. This confirmed our second hypothesis, that the local knowledge in the research area would show distinct differences to surrounding areas. Around 80% of the people in emerging economies depend on therapeutic plants to treat ailments. Indigenous healers are vital to meet the basic health requirements of local populations. The medicinal plants with maximum UV required protection for sustaining biodiversity in the investigation region. Anthropogenic activities, such as urbanization, marble mining, overharvesting, and grazing, were detected as the main threats to local biodiversity, and this, together with increasing market demand, puts increased pressure on plant resources, as we assumed in our third hypothesis. The projects of cultivation of medicinal plants must be implemented to eliminate their extinction in the area under study.
</p>
