<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hemiterpenes are quite rare; one example is isoprene itself, which is a volatile compound present in several plants, especially trees. Monoterpenes are generally responsible for essential oils fragrance, some examples are: limonene, borneol, camphor, pinene, cineole, menthol, thymol, carvacrol. Diterpenes have as a precursor geranylgeranyl diphosphate; examples are phytol, which forms the lateral chains of chlorophylls, and taxol isolated from 
 <italic>Taxus brevifolia</italic> Nutt, which is an important natural antitumor agent. Other renowned diterpenes are labdanes, which are the major components of the resin produced by plants of the Cistaceae family [
 <xref rid="B103-molecules-26-00495" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>], and the gibberellins, important phytohormones regulating plant growth and development [
 <xref rid="B104-molecules-26-00495" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Squalene is triterpenes’ precursor, deriving from numerous compounds, including tetracyclic triterpenes like dammarenes, and pentacyclic triterpenes like lupanes and oleanes. The latter are often found in saponin skeletons, where they are glycosylated with one or more sugar moieties. Saponins are phytogenic biosurfactants, which induce foam formation in aqueous solution, reducing the viscosity of heavy crude oil-in-water emulsions [
 <xref rid="B105-molecules-26-00495" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Triterpenic saponins are found in numerous plants, the most renowned among them are 
 <italic>Saponaria officinalis</italic> L. (soapwort), 
 <italic>Quillaja saponaria</italic> Molina, and 
 <italic>Gypsophila arrostii</italic> Guss. [
 <xref rid="B106-molecules-26-00495" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>], which were, in fact, traditionally used for their soap properties. Saponins are classified on the basis of the differences occurring in their aglycone structure or sugar moiety. For example, on the basis of the sugar moiety they are classified into mono, bi, and tridesmosidic. The type of aglycone and the number of linked sugar residues determine the foam properties and the entity of adsorption at the interface [
 <xref rid="B107-molecules-26-00495" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>].
</p>
