<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preventive treatment with nitroimidazoles have resulted in the emergence of resistant isolates of 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic> which are potentially serious threats endangering birds’ lives particularly wild birds. Nitroimidazole-resistant isolates of 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic> have been reported from different parts of the world including Belgium, Spain, the United States and Iran (Munoz et al., 1998
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>; Gerhold et al., 2008
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>; Rouffaer et al., 2014
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>; Tabari et al, 2017a
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>). In spite of the fact that nitroimidazole-resistant strains of 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic> are becoming prevalent, very few research has focused on finding alternative antitrichomonal agents effective against 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic>. Youssefi et al. (2017)
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref> evaluated the effects of essential oil of 
 <italic>Artemisia sieberi </italic>against 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic>. Treatment with 
 <italic>A. sieberi</italic> 10 μg/ml and metronidazole 20 μg/ml resulted in no viable trophozoite in culture medium after 24 hr (Youssefi et al., 2017
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>). Also, Tabari et al. (2017a) demonstrated the antitrichomonal effects of 
 <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> alkaloid extract against 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic>, both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, and compared the effects of of metronidazole, as a conventional antitrichomonal medication with those of harmine and harmaline, the two alkaloids present in 
 <italic>P. harmala</italic>. It was shown that 
 <italic>P. harmala</italic> alkaloid extract can be considered a potent natural anti-trichomonal agent and an efficacious alternative for treating metronidazole-resistant isolates of 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic> (Tabari et al., 2017a
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>). Seddik and coworkers (2014) reported that garlic was as effective as MTZ in inhibiting 
 <italic>T. gallinae</italic> trophozoites’ growth both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. They also observed side effects like cytotoxicity, carcinogenic effects and neurological dysfunction following MTZ administration, and recommended garlic as a safe alternative for prophylactic and therapeutic uses in case of trichomoniasis (Seddiek et al., 2014
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"> ▶</xref>). 
</p>
