<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Determining the optical properties of thin films and coating application capabilities on the food surface is critical, because these will influence the appearance of the coating product, which is a necessary quality factor
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. All edible films exhibited excellent UV barrier properties in the ultraviolet range of 200–250 nm regardless of type and essential DAS incorporated (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>), which causes oxidative deterioration of food packaging, resulting in discoloration, nutrient, loss, and odor
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. This result was in consistent with those of previous reports on gelatin-chitosan films
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>, which demonstrated that protein-based films were believed to have high ultraviolet barrier properties, such as high content of the UV-absorbing aromatic amino acids tyrosine and tryptophan. The reason that the transmittance of GC-DTE was significantly lower than that of GC-DE was the unique combination of core and wall material in coaxial electrospinning. The transmittance of GC-DE film, in which DHA algal oil powder was directly mixed with gelatin-chitosan by electrospinning, was higher than that of GC-DTE film, in which DHA algal oil powder as a core material was combined with gelatin-chitosan,and the electrospun film without DHA algal oil powder had the lowest light transmittance. The increase in the transparency of the edible film was associated with the addition of DAS, and the color component of DAS and the destruction of the ordered membrane protein network also reduced the transparency of the edible film containing DAS
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>. The addition of DAS had an influence on the appearance and light-blocking properties of the edible films composed by different modes, and in particular, the ultraviolet barrier property was enhanced, which was beneficial to slow down the deterioration of DHA algal oil powder caused by ultraviolet radiation. In practice, the color of the packaged food and the acceptability of the color of the film should be considered in selecting different suitable edible films
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
