<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For determination of phenolic acids, the modified European Pharmacopoeia method [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] was used. Prior to the analysis, the extracts and the standard used for the construction of the calibration curve (chlorogenic acid, 0.025 mg/mL in 70% ethanol) were filtered through a 0.45 μm PTFE syringe filter. Quantifications were performed using an HPLC instrument (Agilent 1200 series, Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA) equipped with an autosampler and a DAD detector. Separation was performed on a Zorbax Eclipse XDB-C18 column (5 µm, 12.5 mm × 4.6 mm, Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA). A mixture of phosphoric acid and water (1:999 
 <italic>V</italic>/
 <italic>V</italic>) was used as mobile phase A, while acetonitrile was used as mobile phase B. Separation was performed at 35 °C using a flow rate of 1.5 mL/min according to the following protocol: 0–13 min (90%–78% A), 13–14 min (78%–60% A), and 14–20 min (60%–40% A). Quantification was carried out at 330 nm. The calibration curve of chlorogenic acid with the corresponding coefficient of determination (
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sup>2</sup>) was y = 1834.03x + 7.12 (
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.99964), where y is the absorbance at 330 nm and x is the weight of the analyte (μg). The limit of detection (LOD) and limit of quantification (LOQ), determined according to [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-25-05142" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], were 0.0314 μ and 0.095 μg, respectively. Retention times (t
 <sub>R</sub>) of the analytes were 6.40 ± 0.01, 7.03 ± 0.02, and 16.27 ± 0.01 min for caftaric, chlorogenic, and cichoric acids, respectively. The contents of caftaric and cichoric acids were calculated as chlorogenic acid equivalents (CAE). Total phenolic acids (TPA) were calculated as the sum of caftaric, chlorogenic, and cichoric acid contents. An example of a chromatogram is presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05142-f005">Figure 5</xref>.
</p>
