<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This experiment revealed a pronounced decrease in developmental rate of 
 <italic>A. artemisiifolia</italic> seedlings when reared at low temperatures and provided with weak solutions of nutrients. This suggests that physiological mechanisms at an early stage in their development contribute to shaping the current distribution of this species in the Czech Republic. The negative response to low temperature is in accordance with its current distribution only in the warmest parts of the country (
 <xref rid="PLV044C26" ref-type="bibr">Jehlík 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLV044C38" ref-type="bibr">Pyšek 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
  <italic>a</italic>
 </xref>). This corresponds to the distribution pattern in Austria (
 <xref rid="PLV044C15" ref-type="bibr">Essl 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2009
 </xref>), but differs from that in Hungary where the occurrence correlates with low temperatures (
 <xref rid="PLV044C36" ref-type="bibr">Pinke 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2011
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="PLV044C37" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). As the spring and summer temperatures in Hungary are within the thermal window identified by our experiments, this might indicate the importance of other environmental factors such as precipitation and soil characteristics in determining the distribution in this country (
 <xref rid="PLV044C36" ref-type="bibr">Pinke 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2011
 </xref>). The spring and summer temperatures in most of the Czech Republic are also within the common ragweed's thermal window, but at low temperatures the plants' development is delayed. For 
 <italic>A. artemisiifolia</italic>, an opportunistic species confined to open, disturbed and nutrient-rich ruderal sites and arable land (
 <xref rid="PLV044C38" ref-type="bibr">Pyšek 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
  <italic>a</italic>
 </xref>), the above factors are likely to influence its already rather poor competitive ability (
 <xref rid="PLV044C31" ref-type="bibr">Leskovšek 
  <italic>et al</italic>. 2012
  <italic>a</italic>
 </xref>) in regions where temperatures and nutrient supply are suboptimal, and adversely affect the early stage of population establishment.
</p>
