<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010" class="p">The Exploration and Production (E&amp;P) industry have continued to drill more and more technically complex wells owing to the need to boost production in consonance with the growing demand for hydrocarbon. Around the world, hydrocarbon exploration and well development projects have expanded progressively and these were occasioned by the recent advancements in oil economics, gas exploration as well as drilling technology. The improvements recorded in oil and gas exploration, have led to the drilling of extended-horizontal and ultra-deep water wells which are technically challenging and expensive. One of the challenges encountered is hole cleaning which is caused by the selection and use of an in appropriate drilling fluid or improper mud treatment (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Adenubi et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dokhani et al., 2016</xref>). To ensure an efficient and relatively safe drilling operation, an appropriate mud design and selection are required. When one fails to appropriately evaluate the performance of a drilling fluid for a given well, there are high tendencies of cost overrun and hole instability which may subsequently result in loss of the well. To avoid fluid-related challenges, the selected drilling fluid design must be somewhat flexible, so as to accommodate several design parameters. At the design stage, it is vital to identify the technical challenges that the properties of the selected fluid may impact on the wellbore/hole-section. Literature has shown that the objective of successfully completing a well is not only to reach the desired depth, but to also ascertain the formation evaluation requirements and productivity potential of the reservoir (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pink et al., 2012</xref>). These challenges can be adequately managed with the help of a real-time drilling fluid selection tool that has the capacity to choose the target-fluid for a particular operation, ensure high well-performance and thus remedy wellbore problems (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Okoro et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jain and Mahto, 2017</xref>). Real-time computer models are integral parts of drilling automation systems that have been developed and tested to provide oversight-monitoring and prediction over during drilling operation. Drilling automation is the control of the drilling process by computers which ultimately reduces human intervention. The most significant effort in drilling fluid automation has been on real-time drilling fluid monitoring. Although post-drilling analysis is necessary, information gathering and quick action/response in real-time are rather, of higher importance. When selecting a drilling fluid for a particular hole-section, it is expected that the selected fluid is cost effective without jeopardizing wellbore stability during drilling (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Okoro et al., 2018a</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>). Selection of an apt drilling fluid is a vital component in well completion operations, hence, a good drilling mud helps eliminate additional cost for the operator. The ability of the operator to simulate down-hole conditions in order to optimize drilling fluid design is one of the key factors that reduce the non-productive time during drilling operations. It also allows real-time management of wellbore conditions through measurements while drilling. Successful drilling requires knowledge of the type and characteristics of the formation being drilled which will help determine the type of fluid to be used during drilling and well completion. However, the objective of this study is to develop a real-time computer model that integrates characteristics of the formation zone such as geological composition (lithology and mineralogy) in its algorithm which helps to ascertain the optimum fluid features from core data analysis using data generated from Measurements While Drilling (MWD) and Logging While Drilling (LWD) operations.
</p>
