<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par61">Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) includes both ulcerative colitis (UC) and Crohn’s disease; both conditions are chronic and relapsing diseases of the gastrointestinal tract [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. IBD includes severe gastrointestinal symptoms associated with the ulceration of the mucosa and submucosa of the colon and the rectum [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]; this disease is quite prevalent and affects a large number of individuals each year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Previous research has revealed roles that both TNF-α and interleukins contribute to the pathogenesis of IBD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. The administration of PO reversed the colonic damage and reduced the disease activity indicators, including levels of colonic myeloperoxidase (MPO) in the 2,4,6-trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid-induced model of ulcerative colitis in rats [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Likewise, the administration of PA resulted in suppressed levels of colonic MPO as well as pro-inflammatory cytokines (i.e., TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL-6). The administration of PA also resulted in the suppression of several anti-inflammatory cytokines, including IL-4 and IL-10. UC-associated cellular pathology is dominated by the actions of activated Th2 cells, which mainly produce IL-4; likewise, IL-10 provides negative feedback during inflammation, as observed in studies featuring dextran sodium sulfate (DSS)-treated mice. The administration of PA also induces the expression of mRNA encoding mucin-1 and mucin-2 as well as the expression of the tight junction proteins that maintain the integrity of the intestinal epithelial barrier in mouse models of acute colitis. PA can also modulate the expression of apoptosis-related Bax and Bcl-2 proteins and thereby limit the pathology associated with DSS-induced signaling leading to cell death; PA can also downregulate the expression of the necrosis-associated protein, receptor-interacting protein kinase 3 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Other studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] revealed that the PA-mediated activation of cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) via a pregnane X receptor (PXR)-dependent mechanism resulted in attenuated inflammation via downstream signaling, which ultimately served to inhibit NF-κB activation and nuclear translocation; importantly, this study identified PA as a critical exogenous agonist of PXR. In vivo experiments revealed that PA prevented DDS-induced inflammation in mice by regulating PXR–NF-κB signaling. Taken together, these studies suggest that patchouli may have a profound impact on the pathogenesis of IBD mainly by its capacity to alleviate inflammation and modulate cellular apoptosis. Moreover, the identification of PA as a PXR agonist and a mediator of PXR–NF-κB signaling has provided insights into novel therapies that might be used to treat colitis. The pharmacological activities of patchouli with respect to peptic ulcer disease are included in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.
</p>
