<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>S. fulvellum</italic> is known to produce different polysaccharides, like fucoidans (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(e)</xref>), alginates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(f)</xref>), and laminarans (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2(g)</xref>). Laminarans and fucoidans are the main water-soluble polysaccharides in brown algae, whereas high-molecular mass alginic acids represent alkali-soluble polysaccharides. Alginic acid has two basic components, 
 <italic>α</italic>-1,4-linked L-guluronic acid and 
 <italic>β</italic>-1,4-linked D-mannuronic acid (both of which are hexuronic acids), arranged in homopolymeric blocks separated by regions of alternating sequences of the two monomers [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Fucoidans are a class of sulfated polysaccharides commonly present in the extracts of brown seaweeds [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Fucoidan is largely composed of 
 <sub>L</sub>-fucose and sulfate groups. It is used worldwide, especially by the food and pharmaceutical industries because of its diverse bioactive effects like anticoagulant, antioxidant, anticancer, anti-inflammatory, and immune-modulatory activities. Fucoidan is a homofucose polysaccharide usually classified into the following two types: the first (I) is composed of repeated (1 → 3)-
 <sub>L</sub>-fucopyranose units, while the other type (II) alternates repeated (1 → 3)- and (1 → 4)-
 <sub>L</sub>-fucopyranose units. Laminaran is a major storage polysaccharide present in brown seaweeds [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. It represents 35% of the dry weight of seaweeds. Laminaran consists of glucose monomers joined together mainly by a (1,3)-
 <italic>β</italic>-D-glucan backbone with 
 <italic>β</italic> (1,6) glycosidic bonds. In recent years, brown seaweeds have become important sources of natural compounds [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], many of which have been proven to possess bioactive effects [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Therefore, the need to isolate novel bioactive compounds from edible seaweeds has increased recently.
</p>
