<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Membrane lipids are the least studied biomolecules. First, the tools for the study of lipids are not as powerful as the tools used for investigating genes and proteins. Second, lipids occur in membranes in the form of ensembles, including around tens of thousands of individual members, which in turn are representative of a variety of hundreds of different molecular species [
 <xref rid="B14-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Third, the high plasticity and flexibility of biological membranes allow them to maintain their bioactivity despite the effect of external insults (reviewed in [
 <xref rid="B15-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]). Nonetheless, cells depend upon lipids for three main functions, namely energy storage, compartmentalization and signaling (reviewed in [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-20-02167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]):
 <list list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Energy storage: lipid droplets used for this function contain mainly triacylglycerol and steryl esters thanks to their relatively reduced state. These anhydrous reservoirs are needed for the efficient storage of caloric reserves and as stores of fatty acid and sterol components for membrane biogenesis.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Compartmentalization: the milieu of cellular membranes is made of lipids of amphipathic nature, comprising both a hydrophobic and a hydrophilic portion. This amphipathic nature provides the physical basis for spontaneous membrane formation because the hydrophobic moieties are prone to self-associate when dissolved in water. This predisposition to self-associate enabled the segregation of an internal milieu from the external milieu when the first cells originated. Later on, this scheme was repeated inside the cell to generate discrete organelles allowing, first, the separation of specific chemical reactions, second, the limitation in the spreading of reaction products and, third, an improvement in biochemical efficiency. Furthermore, lipids are responsible of membrane ability of budding, tubulation, fission and fusion, all them indispensable for cell division, biological reproduction and intracellular membrane trafficking.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Signaling: in signal transduction, lipids first define membrane domains that allow the aggregation and dispersion of particular proteins, and subsequently organize secondary signaling or effector complexes; they can also act as first and second messengers. The rupture of amphipathic lipids generates bipartite signaling elements, which can be spread both within a membrane (by hydrophobic portions of the molecule) and through the cytosol (by soluble/polar portions of the molecule).</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
