<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Materials and Chemicals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methanol (MeOH), diethyl ether, petroleum ether, formic acid, hydrochloric acid, and acetone were purchased from J.T. Baker B.V. (Deventer, the Netherlands). Hexane, ethanol (EtOH), chloroform (CHCl
   <sub>3</sub>), anhydrous sodium sulfate (Na
   <sub>2</sub>SO
   <sub>4</sub>), and potassium hydroxide (KOH) were bought from Carlo Erba Reagents (Milan, Italy). Deionized water (&gt;18 MΩ cm resistivity) was obtained from a Milli-Q SP Reagent Water System (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). Supelco™ 37 Component FAME Mix, containing the methyl esters of 37 fatty acids (Supelco, Bellefonte, PA, USA; catalog No. 47885-U), was used. Lipase from porcine pancreas (EC 3.1.1.3), 
   <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2-diacylglycerol kinase from 
   <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span> (DAGK; EC 2.7.1.107), cholesterol (≥99%), ergosterol (≥95%), stigmasterol (~95%), β-sitosterol (≥95%), 5-α-cholestane (≥97%), γ-linolenic acid (≥99%), 2′,7′-dichlorofluorescein, 
   <span class="italic">N</span>,
   <span class="italic">O</span>-bis(trimethylsilyl)trifluoroacetamide (BSTFA), 1-octadecanol (99%), 1-docosanol (98%), 1-octacosanol (≥99%), lutein (≥97%), and β-carotene (≥97%) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Collection of Pumpkin Samples</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pumpkin belongs to the family 
   <span class="italic">Cucurbitaceae</span>. The samples (
   <span class="italic">C. maxima</span> L., var. Berrettina) were taxonomically identified by Luigi Frassineti (Tuder Green Service, Todi, Italy). It is a leafy green vegetable with medium-large flattish fruits with green-gray, moderately hard knobby skin, edible yellow/orange flesh, and a central cavity with numerous plump, whitish-yellow seeds. Three pumpkins cultivated in central Italy (Todi) and collected in autumn 2016 were selected for their uniformity of shape, weight, and color. The fresh pumpkin samples were weighed (about 2.5 kg each), peeled, and, after manual removal of seeds, cut into small pieces (1.5 cm × 1.5 cm × 1.5 cm) and analyzed. The seeds were cleaned to remove impurities and dried at 60 °C for 24 h in a hot-air fan oven. After that, the seeds were reweighed until the weight was constant. The samples were stored in a dry place in the dark at room temperature.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Determination of Pumpkin Chemical Composition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Crude fat, protein, moisture, and ash contents of pumpkin samples were determined according to the procedures described in the Association of Official Analytical Chemists (AOAC) method [
   <a rid="B23-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-foods-07-00030">23</a>]. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Seed Lipid Extraction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dried pumpkin seed samples were ground using a kitchen grinder (Oster, model 869-50R, Lakewood, CA, USA). Extraction of lipid fraction of the pumpkin seeds was performed using petroleum ether as a solvent in a Soxhlet extractor, according to AOAC procedure [
   <a rid="B23-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-foods-07-00030">23</a>]. The extract was dried over Na
   <sub>2</sub>SO
   <sub>4</sub>, and then the solvent was evaporated under reduced pressure using a rotary evaporator (Büchi Rotavapor B-480, Essen, Germany) at 40 °C. Finally, the residue was weighed and dissolved in hexane. The recovered oil was stored at 4 °C until use.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Isolation of TAG Fraction from Oil Samples</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The TAG fraction was isolated by thin layer chromatography (TLC), according to the method described by Cossignani et al. [
   <a rid="B24-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-foods-07-00030">24</a>], from total fat of pumpkin seed samples using silica gel plates (SIL G-25, 0.25 mm, 20 cm × 20 cm; Macherey-Nagel, Germany) and petroleum ether/diethyl ether/formic acid (70:30:1, 
   <span class="italic">v/v/v</span>) as a developing solvent. The TAG fraction was scraped off, extracted with hexane/diethyl ether (1:1, 
   <span class="italic">v/v</span>), subjected to transesterification, and analyzed by high-resolution gas chromatography (HRGC) as reported in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot6-foods-07-00030" href="#sec2dot6-foods-07-00030">Section 2.6</a> to obtain the constituent fatty acid methyl esters (FAME). The obtained data represent the total composition of FA esterified in all 3 
   <span class="italic">sn</span>-positions of TAG, named A
   <sub>t</sub>.
  </p>
  <sec id="sec2dot5dot1-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.1. Stereospecific Analysis of TAG</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stereospecific analysis procedure [
    <a rid="B25-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-foods-07-00030">25</a>] carried out on TAG of pumpkin seed oil isolated as reported in the previous paragraph involved the following steps:
    <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>The pancreatic lipase procedure (
       <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot5dot2-foods-07-00030" href="#sec2dot5dot2-foods-07-00030">Section 2.5.2</a>) to obtain the FA% intrapositional composition of 
       <span class="italic">sn</span>-2 position of glycerol backbone of TAG, named A
       <sub>2</sub>;
      </p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p>Preparation of 
       <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,3/
       <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2(2,3)-diacylglycerol (DAG), followed by the DAGK enzymatic procedure (
       <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot5dot3-foods-07-00030" href="#sec2dot5dot3-foods-07-00030">Section 2.5.3</a>), to obtain the FA% intrapositional composition of 
       <span class="italic">sn</span>-1 and 
       <span class="italic">sn</span>-2 positions of glycerol backbone of TAG, named A
       <sub>1,2</sub>.
      </p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot5dot2-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.2. Pancreatic Lipase Procedure</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrolysis of TAG was carried out according to the method provided by the Italian fat and derivate control standards (Norme Italiane per il Controllo dei Grassi e Derivati (NGD) method) [
    <a rid="B26-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-foods-07-00030">26</a>]. Tris-HCl buffer (pH 8.08), bile salts, CaCl
    <sub>2</sub>, and pancreatic lipase were added to an aliquot of TAG. The mixture was incubated under magnetic stirring in a water bath at 40 °C for 5 min, and then 6 M HCl and diethyl ether were added and the mixture was centrifuged. Diethyl ether was dried by anhydrous Na
    <sub>2</sub>SO
    <sub>4</sub> and evaporated under nitrogen flow to small volume. The hydrolytic products were separated on TLC plates, and the developing solvent system was petroleum ether/diethyl ether/formic acid (70:30:1, 
    <span class="italic">v/v/v</span>). The band corresponding to 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-2-monoacylglycerols (
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-2-MAG), visualized with 2′,7′-dichlorofluorescein spray, was scraped off, methylated, and analyzed by HRGC as reported in 
    <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot6-foods-07-00030" href="#sec2dot6-foods-07-00030">Section 2.6</a> to obtain the constituent FAME. The obtained data represent the intrapositional composition of FA esterified in 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-2 position, named A
    <sub>2</sub>.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot5dot3-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.3. 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,3/
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2(2,3)-Diacylglycerol (DAG) Preparation
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An aliquot of TAG was dissolved in anhydrous diethyl ether, and freshly prepared ethyl magnesium bromide in anhydrous diethyl ether was added. The mixture was shaken, and then pentane (0.1% acetic acid) and water were added. The solution was vortexed and centrifuged (ALC 4218 centrifuge, Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The water was removed and the organic phase was dried over anhydrous Na
    <sub>2</sub>SO
    <sub>4</sub> and concentrated with solvent removal under nitrogen stream. The DAG mixture was applied to TLC plates previously treated with 5% boric acid solution (methanol/water, 80:20, 
    <span class="italic">v/v</span>) and then activated for 1 h at 120 °C. The developing system was hexane/diethyl ether (60:40, 
    <span class="italic">v/v</span>). The band containing the 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2(2,3)-DAG fraction (Rf ≈ 0.30; Rf of the 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,3-DAG band ≈ 0.35), located by iodine vapor exposition, was scraped off and extracted with diethyl ether.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot5dot4-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.4. DAGK Enzymatic Procedure</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2(2,3)-DAG ethereal solution was concentrated under nitrogen stream, then cardiolipin solution, buffered 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2-DAGK, buffer, and Na
    <sub>2</sub>ATP were added, mixing each time. After incubation at 40 °C for 90 min under constant stirring, chloroform/methanol (2:1, 
    <span class="italic">v/v</span>) was added to the mixture to stop the reaction and extract the products of interest. The combined extracts were concentrated, treated with anhydrous Na
    <sub>2</sub>SO
    <sub>4</sub>, and applied to TLC plates. The developing system was chloroform/methanol/25% ammonia (65:25:5, 
    <span class="italic">v/v/v</span>). The band of the 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2-phosphatidic acids (
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2-PA), visualized with 2′,7′-dichlorofluorescein spray (Rf ≈ 0.1), was scraped off, methylated, and analyzed by HRGC with flame ionization detection (FID) as reported in the following paragraph to obtain the constituent FAME. The obtained data represent the intrapositional composition of FA esterified in 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2 positions, named A
    <sub>1,2</sub>.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The FA composition at the 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1- and 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-3-positions was obtained applying the following formulas:
    <div class="disp-formula">A
     <sub>1</sub> = 2A
     <sub>1,2</sub> − A
     <sub>2</sub>
     <span class="label">(1)</span>
    </div>
    <div class="disp-formula">A
     <sub>3</sub> = 3A
     <sub>t</sub> − A
     <sub>2</sub> − A
     <sub>1</sub>
     <span class="label">(2)</span>
    </div> where A
    <sub>1</sub> = % intrapositional composition of FA esterified in 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1 position; A
    <sub>1,2</sub> = % intrapositional composition of FA esterified in 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-1 and 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-2 positions; A
    <sub>2</sub> = % intrapositional composition of FA esterified in 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-2 position; A
    <sub>t</sub> = % total composition of FA esterified in all 3 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-positions of TAG; A
    <sub>3</sub> = % intrapositional composition of FA esterified in 
    <span class="italic">sn</span>-3 position.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot6-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6. Preparation of FAME and HRGC-FID Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The FAME of TAG, 
   <span class="italic">sn</span>-2-MAG, and 
   <span class="italic">sn</span>-1,2-PA fractions were prepared by transesterification. Hexane and 2 N methanolic KOH were added to the fraction and stirred for 3 min, then water was added. The organic phase (upper) containing the FAME was dried over anhydrous Na
   <sub>2</sub>SO
   <sub>4</sub>, then analyzed by HRGC. A DANI GC1000 DPC gas chromatograph (Norwalk, CT, USA) equipped with a split-splitless injector and a flame ionization detector (FID) was used. Separation was obtained using the CP-Select CB for FAME fused silica capillary column (50 m × 0.25 mm i.d., 0.25 μm f.t.; Varian, Superchrom, Milan, Italy). Chromatograms were acquired and processed using Clarity integration software (DataApex Ltd., Prague, Czech Republic). The injector and detector temperature was 250 °C. The oven temperature was held at 180 °C for 6 min, and raised to 250 °C at 3 °C/min; the final temperature was held for 10 min. Carrier gas (He) flow rate was 1 mL/min; the injection volume was 1 µL with a split ratio of 1:70. A standard solution containing 37 FAME was used to identify the individual FA. The percentage of each FA was calculated using the peak area of the samples. The data were normalized considering only the main reported FA (% mol mean values ≥0.1). 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot7-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.7. Alkaline Hydrolysis of Pumpkin Seed Oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alkaline hydrolysis of pumpkin seed oil was carried out according to the method reported by Cossignani et al. [
   <a rid="B27-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-foods-07-00030">27</a>]. Prior to alkaline hydrolysis, 0.2% 5-α-cholestane in CHCl
   <sub>3</sub> and 1% 1-octacosanol (used as internal standards) were added to the oil samples, then the American Oil Chemists’ Society (AOCS) method (Ch 6–91) was used [
   <a rid="B28-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-foods-07-00030">28</a>]. The products obtained after alkaline reaction were applied to TLC silica gel plates previously treated with 0.2 N KOH in MeOH, then activated for 1 h at 100 °C. The developing system was hexane/diethyl ether (65:35, 
   <span class="italic">v/v</span>). The band containing the sterols, visualized with 2′,7′-dichlorofluorescein spray, was scraped off and extracted with CHCl
   <sub>3</sub>. Then the solvent was evaporated and removed under nitrogen stream.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot8-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.8. Preparation of Trimethylsilyl Ether Derivatives and HRGC-FID Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The silylation reaction was carried out as described by Lombardi et al. [
   <a rid="B29-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-foods-07-00030">29</a>] with slight modifications. In brief, BSTFA and acetone were added to the sterol fraction and the reaction was carried out at 40 °C for 20 min to obtain trimethylsilyl ether (TMSE) derivatives. Sterols and alcohols, as TMSE derivatives, were analyzed using a DANI GC1000 DPC gas chromatograph equipped with a split-splitless injector and FID. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separation of TMSE sterols and alcohols was obtained using the AT-1701 fused silica capillary column (25 m × 0.25 mm i.d., 0.2 μm f.t.; Alltech, Milan, Italy). </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For analysis of TMSE sterols, the following chromatographic conditions were used: injector and detector temperature was 300 °C; oven temperature of 260 °C was held for 4 min, then increased to 300 °C at 1.5 °C/min, and the final temperature was held for 30 min; carrier gas (He) flow rate was 1.2 mL/min. </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For analysis of TMSE alcohols, the following chromatographic conditions were used: injector and detector temperature was 290 °C; oven temperature was held at 180 °C for 3 min, raised to 260 °C at 6 °C/min for 15 min, then raised to 280 °C at 2 °C/min for 30 min. </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chromatograms were acquired and processed using Clarity integration software. The percentage of each sterol was calculated by using the peak area of the samples corrected with the correction factor equal to 1 as reported by Laakso [
   <a rid="B30-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-foods-07-00030">30</a>]. TMSE sterols were also analyzed by HRGC coupled with mass spectrometry (MS) detector as described in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot9-foods-07-00030" href="#sec2dot9-foods-07-00030">Section 2.9</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot9-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.9. HRGC-MS Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A Shimadzu GCMS-QP2010 gas chromatograph equipped with a quadrupole mass spectrometer (Shimadzu, Milan, Italy) and split-splitless injector maintained at 300 °C was used. The following MS parameters were used: interface temperature 270 °C; MS ionization mode electron ionization; detector voltage 0.9 kV; acquisition mass range 50–500 u; scan speed 1000 u/s; acquisition mode full scan; scan interval 0.5 s; solvent delay 6 min. Data were collected by GC-MS Solution software (Shimadzu). The column and the chromatographic conditions were the same as those reported in 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2dot8-foods-07-00030" href="#sec2dot8-foods-07-00030">Section 2.8</a>. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">TMSE sterols and alcohols were identified by comparing retention times and mass spectra to those of authentic TMSE-derivatized compounds. Confirmation of these structures was achieved by HRGC-MS using the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST; Gaithersburg, MD, USA) 2008 library to match mass spectral peaks of phytosterol standards to those found in pumpkin seed oil samples. Comparisons of parent molecular ion (M+) and fragmentation ions/patterns were employed to assist in elucidating the identities of the phytosterols. In addition to the presence of specific ion fragments, the relative intensity of the ion fragments was considered. Some compounds, for which commercial standards are not available, were tentatively identified by comparison of relative retention times, M+ values, and fragmentation patterns with data obtained from olive oil analysis or from MS spectra reported in the literature. </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot10-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.10. Carotenoid Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The seed oil carotenoids were analyzed by HPLC with diode-array and mass spectrometry detection systems (DAD-MS). To perform this determination, a seed oil sample was diluted fourfold and injected into the HPLC system. Quali-quantitative determination of carotenoids was carried out using the HPLC-DAD-MS validated method described in Blasi et al. [
   <a rid="B31-foods-07-00030" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-foods-07-00030">31</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot11-foods-07-00030" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.11. Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FA, sterol, alcohol, and carotenoid composition data are reported as mean values and standard deviation (SD). HRGC analyses were carried out in duplicate. Data were processed and edited with Microsoft Excel 2016 (Microsoft, Redmond, MA, USA).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
