<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par63">
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> is a Gram-negative bacterial species that colonizes the gut of ~ 50% of the human population worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]; 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> has been associated with various gastrointestinal diseases including gastritis, peptic ulcers, and gastric cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Previous research identified bacterial virulence factors that promote the pathogenesis of 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>-associated disease. Among the mechanisms that have been discovered, 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> produces urease, which hydrolyzes urea in peripheral circulation; this yields bicarbonate and ammonia that can counteract the acidic environment in the stomach [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. However, 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> also releases pro-inflammatory toxins, such as vacuolating cytotoxin A (Vac A) and cytotoxin-associated gene A (Cag A); these toxins promote the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines that ultimately damage the epithelial cells in the gastric mucosa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> can survive and persist within macrophages, as urease production serves to modulate the phagosome pH and the formation of megasomes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. PA is a critical pharmacological agent isolated from patchouli that exhibits antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> both in vitro and in vivo. PA has selective antibacterial activity against 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>; it has no impact on the survival and proliferation of normal gastrointestinal bacteria and does not promote bacterial resistance. The administration of PA limits the adhesion and motility of 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>, and inhibits the expression of critical bacterial genes together with host inflammatory mediators [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. PA has been shown to inhibit the activity of urease protein in both acidic and neutral conditions by blocking both protein maturation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] and the pathway that facilitates the translocation of Ni
 <sup>2+</sup>, which eventually decrease the acid resistance of this bacterial strain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. PA at 25 and 50 µM can inhibit intracellular 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>-associated urease activity by downregulating the expression of genes encoding ureB, ureE, ureI, and nixA; this reduces the UreB protein level and thus facilitates macrophage-mediated antimicrobial activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. PA also promotes direct cytoprotective effects and limits the damage to epithelial cells associated with persistent 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> infection. Recent studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] revealed that PA could also reverse the cytotoxicity for gastric epithelial cells (GES-1) that results from an overabundance of 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>-associated urease. Specifically, the administration of PA effectively attenuated GES-1 apoptosis by actions that support the integrity of the mitochondrial membrane potential, which attenuate oxidative stress by decreasing the contents of intracellular reactive oxygen species (ROS) and MDA, and which promote the synthesis and activation of both SOD and CAT. As such, PA serves as an anti-inflammatory agent by eliminating 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> and inhibiting the expression of bacterial virulence factors and also by its actions that modulate signaling via the NF-κB and NLRP3 inflammasome activation pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. PA can also reduce 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>-mediated neutrophil recruitment and activation by inhibiting the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines, by its actions that target p22 and p47-phox, as well by modulating the expression of the 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> neutrophil activation-related gene [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Furthermore, PA can eradicate 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> and limit oxidative stress by blocking bacterial escape from the intracellular lysosome compartment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. The pharmacological mechanisms used by PA to target 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic>-induced GU are shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Taken together, these results suggest that patchouli extracts may be useful for the treatment of GU activities by their capacity to inhibit oxidative damage, reverse inflammation, induce apoptosis-associated signaling pathways, and eliminate the 
 <italic>H. pylori</italic> pathogen.
</p>
