<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Oregano (
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic>) is another popular herb and originates from the Mediterranean region, but nowadays used globally as food flavoring. Oregano essential oil has been used in folk medicine since ancient times and presents antioxidant and antibacterial activity [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. A main component of oregano essential oil (more than 60% of the oil composition) is carvacrol, a monoterpenoid phenol, which can be also be found in thyme or bergamot, but in lower concentrations [
 <xref rid="B31-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Our oregano oil sample presented a very high content of carcavrol (80.5%), which supports the antimicrobial effect findings. Carvacrol presents a good antibacterial activity by permeabilization and depolarization of the cytoplasmic membrane, as shown in several recent studies [
 <xref rid="B32-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Carvacrol also inhibit microbial toxin production, inhibit biofilm formation, reduce the fimbriae production and the swarming motility of uropathogenic 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and present anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref rid="B34-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Carvacrol is slightly soluble in water, at a concentration of 1.25 mg/mL at 25 °C [
 <xref rid="B36-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. The high carvacrol content of oregano oil together with its water solubility may explain the good antibacterial effect of its aqueous extract compared with the aqueous extract of other essential oils. Oregano oil presented the best antibacterial effect and was the only tested oil that presented bactericidal effect on all tested bacteria, including 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and MRSA. Only the thyme aqueous extract presented comparable effect (though not on 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>), but the carvacrol content of thyme oil is lower than in oregano oil, of up to 45% according do other studies [
 <xref rid="B37-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] (though in our thyme essential oil sample, carvacrol was not present). The hydroxyl group position is the single difference between carvacrol and thymol, but this, together with the terpenes’ concentrations in oils, can explain the slightly different activity. Due to this difference, carvacrol also better protects against 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas</italic> spp. biofilm development [
 <xref rid="B38-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. It was previously shown that carvacrol and thymol impairs the cell membrane, increase the membrane permeability and decrease the cytoplasmic pH in 
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B39-pathogens-08-00015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. 
</p>
