<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mohammadian et al. [
 <xref rid="B59-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] stated that 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> hydroalcoholic extract administration promotes hepatic function and inhibits the concentration of oxidative stress indices. Consistently, the extract of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> promotes and maintains the structural morphology of the hepatocellular membrane resulting in reduced activities of aspartate aminotransferase and alanine aminotransferase in serum. Amat et al. [
 <xref rid="B35-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] also supported the hepatoprotective effect of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic>. The plant inhibited sleep time induced by hexobarbitone and displayed choleretic activity (bile flow and bile solids) and excretory action as well as stimulates the secretion of bile acids. Similarly, 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> showed antioxidant action through free radical scavenging effect on hydrogen peroxide (H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>) and DPPH. Hence, the plant could serve for decreasing liver injury and as a substitute for synthetic drugs used in the management of liver disease. Though hepatoprotective effects of this herb is probable at doses lower than 200 mg/kg [
 <xref rid="B35-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] but at high doses, 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> plays antioxidant and anti-inflammatory role thus induce hepatotoxicity by inflammation and oxidation due to its thujone bioactive constituent [
 <xref rid="B60-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> extracts are examined for hepatoprotective effect with acute liver toxicity which is demonstrated by decreasing lipid peroxidation and toxicity to tetrachloromethanes (CCl
 <sub>4</sub>) [
 <xref rid="B62-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The bioactive molecules present in 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> such as phenolic acids, flavonoids, sesquiterpene lactones, and tannins exhibit hepatoprotective action in vivo [
 <xref rid="B35-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Gilani et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-09-00353" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] also ameliorated hepatic disorders including hepatitis and other hepatobiliary diseases. The possible mode of actions based in its hepatoprotective properties includes liver microsomal drug-metabolizing enzymes suppression, free radical scavenging activity, and/or calcium channels blockage. Consistently, dicaffeoylquinic acids and caffeoyl saw in 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> displayed hepatoprotective effect.
</p>
