<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">
 <italic>Dendrobium longicornu</italic> is widely used in traditional medicine for the treatment of fever and cough, as well as in tonic to produce the body fluid and nourish stomachache [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>]. The whole plant of 
 <italic>D. longicornu</italic> largely contains bibenzyl and phenanthrene, as well as minimal amounts of monoaromatics, steroid and flavonoid derivatives [
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>]. Due to the presence of such compounds, its extract has been shown the antioxidant, antimicrobial and cytotoxic effects [
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Its wild resource has been depleted by overexploitation to meet the demand in traditional medicine. There is also difficulty in the germination of its seeds in nature without prior symbiosis with special mycorrhizal fungi [
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>]. Hence, it has to be found as threatened species in Appendix II of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species (CITES). Plant tissue culture technique provides a way forward to conserve its natural population [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and production of bioactive secondary metabolites [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Several chemical compounds of pharmaceutical significance like alkaloids, polyphenols, anthocyanins and carotenoids are synthesized and accumulated on 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> developed tissues [
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Protocorm is a special organ induced from seed culture that belongs to the somatic embryo and undergo growth and differentiation into plants. They are highly proliferated tissues which accumulate high content of secondary metabolites [
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>]. Recent studies have focused on the biomass production of protocorms and callus for harvesting bioactive compounds through 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> culture 
 <italic>via</italic> suspension and bioreactor [
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>]. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> developed protocorms of 
 <italic>D. longicornu</italic> were used as the main material source in the bioactivity assays. The objectives of the present study were to establish 
 <italic>D. longicornu</italic> protocorm culture for the production of bioactive secondary metabolites and examine the effect of an extract isolated from protocorms on DPPH free radicals, bacterial growth and cancer cell proliferation.
</p>
