<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> ethanolic extract inhibits the motility of the 
 <italic>H. contortus</italic> through a destructive and inhibitive effect on the enzyme acetylcholinesterase (AChE). The enzyme rapidly hydrolyzes acetylcholine (neurotransmitter) and thus, limits and terminates the cholinergic synaptic transmission (
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr">Taylor, 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Lee, 1996</xref>). Inhibition of ACheE leads to the accumulation of acetylcholine, thereby interrupting the neuromuscular transmission causes paralysis of musculature. Due to muscular discoordination/paralysis food swallowing and movement through the digestive system is stopped. The parasites enter the state of starvation and energy deprivation and thus, unable to survive inside the host (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">Kaur and Sood, 1982</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">Opperman and Chang, 1992</xref>). The antiparasitic activity of 
 <italic>A. sativum</italic> may also be attributed to the sulfur containing compounds (e.g., ajoene and allicin) which can possibly form disulphide bonds with free thiol groups, and thus, inhibit enzymes or other proteins, which are important for survival of the parasite (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Krstin et al., 2018</xref>). Crude aqueous extract of 
 <italic>Achillea millefolium</italic> L. has profound anthelmintic activity, this could be due to the presence of several key chemical constituents one of which is eugenol. It is reported that eugenol can cause alteration of cell shape, membrane blebs (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">Machado et al., 2011</xref>), restrict cell growth, swelling, and collapsing cell membrane and arrest cell division (
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr">Ueda-Nakamura et al., 2006</xref>). The compound artemisinin of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> can inhibit vital enzymes of metabolic cascade by forming covalent bonds and resulting in irreversible inhibition of the enzyme (s) activities. The enzymes include S-adenosyl-methionine synthesase (SAMS), spermidine synthase (SpdSyn), L-lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), pyruvate kinase, and ornithine aminotransferase (OAT) (
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>). Artemisinin is also reported to disrupt mitochondrial membrane potential, cause cytochrome c release into the cytoplasm (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2016</xref>), and inhibit the electron transfer and oxidative phosphorylation of mitochondria, with final activation of caspase-3-mediated apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2005</xref>). Additionally, crude aqueous extract of 
 <italic>A. absinthium</italic> can induce ultrastructural changes such as tegumental damage, nephridial canal epithelium lining and intrauterine eggs destruction, lipid accumulation, glycogen depletion, and finally worm paralysis and death (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Beshay, 2018</xref>). Similar anthelmintic effects of tegumental disorganization/perforation and adult worm paralysis were also observed for 
 <italic>C. procera</italic> aqueous and ethanolic extracts (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Khalil et al., 2016</xref>). Bromelain extracted from 
 <italic>Ananas comosus</italic> (L.) Merr. stem has been found as potent anthelmintic against gastrointestinal nematodes (
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr">Stepek et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Domingues et al., 2013</xref>). Bromelain removes and digests the cuticle layer of nematodes resulting in immobility and death of the parasites (
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr">Stepek et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">Stepek et al., 2006</xref>).
</p>
