<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Natural products have been explored in finding anti-HIV agents with a critical focus in four mechanisms. They are HIV integrase strand transfer inhibitors [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], Nucleoside Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors (NRTIs), Nonnucleoside Reverse Transcriptase Inhibitors (NNRTIs), and Protease Inhibitors (PIs) [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Integrase is a key enzyme by which HIV inserts (integrate) its viral DNA (proviral) into the DNA of the host CD4 cell. Thus, inhibiting the integrase in the cellular level is a significant target for anti-HIV drug discovery [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. As per the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), Raltegravir was the first integrase strand inhibitor (INSTI) to be approved in 2007, followed by elvitegravir in 2012 and dolutegravir in 2014. [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Natural product discovery has been conducted much time by specifically inhibiting the integrase target [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Another target of anti-HIV drugs is reverse transcriptase inhibitors. The reverse transcriptase, a RNA-dependent DNA-polymerase, has been used by the virus to convert RNA to DNA, which is called reverse transcription. Hence, blocking reverse transcription will inhibit HIV replication [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In the last phase of viral replication, a viral protease is necessary for the cleavage of a large precursor polyprotein. This cleavage of a protein precursor is crucial for the viral particle maturation and infectivity. Saquinavir, indinavir, ritonavir, and nelfinavir are a few examples of approved protease inhibitors by the WHO [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-04878" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Thus, inhibiting protease is also considered as a significant target of anti-HIV natural products.
</p>
