<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In certain rural regions of the world, communities continue to live a traditional lifestyle and thus consume diets resembling those of our early ancestors which are naturally high in fibre. For example, inhabitants of a rural African village in Burkina Faso still consume a high fibre diet similar to that of early human settlements at the time of the birth of agriculture. A comparative study examining the gut microbiota composition of the children of Burkina Faso versus European children (from Florence, Italy) consuming a Western diet (age of participants, 1−6 years) revealed a significantly higher richness and biodiversity in the gut microbiota of the Burkina Faso group [
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>]. The African children also displayed an enrichment of Bacteroidetes and depletion of Firmicutes relative to their European counterparts. Within the Bacteroidetes, the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Prevotella</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Xylanibacter</italic> were uniquely abundant in the African children being absent in the European children. These specific bacteria harbor genes for cellulose and xylan hydrolysis. In contrast, the potentially pathogenic 
 <italic class="italic">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">Shigella</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia</italic>) were significantly over-represented in European children compared to their African counterparts. Furthermore, SCFAs were significantly more abundant in the African children. The authors hypothesise that the gut microbiota of the Burkina Faso children evolved with their polysaccharide-rich diet and protects them from inflammation and non-infectious colonic diseases. The traditionally-living Hadza people of Tanzania are one of the last hunter-gatherer communities in the world. A recent study reported no evidence of cardiovascular disease risk factors in this population [
 <xref rid="B188-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">188</xref>] and older studies reported that this group of people had relatively low rates of metabolic diseases, infectious diseases or nutritional deficiencies compared to other settled groups in the surrounding regions [
 <xref rid="B189-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">189</xref>,
 <xref rid="B190-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">190</xref>,
 <xref rid="B191-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">191</xref>]. A comparison of the gut microbiome of the Hadza people with an Italian urban cohort revealed higher levels of microbial richness and diversity in the Hadza group [
 <xref rid="B192-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">192</xref>]. These studies suggest that the Western microbiota, even in a healthy person, may in fact be dysbiotic in terms of microbial diversity owing to the low consumption of MACs, and predisposes its host to a range of diseases, particularly those which are characterised by an inappropriate immune response, a theory which has been proposed by Sonnenburg and Sonnenburg [
 <xref rid="B70-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. 
</p>
