<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While the exact mechanisms underlying the link between low microbial diversity, diet and disease are not fully understood, SCFAs undoubtedly play a role given that low MAC diets are directly linked to low SCFA levels [
 <xref rid="B70-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. Livanos et al. [
 <xref rid="B206-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">206</xref>] reported a significant decrease in the proportion of the SCFA-producing Clostridial Clusters IV/XIVa in intensive care unit patients 72 h following hospital admission which was associated with reduced gut microbiota diversity and community stability over time. Simultaneously, the facultative anaerobe 
 <italic class="italic">Enterococcus</italic> significantly expanded. These changes were associated with receipt of broad-spectrum antibiotics. The depletion of SCFAs and in particular butyrate producers has been reported in cases of CDI and asymptomatic carriage of 
 <italic class="italic">C. difficile</italic>, in sufferers of nosocomial diarrhoea and in MRSA-positive patients [
 <xref rid="B199-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">199</xref>,
 <xref rid="B200-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">200</xref>,
 <xref rid="B201-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">201</xref>,
 <xref rid="B202-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">202</xref>]. The potential importance of butyrate in maintaining an oxygen-depleted environment in the lumen and impeding colonisation by facultative anaerobes has already been mentioned [
 <xref rid="B133-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">133</xref>]; however, its specific role, if any, in colonisation resistance against 
 <italic class="italic">C. difficile</italic> infection has not yet been elucidated and thus the viable bacteria themselves are most likely the responsible agents [
 <xref rid="B200-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">200</xref>,
 <xref rid="B207-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">207</xref>]. Indeed, the loss of a specific butyrate-producing species, 
 <italic class="italic">C. scindens</italic>, a member of the 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium</italic> XIVa clade [
 <xref rid="B208-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">208</xref>], was directly associated with susceptibility to 
 <italic class="italic">C. difficile</italic> infection in a mouse model as a result of antibiotic treatment [
 <xref rid="B144-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">144</xref>]. Administration of 
 <italic class="italic">C. scindens</italic> alone or in combination with three other bacteria to antibiotic-treated mice ameliorated CDI. In this case, secondary bile acids produced by 
 <italic class="italic">C. scindens</italic> were found to be responsible for the anti-
 <italic class="italic">C. difficile</italic> effect. However, a recent study reported the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">C. scindens</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. difficile</italic> in the same stool sample and suggested that the former does not inhibit the latter [
 <xref rid="B209-nutrients-11-00923" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">209</xref>] but the study does not provide data on bile acid profiles or the 7-α -dehydroxylating activity of 
 <italic class="italic">C. scindens</italic>, the enzyme responsible for secondary bile acid production. 
</p>
