<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>The recent focus is on the analysis of biological activities of extracts from thirteen folk medicinal plants from arid and semi-arid zones of Balochistan, Pakistan. Only a small proportion of them have been scientifically analyzed. Therefore the present investigation explores the biochemical and bioactive potential of different plant parts. Superoxide dismutase was detected maximum in 
  <italic>Fagonia indica</italic>, (184.7±5.17 units/g), ascorbate peroxidase in 
  <italic>Tribulus pentandrus</italic> (947.5±12.5 units/g), catalase and peroxidase were higher in 
  <italic>Peganum harmala</italic> (555.0±5.0 and 2597.8±0.4 units/g, respectively). Maximum esterase and α-amylase activity was found in 
  <italic>Zygophyllum fabago</italic> (14.3±0.44 and 140±18.8 mg/g, respectively). Flavonoid content was high in 
  <italic>T</italic>. 
  <italic>pentandrus</italic> (666.1±49 μg/ml). The highest total phenolic content and tannin was revealed in 
  <italic>F</italic>. 
  <italic>olivieri</italic> (72125±425 and 37050±1900 μM/g, respectively). The highest value of ascorbic acid was depicted in 
  <italic>F</italic>. 
  <italic>bruguieri</italic> (F.b.N) (448±1.5 μg/g). Total soluble proteins and reducing sugars were detected higher in 
  <italic>P</italic>. 
  <italic>harmala</italic> (372.3±54 and 5.9±0.1 mg/g, respectively). The maximum total antioxidant capacity was depicted in 
  <italic>Tetraena simplex</italic> (16.9±0.01 μM/g). The highest value of lycopene and total carotenoids exhibited in 
  <italic>T</italic>. 
  <italic>terrestris</italic> (7.44±0.2 and 35.5±0.0 mg/g, respectively). Chlorophyll contents were found maximum in 
  <italic>T</italic>. 
  <italic>pentandrus</italic> var. 
  <italic>pterophorus</italic> (549.1±9.9, 154.3±10, and 703.4±20.2 ug/g, respectively). All taxa exhibited anti-inflammatory activity and anti-diabetic potential. 
  <italic>Z</italic>. 
  <italic>eurypterum</italic> seeds exhibited the highest anti-inflammatory potential (96%), along with other taxa indicated (96–76%) activity when compared with the standard drug diclofenac sodium (79%). Seeds of 
  <italic>T</italic>. 
  <italic>pentandrus</italic> (85%) exhibited the highest anti-diabetic activity. The other taxa also exhibited inhibitory activity of α-amylase ranging from (85–69%) compared with Metformin (67%) standard drug. Phytochemical screening revealed that selected taxa proved to be the potential source of natural antioxidants and could further be explored for 
  <italic>in-vivo</italic> studies and utilized in pharmaceutical industries as potent therapeutic agents validating their ethno-pharmacological uses.
 </p>
</abstract>
