<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Another conifer tree, the Chinese fir (
 <italic class="italic">Cunninghamia lanceolata</italic> (Lamb.) Hook.) has great ecological and economic importance being one of the most important plantation species in Southern China for industrial wood production. However, establishment and productivity decline of the replanted Chinese fir plantations has remained a significant problem [
 <xref rid="B261-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">261</xref>]. Phenolics were considered as allelochemicals responsible for autotoxicity in the replanted Chinese fir stands. Huang et al. [
 <xref rid="B136-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">136</xref>] showed that both total phenolic content and water soluble phenolic content in the Chinese fir stump-roots were negatively correlating with the growth of the Chinese fir seedlings. However, later it was proven that individual phenolics and triterpenoid friedelin isolated from toxic Chinese fir soil stimulated the growth of Chinese fir, whereas novel cyclic dipeptide (6-hydroxy-1,3-dimethyl-8-nonadecyl-[1,4]-diazocane-2,5-diketone) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01636-f013" class="xref">Figure 13</xref>) significantly inhibited the growth of Chinese fir [
 <xref rid="B139-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">139</xref>]. The observation that cyclic dipeptide is a highly active allelochemical was proved in [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>], where differences in the cyclic dipeptide contents in the leaf and root extracts, and in the rhizosphere soil from Chinese fir plantations of different age also explained the observed allelopathic effects. However, poor natural regeneration in coniferous forests could be caused also by other reasons. In order to estimate the leaf litter effect on germination and growth of Chinese fir seedlings the artificial plastic litter that has only the physical properties of litter was compared with natural litter that has chemical effects as nutrients and allelochemicals [
 <xref rid="B140-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">140</xref>]. The results showed that effects of plastic and natural litters did not differ, suggesting that the Chinese fir litters were primarily of physical rather than biological or chemical effect. Job da Silva et al. [
 <xref rid="B62-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>] also showed that the 
 <italic class="italic">E. saligna</italic> leaf litter physically suppresses the establishment of grassland vegetation. Chen and Wang [
 <xref rid="B137-molecules-24-01636" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">137</xref>] reported that allelochemicals of Chinese fir were released into the soil through the roots. It’s quite possible that the Chinese fir allelopathic effects were primarily connected with root exudates rather than litter leachates. In addition, the study was conducted in the controlled environment, and the results in the field could be quite different.
</p>
