<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">The differences in the species inventory we found compared to Van den Berg [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] may be caused by social or medical factors, such as the incidence of certain diseases for which our newly recorded plants are used for healing. For example, the prevalence of diabetes in Brazilian adults has increased since the 1980’s [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], and both 
 <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> and 
 <italic>Bauhinia</italic> species are employed to treat it in Brazil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. 
 <italic>Bauhinia</italic> species are also used to treat high cholesterol, kidney diseases, and high blood pressure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Although recovered by our survey, these plants were not documented before at the VOP, most likely due to their absence or lack of popularity during the time frame of the previous survey [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Furthermore, differences in plant inventory, especially the higher proportion of introduced species in our study compared to Van den Berg’s 1960–1980’s study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], may be influenced by environmental factors. Forest degradation and deforestation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] caused by logging [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], cattle ranching [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], and fires [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>] prompt a reduction in the availability of medicinal and native hardwood species, pushing a demand for introduced medicinal species to treat human diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. However, the most popular medicinal species in Belém listed by Shanley and Luz [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] partly overlap with our survey, but also partly with Van den Berg [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. This implies that it is yet unknown what the impacts of deforestation are on the availability of medicinal plants at the VOP.
</p>
