<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the present study, we report the characterization of a collection of 38 Sardinian almond local cultivars. Most of these genotypes were early blooming and showed wide ranges of variation for several quality-related traits. The kernel oil content ranged from 52.3% in the cultivar 
 <italic class="italic">Malissa Tunda</italic> up to 64.47% in the cultivar 
 <italic class="italic">Ibba</italic>. Such a range of variability is in line with data reported for other collections of commercial or local almond genotypes. For example, Kodad et al. [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] reported comparable ranges of variability in the kernels of 73 almond cultivars typical of 10 almond-producing countries and grown at the CITA Institute. Similar ranges of variability were detected for almond cultivars grown in Egypt [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], Greece [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], India [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], Iran [
 <xref rid="B31-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], and Italy [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Higher ranges of variability were reported in studies which considered breeding trials, such as Turkish selections (25–61%) [
 <xref rid="B34-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] or Afghan [
 <xref rid="B36-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>] and Spanish selections [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] (43–63% and 40–67%, respectively). Interestingly, lower ranges of variability were reported for a collection of California almond cultivar and breeding selections, resulting from peach gene introgressions, and in a comparative study between Californian and European cultivars cultivated in Spain [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>].
</p>
