<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The tocopherols in kernel protect polyunsaturated fatty acids against peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. They also have protective roles in human health due to hypocholesterolemic, anticancer, and neuroprotective properties [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. We found that the Sardinian cultivars showed a wide variation of 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm61" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">α</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>-tocopherol content in kernels, ranging from a minimum of 301.28 mg/kg of oil of the cultivar 
 <italic class="italic">Emilio 91</italic> to 589.41 mg/kg of oil of the cultivar 
 <italic class="italic">Farci</italic>. These ranges are in agreement with data reported for Spanish (335–
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm62" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mn class="mn">551.7</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> mg/kg) [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] and Italian cultivars [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] (350–471 mg/kg) but slightly lower than those reported for Moroccan and Californian cultivars (
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm63" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mn class="mn">300.9</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>–646 mg/kg) [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. However, it is important to underline that tocopherol accumulation in almond kernel is significantly affected by drought stress and temperature during kernel maturation [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. The highest tocopherol concentrations (646 mg/kg) were found when the almond development coincided with spring and summer, with a warmer mean temperature in studies conducted in Northwestern Argentina or Afghanistan [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-plants-07-00086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Therefore, it is possible that the early blooming Sardinian cultivars may have the potential to accumulate higher levels of tocopherol if grown in environments with higher mean temperatures during kernel development.
</p>
