<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0185">Haloculture, in addition to avoiding land degradation, makes it possible to carry out commercial activities in marginal lands (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Abdelly et al., 2008</xref>). These activities could be production of forage, wood, medicinal plants, edible and oily seeds, vegetables, and biomass/bioenergy or poultry/livestock rearing (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Ayyam et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Khan and Ansari, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Pirasteh-Anosheh et al., 2016</xref>). Furthermore, it has been demonstrated that the adoption of haloculture improves the characteristics of a soil, reducing the soil salinity and making sustainable use of unconventional water (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Abdelly et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Duarte and Caçador, 2021</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">Qureshi et al., 2018</xref>). A sample of a haloculture complex in the southwest of Iran is shown in 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> . The haloculture approach has three main purposes: water reuse through irrigation with wastewater, degraded/salinized land exploitation, and produce higher value-added products (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Ashraf et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Nikalje et al., 2018</xref>). On this basis, it is possible to state the most important aims of haloculture are (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Al-Attar, 2002</xref>):
 <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015">
  <list-item id="u0035">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0190">production of more food and creation of more sustainable livelihoods per unit of water applied</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0040">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="p0195">better management of human water and soil use to conserve the quantity and quality of freshwater and terrestrial ecosystems that provide services to humans and all living things</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
