<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The paper reviewed recent articles on the biopesticide activity of 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> compounds and extracts. The ability of 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic>-derived products to protect crops against fungi, bacteria, insects, nematodes, and weeds was analyzed. The vast majority of studies have been performed on plant extracts, especially volatile oils, and only a small number of articles have evaluated the properties of isolated compounds. The analysis of the literature data shows that the main substances with pesticide action in the genus 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> belong mainly to terpenoids (mono- and sesquiterpenes), but also to flavones, coumarins, and phenolic acids. Experiments show that the activity of the extract often exceeds that of the isolated compounds, and, in addition, the use of a mixture of substances prevents the appearance of the resistance of the pathogen to the pesticide used. Although of natural origin, 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic> biopesticides are not without toxicity against non-target organisms and, to date, only a few investigations have been conducted into the environmental impact of these products. In addition, very few studies have evaluated the effectiveness of 
 <italic>Artemisia</italic>-derived pesticides in the field, most being performed in vitro, and few in planta. The efficiency of these treatments in crops also depends on the mode of application, and the formulation of natural pesticides in modern and innovative structures such as nanosystems can improve their activity. The investigation of different possible alternatives to chemical pesticides could prove highly beneficial and, implicitly, the use of plants and nano-biopesticides can represent the future of research in this field. Plants can serve as good sources of compounds with such properties, while nano-sized formulations could provide fast, cost-effective synthesis methods and stability of formulation. At the same time, such formulations are bio-degradable, environmentally friendly, and provide an increased biological activity, as well as a slow release of active substances. Therefore, the application of nanosystems for the control of plant pathogens can be a rapidly emerging area in the management of plant diseases.
</p>
