<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Caseins are the major protein of bovine and ovine milk present in the form of macromolecular aggregates, and due to the difference in phosphate content, various casein fractions are present in milk (
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table-3</xref>) [
 <xref rid="ref120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">121</xref>]. For example, phosphate content of α, β, and κ caseins is 10, 5, and 1 moles per casein mole, respectively, while phosphates are responsible for providing the antioxidant activities on casein micelles. Antioxidation mechanisms of action are complex; however, higher effect was achieved by normalizing Fe2+/Fe3+; it seems that casein diminishes LPO due to autoxidation of iron [
 <xref rid="ref122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">122</xref>]. Milk proteins have shown antioxidant capacity for the scavenging of ROS. Studies have shown that casein inhibited the lipoxygenase-catalyzed lipid autoxidation. Free amino acids cannot quench the free radicals, and for the scavenging of free radicals, primary structure of casein molecules acts as scavenger [
 <xref rid="ref123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">123</xref>]. Phosphoserine residues associated with casein molecules and inorganic phosphate present in casein and serum can bind the non-heme iron. In a previous investigation, it was observed that 72% and 21% of the supplemented non-heme iron in skim milk were isolated from α- and β-caseins, respectively, phosphoryl-rich peptides of casein phosphatides can bind the divalent metal, and casein-derived peptides inhibited the lipoxygenase activity [
 <xref rid="ref124" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">124</xref>]. Casein-derived phosphopeptides revealed the primary and secondary metabolites responsible for the sequestering of iron and direct scavenging activity in lipid and aqueous food systems [
 <xref rid="ref125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>]. Browning is a serious problem in many foods, and casein-based coatings are commercially used to prevent oxidation-induced browning of fruits and vegetables. Efficacy of calcium caseinate and whey powder in delaying the enzymatic browning in slice potatoes and apples was investigated; the results showed that milk protein-based edible coating efficiently postponed the enzymatic browning. Whey protein powder revealed better antioxidant activity than calcium caseinate, and the differences in antioxidant activity of whey protein and caseinate were attributed due to the differences in amino acid profile [
 <xref rid="ref126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">126</xref>].
</p>
