<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Therapeutic agents with high lipid solubility can penetrate cells more rapidly than therapeutic agents with water solubility. So, lipid or water solubility should be assessed.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Most of the therapeutic agents are available as weak acids or weak bases. Thus the pH of therapeutic agents should be addressed appropriately.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Oxidation-reduction potential (ORP) [
   <xref rid="B133-pharmaceuticals-13-00283" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>], also known as redox, should be determined because it reflects a molecule’s ability to oxidize or reduce another molecule. Reducers have negative ORP and oxidizers have positive ORP. Typically, all organs in our body have negative OPR (−10 to −250 mV of ORP). Oxidizers can oxidize another molecule, which causes it to lose electrons. Oxidizers become free radicals after accepting radicals and cause many diseases. On the other hand, free radicals can be neutralized with reducers and antioxidants, causing body improvement and rejuvenation. For medicinal benefits, CH or their major active constituents should have negative ORP and play a role as a reducer or antioxidant. Therefore, the proposed application of redox reactions is useful for CH determination in pharmaceuticals (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pharmaceuticals-13-00283-f011">Figure 11</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Oxygen partial pressure (PO
   <sub>2</sub>) [
   <xref rid="B134-pharmaceuticals-13-00283" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]: PO
   <sub>2</sub> is the force exerted by oxygen. In the human body (highly aerobic organism), oxygen plays a role in energy production. Therefore, oxygen supply at the tissue must match metabolic demand. PO
   <sub>2</sub> is useful to maintain homeostasis (the balance between oxygen delivery and its consumption) within organ and tissue. Each organ and tissue has its PO
   <sub>2</sub> requirements in order to function correctly. PO
   <sub>2</sub> is useful in predicting oxygen and oxygen movement will move from a higher PO
   <sub>2</sub> area to a lower PO
   <sub>2</sub> area. Typically, PO
   <sub>2</sub> in tissue is low because oxygen is used in cellular respiration. When PO
   <sub>2</sub> in tissue increased by several factors such as stress, anesthesia, tumor and diabetes, oxygen availability is low or hypoxia. In consideration of CH’s pharmacology, the importance of hypoxia as below is concerned [
   <xref rid="B135-pharmaceuticals-13-00283" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>].
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
