<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Essential Oil Administration by Inhalation in an Inhaling Chamber</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each pharmacological test, seven groups containing five mice each were assembled. Each group was represented by mice that inhaled the following: nebulized air only (control group); the formulation vehicle without essential oil (vehicle group); and one of the formulations (A–E). The inhalation process was carried out in a chamber that was previously developed by our group (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1</a>) [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>]. The chamber contains a central structure connected to five animal holders (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>, 1) with lids (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>, 2), and nebulized air passes directly and continuously through these animal holders. The central chamber (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>, 3) has an outlet for air collection, known as a sampling port (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>, 9), which has a threaded plastic cap with a septum to avoid air loss during
  <span class="italic"> in vivo</span> tests. First, this chamber was assembled and coupled to the nebulizer cup by means of a silicone hose. Then, 5 mL of the test formulation, prepared as described above, was dispersed in a sufficient volume of purified water to a final volume of 15 mL and placed in the nebulizer cup. Animals were placed into the animal holders; the nebulizer was turned on and the formulation was nebulized into the inhalation chamber and each of the five animal holders simultaneously. The nebulized air was blown into the chamber from the head (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">Figure 1(a)</a>, 4) to the bottom by a central tube, generating a vortex that optimizes saturation and allows more uniform air distribution to the animals [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all of the pharmacological tests, the inhalation lasted twenty minutes. All 15 mL were consumed.</p>
</sec>
