<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2.5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. Chemical Analysis of the Air Nebulized inside the Chamber</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical analysis of the nebulized air inside of the inhalation chamber was performed to assess the chemical composition of the volatiles inhaled by the animals. For analysis, the formulations were prepared as described above. The air inside of the chamber was collected (100 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L) at 1 and 15 minutes after the nebulization started from the static headspace using a Hamilton Bonaduz AG syringe, Microliter™ Syringe, 2.500 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>L, and analyzed. Between each test, the chamber and nebulizer cup were washed with ethanol and water and dried.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nebulized air relative compositions were obtained using gas chromatography coupled with a flame ionization detector (GC-FID) using two Agilent 7890 gas chromatographs. Separation was accomplished with a HP-5 fused silica capillary column (30 m × 0.32 mm i.d., 0.25 
  <span class="italic">μ</span>m phase thickness). The operating conditions were as follows: split ratio 1 : 10; injector temperature 250°C; carrier gas: hydrogen, 1.5 mL/min, constant flow; column temperature, 60°C (no hold), 3°C per min to 240°C; and detector temperature: 280°C. Between each analysis, the system was purged to avoid residual component carry over.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linear retention indices were calculated by injection of a series of
  <span class="italic"> n</span>-alkanes (C
  <sub>7</sub>–C
  <sub>26</sub>) [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>] using the same column and conditions as described above for GC analyses. Peak identification was performed by comparison with chromatograms and retention times obtained previously by our group [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
