<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3.5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. Rota-Rod Test</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rota-rod test is a safe and efficient test to assess an animal's motor coordination and balance. It has been employed to directly measure the influence of essential oils and their components on the central nervous system [
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>, 
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>]. Another advantage of the rota-rod test is that it allows distinguishing analgesic or anti-inflammatory effects from possible sedative effects since nonspecific muscle relaxation effects may reduce motor coordination and mask the mice's response to nociception [
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although
  <span class="italic"> quilombolas</span> reported mild drowsiness and relaxation after burning and inhalation of the
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> oleoresin [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>], all of the tested animals remained conscious and no visible effects on their behavior were observed from
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> formulation inhalation. The amount of alcohol in the formulation did not appear to affect the behavior of the animals since administration of the vehicle alone (which contains alcohol) did not generate any behavioral changes. Although it is well-known that several monoterpenes can induce seizures [
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>], we did not observe this effect in the tested mice.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">None of the formulations with essential oils presented sedative or motor coordination depressant effects after nebulization and inhalation since the number of animal falls was quite reduced (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tab5" href="#tab5">Table 5</a>). However, it should be taken into account that the
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> formulations evaluated in the present study only contained the volatile fractions (essential oils) and that
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> was not submitted to combustion. Burning of an oleoresin, as is usually done in the traditional use, may induce changes in the chemical composition, as pyrolysis may occur. This effect was not evaluated here. However, during the traditional mode of use, burning occurs slowly and at least some of the volatile compounds pass to the vapor phase by evaporation due to the heating flux, before pyrolysis, similar to cigarette burning, for example. Therefore, both the original compounds and pyrolysis products might be present in the smoke inhaled during traditional use. Nevertheless, the absence of sedative or motor coordination depressant effect is a satisfactory result since it demonstrates that any of the observed anti-inflammatory or antinociceptive effects are associated with a depressor effect above the central nervous system. Other essential oils, such as
  <span class="italic"> Chrysopogon zizanioides</span> [
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>] and
  <span class="italic"> Croton sanderianus</span> [
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>], also have antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory activity without sedative properties. Myrcene and linalool, which are components of the
  <span class="italic"> breu</span> essential oil, have sedative and motor system depressant activities at high concentrations [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>, 
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. However, it appears that their concentrations in the nebulized and inhaled air fractions were not enough to trigger such effects.
 </p>
</sec>
