<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the last 10 years, microencapsulation has been intensively researched for the medical, bio-medical, agricultural, food, cosmetic, and textile industries [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Produced micro/nano particles has great contribution to science and economy [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Microencapsulation is a process where a functional barrier is established between the core and the wall material to avoid chemical and physical reactions and to preserve the biological, functional and physicochemical properties of the core material [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It is also a process in which microscopic particles of solids or droplets of liquids (or gasses) are confined in an inert shell, which in turn isolates and protects them from the external environment [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Numerous techniques for microencapsulation are available depending on the nature of the encapsulated substance and on the type of polymer used [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. A widely used method for the encapsulation of water insoluble substances within water insoluble polymers is the solvent removal method [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Generally, the resulting product of the microencapsulation process is called a “microcapsule”. Such capsules are micrometer (1 μm) size and have a spherical or irregular shape. Microcapsules can be divided into two parts: The core and the wall. The core (the intrinsic part) contains the active ingredient, while the wall (the extrinsic part) protects the core permanently or temporarily from the external atmosphere [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The microcapsules produced according to the invention can have different broad applications depending on the exact nature of the substance contained therein, as well as on the re-release properties of the substance, which is controlled by the wall-forming material that imparts the properties of the wall of the microcapsules. One example of use is in dermal formulations where substance is dermally active. As will be seen, the invention is not limited by the intended use of the microcapsules or the type of substance encapsulated therein [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-02390" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. 
</p>
