<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our results have three major implications for management and policy. First, given the high relative importance of socio-economic pressures for RRI, regions facing high human pressures like habitat degradation and intensive land use provide more opportunities for naturalized species to spread and cause negative impacts on the environment. Given the considerable recent increases in these pressures (
 <xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">Waters 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>), the emergence of new pressures, such as climate change (
 <xref rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr">Walther 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2009
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Dullinger 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>), and the fact that time lags of several decades are frequent in large-scale plant invasions responding to these pressures (
 <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Seebens 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2015
 </xref>), a further increase in the RRI is inevitable unless effective management policies are put in place (
 <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">Tittensor 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>). Second, alien species are already implicated in the majority of extinctions of species on islands (
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Sax and Gaines 2008</xref>). Our results support recent findings (
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Moser 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2018
 </xref>) that the future of extant island biodiversity may become even more severely compromised by biological invasions. Third, to meet international biodiversity goals such as the Aichi biodiversity targets 9 (on reducing the impacts of invasive species) and 12 (on preventing extinctions) (
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">McGeoch 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>), it will be pivotal to disrupt the connection between socio-economic development (e.g. per-capita GDP, trade; 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Pyšek 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Seebens 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2015
 </xref>) and rising levels of naturalized and invasive plants by implementing comprehensive and effective biosecurity policies targeted to pathway management, early detection and rapid response (
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Early 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>), especially focussing on islands. Finally, we believe that for informed invasive alien species policies and management it is important to take into account insights from the analyses of the relative and absolute richness of alien species.
</p>
