<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the Chinese Pharmacopoeia (2015), FCB is derived from the dried bulbs of six 
 <italic>Fritillaria</italic> species, including FC, FP, FU, FD, FT, and FW [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). It is worth noting that these 
 <italic>Fritillaria</italic> species are generally perennial herbs and have strict requirements for the growing environment. Among them, FC commonly grows in high altitude habitats from 3200–4200 m, has a disjunct distribution across the high mountain areas of Southern and Eastern Tibet, northwestern Yunnan, and western Sichuan. FP is mainly distributed at altitudes between 2800 and 4400 m in Southern Gansu, eastern and southern Qinghai, and western Sichuan. FU usually grows at the altitudes between 3200 and 4500 m in northwest of Sichuan and southeastern of Qinghai. FD is chiefly distributed at the altitudes between 3800 and 4700 m in northwestern Yunnan, western Sichuan, southern Qinghai, and Tibet. FT primarily grows at the altitudes between 2400 and 3150 m in Shaanxi (Qinling Mountains and its south), southeastern Gansu, northeastern Sichuan, and northwestern Hubei [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. FW is mainly distributed at altitudes between 2500 and 3600 m in northwestern Sichuan [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). Based on the difference in botanical origins and producing areas, FCB is divided into different types (including songbei, qingbei, and lubei) which have different efficacies and prices. It has long been acknowledged that songbei has the highest medicinal value and excellent quality [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In the recent years, the enhancement of health consciousness has induced an increase of the demand of FCB. Also, over 2000 tonnes of FCB was used in China each year [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The production of medicinal preparations containing FCB was an industry with an estimated value of US $400 million per year [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, the sources of wild FCB is inadequate for the increasing domestic and international market demand because the original plants of wild FCB grow extremely slow, and they usually require, at least, five years to grow into an apparent size [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. As a result, extensive commercial use and limited wild stocks lead to a high price of FCB. From 2013 to 2016, the price of FCB has reached 3000 Yuan (RMB) per kg [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Terribly, the huge market demand and high profit of FCB further exacerbated the overexploitation of wild sources. Nowadays, these used species in 
 <italic>Fritillaria</italic> genus have been classified as precious, rare, and threatened species by the Endangered Species Scientific Commission of China in 2012 [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
