<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Artemisia vulgaris</italic> is a herbaceous plant which grows up to a length of 2.5 m and has a width of 75 cm. It is characterized by an intense aroma that is readily released when the leaves are crushed [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and a spicy taste [
 <xref rid="B44-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The plant has a thick main root and many small, fibrous lateral roots. The roots take on a light-brown color and measure up to 1 cm. They remain in the upper layer of the soil, at a depth of 7–18 cm, forming a vast, underground network [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The stems of the plant are slightly wavy, straight, or branched, having a brown color at the lower end, and become woody with age, appearing green further up and purple at the top. Some of the stems are also hairy [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The leaves are 5–10 cm long. They are set densely, and alternately, primarily in the upper parts of the stem. The lower leaves with short petioles are divided into segments and take on a feathery shape, while the middle and upper ones are smaller and single or double pinnate. The dorsal side of the leaves has a dark green color, while the ventral side is whitish and tomentose [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Small, almost bare, yellowish or brown-red flowers are embedded in small baskets that form heavily branched panicles with numerous lanceolate bracts at the top of the shoots [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. One basket may contain around 15–30 flowers with numerous stamens [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Studies conducted in the eastern part of the USA showed that the inflorescences contain 52% of ligulate flowers and 48% of tubular flowers [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], of which 25–50% are female [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-25-04415" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
