<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38" class="p">Besides the changes in the contents of macroelements, their mutual relationships are also very important from the viewpoint of the nutritive value of the host plant. An optimum value of K/(Ca + Mg) ratio for plants to grow and develop should range within 1.6/1–2.1/1 (Matraszek et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2015</xref>). In our study, the value of the parameter was very different, depending on the analysed part of plant, reaching the values ranging from 0.36 in roots up to 4.05 in their aboveground parts. In the latter, the higher doses of diesel fuel and engine oil led to the lowering of the value of K/(Ca + Mg) ratio. At the same time, almost all of the analysed PDSs caused the increase in the value of Ca/Mg ratio in the aboveground parts. The above changes were principally conditioned upon the increase in calcium content, with only slight changes in the magnesium contents in these parts of plants. The value of N/S ratio can differ much between plant species as well between the particular parts of plant. Jamal et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">2010</xref>) indicate the ratio of 15:1 as an optimum value. In our earlier studies, we obtained similar values in broad bean plants growing on soil contaminated with the same doses of PDSs (Rusin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2017</xref>). However, in the roots and shoots of spring wheat, Matraszek et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2015</xref>) obtained the values of this parameter ranging from 0.90 to 4.40. In the studies that we carried out, this parameter also attained low values—from 1.72 in aboveground parts, 3.84 in roots, and up to 4.62 in grain, which was principally associated with the relatively low nitrogen content. Under the effects of diesel fuel and the higher dose of petrol, the value of this parameter was slightly elevated, which could suggest the improvement in the condition of host plant. It was not, however, reflected in the developmental parameters of aphids.
</p>
