<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29" class="p">The average fecundity of wingless females of 
 <italic class="italic">R. padi</italic> on wheat in uncontaminated conditions ranges to 40 larvae but depends on the cultivars of wheat and the generation of pests. Aphid life span is about 28 days (Aqueel and Leather 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2011</xref>). In our experiment, analysed fecundity of aphids was at a similar level, while life span was slightly lower. All the PDSs applied in the presented experiment (except for lower dose of petrol) adversely affected the developmental parameters of the bird cherry-oat aphid, resulting in the decreased fecundity, shortening of the average life span, as well as decreasing its intrinsic growth rate in general. In the available publications, there is little information on the effects of soil contamination with PDSs upon the developmental parameters of herbivores. Our earlier studies (Rusin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2017</xref>) demonstrated that the contamination of soil with PDSs had a negative impact on the developmental parameters of black bean aphid 
 <italic class="italic">Aphis fabae</italic> Scop., which corresponds to the results obtained in the presented experiment involving the bird cherry-oat aphid. In the aforementioned experiments, the same PDSs used in the same doses caused the significant shortening of life span in three generations of 
 <italic class="italic">A. fabae</italic> feeding upon the plants growing on contaminated soil, by approx. 30%. In the presented experiment, the higher doses of engine oil and diesel fuel brought about the shortening of the life span of the first and second generation of 
 <italic class="italic">R. padi</italic> aphids by approx. 50%, and in the third generation—by approx. 70%. In both experiments, the oils had the most adverse effect on the intrinsic growth rate and fecundity of aphids, and their higher doses had completely inhibited the process of giving birth to larvae by the third-generation females. Along with the increase of the concentrations of PDSs in soil, their adverse effects towards the studied pests also increased. The studies on the bionomics of 
 <italic class="italic">A. fabae</italic> on broad bean growing on the soil contaminated by the same PDSs but in lower dose (6 g kg
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> of soil) showed the fecundity in the first and second generations lowered by approx. 25%, whereas the life span did not change. All the PDSs, however, caused the significant lowering of the value of intrinsic growth rate in the second generation of 
 <italic class="italic">A. fabae</italic> (Gospodarek and Nadgórska-Socha 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2016</xref>). Because of the above, it seems that 
 <italic class="italic">R. padi</italic> is characterised by the higher sensitivity to the presence of PDSs in soil than 
 <italic class="italic">A. fabae.</italic>
</p>
