<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Iron-deficiency anemia is the most common nutritional disorder worldwide with impact on health and economy. In spite of a number of commercially available supplements, this deficiency is a global public health problem due to the poor tolerability of the standard care soluble iron salts (such as ferrous sulfate), which results in non-compliance and ineffective correction of iron-deficiency anemia. On the other hand, poorly water-soluble compounds cause less sensory changes, but are not well absorbed [
 <xref rid="B225-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">225</xref>]. Nanoformulations of iron were proposed to fortify food and feed to address these issues due to enhanced bioavailability, good product stability, limited side effects and the absence of changes of taste and color of the fortified foods [
 <xref rid="B226-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">226</xref>]. In addition, in vitro and in vivo experiments have shown that iron NPs can be considered safe [
 <xref rid="B227-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">227</xref>]. Ferritin, which is well absorbed [
 <xref rid="B228-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">228</xref>] is itself composed of an iron oxide nanocore surrounded by a protein shell. Recently, Powell et al. [
 <xref rid="B229-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">229</xref>] synthesized tartrate-modified, nano-disperse ferrihydrite having small primary particle size and enlarged or strained lattice structure (about 2.7 Å for the main Bragg peak versus 2.6 Å for synthetic ferrihydrite) that was able to efficiently provide GI delivery of soluble Fe(III) without the risk of free radical generation in murine models, where GI delivery did not depend on luminal Fe(III) reduction to Fe(II), and absorption was similar to that of FeSO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>. This nanoformulation could be considered as a potentially side effect-free form of Fe supplementation to human suffering from anemia.
</p>
