<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">EVOO and butter were obtained and characterized as indicated [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. ROO was obtained from a large commercial store (Hacendado, Mercadona, Jaén; 76.6% MUFA, 7.1% PUFA, 16.3% SFA). All experimental procedures were reviewed and approved by the Bioethics Committee of the University of Jaén in accordance with 86/609/EEC, initially on 29 December 2010 for project AGR 6340 and extended for project PP2015/08/09. The procedure was followed as described previously [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Mice were housed at constant temperature (23 °C), constant humidity (50%), and with a constant day length (12 h) and, twenty-four hours before sacrifice, they were individually placed in metabolic cages so that food intake, water intake, diuresis, body weight (BW), and systolic blood pressure (SBP) could be determined for each animal. After twelve weeks, feces from each mouse were also saved individually right after deposition and total DNA was extracted immediately as indicated below or kept at −80 °C until use. SBP was monitored as previously described [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. At the end of the twelve-week period and after collecting all data (food and water intake, diuresis, body weight and SBP) and feces, animals were anesthetized, and blood samples were obtained through the left cardiac ventricle. Finally they were sacrificed by perfusing them through the same ventricle with saline solution [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Insulin, fasting glucose, triglycerides, total cholesterol, and HDL were measured as previously reported [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Leptin and ghrelin concentrations in plasma were also determined as previously reported [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-microorganisms-07-00061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>].
</p>
