<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26" class="p">Most studies on a single species so far focused on the relationship of nutrients to one or a distinct set of traits – often times related to fitness (e.g., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>]). We think that our multiple traits approach – also including presumable neutral characters – better allows to disentangle patterns and mechanisms of nutrient influence on the mean and variance as well as the inherent plasticity of traits. In our experiment, all traits responded to diet and showed quadratic reaction norms (= optima) of different strength (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Physiological theory formally conceptualized this quadratic (or concave) response of fitness relevant performance traits as “threshold elemental ratio” [for element stoichiometry; 26] or as “Bertrand’s rule” for the concentration of essential micronutrients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>] and also macronutrients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>]. While the first concept is a stoichiometric approach based on the proportional relationship of elements, the latter uses absolute concentrations or the amount of nutrient intake to explain reaction norms of individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. Yet, both concepts are unified by a similar prediction: if a food is too unbalanced (containing too low levels of a certain nutrient or element) to reach the intake target, the benefits gained from increasing the amount or ratio of this nutrient or element also increases until they reach an equilibrium. More nutrients/elements beyond this threshold (the intake target) are associated with increasing costs for the regulatory mechanisms resulting in physiological disadvantage higher than the original benefit [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. Our results for C/N show that a simple threshold elemental ratio (presumably close to our model species intake target) applies to multiple traits and, even more important, also to their variability and thus to phenotypic plasticity. This is because the variability of each trait across resources was heteroscedastic, indicating that food quality not only changed the mean (e.g., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>]), but also the variation of a trait [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. These findings could help to propose a general eco-physiological mechanism causing dietary related intraspecific trait variation derived for our model system: the low performance and high plasticity of animals feeding on resources from the “edges” of an elemental or nutritional gradient ingest imbalanced food with stoichiometric shortcomings which causes stress related costs to deal with the deficits as well as surpluses of elements or nutrients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. While at low N-content (high C/N ratio) trait performance was limited by a short supply of protein, mites shifted to a C-limited trait performance at high level of N (low C/N). Consequently, high variability of all traits (i.e. high phenotypic plasticity) occurred if either protein (N) or energy (C) limited the formation and performance of traits. More general (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>): if there is a considerable trade-off between consumed surplus and deficit nutrients in one resource, the variation across multiple traits within a phenotype is high, while the trait mean is low. Reciprocally, trait variation is low, and the trait mean is high at nutritional optima where no essential nutrient is in short supply and a respective genotype can almost bear its full potential. This connection of trait means and variances across resources (expressed as a direct negative relationship, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>) is further evidence for the wide applicability of the balanced diet hypothesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. The concave responses of all traits and their variability to overall food quality (C/N ratio) in our experiments not only indicated that the threshold-elemental-ratio-rule applied for a wide range of traits and their variability, but further suggest costs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>] to maintain a high mean and low variance of a trait. This means that mites feeding on “edge” resources must deal with high costs during allocating resources compared to mite consuming the “optimum” food. Despite these costs, however, variation at the “edges” may still be beneficial, because it enables at least a small number of individuals to survive unfavored conditions. For instance, a recent synthesis by Forsman and Wennersten [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>] found that variation seems to be more important under stressful circumstances when animals are forced to exist under suboptimal conditions - like stoichiometrically imbalanced food not meeting the intake target [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>] - and may enable the survival of a population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>].
</p>
