<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0015">
 <p>Optimizing the processing technology is an effective way to improve the yield of active ingredients for the industrial production of medicinal crops. Baikal Skullcap (
  <italic>Scutellaria baicalensis</italic> Georgi) is a perennial herb in the 
  <italic>Lamiaceae</italic> family and its dried root is used as a famous traditional Chinese medicine (TCM). Modern pharmacological studies have shown that the active ingredients of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> have important pharmacological effects including anti-oxidation, anti-bacterial, anti-viral, anti-tumor, and anti-inflammation. Specifically, it is recently found that 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> has significant curative effects on the treatment of corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-19). In recent years, the market demand for the medicinal products of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> is increasing because of its great medicinal values. However, the annual yield of active ingredients originated from the root of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> is limited due to that little progress has been made on the traditional processing technology used in the extraction process. A pressing issue faced by both herbalists and scientists is how to improve the processing efficiency, thereby obtaining the maximum yield of products for 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>. In this study, a systematic analysis on the effects of growth years and post-harvest processing on the contents of medicinal active ingredients of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> was conducted. The contents of eight active ingredients (baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, wogonin, scutellarin, scutellarein, apigenin, and chrysin) in roots of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> of different growth years (ranging from 1 year to 15 years) were estimated using high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) and further analyzed to determine the optimal harvest period. In particular, the contents of six active ingredients in different parts (cortex and stele) of the root of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> were estimated and compared. Meanwhile, the dynamic changes of the contents of active ingredients in fresh-crush and fresh-cut roots of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> at room temperature were compared and analyzed to reveal the influence of post-harvest treatment on the contents of active ingredients. In addition, the effects of six different post-harvest treatments on the contents of active ingredients were systematically designed and compared to determine the best primary processing technology. The results showed that the best harvesting period for 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> should be determined as 2–3 years based on comprehensive evaluation of active ingredient content, annual yield increment, and land use efficiency. The contents of active ingredients including baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, and wogonin in cortex were significantly higher than those in stele (
  <italic>P</italic> ≤  0.05). The contents of baicalin, wogonoside, and scutellarin in fresh roots of 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic> significantly reduced as the storage time increased, but the reduction of fresh-cutting was significantly lower than that of fresh-crushing. For the effects of different processing treatments, the contents of four main active ingredients (baicalin, wogonoside, baicalein, and wogonin) under drying (
  <italic>D</italic>) and cutting-drying (
  <italic>C–D</italic>) treatments were significantly higher than those of the other four treatments (
  <italic>P</italic> ≤  0.05). Collectively, the above results will not only provide novel processing methods that will improve the yield of active ingredients for 
  <italic>S. baicalensis</italic>, but also shed light on the optimization of processing technology for the industrial production of medicinal crops.
 </p>
</abstract>
