<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This review carried out a bibliographic survey, taking into account 99 scientific articles on this topic published from 2006 to 2020. 
 <xref rid="molecules-26-00495-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the information about waste type, its plant source, industrial sector of provenience, contained secondary metabolites, reported bioactivity, and potential use for its valorization. The survey included 64 plants generating wastes, mainly derived from the food and beverage industries, followed by the herbal, agriculture, and forestry industries, and only one report was dedicated to a plant waste from the perfume industry. Moreover, according to this survey, wastes from 16 plant species originated from more than one industrial sector. This is easily understandable taking into account that the majority of the industrial products undergo different steps in the production chain. For example, different kinds of wastes are generated from 
 <italic>Castanea sativa</italic> cultivated for nuts production, and these wastes originate at different level of the production chain. In particular, spiny burs are the main agricultural residue from tree cultivation, while husks are discarded by the food industry when producing chestnut flour. The beverage industry generates also a considerable amount of wastes/by-products from plant origin, most prominent among them fruit pomace and or/peel. Nevertheless, a conspicuous number of wastes are also produced during the previous steps of the supply chain, namely, the fruit production itself leads to several agricultural residues. An example is provided by the wine production chain, where grape pomace is the main final waste, even though the cultivation of 
 <italic>Vitis vinifera</italic> L. itself generates residuals like green prunings. In this case, as highlighted also by our survey, due to their content in polyphenols, flavonoids, and tannins, grape pomace and skin are strongly valorized by-products (12 publications were focused on the requalification of these wastes). However, as pointed out by Acquadro et al. [
 <xref rid="B225-molecules-26-00495" ref-type="bibr">225</xref>], green pruning might be exploited for its phenolic content.
</p>
