<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flavonoids are the most potent antioxidant identified in significant amounts in fruit and vegetable. Catechin is one of the most important flavonoids, with a comparatively high antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00137" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Catechins have the beneficial effect of preventing skin damage. Catechins are important ingredients in the tea plant that have exhibited intensive anti-oxidant and other representative physiological activities in experimental animals. They are members of the group of polyphenol compounds found in many medicinal plants. The major sources of catechin are 
 <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic> (
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic>) and 
 <italic>C. assumica.</italic> Green tea contains 75–80% water and polyphenol (flavanols, flavandiols, flavonoid, and phenolic acid) compounds [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00137" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Green tea is a popular beverage consumed worldwide for its long history and numerous health benefits due to the presence of various amounts of catechins such as catechin, (–)-epigallocatechin-3-gallate, (–)-epicatechin-3-gallate, (–)-epigallocatechin, and (–)-epicatechin. Several investigational studies have indicated that the antioxidant properties of green tea come from the flavonoids. Catechins provide several health advantages by scavenging free radicals thus retarding extracellular matrix degradation induced by ROS, ultraviolet radiation and pollution. The health raising properties of catechins are commonly related to their redox antioxidant capacity rather than to the other molecular activities. Catechins are one of the most important flavonoids, with antioxidant and anti-inflammatory properties rendering them a potent therapeutic for diseases where the mentioned processes are critical negative elements [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-26-00137" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A number of scientists have isolated catechin from different plants and evaluated them to be beneficial in controlling oxidative stress, diabetes, high blood pressure, lipid absorption and glucose intolerance induced by a high fat diet [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-00137" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-26-00137" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-26-00137" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
