<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A balanced lipid profile or lipid panel is required for the proper metabolic function of the body. An imbalance in the lipid profile (dyslipidaemia) leads to several diseases, such as coronary artery disease, stroke, peripheral arterial disease, cancer, atherosclerosis, and myocardial infarction. Lifestyle, food habits, disease, and drugs are responsible for dyslipidaemia due to the enhanced mobilisation of lipids from adipose tissue to plasma. Diabetes, one of the diseases that affects antioxidant defence systems, causes oxidative stress and alters the lipid profile due to overproduction and/or insufficient removal of ROS [
 <xref rid="B52-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Diabetic Wistar rats and albino rabbits were treated with ethanolic extract of ASLs at various doses (200, 300, 350, and 400 mg/kg). The most significantly positive result was observed with a dose of 350 mg/kg, which reduced TC, LDL, and TGs by approximately 49.3%, 71.9%, and 28.7%, respectively, and increased the level of HDL (30.3%) [
 <xref rid="B64-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In another experiment, streptozotocin (50 mg/kg) induced diabetic albino Wistar rats treated with a water extract of ASLs. Treatment reduced MDA levels, activated antioxidant enzymes, and maintained the lipid profile (lower TGs, TC, and higher HDL) [
 <xref rid="B52-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Diabetic mice treated with methanolic extract of ASLs (250 mg/kg body weight) significantly reduced serum TC (34.7%), TGs (50%), and LDL (53%) and improved HDL (53%) levels compared to nontreated mice. The author suggests that the activation of lipoprotein lipase (LPL) and stimulation of β-cells are responsible for hypolipidaemic activity, as they secrete sufficient insulin to clear triglycerides from plasma [
 <xref rid="B75-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. The application of an alcoholic extract of ASLs in streptozotocin-induced albino rats significantly reduced TC and TGs but increased HDL. Moreover, with the improvement of the lipid profile, a significant weight reduction (19.46%) was reported in the treated rats compared to the control after 28 days of treatment [
 <xref rid="B76-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The presence of higher levels of flavonoids in the leaf may be responsible for the same result. Methanolic extract containing THDMF-Rha was found to be effective in reducing lipid concentrations (TC, TGs, VLDL, LDL, and HDL) in serum [
 <xref rid="B48-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In another study, the application of both aqueous and ethanolic ASL extracts (300 mg/kg b.w.) significantly decreased the levels of CL, TGs, and LDL cholesterol and significantly increased HDL cholesterol levels in alloxan (150 mg/kg)-induced diabetic rats [
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-11-00614" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The present study has shown that ASL extracts potently cause weight loss and maintain the lipid profile in serum.
</p>
