<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to AgNPs, other nanoparticles, such as Cu and CuO NPs [
 <xref rid="B83-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>], ZnO NPs [
 <xref rid="B85-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>], and TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> NPs [
 <xref rid="B87-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>], have been used to improve the antimicrobial activity of chitosan. In the case of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanoparticles, it is accepted that their antimicrobial activity is based on photocatalytic processes under UV-light irradiation that generate reactive oxygen species (ROS) [
 <xref rid="B89-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>]. However, recent studies have also demonstrated biocidal properties of TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanocomposites under visible light [
 <xref rid="B88-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>], which might improve their applicability since there is a low proportion of UV light in the total solar irradiance. Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="B88-materials-12-00641" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>] prepared chitosan-TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> composites with efficient antimicrobial activities under visible light. They incorporated TiO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> nanoparticles into chitosan and evaluated the antimicrobial behavior against food-borne pathogenic microbes, including 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. albicans</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">A. niger</italic>, under visible light irradiation (a 20 W daylight lamp). The films exerted high antimicrobial activity against the tested strains with 100% sterilization in 12 h. The good performance obtained under visible light irradiation was attributed to the decreased transmittance found in the visible light region, which enabled the films to have a photocatalytic antimicrobial effect.
</p>
