<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To promote the compatibility with PLA-lignin bioplastics and limit the negative properties of lignin, compatibilizers, such as polyethylene glycol, maleic anhydride, diglyme and phytic acid are generally introduced. Ternary biocomposites containing poly-
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-lactic acid, polyethylene glycol and softwood KL have been formed. However, in comparison with the poly-
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-lactic acid/lignin system, the biocomposites where poly-
 <sc class="sc">l</sc>-lactic acid was plasticized with 30 wt % polyethylene glycol and lignin indicated higher deformability. An excellent balance between stiffness and flexibility has been attained in the ternary biocomposites as the content of polyethylene glycol increased [
 <xref rid="B73-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. PLA, polyolefin grafting maleic anhydride and cellulolytic enzyme lignin were blended and used to produce the bioplastics by extrusion. The study found that the mechanical properties changed as the contents of components varied in the bioplastics. In contrast with original PLA, the Young’s modulus and tensile strength of the biocomposites decreased, but the impact strength and the elongation at break improved effectively. SEM observations revealed that the cellulolytic enzyme lignin acted as a bridging function between PLA and polyolefin grafting maleic anhydride, promoting their compatibility and resulting in the improvement of toughness and ductility of the blends [
 <xref rid="B114-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">114</xref>]. Different amounts of diglyme were introduced into PLA biocomposites in order to avoid fiber agglomeration during blending. The tensile strength followed a positive and lineal relationship with fiber contents in the diglyme-containing biocomposites. In addition, the tensile strength of PLA biocomposites reinforced by 30 wt % lignin presented the same amount as polypropylene composites reinforced by 20 wt % glass fibers, which might pave a way to substitute the synthetic composites [
 <xref rid="B115-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">115</xref>]. Lignin, phytic acid and PLA combinations were used to develop bio-based flame-retardant systems. The composites were prepared by melt blending. Incorporating these two additives has been shown to present an effective way to limit the negative effect of each of them and improve the properties of the produced composites. On the first hand, lignin reduced the composite hygroscopy significantly with the aid of phytic acid. On the second hand, the addition of phytic acid generated better dispersion of lignin into the matrix, which restricted PLA thermal degradation. Some positive effects of the combinations on the mechanical properties have also been confirmed. The elongation at break increased from 3.1% to 12.6% for one formulation [
 <xref rid="B116-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. To fabricate PLA bioplastics, PLA, silver nanoparticles and Organosolv lignin were incorporated into polymer blends with lignin serving as a reducing agent. Incorporation of silver nanoparticles and lignin did not change the chemical structure of PLA, as revealed by FT-IR results. The water vapor barrier and mechanical properties of the bioplastics increased after incorporation of silver nanoparticles and lignin. The bioplastics with silver nanoparticles presented potential antimicrobial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B117-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>]. In order to make compatible PLA/lignin blends, triallyl isocyanurate was blended. The formation of PLA-lignin crosslinked structures was confirmed by FT-IR and DSC studies. The compatibility of the resulting blends was further validated by observing the significant improvement in the thermal and mechanical properties, the surface morphology, and 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">g</sub> behaviors of PLA/lignin blends [
 <xref rid="B118-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">118</xref>].
</p>
