<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemicals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Formalin, hematoxylin, eosin, ethanol, paraffin, chloroform and diethyl ether were bought from Merck Co., (Germany). Kits for the measurement of triacylglycerol (TAG), total cholesterol (TC), high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (HDL-C), low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Steinheim, Germany). Standard choline-deficient diet (CDD) was supplied from Harlan Teklad (Milano, Italy).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant material and extraction</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The plant was purchased from market and was authenticated by botanist as 
   <span class="italic">P. anisum</span> L. (voucher number: PMP-667). Extraction of the fruits was performed using boiling water, and the collected extract was concentrated by rotary evaporator at 45°C temperature. Essential oil of the fruits was obtained by steam distillation method using Clevenger apparatus. Essential oil was analyzed using an Agilent 6890 gas chromatography (GC) system equipped with a BPX5 column (30 mm × 0.25 mm, film thickness 0.25 µm). The column temperature was programmed from 50°C, being held for 5 min, at a rate of 3°C/min to 240°C, at a rate of 15°C/min to 300°C, and being held for 3 min. The injector temperature was set at 290°C. Helium was used as a carrier gas with a flow rate of 0.8 mL/min. Mass spectroscopy (MS) was Agilent 5973 model mass detector with electron ionization system with ionization energy of 70 eV, and ionization source temperature of 220°C was used. For GC and GC-MS analysis, 1 µL of the essential oil dissolved in hexane was injected by the split mode (1:25). Electronic integration of the Flame Ionization Detector peak areas was used for determination of quantitative data. MSD Chemstation software (Agilent Technologies) was used for data analysis. Components were identified using their retention times to n-alkanes compared to those of Wiley 275 library and those described by Adams (2004).[
   <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">In vivo</span> investigation
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Male Wistar rats, aged 8–9 weeks and weighted 250–300 g, were used for this study. The animals were individually kept under standard vivarium condition (temperature of 25 ± 1°C and relative humidity of 45%–55%, 12 h light, and 12 h dark cycle) with free access to food and water for 1 week to become adapted to the animal laboratory condition. The experiment was approved by the animal ethics guidelines of Tehran University of Medical Sciences. NAFLD was induced with a CDD composed of lard (TD 98262) containing 6.5% kcal from protein, 46.7% kcal from carbohydrate, and 46.8% kcal from fat.[
   <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>] Rats were randomly divided into ten groups with six animals in each group.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment was performed in two phases. In the first phase (90 days), all experimental groups received CDD for the induction of NAFLD, except one group which received normal pellet diet (sham). At the end of this phase, blood samples, collected from the jugular vein, were analyzed for the confirmation of NAFLD induction.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second phase, lasted 30 days, sham group continued treatment with normal diet while CDD-treated animals received the following treatments: CDD along with vehicle (as negative control), simvastatin (10 mg/kg, as positive control), 25 mg/kg anise fruit extract (AE), 50 mg/kg AE, 100 mg/kg AE, 200 mg/kg AE, 0.125 ml/kg anise fruit essential oil (AO), 0.25 ml/kg AO, and 0.5 ml/kg AO. The suggested doses for AO were calculated based on a primary study for the determination of LD50. Animal weight gain was periodically measured. At the end of the second phase, all rats were sacrificed, blood samples were collected in heparinized test tubes, and the sera were obtained after centrifuge (3000 rpm) for 20 min.[
   <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>] Serum levels of TC, LDL-C, HDL-C, TAG, AST, and ALT were measured using standard laboratory kits.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Histological investigations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Livers of sacrificed animals were also collected and fixed in buffered formalin (10%). Segments of 5 µm thickness were embedded in paraffin and were stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H and E) for the investigation of histological changes under ×100 magnification (optical microscope, ZEISS GERMANY).[
   <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">21</a>]
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessment of oxidative damage biomarkers</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate biomarkers of oxidative stress, blood samples were obtained using tubes containing EDTA and were centrifuged at 3000 g for 15 min. Plasma was frozen under −80°C temperature to assess the following markers:</p>
  <sec id="sec3-1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Myeloperoxidase</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Defrosted plasma was mixed with 50 mM phosphate buffer containing 0.167 mg/ml o-dianisidine hydrochloride and 0.0005% H
    <sub>2</sub>O
    <sub>2</sub>. Absorbance of the mixture was measured at 460 nm for 3 min using an ultraviolet-visible spectrophotometer (GBC, Cintra 40). One unit of myeloperoxidase (MPO) activity was equal to the change in absorbance per min at room temperature in the final reaction.[
    <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">21</a>]
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3-2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lipid peroxidation</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluation of lipid peroxidation (LPO) was performed using thiobarbituric acid reactive substances. Trichloroacetic acid (20%) was mixed with defrosted plasma, and the residual was reacted with 0.05 M sulfuric acid (H
    <sub>2</sub>SO
    <sub>4</sub>). 2-thiobarbituric acid was then mixed with the solution, and the mixture was incubated for 30 min in boiling water bath. Extraction of the final solution was performed with n-butanol, and the absorbance was measured at 532 nm (ELISA reader, Biotek, Germany).[
    <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">22</a>]
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3-3" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total thiol molecule</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plasma total thiol molecule (TTM) was measured using the reaction of 5’5’-dithiobis-nitrobenzoic acid with the samples which resulted in a yellow complex. The absorbance was then read at 412 nm.[
    <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">23</a>]
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec3-4" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ferric-reducing ability of plasma</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fresh ferric-reducing ability of plasma (FRAP) reagent (25 mL of 0.3 M acetate buffer, 2.5 mL of TPTZ solution, and 2.5 mL of FeCl
    <sub>3</sub>.6H
    <sub>2</sub>O solution) was reacted with defrosted plasma, and the absorbance of the obtained blue complex was measured at 593 nm.[
    <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">22</a>]
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2-6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All treatment groups were compared using one-way analysis of variances followed by Tukey's 
   <span class="italic">post hoc</span> test in SPSS 15 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL). Statistical significance was defined as 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
