<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) is defined as a spectrum of chronic liver disorders caused by irregular accumulation of fat in liver tissue which results in steatosis, inflammation, and in severe cases, cirrhosis. NAFLD is categorized into two main types including simple steatosis (fatty liver) and nonalcoholic steatohepatitis. The former is usually considered as a benign condition, whereas the latter has severe complications such as inflammation, hepatocellular injury, fibrosis, cirrhosis, and hepatocellular carcinoma.[
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Today, NAFLD is one of the most popular chronic liver disorders, especially in developed countries, with a prevalence of 20%–30%, which is estimated to be increased due to the unhealthy pattern of diet rich in high-fat and high-carbohydrate foods.[
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">2</a>] Intake of lipogenic sugars including fructose and sucrose, trans-fatty acids and saturated fats as well as insulin resistance is demonstrated to play an important role in the pathogenesis of NAFLD.[
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>
  <a rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref3">3</a>
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The current treatment approaches for the management of NAFLD include lifestyle modification, antioxidant therapy, oral antidiabetics, lipid-lowering agents, surgical interventions, and in the end stage of hepatic injury, liver transplantation; however, not all of the mentioned choices provide acceptable result and are not always well tolerated by patients in long-term use.[
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">1</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Medicinal plants have been widely used for different indications by people all over the world. Traditional medicine in different countries has provided an attractive source of natural agents for the management of chronic disorders including metabolic syndrome, hyperlipidemia, type 2 diabetes mellitus, and gastrointestinal complications.[
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Pimpinella anisum</span> L., commonly known as anise, is a member of the family Umbelliferae (Apiaceae) and has a long history of medicinal use in traditional Iranian medicine (TIM). 
  <span class="italic">P. anisum</span> is carminative and diuretic and has been claimed to be useful for epilepsy and melancholy in TIM which is also confirmed in animal experiments.[
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a>
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fruit volatile oil, the main constituent obtained from the plant, contains trans-anethole as the principle component as well as cis-anethole, estragole, γ-himachalene, eugenol derivatives, carvone, β-caryophyllene, α-cuparene, β-bisabolene, p-anisaldehyde, and other terpenic compounds.[
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>] On the other hand, flavonoids such as quercetin 3-glucuronide, rutin, luteolin derivatives, isoorientin, apigenin derivatives and isovitexin as well as lignin-carbohydrate protein complexes and phenolic glycosides also exist anise fruit extract.[
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Different extracts and essential oil of anise showed antibacterial and antifungal activity against pathogens such as 
  <span class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Streptococcus pyogenes</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli</span>, and several species of the fungus, 
  <span class="italic">Candida</span>.[
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>] A double-blind, randomized clinical trial demonstrated beneficial effects of anise fruit in the treatment of dyspepsia. It decreased gastrointestinal complications and improved quality of life in patients with functional dyspepsia.[
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">16</a>] In a study by Jamshidzadeh 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., different extracts and essential oil of anise fruit showed hepatoprotective activity in human hepatoma cell line. The preparations also decreased cellular and oxidative damage caused by CCl
  <sub>4</sub> in liver tissue of Sprague-Dawley rats.[
  <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">17</a>] Anise fruit also showed antidiabetic and lipid-lowering activity in a clinical trial in type 2 diabetic patients which was, at list in part, explained by its antioxidant activity.[
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taking into account the above-mentioned information regarding the biological activities of anise fruits in ancient and modern medicine, the current study has been performed to assess possible effect of 
  <span class="italic">P. anisum</span> fruit extract as well as essential oil in animal model of NAFLD. For this purpose, biochemical parameters related to NAFLD along with histopathological investigation of liver tissue have been considered as primary outcomes. As oxidative stress has a major role in pathophysiology of NAFLD, the biomarkers associated with oxidative stress have been also determined as secondary outcomes.
 </p>
</sec>
