<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Frostbite is an injury caused by freezing of the skin and underlying tissues commonly caused by exposure to cold-weather conditions and contact with ice, freezing metal, or cold liquids. It represents a continuum of tissue injuries, ranging from superficial insult to deep tissue damage [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Although a comprehensive epidemiological study is yet to be surfaced, it is estimated that 366 out of 1000 mountaineers suffer frostbite per year [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It is assessed that men in the age bracket of 30-49 are most at risk of frostbite due to greater chances of exposure. Expectedly, frostbite has been reported to affect military personnel [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and mountaineers [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] followed by the general population [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Frostbite usually occurs at the exposed area where temperature is below the freezing point, i.e., -2°C (28°F). Its severity depends upon the exposure time [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Frostbite injury causes loss of productivity, pain, and economic burden and has potential of permanent disability [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The pathogenesis of frostbite is not very clear, but according to reported studies, it includes direct cold damage to tissues and injury from ice crystal formation which causes protein disruption [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], arterial vasoconstriction, thrombus formation, and ischemia [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The suitable treatment of frostbite is chosen depending upon its severity and duration [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The clinical treatments available for frostbite are anticoagulation therapy [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], vasodilators [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], thrombolytic therapy, sympathectomy [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], hyperbaric oxygen [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and surgical treatment.
</p>
