<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">16S rRNA gene clone library</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 16S rRNA gene is well-known as a marker gene for the reconstruction of prokaryotic (bacterial and archaeal) phylogenies and for the investigation of microbial diversity (Woese and Fox, 
  <a rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" href="#B108">1977</a>; Klindworth et al., 
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">2013</a>). The construction of clone libraries based on 16S rRNA genes has extensively been used to investigate bacterial communities until the advent of next generation sequencing (NGS). 16S rRNA gene-based clone library analysis provides a useful, though somewhat limited, tool for capturing the diversity and composition of bacterial communities (Kumar et al., 
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">2007</a>; Schäfer et al., 
  <a rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90">2010</a>). In the literature on the DWH oil spill, 16S rRNA gene-based clone library analysis was one of the most popular techniques for investigating microbial communities. Several studies using 16S rRNA gene clone libraries revealed the microbial community responses to the contamination caused by the deep-sea plumes of hydrocarbons. These communities exhibited significant differences in different habitats (plume and non-plume water, surface and deep-sea water, sediments, and beach sands; see Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>) and presented dramatic changes over the duration of the spill (Hazen et al., 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2010</a>; Valentine et al., 
  <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">2010</a>; Kessler et al., 
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">2011</a>; Redmond and Valentine, 
  <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>; Yang et al., 
  <a rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110">2016</a>). For instance, Hazen et al. (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2010</a>) identified members of the order 
  <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span> in the γ
  <span class="italic">-Proteobacteria</span> class as dominant in deep-sea plumes. 
  <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span> were not detected in most of the plume samples in June, while 
  <span class="italic">Cycloclasticus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> were dominant (more than 95% of the sequences). This indicates that the DWH 
  <span class="italic">Oceanospirillales</span> bloomed initially, followed by 
  <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Cycloclasticus</span> (Redmond and Valentine, 
  <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>; Yang et al., 
  <a rid="B110" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Construction and analysis of 16S rRNA gene clone libraries provided useful information on the structures and responses of bacterial communities during the first stage after the spill occurred. However, the 16S rRNA gene clone library technique became less prevalent after NGS was used to investigate microbial communities.</p>
</sec>
