<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What kind of methods should be used in future studies?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The culture-dependent and culture-independent methods discussed in this review can partially reveal the responses of indigenous bacterial communities to the DWH oil spill, whereas a full map of bacterial community composition and activity cannot be described by a single method (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a>). Biodegradation efficiency and metabolite mechanisms can be adequately researched by obtaining pure cultures of bacterial strains. However, the uncultivability of bacteria from marine environments (&gt;99% of microorganisms resist cultivation in the laboratory Kaeberlein et al., 
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">2002</a>) is a dramatic obstacle for revealing the real executors of 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> biodegradation. The 16S rRNA gene-based culture-independent methods, including DGGE, clone libraries, and NGS, can be comprehensively used to identify the bacterial composition in oil spill sites, but these methods provide limited information on metabolism of bacterial communities. Metagenomics and metatranscriptomics based on NGS can provide detailed information on a broad overview of the metabolic potentiality of bacterial communities in the polluted environment at the DNA and RNA levels, respectively. Nevertheless, these two meta-omics techniques provide limited information on the specificity of a metabolic process or the differences due to physiological or environmental conditions. The amplification bias is another obstacle in the application of these two meta-omics techniques (Lasken, 
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">2012</a>). Single-cell sequencing can provide genomic information on uncultivable bacteria, and it can help predict the potential pathways of biodegradation performed by the studied cell. However, single cell DNA/RNA sequences usually have high amplification bias. This is usually caused by some genomic regions being amplified more than others (Ning et al., 
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">2014</a>). Furthermore, analysis of single cell sequencing data always needs support from meta-omics data for additional analysis. In addition, the determination of metabolic products is also necessary for unraveling of environmental PAH biodegradation processes and also to describe microbial interactions effecting the biodegradation process (Vila et al., 
  <a rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103">2015</a>). Therefore, a combination of different approaches is necessary for a full understanding of the composition and activity of bacterial communities. Application of integrated approaches could: (1) deeply describe the components of a complex community, including existing organisms, functions, and their activities at a given time point (Zimmerman et al., 
  <a rid="B118" ref-type="bibr" href="#B118">2014</a>); (2) identify key players, sometimes diverse, rare taxa instead of majority groups (Kleindienst et al., 
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">2016</a>); (3) reveal more complicated microbial interactions by determining the connections of both cultured and currently uncultured microorganisms (Abraham, 
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">2014</a>); (4) predict functions of the whole community with the help of different bioinformatic tools which can improve prevention and remediation of potential perturbations (Ivshina et al., 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Summary of various methods that have been applied and techniques that could be applied, but have not yet been conducted, to investigate the responses of microbial communities to the DWH oil spill. 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> The histogram based on 16S rRNA gene-based high-throughput data can reveal microbial diversity and community succession. 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span> The histogram based on genomic and transcriptomic data analysis can identify and classify different functional genes involved in different pathways based on the COG database. 
    <span class="bold">(C)</span> The reconstructed molecular ecological network between microorganisms based on 16S rRNA gene, metagenomic, metatranscriptomic, and metaproteomic data can indicate the interactions and co-acclimation of microorganisms in a changing environment. 
    <span class="bold">(D)</span> Phylogenetic relationship and community succession can be detected by generating a phylogenetic tree based on 16S rRNA gene and genomic information. All these figures were generated based on our own unpublished data.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fmicb-09-00520-g0001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the first microbial study after the oil spill, Mason et al. (
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">2010</a>) applied the PhyloChip 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) microarray and clone library to study the bacterial community composition in the oil plume. The authors successfully isolated oil-degrading bacteria by a convenient cultivation method. Additionally, multivariate analysis of phospholipid fatty acid (PLFA) was applied in this study to analyze the composition of bacterial communities by identifying different assemblages of PLFA. Mason et al. (
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">2012</a>) investigated the role of the indigenous microbial community by combining different molecular methods including 16S rRNA gene sequencing, metagenomics, metatranscriptomics, and single-cell genomics. These methods based on NGS are currently prevalent in the field of microbial ecology, and they can provide abundant information for thorough analysis of the composition and behavior of the bacterial communities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis based on SIP is a typical strategy for bacterial community study that combines culture-dependent and culture-independent approaches. First, cultivation is necessary to obtain molecular markers (DNA, RNA, proteins, or PLFA) that are labeled with a stable isotopic element (e.g., 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C, 
  <span class="sup">15</span>N, and 
  <span class="sup">18</span>O). The labeled molecular markers can then be analyzed by 16S rRNA gene sequencing (clone library or NGS), metagenomic analysis, metatranscriptomic analysis, and mass spectrometer (MS) analysis. These methods can be used to generate data to reveal the bacterial community and activity. SIP analysis is a powerful tool for linking microbial species and metabolism (Dumont and Murrell, 
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">2005</a>). By using DNA-SIP in combination with 16S rRNA gene clone libraries and T-RFLP analysis, Redmond and Valentine (
  <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">2011</a>) demonstrated that bacteria in the genus 
  <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> were active in ethane and propane oxidation in oil polluted deep-sea water plumes. Mason et al. (
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">2014b</a>) used surface sediments polluted by the DWH oil spill and 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C-labeled hydrocarbons to perform mineralization experiments. They successfully found that the key hydrocarbon degradation pathway by sediment microbes was as follows: propylene glycol, dodecane, toluene, and phenanthrene. By monitoring the biodegradation efficiency of 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C-labeled different hydrocarbons (aliphatic and aromatic), Gutierrez et al. (
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2013</a>) applied 16S rRNA gene-based NGS and qPCR detection to reveal the activity of bacterial communities. The results indicated that the different bacterial phyla were responsible for the degradation of different hydrocarbons. For instance, bacteria in the genera 
  <span class="italic">Alcanivorax</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Marinobacter</span> were found to be enriched in the experimental setups with the addition of aliphatic hydrocarbons, whereas 
  <span class="italic">Alteromonas, Cycloclasticus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Colwellia</span> dominated the experimental setups supplemented with polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon.
 </p>
</sec>
