<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Thailand is part of the Indo-Burmese biodiversity hotspot [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and houses over 11,000 plant species [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], including over half of the world’s ginger genera [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Many gingers have had an intricate relationship with Thai culture since time immemorial. Several Thai food recipes use gingers as spices, such as the well-known Tom-Yam, which is cooked using rhizomes of galangal 
 <italic>Alpinia galanga</italic> (L.) Wild. Other species, such as finger roots (
 <italic>Boesenbergia rotunda</italic> (L.) Mansf.), ginger (
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> Roscoe) and turmeric (
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L.) are important components in different Thai curry pastes. Some gingers, especially species of 
 <italic>Globba</italic>, are used in rituals because of their pleasing scents, and many of them have propitious local names. Although gingers have many different uses, their medicinal properties may be the most important of all. A study of plant families in Thailand showed that species of the ginger family are among the most ethnobotanically important in the country [
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Many studies of plant uses have appeared since ethnobotany was introduced as a research field into the Thai academic system in 1990. Nevertheless, those studies mostly focused on uses other than the medicinal uses of gingers, and there were only a few use reports of medicinal gingers in each study. A few publications, however, deal exclusively with the use of gingers as medicine. For instance, there is a Master’s thesis on traditional knowledge of the cultivation and uses of gingers, but it is limited to 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Another study of the medicinal and auspicious plants in the ginger family focused on chemotaxonomy, but the study was limited to one subdistrict in Chiang Mai province [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. One study did cover the ethnomedicinal uses of gingers in many parts of Thailand, and documented 77 use reports from 58 species [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-00906" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Here, we mined all available ethnomedicinal references for uses of gingers in Thailand, and we identify those species that are potential candidates for further pharmacological study using the ICPC-2 standard. Specifically, we aim to answer the following questions: (1) Which species and genera of gingers have been used as medicine in Thailand? (2) Which medicinal categories were most commonly treated by gingers? (3) Which ginger species have the potential for specific treatments, and could be candidates for further pharmacological research?
</p>
