<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Differences between Native and Introduced 
 <italic>P. australis</italic> have been observed in associated oomycete
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup> and archaeal communities
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. These consistent differences between Native and Introduced lineages across multiple microbial domains support the view that lineage exerts a dominant control on soil rhizosphere communities, one that may promote invasion success through plant–soil feedbacks, spillover, and soil legacies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. In our common garden experiment, we found no evidence that lineage-driven bacterial communities directly affected plant fitness in the absence of competitors. Therefore, any effects of lineage-specific bacterial communities on invasion success likely comes from effects on competitors via plant–soil feedbacks. An extensive body of literature documents the important role of plant–soil feedbacks, particularly the escape from pathogens in the native range, in promoting invasion success
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. These conclusions, however, are typically inferred from measuring plant growth responses when grown in soils that have been preconditioned with either native or invasive plants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>, or from soils collected from native and invasive ranges
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, in most cases the actual microbial mechanism for observed negative soil feedbacks is implied rather than documented. Although we have yet to test how the bacterial community changes after cross transplanting native and invasive plants into preconditioned soils, our work nonetheless sheds light on possible bacterial underpinnings of plant–soil feedbacks.
</p>
