<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Nigella sativa</italic> has anti-proliferative, pro-apoptotic, anti-oxidant, cytotoxic, anti-mutagenic, and anti-metastatic effects, underlined by several mechanisms reviewed by (
 <xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr">Majdalawieh and Fayyad, 2016</xref>). Studies in cell lines, including in human lung (A-549 cells), epithelial cervical (HeLa and SiHa) and Michigan Cancer Foundation-7 (MCF-7) breast cancer cells, have shown that the administration of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> alcoholic seed extracts, seed oil and nanoemulsions markedly lowered the cell viability, inducing apoptotic cell death, and/or altered the cellular morphology, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values between 0.41-82 μL/mL in some cases (
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">Shafi et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Hasan et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Al-Sheddi et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B163" ref-type="bibr">Periasamy et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Butt et al., 2019</xref>). Among these studies, 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Hasan et al. (2013)</xref> revealed the presence of thymoquinone as the potential active 
 <italic>Nigella</italic> constituent. Concerning 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies, supplementation of different doses of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> ethanolic extract (seed) on daily basis (150, 250, 350 mg/kg), thymoquinone (20 mg/kg), and daily dose of silymarin (100 mg/kg) prevented from the hepatocellular carcinoma proliferation provoked by diethylnitrosamine through multiple pathways: reduction in 
 <italic>p</italic>-EGFR and 
 <italic>p</italic>-ERK1/2, deactivation of EGFR/ERK1/2 signaling, down regulation of target genes (c−fos, PCNA, and Bcl2), suppression of cell proliferation, reduction in alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) and hepatic enzymes, and enhancement in the levels of antioxidant enzymes (
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">Shahin et al., 2018</xref>). Other 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies suggested a protective effect of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> seeds oil and thymoquinone against breast carcinogens (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Linjawi et al., 2015</xref>) with dosages between 1 and 10 mg/kg. The water extract of 
 <italic>N. sativa</italic> has shown immunomodulatory and anti-tumor effects on Ehrlich ascites carcinoma in mouse model (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Aikemu et al., 2013</xref>), but its composition was not characterized.
</p>
