<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We need additional mechanistic work to assess whether similar processes occur in other regions throughout the range of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> in North America. We were unable to link a chronosequence to population trends at our long‐term sites because we established quadrats after the initial colonisation phase had occurred. In addition, the small‐scale patch dynamics described as advance and retreat (Nuzzo, 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0080" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>) and the potential for long‐lasting legacy effects (Bezemer 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>) may lead to erroneous conclusions. But because abundance and vigour declines are a function of local residence times and small‐scale patch dynamics (at the order of a few m), a perplexing local and regional invasion dynamic emerges. At invaded sites 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> abundance typically initially increases with some annual fluctuations and patchy spread through a site. The areas first occupied then go through a prolonged phase of decline until λ is reduced to &lt;1, whereas at the same time 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> populations at the invasion fronts are rapidly expanding. The continued availability of previously unoccupied areas allows 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> to spread regionally and across the continent. This is likely to continue, although only areas already invaded by introduced earthworms appear to allow 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> invasions, (Nuzzo 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), thus limiting available habitat the species may be able to colonise in North America. The potentially available habitat for expansion of 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> continually shrinks as once occupied patches become inhospitable, at least for establishment and maintenance of large populations. Although we also do not know how long this biotic resistance may last (but see Bezemer 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Furthermore, rapid evolutionary changes in the invader and the invaded lead to a reduction in 
 <italic>A. petiolata</italic> impact as a function of residence time (Lankau 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Lankau, 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2012a</xref>; Lankau 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="ele13649-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).
</p>
