<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vivo wound healing efficacy of NLC o/e</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f7-ijn-13-175" href="#f7-ijn-13-175">Figure 7</a> reports the profiles of wound area (cm
  <span class="sup">2</span>) as function of time. All the wounds treated with NLC o/e, as either nanoparticle suspension or nanoparticle suspension containing 5% w/w pull, and with saline solution (control) showed similar lesion area vs time profiles. After 4 days of treatment, NLC o/e suspension showed a significantly lower lesion area (not significantly greater than time 0) with respect to NLC o/e containing pull and saline solution, which were characterized by significantly greater dimensions than time 0 (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05). At the 7th and 10th day of treatment both the lesions treated with NLC o/e, as either nanoparticle suspension or as nanoparticle suspension containing pull, presented dimensions not significantly different from each other and significantly lower than the lesion treated with saline solution (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05). At the 15th day of treatment NLC o/e suspension presented the highest lesion reduction (one-way ANOVA, multiple range test 
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05) indicating the capability of these nanoparticles to speed up tissue repairing. Given the high variability of results, such a difference could not be observed at 18th day of treatment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8</a> reports microphotographs of skin sections of the wound area, stained with H&amp;E, taken at the 18th day of treatment with saline solution (A), NLC o/e suspension (B), and NLC o/e suspension containing pull (C). Microphotograph of intact skin (D) is reported for comparison.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In correspondence with the wound treated with saline solution (control) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8A</a>), a large part of epidermis was replaced by an eosinophil necrotic tissue (asterisk), and in the peripheral regions of the lesion, epidermis (bracket) was visible. In the underlying dermal connective tissue, an abundant granulation tissue (arrow) was present; moreover, collagen fibers were dispersed and not yet organized in large bundles, typical of the reticular layer of the dermis. There was no evidence of skin appendages (hair follicles and glands), while there were numerous vacuoles of different size (black star), delimited by a wall consisting of a monolayer of flattened cells (endothelium), probably corresponding to dilated vessels.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In correspondence with the wound treated with NLC o/e suspension (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8B</a>), epidermis (bracket) appeared continuous and well organized in multiple cell layers with a fair degree of keratinization. In the underlying connective tissue, skin appendages were vacant, but dermal papillae (white star) began to reform. A mild inflammatory infiltrate was visible (arrow), as well as a number of blood vessels (black star). Some scattered collagen fibers were present at the border with epidermis, while in the reticular layer of the dermis, the typical large bundles of collagen (white arrow) were already formed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In correspondence with the wound treated with NLC o/e suspension containing 5% w/w pull (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8C</a>), skin appeared completely re-epithelized, and epidermis (bracket) was well organized in multiple cell layers, with a fair degree of keratinization, similar to the structures observed in the section obtained from wound treated with NLC o/e (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8B</a>). Dermal papillae (white star) were in developing phase; furthermore, granulation tissue (arrows) and dilated vessels (black star) were present in a limited area, while collagen fibers were organized in large bundles, typical of the reticular layer of the dermis (white arrow).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Normal skin (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f8-ijn-13-175" href="#f8-ijn-13-175">Figure 8D</a>) was characterized by epidermis (bracket), well organized in multiple cell layers, with a fair degree of keratinization and showed numerous dermal papillae (white star). Dermal layer was characterized by large bundles of collagen fibers (white arrow) and showed a lot of dermal appendages (white triangle), such as sebaceous glands and hair bulbs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, NLC e/o suspension containing pull promoted an excellent healing, with a good re-epithelization and stratum corneum formation. Although in the underlying connective tissue, skin appendages were vacant, collagen fibers were organized in large bundles typical of the reticular layer of the dermis. Moreover, dermal papillae began to reform. There was only a mild inflammatory infiltrate, visible in a small portion in the center of the wound.</p>
</sec>
