<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ab005">
 <p>Various metabolites exist in the medicinal plants have lot of potential to cure various diseases and disorders. Plants such as, 
  <italic>Vetiveria zizanioides</italic>, 
  <italic>Trichosanthes cucumerina</italic>, and 
  <italic>Mollugo cerviana</italic> were collected from Western Ghats, Tamilnadu, India. Phytochemicals were extracted from these plants using various organic solvents and tested against Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. The phytochemicals such as, carbohydrate, alkaloids, steroids, saponins, flavonoids and tannin were detected from these medicinal plants. Among the extracts, methanol showed potent activity and this solvent was used to extract polyherbal medicinal plants. Methanol extract of 
  <italic>V. zizanioides</italic> was found to be highly active against 
  <italic>E. coli</italic> (27 ± 2 mm), 
  <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> (19 ± 3 mm) and 
  <italic>B. subtilis</italic> (18 ± 2 mm). Ethyl acetate extract showed high activity against 
  <italic>E. coli</italic> (24 ± 2 mm), 
  <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> (22 ± 3 mm) and 
  <italic>B. subtilis</italic> (20 ± 1 mm). These three plants were taken at 1:1:1 ratio and extracted with methanol at 1:10 ratio and synergistic activity was tested against bacterial pathogens. Synergistic activity of polyherbal extract was analyzed. The extracted crude herbal medicine was found to be effective against 
  <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, E. coli, Enterbacter</italic> sp.
  <italic>, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Bacillus subtilis</italic> and 
  <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>. The zone of inhibition was 33 ± 3 mm, 17 ± 2 mm, 22 ± 2 mm, 40 ± 2 mm, 33 ± 1 mm and 38 ± 2 mm zone of inhibition against 
  <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
  <italic>S. aureus</italic>, 
  <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, 
  <italic>P. mirabilis</italic>, 
  <italic>B. subtilis</italic> and 
  <italic>Enterobacter</italic> sp. Polyherbal extract was found to be highly effective against 
  <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> and 
  <italic>Enterobacter</italic> sp. MIC values of polyherbal extract ranged from 29 ± 2.5 µg/ml to 34 ± 2.5 µg/ml. MIC value was found to be less against 
  <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> and was high against 
  <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Antioxidant property varied between 49 ± 3% and 95.3 ± 2%. At 20 µg/ml antioxidant activity was reported as 49 ± 3% and it was increased at higher concentrations of polyherbal extract. Two cell lines (HeLa and MCF cell lines) were selected to analyze cytotoxic activity of polyherbal extract. The methanol extract of polyherbal fraction showed cytotoxicity against these two cell lines. The LC50 value was 467 ± 2.9 µg/ml against HeLa cell line and &gt;800 µg/ml against MCF-7 cell lines. The polyherbal extract showed antibacterial, antioxidant and anticancer activities.
 </p>
</abstract>
