<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In forest ecosystems, invasive alien plants not only impact upon biodiversity and forestry activities but can also directly impact human and livestock health by facilitating the transmission of pathogens and parasites. The understory structure provided by invasive alien shrubs such as Japanese barberry (
 <italic>Berberis thunbergii</italic>) and multiflora rose (
 <italic>Rosa multiflora</italic>) provide a buffered microclimate that limits desiccation-induced mortality of the blacklegged tick (
 <italic>Ixodes scapularis</italic>) increasing their density as well as the prevalence of infection with the spirochete 
 <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> the causative agent of Lyme disease that affects both human and livestock health [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. High rates of pathogen transmission will occur where the main reservoir hosts also preferentially associate with the increased cover provided by invasive alien shrubs. Not all cross- sectoral impacts need be through the spread of disease. Due to its painful sting, the red imported fire ant (
 <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>) causes significant impacts on human and livestock health, but it also directly destroys crops at the seedling stage and dramatically reduces the diversity of native invertebrates through predation [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. A high alien weed density in small grain cereal crops can reduce yields but also increase the prevalence of the alien fungal disease fusarium head blight that leads to shrunken, low quality grains as well as results in the contamination of grains with mycotoxins that are hazardous to animal and human health [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Common ragweed (
 <italic>Ambrosia artemisiifolia</italic>) reduces crop yield, outcompetes native vegetation and produces large quantities of allergenic pollen that is a significant cause of asthma and rhinitis in humans [
 <xref rid="ETLS-4-539C46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].
</p>
