<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We performed the analysis using information found in the Great Lakes Aquatic Nonindigenous Information System (GLANSIS in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-plants-10-00406">Supplementary Materials</xref>, 
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.glerl.noaa.gov/glansis/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.glerl.noaa.gov/glansis/</uri> NOAA Great Lakes Environmental Research Laboratory, Ann Arbor, MI, USA; accessed on 1 September 2020). GLANSIS provides information about aquatic nonindigenous species in the Laurentian Great Lakes region of North America and imposes the following criteria for inclusion of nonindigenous aquatic plants in the database:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Geographic criterion: Only species that are found in the Great Lakes basin below the ordinary high water mark—including connecting channels, wetlands, and waters ordinarily attached to the Lakes—were included in the GLANSIS nonindigenous species list. Species that have been collected from inland lakes within the Great Lakes basin but do not meet this geographic criterion were excluded.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Aquatic criterion: The United States Department of Agriculture (USDA) wetland indicator status was used as a guideline for determining whether wetland plants should be included in the list. Obligate, facultative wetland, and facultative plants were included as aquatic. Facultative upland and upland plants were excluded, even if found below the ordinary high water mark.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Nonindigenous criterion: The species included in the GLANSIS nonindigenous list were those that met at least three of the following criteria based on Ricciardi 2006 [
    <xref rid="B18-plants-10-00406" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]:
    <list list-type="simple">
     <list-item>
      <label>⚬</label>
      <p>The species appeared suddenly and had not been recorded in the basin previously.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>⚬</label>
      <p>It subsequently spreads within the basin.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>⚬</label>
      <p>Its distribution in the basin is restricted compared with native species.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>⚬</label>
      <p>Its global distribution is anomalously disjunct (containing widely scattered and isolated population).</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>⚬</label>
      <p>Its global distribution is associated with human vectors of dispersal.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <label>⚬</label>
      <p>The basin is isolated from regions possessing the most genetically and morphologically similar species.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Reproducing and overwintering criterion: A nonindigenous species was considered to be in at least the early stages of establishment if it had a reproducing population within the basin and was capable of overwintering, as inferred from multiple discoveries of adult and juvenile life stages over at least two consecutive years. Given that successful establishment may require multiple introductions, species were excluded if their records of discoveries were based on only one or a few non-reproducing individuals whose occurrence may reflect merely transient species or unsuccessful invasions.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
