<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on 
 <xref rid="molecules-24-02025-t005" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 5</xref>, bruise detection, yield estimation, and disease identification are the three most common applications with imaging technique in agriculture. In bruise detection, a hyperspectral camera with broad operating wavelength from 400 to 5000 nm [
 <xref rid="B78-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>], a non-destructive and non-contact infrared sensing thermogram [
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>], and an infrared thermal imaging camera with high temperature resolution of 0.1 K [
 <xref rid="B70-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>] are among the instruments employed as the imaging technique. Moreover, the thermal camera with temperature resolution better than 0.5 °C [
 <xref rid="B79-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>], colour stereo vision camera which creates a 3D environment for further processing [
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>], and grading machine with a high accuracy of 96.47% [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] are employed for yield estimation. However, the grading machine proposed in [
 <xref rid="B57-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] has a small capacity in estimation for 300 tomatoes per hour and does not efficiently work for tomato images with high specular reflection. In addition, infrared thermography is a popular device for disease identification due to its non-invasive monitoring and indirect visualization of downy mildew development [
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. This device takes the colour reflectance image for the detection of 
 <italic class="italic">V. inaequalis</italic> development on apple leaves [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>] and detects the pathogen in grapevines [
 <xref rid="B84-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. Additionally, an X-ray computed tomography scanner is utilized to obtain the cross-section of onion inoculated by pathogens [
 <xref rid="B90-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>], whilst an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) is presented to track the foliar disease in soybean [
 <xref rid="B98-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">98</xref>].
</p>
