<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The clinical use of doxorubicin in the management of solid and hematological cancers has been widely limited by its off-target severe cardiotoxicity which manifests biochemically by elevation of serum enzyme markers of cardiotoxicity. The diagnostic serum marker enzymes of cardiotoxicity are AST, ALT, CK-MB, LDH, and cTnI which leak from cardiac tissue damage to the bloodstream due to their tissue specificity and serum catalytic activity [
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. DOX administration may result in the damage to the myocardial cell membrane or make myocytes more permeable, resulting in the leakage of the diagnostic cardiac enzyme markers cardiac AST, ALT, CK-MB, LDH, and cTnI into the bloodstream and their high circulating levels. In the present study, DOX-mediated cardiotoxicity was fully established as evidenced by the profound elevations in the serum cTnI and LDH levels which is in complete agreement with previous studies [
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. With oral 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> pretreatments, the serum levels of cTnI and LDH were profoundly attenuated toward normal serum level indicating the ameliorative potential of 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> in DOX-mediated cardiotoxicity. These effects were probably mediated through high antioxidant and/or free radical scavenging activities of 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> on the myocardium, thus reducing the damaging effects of DOX to the cardiac muscle fibers, subsequently minimizing the leakage of such enzymes in the serum. Similarly, ROS-mediated mechanism is one of the proposed DOX-mediated cardiotoxicity mechanisms, leading to oxidative stress that causes cardiomyopathy [
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Oxidative stress has been reported to increase lipid peroxidation as indicated by an increase in MDA levels and altered enzymatic and nonenzymatic antioxidant systems [
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In this study, MDA level was profoundly increased by DOX treatment, while DOX treatment also suppressed the cardiac tissue activities of SOD, CAT, GPx, GST, and GSH levels in the treated rats in agreement with other studies. These altered biochemical alterations were supported by histological lesions characterized by myocyte congestion and coronary intravascular microthrombi formation. DOX has been previously reported to profoundly reduce vascular blood flow, disintegrate vascular endothelium, and promote GPIIb/IIIa-mediated platelet adhesion and aggregation, all resulting in microthrombi formation [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The fact that 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> prevented microthrombi formation in DOX-treated coronary vasculature as evidenced by histopathological results of this study highlighted the possible inherent antithrombotic potential of 
 <italic>IGESE</italic>; although, further studies are still needed in this respect in order to validate this hypothesis. However, 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> profoundly attenuated significant alterations in the cardiac tissue oxidative markers whose activities were significantly suppressed by DOX intoxication. 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> has the tendency to neutralize ROS like superoxide radicals, singlet oxygen, nitric oxide, and peroxynitrite, thereby reducing the damage to lipid membranes [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Similarly, oral 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> pretreatments profoundly improved and reversed the DOX-induced histological lesions especially at 200 mg/kg/day and 400 mg/kg/day of 
 <italic>IGESE</italic> pretreatments.
</p>
