<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The medicinal properties of mushrooms are due to the numerous and diverse secondary compounds and metabolites present in the mycelial and/or carpophore structures, which can act, in a synergistic or non-synergistic manner, on various biological functions of the human organism. All these properties were initially detected, demonstrated, and elucidated by in vitro tests, the first necessary step in highlighting the relevant potential of a given fungus for therapeutic purposes, followed by in vivo tests on animal models, usually murine, for the first investigations of the effects of the substances in living cells and systems. Nevertheless, although this research aims to develop drugs and natural products for human health care, few studies have been conducted within the framework of clinical trials, a domain that is still rather unstructured, with numerous shortcomings and gaps. As there is no standard for the procedure and evaluation of results, the value of such studies is undermined in several respects. First of all, the basic experimental design, which often examines a sample that is too small and therefore not sufficiently representative, and can lead to false positive results [
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Moreover, not all trials are randomized or have a placebo control [
 <xref rid="B104-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>], nor are double-blinded, and there is generally a lack of uniqueness of purpose, so only some parameters are taken into account and others are neglected, such as safety and side effects. Several, then, are not double-blinded, so the variable of uncontrollable human bias comes into play. Some studies also rely on the methodology of subjective assessments of certain parameters, such as quality of life, so the result examined may not have any real scientific value [
 <xref rid="B66-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
