<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">The antibiotic treatment of LD is a real challenge, sometimes with unpredicted outcomes, and is another paradox in the LD portfolio. Although seemingly illogical, multiple frontline antibiotics used to cure early LD are triggering, at much lower concentrations than used in therapy, the transformation of the spiral form of 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> into varieties of persisting forms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>]. As a result, the 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic> population becomes tolerant to the antibiotics that induced the morphological transformation. A good example of this paradox is doxycycline and amoxicillin, which at high concentrations are capable of eliminating 98% of replicating 
 <italic class="italic">Borrelia</italic>, but show poor activity against a stationary phase culture that is rich in persisting forms. Both drugs are ineffective against RBs, the formation of which they induce in culture [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" class="xref">102</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" class="xref">105</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" class="xref">106</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" class="xref">108</xref>]. It is interesting to note that morphologically changed forms represent spirochete populations with different gene expression profiles, characteristic for the specific antibiotic, doxycycline or amoxicillin, used for 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> culture treatment. It was shown that treatment of 
 <italic class="italic">B. burgdorferi</italic> B31 culture for six days with 50 μg/ml of doxycycline or 50 μg/ml of amoxicillin resulted in differential expression of 675 genes in the doxycycline-tolerant population (340 downregulated and 335 upregulated) and 516 genes in the amoxicillin-tolerant population (174 downregulated and 342 upregulated) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>]. Binding to the 30S ribosomal subunit, doxycycline obstructs the protein synthesis that causes the cell envelope defect. Amoxicillin inhibits the synthesis of bacterial cell walls that results in the death of bacteria. A comparison of the pathways of doxycycline- and amoxicillin-induced RBs shows that they share some common features that likely contribute to the enabling of spirochete survival under antibiotic pressure by downregulation of outer membrane lipoprotein gene expression. It is possible that one of the strategies spirochetes use to survive antibiotic treatment is the reduction of drug targets [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>].
</p>
