<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The mechanisms responsible for the beneficial anti-oncotic action of milled flaxseed have been studied in cell culture, in animal experiments and in human trials. The rich compositions of both SDG and ALA have been postulated to play a role in the beneficial action of flaxseed on cancer [
 <xref rid="B37-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Lignans like SDG reduce the breast cancer mortality by 33–70% and reduce all-cause mortality by 40–53% [
 <xref rid="B36-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Doses of 50 mg of SDG will reduce tumours [
 <xref rid="B38-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. However, it is unlikely that SDG is itself responsible for the anti-tumour activity. SDG is restricted to the gastro-intestinal space and does not enter the blood stream. It is metabolized within the gastrointestinal tract to the enterolignans: enterolactone and enterodiol [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. These compounds have estrogenic and antioxidative properties [
 <xref rid="B36-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Enterolactone and enterodiol can bind to estrogen receptors and alter cell growth [
 <xref rid="B37-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. It is likely that these metabolites of SDG are ultimately responsible for the anti-tumour capacity of SDG [
 <xref rid="B41-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. The anti-inflammatory action of ALA may also play a role [
 <xref rid="B41-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Flaxseed oil (enriched in ALA) also potentiates the anti-tumour action of drugs used in oncotic therapy. Flax oil administered with trastuzumab for epidermal growth factor receptor 2 positive breast cancer enhanced the anti-tumour effects of trastuzumab and significantly lowered the concentrations of trastuzumab needed to kill tumours in athymic mice [
 <xref rid="B48-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. Similar results have been observed using flaxseed with tamoxifen, another anti-tumour drug [
 <xref rid="B37-nutrients-11-01171" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>].
</p>
