<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par69">Antibiotics have always been bliss for the human civilization; however, their irrational and irresponsible use has significantly contributed to antimicrobial resistance. There is a promising future for the medicinal plants’ usage and their hidden potential could be decisive in changing the course of medical history [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Keeping this in mind, the present study aimed at scientifically exploring the bioactive potential of 
 <italic>Symplocos racemosa</italic>. It has been observed that most of the antimicrobial compounds identified in plants are mostly aromatic or saturated organic molecules, which can easily be solubilized in organic solvents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] and in the present study, ethyl acetate was able to extract out the antimicrobial components from 
 <italic>Symplocos racemosa</italic> to a maximum extent, followed by butanol and hexane. The better antimicrobial potential of the ethyl acetate extract may be attributed to the better solubility of such residues in ethyl acetate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The presence of major groups like flavonoids, cardiac glycosides, saponins, tannins, triterpenes and phytosterols are in consonance with other reports on this plant [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] and other medicinal plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Cardiac glycosides were the most abundant followed by flavonoids whereas triterpenes were present in least quantity. Quite encouragingly, flavonoids and cardiac glycosides were effective against 12 and 9 strains respectively and our results are well supported by the previous observations for various plant parts of 
 <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], where these were quite effective against the Gram positive, Gram negative and the yeast strains. The significance of the study can be gauged from the fact that these phytoconstituents were highly effective against resistant microbes e.g., MRSA and 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, which cause severe infections in hospitals/healthcare settings, which is in line with another study on 
 <italic>Eugenia jambolana</italic> seed extracts which was effective against MDR human pathogens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The antimicrobial potential of phytoconstituents is well-supported by the fact that these substances serve as plant defense mechanisms against predation by microorganisms and that the wide array of such microbial infections could have triggered the synthesis of such vast variety of phytoconstituents with a wide and variable spectrum [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The results obtained from ADA and MIC is supportive of each other. MIC determination is an effective method for evaluating the efficacy of an antimicrobial [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>], where all the extracts were quite effective against MRSA, 
 <italic>Candida albicans, Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> etc., which highlights the importance of the study. The MIC values obtained in this study (0.5–10 mg/mL) were comparable to or lower than the values obtained for other medicinal plants’ extracts, viz., 0.4–4 mg/mL [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]; 2.5–5 mg/mL [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], 5–20 mg/mL [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. VCC studies give an assessment of the microbistatic/cidal effect of the compound, which further endorsed the potential of this medicinal plant, as it showed a significant bactericidal effect against MRSA, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Staphylococcus aureus, Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> etc. The PAE gives an idea of the time period upto which the compound is effective post-exposure and hence could be a decisive factor for development of any natural compound into a useful drug. The PAE in this study ranged from 2 to 6 h. The in vitro biosafety evaluation of the ethyl acetate extract and phytoconstituents by Ames and MTT assay proved them to be non-mutagenic and non-cytotoxic, respectively.
</p>
