<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par72">So as to establish the active compounds which impart a significant and broad spectrum antimicrobial potential to the most active groups of phytoconstituents (flavonoids), the chromatographic and spectroscopic techniques such as TLC and GC-MS methods were employed. The chromatogram revealed the presence of several bands (S1-S4) with varying R
 <sub>f</sub> values. The number of separated bands, corresponding to the number of separated compounds, strictly depended on the solvent system used. It means that the separation of bands depends on the nature and interaction of the compounds being separated with the solvents of the used system. The bands obtained were quantitatively separated using preparative-TLC method, where one band i.e.
 <italic>,</italic> S3 was found to be the active with a broad spectrum. Hence, it was further subjected to GC-MS analysis so as to identify the antimicrobial components in this active band. Interestingly, the presence of compound Bicyclo[2.2.1]heptan-2-one,1,7,7-trimethyl-, (1S)- as one of the major compounds in band S3 corresponded well with a report on the GC-MS analysis of the methanolic extract of 
 <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> leaves, where this compound was identified as one of the major bioactive phytochemical compounds and possessed antimicrobial activity, which provided further credence to the study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Its presence as a major phytochemical compound was also in concordance with other studies on chloroformic extract of 
 <italic>Acacia karoo</italic> root and 
 <italic>Artemisia lavandulaefolia</italic> essential oil, where Bicyclo[2.2.1]heptan-2-one,1,7,7-trimethyl-, (1S)- was present as a major bioactive phytochemical constituent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Also, another major compound “Silane, Dimethyl(dimethyl(dimethyl(2-isopropylphenoxy)silyloxy)silyloxy)(2-isopropylphenoxy)-” was also identified as a metabolic component of a wild edible mushroom 
 <italic>Pleurotus cornucopiae</italic> (Paulet), by GC/MS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Similarly, this compound has also been reported as a phyto-compound present in the extract of 
 <italic>Terminalia arjuna</italic> upon its GC–MS analysis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Similarly, compound “7,11b-Dihydro-6H-indeno[2,1-c] chromene 3,4,6a,9,10-pentol pentakis (trimethylsilyl)ether” has also been reported as a major bioactive components in the GC-MS analysis of the ethanol extract from leaves of 
 <italic>Combretum albidum</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>].
</p>
