<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antioxidant testing assays</div>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DPPH radical scavenging activity</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radical scavenging activity of the different fractions was determined using DPPH radical as a reagent according to the method of Kirby and Schmidt with some modifications [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Briefly, 1 ml of a 4% (
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">v</span>) solution of DPPH radical in ethanol (PubChem CID: 702) was mixed with 500 μl of sample solutions (different concentrations). The mixture was incubated for 20 min in the dark at room temperature. Scavenging capacity was read spectrophotometrically by monitoring the decrease of the absorbance at 517 nm. Lower absorbance of the reaction mixture indicates higher free radical scavenging activity. Ascorbic acid was used as standard. DPPH radical scavenging activity (%) was calculated according to the formula: DPPH radical scavenging activity (%) = [(OD
   <sub>blank</sub> − OD
   <sub>sample</sub>)/OD
   <sub>blank</sub>] × 100.
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">OD
   <sub>blank</sub> is the absorbance of the control reaction containing all reagents except the tested compound. OD
   <sub>sample</sub> is the absorbance of the test compound. Extract concentration providing 50% inhibition (IC
   <sub>50</sub>) was calculated from the graph plotting inhibition percentage against extract concentration. Tests were carried out in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">β-Carotene bleaching assay</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The antioxidant activity was determined according to the β-carotene bleaching method described by Pratt [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. A stock solution of β-carotene/linoleic acid mixture was prepared as follows: 0.5 mg of β-carotene (PubChem CID: 5,280,489) was dissolved in 1 ml of chloroform (PubChem CID: 6212) with 25 μl of linoleic acid (PubChem CID: 5,280,450) and 200 mg of Tween-20 (PubChem CID: 443,314). Chloroform was completely evaporated, using a vacuum evaporator. Then, 100 ml of distilled water, saturated with oxygen (30 min), were added and the obtained solution was vigorously shaken. Four ml of this reaction mixture were dispensed into test tubes and 200 μl of each sample, prepared at different concentrations, were added. The emulsion system was incubated for 2 h at 50 °C. The same procedure was repeated with Butylated hydoxytoluene (BHT) as positive control and a blank as a negative control. After this incubation period, the absorbance of each mixture was measured at 490 nm. Antioxidant activity in β-carotene bleaching model in percentage (A %) was calculated with the following equation: A %  = 1 − (A
   <sub>0</sub> – A
   <sub>t</sub>/A
   <span class="sup">’</span>
   <sub>0</sub>−A
   <span class="sup">’</span>
   <sub>t</sub>) × 100, where A
   <sub>0</sub> and A’
   <sub>0</sub> are absorbances of the sample and the blank, respectively, measured at zero time, and A 
   <sub>t</sub> and A’
   <sub>t</sub> are absorbances of the sample and the blank, respectively, measured after 2 h. All tests were carried out in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
