<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study has a number of limitations:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>-</label>
   <p>Murine macrophages were used and stimulated by human LDLs. This experimental design is commonly used in the literature. In addition, this cellular model was chosen as we plan to carry out in vivo studies to assess the bioactivity of decoctions in a mouse model of atherosclerosis. Furthermore, isolation of LDLs in mice is difficult to achieve due to limited blood volume [
    <xref rid="B55-nutrients-13-00280" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>-</label>
   <p>The precise compounds and mechanisms responsible for the inhibition of the uptake of ox-LDL by 
    <italic>P mauritianum</italic> and 
    <italic>S cumini</italic> decoctions would deserve further investigation but cannot be explained by the presence of a single compound. Each decoction constitutes a complex set of molecules that can exert their effects synergistically. In addition, mechanistic aspects could to be investigated (for example, the study of the impact of decoctions on the expression of scavengers’ receptors).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>-</label>
   <p>In a physiological context, polyphenols can be transformed into secondary metabolites by intestinal of hepatic enzymes (including both host and microbiota enzymes).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>-</label>
   <p>In order to be able to evaluate the curative or preventive potential of the different decoctions tested, our in vitro study would benefit from being extended by studies on an in vivo model.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>-</label>
   <p>In summary, we demonstrated the effects of eight medicinal plant decoctions on ox-LDL cytotoxicity; we then showed that certain medicinal plant decoctions were able to significantly limit ox-LDL uptake and subsequent foam cell formation. Finally, we report the potential of decoctions to inhibit NF-κB activation, suggesting that herbal teas may prevent the activation of inflammatory signaling pathways.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
