<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">The emergence of multidrug-resistant bacteria is a worldwide concern and in order to find an alternative to this problem, the occurrence of antimicrobial compounds in 
   <italic class="italic">Plectranthus amboinicus</italic> essential oil was investigated. Thus, this study aims to determine susceptibility of 
   <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from food to antibiotics, 
   <italic class="italic">P. amboinicus</italic> essential oil (PAEO) and carvacrol.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">Leaves and stem of 
   <italic class="italic">P. amboinicus</italic> were used for extraction of essential oil (PAEO) by hydrodistillation technique and EO chemical analysis was performed by gas chromatography coupled to a mass spectrometer. 
   <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains (
   <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 35) isolated from food and 
   <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> ATCC 6538 were used to evaluate the antimicrobial and antibiofilm activity of PAEO and carvacrol. All strains (
   <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 35) were submitted to antimicrobial susceptibility profile by disk diffusion method. Determination of MIC and MBC was performed by microdilution technique and antibiofilm activity was determined by microtiter-plate technique with crystal violet assay and counting viable cells in Colony Forming Units (CFU).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">Carvacrol (88.17%) was the major component in the PAEO. Antibiotic resistance was detected in 28 
   <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> strains (80%) and 12 strains (34.3%) were oxacillin and vancomycin-resistant (OVRSA). From the 28 resistant strains, 7 (25%) showed resistance plasmid of 12,000 bp. All strains (
   <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 35) were sensitive to PAEO and carvacrol, with inhibition zones ranging from 16 to 38 mm and 23 to 42 mm, respectively. The lowest MIC (0.25 mg mL
   <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) and MBC (0.5 mg mL
   <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) values were observed when carvacrol was used against OVRSA. When a 0.5 mg mL
   <sup class="sup">−1</sup> concentration of PAEO and carvacrol was used, no viable cells were found on 
   <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> biofilm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">The antibacterial effect of carvacrol and PAEO proves to be a possible alternative against planktonic forms and staphylococcal biofilm.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
