<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Oxidative stress can produce reactive oxygen such as superoxide (O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>), hydrogen peroxide (H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>), and hydroxyl radical (HO). These reactive oxygen species can disrupt the balance of normal metabolic activity in the human body and are associated with many chronic diseases such as aging, cancer, atherosclerosis, and inflammation [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-00242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. As a result, research of natural antioxidants has gradually become a hot spot. These antioxidants can remove excess free radicals from the body and relieve conditions caused by excessive free radicals [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-00242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-00242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. There has been extensive research on the antioxidant activities of plant EOs. Most current research on antioxidants is focused on citrus EOs. For example, the antioxidant properties of 34 kinds of citrus EOs have been tested. The results showed that most of the EOs have good inhibitory effects on 2,2-diphenyl-2-picryhydrazyl (DPPH), which are significantly better than the effects of water-soluble vitamin E [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Extract of sweet orange peel have significant inhibitory effects on DPPH, with 50% inhibitory concentrations (IC
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>) of 600 μL/mL [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-00242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Moreover, the EOs extracted with a cold pressing method also have high antioxidant activity, because cold pressing can better preserve the active ingredients in EOs [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-00242" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. However, the above studies are limited to the antioxidant activities of EO mixtures as a whole, while there have been few studies of the antioxidant activities of specific components in EOs.
</p>
