<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="fsn3570-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oil extraction</div>
 <sec id="fsn3570-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maceration method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This method was used for oil extraction from dried samples (
   <span class="italic">DTRWN</span> 60 min, 
   <span class="italic">DORWN</span> 60 min, and 
   <span class="italic">DWN</span>) as described by Womeni et al. (
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0029">2016</a>). The nuts were separately grinded to pass 1 mm sieve. A quantity of 80 g of each power was separately macerated in 400 ml of hexane at room temperature for 24 hr with constant shaking. After that, the mixture was filtered using the whatman paper N1, and the filtrate was concentrated on a rotatory evaporator at 40°C. The extracted oils were stored in the refrigerator at 4°C for further analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3570-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bligh and dyer method</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oils were extracted from samples containing water (
   <span class="italic">FBWN</span> 60 min
   <span class="italic">, TRFWN 30 min, FWN</span>,
   <span class="italic"> and DBWN</span> 60 min) using the method described by Bligh and Dyer (
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0009">1959</a>). About 80 g of nuts were introduced in a grinding machine (Moulinex) to which 100 ml of chloroform and 200 ml of methanol were subsequently added. The mixture was grinded for 3 min; follow by the addition of 100 ml of chloroform and 100 ml of water. The mixture was again grinded for 1 min, and filtered. The final extraction was ensured by the addition of chloroform, this in order to respect the following proportion: 2:2:1.8 for chloroform, methanol, and water, respectively. After separating the different phases in a funnel, the organic phase was collected and dried using sodium anhydrous. The organic solvent was then eliminated by evaporation on a rotatory evaporator at 45°C under reduced pressure. The extracted oils were stored in the refrigerator at 4°C for further analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3570-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effect of processing on the quality of walnut oil</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The determination of the peroxide value of walnut oil samples was made following the spectrophotometrical IDF standard method, 74A: 1991 (IDF, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0015">1991</a>). Its iodine and acid values were determined according to the procedure of AOCS Official Method CD 1‐25 and CD 3d‐63 respectively (AOCS, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0004">2003</a>). Finally, its thiobarbituric acid value was evaluated as described by Draper and Hadley (
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0012">1990</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3570-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effect of different processing methods on the proximate composition of walnut</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moisture, fat, ash, and protein content of all the samples were determined using standard analytical methods described by AOAC procedures (AOAC, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0002">1990</a>). Moisture content was determined by drying walnut seeds in oven at 103°C until a constant weight was achieved according to the AOAC procedures 925.40 (AOAC, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0002">1990</a>). Ash content was determined by incineration of walnut seeds at 550°C according to the AOAC procedures 942.05 (AOAC, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0002">1990</a>). Nitrogen (N) content was determined using micro‐Kjeldahl method, according to AOAC procedures 984.13 (AOAC, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0002">1990</a>), the protein content was calculated as N × 6.25. Lipid content was determined using Soxhlet apparatus with hexane, following AOAC 963.15 methodology (AOAC, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0002">1990</a>). The total percentage carbohydrate content was determined by the difference method as reported by Onyeike et al. (
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0022">2015</a>). This method involved adding the total values of crude protein, crude fat, moisture and ash constituents of the sample and subtracting it from 100. All samples were analyzed in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="fsn3570-sec-0011" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effect of processing on the mineral composition of walnut</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the determination of minerals, walnut seeds were ashed at 550°C and the ash boiled with 10 ml of 20% HCl in a beaker and then filtered into a 100 ml standard flask to determine the mineral content. Calcium (Ca), magnesium (Mg), sodium (Na), potassium (K), and iron (Fe) were determined by atomic absorption spectrometer (Varian 220FS Spectra AA, Les Ulis, France). Phosphorus (P) was determined colorimetrically using the vanado molybdate, according to AOAC procedure 965.17 (AOAC, 
   <a rid="fsn3570-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#fsn3570-bib-0003">1999</a>). Mineral contents of the samples were determined from calibration curves of standards minerals. All samples were analyzed in triplicate.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
