<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are a great number of unexpected environmental, social, or pathological stimuli that happen during life and that can trigger stress. Being exposed to external stressors is recognized to increase the risk of psychiatric disorders such as depression, high susceptibility to infections, cancer development, and immune dysfunctions especially due to the higher levels of glucocorticoids (
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>). There is growing evidence in recent years indicating that exposure to certain psychological experiences, including stress-induced diseases, is closely connected with variations in immune parameters. In some cases, it has been noticed that both depression and chronic stressors have had significant connections with reduced adaptive/acquired immunity and inflammation; however, only recent studies have pointed out that after being exposed to stress or during certain episodes of depression, an innate inflammatory/immune response is strongly activated (
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>). The study by Munhoz, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., for instance, reveals that chronic unpredictable stress potentiated lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-induced nuclear factor kappa B (NFκB) activation and mRNA expression of pro-inflammatory genes in the frontal cortex and hippocampus (
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>). Among the essential signaling components of the mammalian host defense system are Toll-like receptors (TLRs) (
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>). Recently, a number of research works have shown interest in TLRs and their potential roles in neuropathology (
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>). The finding that neurons, astrocytes and resident microglia express TLRs, just like immune cells (
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>), has challenged the way neuroscience explains the role of the brain’s immune system (
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>). In an experimental model of depression in rodents, the expression of mRNA levels for Tolllike receptor 4 (TLR-4) in the brain cortex overweighed those in a normal brain (
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>).
</p>
