<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to the discovery of a novel 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> species, the present case also represents the first case of 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> subhepatic abscess in a liver transplant recipient. Among all the 37 cases of 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> infections reported, 33 (89.2%) were caused by 
 <italic>Pleurostoma richardsiae</italic>, and the remaining four cases were due to 
 <italic>Pleurostoma hongkongense, Pleurostoma ochraceum, Pleurostoma ootheca</italic> and 
 <italic>Pleurostoma repens</italic>, respectively. For predisposing factors, more than 70% of 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> infections have major underlying diseases (
 <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The commonest medical conditions leading to systemic immunosuppression are diabetes mellitus (33.3%), malignancies (18.5%) and renal transplant (18.5%). Of all the 37 cases, 27 (73.0%) had infections (osteomyelitis, cutaneous/subcutaneous nodules, masses, lesions, cysts or abscesses, bursitis, cellulitis, eumycetoma and chromoblastomycosis) of the extremities, with 18 cases (66.7%) involving the lower limbs only, six (22.2%) infecting the upper limbs only and three (11.1%) affecting both upper and lower extremities. The portal of entry of the fungus is believed to be direct inoculation of the dematiaceous fungus through the skin as a result of unnoticed minor trauma. 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> infection has only been reported in one other liver transplant recipient (Case 35, 
 <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), who was a 57-year-old Thai man with disseminated phaeohyphomycosis and hepatic artery and portal vein thrombosis due to 
 <italic>Pleurostoma richardsiae</italic> [
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The fungus was recovered from the patient’s blood as well as the blood clot from the failed liver graft. Identification of the fungus was achieved through ITS sequencing. On the other hand, our present case had surgical site infection with subhepatic space infection. Although the route of infection cannot be ascertained, we speculate that the fungus has invaded through the wound of the surgical site and settled in the subhepatic space. 
</p>
