<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>DNA sequencing should be performed to accurately identify 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> species from fungal cultures with 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic>- or 
 <italic>Phialophora</italic>-like morphologies. Microscopically, 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> species are characterized by the possession of 
 <italic>Phialophora</italic>-like single, separate, hyaline to pigmented, monophialidic, short conidiophores with inconspicuous or flaring collarettes producing smooth, hyaline, dimorphic conidia, either straight to allantoid or short and ellipsoid, aggregated as slimy masses at the apices of conidiogenous cells during their asexual life cycles [
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. However, identification to the species level is best performed by DNA sequencing of one or more conserved markers, especially the ITS region [
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9–11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25–27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Notably, two early cases of subcutaneous nodules were originally reported as 
 <italic>Pleurostoma repens</italic>-associated based on morphological identification of the filamentous fungi isolated [
 <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. However, subsequent molecular studies revealed that the two fungal isolates were actually 
 <italic>Phaeoacremonium krajdenii</italic> instead [
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. As for MALDI–TOF MS, although it has been increasingly used for the rapid identification of filamentous fungi in clinical microbiology laboratories, use of this technology for 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> identification is still not possible since reference protein mass spectra for 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> species are still lacking in the databases by the two major commercial platforms (Bruker Daltonics and Vitek, bioMérieux). Moreover, our attempt of MALDI–TOF MS analysis using the Bruker Daltonics platform for our case isolate HKU44
 <sup>T</sup> as well as other reference 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> strains also failed in generating interpretable protein mass spectra for database matching, probably due to difficulties in extracting cellular proteins during formic acid digestion. An optimal protein extraction protocol for sample preparation and expansion of the reference mass spectral libraries will be essential before MALDI–TOF MS could be utilized for the rapid identification of 
 <italic>Pleurostoma</italic> species.
</p>
