<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Agro-based polymers, i.e., starch, sodium alginate, pectin, chitosan, cellulose, whey protein, gelatin, soy and gluten proteins have been extensively used for the production of environment-friendly food films or packaging. In addition, the combination of agro-based polymers and derived-plant bioactive compounds (phenolic compounds, carotenoids, vitamins, among others) allows the development of bioactive films with antioxidants, antimicrobial activity and innovative colors. Different methods have been used for the production of bioactive films, such as the use of inherently bioactive biopolymer materials, the direct incorporation of free or encapsulated bioactive compounds into the film-forming solution and the spraying of free or encapsulated bioactive compounds onto the film-forming solution already on the support plates, among others. The functional, barrier and resistance properties presented by the films are directly influenced by the interactions between the bioactive compounds and the film-forming solution. In general, films produced with agro-based polymers still have limited mechanical and barrier properties when compared to synthetic plastic films. The use of bioactive films to increase the shelf life, stability and safety of foods has proved to be promising. In addition, the strategic use of bioactive films as vehicles and targeted delivery of bioactive compounds to food has proved to be useful for the stability and safety of foods that have been packaged with them. The improved stability and controlled release rate provided by the films allow the bioactive compounds to be transferred from the film to the surface of the food, where they start to act, preventing the growth of microorganisms and the oxidation of compounds, such as lipids. However, information on the mechanisms involved in this process is still limited especially regarding the controlled release of the bioactive compound into the food. Although films have several positive characteristics such as biodegradability and bioactive properties, they are still produced on a laboratory scale, and issues related to processing difficulties, high cost, and difficulties in standardizing film properties need to be resolved so that their production can move onto an industrial scale.</p>
