<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Carduus</italic>, commonly known as plumeless thistles, is a genus in the Asteraceae family that exhibits both medicinal value and invasive tendencies. However, the genomic data of 
   <italic>Carduus</italic> (i.e., complete chloroplast genomes) have not been sequenced.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>We sequenced and assembled the chloroplast genome (cpDNA) sequences of three 
   <italic>Carduus</italic> species using the Illumina Miseq sequencing system and Geneious Prime. Phylogenetic relationships between 
   <italic>Carduus</italic> and related taxa were reconstructed using Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian Inference analyses. In addition, we used a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in the protein coding region of the 
   <italic>matK</italic> gene to develop molecular markers to distinguish 
   <italic>C. crispus</italic> from 
   <italic>C. acanthoides</italic> and 
   <italic>C. tenuiflorus</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The cpDNA sequences of 
   <italic>C. crispus, C. acanthoides</italic>, and 
   <italic>C. tenuiflorus</italic> ranged from 152,342 bp to 152,617 bp in length. Comparative genomic analysis revealed high conservation in terms of gene content (including 80 protein-coding, 30 tRNA, and four rRNA genes) and gene order within the three focal species and members of subfamily Carduoideae. Despite their high similarity, the three species differed with respect to the number and content of repeats in the chloroplast genome. Additionally, eight hotspot regions, including 
   <italic>psbI-trnS_GCU</italic>, 
   <italic>trnE_UUC-rpoB</italic>, 
   <italic>trnR_UCU-trnG_UCC</italic>, 
   <italic>psbC-trnS_UGA</italic>, 
   <italic>trnT_UGU-trnL_UAA</italic>, 
   <italic>psbT-psbN</italic>, 
   <italic>petD-rpoA</italic>, and 
   <italic>rpl16-rps3</italic>, were identified in the study species. Phylogenetic analyses inferred from 78 protein-coding and non-coding regions indicated that 
   <italic>Carduus</italic> is polyphyletic, suggesting the need for additional studies to reconstruct relationships between thistles and related taxa. Based on a SNP in 
   <italic>matK</italic>, we successfully developed a molecular marker and protocol for distinguishing 
   <italic>C. crispus</italic> from the other two focal species. Our study provides preliminary chloroplast genome data for further studies on plastid genome evolution, phylogeny, and development of species-level markers in 
   <italic>Carduus</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
