<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cyclic monoterpenes (I) not containing oxygen atoms are common components in the essential oils of most citrus fruit peels. Previous work has suggested that the mechanism for the formation of 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene occurs during a rearrangement reaction in which limonene rearranges to form terpinenes, which then dehydrogenates to form 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, while pinene and limonene can interconvert with each other through isomerization (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="medicines-04-00001-f003">Figure 3</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B22-medicines-04-00001" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Oils obtained using three different methods have no significant differences in their pinene (α- or β-) content. However, when only focusing on the three most abundant compounds (limonene, γ-terpinene, and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene), the oil obtained by vacuum distillation possessed a relatively low content of limonene (47.6%), a relatively high content of γ-terpinene (29.5%), and an absence of 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene, while the oil obtained by hydrodistillation revealed limonene (60.1%), γ-terpinene (6.1%), and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene (17.6%). Notably, the oil produced from ultrafiltration had the highest limonene (64.7%) and 
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene content (26.1%), and the lowest γ-terpinene content (0.1%). The differences in content between these three compounds are most likely related to the considerable interconversion which occurs during the isolation process (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="medicines-04-00001-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The significantly different isolation conditions, including pressure, temperature, and time, seems to have largely influenced the rates of interconversion. For example, ultrafiltration is a slow procedure with an outflow speed of only 20–30 mL/h, so it was necessary to complete this at relatively high pressures (0.15–0.18 MPa) for long periods of time (10–15 h), while vacuum distillation is almost complete within 0.5–1 h, at a pressure of 0.03–0.05 MPa and a temperature of 80–85 °C.
</p>
