<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48" class="p">The quantification of genes was performed with RT-PCR analysis. All the gene-specific primers are presented in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>, and the sequences were obtained from our previous transcriptome sequencing of Chinese perch [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>]. Followed by designing primers on Primer 5.0 software, all the primers lists were sent to Sangon Biotech Company (Shanghai, China) for synthesizing. The specificity of the primers was determined through sequencing, and the melting curve of PCR products. Plasmid containing target fragments were dilated 10-fold and qPCR was conducted using different dilutions as templates to construct standard curves for genes. The amplification efficiencies were analyzed according to the slope of the standard curve in a given run. Moreover, several housekeeping genes containing 
 <italic class="italic">β-actin</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">rpl13a</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">b2m</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">ywha2</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">hmbs</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">sdha</italic> were chosen based on the published article [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>]. After comprehensive comparison of the candidate housekeeping genes, the 
 <italic class="italic">rpl13a</italic> gene expression was more stable to apply as an internal reference. All amplifications for each sample were determined by MyiQ™ 2 Two-Color Real-time PCR Detection System (BIO-RAD, USA). The reaction volume was containing 10 μL 1 × AceQ® qPCR SYBR® Green Master Mix (Code no. Q121–02/03; Vazyme, China), 0.4 μL of each primer and 1 μL cDNA. And the PCR cycling parameters were 95 °C for 5 min followed by 40 cycles at 95 °C for 10 s, annealing temperature for 30 s and a melt curve step from 65 °C, gradually increasing from 0.5 °C/s to 95 °C, with acquisition data every 6 s. The technical error was excluded by performing, in triplicate of each sample. Gene expression levels were quantified relative to the expression of 
 <italic class="italic">rpl13a</italic> using the optimized comparative Ct (2
 <sup class="sup">-ΔΔCt</sup>) value method [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>]. All data are presented with mean ± S. E.M. (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 6).
</p>
