<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The process technology adopted using polymers are usually more energy-friendly in respect to the use of other materials (the working process temperature profile is above 300 °C, while the temperature profile used to process the plastic is typically below 300 °C). The packaging materials incorporate, sometimes, plasticizers, stabilizers, and fillers. Plasticizers are used to modulate the mechanical performance (ductility, strengthen, flexibility, and toughness of polymers; though induced a reduction of stiffness and hardness) [
 <xref rid="B43-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">123</xref>], while stabilizers are included into the polymers to moderate the reduction of mechanical characteristics induced by UV light and oxygenation, and fillers tend to improve or preserve the mechanical and barrier performances in respect to the neat/control [
 <xref rid="B24-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">124</xref>]. In addition, technological developments have permitted the reduction of the weight of packages (at around 28% in the last few years [
 <xref rid="B105-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]), which in turn induces relevant savings not only in terms of transportation costs, but also in terms of environmental issues. Regarding this issue, in the last decades, the growing environmental contamination brought by the high impact of plastic wastes based on petroleum extracts has attracted the attention of industrial and academic researchers to design and develop some innovative polymeric systems. In this context, bio-based polymers have attracted some interest in respect to conventional ones. Green polymers symbolize a strategic option to design and realize new eco-friendly and sustainable systems that are able to reduce/minimize the plastic wastes stored every day in landfills, and the emission of greenhouse gases (GHG), which strongly depend on fossil extraction, production, use, and end-life [
 <xref rid="B24-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-materials-12-00471" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">125</xref>]. There is an increasing interest worldwide to substitute traditional plastics with bio-based ones, mainly in packaging sector. The utilization of bio-based materials and resources is seen as one of the numerous strategies able to reduce the environmental impacts induced by the use of petroleum-based extracts. 
</p>
