<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The rats were divided into 4 groups (
 <italic>n</italic> = 7 animals/group): the control group (sham-operated) (I), the Aβ1-42 (1 mM, Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany), alone-treated group (II), and the Aβ1-42 receiving OmEO by inhalation groups (Aβ1-42+ 1%OmEO (III) and Aβ1-42+ 3%OmEO (IV)). InVivoStat and R-based statistical packages were used to confirm that 
 <italic>n</italic> = 7 animals per group is appropriate [
 <xref rid="B36-antioxidants-09-00919" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Moreover, considering a significance level of 0.05, the power to detect a 20% biologically relevant change from control is 93%. Sham and Aβ1-42 groups received 1% Tween 80 solution through inhalation. OmEO was diluted with 1% Tween 80 (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>). OmEO exposure (200 μL, either 1% or 3%) was via an electronic vaporizer (KBAYBO, China). Rats were treated by inhalation with OmEO (1% and 3%), which started at day 5 post-surgery (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antioxidants-09-00919-f001">Figure 1</xref>) and lasted till the end of the behavioral tests (21 days), for 15 min each day. As for the concentrations indicated in the pharmacological tests, 1% essential oil, commonly used in aromatherapy, and a concentration of 3% were used to increase the effects, as we previously stated [
 <xref rid="B34-antioxidants-09-00919" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. On day 27 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="antioxidants-09-00919-f001">Figure 1</xref>), all the rats were euthanized with overdoses of sodium pentobarbital (150 mg/kg, b.w., i.p., Sigma-Aldrich, Darmstadt, Germany) and brain regions were excised on ice. From three randomly selected rats per group, the excised hippocampi were collected in RNA Save solution (Biological Industries, Beit-Haemek, Israel) and stored at −80 °C for further RNA isolation and qRT-PCR analysis. From the other three randomly selected rats per group, the excised hippocampi were immediately stored at −20 °C for further biochemical parameter assessments. From the remaining one rat per group, the hippocampi and the surrounding cerebral cortices were excised and immediately stored at −80 °C for proteome analysis (for surgery details, see 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-antioxidants-09-00919">Supplemental File 1</xref>).
</p>
