<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants contain a wide variety of pharmacologically important bioactive compounds, such as flavonoids, quinines, tannins, and ascorbic acid reported for their antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and hypoglycemic properties. The plants of 
 <italic>Begenia</italic> genus have traditionally been used for the treatment of diarrhea, cough, ulcer, vomiting, and kidney stones [
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The extracts of 
 <italic>Bergenia</italic> rhizomes have also been reported for their anti-inflammatory, analgesic, antibacterial, and diuretic properties. Moreover, these extracts have also been topically applied to the wounds, eyesores, and boils [
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Bergenin, a 
 <italic>C</italic>-glucoside of 4-
 <italic>O</italic>-methylgallic acid, is naturally found in the rhizomes of 
 <italic>Caesalpinia digyna</italic>, 
 <italic>Mallotus japonicas</italic>, 
 <italic>Mallotus philippinensis</italic>, 
 <italic>Corylopsis spicata</italic>, 
 <italic>Sacoglottis gabonensis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Bergenial crassifolia</italic>. Other components obtained from 
 <italic>Bergenia</italic> species include bergenan, β-sitosterol, polyphenols, and galloylarbutin. Bergenin, an isocoumarin derivative with five hydoxyl groups, is reported several important pharmacological activities, such as anti-inflammatory, hypolipidimic, antimalarial, hepatoprotective, antiarrhythmic, anti-HIV, and neuroprotective activities [
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The hepatoprotective, and neuroprotective activities of bergenin were reported to be mediated through its free radical scavenging property in both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> models [
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Our previous study had shown anti-inflammatory properties of bergenin, where it inhibited the production of inflammatory mediators, such as NO, and TNF-α [
 <xref rid="pone.0241349.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
