<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Countries other than China focus very less on their traditional medicinal plants that could be a potential source of active antiviral molecules. For example, India has a long record of using plants in treating virus-induced respiratory diseases; however, further research towards pinpointing the molecules having roles in antiviral activity is limited. A few Indian collections of medicinal herbs were reported to demonstrate anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties and can be used for the treatment of COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bb0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. For instance, 
 <italic>Vitex trifolia</italic> and 
 <italic>Sphaeranthus indicus</italic>, the medicinal plants from Southern India, have been reported to target cytokines, thus reducing the inflammation during respiratory diseases, including SARS-CoV at a concentration of 400 ng/mL [
 <xref rid="bb0430" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Similarly, several species used in the daily diet contain metabolites such as curcumin and quercetin, which were found to interact with proteases of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bb0380" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Further, Unani medicine, having an antiviral effect against measles and similar virus disease, has been proposed to provide an inhibitory effect on SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The antiviral compounds reported so far in plant species are summarized in 
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> , and their target sites of action on SARS-CoV-2 are shown in 
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> . In addition to antiviral activity, plant extracts also possess antioxidant, antipyretic, anti-asthmatic, bronchodilator, expectorant, analgesic, and anti-inflammatory activities that have application in the treatment regime of respiratory diseases (
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> ). Several herbs have been reported to possess immune-boosting properties, and this includes 
 <italic>Ocimum tenuiflorum</italic>, 
 <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic>, 
 <italic>Trigonella foenum-graecum</italic>, 
 <italic>Allium sativum</italic>, and 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>. However, there is no comprehensive study performed to identify the active biomolecules that interact with the immune system of the human body to enhance the resistance to diseases. The prevalence of COVID-19 as a pandemic has mandated research and development for identifying vaccines, therapeutic and diagnostic molecules; however, such searching for those biomolecules in plants is not being performed at the right pace. In case of plant-based vaccines, research is appropriately being carried out to express novel virus-like particles (VLP) in plants that could serve as potential antigens for eliciting immune responses. The prime advantages of plant-based vaccines are their purity (free from human pathogens), low cost for production, transportation, and storage [
 <xref rid="bb0350" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. In case of diagnostic reagents, plants serve as a suitable host for expressing viral proteins to develop assay kits for effective detection and diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 (reviewed in [
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]). Given this, the review explicitly covers the identification and isolation of plant-based therapeutic molecules and the role of genomics and biotechnology in reaping the maximum benefit out of plants for effective treatment of potential diseases.
</p>
