<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mints were also used to control respiratory ailments, although literary sources are not abundant. Plutarch (46–119) in his 
 <italic>Moralia</italic> wrote of the habit of Heraclitus, the Greek philosopher of Ephesus, of drinking cold water with spigs of pennyroyal before giving a speech [
 <xref rid="B105-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Pliny made a similar reference and advised taking watermint juice ‘when a person is about to engage in a contest of eloquence, but only when taken just before’ [
 <xref rid="B17-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. For lower respiratory tract problems, Theodorus Priscianus (b. 300), a physician from the 5th century Byzantine empire, used pennyroyal in an herbal mixture for chestpain [
 <xref rid="B38-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Aëtios of Amida wrote of a cough medicine containing pennyroyal in a mixture of pepper, hyssop, terebinth, fresh butter, and honey [
 <xref rid="B38-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Gil Rodrigues de Valadares (Giles of Santarém, 1185–1265), a Portuguese Dominican friar and physician, wrote mint-based medicinal preparations, which can be found in 
 <italic>Códice Eborense CXXI/2-19</italic>. For aphonia, Giles of Santarém prescribed a mixture of mint juice, ground pepper, malva seeds, egg yolk powder, and honey to be applied to the tongue [
 <xref rid="B106-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Another interesting reference found centuries later is made to Jean-Paul Marat (1743–1793), the famous French physician, scientist, and politician from the French Revolution. Marat prescribed a mixture of mint and tolu balms and vegetable extracts, as well as a secret nostrum, to treat the Marquise de Laubespine from tuberculosis, a case that increased his popularity among French elites [
 <xref rid="B107-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Research has shown that mints’ compounds create the perception of nasal decongestion but also display bronchodilator and antitussive properties [
 <xref rid="B108-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Indeed, the menthol-based Vicks
 <sup>®</sup> chestrub is extremely popular in the United States for treating common colds [
 <xref rid="B112-biology-09-00484" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>].
</p>
