<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">Literature lacks sufficient data regarding addition of natural antibacterial agents to glass ionomer cement (GICs). Hence, the aim of the study was to increase the antimicrobial properties of GICs through its modification with mixture of plant extracts to be evaluated along with an 0.5% chlorohexidine-modified GIC (CHX-GIC) with regard to biological and compressive strength properties. Conventional GIC (freeze-dried version) and CHX were used. Alcoholic extract of 
  <italic>Salvadora persica, Olea europaea</italic>, and 
  <italic>Ficus carcia</italic> leaves were prepared using a Soxhlet extractor for 12 h. The plant extract mixture (PE) was added in three different proportions to the water used for preparation of the dental cement (Group 1:1 PE, 2:1 PE, and 1:2 PE). Specimens were then prepared and tested against the unmodified GIC (control) and the 0.5% CHX-GIC. Chemical analysis of the extract mixture was performed using Gas chromatography–mass spectrometry. Antimicrobial activity was evaluated using agar diffusion assay against 
  <italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic> and 
  <italic>Streptoccocus mutans</italic>. Compressive strength was evaluated according to ISO 9917-1:2007 using a Zwick testing machine at a crosshead speed of 0.5 mm/min. Antimicrobial activity against 
  <italic>Streptoccocus mutans</italic> was significantly increased for all the extract-modified materials compared to the unmodified cement, and the highest concentration was comparable to the CHX-GIC mixture. The activity against 
  <italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic> was also significantly increased, but only for the material with the highest extract concentration, and here the CHX-GIC group showed statistically the highest antimicrobial activity. Compressive strength results revealed that there was no statistically significant difference between the different mixtures and the control except for the highest tested concentration that showed the highest mean values. The plant extracts (PEs) enhanced the antimicrobial activity against 
  <italic>S. mutans</italic> and also against 
  <italic>M. luteus</italic> in the higher concentration while compressive strength was improved by addition of the PE at higher concentrations.
 </p>
 <p id="Par2">
  <graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10856_2020_6455_Figa_HTML" id="MO1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </p>
</abstract>
