<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec29" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussions</div>
 <sec id="Sec30" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical composition of the 
   <span class="italic">R. acaule</span> essential oil
  </div>
  <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the literature, the comparison of the chemical composition of our essential oil (RaEO) with that of 
   <span class="italic">Rhaponticum carthamoides</span> roots studied by Skała et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>], revealed important similarity. In fact, these authors reported sesquiterpene hydrocarbons as the main class of chemicals in this essential oil (54.7%). Furthermore, Havlik et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>] noted that sesquiterpene lactones exist in all parts of 
   <span class="italic">Rhaponticum carthamoides</span> while the sesquiterpene hydrocarbons were identified only in essential oil. On the other hand, Benyelles et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>] reported that the essential oil extracted from the roots of 
   <span class="italic">R. acaule</span> was characterized by a large amount of alcohol derivatives (69.2%). Finally it is worth to note that for the essential oil of the aerial part of the same species (
   <span class="italic">R. acaule</span>), Boussaada et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>] described a composition richer in diterpenoids (23.7%), aromatic compounds (23.6%) and oxygenated sesquiterpenes (21.3%). However, these authors collected the plant material in the completely different habitat of Tunisia. Indeed, the differences between the chemical compositions of the essential oil obtained from the same species may be attributable to environmental factors (geographical, climatic, and seasonal), development stage and genetic variability [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. Additionally, chemotypes and individual variability may appear within the same plant species, resulting in the differences in chemical compositions of the raw materials [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec31" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Antioxidant activity</div>
  <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the many publications on the chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of essential oils for the 
   <span class="italic">Rhaponticum</span> genus, little information is available about their antioxidant activity [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. Therefore, this is the first report about the antioxidant activity of the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">R. acaule</span>. Overall, according to the three tests used in this study (ABTS radical scavenging activity, Reducing power and Phosphomolybdenum assay), the obtained antioxidant activity of the RaEO might be attributed to the presence of high percentages of mainly germacrene D (49.2 ± 1.1%), methyl eugenol (8.3 ± 0.28%), (E)-β-ionone (6.2 ± 0.18%) and β-caryophyllene (5.7 ± 0.17%) (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Similarly to our results, some works reported that several essential oils having low phenolic compounds amounts also exhibits interesting antioxidant capacity [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. However, it’s difficult to correlate the antioxidant activity of a total essential oil to one or few active compounds. Both minor and major compounds should make a significant contribution to the activity of the oil.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec32" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">α-glucosidase inhibition</div>
  <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the available approaches, inhibition of α-glucosidase has appeared to be a potential therapeutic target for the treatment and prevention of type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. For a long time plant food rich in polyphenols have been reported to cause effects similar to insulin in the utilization of glucose and act as good inhibitors of key enzymes like α-glucosidase associated with type 2 diabetes and lipid peroxidation in tissues [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]. On the other hand, according to literature, few reports exist for the inhibition activity of α-glucosidase by essential oils. In this study, our results revealed that the RaEO exhibited good antidiabetic activity which is 42-fold higher than that of acarbose used as commercial inhibitor. This interesting antidiabetic activity may be due to the large amount of sesquiterpene hydrocarbons, especially germacrene D, as hypothesized by Sarikurkcu et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>] using the essential oils of three 
   <span class="italic">Phlomis</span> species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec33" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Xanthine oxidase inhibition</div>
  <p id="Par64" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is well known that allopurinol, an inhibitor of xanthine oxidase which is structurally related to xanthine, binds to the active site of this enzyme, causing its inhibition. This drug has been clinically used for more than 40 years. Unfortunately, the appearance of several side effects including fever, allergic reactions, skin rashes, hepatitis, and nephropathy limit the clinical use of allopurinol. For this reason, the search for novel natural xanthine oxidase inhibitors would be beneficial to treat gout and other diseases.</p>
  <p id="Par65" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our case, the significant xanthine oxidase inhibition exercised by the RaEO may be explained by the high amount of sesquiterpene hydrocarbons contained in this essential oil. Our results are in good agreement with those obtained by Kaurinovic et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] with the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Marrubium peregrinum</span> L., which is rich in β-caryophyllene, bicyclogermacrene and germacrene D.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec34" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pancreatic lipase inhibition</div>
  <p id="Par66" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the literature, Asteraceae species are well documented for their antimicrobial activities, but to the best of our knowledge there are no studies about their pancreatic lipase inhibition ability. Thus, this is the first study conducted on the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">R. acaule</span> to inhibit pancreatic lipase. In this work, Turkey pancreatic lipase (TPL) was used to measure the anti-lipase activity of RaEO.
  </p>
  <p id="Par67" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the method A (preincubation of lipase with inhibitor), the RaEO exhibited promising anti-lipase activity which is comparable with that of pure THL used as a standard inhibitor against pancreatic lipase. In the same way and according to the literature, the inhibition of pancreatic lipase by the essential oil of 
   <span class="italic">Salvia judaica</span> (Lamiaceae) flowers was determined colorimetrically and compared with Orlistat used as a positive control by Afifi et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. The IC
   <sub>50</sub> value (0.108 mg/mL) obtained in this study was very close to that obtained with RaEO (0.2 mg/mL). In this work, similarly to our essential oil, the aroma profile of the 
   <span class="italic">Salvia judaica</span> (Lamiaceae) flowers was found to be mainly composed by sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (71.8%).
  </p>
  <p id="Par68" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the type of inhibition exerted by the RaEO on the TPL, the method B (inhibition during lipolysis) was used. Our results revealed that the obtained lipase inhibition was irreversible. Similar results have been reported by Gargouri et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>] using pure THL as inhibitor for porcine pancreatic lipase. In this case, the lipase hydrolysis rate of olive oil decreased rapidly to reach 10%, with final THL concentration of 200 μM. Gargouri et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>] have described two types of inhibition: the reversible inactivation obtained with amphiphiles compounds, such as detergents and some proteins. This inhibition is due to the modification of the interface quality, which prevents the binding of lipase to the interface [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]; the irreversible inhibition was obtained in the presence of colipase and bile salt and cannot be suppressed by renewal or excess of interface. The irreversible inhibition was obtained with specific reagents, such as THL, C12:0-TNB and E600 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
