<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">After the conversion of organic waste by 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae, organic waste accumulation is reduced, and pollution and harm to the environment are decreased. In its ecology, 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> fly is similar to the housefly. However, the larvae of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> fly can produce pheromones that are repellent to houseflies, which results in no oviposition or breeding of houseflies in excrement. Similar effects of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> fly against other noxious insects, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</italic>, have been observed [
 <xref rid="B3-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. Following the inoculation of chicken manure with labelled 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella enterobacter</italic>, the use of 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae to convert the manure was found to reduce the abundances of these pathogens by more than 2000 times [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. The larvae not only inhibited 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> but also displayed the ability to escape the symbiotic matrix with 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic>, especially at a temperature of 27 °C. In addition, the larvae affected the growth of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> in cow dung and showed good antibacterial properties. Furthermore, it has been shown that during conversion, some organic pollutants, such as antibiotics and pesticides, are degraded [
 <xref rid="B159-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>], the accumulation of metals in the organic waste is decreased [
 <xref rid="B48-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">160</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">161</xref>,
 <xref rid="B162-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">162</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">163</xref>], and the abundances of pathogens and harmful microorganisms are reduced [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B164-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">165</xref>] by the larvae. In addition, the conversion of organic waste by 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae results in no accumulation of antibiotics, pesticides, dioxins, polychlorinated biphenyls or polyaromatic hydrocarbons in the insect body; only heavy metal accumulation has been observed [
 <xref rid="B159-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">161</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">166</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-animals-09-00349" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">167</xref>]. Thus, in addition having saprophytic characteristics, 
 <italic class="italic">H. illucens</italic> larvae is an important insect for environmental protection because it has the ability to digest or decompose harmful bacteria in the environment and reduce the harmful effects of waste on the environment.
</p>
