<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) is one of the re-emerging vector-borne viral diseases and considered as a neglected tropical disease, mainly because the affected regions are Africa and Southeast Asia. The recent outbreak of CHIKV in Central and South America also raised the possibility of massive epidemics linked to the worldwide proliferation of the mosquito vectors that transmit this disease. Moreover, there are no currently approved vaccines or antiviral treatments available yet for the prevention of CHIKV infection; it is therefore imperative to look for new bioactive molecules, and we found that several plants (
 <italic>Kalanchoe pinnata, Ampelocissus tomentosa</italic>, and 
 <italic>Paris polyphylla</italic>) show activity against CHIKV (
 <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Taking into account the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values for inhibition of CHIKV replication and the SI value, further research is warranted on the structural elucidation of the active constituents. To identify novel inhibitors of CHIKV replication, researchers have selected Euphorbiaceae species, and upon bioassay-guided purification, they have isolated daphnane- and tigliane-type esters with anti-CHIKV activities. Euphorbia species are characterized by their ability to produce diterpenoids belonging to the tigliane, ingenane, and jatrophane chemical classes, along with other types of diterpene esters. In our study, we also found promising results of 
 <italic>P. tithymaloides</italic> (Euphorbiaceae species) extracts against CHIKV; however, its antiviral action was not selective. The moderate cytotoxicity might be due to the presence of pedilstatin or eurphorbol, which have already been established as irritants and carcinogens. Likewise, a recently published manuscript by Shrestha et al. [
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] reported that 
 <italic>Paris polyphylla</italic> was the second most widely used plant in Eastern Nepal (use-value = 0.96, fidelity level = 77.42) to treat a wide range of ailments (
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In earlier published work, we also found the promising activity of 
 <italic>P. polyphylla</italic> on Leishmania; however, its action was nonselective due to its toxic effect on the MRC-5 cell line [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. We also found activity from these plants against 
 <italic>Candida</italic> and CHIKV. However, due to its toxic nature, caution is necessary since deleterious health consequences may occur if high doses are administered for a long time.
</p>
