<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Bone marrow MSCs in mammals retain a high degree of plasticity and their fate is affected by cell culture medium composition [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. In the present study, accumulation of lipid content induced by fatty acids added to the media was dose-dependent as confirmed through quantification and microscopy observation of the morphological changes, and the intensification of the red aura occupied in the cells by ORO staining. Previously, the ability of MSCs derived from bone to differentiate, in addition to osteoblasts, into adipocyte-like cells was demonstrated, by applying adipogenic media containing two different concentrations of lipid mixture; thus, confirming their multipotentiality [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. The presence of fatty acids in such specific media seems to be critical to shoot the adipogenic process in undetermined fish cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], and this has also been observed in avian adipocyte precursor cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Accordingly, in the present study, the cells began to accumulate lipids potentially inducing adipocyte-like differentiation in response to the fatty acid treatments. However, LA and the combinations containing this fatty acid were those that produced a greater effect, whereas the combination of the two fatty acids mainly present in fish oil (EPA+DHA) caused lower lipid deposition. Similarly, in mature salmon adipocytes it was observed that fatty acids from vegetable oils (i.e. oleic acid) were able to induce more triacylglycerol accumulation than fatty acids characteristic of fish oils [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Other studies have also shown this lower capacity of fatty acids from fish oils to be stored in adipose cells, such as those performed on 3T3-L1 pre-adipocytes, where DHA reduced dose-dependently fat deposition likely by suppressing lipid filling [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. Overall, the data suggest that the n-6 PUFA LA may stimulate the uptake and depot of extracellular fats in these adipocyte-like cells, more than the other treatments tested.
</p>
