<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To corroborate the differential action of EPA and LA driving adipocyte-like development of bone-derived MSCs through PPARγ activation, their effects in combination with two PPARγ antagonists were evaluated. According to the results, LA action was unaffected, demonstrating the direct effect of this fatty acid on the transport of lipids due to 
 <italic class="italic">fabp11</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">fatp1</italic> up-regulated gene expression. With regards to EPA treatment, the antagonist GW9662 did not cause any change, but the use of the specific antagonist T0070907, triggered a remarkable down-regulation on transcript levels of the three fatty acid transporters and the factors 
 <italic class="italic">rxr</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">cebpb</italic>, although not of 
 <italic class="italic">pparg</italic>. Accordingly, in mammals GW9662 shows negligible effects on transcription compared to T0070907, which displays properties of an inverse agonist, showing effects on transcription opposite to well-known PPARγ agonists such as [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Similarly, the antiobesogenic effect of these antagonists has been shown in zebrafish larvae 
 <italic class="italic">in vivo</italic>, although without performing transcriptomic analyses [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. Overall, the current data would suggest an inhibition of the adipogenic process, including lipid internalization, mediated at least in part by the incapability of EPA to activate PPARγ and the companion transcription factors. In agreement with this hypothesis, other authors using this same antagonist showed a decrease in 
 <italic class="italic">cd36</italic> mRNA levels not depending on the increased gene expression of 
 <italic class="italic">pparg</italic>, but elevated PPARγ activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. Thus, blockage of EPA action by T00709007 indicates that via the action of this transcription factor, EPA may also up-regulate fat transporters to ultimately stimulate adipocyte differentiation of MSCs. These results agree with the capacity of n-3 LC-PUFA to promote the formation of healthy new adipocytes [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref072" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>]. An example of a similar scenario may be the antidiabetic treatment with the full PPARγ agonists, the thiazolidinediones (i.e. troglitazone or pioglitazone), which have been shown, at least in rodent models, to favor remodeling of the adipose tissue by promoting pre-adipocyte recruitment for hyperplastic growth [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pone.0215926.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>].
</p>
