<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the blood stages of the malaria parasite’s lifecycle, the 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> species digests haemoglobin from the human host to support its metabolic requirements and for sustenance [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. The process leads to the concomitant formation of free haem molecules that are toxic to the parasite through the production of reactive oxygen species, leading to its death. To counteract this effect, the malaria parasite has developed a pathway that biocrystallizes free heme molecules into insoluble, non-toxic crystalline hemozoin, also known as the malaria pigment. This takes place inside the parasite’s acidic DV (pH 5.2–5.6). Traditional antimalarial drugs, most notably quinolines, have been proposed to induce antimalarial activity by blocking this pathway via binding interaction with heme [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. For instance, chloroquine accumulates in the plasmodial DV and binds to polymerizing heme complexes to halt the biocrystallization process, thereby liberating more heme molecules to kill the parasite [
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. It is on this premise that this pathway has been a subject of widespread research interest to devise novel bioactive compounds for antimalarial activity through its blockade. Organometallic complexes of transition metals, such as ferroquine, have been successfully applied to target heme detoxification [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Apart from this, several organometallic complexes show reversible redox character capable of generating ROS due to the presence of the metallic centre and can also introduce new therapeutic benefits, including high lipophilicity and improved cell membrane permeability [
 <xref rid="B99-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>].
</p>
