<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This review aims to give a perspective of the approaches and strategies used in our group to discover bioactive xanthone derivatives, and/or pharmacological probes, from natural and synthetic sources. Given the objective of this review, most of the references indicated throughout the text correspond mainly to the contribution of our group in this area.The hit compounds discovered for several targets and with diverse biological activities were highlighted and could be useful models to develop a vast number of heterocyclic privileged scaffolds. Not only is important to reach high-affinity hits but a strong investment should follow on safety, PK, process chemistry and comprehensive SAR understanding. Being focusing in the (thio)xanthonic scaffold is considered one of the strengths of our research group. However, we also aim for diversity and innovation by researching less explored areas (such as marine natural products), and most importantly by following a multi- and interdisciplinary approach, engaging chemistry of natural products, organic and medicinal chemistry, structure determination and purification, green chemistry, physicochemical properties and ADMET, validated in silico and HTS screenings, intellectual protection, drug delivery systems, etc. In summary, taking into account the chemical “family tree” based on xanthone (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f022">Figure 22</xref>), our group has:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>(1)</label>
   <p>isolated new compounds from terrestrial and marine sources and/or analyzed species not yet studied with regard to their secondary metabolites;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(2)</label>
   <p>used Nature-based strategies to guide the synthetic ways whenever possible;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(3)</label>
   <p>synthesized these compounds for structure elucidation purposes to obtain them through “greener” methods and in quantities suitable for biological/pharmacological assays, as well as to obtain nature-based analogues with improved druglike properties;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(4)</label>
   <p>contributed with new data in the area of NMR and X-ray crystallography;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(5)</label>
   <p>evaluated several biological activities for different chemical families of xanthone derivatives; the main focus was in the area of antitumor and antimicrobial agents, especially taking into account MDR, which we believe should be pursuit in Academia; other areas of intervention include cardiovascular, antimalarial, anti-inflammatory, anti-obesity, hepatoprotection, etc. More recently, the area related to the discovery of environmental-benign AF agents was also explored;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(6)</label>
   <p>explored the mechanisms of action, SAR and structure-activity-properties-relationship (SAPR);</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(7)</label>
   <p>formulated some compounds in nanoparticles, liposomes and proliposomes (drug delivery systems), especially with xanthones with potential antitumor activity;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(8)</label>
   <p>determined the drug-likeness of some hit compounds (ADMET assays), as this should be carried out as soon as possible in the pipeline of drug discovery and development;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(9)</label>
   <p>obtained several chiral derivatives of xanthones and studied enantioseparation and enantioselectivity with regard to various biological activities, as well as analytical applications as chiral selectors for liquid chromatography.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
