<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rh(III)ClCp* silyl congeners (
 <bold>65</bold>–
 <bold>66</bold>) of Ru(II)(
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene) ferrocenyl and 3,4-dichlorophenyl TSC complexes (
 <bold>40</bold>–
 <bold>41</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f010">Figure 10</xref>) were also screened for their antimalarial potential against CQS NF45 and CQR Dd2 parasitemia in vitro, with the majority exhibiting better activity compared with the ruthenium(II) analogues (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f016">Figure 16</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The activity of the Rh(III) compounds was correlated to their β-hematin inhibition activity. Intriguingly, the carbosilane complex 
 <bold>66b</bold> was the most active in the series and exhibited better β-hematin activity than the control drug, chloroquine. This could be explained by the high lipophilic character of the silyl motif, which might enhance the binding interactions of 
 <bold>66b</bold> to the growing hemozoin polymer chain. Also noteworthy were the minimal instances of cross resistance and general toxicity observed for these complexes, as indicated by their low resistance indices when comparing activities on both strains and high selectivity indices on the mammalian CHO cell line. Similarly, Rh(III)ClCp* benzimidazole complexes (
 <bold>67</bold>) inhibited the growth of sensitive strains of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic>, albeit less effective than the Ru(II)Cl(
 <italic>p</italic>-cymene) (
 <bold>54</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f013">Figure 13</xref>) and Ir(III)ClCp* (
 <bold>25</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f006">Figure 6</xref>) derivatives [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Conjugation of these complexes to the 4-aminoquinoline nucleus significantly enhanced the activity of the compounds (
 <bold>68</bold>–
 <bold>69</bold>), making them more potent than the Ir(III) congeners with higher selectivity towards the malaria parasites (NF54 and K1) over the mammalian CHO cells (SI &gt; 20) [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Collectively, data from these studies seem to reinforce the previous observation regarding the beneficial pharmacological effects of the +3 oxidation state on the antiplasmodial activity of Rh(III) complexes.
</p>
