<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Breast cancer represents the most common cancer disease among women. It represents the second-highest rate leading cause of women mortality worldwide [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Chemotherapy is the most common for cancer treatment. Developing cancer drugs is essential to discover more active products with high potential [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This work represents an attempt to develop new therapeutic compounds of high efficacy in treating breast cancer disease. Literature reports confirmed the important diverse types of pharmaceutical activities of thiazole, pyrane, and/or pyridine derivatives. Thiazoles have concerned a great era of attention due to their association with various types of biological activities. Their derivatives exhibited important potency as anticancer [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], antibacterial [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], antimalarial [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] agents, and HIV-inhibitors [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Also, pyrane containing derivatives have been identified as anticancer [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], antimicrobial [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and antimalarial [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] agents. Furthermore, literature survey reported that compounds containing pyridine ring demonstrated anticancer [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], antimicrobial [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], antiviral [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], and antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] activities. Based on our recent work which demonstrated that various tetralone-based derivatives verified significant inhibitory activity towards different types of cancer disease, they displayed highly significant cytotoxic activity against MCF-7 human cancer cells (breast cancer), for all the tested compounds, all of them showed activity more potent than that obtained by the reference drug (Doxorubicine) [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Also, significant cytotoxic effects on U373 (human glioblastoma cells) were testified [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Additionally, cytotoxic activity against HepG-2 (human cancer cells) was established [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. These facts motivated us to synthesize new compounds derived from coupling of 6-methoxy-1-tetralone with different heterocyclic ring systems such as thiazole, pyrano [2,3-d] thiazole, and dihydrothiazolo [4,5-b] pyridine in one molecule aiming to construct new candidates of enhancing anticancer activity. Herein, 6-methoxy-1-tetralone was used as good building blocks to construct the desired heterocyclic products.
</p>
