<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Chronic noncommunicable diseases (CNCDs) are one of the greatest public health problems today, responsible for 68% of the world’s deaths in 2012 [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>], and for 68.3% of deaths in Brazil in 2011 [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The Global Action Plan for the Prevention and Control of NCDs 2013–2020 [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] from the World Health Organization (WHO) establishes some priority goals for improving the health status of the population, including reducing the prevalence of smokers, increasing prevalence of physically active persons, reducing the relative coronary risk, periodontal disease, caries, as well as controlling high blood pressure, diabetes, overweight and obesity. The Strategic Action Plan for Coping with CNCDs in Brazil from 2011 to 2022 is based on three main guidelines: (i) Surveillance, information, assessment and monitoring; (ii) health promotion; and (iii) integral care [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], ratifying the need to develop health strategies that are capable of embracing health complexity. Accordingly, the promotion of global health should be understood as a mechanism that works only with an interdisciplinary and integrated effort, aimed at an aggregating knowledge of several scientific fields that dialogue for holistic health [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. In the context of work, CNCDs impact on the reduction of labour force participation, the number of hours worked, greater job rotation and early retirements, as well as the commitment of salaries, gains and achieved position. Estimates for Brazil suggest that the loss of labour productivity and the decrease in family income resulting from only three CNCDs, i.e., diabetes, heart disease and stroke, led to a loss in the Brazilian economy of 4.18 billion US dollars (USD) between 2006 and 2015 [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. 
</p>
