<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the current scenario of transformative health care, it is imperative that health professionals focus on care that is centred on the need of each individual in an integrated way [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Thus, the process of interdisciplinary work in health teams, emerging and increasingly urgent, has been supported by innovative policies, practices and care models that bring professionals and patients closer to the limits of traditional disciplinarity [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. In this context, interprofessional education is understood as a practice of achieving interdisciplinarity as members of more than one care profession are allowed to learn together and in an interactive way, in order to improve interprofessional collaboration or the health and the well-being of patients [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Interprofessional collaboration has been associated with a number of positive outcomes, including improvements in patient safety and case management, optimized use of the skills of each health care team member, and provision of improved health services, identified as crucial to provision of effective and efficient health care when considering the complexity of individuals’ health needs [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. A study conducted in Mexico by Barceló et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] in 2010 identified, in some cases, improvement in glycaemic control of groups submitted to follow-up by an interdisciplinary team composed of physicians, nurses, nutritionists and psychologists, compared to groups undergoing usual care. The proportion of people with good glycaemic control (A1c &lt; 7%) among those in the intervention group increased from 28%, before the intervention, to 39%, after the intervention. Overall, the proportion of patients achieving three or more quality improvement goals increased more than four-fold between the intervention group, from 16.6% to 69.7% (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), while among the usual care group if decreased from 12.4% to 5.9% (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> = 0.12), although not statistically significant. According to the need of interprofessional collaboration, the field of worker’s health has, since its emergence, a great potential for disciplinary integration in order to try to organize care in a more comprehensive way, translated into factors of influence on the worker’s health, difficult to achieve by the disciplines alone [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Occupational health assessments are essential in the examination of the health conditions of the worker and in the preservation of health by the development of the day to day work. In addition, it is the opportunity to assess the worker’s overall health, including the risk factors for CNCDs. According to the Regulatory Norm (NR) 7 [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], workers should be examined annually in the periodic assessment. However, this timeframe interval may be long for an adequate monitoring of the risks to the workers’ health. The implementation of a management policy for the risk factors of the CNCDs in a company enables the improvement of health, productivity and quality of life for all workers [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>].
</p>
