<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Skin samples (usually from breast reduction or other cosmetic surgeries) with hair (usually vellus) were obtained from Professor Yoram Milner, Head of Meyer's Skin Biochemistry Research Laboratory, Life Science Institute, Hebrew University, Givat Ram. The sebaceous glands were extracted under sterile conditions either individually or by the “shearing” method [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For each substance/extract tested and for isotretinoin (positive control), glands (10–20 glands/well) were floated on a preweighed nitrocellulose paper in a six-well plate [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The glands were distributed into the wells of the plate by rotation as they were extracted. The nitrocellulose paper with the glands was then weighed to obtain the wet weight of the glands. The glands were returned to the plate which was then incubated with growth media for primary cell cultures (F12-DMEM plus growth factors [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and 0.02% v/v antibiotic solution (penicillin 10,000 U/ml, streptomycin 10 mg/ml, and amphotericin B 0.025 mg/ml, Biological Industries, Israel) in a tissue culture incubator (5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>, 37°C). After a recovery period of about 12 hr [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], the growth media were replaced with serially diluted, sterile, filtered preincubation media (growth media + test substance) in duplicates to give 50, 5, and 0.5 mg/ml test substance/duplicate. In each experiment, a plate containing glands with a positive control (1 mM isotretionoin in DMSO [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]) and a negative control (the solvent vehicle) was used. At the end of a 12–24 hr preincubation period, the glands were weighed again. A reduction in weight represent an indication of overall cellular damage to the glands [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The media in each well were then replaced with 1 ml incubation media (preincubation media + 2 
 <italic>μ</italic>Ci/ml [
 <sup>14</sup>C]-Na-acetate, 100 
 <italic>μ</italic>Ci/ml, 50 mCi/mmol in ethanol vehicle) to a final concentration of 2 
 <italic>μ</italic>M acetate and the glands were incubated for an additional 8–24 hr. After the incubation, the glands were washed thoroughly (about 10 times) with nonradioactive 0.2 mM Na-acetate in PBS, and their lipid contents were extracted and separated by the Bligh and Dyer method [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The lipids were dried in a speedvac to the extent they can be possibly weighed (with 0.1 mg accuracy). The dried and extracted lipids were resuspended in a known amount of resuspension buffer (chloroform : methanol 1 : 2) [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. A part of the resuspended lipids (20–50%) were counted in a scintillation counter, and the rest were stored at −20°C.
</p>
