<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The exclusion criteria were epidural anesthesia/analgesia and other conditions that might influence gastrointestinal motility such as a history of abdominal surgery other than cesarian, chronic constipation or other gastrointestinal disorders, chronic use of opiates, chronic use of drugs with impact on intestinal peristalsis, cesarean hysterectomy, extensive adhesiolysis, peritoneal carcinomatosis, severe postpartum hemorrhage (exceeding 500 ml), the development of complications during or within 24 h after surgery, severe organ (kidney, liver, or heart) dysfunction and using other prokinetic drugs. Furthermore, the women with acute gestational complications such as preeclampsia and those who received magnesium sulfate were excluded, because this medication may affect intestinal peristalsis. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants before surgery. Two consultant surgeons performed all operations, and the technical aspects of the surgery were left to the individual surgeons' discretion. The duration of surgery was the time between incision of skin and dressing placement. The estimated intraoperative blood loss (in ml) was documented. A recovery program was employed after surgery in all participants for postoperative management. This program comprises early removal of urinary catheter, early mobilization, and drinking of liquids as soon as bowel movement occurs or passage of flatus and progress to a normal diet on the basis of tolerance after the operation. Postoperative pain was controlled using intravenous Pethidine (10 mg/kg) as a baseline analgesic treatment immediately after surgery for all patients. Thereafter, rescue pain relief was administered by the reception of Diclofenac suppository if necessary. Discharge of patients was based on off intravenous fluids, regular diet toleration and stool passing, full ambulant and without evidence of complications. A block randomization list was generated for 150 patients without stratification based on a computer-generated random allocation sequence with six sequences in each block. Randomization to three groups of study, intervention group (chamomile oil), placebo group (paraffin oil), and control group (no intervention), occurred preoperatively. The allocation was carried out by research assistant on the day of surgery after obtaining informed consent. Allocation assignments were deposited in consecutively, sealed, numbered, and opaque envelopes. The patient and the investigator were blinded to treatment assignment in the intervention group and placebo group. In the intervention group, chamomile oil (20 drops) was applied topically on the abdominal region after consciousness and stability of patient every 1 h in the first 4 h and then every 8 h until fecal defecation. Placebo group received placebo oil (paraffin oil) in the same manner. All group received postoperative routine care. The therapy was administered by the research assistant and was recorded in the patient's file on a separate masked record. The preparation of chamomile oil was done according to that proposed in traditional Persian medicine manuscripts. For this purpose, 200 g dried flowers of 
 <italic class="italic">M. chamomilla</italic> var. chamomilla was soaked in 1 L of distilled water for 24 h. Thereafter, it was boiled by medium heat until one quadrant of the content was remaining. Then, it was filtered, and the same volume of mineral oil was added to the filtrate and placed over medium heat until the water was fully evaporated and only the oil remained.[
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] The final product was packaged in airtight, light-resistant containers.
</p>
