<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several halophytic grasses have been studied for their biological activities, with particular emphasis on their antibacterial, antifungal, antiviral, spasmolytic and antidiarrheal activities. Furthermore, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, antidiabetic and anti-obesity properties, as well as anticarcinogenic and hepatoprotective effects, were also studied. In the case of 
 <italic class="italic">A. donax</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. dactylon</italic>, extensive reviews about these aspects are already available. Al-Snafi compiled valuable information focusing on the different biological activities of 
 <italic class="italic">A.donax</italic> [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Following the same path, Asthana and co-workers also revealed the potential of 
 <italic class="italic">C. dactylon</italic> to be used in medicine [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Therefore, the pharmacological potentials of these species will not be discussed here. Besides these two species, 13 halophytic grasses, accounting 10% of the diversity of the 
 <italic class="italic">taxa</italic>, were studied regarding their biological activities. Conversely, some of the species discussed in this chapter were not studied concerning their phytochemical composition, which is the case of 
 <italic class="italic">E. colona</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eleusine indica</italic> (L.) Gaertn, 
 <italic class="italic">D. aegyptium</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Phragmites australis</italic> (Cav.) Trin. ex Steud. and 
 <italic class="italic">Phragmites karka</italic> (Retz.) Trin. ex Steud.. The species with the greater number of described activities was 
 <italic class="italic">D. bipinnata</italic> followed by 
 <italic class="italic">E. indica</italic>, whose chemical composition is not known (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-20-01067" class="xref">Table S1</xref>). It is important to highlight that plant extracts should not be used without the knowledge of their chemical composition since the two aspects are inseparably linked because the pharmacological activities cannot be studied without knowledge of the substance present in the extracts. 
</p>
