<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Application of herbal drugs or herbal therapies could be dated back since ancient times of human history and it is still being practiced in many places all over the world [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Among the herbal drugs applied worldwide, traditional Chinese medicines (TCM) is a large group of plants, animals or minerals applied in remedies following the medical principles developed in ancient China. Nowadays, with system scientific research and modern production technologies, more and more people worldwide have had traditional therapies including TCM in daily life for many reasons [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. According to “WHO traditional medicine strategy: 2014–2023”, over 100 million Europeans have tried traditional and complementary medicine products and healthcare services, one fifth of the consumers are reported to be regular users. The same phenomenon has also been found in Africa, Asia, Australia and North America with an estimated output of Chinese materia medica to be US$83.1 billion in 2012 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. With such amount of consumption worldwide, problems associated with herbal drugs and TCM application have been increasingly reported. For example, a very early report showed that young women applied slimming regimen consisted of 
 <italic>Stephania tetrandra</italic> and 
 <italic>Magnolia officinalis</italic> resulted in renal fibrosis due to the misuse of 
 <italic>Aristolochia fangchi</italic> as 
 <italic>Stephania tetrandra</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. It was also reported that exposure to aristolochic acids and their derivatives in herbal drugs (such as 
 <italic>Aristolochia manshuriensis</italic>) could give rise to kidney failure and hepatocellular carcinomas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Medical incidents of herbal drugs treatments are highly related to the quality of herbal drugs, which might due to adulterants, contaminations (such as pesticides and heavy metals), and might also because of the wrong botanical parts used during treatment. Furthermore, incidents may also happen due to processing of herbal drugs, which may involve change in the content of active components and even transforming components in herbal drugs into toxic chemicals. In a recent market study conducted in UK, of the 211 samples investigated, 20 unofficial species were found and 17 samples were detected to have different degree of contamination with other impurities, including other plants, stones and earth etc. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Thus, it is very important to monitor the quality of herbal drugs and TCM.
</p>
