<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Natural insecticides, especially plant essential oils, have been used extensively to interrupt host seeking of blood-feeding insects [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. These compounds are attractive alternative tools to synthetic chemical repellents because they are considered to have low toxicity to humans, animals and the environment [
 <xref rid="B18-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Because of their minimum risk, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) have exempted some plant-derived compounds from full registration [Section 25(b) of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act of United States] [
 <xref rid="B21-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Reduced registration requirements by EPA has led to a flood of essential-oil based products available commercially for indoor use. Many of these compounds have been evaluated in the laboratory for repellent activity against urban pests [
 <xref rid="B22-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Essential oil constituents such as geraniol and citronellol had repellent activity on 
 <italic>Triatoma rubida</italic> (Uhler)
 <italic>, T. protacta</italic> (Uhler)
 <italic>,</italic> and 
 <italic>T. recurva</italic> (Stal) (Hemiptera: Reduviidae) [
 <xref rid="B25-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], while carvacrol, eugenol, and geraniol repelled 
 <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic> (Stål) and 
 <italic>T. infestans</italic> (Klug) (Hemiptera: Reduviidae) [
 <xref rid="B26-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Thymol was reported as having repellent activity against 
 <italic>Blatella lateralis</italic> (Walker) (Blattodea: Blattidae) [
 <xref rid="B24-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In bed bugs, several studies have evaluated the contact toxicity [
 <xref rid="B27-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], fumigant toxicity [
 <xref rid="B29-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and residual toxicity [
 <xref rid="B34-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] of plant-derived pesticides, but few have studied in detailed their repellency. Anderson et al. [
 <xref rid="B36-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] demonstrated the efficacy of three naturally occurring repellents, para-menthane-3,8-diol, delta dodecalactone, and gamma dodecalactone to prevent bed bugs from hiding in substrate-treated areas. Catnip oils also exhibited high repellency activity against bed bugs, but their residual effect was shorter than DEET [
 <xref rid="B37-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Sharififard et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] conducted laboratory evaluations with essential oils of oregano 
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> and demonstrated 100% repellency against bed bugs up to 24 h. In choice tests, bed bugs seemed to avoid contacting areas treated with lethal doses of two essential oil-based products, EcoRaider
 <sup>®</sup> and Bed Bug Patrol
 <sup>®</sup> [
 <xref rid="B27-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The latter three studies did not characterize the repellency or avoidance induced by major constituents of the essential oils in bed bugs. There is also an anecdotal report of the lack of repellency activity of cedar and peppermint oil against bed bugs [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], which might be explained by the absence of essential oil constituents (EOCs) with repellent properties in the composition of these essential oils. Identification of EOCs with repellent activity will help develop potentially efficacious essential oil-based formulations. Recently, medium-chain length fatty acids from coconut oil exhibited strong and lasting repellent activity against various blood-sucking arthropods, including bed bugs [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-12-00184" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The easing of the US government requirements for plant product registration, the relative low production cost of many of these materials, and the perception by consumers as “green”, make these products likely to be adopted and incorporated into IPM programs for bed bugs.
</p>
