<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">Invasive plants are considered major threats to biodiversity in different ecosystems worldwide, and the ability to form persistent seed banks is one of the most important strategies of the invasive plants to colonize new habitats (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Gawad and El-Amier, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Rai and Singh, 2020</xref>). The invasive plants have been recognized to lose biodiversity due to competition with the native plants. In Taif region, 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> was observed as an invasive plant in several habitats, where it is considered as one of the major invaders in Suadi Arabia (
 <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">Thomas et al., 2016</xref>). It grows in high altitude (800–2700 m.a.s.l.) with a wide range of soil conditions that enables it to grow vigorously and spread as a monospecific stand (
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Florentine et al., 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Al-Robai et al., 2019</xref>). In the present study, the soil seed bank analysis of the studied stands revealed that the plant species density under canopy of 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> was lower than that outside canopy. Also, some species existed only outside the canopy and others were recorded only under the canopy. The presence of these species under canopy could be attributed to the facilitation by 
 <italic>N. glauca</italic> shrub (
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Badano et al., 2015</xref>), while the absence of other species could be ascribed to the competition or allelopathic interference (
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Alshahrani, 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">El-Kenany et al., 2017</xref>). The invasive species can modify the soil composition and soil microbiota, and thereby facilitate or inhibit the native species (
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Jordan et al., 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">Molina-Montenegro et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
