<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some of the effects of EO can be indirectly related to EO activity on gut microbiota. Most of the studies have reported EO’s effects on gut microbiota in pigs and poultry, whereas research on EOs’ impact on ruminant microbiota is somehow lagging. Feeding pigs with a blend of oregano and cinnamon oil increased 
 <italic>Lactobacillaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>Ruminococcaceae</italic> and decreased 
 <italic>Clostridiaceae</italic> in the intestine [
 <xref rid="B200-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">200</xref>]. 
 <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and 
 <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic> were the two most dominant phyla in a study involving a mixture of EOs and organic acids in weaned piglets, which also induced an increase in performance [
 <xref rid="B201-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>]. Dietary supplementation with EO was associated with increased Lactobacilli and decreased coliforms in vivo [
 <xref rid="B202-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">202</xref>]. Feeding thymol- and cinnamaldehyde-supplemented diets induced a decrease in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> carriage in piglets at a similar level to that obtained with in-feed antibiotics [
 <xref rid="B203-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>]. These results are mostly consistent using, in most cases, culture-related techniques. Introducing next-generation sequencing approaches to study EOs’ impact on microbiota would probably provide more insights into the relationship between EO and the microbial community in the intestine and, in turn, how this relationship may shape the immune system. In poultry, treatment with EO has a synergistic effect with antibacterial peptides to reduce pathogenic intestinal microbiota’s negative impact. Indeed, cecal microbiota composition can be substantially changed with either cinnamaldehyde alone or in combination with citral in the feed [
 <xref rid="B204-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>]. It is commonly found that EO may exhibit a potential antimicrobial activity against bacteria, archaea, protozoa, or fungi in the rumen [
 <xref rid="B205-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>]. Patra described EOs’ potential to inhibit hyper-ammonia production bacteria, selective inhibition of 
 <italic>Selenomonas ruminantium</italic> by thymol, and no substantial EO effects on ruminal ciliate protozoa. At high doses, EO can be highly inhibitory for most ruminal microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B206-antioxidants-10-00330" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>].
</p>
