<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">It is highlighted that for developing countries, the quality management concepts and validation and risk management must be understood, adopted and employed (World Health Organization 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2006</xref>) to be able to implement cleanrooms according to tissue establishments developed-countries health authorities (COMMISSION DIRECTIVE 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2003</xref>/94/EC 2003), which also lead to the challenge of the supervision and control capacity by the authorities from developing countries. In Chile, the ISP is in charge of supervising tissue establishments and banks of the healthcare system and everything related to the authorization, quality control, surveillance and importing of cells and tissues. However, it is the MINSAL who through the ISP service must direct biotechnological/biomedicine development according to health policies based on national reality and epidemiology with data-driven priority setting process. Tissue transplantation could be evaluated through “management commitments” of health services, which would later be evaluated by any division in charge of the healthcare network and be enhanced through financial stimuli associated with performance. For example, the ISP from Chile can enhance this development through activity plans in conjunction with tissue banks. Finally, the governmental, clinical and academic sectors have the responsibility of this development in order to achieve compliance with international quality and excellence standards. In the EU this has been established as a “dialogue structure” between the health authorities, clinicians and the tissue establishments (European Directorate for the Quality of Medicines &amp; Healthcare (EDQM) 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2019</xref>). Tissues and cells as scientific area can be assumed as a beneficence for healthcare users (i.e. patients) as they are highly demanded for universal coverage and, at the same time, a necessity for future sustainable health systems development.
</p>
