<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The dietary supplementation for 20–60 days with different EOs usually improved oxidative status of freshwater fish. Channel catfish (
 <italic class="italic">Ictalurus punctatus</italic>) fed with 0.5 mL per kg EO of 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare</italic> increased plasma lysozyme, catalase, and superoxide dismutase compared to fish fed a control diet (
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zheng et al., 2009</xref>). The dietary addition of the EOs of 
 <italic class="italic">Cymbopogon citratus</italic> (0.2 g per kg) and 
 <italic class="italic">Pelargonium graveolens</italic> (0.4 g per kg) enhanced catalase and lysozyme activities and glutathione reductase content and reduced malondialdehyde from the whole body of the Nile tilapia compared to the basal diet (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Al-Sagheer et al., 2018</xref>). Silver catfish fed 2.0 mL per kg EO of 
 <italic class="italic">A. triphylla</italic> presented lower TBARS, lipid hydroperoxide, superoxide dismutase, catalase, and non-protein thiols in the brain, liver, and muscle of fish fed a control diet (
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zeppenfeld et al., 2017</xref>). The same species fed diets supplemented with EO of 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> (linalool chemotype, around 0.5–2.0 mL per kg) stimulated superoxide dismutase, catalase and glutathione peroxidase activities and non-protein thiols content, whereas reduced lipoperoxidation and TBARS in several organs compared to those fed a control diet (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saccol et al., 2013</xref>). Finally, hepatic superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase activities enhanced while catalase, glutathione reductase, glutathione-S-transferase and malondialdehyde decreased in rainbow trout fed 0.5–1.0 g per kg diet of EOs of 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia officinalis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha spicata</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</italic> compared to that of the control-diet fed group (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sönmez et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
