<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085" class="p">In the early history, it was noticed that oil forms a thin layer over water surface when spread onto the water surface which showed the properties like the dampening surface waves and ripples. The scientific breakthrough in the era came into notice when in 1774 Sir Benjamin Franklin, an American Scientist first reported to the British Royal Society, the calming behaviour of a teaspoonful of oil (2 ml) over an acre of a pond on Clapham 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[44]</xref>. It was Lord Rayleigh 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[45]</xref> who first gave the idea about the thickness of such floating oil films. He commented that maximum thickness of this oil film is one molecule thick. Agnes Pockel demonstrated that this oil film could be controlled by movable barrier 
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[46]</xref>. Based on Pockel's experiment modern Langmuir trough has been developed. Extensive monolayer theory was developed by I. Langmuir 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[47]</xref>. He was awarded Nobel prize for his experiments suggesting that single layers of atoms that were bound within the underlying surface could be formed an adsorbed films of great stability. However, several years later it was K. Blodgett who for the first time developed a technique for transfer of the floating films from the air-water interface onto solid substrate 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[48]</xref>. Such transferred mono- and multilayer assemblies on solid substrate are now referred to as Langmuir-Blodgett (LB) films. After the pioneering work done by Langmuir and Blodgett, it took almost half a century before scientists all around the world started to realize the opportunities of this unique technique. It was Khun and his collaborators who revived and demonstrated the potential of the field 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[49]</xref>. His work stimulated interest in the topic in Europe, USA and Japan and now throughout the world. The first international conference on Langmuir-Blodgett (LB) films was held in 1979 and since then the use of this technique is increasing among the scientists throughout the world working on various different field of research. Extensive studies on LB films are now being going on. Various review articles has been published time to time since the revival of the interest in research related to different aspects of LB films [
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>].
</p>
