<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Triazole is an important heterocyclic moiety that occupies a unique position in heterocyclic chemistry, due to its large number of biological activities. It exists in two isomeric forms i.e. 1,2,4-triazole and 1,2,3-triazole and is used as core molecule for the design and synthesis of many medicinal compounds. 1,2,4-Triazole possess broad spectrum of therapeutically interesting drug candidates such as analgesic, antiseptic, antimicrobial, antioxidant, anti-
   <italic>urease</italic>, anti-inflammatory, diuretics, anticancer, anticonvulsant, antidiabetic and antimigraine agents.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">The structures of all synthesized compounds were characterized by physicochemical properties and spectral means (IR and NMR). The synthesized compounds were evaluated for their in vitro antimicrobial activity against Gram-positive (
   <italic>B. subtilis</italic>), Gram-negative (
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and 
   <italic>E. coli</italic>) bacterial and fungal (
   <italic>C. albicans</italic> and 
   <italic>A. niger</italic>) strains by tube dilution method using ciprofloxacin, amoxicillin and fluconazole as standards. In-vitro antioxidant and anti-
   <italic>urease</italic> screening was done by DPPH assay and indophenol method, respectively. The in-vitro anticancer evaluation was carried out against MCF-7 and HCT116 cancer cell lines using 5-FU as standards.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results, discussion and conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par3">The biological screening results reveal that the compounds 
   <bold>T</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>5</bold>
   </sub> (MIC
   <sub>
    <italic>BS</italic>, 
    <italic>EC</italic>
   </sub> = 24.7 µM, MIC
   <sub>
    <italic>PA</italic>
   </sub>, 
   <sub>
    <italic>CA</italic>
   </sub> = 12.3 µM) and 
   <bold>T</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>17</bold>
   </sub> (MIC
   <sub>
    <italic>AN</italic>
   </sub> = 27.1 µM) exhibited potent antimicrobial activity as comparable to standards ciprofloxacin, amoxicillin (MIC
   <sub>Cipro</sub> = 18.1 µM, MIC
   <sub>Amo</sub> = 17.1 µM) and fluconazole (MIC
   <sub>Flu</sub> = 20.4 µM), respectively. The antioxidant evaluation showed that compounds 
   <bold>T</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>2</bold>
   </sub> (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 34.83 µg/ml) and 
   <bold>T</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>3</bold>
   </sub> (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 34.38 µg/ml) showed significant antioxidant activity and comparable to ascorbic acid (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 35.44 µg/ml). Compounds 
   <bold>T</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>3</bold>
   </sub> (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 54.01 µg/ml) was the most potent 
   <italic>urease</italic> inhibitor amongst the synthesized compounds and compared to standard thiourea (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 54.25 µg/ml). The most potent anticancer activity was shown by compounds 
   <bold>T</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>2</bold>
   </sub> (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 3.84 μM) and 
   <bold>T</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>7</bold>
   </sub> (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 3.25 μM) against HCT116 cell lines as compared to standard 5-FU (IC
   <sub>50</sub> = 25.36 μM).
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
