<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The efficacy, performance, and safety of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> have been witnessed and widely applied in traditional Indian, Asian, and Chinese medicines, herbs or food and beverages, and pharmaceutical products [
 <xref rid="B109-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. A report by the Cosmetic Review Ingredient [
 <xref rid="B60-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] expert panel confirmed the safety of various 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> extracts in the current practices of use, based on the reported research including limited data on in vitro human cell cultures and oral administration in human studies. According to the World Health Organization (WHO), the recommended dosage for oral intake of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> is 1.00 to 2.00 g per day for scar surface or wound healing. In terms of tea or juice preparation using the dried plant, the dosage is 0.33–0.68 g per meal [
 <xref rid="B1-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. To date, no toxic effects from 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> intake have been reported by the WHO [
 <xref rid="B42-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> extracts and asiatic acid were orally administered in an experimental hamster and rabbit model. No toxic effect was observed after intake of 1.0 mg/kg of asiatic acid [
 <xref rid="B59-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] or 1 mg/kg of asiaticoside [
 <xref rid="B110-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. In fact, administering asiaticoside at 1.00 g/kg of the patient’s body weight has been demonstrated to be non-toxic in the oral application of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> extract [
 <xref rid="B1-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Acute oral administration of 1 g/kg body weight of an ethanolic 50% extract and alcoholic extracts of 
 <italic>C. asiatica</italic> also showed no toxicity at doses of 350 mg/kg when given to rats [
 <xref rid="B111-antibiotics-10-00457" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>].
</p>
