<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Croton matourensis</italic> Aubl. (synonym 
 <italic class="italic">Croton lanjouwensis</italic> Jabl.) is a tree widely spread in the Amazon rainforest and in some regions of Central America (Panama). In Brazil, it is popularly known as “orelha de burro”, “maravuvuia”, and/or “sangrad’água”, and is used in folk medicine as a depurative and in the treatment of infections, fractures, and colds [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. However, only few research papers are found for this species [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-Pinene, elemecine, 
 <italic class="italic">α</italic>-phellandrene, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>-cymene, linalool, and 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>-caryophyllene were found as the main constituents in the essential oil (EO) from the leaves, fruit, inflorescence, and bark of 
 <italic class="italic">C. matourensis</italic> collected from the Brazilian Amazon rainforest [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. Additionally, the seco-labdane diterpene named maravuic acid was isolated from the bark of 
 <italic class="italic">C. matourensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. More recently, the chemical composition and cytotoxic activity of the EO from the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">C. matourensis</italic> collected in Venezuela were reported [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], in which fenchyl acetate, methyleugenol, isoelemicine, elemicine, spathulenol, and valencene were found as main constituents, and cytotoxic potential was observed in LoVo (human colon carcinoma) and HeLa (human cervical cancer) cell lines [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-23-02974" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. However, in vivo antitumor properties have not been investigated. In this work, we investigated the chemical composition, in vitro cytotoxicity, and in vivo antitumor effect of the EO obtained from the leaves of 
 <italic class="italic">C. matourensis</italic> collected from the Amazon rainforest.
</p>
