<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The average oil recovery factor (RF) on the Norwegian Continental Shelf (NCS) is 47% and on a global basis the average recovery factor remains less than 40% [
 <xref rid="B1-nanomaterials-09-00665" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. In addition, oil production rates at existing fields are declining and the frequency of new field discoveries has diminished substantially in the last few decades [
 <xref rid="B2-nanomaterials-09-00665" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Thus, it is essential to target the residual oil remaining in petroleum reservoirs and achieve higher recovery factors from existing fields. Deployment of new and innovative production technologies is necessary to achieve this goal. One of the technologies is called enhanced oil recovery (EOR) and includes any technique where fluids/material that are not normally present in a reservoir is injected into it. The three primary categories of EOR include: thermal, chemical and miscible or solvent injection [
 <xref rid="B3-nanomaterials-09-00665" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Thermal recovery is typically utilized in heavy oil reservoirs. The method applies heat to reduce oil viscosity, facilitating mobilization of oil towards the production well. Chemical methods fall into three different groups: polymer flooding, surfactant-polymer (SP) flooding and alkaline-surfactant-polymer (ASP) flooding. The main idea is to add chemicals to the water flooding stage to either increase the mobility ratio (polymer), reduce the interfacial tension (surfactant), or create micro-emulsions (alkali). Miscible or solvent injection involves injection of a mutually miscible low viscosity solvent to mobilize residual oil trapped in the reservoir rock [
 <xref rid="B4-nanomaterials-09-00665" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-nanomaterials-09-00665" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Chemical flooding with polymer additives is considered the most promising EOR method [
 <xref rid="B6-nanomaterials-09-00665" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] for implementation on the Norwegian continental shelf.
</p>
