<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The responsiveness of circulating fatty acid concentrations to interventions varies according to the specific fatty acid structure. As a general rule, fatty acids that can be synthesized de novo from carbon sources producing acetate (endogenous) are more difficult to associate with dietary intake (exogenous) of the same fatty acids (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>). Thus, most SFAs and MUFAs in blood tend to have weaker associations with and inconsistent correlations to dietary intakes. Fatty acids that are primarily sourced from the diet tend to show stronger associations between blood and diet concentrations. While this includes n–3 and n–6 PUFAs, it can also extend to other “unique” exogenous fatty acids, such as odd-chain, branched chain fatty acids, as well as fatty acids with 
 <italic class="italic">trans</italic>- and conjugate bonds (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>). However, even with these dietary or “exogenous” fatty acids, the blood-diet relationship can be dictated by variation in endogenous fatty acid interconversion via C2 elongation, desaturation, and β-oxidation metabolism of the specific fatty acids of interest. For example, within the PUFA families, blood EPA and DHA correlate strongly with dietary intake of EPA and DHA, whereas n–6 arachidonic acid in blood and intake are less responsive (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>), suggesting that other factors, such as intake of other dietary fatty acids (i.e., 18:2n–6) and metabolic flux, have significant influence on n–6 arachidonic acid blood status (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>). Blood fatty acids may also provide insight into shifts in other macronutrient intakes, as increased n–7 fatty acids and decreased 18:2n–6 have been associated with low-fat/high-carbohydrate diets as they represent a shift toward increased endogenous or de novo fatty acid production (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>).
</p>
