<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Laothaweerungsawat et al. investigated the effect of OEO encapsulation in microemulsion-based systems on in vitro transdermal delivery of carvacrol, the major component of this essential oil, possessing analgesic and anti-inflammatory activity [
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-21-09653" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Microemulsion systems containing OEO were successfully obtained using Tween 60 and butylene glycol as surfactant and co-surfactant, respectively. From the pseudoternary phase diagram constructed using water dilution method, three microemulsion formulations were selected and evaluated for different physicochemical properties, including appearance, particle size and size distribution, zeta potential, viscosity, pH, and stability. Furthermore, irritation potential of OEO microemulsions (expressed as Irritation Score) versus that of a 5% (
 <italic>w</italic>/
 <italic>w</italic>) OEO solution in butylene glycol were investigated using the hen’s egg test. Transdermal absorption and skin maintenance of carvacrol from the formulation was studied 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Finally, the IL-6 and TNF-α secretion was determined to evaluate the anti-inflammatory activity of OEO containing microemulsions. According to the results of physicochemical characterization, the optimal formulation was considered the microemulsion containing 5% OEO as oil phase and active component, 25% Tween 60 as surfactant, 25% butylene glycol as cosurfactant, and 45% deionized water. With the narrowest polydispersity index (0.30 ± 0.07) and the lowest surfactant matter, this formulation of OEO displayed the smallest droplet size (179.5 ± 27.9 nm). The skin irritation effect of OEO was reduced to a large extent by this formulation (IS = 3.1 ± 0.10 versus IS = 4.8 ± 0.02 of blank formulation and IS = 5.0 ±0.01 of 5% OEO solution). Furthermore, this OEO microemulsion released carvacrol in a sustained manner, delivered 6.5 times more carvacrol through the skin than the OEO solution and produced the retention of a significant amount of carvacrol in the skin layer (2.6 ± 1.3%). The OEO anti-inflammatory activity was greatly improved by its incorporation in this microemulsion, which exhibited more potency in inhibiting IL-6 secretion and a comparable inhibitory effect on TNF-α secretion to that of dexamethasone [
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-21-09653" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
