<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We analyzed a total of 23 rat stomach samples and 28 rat fecal samples, which were collected from different individuals. We used BIRDF1/AWCintR2 primer pair, which targets a ~350 bp region in the COI gene (Zarzoso‐Lacoste et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). BIRDF1/AWCintR2 was selected as most relevant from a wider range of primers based on similar types of samples (Zarzoso‐Lacoste et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). We used CytbCorL (5′‐ACTGCGACAAAATCCCATTC‐3′) and CytbCor3 (5′‐GACTCCTCCTAGTTTATTTGGG‐3′), which targets a ~233 bp region of the Cytb gene and was designed to target corvid DNA, but also previously amplified babbler DNA (Renner et al., 
 <xref rid="ece37171-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Each 25‐μl PCR reaction consisted of 1.25 U of AmpliTaq Gold DNA Polymerase (ThermoFisher), 1.5 μM MgCl, 200 nM dNTPs, 200 nM reverse primer, 200 nM forward primer, 20 ng/μl BSA and 3 μl DNA template. PCR conditions were 95°C for 10 m, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15, 30 s at the annealing temperature (57°C for BirdF1/AwCintR2 and 51°C for CytbCorL/CytbCor3 respectively), 72°C for 45 s and a final extension (72°C for 5 m). Any PCR products within the appropriate size range visualized via gel electrophoresis were then cleaned using ExoSAP‐IT (United States Bio‐chemical), and Sanger sequenced from the forward primer direction using the BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit (Applied Biosystems, Inc). The sequenced products were column filtered, dried down, rehydrated with 10 μl of HPLC purified formamide, and then analyzed on an Applied Biosystems 3130xl DNA Analyzer. Individual sequences were assembled and edited in Sequencher 5.1 (GeneCodes). We sequenced 45 putative bird positive samples from BIRDF1/AWCintR2 primer pair and 23 putative bird positive samples from CytbCorL/CytbCor3 primer pair.
</p>
