<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53" class="p">Our network analysis confirmed the superiority of WGCNA in analysing highly multivariate and complex data. A detailed and clear insight into the spatiotemporal dynamics associated with the maturity of lavender flower has been obtained via WGCNA. The temporal regulation of gene expression plays an important role in plant growth and development. Detailed information about gene expression is crucial for understanding the molecular mechanisms underlying any developmental process. Recently, integrated analysis of gene co-expression and terpenoid accumulation has provided new insights into the regulatory processes of terpenoid metabolism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>]. CYP450s, which typically catalyse irreversible reactions and consequentially represent ideal points of control for metabolic bifurcation, are the major source of the chemical diversification of terpenoids, especially members of the CYP71 clan. In our work, many CYP450s, such as 
 <italic class="italic">CYP71D13</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">CYP71A1</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">CYP76AH1</italic>, were co-expressed with genes related to terpenoid biosynthesis. Increasing evidence indicates that many TPS/CYP450 gene pairs are found together in multiple sequenced plant genomes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>]. Gene–metabolite co-expression analysis has successfully identified novel 
 <italic class="italic">CYP450</italic> genes involved in terpenoid indole alkaloid biosynthesis and regulation in periwinkle (
 <italic class="italic">Catharanthus roseus</italic>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>] and two 
 <italic class="italic">CYP450</italic> genes involved in triterpene saponin glycyrrhizin biosynthesis in Glycyrrhiza plants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. In Arabidopsis, 
 <italic class="italic">CYP71B31</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">CYP76C3</italic>, together with 
 <italic class="italic">TPS10</italic> [form (2)-(R)-linalool] and TPS14 [form (+)-(S)-linalool], are co-expressed in flowers at anthesis and catalyse the oxidation of the two enantiomers of linalool to produce a sets of hydroxylated or epoxidized products [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">CYP76C1</italic>, which was co-expressed with 
 <italic class="italic">TPS10</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">TPS14</italic>, was also identified as a major linalool metabolizing oxygenase in Arabidopsis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. These subsequent oxidative steps are catalysed by members of the CYP450 superfamily, indicating the coordination of TPS and CYP450s in producing impressively diverse terpenoids that play important roles in the ecological interaction of plants with biotic and abiotic stress.
</p>
