<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6370847</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30741927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8577</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-08577-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>N-formyl-stabilizing quasi-catalytic species afford rapid and selective solvent-free amination of biomass-derived feedstocks</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3604-9271</contrib-id><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Hu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Haixin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Yaqiong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hiraga</surname><given-names>Yuya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7391-372X</contrib-id><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Zhen</given-names></name><address><email>zhenfang@njau.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9754-2417</contrib-id><name><surname>Hensen</surname><given-names>Emiel J. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Masaru</given-names></name><address><email>meijin@scf.che.tohoku.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9174-7681</contrib-id><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Richard Lee</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><address><email>smith@scf.che.tohoku.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9750 7019</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.27871.3b</institution-id><institution>Biomass Group, College of Engineering, </institution><institution>Nanjing Agricultural University, </institution></institution-wrap>40 Dianjiangtai Road, 210031 Nanjing, Jiangsu China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2248 6943</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.69566.3a</institution-id><institution>Graduate School of Environmental Studies, </institution><institution>Tohoku University, </institution></institution-wrap>6-6-11, Aoba, Aramaki, Aoba-ku, Sendai, 980-8579 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2248 6943</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.69566.3a</institution-id><institution>Research Center of Supercritical Fluid Technology, Graduate School of Engineering, </institution><institution>Tohoku University, </institution></institution-wrap>6-6-11, Aoba, Aramaki, Aoba-ku, Sendai, 980-8579 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0398 8763</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.6852.9</institution-id><institution>Department of Chemical Engineering and Chemistry, Laboratory of Inorganic Materials Chemistry, Schuit Institute of Catalysis, </institution><institution>Eindhoven University of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>P.O. Box 513, 5600 MB Eindhoven, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>699</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Nitrogen-containing compounds, especially primary amines, are vital building blocks in nature and industry. Herein, a protocol is developed that shows in situ formed N-formyl quasi-catalytic species afford highly selective synthesis of formamides or amines with controllable levels from a variety of aldehyde- and ketone-derived platform chemical substrates under solvent-free conditions. Up to 99% yields of mono-substituted formamides are obtained in 3&#x02009;min. The C-N bond formation and N-formyl species are prevalent in the cascade reaction sequence. Kinetic and isotope labeling experiments explicitly demonstrate that the C-N bond is activated for subsequent hydrogenation, in which formic acid acts as acid catalyst, hydrogen donor and as N-formyl species source that stabilize amine intermediates elucidated with density functional theory. The protocol provides access to imides from aldehydes, ketones, carboxylic acids, and mixed-substrates, requires no special catalysts, solvents or techniques and provides new avenues for amination chemistry.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Processes for efficient production of primary, secondary or ternary aminated compounds are constant challenges for chemical and pharmaceutical industries. Here, the authors develop selective and sustainable amination chemistry widely applicable to chemical substrates via formic acid.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Fragile ecosystems of our Earth and societal concerns over climate change are motivating industry to shift chemical production from conventional fossil resources to renewable biomass<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. As an important class of organic molecules, amines are widely applied in daily necessities and industrial commodities, such as fine chemicals, drugs, polymers, and functional materials<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Particularly, nitrogen species are contained in over 80% of the top 200 pharmaceuticals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. A number of bio-based amines (e.g., aryl-amines, furyl-amines, alkyl-amines, and alkanolamines) have been reported to be efficiently synthesized from small platform molecules via a range of reaction routes like reductive amination of carbonyl compounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, reductive aminolysis of simple sugars<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, and hydrogenation-decarbonylation of amino acids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Among these approaches, catalytic reductive amination of carboxides using molecular hydrogen is extensively performed over either transition (Raney Ni) or noble metals (e.g., Ru, Pd)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, the synthesis of primary amines is often difficult to achieve in the desired selectivity due to simultaneous formation of secondary and tertiary amines with some of the issues being formation of inactive complexes from catalyst deactivation, use of high-pressure hydrogen gas or pungent and basic ammonia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, which impede practical manufacture. Although gaseous or aqueous ammonia can be employed at moderate pressures, organic solvents (e.g., tetrahydrofuran, dioxane, and alcohols) along with additives are typically involved<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. Therefore, development of effective and green catalytic processes for preparation of primary amines and relevant N-containing molecules, especially from biomass resources, is required for future sustainable society.</p><p id="Par4">Formamide is a versatile chemical feedstock for pharmaceutical manufacture and is used in softeners for paper/fiber and as solvent for ionic compounds, resins and plasticizers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Extensive application of formamide renders it to be commercially available in large quantities in which it is industrially produced by either carbonylation of ammonia or ammonolysis of alkyl formate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Treatment of formic acid with ammonia to give ammonium formate, followed by heating can also yield formamide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Formamide has a large dipole moment with similar solvation properties as water<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The relatively high dielectric constant of formamide (ca. 108) compared with that of water (ca. 80) make it an interesting reactant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> for microwave-assisted and flow chemistry studies. In the past decade, microwave has been explored for accelerating biopolymer transformations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, while little attention has been given to upgrading small biomass-derived platform molecules.</p><p id="Par5">Aldehydes, ketones and carboxylic acids in diverse structures are available from lignocellulosic biomass via thermal or catalytic processes, while those carbonyl compounds, especially furanic aldehydes are seldom studied for amination due to the easy furan-ring opening reaction and the active &#x02013;CHO randomly vulnerable to amino species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. In previous reports, the use of appropriate metal catalysts is a prerequisite for efficient reductive amination, typically via two reaction routes, including initial reduction to alcohols followed by amination or first amination to give imines coupled with subsequent hydrogenation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Leuckart-type reactions are a classical approach to produce N-formylated compounds in moderate selectivity under conventional heating conditions, but due to uncontrollable amination levels, and the employed substrates, they are typically limited to petroleum-based and relatively stable aldehydes or ketones, apart from necessary long reaction times<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. The obtained products are generally restricted to bear C<sub>1</sub> or multiple common substituents, and the involved reaction mechanism is ambiguous<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Herein, we report an efficient solvent-free protocol for selectively controlling different levels of amination of pentose-derivable furfural (FUR) using formamide (AM) and formic acid (FA) or ammonium formate (AMF) reactants under rapid heating conditions offered by microwave irradiation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Presence of the formyl species (N-formyl carbinolamine, N-formyl imine, and <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02019;-(furan-2-ylmethylene)diformamide (FDFAM)), originating from AM/FA/AMF reactants, plays key roles in forming nitrogen-containing products at specific levels. The protocol can be extended to series of other bio-based carboxides including sugars to give moderate to nearly quantitative yields of primary amines with equivalent methyl formate (HCOOMe) by post-treatment mild methanolysis. The catalytic system is applicable to efficient synthesis of N-formyl imides for producing combination compounds, polymer-free monomers or heterocyclic compounds from aldehydes, ketones, carboxylic acids, or their mixtures (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We elucidate reaction pathways of in situ generated N-formyl species with kinetic and control experiments, deuterium isotope labeling reactions, and density functional theory (DFT) calculations.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic of selective production of amines, formamides and N-formylimides. FUR: furfural, FDFAM: <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02019;-(furan-2-ylmethylene)diformamide, <bold>1</bold>: <italic>N</italic>-(furan-2-ylmethyl)formamide, <bold>2</bold>: <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-bis(furan-2-ylmethyl)formamide, <bold>3</bold>: tris(furan-2-ylmethyl)amine, <bold>4</bold>: furfurylamine, <bold>5</bold>: bis(furan-2-ylmethyl)amine</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e525"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Mono-substitution of N-formamide</title><p id="Par6">Our study began with the microwave-assisted amination of furfural with formamide (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) that shows product yields for several reaction conditions. <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR spectra of major isolated formamides <bold>1</bold> and <bold>2</bold> are provided (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). In absence of FA, only 3% yield of <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02019;-(furan-2-ylmethylene)diformamide (FDFAM) with &#x0003c;5% FUR conversion was obtained at 160&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in 10&#x02009;min (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 1). Elevation of reaction temperature to 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C or use of a solid acid catalyst (Amberlyst-15) gave an increase in FDFAM yield (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, entries 1&#x02013;2), but neither <bold>1</bold> nor <bold>2</bold> was formed due to the lack of a hydrogen source. Instead, addition of FA significantly promoted the initial amination reaction, exclusively giving secondary amide <bold>1</bold> in 92% yield (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 2) without high extent of further amination with FUR to tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> (only 5% yield) at complete FUR conversion. This implies that FA is an excellent H-donor apart from acting as an acidic species in the cascade reaction. To elucidate whether diformamide FDFAM is a byproduct or intermediate for formation of <bold>1</bold>, a time-course study at different reaction temperatures from 120 &#x000b0;C&#x000a0;to 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C was conducted (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). At 120&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, moderate FDFAM yields of 65% and 67% were obtained after 10&#x000a0;min and 15&#x02009;min, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 3). Although FUR was not completely converted even after 30&#x02009;min at 120&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3a</xref>), FDFAM was gradually consumed to afford <bold>1</bold> (up to 32%). When reaction temperature was raised to 140&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, no more than 50% yield of FDFAM with a higher yield of product <bold>1</bold> (65%) was observed after 15&#x02009;min (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3b</xref>), while after reaching the maximum value (92%) at 160&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, a decrease in the yield of <bold>1</bold> was detected by prolonging reaction time from 10&#x000a0;min to 15&#x02009;min (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3c</xref>). These results (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>) show that the amination is a temperature-dependent process with FDFAM as a key intermediate, which is in accord with the modeled reaction rate constants (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). At 180 &#x000b0;C&#x000a0;and 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, complete FUR conversion occurred in 3&#x000a0;min and 2&#x02009;min, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 4). However, tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> was more prone to be formed instead of secondary amide <bold>1</bold> especially for extended reaction times (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3d, e</xref>). Notably, the mass balance (carbon basis) for all tested reaction systems was no less than 94% and the co-products were mainly FDFAM and tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> besides product <bold>1</bold> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entries 1&#x02013;4; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), and tertiary amine <bold>4</bold> with some unknown products being generated at 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C after long reaction times (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>). These results hint that the presence of the N-formyl group, originating from either formamide or formic acid, can stabilize <bold>1</bold> or <bold>2</bold> at relatively harsh conditions, which is well-supported by the lower reactivity that <bold>1</bold> displays in formic acid - formamide mixtures over that in its neat state at conditions of 160&#x02009;&#x000b0;C under microwave irradiation (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Microwave-assisted amination of furfural (FUR)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Entry</th><th colspan="4">Reactant (mmol)</th><th rowspan="2">Temp. (&#x000b0;C)</th><th rowspan="2">Time&#x000a0;(min)</th><th rowspan="2">FUR&#x000a0;Conv. (%)</th><th colspan="4">Product Yield (%)</th><th rowspan="2">CB&#x000a0;(%)</th></tr><tr><th>FUR</th><th>FA</th><th>AM</th><th>AMF</th><th>FDFAM</th><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>160</td><td>10</td><td>&#x0003c;5</td><td>3</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>99</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>160</td><td>10</td><td>100</td><td>&#x0003c;1</td><td>92</td><td>5</td><td>0</td><td>98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">3</td><td rowspan="2">2</td><td rowspan="2">6</td><td rowspan="2">10</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="2">120</td><td>10</td><td>81</td><td>65</td><td>9</td><td>&#x0003c;2</td><td>0</td><td>95</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>92</td><td>67</td><td>17</td><td>2</td><td>0</td><td>94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">4</td><td rowspan="2">2</td><td rowspan="2">6</td><td rowspan="2">10</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02013;</td><td>180</td><td>3</td><td>99</td><td>2</td><td>78</td><td>17</td><td>0</td><td>98</td></tr><tr><td>200</td><td>2</td><td>100</td><td>&#x0003c;1</td><td>61</td><td>35</td><td>1</td><td>97</td></tr><tr><td>5<sup>a</sup></td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>180</td><td>60</td><td>83</td><td>&#x0003c;1</td><td>69</td><td>10</td><td>0</td><td>97</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>12</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>180</td><td>3</td><td>100</td><td>&#x0003c;1</td><td>98</td><td>&#x0003c;1</td><td>0</td><td>&#x0003e;99</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>2</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>200</td><td>3</td><td>97</td><td>&#x0003c;1</td><td>12</td><td>83</td><td>0</td><td>98</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12</td><td>195</td><td>5</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td>&#x0003c;2</td><td>2</td><td>88</td><td>92</td></tr><tr><td>9<sup>b</sup></td><td>2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12</td><td>195</td><td>5</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td>6</td><td>3</td><td>80</td><td>89</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>10</td><td>100</td><td>0</td><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>66</td><td>88</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Reactants formic acid (FA), formamide (AM) and ammonium formate (AMF)</p><p><sup>a</sup>Oil bath</p><p><sup>b</sup>0.5&#x02009;mmol water added to reactant solution (5&#x02009;wt% H<sub>2</sub>O)</p><p>FDFAM: <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02019;-(Furan-2-ylmethylene)diformamide, <bold>1</bold>: <italic>N</italic>-(furan-2-ylmethyl)formamide, <bold>2</bold>: <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>&#x02019;-bis(furan-2-ylmethyl)formamide, <bold>3</bold>: tris(furan-2-ylmethyl)amine), CB: carbon balance</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Mode of heating</title><p id="Par7">Conventional oil-bath heating was examined for furfural amination with formamide under identical reaction conditions, while hours were required for complete conversion of furfural at reaction temperatures of (120 to 160)&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. A temperature of 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C was adopted for comparing product distribution and reaction rates of different heating modes (oil-bath and microwave). Based on the reaction pathways for amination of furfural with formamide and formic acid, rate data in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref> were fitted assuming pseudo first-order reaction kinetics, with rate constants (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>&#x02013;<italic>k</italic><sub>5</sub>) for each step being collected in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>. Compared with microwave-assisted heating at 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for complete conversion of furfural (3&#x02009;min; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 4), only 83% furfural conversion was attained with oil-bath heating for 60&#x02009;min (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 5). The ratio of kinetic rate constants (<inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_i^{\mathrm{{mw}}}/k_i^{\mathrm{{oil}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02215;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) were much larger for each reaction step as illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>, which means that microwave facilitates C&#x02013;N bond formation between furfural and formamide (<inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_1^{\mathrm{{mw}}}/k_1^{\mathrm{{oil}}} = 43.1$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02215;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>43.1</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) or product <bold>1</bold> (<inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_3^{\mathrm{{mw}}}/k_3^{\mathrm{{oil}}} = 22.5$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02215;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.5</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) that contains the amino group, while it has little effect in the reduction step (<inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_2^{\mathrm{{mw}}}/k_2^{\mathrm{{oil}}} = 2.4$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02215;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.4</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). The relatively high polarity of formamide estimated by its log<italic>P</italic> value (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>) means that microwave energy most likely has a greater effect on formamide than formic acid. Microwave heating can promote side reactions derived from furfural (<inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_4^{\mathrm{{mw}}}/k_4^{\mathrm{{oil}}} = 11$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02215;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and tertiary amide <bold>3</bold> (<inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$k_5^{\mathrm{{mw}}}/k_5^{\mathrm{{oil}}} = 7.3$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02215;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.3</mml:mn></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) as in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>, however, these effects can be minimized with short reaction times (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a, b</xref>), thus showing the great potential of selective production of either product <bold>1</bold> or <bold>2</bold> from furfural under microwave irradiation.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Amination of furfural (FUR) with formamide (AM). Time course for reactants heated by <bold>a</bold> microwave and <bold>b</bold> oil bath modeled with the assumption of pseudo-first-order reaction kinetics (black diamond, FUR; gray triangle, FDFAM; red circle, <bold>1</bold>; blue triangle, <bold>2</bold>; brown triangle, Other products). Rate constants of <bold>c</bold> microwave (<inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathop {k}\nolimits_{{i}}^{{\mathrm{mw}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo> k</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and oil heating (<inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathop {k}\nolimits_{{i}}^{{\mathrm{oil}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo> k</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and ratios (<inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathop {k}\nolimits_{{i}}^{{\mathrm{mw}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo> k</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">mw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>/<inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mathop {k}\nolimits_{{i}}^{{\mathrm{oil}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo> k</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">oil</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) for cascade reactions (<italic>i</italic>) at reaction conditions (2&#x02009;mmol FUR, 6&#x02009;mmol FA, 10&#x02009;mmol AM, 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C). Product distributions for <bold>d</bold> furfural/formic acid/formamide molar ratios with FUR set at reaction conditions (2&#x02009;mmol FUR, 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 3&#x02009;min). Error bars with standard deviation (<italic>&#x003c3;</italic>) of &#x02264;4.3%</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1589"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">Temperature-time plots of reaction mixture and reactants clearly indicate the promotional role of formamide on heating rate (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). Although microwave heating effects are correlated with variable parameters (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>), the heating ramp is controllable over a wide range<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, which is helpful for studying reaction selectivity with heating rate. In this regard, flow chemistry with the proposed protocol, as a rapid and regulatable heating approach could be a promising research topic for synthesis of nitrogen-containing compounds.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Control of selectivity</title><p id="Par9">To demonstrate control of selectivity towards the secondary amide <bold>1</bold> or tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> from furfural amination, it was necessary to examine the FUR/FA/AM molar ratio. Gratifyingly, <bold>1</bold> was predominately formed in quantitative yields of 98% at 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in 3&#x02009;min (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 6), by slightly increasing molar content of AM from 10&#x02009;mmol (entry 4) to 12&#x02009;mmol (entry 6). The reaction process was monitored by recording GC-MS spectra of the liquid mixture (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13</xref>) for different time intervals (up to 3&#x02009;min), in which the high-purity of final solutions after reaction without post-treatment was confirmed by <sup>13</sup>C NMR (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14</xref>). In previous literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, alkylation of primary amines can occur by removal of NH<sub>3</sub> to yield secondary or tertiary amines. In the present system, this type of reaction seems to take place when furfurylamine and FA were used as starting materials (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">15</xref>) giving <bold>2</bold> in yields of ca. 10% at 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min reaction time as illustrated by GC-MS (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">16</xref>), and secondary amide <bold>1</bold> was formed as the primary product (ca. 85%) by N-formylation of furfurylamine with FA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. In contrast, almost no tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> was formed when secondary amide <bold>1</bold> was used as substrate with AM and FA (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17</xref>), which means that the free amino group in furfurylamine is more vulnerable to react with itself and an active species (e.g., FA), as compared with <bold>1</bold> that contains the N-formyl group. To elucidate the activity of the N-formyl species in the FUR amination, product distributions were further studied by adjusting FUR/FA/AM molar ratios and using relatively high temperatures (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). Complete FUR conversion with approximately equivalent secondary amide <bold>1</bold> (42%) and tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> (52%) was observed at a FUR/FA/AM molar ratio of 2:6:10, while a decrease of AM to 4&#x02009;mmol or FA to 2&#x02009;mmol resulted in <bold>2</bold> (67%) or <bold>1</bold> (43%) being the main product, respectively (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, entries 3&#x02013;5). Relatively lower FUR conversion (76%), but much higher FDFAM yield of 16%, was observed for a FUR/FA/AM ratio of 2:2:10, indicating that FA acts as both acid catalyst and H-donor in the cascade reactions. A relatively larger amount of both FA and AM was able to afford 100% FUR conversion with ca. 99% mass balance at FUR/FA/AM molar ratios of 2:10:15 and 2:15:15 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). As expected, relatively high yields of tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> (83%) could be obtained by reducing the amount of AM (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 7), that probably decreased the amount of stabilized secondary amide <bold>1</bold> under microwave irradiation. The increased yield of <bold>2</bold> could also be due to the presence of relatively higher amounts of FA that allow FA to act as an acid catalyst to activate <bold>1</bold> for further amination. This speculation is supported by the significantly inferior reactivity between <bold>1</bold> and FUR without FA (&#x0003c;3% yield of <bold>2</bold>) or in presence of Et<sub>3</sub>N equivalent to FA (ca. 15% yield of <bold>2</bold>) under otherwise identical reaction conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Role of N-formyl species in intermediate stabilization</title><p id="Par10">Taking into account the effect that the N-formyl species has on product selectivity, ammonium formate (AMF), which is a promising ammonia precursor that forms in situ during thermal decomposition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>, was chosen for microwave-assisted amination of furfural, since AMF can donate hydrogen by formate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the tertiary amine <bold>3</bold> was found to be the primary product with lesser amounts of the amides <bold>1</bold> (&#x0003c;5%) and <bold>2</bold> (&#x0003c;8%) at (185 to 205)&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>), and a maximum yield of tertiary amine <bold>3</bold> (88%) was obtained at 195&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in 5&#x02009;min (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 8). Analysis of reaction mixtures with GC after different time intervals at 195&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">19</xref>) confirmed that NH<sub>3</sub> was present in large quantities even after 30&#x02009;min reaction time, while only low amounts of formamide were formed throughout the reaction period. The higher polarity of ammonium formate compared with that of formamide (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>) may be positively correlated with energy adsorption efficiency under microwave irradiation and probably allows for rapid decomposition to generate NH<sub>3</sub>, as compared with formation of formamide by dehydration. As a result, absence of primary and secondary amines, <bold>4</bold> and <bold>5</bold>, in the tested GC spectra was most likely the result of rapid transformation of these species into tertiary amine <bold>3</bold> via two successive amination reactions (major) or into secondary and tertiary amides, <bold>1</bold> and <bold>2</bold> via N-formylation (minor) in the heating system (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">20</xref>). By increasing the molar ratio of FUR to AMF from 1:12 to 12:12, the yield of tertiary amine <bold>3</bold> was significantly reduced from 88% to 57% while both secondary and tertiary amides, <bold>1</bold> and <bold>2</bold>, were formed in almost constant yields (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">21</xref>). These unusual results highlight the significance of AMF on the promotion of three consecutive amination reaction processes to produce the tertiary amine <bold>3</bold> under microwave irradiation. We speculated that neither AM nor FA is formed to a large extent, which could be verified implicitly by additional experiments that showed enhanced selectivity toward secondary and tertiary amides <bold>1</bold> and <bold>2</bold> after addition of (5 to 25) wt% water that promoted formation of FA through hydrolysis of AMF (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entry 8 versus entry 9; Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">22</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">23</xref>). Formation of tertiary amine <bold>3</bold> in high yield and selectivity can be attributed to the lack of N-formyl stabilizing species in the sequence of aminations. Presence of excess water would result in side reactions, such as furan-ring opening and condensation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> to give unknown byproducts or insoluble humins, thus lowering the carbon balance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Reaction mechanism</title><p id="Par11">In the catalytic mechanism, two routes are typically considered for reductive amination of carbonyl compounds to amines (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">24</xref>), including initial reduction to alcohols followed by amination or first amination to give imines coupled with subsequent hydrogenation or hydrogenolysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>. In the present reaction system of FUR amination with AM and FA, gem-diamine (FDFAM), as discussed vide supra, was found to be the key intermediate that is accessible to secondary amide <bold>1</bold> after reduction with FA (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25</xref>). However, neither imine nor carbinolamine intermediates were detected by GC-MS for tested reaction systems at temperatures up to 200&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for variable reaction times (even &#x0003c;30&#x02009;s). Considering the relatively low stability of these intermediates, <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR, without high-temperature vaporization of samples during the analytical process, seemed to be a better tool for investigating reaction pathways. Several control experiments were designed, and the resulting spectra are shown in Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">31</xref>. When FUR, AM, and FA were used as starting materials under reaction conditions of 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02009;min reaction time (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">26a</xref>), secondary amide <bold>1</bold> was found to be the major product with a certain amount of water (2.4 ppm) being formed with a fair amount (6.8 ppm) of AM residual. Similarly, only the sole secondary amide <bold>1</bold> was generated even in replacement of FUR and AM with furfuryl alcohol and furfurylamine, respectively (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">26d</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">27</xref>), demonstrating the high reactivity between furfurylamine <bold>4</bold> and FA and the good stability of secondary amide <bold>1</bold> to resist attack of the active primary amino group in furfurylamine. In contrast, a mixture of the secondary amide <bold>1</bold> (major) and tertiary amide <bold>2</bold> (minor) were observed using FUR, furfurylamine, and FA as substrates (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">26c</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">30</xref>), giving further evidence for the superior reactivity between furfurylamine and FA to that between furfurylamine and FUR, as well as confirming the pronounced promotional role of microwave on C&#x02013;N bond formation rather than on the reduction step as shown previously in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>. Moreover, furfuryl alcohol was stable in AM (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">26f</xref>), while it was degraded to levulinic acid in high degrees after addition of FA (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">26b</xref>), indicating the full capability of FA in the cleavage of C&#x02013;O or C&#x02013;N bond during reduction.</p><p id="Par12">In this cascade reaction process, FA can be proposed to act as not only H-donor but also as an acidic catalyst. <sup>1</sup>H&#x02013;<sup>13</sup>C NMR HSQC (DEPT) spectra of FUR amination with AM using normal and deuterium-labeled FA (DCOOD) explicitly proved the incorporation of D from FA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">32</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">33</xref>), and moreover, the presence of unconverted FUR in the reaction system using deuterium-labeled FA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) indicated its relatively slower reaction rate compared with that using undeuterated FA. A primary kinetic isotope effect (<italic>k</italic><sub>H</sub>/<italic>k</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.8) was observed, which is higher than typical transfer hydrogenation or dehydrogenation of FA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>, clearly affirming the additional role of FA possibly as an acid in the reaction process. Mass spectra showed that secondary amide <bold>1</bold> was formed with +1 and +2 mass shifts besides 125 (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic>, amu) in comparable intensity using DCOOD from that using HCOOH (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">34</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">35</xref>). This manifests that the N-formyl imine (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;2) derived from carbinolamine (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;1) along with FDFAM (<italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;1) could all be intermediates in the formation of secondary amide <bold>1</bold> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">36</xref>). Based on the above results, despite being unable to directly trace the N-formyl imine or carbinolamine intermediate, the reaction pathways could thus be elucidated (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25</xref>). With a relatively high thermal stability under microwave irradiation, FDFAM is rapidly produced in detectable amounts from in situ formed N-formyl imine or carbinolamine intermediates by addition of AM, and all of these species are further converted to secondary amide <bold>1</bold> through hydrogenation (for imine) or hydrogenolysis (for carbinolamine and FDFAM). With respect to further transformation of <bold>1</bold> to tertiary amide <bold>2</bold>, neither imine nor gem-diamine was formed as intermediate, except for the secondary carbinolamine (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25</xref>). In this case, an appropriate relative ratio of furfural to AM for generation of the carbinolamine, as well as an optimal reaction temperature for its hydrogenolysis other than degradation by FA should be the key factor for selectivity control, which is in good agreement with the obtained results (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, entries 6&#x02013;7). In amination of furfural and AMF, a certain amount of AM was observed after reaction (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">26e</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">31</xref>), showing the occurrence of AMF dehydration besides the dominant route to thermal decomposition of AMF into ammonia and FA (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">25</xref>). Due to limited amounts of FA forming in situ during the reaction, primary and secondary amines, <bold>4</bold> and <bold>5</bold>, seemed to be major intermediates that rapidly led to tertiary amine <bold>3</bold>. The nearly changeless yields of secondary and tertiary amides, <bold>1</bold> and <bold>2</bold>, at different reaction time courses (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>) may be closely related to their high stability in AM, while it may possibly testify to the superior activity of FA in the reduction of imine to that of formylimine.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><sup>1</sup>H-<sup>13</sup>C NMR HSQC (DEPT) spectra of microwave-assisted amination of FUR and AM. Panel <bold>a</bold> normal FA and Panel <bold>b</bold> deuterium-labeled FA (red color: CH or CH<sub>3</sub>, green color: CH<sub>2</sub>); Reaction conditions: 2&#x02009;mmol FUR, 6&#x02009;mmol FA, 12&#x02009;mmol AM, 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 3&#x02009;min</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e2058"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>DFT calculations</title><p id="Par13">Considering the significance of primary amines and relative simplicity of the product distribution, DFT calculations [T&#x02009;=&#x02009;180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, B3LYP/6-311+G(2s,2p)] were performed to study the reaction mechanism. In the reductive amination of FUR and NH<sub>3</sub> to furfuryl amine in the presence of metal catalyst, a furfurylimine (furan-2-ylmethanimine) has been proposed to be a key intermediate in the reaction mechanism, although it could not be detected<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. However, in the absence of metal catalyst, computational calculations disclose that high energy barriers for the transition state (<bold>TS</bold>, as high as 188&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) exist in the initial formation of the furfurylimine from FUR and NH<sub>3</sub> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">37</xref>). In sharp contrast, the activation energy for amination of FUR and AM in presence or absence of FA is relatively lower or higher (152 kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>&#x000a0;or 245&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">37</xref>), clearly demonstrating the promotional role of FA during the initial C-N bond formation and the stabilizing effect of N-formyl species in the reaction system, respectively.</p><p id="Par14">Based on the obtained experimental results, gem-diamine FDFAM, N-formyl imine and N-formyl carbinolamine are key species in the quasi-catalytic amination pathway. To elucidate the underlying mechanism, different paths proceeding through these species were devised giving the obtained computational free energy profiles (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">38</xref>). The target product was designated as <italic>N</italic>-(furan-2-ylmethyl)formamide (<bold>1</bold>) starting from FUR and AM with FA. Initially, C-N bond formation between FUR and AM occurs via direct addition to give corresponding N-formyl carbinolamine, and free energy of <bold>TS1</bold> as 152&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, in agreement with the experimentally observed activation energy 148&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> under oil-heating conditions (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">39</xref>). The slightly higher reaction barrier is consistent with the relatively high temperatures (e.g., 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) that allow the reaction to proceed smoothly. With FA acting as an acid, the formed N-formyl carbinolamine can be further transformed into N-formyl imine by dehydration via <bold>TS2</bold> (&#x02206;<italic>G</italic><sup>#</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;72&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). When FA is absent for the same dehydration step, much higher activation energy (194&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">37c</xref>) was required, explicitly clarifying the acidic role of FA. Afterwards, the formed imine is capable of being further converted to <bold>1</bold> using FA as H-donor sequentially overcoming <bold>TS3</bold> via <bold>IM1</bold>. In view of the relatively low reaction barrier (&#x02206;<italic>G</italic><sup>#</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;62&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> versus 113&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), product <bold>1</bold> is preferably formed from N-formyl carbinolamine than from FDFAM via <bold>TS5</bold>. However, sole FDFAM with relatively low free energy (15&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) generated in situ from N-formyl imine with AM and FA through <bold>TS4</bold> (&#x02206;<italic>G</italic><sup>#</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;104&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) accounts for the observation of certain quantities of FDFAM during the initial reaction stage consistent with the experimental results. In other words, N-formyl carbinolamine seems to be involved in the predominant reaction route, while FDFAM as a key intermediate most likely acts to sustain high carbon balances observed experimentally by stabilizing reaction species.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Computed free energy profiles for amination of FUR and AM using FA to product <bold>1</bold>. TS: transition state, IM: intermediate. Conditions and basis set: [<italic>T</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, B3LYP/6-311+G(2s,2p)]. Values in parentheses are free energies (kJ mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) based with respect to the starting energy of the three separated reactants FUR, AM, and FA</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2207"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">In the progress of the reaction, proton-transfer interactions between AM and FA may also contribute to the superior reactivity of the catalytic system (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">40</xref>); microwave effects were not considered in the DFT calculations. Initial C&#x02013;N bond formation was observed to be the rate-determining reaction step (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), while the medium reaction energy barrier (152&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) could be overcome by performing the amination at relatively high temperatures, which is in accordance with the oil-heating experimental activation energy (148&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). However, under microwave irradiation, the experimental activation energy was found to be <italic>ca</italic>. 50&#x02009;kJ&#x02009;mol<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, clearly elaborating the promotional role of microwave heating in the facilitation of C&#x02013;N bond formation. With addition of SiC powder into reaction mixtures of FUR, AM, and FA (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>), the reaction rate can be further accelerated despite forming a certain amount of carbon, which also affirms the positive role of rapid heating in the reaction process. When an oil bath was used as the heating source, the sluggish heating and cooling steps might impede amination to effectively take place. Nevertheless, the key FDFAM species could be clearly identified, thus confirming the amination chemistry illustrated in context.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Extension of substrate scope</title><p id="Par16">Conventional preparation of primary amines from ammonia generally involves unexpected reaction pathways such that metallic materials with specific catalytic functionalities are required to control product selectivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>. Here, furfurylamine <bold>4</bold> was found to be synthesized in good yields (94%) by simple treatment of secondary amide <bold>1</bold> in methanol with Cs<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, and secondary amine <bold>5</bold> could be obtained in 96% yields from tertiary amide <bold>2</bold>. Encouraged by the outstanding selectivity shown in the previous trials, a number of biomass-derived carboxides were employed as starting materials to investigate the protocol generality, especially for selective production of primary amines (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). As expected, all aldehydes and ketones examined could be efficiently converted into primary amines in mostly quantitative yields through the corresponding formamides (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, entries 1&#x02013;11). Although some aliphatic ketones or aldehydes containing active substituent groups (e.g., &#x02013;OH) gave relatively inferior yields of formamides related to side reactions that occur under microwave irradiation (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, entries 6, 8), the selectivity towards primary amines was still comparable with the others.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Selective production of formamides and primary amines from carboxides</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Figa_HTML.gif" id="d29e2291"/>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Reaction conditions: 2&#x02009;mmol substrate, 6&#x02009;mmol FA, 12&#x02009;mmol AM, 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (microwave), 3&#x02009;min</p><p><sup>b</sup>Reaction conditions: 1&#x02009;mmol formamide, 2&#x02009;mL methanol, 3&#x02009;mmol Cs<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (oil bath), 1&#x02009;h; Co-product is the equivalent methyl formate</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par17">FUR and 5-hydroxymethylfurfural (HMF) are two important platform molecules derived from pentose and hexose saccharides, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>, both of which could be subjected to amination (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, entries 1 and 2). Besides formamide, <italic>N</italic>-methylformamide and <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylformamide were able to be used as nitrogen sources, affording homologous <italic>N</italic>-methyl-furfuryl and <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethyl-furfuryl amines (Table 3,&#x000a0;entries 4&#x02013;6). However, presence of the hydroxy group in HMF, while being inert for amination, causes serious side reactions like condensation or polymerization to give insoluble black humins, especially after long reaction times.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Synthesis of furfuryl amines from furfuryl aldehydes or sugars with formamides</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="7">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Figb_HTML.gif" id="d29e2360"/>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2">Entry</th><th colspan="4">Substrate</th><th rowspan="2">Time (min)</th><th rowspan="2">Yield (%)</th></tr><tr><th>Sugar</th><th>R</th><th>R<sup>1</sup></th><th>R<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>3</td><td>92</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>HOCH<sub>2</sub></td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>2</td><td>63</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>H</td><td>CH<sub>3</sub></td><td>H</td><td>4</td><td>90</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>HOCH<sub>2</sub></td><td>CH<sub>3</sub></td><td>H</td><td>3</td><td>61</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>H</td><td>CH<sub>3</sub></td><td>CH<sub>3</sub></td><td>5</td><td>85</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>HOCH<sub>2</sub></td><td>CH<sub>3</sub></td><td>CH<sub>3</sub></td><td>3.5</td><td>56</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>Xylose</td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>10</td><td>83</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>Fructose</td><td>HOCH<sub>2</sub></td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>6</td><td>74</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>Glucose</td><td>HOCH<sub>2</sub></td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>10</td><td>45</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>Sucrose</td><td>HOCH<sub>2</sub></td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>7.5</td><td>62</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>Cellobiose</td><td>HOCH<sub>2</sub></td><td>H</td><td>H</td><td>10</td><td>26</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Reaction conditions: 2&#x02009;mmol furyl aldehyde or 1&#x02009;mmol sugar, 12 mmol N-formyl compound, 6&#x02009;mmol FA, 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (microwave); When R<sup>1</sup> and/or R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;H, 2&#x02009;mL methanol with 6&#x02009;mmol Cs<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> was added after the reaction and microwave-treated at 120&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4&#x02009;min</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">Monosaccharides (xylose, fructose, and glucose) and disaccharides (sucrose and cellobiose) can be upgraded via the amination chemistry (Table 3,&#x000a0;entries 7&#x02013;10). Cellulose is not directly applicable to the amination chemistry, while its oxidized counterpart (dialdehyde cellulose) could be aminated to a great extent (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">41</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">42</xref>). These results demonstrate the feasibility and versatility of the quasi-catalytic amination chemistry for selective production of diverse nitrogen-containing compounds from renewable biomass resources.</p><p id="Par19">N-formylimides are biologically active moieties and are versatile building blocks in organic synthesis and they are typically synthesized by N-formylation of amides or lactams employing sophisticated reagents as catalysts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. Herein, direct conversion of alkyl and aryl carboxylic acids <bold>6</bold> to corresponding N-formylimides <bold>7</bold> with moderate yields (61% to 84%) could be achieved using the quasi-catalytic amination chemistry within (4 to&#x000a0;7) min (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The reaction system was compatible with different dicarbonyl species, whereas carboxylic acid, aldehyde, and/or ketone groups were able to be simultaneously aminated into a wide range of nitrogen-containing compounds with N-formylimides and/or N-formamide moieties. Appropriate amounts of FA were found to be essential in obtaining optimal product yields, otherwise the co-products would be formed by partial or complete removal of N-formyl species due to the presence of acidic carboxylic group in the substrates (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">43</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Synthesis of N-formylimides and N-formamide moieties (<bold>7</bold>) from AM and carbonyl compound (<bold>6</bold>). Reaction conditions: 1&#x02009;mmol <bold>6</bold>, 12&#x02009;mmol AM, 12&#x02009;mmol FA, 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (microwave)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2723"/></fig></p><p id="Par20">In the reaction systems (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), neither cross-polymerized nor self-polymerized products were detected in high extents, which is ascribed to the stabilizing effect of the N-formyl species, as well as to steric hindrance effects (e.g., para-position for aromatic rings, trans-configuration for double bonds). Interestingly, both saturated linearly alkyl and ortho-substituted aromatic dicarbonyl compounds (<bold>8</bold>) are prone to undergo self-cyclization through two sequential amination processes after a relatively long reaction time (5&#x02013;12&#x02009;min), giving N-formyl cyclamines (<bold>9</bold>), N-formyl lactams (<bold>10</bold>), or N-formyl cyclic imides (<bold>11</bold>) in moderate to good yields (68&#x02013;93%), which is closely dependent on the type of starting carbonyl species (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). A poor yield of <bold>9d</bold> (31%) obtained from 2,5-hexanedione further indicated steric hindrance effects in the secondary amination. In this regard, an appropriate choice of substrates with desired structures and functionalities has great potential for selective synthesis of nitrogen-containing scaffolds.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Synthesis of N-formyl cyclamines (<bold>9</bold>), N-formyl lactams (<bold>10</bold>), or N-formyl cyclic imides (<bold>11</bold>) from AM and dicarbonyl compounds (<bold>8</bold>). Reaction conditions: 1&#x02009;mmol <bold>8</bold>, 8&#x02009;mmol AM, 12&#x02009;mmol FA, 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (microwave)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2771"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">Apart from the two-component amination between mono-carbonyl or dicarbonyl compounds and AM, a three-component synthetic route was examined, where carboxylic acid, aldehyde/ketone, and AM were used as substrates (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Both alkyl and aromatic carboxylic acids are subjected to the three-component amination with AM and aldehydes or ketones, affording N-formylimides in moderate yields (56&#x02013;87%). These results clearly demonstrate the versatility of the quasi-catalytic amination chemistry for controllable synthesis of formamides, amines, and imides.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Three-component synthesis of N-formylimides from carboxylic acids, AM, and aldehydes/ketones</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="6">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_Figc_HTML.gif" id="d29e2797"/>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2">Entry</th><th colspan="3">Substrate</th><th rowspan="2">Time (min)</th><th rowspan="2">Yield (%)</th></tr><tr><th>R</th><th>R<sup>1</sup></th><th>R<sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>n-propyl</td><td>methyl</td><td>isobutyl</td><td>&#x000a0;8</td><td>&#x000a0;75</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>n-butyl</td><td>methyl</td><td>isobutyl</td><td>10</td><td>78</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>phenyl</td><td>methyl</td><td>isobutyl</td><td>10</td><td>56</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>n-propyl</td><td>methyl</td><td>phenyl</td><td>6</td><td>72</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>n-butyl</td><td>methyl</td><td>phenyl</td><td>6</td><td>68</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>phenyl</td><td>methyl</td><td>phenyl</td><td>10</td><td>63</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>n-propyl</td><td>H</td><td>phenyl</td><td>5</td><td>87</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>n-butyl</td><td>H</td><td>phenyl</td><td>5</td><td>84</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>phenyl</td><td>H</td><td>phenyl</td><td>7</td><td>80</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>n-propyl</td><td>H</td><td>furyl</td><td>4</td><td>75</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>n-butyl</td><td>H</td><td>furyl</td><td>4</td><td>66</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>phenyl</td><td>H</td><td>furyl</td><td>5</td><td>71</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Reaction conditions: 1&#x02009;mmol carboxylic acid, 10&#x02009;mmol AM, 1&#x02009;mmol aldehyde or ketone, 12&#x02009;mmol FA, 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C (microwave)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par22">We developed a simple two-step protocol for selective synthesis of primary amines that provides quantitative yields from many types of chemical and bio-related substrates. Not only primary amines, but also secondary and tertiary amides, tertiary amines and imides can be selectively and rapidly produced in several minutes under rapid heating with microwave irradiation by regulating reactant ratio, ammonia precursor, substrate type, and content or releasing mode of hydrogen species. The N-formyl quasi-catalytic species stabilizes formamides, thus affording superior selectivity toward secondary and tertiary amides, while the tertiary amine is most likely formed via reductive amination of furfural with ammonia formed in situ from thermal decomposition of ammonium formate where N-formyl species exists in relatively low amounts during reaction. Kinetic studies show that the C&#x02013;N bond formation other than reduction step can be significantly enhanced under rapid heating with microwave irradiation compared with conventional convective heating. DFT calculations confirm that the initial C&#x02013;N bond formation has a relatively high energy barrier in the rate-determining reaction step. Formic acid acts as both acid catalyst and H-donor, which promotes dehydration, selective C&#x02013;N bond formation and its subsequent reduction. The protocol can be potentially applied in industrial settings and moreover, control of C&#x02013;N bond formation processes with microwave, flow chemistry or rapid-heating approaches may facilitate selective establishment of production and synthesis methods for nitrogen-containing structures.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Reaction procedures</title><p id="Par23">A typical procedure for the microwave-assisted experiments was as follows. Reactants, furfural (FUR, 2&#x02009;mmol) or other carbonyl compounds (1 or 2&#x02009;mmol) and a given amount of formic acid (FA) and formamide (AM) or ammonium formate (AMF) were loaded into a thick-walled (wall thickness of 1.2&#x02009;mm, inside diameter of 13.6&#x02009;mm) Pyrex glass tube (10&#x02009;mL, maximum pressure &#x0003c;10&#x02009;MPa, Taiatsu Techno. Corp., Japan). The tube was then mounted into an outer polycarbonate tube and sealed with two PEEK screw caps with special seal joints (Taiatsu Techno. Corp., Japan). A thermocouple was inserted into the reactor through a stainless steel sleeve (diameter in 1.5&#x02009;mm), which was used to control the temperature inside the reactor. Prior to conducting reaction, N<sub>2</sub> gas was employed to purge air inside the reactor for 3 times and finally set to 2&#x02009;MPa to suppress solution boiling. Vacuum was applied between the inner glass tube and the outer polycarbonate tube to reduce heat losses. All reactions were conducted using microwave heating apparatus (Shikoku Instrumentation Co. Ltd., Japan, model &#x003bc; Reactor, SMW-087, 2.45&#x02009;GHz, maximum power 700&#x02009;W)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Zero reaction time was defined as the point that the system attained the target reaction temperature. In the procedures, (12 to 40)&#x02009;s was required for heating with microwave irradiation from 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C to target temperatures of (120 to 200)&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The specific reaction temperature could be nicely kept by automatically real-time change of microwave power. After passing the desired reaction time, tap water was introduced into the jacket of the tube (by internal reduced pressure provided by a vacuum pump) to rapidly cool its contents (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">44</xref>) and to terminate the reaction. The cooled reaction tube was depressurized and its contents were diluted with THF (2&#x02009;mL) prior to sample analysis. Samples were analyzed with liquid chromatography using <italic>n</italic>-hexane/ethyl acetate (1:1, v/v) as mobile phase. Structures were confirmed by <sup>1</sup>H, <sup>13</sup>C NMR (JEOL-ECX 500 NMR spectrometer, CDCl<sub>3</sub>) and GC-MS (Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">53</xref>). NMR spectra of some representative formamide products (<bold>1</bold> and <bold>2</bold>) are shown in Supplementary Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par24">In the oil-bath experiments, a Teflon-lined stainless steel autoclave was used (inner volume 10&#x02009;mL), in which the target reaction temperatures were identical to those of the microwave-assisted experiments. Zero reaction time was defined as the point in which the autoclave was placed into an oil-bath that was preheated to 180&#x02009;&#x000b0;C or another specific temperature. After a given reaction time, the autoclave was taken out of the oil bath and immediately cooled-down to ambient temperature with tap-water. After cooling, the autoclave was opened and THF was added to the reacted mixture that was analyzed. Separate experiments were conducted and repeated 2&#x02013;3 times for each sample. The obtained conversions and yields are average of 2&#x02013;3 individual experiments, with standard deviation (<italic>&#x003c3;</italic>) in the range of 0.5&#x02013;4.3%, as given by error bars in appropriate figures.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Isotope-labeled experiments</title><p id="Par25">For the isotope-labeled studies, <sup>1</sup>H, <sup>13</sup>C, and <sup>1</sup>H&#x02013;<sup>13</sup>C HSQC NMR spectra of the reaction mixtures were used in the experiments at the given reaction conditions with either normal or deuterium reagents. Analyses were performed with deuterated solvents (THF-d<sub>8</sub> or CDCl<sub>3</sub>) on a JEOL-ECX 500 NMR spectrometer. GC-MS spectra for some of the liquid mixtures were measured to determine the incorporated D in the products.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Product analyses</title><p id="Par26">GC-MS (Agilent 6890N GC/5973 MS, Santa Clara, CA) was used to identify liquid products, intermediates and major by-products. GC-MS spectra of representative products are shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">40</xref>. Concentrations of organic acids (e.g., formic acid and levulinic acid) were determined with HPLC (LC-20A, Shimadzu, Kyoto) fitted with an Aminex HPX-87H column (Bio-Rad, Richmond, CA) and a refractive index (RI) detector. Quantitative analyses of the reaction mixtures were made with a GC (Agilent 7890B) with an HP-5 column (30&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.320&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) and a flame ionization detector with naphthalene as internal standard using standard curves (R<sup>2</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.995) made from commercial samples or the isolated products. In addition, <sup>1</sup>H NMR was also used for quantification of unpurified products in the reaction mixtures using 1,3,5-trimethoxybenzene as the internal standard.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Computational methods</title><p id="Par27">All DFT calculations were carried using the hybrid functional B3LYP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup> as implemented in Gaussian 09 D.01 software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. The all-electron 6-311+G(d,p) basis set was used for all atoms. The polarized continuum&#x000a0;model (PCM)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup> with standard parameters for water solvent (&#x003b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;78.3) was used to account for bulk solvent effects during geometry optimization, frequency analysis and searching of transition states. All relative energies discussed in this paper are referred to Gibbs energies considering the zero point energy (ZPE) correction at 453.15&#x02009;K. For comparison, free energies were re-calculated at the level of M06-2X/def2-TZVP, and the relevant free energy diagrams are provided in supplementary information (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">54</xref>). After cross-checking, the B3LYP functional provides closer representation of the experimental data compared with M06-2X, so that the B3LYP functional was assessed to be suitable to simulate the studied system. In addition, corresponding 3D figures and Cartesian coordinates are supplied in Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">55</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">58</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">Supplementary Data&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><sec id="Sec16"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_8577_MOESM3_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Data 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Journal peer review information</bold>
<italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks Tiefeng Wang, Raphael Wischert and the other anonymous reviewer for their contribution to the peer review of this work. Peer reports are available.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41467-019-08577-4.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work is financially supported by Nanjing Agricultural University (68Q-0603), International Postdoctoral Exchange Fellowship Program of China (20170026), Postdoctoral Science Foundation of China (2016M600422), and Jiangsu Postdoctoral Research Funding Plan (1601029A) for study at Tohoku University. We thank Chengjiang Fang (Guizhou University) for recording part of the NMR spectra, and also acknowledge the Research Center of Supercritical Fluid Technology (Director, Prof. Hiroshi Inomata) of Tohoku University for logistics support. Special thanks to Professor Sir Martyn Poliakoff (University of Nottingham) for providing helpful comments on the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>H.L., R.S., and Z.F. conceived the concept and directed the project. H.L., H.G., and Y.H. conducted experiments and analyses. Y.S. and E.J.M.H. performed the DFT calculations. H.L., R.S., M.W., and Z.F. discussed the experiments and results, and prepared the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increasing the revenue from lignocellulosic biomass: maximizing feedstock utilization</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e1603301</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1603301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28560350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Universal kinetic solvent effects in acid-catalyzed reactions of biomass-derived oxygenates</article-title><source>Energy Environ. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7EE03432F</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient valorization of biomass to biofuels with bifunctional solid catalytic materials</article-title><source>Prog. Energ. Combust. Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pecs.2016.04.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Urrutigo&#x000ef;ty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tandem hydroaminomethylation reaction to synthesize amines from alkenes</article-title><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2018</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>3833</fpage><lpage>3861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.7b00667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29493233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct alkylation of amines with primary and secondary alcohols through biocatalytic hydrogen borrowing</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>10491</fpage><lpage>10494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201705848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werkmeister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Junge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Beller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copper-catalyzed reductive amination of aromatic and aliphatic ketones with anilines using environmental-friendly molecular hydrogen</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2371</fpage><lpage>2374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c2gc35565e</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Asymmetric synthesis of chiral primary amines by ruthenium-catalyzed direct reductive amination of alkyl aryl ketones with ammonium salts and molecular H<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2018</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>2024</fpage><lpage>2027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.7b12898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29377687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High performance of a cobalt-nitrogen complex for the reduction and reductive coupling of nitro compounds into amines and their derivatives</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e1601945</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1601945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28232954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chusov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>List</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reductive amination without an external hydrogen source</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2014</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>5199</fpage><lpage>5201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fasano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Radcliffe</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingleson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>B(C<sub>6</sub>F<sub>5</sub>)<sub>3</sub>-catalyzed reductive amination using hydrosilanes</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1793</fpage><lpage>1798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscatal.5b02896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagadeesh</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MOF-derived cobalt nanoparticles catalyze a general synthesis of amines</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aan6245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28935769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Froidevaux</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Negrell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caillol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascault</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutevin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biobased amines: From synthesis to polymers; present and future</article-title><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2016</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>14181</fpage><lpage>14224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.6b00486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemicals from biomass: chemoselective reductive amination of ethyl levulinate with amines</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>5812</fpage><lpage>5821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscatal.5b01113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lactate-based ionic liquid catalyzed reductive amination/cyclization of keto acids under mild conditions: A metal-free route to synthesize lactams</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>7772</fpage><lpage>7776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscatal.7b02231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly stable porous-carbon-coated Ni catalysts for the reductive amination of levulinic acid via an unconventional pathway</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>4927</fpage><lpage>4935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscatal.7b01786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Versatile CO-assisted direct reductive amination of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural catalyzed by a supported gold catalyst</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3880</fpage><lpage>3887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7GC01579H</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Production of primary amines by reductive amination of biomass-derived aldehydes/ketones</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>3050</fpage><lpage>3054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201610964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelckmans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Catalytic reductive aminolysis of reducing sugars: elucidation of reaction mechanism</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>4201</fpage><lpage>4212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscatal.8b00619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelckmans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermandel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Waes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Moonen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sels</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-temperature reductive aminolysis of carbohydrates to diamines and aminoalcohols by heterogeneous catalysis</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>14540</fpage><lpage>14544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201708216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poissonnier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of homogeneous and heterogeneous reactions in the reductive aminolysis of glucose with dimethylamine</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. B</source><year>2018</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2018.01.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verduyckt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coeck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vos</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ru-catalyzed hydrogenation-decarbonylation of amino acids to bio-based primary amines</article-title><source>ACS Sustain. Chem. Eng.</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>3290</fpage><lpage>3295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.6b03140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelckmans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Renders</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Vyver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sels</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bio-based amines through sustainable heterogeneous catalysis</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>5303</fpage><lpage>5331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7GC02299A</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishizaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawanami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reductive amination of furfural to furfurylamine using aqueous ammonia solution and molecular hydrogen: an environmentally friendly approach</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5GC01352F</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enthaler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ammonia: an environmentally friendly nitrogen source for primary aniline synthesis</article-title><source>ChemSusChem</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cssc.201000145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20572289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klinkenberg</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartwig</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytic organometallic reactions of ammonia</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2011</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201002354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seayad</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of primary amines: first homogeneously catalyzed reductive amination with ammonia</article-title><source>Org. Lett.</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2055</fpage><lpage>2058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ol0200605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12049516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hohn, A. <italic>Kirk</italic>-<italic>Othmer Concise Encyclopedia of Chemical Technology</italic> (John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, New York, 2000).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bipp, H. &#x00026; Kieczka, H. <italic>Ullmann</italic>&#x02019;<italic>s Encyclopedia of Industrial Chemistry</italic> (Wiley-VCH, Weinheim, 2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of formamide by means of formates and oxalates</article-title><source>Chem. News J. Phys. Sci.</source><year>1864</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>291</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Committee on the Limits of Organic Life in Planetary Systems. <italic>The Limits of Organic Life in Planetary Systems</italic> (The National Academies Press, Washington, DC, 2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rico</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lattes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formamide, a water substitute. 12. Krafft temperature and micelle formation of ionic surfactants in formamide</article-title><source>J. Phys. Chem.</source><year>1986</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>5870</fpage><lpage>5872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/j100280a081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perticaroli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Water-like behavior of formamide: jump reorientation probed by extended depolarized light scattering</article-title><source>J. Phys. Chem. Lett.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpclett.7b02943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29243934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de la Luz</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;ndez-Maldonado</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x000fa;&#x000f1;ez-Rojas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bresme</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Alejandre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new force field of formamide and the effect of the dielectric constant on miscibility</article-title><source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2792</fpage><lpage>2800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jctc.5b00080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26575572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computing the dielectric constant of liquid water at constant dielectric displacement</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. B</source><year>2016</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>144201</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.93.144201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insight into aluminum sulfate-catalyzed xylan conversion into furfural in a <italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-valerolactone/water biphasic solvent under microwave conditions</article-title><source>ChemSusChem</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>4066</fpage><lpage>4079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cssc.201701290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28856818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luque</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Men&#x000e9;ndez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenillas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microwave-assisted pyrolysis of biomass feedstocks: the way forward?</article-title><source>Energy Environ. Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>5481</fpage><lpage>5488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C1EE02450G</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mushtaq</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ani</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on microwave assisted pyrolysis of coal and biomass for fuel production</article-title><source>Renew. Sustain. Energ. Rev.</source><year>2014</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2014.07.073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fang, Z., Smith, R. L. &#x00026; Qi, X. <italic>Production of Biofuels and Chemicals with Microwave</italic> (Springer, Heidelberg, Germany, 2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komanoya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinemura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electronic effect of ruthenium nanoparticles on efficient reductive amination of carbonyl compounds</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>11493</fpage><lpage>11499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.7b04481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28759206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High performance catalyst of shape-specific ruthenium nanoparticles for production of primary amines by reductive amination of carbonyl compounds</article-title><source>Chem. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5949</fpage><lpage>5956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8SC01197D</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30079209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A remarkable solvent effect on reductive amination of ketones</article-title><source>Mol. Catal.</source><year>2018</year><volume>454</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcat.2018.05.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chubb</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandin</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Leuckart reaction of some 1,5-diketones</article-title><source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source><year>1953</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>6042</fpage><lpage>6044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja01119a508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loupy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Towards the rehabilitation of the Leuckart reductive amination reaction using microwave technology</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett.</source><year>1996</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>8177</fpage><lpage>8180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0040-4039(96)01865-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanism of the Leuckart reaction</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem.</source><year>1951</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo01145a001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Understanding microwave heating effects in single mode type cavities&#x02014;theory and experiment</article-title><source>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>4750</fpage><lpage>4758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b922797k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20428555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hollmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;hn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tillack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A general ruthenium-catalyzed synthesis of aromatic amines</article-title><source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source><year>2007</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>8291</fpage><lpage>8294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.200703119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cobalt-catalyzed synthesis of aromatic, aliphatic, and cyclic secondary amines via a &#x0201c;hydrogen-borrowing&#x0201d; strategy</article-title><source>ACS Catal.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6546</fpage><lpage>6550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscatal.6b02218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosseini-Sarvari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharghi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ZnO as a new catalyst for N-formylation of amines under solvent-free conditions</article-title><source>J. Org. Chem.</source><year>2006</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>6652</fpage><lpage>6654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo060847z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16901164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000f6;cher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsener</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model gas study of ammonium formate, methanamide and guanidinium formate as alternative ammonia precursor compounds for the selective catalytic reduction of nitrogen oxides in diesel exhaust gas</article-title><source>Appl. Catal. B</source><year>2009</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apcatb.2008.09.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Supported gold nanoparticles catalyzed cis-selective semihydrogenation of alkynes using ammonium formate as the reductant</article-title><source>Chem. Commun.</source><year>2016</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>6013</fpage><lpage>6016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6CC01318J</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerhof</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Upgrading biomass-derived furans via acid-catalysis/hydrogenation: the remarkable difference between water and methanol as the solvent</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4GC01826E</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation and growth of humins via aldol addition and condensation during acid-catalyzed conversion of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural</article-title><source>Energ. Fuel.</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>4745</fpage><lpage>4755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ef2010157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waidmann</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional group dependence of the acid catalyzed ring opening of biomass derived furan rings: an experimental and theoretical study</article-title><source>Catal. Sci. Technol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C2CY20395B</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Catalytic amino acid production from biomass-derived intermediates</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>5093</fpage><lpage>5098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1800272115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29712826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multilateral mechanistic study into asymmetric transfer hydrogenation in water</article-title><source>Chem. Eur. J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>7699</fpage><lpage>7715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.200800559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boddien</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficient dehydrogenation of formic acid using an iron catalyst</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2011</year><volume>333</volume><fpage>1733</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1206613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21940890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maschmeyer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The reductive amination of aldehydes and ketones and the hydrogenation of nitriles: mechanistic aspects and selectivity control</article-title><source>Adv. Synth. Catal.</source><year>2002</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>1037</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1615-4169(200212)344:10&#x0003c;1037::AID-ADSC1037&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senthamarai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simple ruthenium-catalyzed reductive amination enables the synthesis of a broad range of primary amines</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4123</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-06416-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30297832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chheda</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rom&#x000e1;n-Leshkov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumesic</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural and furfural by dehydration of biomass-derived mono-and poly-saccharides</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/B611568C</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient catalytic system for the direct transformation of lignocellulosic biomass to furfural and 5-hydroxymethylfurfural</article-title><source>Bioresour. Technol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2016.11.097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27913172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ruthenium-catalyzed direct N-formylation of lactams with paraformaldehyde</article-title><source>Synlett</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1077</fpage><lpage>1080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0034-1378689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambaiah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudipati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yennam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Behera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An efficient method for the preparation of N-formyl-imide via amidine using propylphosphonic anhydride (T3P&#x000ae;)</article-title><source>Tetrahedron Lett.</source><year>2016</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tetlet.2015.12.046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aida</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RL</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytical conversion of fructose and glucose into 5-hydroxymethylfurfural in hot compressed water by microwave heating</article-title><source>Catal. Commun.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2244</fpage><lpage>2249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.catcom.2008.04.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aida</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RL</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Catalytic dehydration of fructose into 5-hydroxymethylfurfural by ion-exchange resin in mixed-aqueous system by microwave heating</article-title><source>Green. Chem.</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b801641k</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aida</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RL</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Fast transformation of glucose and di-/polysaccharides into 5-hydroxymethylfurfural by microwave heating in an ionic liquid/catalyst system</article-title><source>ChemSusChem</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cssc.201000124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20661994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becke</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Density-functional thermochemistry. III. The role of exact exchange</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1993</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>5648</fpage><lpage>5652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.464913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Frisch, M. et al. Gaussian 09, revision b. 01 (Gaussian Inc., Wallingford, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mennucci</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ab initio study of ionic solutions by a polarizable continuum dielectric model</article-title><source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source><year>1998</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-2614(98)00106-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>