<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A second group of active components used in this study were monoterpenes, which are widespread constituents of essential oils [
 <xref rid="B36-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and also exhibit antimicrobial activity due to their alkyl group that may affect growth and energy metabolism of different microbial populations in the rumen [
 <xref rid="B37-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Among the monoterpenes screened, only lemongrass oil tended to increase propionate and tended to decrease the A:P ratio. In contrast, Hristov et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] used lemongrass in vitro at dose slightly higher to our low dose (80 vs. 100 mg/L) and observed a decrease in total VFA and acetate molar proportion. Another study that used lemongrass at doses ranging between 186 and 1491 mg/L in vitro but in this case, lemongrass had no effect on the rumen microbial fermentation profile [
 <xref rid="B31-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Joch et al. [
 <xref rid="B39-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] used citral, the main active compound of lemongrass at high dose (888 mg/L) and observed a decrease in total VFA and propionate proportion and an increase in acetate molar proportion and A:P ratio. The dose of lemongrass (80 mg/L) used in our study seems to be the more adequate to get a positive effect, because higher doses had no effect or negative effects on rumen fermentation profile. Limonene used in this screening did not improve rumen microbial fermentation at low, medium, and high doses. These results agree with those of Joch et al. [
 <xref rid="B39-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] that used limonene at higher dose compared with us (844 mg/L) but results were the same, no effects on total and individual VFA. In contrast, Castillejos et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] used limonene at doses similar or higher than ours (50, 500 and 5000 mg/L) and observed a decrease in total VFA and the A:P ratio. The tea tree oil used in this experiment did not modify the rumen fermentation profile. This result agrees with those of Hristov et al. [
 <xref rid="B20-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] that used tea tree oil (100 mg/L) and no effect was observed. Busquet et al. [
 <xref rid="B29-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] used tea tree oil at higher dose (3000 mg/L) but total VFA and propionate and acetate molar proportions decreased. We did not find references related to the use of coriander in vitro to modify dairy rumen fermentation profile. However, Joch et al. [
 <xref rid="B39-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] reported that the use of linalool, one of the main active compound of coriander oil, in vitro at 870 mg/L decreased total VFA and propionate proportion. Geraniol oil used in this study did not show any effect on total and individual VFA at low, medium, and high doses. However, Joch et al. [
 <xref rid="B40-animals-11-01205" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] used geraniol at 300, 600, and 900 mg/L, and at 300 mg/L observed a decrease in total VFA and acetate proportion, and an increase in butyrate proportion and the A:P ratio. 
</p>
