<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many investigations have been addressed towards the elucidation of the antiviral activities of compounds from plant world. Once the contribution and quality of the various phytochemicals have been ascertained, their biological activity must be tested using specific assays. The screening of biomolecules for antiviral activity comprises of a number of clinical trials for its teratogenicity, toxicological studies that are carried in vivo and the whole procedure for the same is depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pharmaceuticals-14-00381-f001">Figure 1</xref> [
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This review article describes the numerous chemical classes that are medicinally active such as polyphenols, flavonoids, carotenoids, phytoalexins, minerals, quinines, tannins, lignans, alkaloids, polysaccharides, phytosterols and poly-unsaturated fatty acids that and can be extracted from plants. The phytochemicals presented have important antiviral activities and represent a huge arsenal that can be used against many viral diseases still endemic in various parts of the world. In this context, it must be remembered that Ebola, influenza, acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS), severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS), still represent aggressive forms of viral infections. [
 <xref rid="B12-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Influenza alone is responsible for about 250,000-500,000 deaths annually that occurs due to severe diseases. Furthermore, events such as the usage of hypodermic syringes, blood transfusions and organ transplantations lead to the transmission of viral infections from one person to another and leads to increased cases of viral infections [
 <xref rid="B13-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-pharmaceuticals-14-00381" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The availability of synthetic drugs and vaccines is still too limited to face continuous threats brought by viruses, so turning to the world of natural compounds today represents a logical and intelligent challenge. In this review many examples of antiviral compounds extracted and isolated from plant matrices and in particular from food plants, are reported in order to guarantee a critical contribution for their potential use as new antiviral agents.
</p>
