<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Infectious diseases and invasive species can be strong drivers of biological systems that may interact to shift plant community composition. For example, disease can modify resource competition between invasive and native species. Invasive species tend to interact with a diversity of native species, and it is unclear how native species differ in response to disease-mediated competition with invasive species. Here, we quantified the biomass responses of three native North American grass species (
  <italic>Dichanthelium clandestinum</italic>, 
  <italic>Elymus virginicus</italic>, and 
  <italic>Eragrostis spectabilis)</italic> to disease-mediated competition with the non-native invasive grass 
  <italic>Microstegium vimineum</italic>. The foliar fungal pathogen 
  <italic>Bipolaris gigantea</italic> has recently emerged in 
  <italic>Microstegium</italic> populations, causing a leaf spot disease that reduces 
  <italic>Microstegium</italic> biomass and seed production. In a greenhouse experiment, we examined the effects of 
  <italic>B</italic>. 
  <italic>gigantea</italic> inoculation on two components of competitive ability for each native species: growth in the absence of competition and biomass responses to increasing densities of 
  <italic>Microstegium</italic>. 
  <italic>Bipolaris gigantea</italic> inoculation affected each of the three native species in unique ways, by increasing (
  <italic>Dichanthelium</italic>), decreasing (
  <italic>Elymus</italic>), or not changing (
  <italic>Eragrostis</italic>) their growth in the absence of competition relative to mock inoculation. 
  <italic>Bipolaris gigantea</italic> inoculation did not, however, affect 
  <italic>Microstegium</italic> biomass or mediate the effect of 
  <italic>Microstegium</italic> density on native plant biomass. Thus, 
  <italic>B</italic>. 
  <italic>gigantea</italic> had species-specific effects on native plant competition with 
  <italic>Microstegium</italic> through species-specific biomass responses to 
  <italic>B</italic>. 
  <italic>gigantea</italic> inoculation, but not through modified responses to 
  <italic>Microstegium</italic> density. Our results suggest that disease may uniquely modify competitive interactions between invasive and native plants for different native plant species.
 </p>
</abstract>
