<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0005">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Acetaminophen (
   <italic>N</italic>-acetyl-
   <italic>p</italic>-aminophenol, APAP) is a safe and effective analgesic at therapeutic dosage. However, APAP overdose is a major cause of acute liver injury. 
   <italic>Gamisoyo-san</italic> (GMSYS; 
   <italic>Jiaweixiaoyao-san</italic> in Chinese, 
   <italic>Kamishoyo-san</italic> in Japanese), a traditional herbal formula, is used to treat phlegm and cough in Korea. The purpose of this study was to investigate the hepatoprotective effect of GMSYS against APAP-induced liver injury 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
   <italic>in vivo</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>We evaluated the effect of GMSYS on APAP-induced hepatotoxicity by measuring cell viability in murine BNL CL.2 liver cells. Additionally, BALB/c mice were orally administered with GMSYS once daily for 7 days. Eighteen hours after the last administration, mice were intraperitoneally injected with 200 mg/kg APAP. Plasma alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) levels, hepatic antioxidants, and histological changes were examined.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Pretreatment with GMSYS attenuated the decrease in cell viability induced by APAP in BNL CL.2 cells. In mice, pre-administration with GMSYS alleviated APAP-induced hepatotoxicity by decreasing plasma ALT and AST activities and hepatic malondialdehyde, and by increasing the total glutathione (GSH)/reduced GSH ratio and the activities of several antioxidants such as superoxide dismutase, catalase, GSH peroxidase, GSH reductase, GSH-S-transferase, and heme oxygenase-1.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>GMSYS has a protective effect against APAP-induced acute liver injury by decreasing plasma transaminases and increasing antioxidants. GMSYS may be an effective candidate for the prevention of acute liver injury.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
