<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">One of the main causes for difficulties in the bioactivity study of 
 <italic class="italic">O. fragrans</italic> var. 
 <italic class="italic">thunbergii</italic> essential oil is the complexity of its chemical composition. Recently, complex network approach has emerged in the pharmacological researches, which was also known as “network pharmacology” or “system pharmacology” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>]. This methodology holds a significant potential for extracting biological information from large amounts of chemical data [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>], and enables to predict the target profiles and pharmacological actions of herbal compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>]. For instance, Chandran et al. performed a network to evaluate the immunomodulatory activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Withania somnifera</italic>, and revealed a series of novel bioactive immune target combinations. Chen et al. constructed a multi-parameter network model on the basis of three important parameters to tentatively explain the anti-fibrosis mechanism of herbal medicine 
 <italic class="italic">Sophora flavescens</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>]. Luo et al. used systems pharmacology strategies for anticancer drug discovery based on natural products [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>]. In addition, 
 <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://xueshu.baidu.com/s?wd=author%3A%28Gogoi%20B%29%20&amp;tn=SE_baiduxueshu_c1gjeupa&amp;ie=utf-8&amp;sc_f_para=sc_hilight%3Dperson" class="ext-link" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Gogoi</span> et al. developed a network pharmacology-based virtual screening of natural products from 
 <italic class="italic">Clerodendrum</italic> species for identification of novel anti-cancer therapeutics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. These studies demonstrate that complex network approach has real potential for bioactivity study of natural products [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>].
</p>
