<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Enemy release may cause the initial spread, but the subsequent population dynamics are more complex, and influenced by evolutionary processes. Reduced selection pressure for defences against specialist herbivores may result in the evolution of changed energy investment. For example, the plant may evolve stronger allocation of resources towards growth and reproduction and/or towards defence against generalists (
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Blossey &amp; Nötzold, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Joshi &amp; Vrieling, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">Zangerl &amp; Berenbaum, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Prentis et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Whitney &amp; Gabler, 2008</xref>). However, at the same time, native herbivores may evolve the ability to locate and feed on introduced species (
 <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Vellend et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Pearse &amp; Hipp, 2014</xref>). Therefore, the course of the establishment of an introduced species is complex, with population dynamics modified by evolution: over time, the community of natural enemies attacking an introduced species tends to expand (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Brändle et al., 2008</xref>) and the adverse impact of invasive species tends to wane (
 <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Williamson, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">Simberloff &amp; Gibbons, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Blackburn, Lockwood &amp; Cassey, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Dostál et al., 2013</xref>). This may be due to evolution in both the invader and the species it interacts with (
 <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Vellend et al., 2007</xref>). However, a species’ invasive character is often considered static, and management policies rarely consider the possibility that it may change due to evolutionary adaptation (
 <xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Whitney &amp; Gabler, 2008</xref>).
</p>
