<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Liver fibrosis and cirrhosis are the ultimate consequences of chronic hepatic injury induced by various etiological agents [
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>]. The mechanism of liver fibrosis has been extensively studied. However, effective antifibrotic therapies are lacking [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. The pathogenesis of hepatic fibrosis is generally based on the activation of HSCs and excessive extracellular matrix (ECM) production [
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>]. Oxidative stress plays a central role in triggering these inflammatory and fibrotic responses [
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>]. Among the various signaling pathways involved in pathogenesis of liver fibrosis, TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1/SMAD is considered the most significant signaling pathway [
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>]. Therefore, inhibiting TGF-
  <span class="italic">β</span>1 was found to be efficient in attenuating liver fibrosis [
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>]. The tumor suppressor p53 is another important cell signal primarily stimulated in response to oxidative damage and oncogene activation [
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>]. Accumulating evidences suggested the involvement of p53 in the pathophysiology of various nontumoral fibrotic liver diseases in both human and animals [
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>]. These data suggest that p53 regulation could serve as an important therapeutic target for fibrotic liver diseases.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Medicinal plants and their derivatives contain a wide variety of bioactive phytochemicals with a diverse pharmacological spectrum [
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>]. Essential oils constituents including terpenes, terpenoids, phenylpropenes, and other degradation products have been reported to exhibit strong antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities [
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>]. The effectiveness of some essential oils to alleviate the hepatotoxicity [
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>] and hepatic fibrosis [
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>] has been proven. 
  <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> L. (peppermint) is one of the most popular and widely used herbs. Pharmacological investigations have demonstrated that 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> possesses analgesic, antifungal [
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>], antibacterial [
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>], antiparasitic, and immunomodulatory activities [
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>]. Moreover, the hepatoprotective effects of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> leaves extract [
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>], oil [
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>, 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>], or its active components menthol and menthone [
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>] have been reported. However, to the best of our knowledge, the effect against hepatic fibrosis has not been reported. Therefore, the present study aimed to investigate the effects of 
  <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> L. essential oil (MPEO) against hepatic fibrosis and to elucidate the potential underlying molecular mechanisms.
 </p>
</sec>
