<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the period from 2011 to 2015, interdisciplinary health promotion strategies were implemented during the annual occupational assessment, including consultations with the physical educator, nutritionist, nurse and preventive dentistry, with the objective of expanding clinical and educational opportunities for workers and improving the control of CNCDs. Collaborative health professionals explored patient priorities, providing counselling, focusing in education, and assisting with self-management goals. The physical educator promoted a complete physical assessment, using the Jackson and Pollock’s protocol of 7 folds [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], approaching aspects related to the habits of life in relation to the practice of physical activity, in order to identify what elements of the sedentary behaviour should be altered to improve the health results. Through the weekly food recall and use of educational food models, i.e., dishes, fruits, vegetables, meats, spoons, beverage cups, etc., the nutritionist focused his intervention on improving the subjects’ food profile, seeking to interfere in terms of quality improvement and adequate caloric intake. The work nurse sought to stimulate the improvement of the self-care of workers with their health, as well as to expand healthy practices in the oil industry and within family environment, addressing aspects related to active leisure, level of influence of family relationships on the individual’s health, Fagerström test for nicotine dependence [
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-02148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], regular use of medications, among others. The work dentist began to act in a preventive manner, besides acting as an expert, through the inclusion of procedures such as tartarectomy, fluoride application, assisted brushing and oral examination using the intraoral chamber, enabling the worker to visualize the oral cavity and to identify areas needing greater care. In an integrated and interdisciplinary way, all health professionals guided the subjects in their needs, defining actions aiming to improve their health conditions. In addition to the practices described, an articulated set of preventive and curative health and individual actions and services were established at the levels of complexity of the worker’s health system in the oil industry, such as diet changes, creation of health promotion centres, brushstrokes, tobacco control support groups, and promotion of smoke-free environments, among several others. In summary, the test group was submitted to governmental actions, to the actions carried out by the oil industry and to the interdisciplinary strategies, which included the training of health professionals, broadening the perspective of approaching CNCDs from the perspective of health promotion and distancing from the disease by itself, aiming the self-management of chronic diseases, focusing in the worker-centred care, with the possibility of discussing cases in the interdisciplinary context and with specific referrals for each health need and discussing and assessing the effectiveness of the implemented practices.
</p>
