<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mioc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Mem&#x000f3;rias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0074-0276</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-8060</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7534957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-02760200207</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">00341</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Flavonoid glycosides and their putative human metabolites as potential inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 main protease (Mpro) and RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1809-1372</contrib-id><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>Felipe Moura A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c">
<sup>+</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>Katia Pacheco A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>Luiz Paulo M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>Emmanoel V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koolen</surname><given-names>Hector HF</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>Maria L&#x000fa;cia B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>Antonia Queiroz L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7007-3991</contrib-id><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>Afonso Duarte L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c">
<sup>+</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Universidade Federal do Amazonas, Centro de Apoio Multidisciplinar, Central Anal&#x000ed;tica, Manaus, AM, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Secretaria Municipal de Sa&#x000fa;de, Prefeitura de Itabirito, Itabirito, MG, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Universidade Federal do Amazonas, Departamento de Qu&#x000ed;mica, Manaus, AM, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>Universidade do Estado do Amazonas, Grupo de Pesquisa em Metabol&#x000f4;mica e Espectrometria de Massas, Manaus, AM, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>Universidade Federal do Amazonas, Faculdade de Ci&#x000ea;ncias Agr&#x000e1;rias, Manaus, AM, Brasil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c">+ Corresponding authors: <email>felipemas@ufam.edu.br</email> / <email>souzadq@ufam.edu.br</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con" id="fn2"><p>FMAS - Conceptualisation, methodology, formal analysis, data curation, writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing; KPAS and MLBP - conceptualisation, investigation; LPMO, HHFK and EVC - investigation; AQLS - conceptualisation, investigation, writing - original draft; ADLS - conceptualisation, methodology, formal analysis, data curation, writing - original draft, writing - review and editing, supervision.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>115</volume><elocation-id>e200207</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>BACKGROUND</title><p> Since the World Health Organization (WHO) declared Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) to be a pandemic infection, important severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) non-structural proteins (nsp) have been analysed as promising targets in virtual screening approaches. Among these proteins, 3-chymotrypsin-like cysteine protease (3CLpro), also named main protease, and the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp), have been identified as fundamental targets due to its importance in the viral replication stages.</p></sec><sec><title>OBJECTIVES</title><p> To investigate, <italic>in silico</italic>, two of the most abundant flavonoid glycosides from <italic>Dysphania ambrosioides</italic>; a medicinal plant found in many regions of the world, along with some of the putative derivatives of these flavonoid glycosides in the human organism as potential inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp.</p></sec><sec><title>METHODS</title><p> Using a molecular docking approach, the interactions and the binding affinity with SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp were predicted for quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-rutinoside (rutin), kaempferol-3-<italic>O</italic>-rutinoside (nicotiflorin) and some of their glucuronide and sulfate derivatives.</p></sec><sec><title>FINDINGS</title><p> Docking analysis, based on the crystal structure of 3CLpro and RdRp, indicated rutin, nicotiflorin, and their glucuronide and sulfate derivatives as potential inhibitors for both proteins. Also, the importance of the hydrogen bond and &#x003c0;-based interactions was evidenced for the presumed active sites.</p></sec><sec><title>MAIN CONCLUSIONS</title><p> Overall, these results suggest that both flavonoid glycosides and their putative human metabolites can play a key role as inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp. Obviously, further researches, mainly <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments, are necessary to certify the docking results reported here, as well as the adequate application of these substances. Furthermore, it is necessary to investigate the risks of <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic> as a phytomedicine for use against COVID-19.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>rutin</kwd><kwd>nicotiflorin</kwd><kwd>glucuronides</kwd><kwd>Dysphania ambrosioides</kwd><kwd>phytomedicines</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="34"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Since the appearance of the first cases, reported in December 2019 in Wuhan, China, the new pandemic disease Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has claimed millions of victims and caused hundreds of deaths around the world. Forthwith, Chinese teams sequenced SARS-CoV-2<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> and its important nonstructural proteins (nsp) were revealed, which included spike protein, 3-chymotrypsin-like cysteine protease (3CLpro), also named main protease (Mpro), papain-like protease (PLpro), and RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp).<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> The spike protein binds the virus to the human receptor - a metallopeptidase named angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), while the 3CLpro and the PLpro provide components for packaging new virions from large viral polyproteins translated on host ribosome, and finally the RdRp replicate the SARS-CoV-2 RNA genome.<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> Due to their importance in the viral replication stages, 3CLpro and RdRp have been highlighted as fundamental targets in computational strategies, such as molecular docking.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref> Nowadays, molecular docking represents a powerful, rational and low-cost tool, which allows understanding how these important nsps interacts with ligands at the active site, thus supporting the design and screening of new antiviral agents against COVID-19.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref> Regarding the ligands, drugs used against other human diseases and natural products present in medicinal plants, such as flavonoids, have been the main candidates in virtual screening approaches.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref> On the other hand, since many people have almost none access to medicines, including indigenous tribes and riverside dwellers in Amazon, medicinal plants could be the only possibility of treatment. Thus, the study of these therapeutic plants is a matter of human solidarity and can play an important role in saving lives. <italic>Dysphania ambrosioides</italic> (L.) Mosyakin &#x00026; Clemants (Syn. <italic>Chenopodium ambrosioides</italic> L.) is one medicinal plants commonly found in tropical and subtropical regions and, therefore, accessible as therapeutic agents. <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic> is popularly known in Brazil as &#x0201c;mastruz&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;Erva-de-Santa-Maria&#x0201d; and has been used to treat a number of health problems, such as infections, sinusitis, gastritis, inflammations, and flu.<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> From the phytochemical viewpoint, this species is a promising source of flavonoid glycosides, such as rutin, nicotiflorin, and other quercetin and kaempferol derivatives.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> These flavonoids present great biological potential, including antioxidant and antiviral activities, and some are mentioned as potential substances against Covid-19.<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> Since <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic> and several other flavonoid-producing sources are used worldwide, the absorption, metabolism, and pharmacokinetics of flavonoids have been intensively investigated, and glucuronide and sulfates can be highlighted as important metabolite products in this process.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref> Thus, in the present study, we screened rutin and nicotiflorin, two of the most abundant flavonoid glycosides from <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic>, along with some of their putative derivatives in the human organism using molecular docking, in order to test them as potential inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>
<italic>Ligand preparation</italic> - Initially, the three-dimensional (3D) structures of quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-rutinoside (rutin), quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, quercetin-3&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate, and quercetin were downloaded from ZINC database (http://zinc15.docking.org/) in spatial data file (SDF) format. These structures were used as templates to generate, via Marvin Sketch software (https://chemaxon.com/products/marvin), kaempferol-3-<italic>O</italic>-rutinoside (nicotiflorin), kaempferol, and some of their putative mono-glucuronide and sulfate derivatives (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>), based on previous pharmacokinetic studies on the human organism.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref> Also, theaflavin, a phenolic compound suggested as potential SARS-CoV-2 RdRp inhibitor,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> was downloaded from ZINC database. All explicit hydrogens were added into the structures using Marvin Sketch and the compounds were saved in SDF format. Subsequently, all the structures were subjected to geometry optimisation by the semi-empirical method PM7 using MOPAC2016 software (http://openmopac.net/MOPAC2016.html), being the results saved in protein data bank (PDB) format. Finally, the ligands were prepared for molecular docking using AutoDock Tools.<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref> Briefly, Gasteiger charges were added for each compound and non-polar hydrogens were merged, being the results saved in protein data bank, partial charge (Q), &#x00026; Atom Type (T) (PDBQT) format.</p><p>
<fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1:</label><caption><title>chemical structures of rutin and nicotiflorin, along with some of their putative derivatives in human organism, including sulfate (blue) and glucuronide (green) derivatives.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-gf1"/></fig>
</p><p>
<italic>Protein preparation</italic> - The 3D crystal structures of the SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro (PDB ID: 6W63) and RdRp (PDB ID: 6M71) were retrieved from Research Collaboratory for Structural Bioinformatics Protein Data Bank (RCSB PDB) (http://www.rcsb.org) in PDB format. These receptors were prepared using AutoDock Tools. Briefly, water molecules and bound ligands were removed, polar hydrogens and Kollman charges were added, and the non-polar hydrogens were merged. For both proteins, the protonation states of the amino acid residues were automatically generated by Autodock tools [<inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-s.pdf" id="d38e548" content-type="local-data">Supplementary data</inline-supplementary-material> (Figs 1-2)] based on the protonation states of the original 3D crystal structures. Finally, the results were saved as PDBQT format.</p><p>
<italic>Docking simulations</italic> - The docking simulations were as previously reported,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref> in which the grid box was centered at the ligand X77 in 3CLpro (PDB ID: 6W63) and at the presumed active site<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref> in the RdRp (PDB ID: 6M71). For 3CLpro, the grid box was centered at x = -20.810, y = 19.141, and z = -29.186, with x = 27 &#x000c5;, y = 25 &#x000c5;, and z = 25 &#x000c5; size. On the other hand, the RdRp grid box was centered at the x = 117.382, y = 111.853, and z = 121.073, with x = 22 &#x000c5;, y = 30 &#x000c5;, and and z = 46 &#x000c5; size. The interactions and the binding affinity of the protein-ligand complex were predicted via a docking process using Autodock Vina, which use a Broyden-Fletcher-Goldfarb-Shanno (BFGS) algorithm, through an Iterated Local Search method, to generate different ligand conformers.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref> Regarding scoring function, Autodock Vina uses a hybrid score function that combine empirical and knowledge-based functions.<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref> Finally, the results were viewed with the Discovery Studio software.<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref> Due to the lack of models with ligands for RdRp in the RCSB PDB, only the 3CLpro was tested for redocking.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>
<italic>Molecular docking with 3CLpro (main protease</italic> - <italic>Mpro)</italic> - Docking analysis applied to the 3CLpro protein revealed close scoring function values for rutin (-9.2 kcal/mol), nicotiflorin (-8.9 kcal/mol), and the previously described inhibitor X77 (redocking binding free energy = -8.4 kcal/mol, RMSD = 0.8909 &#x000c5;), which suggests the establishment of favorable interactions for the ligand-3CLpro complex. Moreover, glucuronide derivatives from rutin (-8.4 to -8.5 kcal/mol) and nicotiflorin (-8.0 to -8.3 kcal/mol) presented binding free energies similar to X77. Also, the binding free energies for all sulfate derivatives (-8.1 to 8.4 kcal/mol), except 3-<italic>O</italic>-sulfates (-7.3 to -7.6 kcal/mol), were close to value for X77. By their turn, quercetin (-7.5 kcal/mol) and kaempferol (-7.2 kcal/mol) presented similar binding free energies to 3-<italic>O</italic>-sulfates derivatives.</p><p>In regards to the observed interactions in the presumed active site of 3CLpro, hydrogen bonds and &#x003c0;-based interactions, such as &#x003c0;-sulfur, &#x003c0;-alkyl, &#x003c0;-&#x003c0;, and &#x003c0;-cation interactions, were dominant in almost all tested compounds (<xref rid="t" ref-type="table">Table</xref>) [<inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-s.pdf" id="d38e609" content-type="local-data">Supplementary data</inline-supplementary-material> (Figs 3-19)]. Since recent studies demonstrated that the catalytic dyad (His41 and Cys145) in the receptor-binding pocket of SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>A), such as in SARS-CoV 3CLpro, is fundamental to the proteolytic task, we considered in our interpretation the interactions of ligands with this dyad, along with that observed to x77 inhibitor.<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref> For x77, hydrogen bonds were observed with Gly143, Cys145, His163, and Glu166, along with &#x003c0;-sulfur interactions with Met49 and Cys145, &#x003c0;-alkyl interaction with Cys145, &#x003c0;-amide interaction with Leu141, and &#x003c0;-&#x003c0; interaction with His41 [<inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-s.pdf" id="d38e640" content-type="local-data">Supplementary data</inline-supplementary-material> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>)].</p><p>
<table-wrap id="t" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>TABLE</label><caption><title>Docking analysis data for rutin and nicotiflorin, two of the most abundant flavonoid glycosides from <italic>Dysphania ambrosioides</italic>, along with some of their putative derivatives in human organism</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compounds</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein (PDB iD)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding energy (kcal/mol)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Main interactions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Theaflavin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Trp617, Asp618, Lys621, Cys622, Asp623, Asp760, Asp761, Trp800), PA (Asp760, Asp761)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Gly143, Cys145, His163, Glu166), PS (Met49, Cys145), PAl (Cys145), PAm (Leu141), PP (His41)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-rutinose (rutin)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Asp452, Arg553, Ala554, Thr556, Asp623, Arg624, Asn691, Ser759, Asp760), PSi (Tyr455)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Thr25, His41, Cys44, Met165, Gln189, Thr190), PS (Met165)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin-7-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Arg553, Thr556, Lys621, Asp623, Asp760, Asp761), PA (Asp760)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Thr24, Thr25, Ser46, Phe140, Ser144, Glu166), PC (His41), PS (Cys145), PP (His41), PAl (Cys145)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin-3&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Asp760, Asp761, Trp617, Trp800, Glu811), PAm (Tyr619)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Thr25, His41, Cys44, Ser144, His163, Glu166), PS (Met49), PAl (Met49, Met165)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Trp617, Tyr619, Asp761, Trp800, Glu811, Cys813), PA (Asp760, Asp761), PAl (Cys813)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Glu166, Arg188, Gln189), PS (Cys145), PC (His41), PAl (Met 165)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin-7-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Lys545, Arg553, Ala554, Thr556, Arg624, Asn691), PC (Arg553), PAl (Arg555)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Phe140, Leu141, His163, Glu166, Thr190, Gln192), PS (Cys145), PAl (Met165)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Asp760, Ser814), PA (Asp761, Glu811)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB( Gly143, Ser144, Glu166, Arg188), PS (Met165), PAl (Met165)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin-3&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Asp452, Arg553, Thr556, Tyr619, Lys621, Arg624), PC (Arg553), PAl (Lys621)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (His41, Met49, Ser144, Cys145, His163, Glu166), PC (His41), PS (Cys44, Met49, His163)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Quercetin</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Met615, Ile779, Cys799), PSi (Ile779, Thr801)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Glu166, Asp187, Thr190, Gln192), PS (Met165), PAl (Met165, Pro168)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol-3-<italic>O</italic>-rutinose (nicotiflorin)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-9.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Trp617, Asp760, Lys798, Glu811), PA (Asp623, Asp760)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Met49, Met165, Glu166, Thr190), PS (Cys145), PSi (His41), PP (His41)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol-4&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Tyr619, Cys622, Asp623, Asp761, Lys798, Ser814), PC (Lys621)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Thr25, His41, Arg188, Gln192), PAl (Met49, Met165, Pro168)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol-3-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Trp617, Tyr619, Asp761, Trp800, Glu811, Cys813), PA (Asp760, Asp761), PAl (Cys622, Cys813)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Thr25, Asn142, Gly143, Ser144, His163, Glu166), PS (Met49), PP (His41), PSi (Thr25)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol-7-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Asp761, Lys798, Trp800, Ser814), PAl (Pro620, Lys798)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (His41, Arg188, Gln189, Thr190), PS (Cys44, Met49), PSi (Thr25), PAl (Met49, Cys145)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol-7-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Asp452, Lys545, Arg553, Ala554, Arg555, Thr556, Arg624, Asn691), PC (Arg553)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Cys44, Ser144, His163), PS (Cys145), PP (His41), PAl (Met49, Met165)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol-4&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Lys621, Thr687, Asn691, Asp760), PC (Arg553), PA (Asp623, Asp760), PAl (Lys621, Cys622)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-8.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Ser144, Glu166, Asp187, Gln189), PAl (Met165)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol-3-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-6.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Ser814), PA (Asp761, Glu811)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Glu166, Asp187, Gln189), PS (Met49), PAl (Cys145)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Kaempferol</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RdRp (6M71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Ser778, Glu796), PSi (Ile779, Thr801)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3CLpro (6W63)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-7.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HB (Glu166), PS (Cys44, Met165), PAl (Met49, Pro168)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN"><p>HB: hydrogen bond; PS: &#x003c0;-sulfur; Pal: &#x003c0;-alkyl; PP: &#x003c0;-&#x003c0;; PA: &#x003c0;-anion; PC: &#x003c0;-cation; Psi: &#x003c0;-sigma; Pam: &#x003c0;-amide.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>
<fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2:</label><caption><title>3D representation of rutin-3CLpro complex (A) and nicotiflorin-RdRp complex (B), highlighting key residues in the receptor-binding pockets.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-gf2"/></fig>
</p><p>
<fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3:</label><caption><title>main interactions observed for the top-scored inhibitors of 3CLpro by docking analysis. Only hydrogen atoms that are actually participating in hydrogen bonds were presented.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-gf3"/></fig>
</p><p>For rutin, the top-scored compound for 3CLpro, several hydrogen bonds were observed, including a key interaction with His41, from the catalytic dyad, and interactions with Thr25, Cys44, Met165, Gln189, and Thr190 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>). The observed hydrogen bonds with His41 and Thr190 are in agreement with molecular docking results previously reported to other 3CLpro crystallographic models (PDB ID: 6Y84 and 6LU7).<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref> On the other hand, nicotiflorin presented key interactions with both residues of the catalytic dyad of 3CLpro (His41 and Cys145) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3</xref>), along with key residues observed for x77. In addition to hydrogen bonds with key residues such as Met49, Glu166, and Thr190, this compound presented &#x003c0;-&#x003c0; and &#x003c0;-sigma interactions with His41, and &#x003c0;-sulfur interaction with Cys145 from the catalytic dyad. Key interactions with His41 or Cys145 were also dominant in almost all glucuronide and sulfate derivatives. For example, quercetin-3&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, quercetin-3&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate, kaempferol-7-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, and kaempferol-4&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide presented hydrogen bonds with His41, while quercetin-7-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, quercetin-7-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate, and kaempferol-7-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate presented &#x003c0;-sulfur interaction with Cys145. The main observed interactions between these compounds and 3CLpro are summarised in <xref rid="t" ref-type="table">Table</xref>.</p><p>
<italic>Molecular docking for RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp)</italic> - Docking analysis applied to the RdRp protein revealed scoring function values close for nicotiflorin (-9.2 kcal/mol), rutin (-8.5 kcal/mol), and theaflavin (-9.1 kcal/mol) (<xref rid="t" ref-type="table">Table</xref>). Similarly to the 3CLpro molecular docking, glucuronide derivatives (quercetin = -8.0 to -8.2 kcal/mol; kaempferol = -7.9 to -8.3 kcal/mol) presented close binding free energies to the sulfate derivatives (quercetin = -8.0 to -8.1 kcal/mol; kaempferol-7-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate = -7.9 kcal/mol), except kaempferol-3-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate (-6.7 kcal/mol), quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate (-7.1 kcal/mol), and kaempferol-4&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate (-7.3 kcal/mol). Also, quercetin (-7.4 kcal/mol) and kaempferol (-7.2 kcal/mol) presented similar minor binding free energies.</p><p>Regarding to the observed interactions in the presumed active site of RdRp, hydrogen bonds, &#x003c0;-cation and &#x003c0;-anion interactions were dominant to almost all tested compounds (<xref rid="t" ref-type="table">Table</xref>) [<inline-supplementary-material xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-s.pdf" id="d38e1095" content-type="local-data">Supplementary data</inline-supplementary-material> (Figs 20-36)]. Since this active site includes the motif A (residues 611-626), with the classic divalent cation-binding residue 618, and motif C (residues 753-767), with the catalytic residues 759-761,<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>B) we therefore focused our interpretation on these interactions.</p><p>The observed interactions for theaflavin were near to that previously described in the literature,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> and highlighted several hydrogen bonds, including that with Lys621, Cys622, and Asp623, from motif A, and that with Asp760 and Asp761, from motif C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>), which is suggestive of a good approximation of the present model with the previous model by homology.<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> Also, &#x003c0;-anion interactions were observed with the catalytic residues Asp760 and Asp761 from motif C. For nicotiflorin, the top-scored compound for RdRp, hydrogen bond and &#x003c0;-anion interactions were observed with the catalytic residue Asp760, from motif C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>). In addition, hydrogen bonds with Trp617, along with &#x003c0;-anion interaction with Asp623, from motif A, were also observed to this compound. Also, key interactions were observed to rutin, highlighting hydrogen bonds with Asp623 and Arg624, from motif A, and with the catalytic residue Ser759 and Asp760, from motif C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>). Moreover, several glucuronide and sulfate derivatives, such as quercetin-7-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-sulfate, kaempferol-3-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, and kaempferol-4&#x02019;-<italic>O</italic>-sulphate, presented key hydrogen bonds and &#x003c0;-anion interaction with the catalytic residue from motif C. The main observed interactions between these compounds and RdRp are summarised in <xref rid="t" ref-type="table">Table</xref>.</p><p>
<fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4:</label><caption><title>main interactions observed for theaflavin, rutin and nicotiflorin-RdRp complex by docking analysis. Only hydrogen atoms that are actually participating in hydrogen bonds were presented.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="1678-8060-mioc-115-e200207-gf4"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Rutin and nicotiflorin, as well as other glycoside flavonoids, are present in a large number of therapeutic medicinal plants and are often consumed in the form of herbal teas.<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref> These compounds are vital in diets and are of great interest due their antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and antiviral activities and their human metabolites, which include quercetin from rutin hydrolysis.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref> For this reason, their absorption, metabolism, toxicity, and pharmacokinetics has been intensively investigated.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref> Regarding these studies, rutinoside flavonoids, such as rutin and nicotiflorin, are deglycosylated prior to being absorbed into the circulation and then conjugated mainly with glucuronate and sulfate, these being the main forms in plasma.<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref> Based on this information, it is reasonable to suggest that both quercetin and kaempferol sulfates and glucuronides, demonstrated above as promising SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp inhibitors, could have a key role against these proteins, since the virus is also dominant in plasma. This hypothesis is in accordance with previous <italic>in vivo</italic> antiviral studies performed with rutin. These studies indicate that rutin protects cells for about 24 h against vesicular stomatitis virus, affords immense viral embarrassment in canine distemper virus, and demonstrates a profound antiviral effect against avian influenza strain H5N1.<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> Flavonoid glucuronides have also been described as antiviral agents, including quercetin-3-<italic>O</italic>-glucuronide, here described as a potential 3CLpro inhibitor.<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>26</sup>
</xref> Moreover, previous works have pointed out the effective anti-HIV and anti-HSV activities of flavonoid sulfates.<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>27</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>Recent autopsy studies have permitted Brazilian COVID-19 patients to be treated as sufferers of Dissemination Intravascular of Coagulum (DIC), which can cause failure of several organs, mainly the lungs.<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref> As a preliminary stage for combating the disease, Low Molecular Weight Heparin (LMWH) has been successfully administered.<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>29</sup>
</xref> In addition to its anticoagulant therapeutic effects, LMWH has demonstrated anti-inflammatory effects, endothelial protection and viral inhibition.<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>30</sup>
</xref> Rutin, displayed here as an active agent against 3CLpro and RdRp of SARS-CoV-2, has also proved to have anticoagulant therapeutic effects<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>31</sup>
</xref> as well as anti-inflammatory effects and potential protection against acute lung injury (ALI).<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>32</sup>
</xref> Intravenous or intranasal administration could be an alternative to oral intake, thus improving its bioavailability.<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>33</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>34</sup>
</xref>
<italic>D. ambrosioides</italic> has been used successfully by the riverside population in the Amazon Region for treating cases of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and tuberculosis.<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> These results may also be related to the presence of rutin.</p><p>Overall, these results suggest that rutin, nicotiflorin, and their putative human metabolites, can play a key role as inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and RdRp. Such derivatives, which are expected in plasma, are in fact the most likely compounds for targeting these viral proteins, via oral intake of these flavonoid glycosides. However, at least for rutin, intravenous or intranasal administration can be an alternative for prompt bioavailability, without risk of digestive degradation. Our results, and much of the reported data, suggest rutin and nicotiflorin as possible alternatives for combating the COVID-19 virus. Rutin could even be considered an alternative to LMWH, given its anticoagulant and anti-inflammatory effects and its potential protection against ALI. Obviously, further researches, mainly <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments, are necessary to corroborate the docking results reported here, as well as the adequate application of these substances. Furthermore, it is necessary to investigate the risks of <italic>D. ambrosioides</italic> as a phytomedicine for use against COVID-19.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1"><p>Financial support: CAPES, CNPq, FAPEAM.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>382</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31978945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalonde</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning from the past possible urgent prevention and treatment options for severe acute respiratory infections caused by 2019-nCoV</article-title><source>ChemBioChem</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>730</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32022370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qamar</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Alqahtani</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alamri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis of SARS-CoV-2 3CLpro and anti-COVID-19 drug discovery from medicinal plants</article-title><source>J Pharm Anal</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32296570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of therapeutic targets for SARS-CoV-2 and discovery of potential drugs by computational methods</article-title><source>Acta Pharm Sin B</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32292689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarmah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyndem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An investigation into the identification of potential inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2 main protease using molecular docking study</article-title><source>J Biomol Struct Dyn</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07391102.2020.1763201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational screening of antagonist against the SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) coronavirus by molecular docking</article-title><source>Int J Antimicrob Agent</source><year>2020</year><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>106012</fpage><lpage>106012</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>TrivellatoGrassi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Malheiros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyre-Silva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Buss</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name><surname>Monguilhott</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Frode</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From popular use to pharmacological validation a study of the anti-inflammatory, anti-nociceptive and healing effects of Chenopodium ambrosioides extract</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>145</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23123797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieski</surname><given-names>IGC</given-names></name><name><surname>Balogun</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>DTO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants used by Ribeirinhos in the North Araguaia microregion, Mato Grosso, Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2017</year><volume>205</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28476677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Calhelha</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Due&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos-Buelga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioactivity and chemical characterization in hydrophilic and lipophilic compounds of Chenopodium ambrosioides L</article-title><source>J Funct Foods</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1732</fpage><lpage>1740</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganeshpurkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saluja</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pharmacological potential of rutin</article-title><source>Saudi Pharm J</source><year>2017</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28344465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics and metabolism of dietary flavonoids in humans</article-title><source>Free Radic Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15493450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodbelt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Absorption, conjugation and efflux of the flavonoids, kaempferol and galangin, using the intestinal CaCo-2/TC7 cell model</article-title><source>J Funct Foods</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20046888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential chemical structure of anti-SARS-CoV-2 RNA-dependent RNA polymerase</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>2020</year><volume>92</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32167173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Belew</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4 automated docking with selective receptor flexibility</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>2785</fpage><lpage>2791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19399780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maciel</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Valentim</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunomura</surname><given-names>RCS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and inhibition evaluation of new benzyltetrahydroprotoberberine alkaloids designed as acetylcholinesterase inhibitors</article-title><source>Front Chem</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31620424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the RNA-dependent RNApolymerase from COVID-19 virus</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020</year><volume>368</volume><issue>6492</issue><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32277040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trott</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDockVina improving the speed and accuracy of docking with a new scoring function, efficient optimization, and multithreading</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19499576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Discovery Studio Visualizer</collab></person-group><source>AccelrysInc</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive insights into the catalytic mechanism of middle east respiratory syndrome 3C-Like protease and severe acute respiratory syndrome 3C-Like protease</article-title><source>ACS Catal</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>5871</fpage><lpage>5890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32391184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyupoglu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarfraz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasul</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of potent COVID-19 main protease (Mpro) inhibitors from natural polyphenols: an in silico strategy unveils a hope against CORONA</article-title><source>Preprints</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20944/preprints202003.0333.v1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on plant-based rutin extraction methods and its pharmacological activities</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2013</year><volume>150</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24184193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary avonoid aglycones and their glycosides: Which show better biological signi?cance?</article-title><source>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutri</source><year>2017</year><volume>57</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1874</fpage><lpage>1905</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Middleton-Junior</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogra</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiviral effect of flavonoids on human viruses</article-title><source>J Med Virol</source><year>1985</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2981979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quercetin as an antiviral agent inhibits in uenza A virus (IAV) entry</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new anti-HIV flavonoid glucuronide from Chrysanthemum morifolium</article-title><source>Planta Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>69</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14598216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-in ammatory, antiviral and quantitative study of quercetin-3-O-&#x000df;-D-glucuronide in Polygonum perfoliatum L</article-title><source>Fitoterapia</source><year>2011</year><volume>82</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21570451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro anti-HIV and -HSV activity and safety of sodium rutin sulfate as a microbicide candidate</article-title><source>Antiviral Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>75</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17459492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pathological report of three COVID-19 cases by minimally invasive autopsies</article-title><source>Chinese Journal of Pathology</source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32172546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Piloto</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Morinaga</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jardim</surname><given-names>CVP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamy</surname><given-names>SAED</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heparin therapy improving hypoxia in COVID-19 patients - a case series</article-title><source>MedRxiv</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thachil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The versatile heparin in COVID-19</article-title><source>J Thromb Haemost</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1020</fpage><lpage>1022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32239799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabassum</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rutin-potent natural thrombolytic agent</article-title><source>Int Cur Pharm J</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>435</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rutin decreases lipopolysaccharide-induced acute lung injury via inhibition of oxidative stress and the MAPK-NF-kappaB pathway</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24486341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Naqvi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashafaq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Samim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rutin-encapsulated chitosan nanoparticles targeted to the brain in the treatment of cerebral ischemia</article-title><source>Int J Biol Macromol</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>640</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27264648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishak</surname><given-names>RAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamel</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stealth lipid polymer hybrid nanoparticles loaded with rutin for effective brain delivery - comparative study with the gold standard (Tween 80) optimization, characterization and biodistribution</article-title><source>Drug Deliv</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1874</fpage><lpage>1890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29191047</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>