<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_SJBS2082 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Saudi J Biol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Saudi J Biol Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Saudi Journal of Biological Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1319-562X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2213-7106</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7878694</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1319-562X(20)30645-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.11.082</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Combined <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in silico</italic> approach to evaluate the inhibitory potential of an underutilized allium vegetable and its pharmacologically active compounds on multidrug resistant Candida species</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name><surname>Uma Maheshwari Nallal</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010"><name><surname>Padmini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015"><name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Soon Woong</given-names></name><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025"><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030"><name><surname>Almoallim</surname><given-names>Hesham Saleh M.</given-names></name><xref rid="af025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au035"><name><surname>Alharbi</surname><given-names>Sulaiman Ali</given-names></name><xref rid="af030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au040"><name><surname>Razia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><email>razia581@gmail.com</email><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Department of Biotechnology, Mother Teresa Women&#x02019;s University, Kodaikanal, Tamil Nadu 624101, India</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Department of Biochemistry &#x00026; Bioinformatics, Dr. MGR Janaki College of Arts and Science, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600028, India</aff><aff id="af015"><label>c</label>Department of Environmental Energy Engineering, Kyonggi University, Suwon, South Korea</aff><aff id="af020"><label>d</label>P.G and Research Department of Botany, Jamal Mohamed College (Autonomous), Affiliated to Bharathidasan University, Tiruchirappalli, Tamil Nadu 620020, India</aff><aff id="af025"><label>e</label>Department of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, College of Dentistry, King Saud University, PO Box 60169, Riyadh 11545, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="af030"><label>f</label>Department of Botany &#x00026; Microbiology, College of Science, King Saud University, P.O Box 2455, Riyadh 11451, Saudi Arabia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>razia581@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>08</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1246</fpage><lpage>1256</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab005"><p>Candida infections and related mortality have become a challenge to global health. Nontoxic and natural bioactive compounds from plants are regarded as promising candidates to inhibit these multidrug resistant strains. In the present study, <italic>in vitro</italic> assays and <italic>in silico</italic> molecular docking approach was combined to evaluate the inhibitory effect of crude extracts from <italic>Allium ampeloprasum</italic> and its variety <italic>A. porrum</italic> on Candida pathogens. Phytochemical screening revealed the presence of phenolic acids and flavonoids in higher quantity. Spectral studies of the extracts support the presence of phenols, flavonoids and organosulfur compounds. Aqueous extract of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> showed a total antioxidant capacity of 68&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.7&#x000a0;mg AAE/ g and an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.88&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.1&#x000a0;mg/ml was obtained for DPPH radicals scavenging assay. <italic>C. albicans</italic> were highly susceptible (19.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1&#x000a0;mm) when treated with aqueous <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract. Minimum inhibitory concentrations were within the range of 19&#x02013;40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml and the results were significant (p&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.05). <italic>In silico</italic> molecular docking studies demonstrated that bioactive phytocompounds of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> efficiently interacted with the active site of Secreted aspartyl proteinase 2 enzyme that is responsible for the virulence of pathogenic yeasts. Rosmarinic acid and Myricetin exhibited low binding energies and higher number of hydrogen bond interactions with the protein target. Thus the study concludes that <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> that remain as underutilized vegetables in the <italic>Allium</italic> genus are potential anti-candida agents and their pharmacologically active compounds must be considered as competent candidates for drug discovery.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kg005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>A. porrum</italic></kwd><kwd>Antioxidant activity</kwd><kwd>Anti-candida activity</kwd><kwd>Molecular docking</kwd><kwd>Candidapepsin 2</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0005">Candida species are the most prevalent group of yeast pathogens that are capable of invading the human system. These pathogens can exist as commensals without causing complications until they are regulated by the co-existing microbiota. They occur as superficial infections in hospitalized or immunocompromised victim right after surgery (<xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Bassetti et al. 2018</xref>). Growth and spread of opportunistic candida spp. can trigger minor to severe conditions such as oral thrush, vaginal thrush, gential infections, skin infections, urinary tract infections, and blood stream infections. <italic>Candida albicans</italic> are the leading cause of mucosal infections, but other non-albican species like <italic>C. glabrata</italic>, <italic>C. krusei</italic>, <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic>, <italic>C. tropicalis, C. auris</italic> and <italic>C. haemulonii</italic> can also asymptomatically colonize the human biota (<xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Berkow and Lockhart 2017</xref>). Candidiasis and candidemia have become a global health crisis as more than 250,000 inhabitants are susceptible to these infections every year (<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Arendrup and Patterson 2017</xref>). Azole group drugs (Ketoconazole, Fluconazole, Econazole, Terconazole, Butoconazole and Miconazole) have been recognized as effective therapeutic strategy to combat candida infections but the incessant and redundant use of these drugs have led to the development of multidrug resistant strains of Candida species (<xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">Siwek et al. 2012</xref>).</p><p id="p0010">The mode of action of the azole drugs generally involves the inhibition of 14&#x003b1;-lanosterol demethylase, a vital enzyme required for the biosynthesis of ergosterol, a specific sterol associated with the yeast membrane. Depletion of ergosterol results in the instability of the cell membrane and when combined with the intracellular accumulation of 14&#x003b1; methylated sterols, the membrane and organelle functions can collapse (<xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Hoot et al., 2010</xref>). The recent finding in the mode of action suggests that azoles tend to increase the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) in <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Inhibition of catalases and peroxidases by the drugs can aggravate the generation of ROS resulting in intracellular stress (<xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Dbouk et al. 2019</xref>). It is possible that non-albican species can exert intrinsic resistance to the azole drugs. Moreover, due to incessant and redundant use of these drugs, Candida species have become resistant to the antifungal agents and emerged as multidrug resistant pathogens. When ERG 11 gene associated with production of ergosterol is inactivated by the antifungal agent, pathogens utilize alternative sterols for membrane functions and stability. Nevertheless inhibition of intracellular sterol production has been matched by the uptake of extracellular sterol intake. Other mechanisms involve the over expression of ERG 11 gene, MDR 1p and CDR1p/CDR 2p and activation of TAC<sub>1</sub> gene. High level resistance is observed in Candida species that lose heterozygosity assisted by hyperactive TAC<sub>1</sub> and mutated ERG11 (<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Arendrup and Patterson, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">Siwek et al., 2012</xref>). On the other hand the redundant consumption of azole drugs can lead to side effects such as nausea, vomiting, upset stomach, headache, dizziness, drowsiness, numbness, tingling sensation at nerve endings, rashes, discolouration of the skin, hair loss, decreased sense of taste, abdominal cramps, irritation of genital organs, impotency, adrenal insufficiency and hormone imbalance (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Benitez and Carver 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">The harmless commensal yeast species tends to become a virulent pathogen when opportunities are offered to transverse the barriers on the account of immunosuppression. The key hydrolytic enzymes that assist in the virulence build-up of these yeast species are secreted aspartyl proteinases (SAP), phospholipase B enzymes, and lipases. Almost all Candida spp. show the presence of SAP enzymes that are encoded by ten SAP genes (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Chaffin 2008</xref>). SAP is synthesized as preproenzyme which contains more than 60 amino acids and are processed and transported through the Golgi apparatus to the extracellular membrane. Increase in SAP production has been correlated with the increase in the virulence of <italic>C. albicans</italic> species. <italic>C. albicans</italic> strains isolated from heavily infected candidiasis patients are more proteolytic than the strains obtained from asymptomatic patients. Patients with advanced HIV infections have selection towards virulent proteolytic strains of <italic>C. albicans</italic> when compared to early stage patients (<xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Mani et al. 2016</xref>). Investigation has shown that exposure to anti-candida agents such as azoles can up-regulate the expression of SAP2 gene, conferring resistance towards the agent. It is plausible that this can be a response attempted by the pathogen to overcome the inhibition of other genes (<xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Barelle et al. 2008</xref>). Moreover SAP2 is one of the leading vaccine candidates and has a deep rooted function in candida virulence. Targeting the SAP2 enzyme is rather important because they play a crucial role in cleaving the hydrophobic amino acids in the host protein especially at the site of phenylalanines (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Ghadjari et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Naglik et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">Shukla and Rohatgi, 2020</xref>). Therefore the challenge in treating candida infections is to identify a safe, cost-effective and potent anti-fungal nil or infrequent side effects.</p><p id="p0020">Plants are well known for their medicinal expertise since ancient times. Plant based medicine and traditional medicine is practised nearly by half of the population in developing and under developed nations (<xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Al-Dhabi et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Bin et al., 2020</xref>). Secondary metabolites are inducible in nature and are generally produced by the plants as a response to pathogen attacks. Compounds such as flavonoids, phenols, terpenoids, tannins, have significant toxicity and high molecular weight which makes them potent antifungal agents (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Al-Dhabi and Arasu, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Barathikannan et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">Seca and Pinto, 2019</xref>). Allium genus vegetables that belong to Amaryllidaceae family have remarkable medicinal properties and important ingredient of folklore medicine. <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> (wild leeks) and its variety <italic>A. porrum</italic> (cultivated leeks) are a part of a few cuisines and one of the least studied dietary allium vegetable. The well-known species of the <italic>Allium</italic> genus are onion (<italic>A. cepa</italic>) and garlic (<italic>A. sativum</italic>) which are consumed in everyday human diet and subjected to various biological studies (<xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Bianchini and Vainio 2001</xref>). <italic>A. cepa</italic> and <italic>A. sativum</italic> are potential antimicrobial agents and a recent study reports that Silver nanoparticles synthesized from these species have shown to exert antimicrobial activity against vaginal pathogens Streptococcus pneumoniae&#x000a0;and&#x000a0;Pseudomonas aeruginosa (<xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Bouqellah et al., 2018</xref>). Novel bioactive metabolites from A. sativum have been recently identified as potent anti-cancer drug targets (<xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">Padmini et al., 2020</xref>). Numerous other vegetables under the <italic>Allium</italic> genus have significant medicinal values but still remain unrecognized and underutilized. Like other Allium species, leeks are superior sources of secondary metabolites that include flavonoids, phenolic acids and their derivatives that medicinal values and health benefits (<xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Dey and Khaled, 2015</xref>). <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> are regarded as low energy foods and are reported to have comparatively higher amounts of fibre and zinc than their frequently studied relatives. Additionally they are rich in linoleic acid and bioactive compounds that can revolutionize the current diet (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Ilavenil et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Valsalam et al., 2019</xref>). Few studies show that leeks possess anti-helmintic, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, antimicrobial and anti-cancer properties (<xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Maidment et al., 2001</xref>, <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">Sunaica et al., 2009</xref>). Moreover plant compounds are known to exert least side effects and they have the major advantage of being a part of the daily diet and a source of prevention as well as cure (<xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Karimi et al. 2015</xref>). In the present study, combined <italic>in vitro</italic> phytochemical analysis, spectral analysis, antioxidant assays, anti-candida assays and <italic>in silico</italic> molecular docking approach has been carried out to evaluate the inhibitory effect of <italic>Allium ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extracts on pathogenic Candida species.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Reagents and plant materials</title><p id="p0025">Solvents and chemicals used in the experiment were analytical grade and purchased from Hi-Media (India). Double distilled water was used throughout the experiment. The plant materials were purchased from a local producer at Kodaikanal mountainous region (Tamil Nadu, India).</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Preparation and extraction of plant material</title><p id="p0030"><italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> are characterized by green stalks and long white stem. The procured plant material was transported to the laboratory, washed twice under running tap water and once with double distilled water. The roots and stalks (10&#x000a0;cm away from the white stem) were separated. The remaining portion was chopped into small sections and dried under shade for 10&#x000a0;days, later powdered in a laboratory grinder and stored in air tight containers at room temperature. The extracts were prepared by cold percolation method, the plant powders were weighed and added to different solvent and left for 72&#x000a0;h. The extracts were filtered using Whatman filter paper, grade 1 (11&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m pore size), evaporated and stored for further analysis at 4 &#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Phytochemical analysis</title><sec id="s0030"><label>2.3.1</label><title>Qualitative phytochemical analysis</title><p id="p0035">Preliminary phytochemical screening was done using the procedures of <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Harborne, 1984</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Brunton, 1995</xref>, <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">Wagner et al., 1984</xref>. The extracts were screened for the presence of alkaloids, flavonoids, phenols, saponins, tannins and glycosides.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.3.2</label><title>Quantitative determination of total phenolic content</title><p id="p0040">Total phenolic content (TPC) was determined by Folin-Ciocalteu method according to the method of <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Haq et al. (2012)</xref>. The absorbance was measured at 700&#x000a0;nm using Shimadzu UV&#x02013;Visible spectrometer and the calibration curve (<xref rid="s0165" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>) was plotted using Gallic acid as the standard (y&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0078x&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;0.073; R&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.98). TPC was expressed as Gallic Acid Equivalents (GAE)/ g weight.</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.3.3</label><title>Quantitative determination of total flavonoid content</title><p id="p0045">Total flavonoid content (TFC) was determined by Aluminium chloride method as described by <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al. (2002)</xref>. The absorbance was measured at 405&#x000a0;nm using Shimadzu Uv&#x02013;visible spectrometer and the calibration curve (<xref rid="s0165" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>) was plotted using Quercetin as standard (y&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0056x&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;0.1939; R&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.98). TFC was expressed as Quercetin Equivalents (QE) /g weight.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.4</label><title>Spectral studies</title><sec id="s0050"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Absorption spectroscopy</title><p id="p0050">Ultra Violet-Visible (UV&#x02013;Vis) spectroscopic analysis was performed to identify the presence of phytoconstituents in the plant extracts. The aqueous plant extracts (mg/ml concentration) were dissolved in double distilled water and the spectroscopic analysis was carried out in Shimadzu UV&#x02013;Vis spectrophotometer UV-2600 in the range 200&#x02013;800&#x000a0;nm (<xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Elgubbi et al. 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><label>2.4.2</label><title>Vibrational spectroscopy</title><p id="p0055">Fourier transform Infrared (FTIR) spectroscopic analysis was performed to identify the functional groups present in the plant extracts. 0.1&#x000a0;mg of the dry plant extracts of macerated gently with Potassium bromide and processed to obtain a transparent pellet. The pellet was analysed using Perkin Elmer spectrum 100&#x000a0;N in the range 4000&#x02013;500&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Elgubbi et al. 2019</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>2.5</label><title>Determination of antioxidant activity</title><p id="p0060">Antioxidant activity of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extracts were determined using different invitro antioxidant assays. DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl) radical scavenging assay was done according to <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Manzocco et al. (1998)</xref> and the absorbance was recorded at 517&#x000a0;nm. The ability of the samples to scavenge H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (Hydrogen peroxide) radicals was determined using the method of <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Ruch et al. (1989)</xref> and the absorbance was measured at 230&#x000a0;nm. ABTS (2, 2&#x02032;-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid)) is a commonly employed invitro assay to determine the antioxidant activity of a sample. Absorbance was measure for the samples at 750&#x000a0;nm according to the method of <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Seeram et al. (2006)</xref>. FRAP (Ferric Reducing Antioxidant Power) analysis was done to evaluate the reducing power of the extracts. It was carried out according to the method of <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Oyaizu (1986)</xref> and the absorbance was measured at 700&#x000a0;nm. Phosphomolybdenum assay was done to study the total antioxidant capacity by the method described by <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Prieto et al. (1999)</xref>. The absorbance of the samples was recorded at 695&#x000a0;nm. All the assays were carried out in triplicates.</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>2.6</label><title><italic>In vitro</italic> determination of anticandida activity</title><sec id="s0070"><label>2.6.1</label><title>Agar well diffusion method</title><p id="p0065">The anti-candida activity of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extracts was evaluated against 5 Candida species; <italic>C. albicans</italic> -MTCC 183, <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> -MTCC 184, <italic>C. glabrata -</italic>MTCC 3019, <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> MTCC &#x02212;7043 and <italic>C. krusei</italic> -MTCC 9215. Candida strains were acquired from Microbial Type Culture Collection and Gene Bank (MTCC), Chandigarh, India. Candida cultures were preserved in Potato dextrose agar (PDA) slant at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The culture was incubated in Potato dextrose broth (PDB), overnight in incubator cum shaker at 35&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The optical density of the candida culture suspensions were adjusted to 0.5 McFarland standards. Individual inoculum contained approximately 10<sup>7</sup> CFU/mL. Well diffusion assay was used to determine the anticandida activity of the extracts. PDA was sterilized and poured into autoclaved petridishes. 0.2&#x000a0;ml of various strains of Candida species were uniformly spread on individual petridishes. Plates were allowed to stand for 10&#x000a0;min to facilitate the absorption of the inoculum on the agar. Wells were then cut on the culture media and various dilutions of aqueous <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extract (50 and 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l/ml) were added to each well. Amphotericin B was used as the standard. The plates were incubated at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x000a0;h. After 24&#x000a0;h the inhibition zone diameters were measured and expressed in millimetres.</p></sec><sec id="s0075"><label>2.6.2</label><title>Minimum inhibitory concentration by broth macrodilution</title><p id="p0070">The procured candida pathogens were allowed to grow for 24&#x000a0;h on sterile PDA plates at 37 &#x000b0;C. Sterile test tubes containing 5&#x000a0;ml of Potato dextrose broth were inoculated with candida pathogens that were previously grown in the same medium and adjusted to 0.5 McFarland scale. Two fold dilutions of the aqueous plant extract was added to the suspension medium, thoroughly mixed and incubated for 24&#x000a0;h at 37 &#x000b0;C. MIC of the drug was observed as the concentration at which more than 75% of the candida growth was inhibited in the broth. Amphotericin B was used as the standard antifungal agent (<xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Balouiri et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0080"><label>2.7</label><title><italic>In silico</italic> determination of anti-candida activity by molecular docking</title><p id="p0075">Molecular docking was performed for fifteen bioactive compounds from <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> based on literature and is depicted in the Supplementary Table 1. Molecular docking was performed with AutoDockv4.2.3 in order to predict the binding and structure of the intermolecular complex between the drug targets and the identified phytocompounds. The search methods used are simulated annealing, Genetic Algorithm (GA) and the Lamarckian Genetic Algorithm (LGA). The most efficient and reliable method is LGA (<xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Morris et al. 1998</xref>). Ligands were prepared by retrieving the structures of identified phytocompounds from PubChem database. The structure of drug target was pre-processed by removing ligands, heteroatoms and water molecules from their respective PDB crystal structures (<xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Morris et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Morris et al., 1998</xref>). A grid maps for all atom types of target was generated independently along with electrostatic and desolvation maps by fixing the grid box of 90&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;90&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;90 points with AutoGrid utility. The grid spacing was set to 0.375&#x000a0;&#x000c5; and was centered based on the co-crystallized inhibitors of the respective drug target (<xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">Saravanan et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Padmini et al., 2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>2.8</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0080">The results are expressed as mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard error. One way ANOVA was carried out to determine the significance of the tests with p&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.05 significance level. Microsoft excel 2010, SPSS Version 19.0, Origin Pro 8 packages were used for the analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0090"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0095"><label>3.1</label><title>Preliminary analysis</title><sec id="s0100"><label>3.1.1</label><title>Qualitative phytochemical screening of crude extracts</title><p id="p0085">The plant extracts were screened for various classes of phytocompounds. The results are represented in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Flavonoids were present in all the solvent extracts of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic>. Aqueous extract of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> showed the presence of alkaloids, flavonoids, saponins, terpenoids, phenols and glycosides whereas alkaloids were absent in the <italic>A. porrum</italic> aqueous extract. Phytochemicals were effectively extracted in polar and mid-polar solvents rather than non-polar solvent which were evident in the results of hexane extract.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Phytochemical screening of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extracts.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><bold>Phytochemicals</bold></th><th colspan="4"><bold><italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic></bold><hr/></th><th colspan="4"><bold><italic>A. porrum</italic></bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th/><th><bold>M</bold></th><th><bold>Aq</bold></th><th><bold>Ac</bold></th><th><bold>H</bold></th><th><bold>M</bold></th><th><bold>Aq</bold></th><th><bold>Ac</bold></th><th><bold>H</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Alkaloids</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Flavonoids</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Saponins</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Terpenoids</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Phenols</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Glycosides</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>+</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0040"><p>M: Methanol; Aq: Aqueous; Ac: Acetone; H: Hexane.</p></fn><fn id="sp0045"><p>+: presence of phytochemicals; &#x02212;: absence of phytochemicals.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0105"><label>3.1.2</label><title>Quantification of total phenolic and flavonoid compounds</title><p id="p0090">The total phenol content in the aqueous extract of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> was 14.35&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01&#x000a0;mg GAE/g which was higher than the other extracts. The least was quantified in hexane extract of <italic>A. porrum</italic> (1.96&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;02&#x000a0;mg GAE/g). Flavonoid content in the extracts of both plants was superior when compared to the total phenolics content. The highest amount of flavonoid content was quantified in aqueous extract of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> (19.83&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02&#x000a0;mg QE/g). Methanol and acetone extracts also showed considerable amounts of total phenolics and flavonoids (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Total phenol and flavonoid content in <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum.</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"><bold>Extract</bold></th><th colspan="4"><bold>Total Phenolic Content (mg GAE/g)</bold><xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><hr/></th><th colspan="4"><bold>Total flavonoid Content (mg QE/g)</bold><xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th><bold>M</bold></th><th><bold>Aq</bold></th><th><bold>Ac</bold></th><th><bold>H</bold></th><th><bold>M</bold></th><th><bold>Aq</bold></th><th><bold>Ac</bold></th><th><bold>H</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><bold><italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic></bold></td><td>8.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07</td><td>14.35&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01</td><td>10.56&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td><td>3.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;01</td><td>15.26&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07</td><td>19.83&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td><td>9.34&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01</td><td>1.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td></tr><tr><td><bold><italic>A. porrum</italic></bold></td><td>7.16&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td><td>13.52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07</td><td>10.33&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01</td><td>1.96&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;02</td><td>11.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td><td>17.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;01</td><td>11.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td><td>0.81&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>M: Methanol; Aq: Aqueous; Ac: Acetone; H: Hexane.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p id="np005"><bold>Mean values (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3)&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard error.</bold></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0110"><label>3.2</label><title>Spectroscopic analysis</title><sec id="s0115"><label>3.2.1</label><title>Analysis of phytocompounds absorption spectra by UV&#x02013;Visible spectroscopy</title><p id="p0095">The qualitative UV&#x02013;Vis spectrum of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> aqueous extracts are represented in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Absorption bands were obtained at 236&#x000a0;nm and 275&#x000a0;nm for both the extracts and an additional band was observed for <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract at 316&#x000a0;nm.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig.1</label><caption><p>UV&#x02013;Visible spectrum of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> aqueous extracts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0120"><label>3.2.2</label><title>Identification of functional groups by FT-IR analysis</title><p id="p0100">FT-IR analysis was carried out to identify the functional groups of bioactive compounds present in the aqueous extracts of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum.</italic> Peaks obtained and their assigned functional groups are given in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>. Absorption bands were obtained at 3398.10&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 2937.37&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1644.76&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1129.4&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1054&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1017.91&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 625.04&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for aqueous A. ampeloprasum extract, whereas characteristic peaks were attained at 3418&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 2922.21&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1615.07&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1315.61&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1263.01&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1106.69&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 678.25&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The FT-IR spectrum of both the extracts confirmed the presence of alcohols, amides, aromatics, amines, carboxylic acid and disulphide groups. Additionally, sulfoxide group was identified in <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract.<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>FTIR spectrum illustrating identified functional groups in <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> aqueous extracts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0125"><label>3.3</label><title><italic>In vitro</italic> free radical scavenging, reducing power and total antioxidant capacity</title><p id="p0105">Results represented in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a and 3b showed that <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract was effective in scavenging the DPPH, ABTS and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> radicals when compared to <italic>A. porrum</italic>. IC<sub>50</sub> values of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> aqueous extracts were 0.88&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.1&#x000a0;mg/ml (DPPH assay), 1.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6&#x000a0;mg/ml (ABTS assay) and 0.93&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2&#x000a0;mg/ml (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> assay), whereas aqueous extract of <italic>A. porrum</italic> exhibited IC<sub>50</sub> values of 1.12&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1&#x000a0;mg/ml, 1.50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.5&#x000a0;mg/ml and 1.05&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.5&#x000a0;mg/ml for DPPH, ABTS and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> assays respectively. The inhibition activity of the extracts increased with the increase in the concentration and thus is dose dependent. The IC<sub>50</sub> value of Ascorbic acid was 0.33&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2&#x000a0;mg/ml and 0.39&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1&#x000a0;mg/ml for DPPH and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> assay respectively, Trolox exhibited an IC<sub>50</sub> value 0.59&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.3&#x000a0;mg/ml for ABTS assay. Results of FRAP assay as presented in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>c revealed that the reducing power of the extracts was concentration dependent and an increase was observed in the absorbance of the samples at higher sample concentrations. The maximum absorbance recorded was 2.35 for 1000&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract. 68&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.78&#x000a0;mg AAE/ g and 60.57&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6&#x000a0;mg AAE/ g was found to be the total antioxidant capacity of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extract at g/ml concentration as estimated by Phosphomolybdenum assay (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>d).<fig id="f0015"><label>Fig.3</label><caption><p>(a) Free radical scavenging activity of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract, (b) Free radical scavenging activity of <italic>A. porrum</italic> extract, (c) Reducing power of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and A<italic>. porrum</italic> extracts (d) Total antioxidant capacity of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extracts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0130"><label>3.4</label><title><italic>In vitro</italic> anticandida activity</title><sec id="s0135"><label>3.4.1</label><title>Zone of inhibitions determined by agar well diffusion assay</title><p id="p0110">Aqueous extract of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> showed significant anticandida activity against the treated pathogens. Negative control i.e., distilled water did not exhibit anticandida activity. <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a shows that the maximum zone was observed for <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract against <italic>C. albicans</italic> (19.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1&#x000a0;mm). The inhibitory activity of aqueous <italic>A. porrum</italic> extract was also high against <italic>C. albicans</italic> and a 19.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3&#x000a0;mm zone was observed. The susceptibility of <italic>C. glabrata</italic> was less when compared to the other organisms as represented in <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b. 12.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.8&#x000a0;mm and 8.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1&#x000a0;mm zones were observed against <italic>C. glabrata</italic> when treated with <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extract respectively. The zones of inhibition for <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, <italic>C. krusei</italic> and <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> were within the range of 15&#x02013;19&#x000a0;mm. The results revealed that the inhibitory action of the extracts used was dose dependent. The zone of inhibition observed for Amphotericin B was within the range of 16&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2&#x02013;21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9&#x000a0;mm for the tested pathogens.<fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>(a) Zone of inhibitions of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> (Aa) and <italic>A. porrum</italic> (Ap) at 50 and 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ ml against (a) <italic>C. albicans</italic>, (b) <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, (c) <italic>C. krusei</italic>, (d) <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> and (e) C. <italic>glabrata.</italic> (b) Statistical comparison of anticandida activity of extracts with standard error.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0140"><label>3.4.2</label><title>Minimum inhibitory concentration determined by broth dilution method</title><p id="p0115"><italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extracts were tested for their MIC in serially diluted concentrations. Analysis of Variance (One way ANOVA) revealed that the results were statistically significant (p&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.05). Results presented in <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> show that the lowest MIC was observed against <italic>C. albicans</italic> when treated with both extracts individually which showed that <italic>C. albicans</italic> were the most susceptible organism. As observed in anticandida activity by well diffusion method, <italic>C. glabrata</italic> was the least susceptible organism and a concentration of 33&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ ml of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> extract and 40&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.9&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ ml of <italic>A. porrum</italic> extract were required to inhibit the organism. The MIC of Amphotericin B was observed in the range 10&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3&#x02013;17&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.7&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ ml.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Minimum inhibitory concentrations of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> aqueous extracts for Candida pathogens.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"><bold>Candida Species</bold></th><th colspan="2"><bold>Minimum Inhibitory concentration (&#x003bc;g/ml)</bold><xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref><hr/></th></tr><tr><th><bold><italic>A. ampeloprasum extract</italic></bold></th><th><bold><italic>A. porrum extract</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>C. albicans</italic></td><td>19&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.5</td><td>21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.9</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C. tropicalis</italic></td><td>24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6</td><td>25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.4</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C. krusei</italic></td><td>25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.9</td><td>40&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.1</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C. glabarata</italic></td><td>33&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.9</td><td>40&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.9</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C. parapsilosi</italic></td><td>22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0</td><td>35&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><label>a</label><p id="np010">Mean (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5)&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard error, with significant differences at P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0145"><label>3.5</label><title><italic>In silico</italic> molecular docking to determine the interaction of phytocompounds at the active site of SAP 2 enzyme</title><p id="p0120">Results obtained from <italic>in silico</italic> molecular docking studies performed by Autodock software elucidated the interaction between ligands and target. Selected compounds from organo sulphur, phenol and flavonoid groups satisfied the Lipinski&#x02019;s rule of five that includes criteria such as molecular weight, log P (&#x0003c;+5.6), hydrogen donors (&#x0003c;5), hydrogen acceptors (&#x0003c;10) and molecular refractivity within the range of 40&#x02013;130 (Supplementary Table 2). The active site of SAP-2 enzyme was docked with the phytocompounds from <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic>. The three dimensional structure of SAP 2 enzyme is represented in <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a. Ligands with greater affinity range indicated stronger binding of the compounds with the enzyme. Among the organosulfur compounds S allyl cysteine had the lowest binding energy of &#x02212;4.27&#x000a0;kcal/mol and three hydrogen bond interactions with amino acids Glu202 and Lys271 (2) at the active site of SAP 2 enzyme. Rosmarinic acid showed a binding energy of &#x02212;5.98&#x000a0;kcal/mol which was the lowest among the phenolic acids, hydrogen bond interactions were observed between amino acids such as Glu202 (2), Ser182, Ser180, Gln329, Ser273 and Lys271 present in the active site of the enzyme. Myricetin exhibited a binding energy of &#x02212;6.11&#x000a0;kcal/mol and hydrogen bond interactions was visible between amino acids such as Ser282, Ser277, Glu278, Pro162, Asn9 (2) and Gln11. Rosmarinic acid and Myricetin formed the highest number of hydrogen bonds (7 bonds) with the active site of the enzyme (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Binding efficiency is higher in compounds that have the negative binding energy and the number of hydrogen bond determine the binding strength. The two dimensional and three dimensional interactions of S Allyl cysteine, Rosmarinic acid and Myricetin with SAP 2 enzyme are depicted in <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>(b-d).<fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>(a) Three dimensional representation of SAP protein (PDB ID:3PVK), 2D and 3D representation with 3PVK structure of (b) S allyl cysteine, (c) Rosmarinic acid (d) Myricetin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><italic>In silico</italic> molecular docking study of phytocompounds and their interactions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th><bold>S. No</bold></th><th><bold>Phytochemical active compounds</bold></th><th><bold>Binding energy (kcal/mol)</bold></th><th><bold>Hydrogen bond interactions</bold></th><th><bold>No of h-bond</bold></th><th><bold>Hydrogen bond interacting residues</bold></th><th><bold>Hydrogen bond distance</bold> (&#x000c5;)</th><th><bold>Other interactions</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td>Diallyl disulfide</td><td>&#x02212;3.54</td><td>LEU296</td><td><break/>1</td><td>LEU296(HN&#x02026;S)<break/></td><td>3.05</td><td>GLN295,LEU297,ILE223,<break/>TYR252,PHE251,ILE235,<break/>PHE298,ASP229<break/></td></tr><tr><td/><td>Diallyl trisulfide</td><td>&#x02212;3.56</td><td>GLN329</td><td><break/>1</td><td>GLN329(HN&#x02026;S)</td><td>2.52</td><td>ALA270,LEU327,ILE272,<break/>VAL263,LYS271</td></tr><tr><td/><td><bold>S allyl cysteine</bold></td><td><bold>&#x02212;4.27</bold></td><td><bold>GLU202,LYS271[2]</bold></td><td><break/><bold>3</bold></td><td><bold>GLU202(OE2&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>LYS271(HZ2&#x02026;O)</bold><break/><bold>LYS271(HZ1&#x02026;O)</bold></td><td><bold>2.26</bold><break/><bold>1.71</bold><break/><bold>2.13</bold></td><td><bold>VAL263</bold></td></tr><tr><td/><td>Ajoene</td><td>&#x02212;3.65</td><td>ILE223,TYR225</td><td>2</td><td>TYR225(HH&#x02026;O)<break/>ILE223(HN&#x02026;O)</td><td>2.20<break/>2.32</td><td>ILE305,ILE123,ILE30</td></tr><tr><td/><td>S allyl mercapto cysteine</td><td>&#x02212;3.02</td><td>LYS81,GLN91</td><td>2</td><td>LYS81(HZ1&#x02026;0)<break/>GLN91(HE2&#x02026;0)</td><td>1.70<break/>2.20</td><td>SER90,SER118,GLN48,<break/>THR117,SER116,SER89,<break/>GLY87</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Gallic acid</td><td>&#x02212;4.8</td><td>SER180,LYS271[2],SER182</td><td>4</td><td>SER180(O&#x02026;H)<break/>LYS271(O&#x02026;H)<break/>LYS271(O&#x02026;H)<break/>SER182(O&#x02026;H)<break/><break/></td><td>1.85<break/>1.74<break/>1.81<break/>2.11<break/></td><td>LEU183,TYR179GLY181,<break/>GLN329,ILE272,ILE184,<break/>ALA270,A269,ALA328</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Ferulic acid</td><td>&#x02212;5.02</td><td>ASP138,ASN153,ASP321,<break/>LYS145,LYS129</td><td><break/>5</td><td>ASP138(OD1&#x02026;H)<break/>ASN153(HD22&#x02026;O)<break/>ASP321(OD1&#x02026;H)<break/>LYS129(HZ1&#x02026;O)<break/>LYS145(HZ1&#x02026;O)<break/></td><td>1.94<break/>1.96<break/>1.71<break/>2.29<break/>2.52</td><td>LYS146,LEU320,VAL142</td></tr><tr><td/><td><bold>Rosmarinic acid</bold><break/></td><td><bold>&#x02212;5.98</bold></td><td><bold>GLU202[2],SER182,SER180</bold><break/><bold>GLN329,SER273,LYS271</bold></td><td><bold>7</bold></td><td><bold>GLU202(OE1&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>GLU202(OE1&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>SER182(O&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>SER180(O&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>GLN329(HN&#x02026;O)</bold><break/><bold>SER273(HN&#x02026;O)</bold><break/><bold>LYS271(HZ2&#x02026;O)</bold><break/></td><td><bold>1.79</bold><break/><bold>2.12</bold><break/><bold>2.08</bold><break/><bold>2.23</bold><break/><bold>2.01</bold><break/><bold>2.96</bold><break/><bold>1.69</bold></td><td><bold>ASP261,ILE184,GLY181,</bold><break/><bold>TYR179,ALA328,ILE272,</bold><break/><bold>VAL263</bold></td></tr><tr><td/><td>Sinapinic acid</td><td>&#x02212;5.29</td><td>ASP138,LYS129,LYS145,<break/>ASP321,ASN153</td><td>5</td><td>ASP138(OD&#x02026;H)<break/>LYS129(HZ&#x02026;O)<break/>LYS145(HZ&#x02026;O)<break/>ASP321(OD&#x02026;H)<break/>ASN153(HD&#x02026;O)<break/><break/><break/><break/><break/></td><td>1.82<break/>1.69<break/>2.88<break/>1.87<break/>1.98</td><td>LYS146,VAL142,TYR128,<break/>LEU320</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Caffeic acid</td><td>&#x02212;4.66</td><td>LYS271[2],SER182,LEU27</td><td>4</td><td>LYS271(HZ&#x02026;O)<break/>LYS271(O&#x02026;H)<break/>LEU327(O&#x02026;H)<break/>SER182(O&#x02026;H)</td><td>1.69<break/>1.83<break/>2.81<break/>1.96</td><td>ASN269,ALA270,ILE272,<break/>GLN329,LEU183,ALA328,<break/>GLY181,ILE184</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Naringenin<break/></td><td>&#x02212;6.7</td><td>ASN323,LEU320,THR130,<break/>VAL142</td><td>4</td><td>ASN323(OD&#x02026;H)<break/>LEU320(O&#x02026;H)<break/>THR130(OG&#x02026;H)<break/>VAL142(O&#x02026;H)</td><td>2.22<break/>2.79<break/>2.03<break/>2.03</td><td>ASN153,ASP321,ARG192,<break/>ASP191,LYS129,LYS146,<break/>LYS145,TYR128</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Apigenin</td><td>&#x02212;5.9</td><td>THR6[2],ASP17,THR19</td><td>4</td><td>THR6(HG&#x02026;O)<break/>THR6(O&#x02026;H)<break/>ASP17(HN&#x02026;O)<break/>THR19(OG&#x02026;H)</td><td>2.86<break/>1.81<break/>2.18<break/>2.04</td><td>GLY103,LEU7,ALA16,<break/>GLY102,PHE101,GLY100,<break/>ILE18,ASN24,HIS8,<break/>VAL5</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Quercetin<break/></td><td>&#x02212;6.1</td><td>ASP302[2],ASP211,ASN212,<break/>ASP214</td><td>5</td><td>ASP302(O&#x02026;H)<break/>ASP302(O&#x02026;H)<break/>ASP211(OD&#x02026;H)<break/>ASN212(O&#x02026;H)<break/>ASP214(OD&#x02026;H)</td><td>2.35<break/>2.23<break/>2.20<break/>2.60<break/>1.78</td><td>ALA303,ARG195,ASN304,<break/>GLN227,LEU230,VAL213</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Kaempferol<break/></td><td>&#x02212;6.5</td><td>THR130[2],VAL142,LEU320,<break/>ASN323,ASP321</td><td>6</td><td>THR130(NH&#x02026;O)<break/>THR130(OG&#x02026;H)<break/>VAL142(O&#x02026;H)<break/>LEU320(O&#x02026;H)<break/>ASN323(OD&#x02026;H)<break/>ASP321(OD&#x02026;H)<break/></td><td>1.84<break/>1.93<break/>2.19<break/>2.84<break/>2.27<break/>1.93</td><td>ASP191,ARG192,LYS129,<break/>ASN153,LYS146,TYR128,<break/>LYS145</td></tr><tr><td/><td><bold>Myricetin</bold></td><td><bold>&#x02212;6.11</bold></td><td><bold>SER282,SER277,GLU278,</bold><break/><bold>PRO162,ASN9[2],GLN11,</bold><break/></td><td><bold>7</bold></td><td><bold>SER282(OG&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>SER277(O&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>GLU278(OE&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>PRO162(O&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>ASN9(OD&#x02026;H)</bold><break/><bold>ASN9(HD&#x02026;O)</bold><break/><bold>GLN11(O&#x02026;H)</bold></td><td><bold>2.06</bold><break/><bold>1.97</bold><break/><bold>1.80</bold><break/><bold>1.89</bold><break/><bold>1.96</bold><break/><bold>1.88</bold><break/><bold>2.23</bold></td><td><bold>ALA280,ASP308,THR222,</bold><break/><bold>VAL12,TYR14,ASP163,</bold><break/><bold>ARG312,ALA281</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0150"><label>3.6</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0125">Candida pathogens and related infections have become a major threat to the global health due to their multiple drug resistance traits. Bioactive compounds from higher plants have been a promising source to treat such infections since the time of early drug discovery. Presence of potential active metabolites in Allium vegetables has made them suitable candidates in the pharmaceutical industries. They also exhibit efficient anti-fungal activity against various fungal and yeast pathogens. <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Diba and Alizadeh 2018</xref> have reported the anticandida activity of <italic>A. sativum</italic> and <italic>A. hirtifolium</italic> against clinical isolate of C. tropicalis, whereas <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Mikaili et al 2013</xref> has reported the anticandida activity of <italic>A. sativum</italic> against <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Antifugal activity of <italic>A. cepa</italic> and <italic>A. sativum</italic> against dermatophytes has been reported by <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Latheef et al. 2020</xref>.</p><p id="p0130">The present study focussed on combining the invitro spectral, antioxidant, anticandida studies with <italic>in silico</italic> molecular docking studies to evaluate the inhibitory potential of underutilized Allium vegetable <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and its variety <italic>A. porrum</italic>. It was evident in the preliminary phytochemicals screening that aqueous extracts of both plants showed the presence of numerous phytochemicals when compared to the other extracts. According to <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">Szychowski et al. (2018)</xref> aqueous extracts are found to be efficient in several biological activities due to their efficacy to extricate compounds. Results are in accordance with <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Asemani et al. (2019)</xref> who reports that allium vegetables such as <italic>A. sativum</italic>, <italic>A. cepa</italic>, <italic>A. hirtifolium</italic>, <italic>A. jesidianum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> are a rich source of phytochemicals such as flavonoids, phenolic acids, alkaloids, saponins and organo sulphur compounds. <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2020)</xref> has suggested <italic>A. sativum</italic> as a promising candidate for the treatment of cancer due to the similar active phytocomponents reported in our results. Results of total phenol content was consistent with the reports of <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">Sagar et al. (2020)</xref> and total flavonoid content in the aqueous samples of the present study were parallel to the results of <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Albishi et al. (2013)</xref> in onion samples. The flavonoid content of A. porrum in the present study (17.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;01&#x000a0;mg QE/g) was higher than the results obtained by <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Radovanovic et al. (2015)</xref> for <italic>A. porrum</italic> leaves (10.24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.84&#x000a0;mg QE/g).</p><p id="p0135"><xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Elgubbi et al. (2019)</xref> suggests that the bands in Uv&#x02013;Vis spectrum within the range of 250&#x000a0;nm to 285&#x000a0;nm confirm the presence of flavonoid compounds which supports the results of the present study. Similarly the report also suggests that the presence of hydroxyl and carbonyl groups in the FT-IR spectrum are related to the flavone compounds of the flavonoid group. A study by <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Tasci et al. (2016)</xref> showed that FT-IR spectrum of alliin and allicin in <italic>A. scorodoprasum</italic> showed the presence of OH, COOH, NH<sub>2</sub>, S&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;O, C-O, CN and C-S groups. This finding is consistent with our results from the FT-IR spectrum and suggests that <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> can be good sources of organosulfur compounds and their precursors.</p><p id="p0140">The higher phenol and flavonoid content correlated with the antioxidant activity of the plant sample. Presence of phenols, flavonoids and other phytoconstituents justifies the efficient free radical scavenging activity, reducing power and antioxidant capacity of the tested samples. The results of FRAP assay run parallel to the results of <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Locatelli et al. (2016)</xref> which reported that the dominant organosulfur compounds present in the <italic>allium</italic> vegetables such as allicin and ajoene have high reducing power activity. The antioxidant activity depends on the number of sulfur atoms and their ability to bond; therefore trisulfides are better scavenging agents when compared to disulphide. Allyl methyl disulphide, Methyl propyl sulphide, Dimethyl trisulfide, Dimethyl didulfide, Methyl propyl trisulfide, Propenyl propyl trisulfide are the few sulfur rich compounds reported in leeks (<xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Monika and Abirami, 2018</xref>). Moreover, release of the gasotransmitter Hydrogen sulphide (H<sub>2</sub>S) is one of the most interesting and the least studied free radical scavenging mechanism of organosulfur compounds. Digestion of organosulfur compounds is believed to cause slow release of Hydrogen sulphide (H<sub>2</sub>S) through enzymatic and chemical reactions. H<sub>2</sub>S is reported to be produced in the gut through the digestion of leeks and is considered as an excellent endogenous reducing agent. H<sub>2</sub>S is a highly reactive molecule and can effectively scavenge free radicals such as superoxide radical anion, hydrogen peroxide, hypochlorite and peroxynitrite (<xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">Wen et al. 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0145">The findings of <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Diba and Alizadeh (2018)</xref> demonstrated that aqueous extracts of <italic>A. hirtifolium</italic> and <italic>A. sativum</italic> exhibited significant (p&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.05) anticandida activity against <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, moreover the study suggests that phenols, flavonoids and organo sulphur compounds in the samples were responsible for the anti-candida activity. Similarly our results showed that <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> significantly (p&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.05) inhibited the growth of Candida pathogens and additionally the phytochemicals screening results supports the same. <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Agi and Azike (2019)</xref> suggest that 1&#x000a0;g/ml of fresh <italic>A. sativum</italic> was required to inhibit <italic>C. albicans</italic> whereas our results showed that 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ ml of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> were efficient in inhibiting <italic>C. albicans</italic>. MICs of <italic>A. hirtifolium</italic> and <italic>A. sativum</italic> were 11.66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.36&#x000a0;mg/ml and 21.85&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.57&#x000a0;mg/ml&#x000a0;against <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, however 24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml and 25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml were the determined MICs of <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> extracts required to inhibit <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> in this study. However the findings of the <italic>in vitro</italic> studies showed that wild leeks were rich in phytochemicals and biological properties when compared to the cultivated variety which implies the importance of propagating wild varieties of medicinal plants.</p><p id="p0150">Structure based designing of drugs plays an important role in the development of novel drugs to target several diseases. Molecular docking analysis of selected A<italic>. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> bioactive compounds from the literature against SAP 2 enzyme/Candidapesin 2 demonstrated that organo sulfur compounds, phenolic acids and flavonoids present in the samples can be developed as potential drug candidates to treat candida infections effectively. Several phytocompounds from the plant <italic>Trachyaspermum ammi</italic> were docked against Candidapepsin-1 enzyme, among which Ligustilide showed the lowest binding energy of &#x02212;5.75&#x000a0;kcal/ mol, this was parallel to the docking results of Rosmarinic acid which showed a binding energy of &#x02212;5.98&#x000a0;kcal/mol in our study. However the binding energy of S allyl cysteine (organo sulfur compound) was lower than the compounds reported in <italic>T. ammi</italic> (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Biswal et al. 2019</xref>). The number of hydrogen bonds formed was greater as observed from our docking results of Rosmarinic acid (phenolic acid) and Myricetin (flavonoid). Flavonoids and phenolic compounds exhibited better interactions when compared to the OSCs, this might be due to the low number of hydrogen bond donors and acceptors in the OSCs. Phenolic compounds and flavonoids docked in the study showed higher number of hydrogen bond donors and hydrogen bond acceptors denoting them as potent orally active drugs with low lipophilicity. Further the phenolic compounds and flavonoids present in the allium species can support the activity of the OSCs (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Maharani et al. 2020</xref>). SAP enzymes are considered as the major factors that determine the virulence of Candida spp. Ten SAP enzymes have been reported in <italic>C. albicans</italic>, four types of SAP enzyme have been reported in <italic>C. tropicalis</italic>, eight SAP enzymes have been identified in C. <italic>dubliniensis</italic> and three types of SAP are studied in <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic>. Strikingly none of the SAP enzymes are reported in <italic>C. glabrata</italic> (<xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Parra-Ortega et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Sikora et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Galocha et al., 2019</xref>). The results from the <italic>in vitro</italic> studies and <italic>in silico</italic> molecular docking studies coincide in the assumption that selected phytocompounds might act as effective inhibiting agents of the SAP enzymes that are responsible for the virulence and cell membrane integrity. Additionally, the <italic>in silico</italic> studies gives us a plausible reason as to why <italic>C. glabrata</italic> (absence of SAP enzymes) was the least susceptible species in the <italic>in vitro</italic> studies.</p></sec><sec id="s0155"><label>3.7</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0155">Combination of <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in silico</italic> studies has been carried out for the first time to evaluate the anti-candida potential of the underutilized allium vegetable <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and its variety <italic>A. porrum</italic>. Phenolic acids, flavonoids and organosulfur compounds enhanced the antioxidant property and anticandidal efficacy of the plant extracts. Interaction of the pharmacologically active compounds at the active site of SAP 2/Candidapepsin 2 enzyme with low binding energy and hydrogen bond formation between amino acids provided supporting evidence to the inhibitory activity estimated in the <italic>in vitro</italic> studies. Thus <italic>A. ampeloprasum</italic> and <italic>A. porrum</italic> must be extensively studied like other allium vegetables to evaluate their biological activities and to identify their potential phytocompounds as competent drug of desired therapeutic effect.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0160">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Azike</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal Action of Garlic (Allium sativum) and Ginger (Zingiber officinale) on Some Pathogenic Fungi</article-title><source>Asian J. Res. Biochem.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Khalifa</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic content and antioxidant activities of selected potato varieties and their processing by-products</article-title><source>J. Funct. Foods</source><volume>5</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>600</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0015">Al-Dhabi NA, Arasu MV, Rejiniemon TS. 2015. In vitro antibacterial, antifungal, antibiofilm, antioxidant, and anticancer properties of isosteviol isolated from endangered medicinal plant Pittosporum tetraspermum. Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine.2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0020">Al-Dhabi NA, Arasu MV. 2016. Quantification of phytochemicals from commercial Spirulina products and their antioxidant activities. Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine. 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arendrup</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidrug-Resistant Candida: Epidemiology, Molecular Mechanisms, and Treatment</article-title><source>J. Infect. Dis.</source><volume>216</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>S445</fpage><lpage>S451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28911043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asemani</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamani</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amirghofran</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allium vegetables for possible future of cancer treatment</article-title><source>Phytother Res.</source><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balouiri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadiki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods for <italic>In vitro</italic> evaluating antimicrobial activity: A review</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Anal.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29403965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barathikannan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatadri</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khusro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dhabi</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agastian</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical analysis of Punica granatum fruit peel and its in vitro and in vivo biological properties</article-title><source>BMC Compl. Alternative Med.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>264</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barelle</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gow</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Odds</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Azole antifungals induce up-regulation of SAP4, SAP5 and SAP6 secreted proteinase genes in filamentous Candida albicans cells <italic>In vitro</italic> and in vivo</article-title><source>J. Antimicrob. Chemother.</source><volume>61</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18033783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bassetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Righi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montravers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornely</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What has changed in the treatment of invasive candidiasis? A look at the past 10 years and ahead</article-title><source>J. Antimicrob. Chemother.</source><volume>73</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>i14</fpage><lpage>i25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29304208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benitez</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adverse Effects Associated with Long-Term Administration of Azole Antifungal Agents</article-title><source>Drugs</source><volume>79</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31093949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkow</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluconazole resistance in <italic>Candida</italic> species: a current perspective</article-title><source>Infect Drug Resist</source><volume>10</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28814889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bianchini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vainio</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allium vegetables and organosulfur compounds: do they help prevent cancer?</article-title><source>Environ. Health Perspect.</source><volume>109</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>893</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11673117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dhabi</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmail</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arokiyaraj</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential effect of Allium sativum bulb for the treatment of biofilm forming clinical pathogens recovered from periodontal and dental caries</article-title><source>Saudi J. Biol. Sci.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1428</fpage><lpage>1434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32489278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragunathan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pazhamalai</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romauld</surname><given-names>I.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular docking of various bioactive compounds from essential oil of Trachyaspermum ammi against the fungal enzyme Candidapepsin-1</article-title><source>J. Appl. Pharm. Sci.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouqellah</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of eco-friendly silver nanoparticles using Allium sp. and their antimicrobial potential on selected vaginal bacteria</article-title><source>Saudi J. Biol. Sci</source><volume>26</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1789</fpage><lpage>1794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31762659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Text Book of Pharmacognosy Phytochemistry and Medicinal Plants, Intercept Limited</source><year>1995</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>593</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaffin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candida albicans Cell Wall Proteins</article-title><source>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. reviews</source><volume>72</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>544</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chern</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of Total Flavonoid Content in Propolis by Two Complementary Colorimetric Methods</article-title><source>J Food Drug Anal</source><volume>10</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>182</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dbouk</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Covington</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekaran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increase of reactive oxygen species contributes to growth inhibition by fluconazole in Cryptococcus neoformans</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30616583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An Extensive Review on Allium ampeloprasum A Magical Herb</article-title><source>Int. J. Sci. Res.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>377</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diba</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> and in vivo antifungal activity of Allium hirtifolium and Allium sativum</article-title><source>Avicenna J. Phytomed.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30345234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elgubbi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altajtal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elbath</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical Screening Study and Anti-Candida Evaluation of Acacia raddiana Leaves</article-title><source>EC Nutrition</source><volume>14</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>507</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galocha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pais</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalheiro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Viana</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergent Approaches to Virulence in C. albicans and C. glabrata: Two Sides of the Same Coin</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>2345</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Herrera</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Ruiz</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Mata</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;mara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tardio</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrients, phytochemicals and antioxidant activity in wild populations of Allium ampeloprasum L., a valuable underutilized vegetable</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><volume>62</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghadjari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnie</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epitope mapping Candida albicans proteinase (SAP 2)</article-title><source>FEMS Immunol. Med. Microbiol<italic>.</italic></source><volume>19</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>123</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haq</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanwal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and Cytotoxic activities and phytochemical analysis of Euphorbia wallichii root extract and its fractions</article-title><source>Iran. J. Pharm. Res.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24250446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harborne</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Phytochemical methods</source><year>1984</year><publisher-name>London chapman and Hall ltd</publisher-name><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>188</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoot</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>T.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An A643V Amino Acid Substitution in Upc2p Contributes to Azole Resistance in Well-Characterized Clinical Isolates of Candida albicans</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><volume>55</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>940</fpage><lpage>942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21078937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilavenil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srigopalram</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuppusamy</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ferulic acid in Lolium multiflorum inhibits adipogenesis in 3T3-L1 cells and reduced high-fat-diet-induced obesity in Swiss albino mice via regulating p38MAPK and p44/42 signal pathways</article-title><source>J. Funct. Foods</source><volume>37</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>302</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majlesi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafieian-Kopaei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbaal versus synthestic drugs; beliefs and facts</article-title><source>J. Neuropharmacom.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latheef</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salam</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitra</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of allium cepa and allium sativum against dermatophytes</article-title><source>JASC</source><volume>6</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2844</fpage><lpage>2855</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazareno</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fusari</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cooked Garlic and Antioxidant Activity: Correlation with Organosulphur Compound Compositions</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>220</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27855892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aston</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasco</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of Total Phenolic Content and Antioxidant Activity of Garlic (Allium sativum) and Elephant Garlic (Allium ampeloprasum) by Attenuated Total Reflectance-Fourier Transformed Infrared Spectroscopy</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>59</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>5215</fpage><lpage>5221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21506613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0180"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0175">Maharani, M. G., Lestari, S. R., Lukiati, B., 2020.&#x000a0;Molecular docking studies flavonoid (quercetin, isoquercetin, and kaempferol) of single bulb garlic (Allium sativum) to inhibit lanosterol synthase as anti-hypercholesterol therapeutic strategies. Proceedings of the 3rd international seminar on metallurgy and materials (ismm2019): exploring new innovation in metallurgy and materials.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maidment</surname><given-names>D.C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dembny</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>D.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The anti-bacterial activity of 12 against</article-title><source>Nutr Food Sci.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>241</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menakha</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al aboody</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alturaiki</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Docking of Bioactive Compounds from Piper Plants Against Secreted Aspartyl Proteinase of Candida albicans Causing Oral Candidiasis</article-title><source>Int. J Pharm. Clin. Res.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1389</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manzocco</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anese</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicoli</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant properties of tea extracts as affected by processing</article-title><source>Lebens-mittel-Wissenschaft Und-Technologies</source><volume>31</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>698</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0200"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikaili</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maadirad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moloudizargari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aghajanshakeri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarahroodi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic Uses and Pharmacological Properties of Garlic, Shallot, and Their Biologically Active Compounds</article-title><source>IJBMS</source><volume>16</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24379960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0205"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monika</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abirami</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allium porrum: A review</article-title><source>World J. Pharm. Life sci.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belew</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated docking using a Lamarckian genetic algorithm and an empirical binding free energy function</article-title><source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><volume>19</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1662</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belew</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: Automated docking with selective receptor flexibility</article-title><source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><volume>30</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>2785</fpage><lpage>2791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19399780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0220"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naglik</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hube</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candida albicans proteinases and host/pathogen interactions</article-title><source>Cell Microbiol</source><volume>6</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>915</fpage><lpage>926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oyaizu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on products of browning reactions: antioxidant activities of products of browning reaction prepared from glucosamine</article-title><source>J Nutr.</source><volume>44</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>315</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0230"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padmini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>U.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saravanan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Razia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alwahibi</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravindran</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elshikh</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of novel bioactive molecules from garlic bulbs: A special effort to determine the anticancer potential against lung cancer with targeted drugs</article-title><source>Saudi J. Biol. Sci.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>3274</fpage><lpage>3289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33304133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0235"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Padmini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muthusamy</surname><given-names>Razia</given-names></name><name><surname>Roopavahini</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aruna</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Docking Studies of Allylsulfur Compounds from Allium sativum against EGFR Receptor</article-title><source>IJCRAR</source><volume>3</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0240"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra-Ortega</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz-Torres</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa-Tanaca</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny and evolution of the aspartyl protease family from clinically relevant Candida species</article-title><source>Mem. Inst. Oswaldo Cruz</source><volume>104</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19547880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0245"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrophotometric quantitation of antioxidant capacity through the formation of a phosphomolybdenum complex: specific application to the determination of vitamin E</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>269</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10222007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0255"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radovanovic</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mladenovi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Radovanovic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlovic</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolic</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic Composition, Antioxidant, Antimicrobial and Cytotoxic Activites of Allium porrum L. (Serbia) Extracts</article-title><source>J. Food Nutr. Res.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>569</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0260"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruch</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaunig</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of cytotoxicity and inhibition of intercellular communication by antioxidant catechins isolated from Chinese green tea</article-title><source>Carcinogen</source><volume>10</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>1003</fpage><lpage>1008</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0265"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagar</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pareek</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Aguilar</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of flavonoids, total phenols and antioxidant properties of onion skin: a comparative study of fifteen Indian cultivars</article-title><source>J. Food sci. Tech.</source><volume>57</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2423</fpage><lpage>2432</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0270"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saravanan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential selective inhibitors against Rv0183 of Mycobacterium tuberculosis targeting host lipid metabolism</article-title><source>Chem. Biol. Drug Des.</source><volume>79</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22405030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0275"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seca</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological Potential and Medical Use of Secondary Metabolites</article-title><source>Medicines</source><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>66</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0280"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeram</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henning</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheuller</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heber</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Catechin D. and caffeine contents of green tea dietary supplements and correlation with antioxidant activity</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16506807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0285"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohatgi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination with secreted aspartyl proteinase 2 protein from Candida parapsilosis can enhance survival of mice during Candida tropicalis mediated systemic candidiasis</article-title><source>Infect. Immun.</source><volume>88</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e00312</fpage><lpage>e320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32661125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0290"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sikora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabkowska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swoboda-Kopec</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarzynka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Netsvyetayeva</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaworska-Zaremba</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mlynarczyk</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in proteolytic activity and gene profiles of fungal strains isolated from the total parenteral nutrition patients</article-title><source>Folia Microbiol.</source><volume>56</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21455781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0295"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siwek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefa&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzitko</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruszczak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal effect of 4-arylthiosemicarbazides against Candida species. Search for molecular basis of antifungal activity of thiosemicarbazide derivatives</article-title><source>J Mol. Model.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>4159</fpage><lpage>4170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22535361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0300"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sunaica</surname><given-names>K.-T.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordana</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aleksandra</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Biserka</surname><given-names>L.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of Allium ampeloprasum L. And Allium Cepa L. essential oils on the growth of some yeasts and moulds</article-title><source>Proc. Nat. Sci, Matica Srpska Novi Sad</source><volume>116</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0305"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szychowski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rybczy&#x00144;ska-Tkaczyk</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gawe&#x00142;-B&#x00119;ben</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swieca</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kara&#x0015b;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakubczyk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matysiak - Kucharek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Binduga</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gmi&#x00144;ski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Active Compounds of Different Garlic (Allium sativum L.) Cultivars</article-title><source>Pol. J. Food Nutr. Sci.</source><volume>68</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0310"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tasci</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutuk</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koca</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of alliin and allicin in the plant of Allium scorodoprasum L. subsp. rotundum by using the infrared spectroscopy technique</article-title><source>Acta Hortic.</source><year>2016</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>138</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0315"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valsalam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agastian</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmail</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghilan</surname><given-names>A.K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dhabi</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arasu</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of silver and gold nanoparticles using Musa acuminata colla flower and its pharmaceutical activity against bacteria and anticancer efficacy</article-title><source>J. Photochem. Photobiol., B</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jphotobiol.2019.111670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0320"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bladt</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zgainski</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Plant drug analysis</chapter-title><year>1984</year><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><fpage>320p</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0325"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Y.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Drug Developments of Hydrogen Sulfide on Cardiovascular Disease</article-title><source>Oxid. Med. Cell. Longev.</source><volume>2018</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0330"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemicals of garlic: Promising candidates for cancer therapy</article-title><source>Biomed. Pharmacother.</source><volume>123</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>109730</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31877551</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ref-list id="fr005"><title>Further Reading</title><ref id="b0335"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Rehem</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proximate compositions, phytochemical constituents, antioxidant activities and phenolic contents of seed and leaves extracts of Egyptian leek (Allium ampeloprasum var. kurrat)</article-title><source>Eur. J. Chem.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>190</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0340"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putnik</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabri&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roohinejad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barba</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Granato</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallikarjunan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bursa&#x00107; Kova&#x0010d;evi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of organosulfur compounds from Allium spp. From processing and preservation to evaluation of their bioavailability, antimicrobial, and anti-inflammatory properties</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><volume>276</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30409648</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0165" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary material</title><p id="p0175">The following are the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0005"><caption><title>Supplementary data 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ak005"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p id="p0165">The authors gratefully acknowledge the DSTSERB - Project&#x000a0;Ref. No. SB/EMEQ-431/2014, Department of&#x000a0;Science and Technology, New Delhi, India. The authors extend their appreciation to The Researchers Supporting Project number (RSP-2020/283), King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. The authors are also grateful to the research collaboration among institutes and universities.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d34e1088"><p id="np015">Peer review under responsibility of King Saud University.</p></fn><fn id="s0160" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0170">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.11.082" id="ir005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sjbs.2020.11.082</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>