<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Co-occurrence network analysis was inferred based on the Molecular Ecological Network instruction (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ieg4.rccc.ou.edu/mena/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ieg4.rccc.ou.edu/mena/</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0238478.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0238478.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. In order to reduce rare OTUs, we removed OTUs with relative abundances less than 0.1% of the total number of bacteria sequences. Using the Random Matrix Theory (RMT) approach, the ecological network was constructed using the following steps: Firstly, we standardized the distribution matrix of invaded and uninvaded bacteria into the relative abundance for subsequent Pearson correlation analysis and network construction. OTUs that appeared in less than half of all samples were excluded. Secondly, an appropriate threshold (similarity threshold) for defining network structure was defined to obtain an adjacency matrix, thereby encoding the strength of the connection between each pair of nodes. Finally, network properties were calculated within “global network properties”, “individual nodes centrality” and “module separation and modularity calculation”. Individual node properties in the network were described using the following topological features: average degree (also termed connectivity), which describes the topological property of a node in a network; average clustering coefficient, which evaluates the tendency of neighbors of a node to connect with each other; average geodesic distance, which represents the shortest path length between the connections of any two nodes; module, where a group of nodes are connected more densely to each other than to other nodes; and modularity, which demonstrates a network which could be naturally divided into communities or modules, calculated using Newman’s method [
 <xref rid="pone.0238478.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
