<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mostly found in Europe, Asia, and temperate regions including North America, the 
 <italic>Achillea</italic> genus, belonging to Asteraceae family, is represented by about 85 species [
 <xref rid="B3-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. millefolium</italic> (common yarrow) has been used in many applications such as medicine, veterinary science, and cosmetics [
 <xref rid="B4-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The flowering herbs were reported as possessing tonic, antispasmodic, vulnerary, and diaphoretic activities, among others, and therefore is recommended for colds, flatulence, hysteria, and rheumatism treatments [
 <xref rid="B5-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The chemical composition of 
 <italic>A. millefolium</italic> oils from Québec [
 <xref rid="B6-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], India [
 <xref rid="B7-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], Turkey [
 <xref rid="B3-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], Iran [
 <xref rid="B8-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and European countries (Macedonia, Italy, Lithuania, Hungary, Greece, Moldavia, Latvia, Germany Estonia, Belgium, France, Russia, Armenia, Spain, and Bulgaria) [
 <xref rid="B9-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-medicines-04-00030" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] has been reported in previous studies. However, the reports on antioxidant and antimicrobial properties of 
 <italic>A. millefolium</italic> EO are rather scarce. Considering remarkable chemical polymorphism, which is characteristic of many essential oil-bearing plants, it is of interest to determine the chemical composition and biological activities of plant varieties growing in different regions. 
</p>
