<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">The superior acaricidal and color deformation potential of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>officinalis</italic> oil cultivated in France could be attributed to the high amount of the main components. In our study, the acaricidal and color deformation principle of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>officinalis</italic> oil (France) was identified as 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal. Of the major constituents tested, high toxicity was obtained from caryophyllene oxide, β-caryophyllene, 6-methyl-5-hepten-2-one, 3,7-dimethyl-6-octenal, and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal against 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>farinae</italic> and 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>pteronyssinus</italic>. The acaricidal toxicity of geranyl acetate is comparable with that of DEET. On the other hand, the color alteration of mite bodies was only observed when the 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>farinae</italic> and 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>pteronyssinus</italic> were treated with 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal. In our previous studies on benzaldehyde derivatives from 
 <italic>Morinda officinalis</italic>, 2,3-dihydroxybenzaldehyde was found to be toxic to 
 <italic>Dermatophagoides</italic> spp., and caused color alteration to a dark brown color of the body
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. The 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>officinalis</italic> oil and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal have advantages over 2,3-dihydroxybenzaldehyde, because of their safety for humans. 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>officinalis</italic> oil and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal are on the FDA’s generally recognized as safe (GRAS) list. Furthermore, 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal has been approved as a food additive by the European Commission (EC), because its use does not pose a risk to consumers’ health status
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. Fukumoto 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup> reported that physical and psychological stress may be alleviated by the ingestion of lemon oil containing constituents such as limonene and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal. According to Kennedy 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>, the negative effects of the Defined Intensity Stressor Simulation (DISS) were ameliorated by acute administration of 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>officinalis</italic> oil (600 mg dose), with considerable increase in “calmness” and reduced “alertness”. Taking into account their acaricidal properties, color deformation effects, pleasant fruity scent, and safety for humans, 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>officinalis</italic> oil (France) and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal might become a suitable acaricidal and mite indicator ingredient for the control of 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>farinae</italic> and 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>pteronyssinus</italic>.
</p>
