<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">Investigations of the toxic action mechanisms of naturally occurring acaricides are of practical importance for house dust mite control, because they may provide valuable information on the most suitable formulations to be adopted for their future commercialization
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. In the present study, 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> oil (France) and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal were significantly more effective in closed containers than in open containers. These results indicate that the acaricidal route of action of these compounds was largely a result of vapor action, although the exact mechanism of the oil remains unknown. The fumigant action of 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> oil (France) and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal described, as demonstrated through the current fumigant chamber test (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>), is of practical importance, because it allows the essential oil or its main compound to reach deep refugees in blanket, pillows, carpet, and other fabric materials. This fumigant action system has advantages over the contact action system, because exposure to active constituents can be easily controlled in a closed space using suitable application methods
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, direct and indirect application of sprays containing 0.5 or 1% 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> oil (France) and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal to 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">farinae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pteronyssinus</italic> adults gave rapid action and excellent toxicity. These sprays produced more than 80% mortality against 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">farinae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pteronyssinus</italic> adults 4 h after treatment. Complete mortalities and color alteration of mites were achieved using 0.5% and 1% sprays containing 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal and 1% spray containing 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> oil (France) (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>). No staining was observed in white cotton treated with 1% 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> oil (France) and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). Thus, such spray formulations have great advantage, especially in situations where staining is an issue, such as carpet, mattress, and pillow. Because of the high volatility of the 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> oil (France) and 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal described, the binary mixture formulations of 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">officinalis</italic> oil (France) or 3,7-dimethyl-2,6-octadienal and acaricidal compounds with contact action (e.g. 3-methylacetophenone
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>, or 4-chloro-6-isopropyl-3-methylphenol
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup>) could be useful agent for mite control in space where a window is open.
</p>
