<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although widely used in traditional medicines and studied well for its pharmacological activities, the chemical constituents of 
 <italic>C. hirsutus</italic> are not well explored. Earlier studies in 1960s and 1970s have reported the presence of alkaloids through preliminary phytochemical screenings and isolation and identification of a few alkaloids such as trilobine, isotrilobine, coclaurine and magnoflorine [
 <xref rid="B33-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and other compounds i.e., 
 <italic>β</italic>-sitosterol, ginnol and monomethyl ether of inositol [
 <xref rid="B36-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Few studies performed during or after 1980s, have reported several alkaloids from various plant parts. The list of alkaloids isolated from 
 <italic>C. hirsutus</italic> is given in 
 <xref rid="medicines-07-00069-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and their structures are represented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="medicines-07-00069-f003">Figure 3</xref>. Three flavonoids rutin, liquiritin and quercetin were also reported from the leaves [
 <xref rid="B37-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. A triterpene derivative, hirsudiol is also reported from the ethanol extract of whole plant [
 <xref rid="B38-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Similarly, 
 <italic>β</italic>-sitosterol and 28-acetyl botulin were isolated from the aqueous extract of aerial parts [
 <xref rid="B39-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Many studies have reported the preliminary phytochemical screening of the extracts and presence of carbohydrates, steroids, alkaloids, glycosides, flavonoids, tannins and saponins [
 <xref rid="B40-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Further, gas chromatography-mass spectroscopy (GC-MS) analysis of the extracts have revealed the presence of various compounds [
 <xref rid="B40-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-medicines-07-00069" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. 
</p>
