<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The isolate SC1 of 
 <italic>Trichoderma atroviride</italic>, as an experimental biocontrol agent, provided effective control of vinegrape root rot disease caused by 
 <italic>A. gallica</italic> and 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic> [
 <xref rid="B280-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">280</xref>]. 
 <italic>T. atroviride</italic> SC1 grew sustainably on the barks of different plant species, such as larch, fir and pine for an extended period, up to 16 weeks. The best survival rate of this antagonist was detected on the bark mixture of these species. Bark pre-inoculated with 
 <italic>T. atroviride</italic> SC1 was applied as mulch to strawberry; as a result, it significantly reduced the extent of root colonization by 
 <italic>A. gallica</italic> on strawberry plants [
 <xref rid="B88-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Application of 
 <italic>T. harzianum</italic> to the soil surrounding the wood-borne inoculum of 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> caused a significant reduction in the viability of the pathogen [
 <xref rid="B255-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">255</xref>]. 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> failed to invade the stem sections colonized by 
 <italic>T. harzianum</italic> and had low viability in the plant materials inoculated with 
 <italic>Trichoderma</italic> [
 <xref rid="B256-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">256</xref>]. The use of air-spading combined with 
 <italic>T. harzianum</italic> inoculation also proved to be a potential joint cultural/biocontrol strategy against 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic> in a forest [
 <xref rid="B281-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">281</xref>]. Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B282-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">282</xref>] performed a large-scale screening approach to identify potential biocontrol candidates among 
 <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains isolated from healthy and 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic>-damaged forests. The isolates were examined for in vitro antagonistic abilities towards 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic> species as well as for the production of siderophores and indole-3-acetic acid, resulting in the selection of a 
 <italic>T. virens</italic> and 
 <italic>T. atrobrunneum</italic> strain, which were tested under field conditions where their application revealed better survival of Turkey oak seedlings under 
 <italic>Armillaria</italic>-infested soil conditions. Rees et al. [
 <xref rid="B283-pathogens-10-00076" ref-type="bibr">283</xref>] focused on the isolation of endophytic 
 <italic>Trichoderma</italic> strains and their investigation regarding the potential to control 
 <italic>A. mellea</italic>, and found that strains of 
 <italic>T. virens</italic> and 
 <italic>T. hamatum</italic> possessed the best antagonistic abilities on pre-colonized hazel disks.
</p>
