<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">Francis and Chidambaram (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Francis and Chidambaram, 2019</xref>) showed that an acceptable alternative chocolate product could be formulated with up to 50% v/v CB substitution with a sodium alginate-pectin-citric acid hydrogel. This strategy led to the formation of the desired form V CB polymorph. This hydrogel also allowed the chocolate product to be more resistant to heat. In fact, at 50–100% v/v substitution the final product kept its original structure at temperatures up to 80 ​°C (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Francis and Chidambaram, 2019</xref>). Heat resistance is beneficial for chocolate products in hotter climates than the UK and it avoids chocolate melting in the hands of consumers. Too high melting point can, however, have negative consequences on mouth feel and melting processes during manufacturing. Another type of hydrogel that has been considered is an agar hydrogel that can replace CB to up to 80% in volume, greater than the previous two options, while keeping chocolate quality attributes (
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Skelhon et al., 2013</xref>). The agar hydrogel was emulsified into the CB using shear cooling techniques (e.g., ultra-turrex equipment) (
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Skelhon et al., 2013</xref>). Different effects can occur with larger scale processing machinery compared to laboratory equipment; which needs to be considered when scaling up low fat chocolate production. 
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Skelhon et al. (2013)</xref> looked at the substitution of CB with hydrogels in dark, milk, and white chocolate in contrast with other studies that tend to look at only one type of chocolate. Additionally, the hydrogel is shown to produce a chocolate with a similar visual appearance to traditional chocolate, with a substantial amount of form V CB crystals, and with no higher tendency to fat blooming than normal chocolate. (
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Skelhon et al., 2013</xref>). Therefore, hydrogels seem to be a promising strategy to reduce the amount of CB for an acceptable novel alternative chocolate product. However, checking the taste and sensory properties of these products is essential to confirm if hydrogels can be used, especially at high substitution levels, and still provide a high-quality product.
</p>
