<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To increase the penetration channel and separation efficiency, there are some attempts at using inorganic and metal-based 3D-PMs (normally are ceramic foams or copper/nickel foams etc.) [
 <xref rid="B42-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. However, their significant disadvantages such as brittle, lack of elasticity, ease of corrosion in acid/base environment, unable to be reused, and difficulty in surface modification restrict the application in oily wastewater treatment. Recently, polymer-based three-dimensional porous materials (3D-PMs) (such as sponge [
 <xref rid="B46-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], foam [
 <xref rid="B49-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>], and aerogel [
 <xref rid="B53-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]) with multi-layered network structure, higher porosity, adsorption capability, long penetration channel, and tunable pore structure are regarded as promising alternates for effectively oil/water separation after being functionalized with special wettability [
 <xref rid="B56-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. This is because polymers are always light in weight, ease of processability, resistance to corrosion, chemical stability, and the abundant functional groups on the surface which can be modified with a variety of materials easily [
 <xref rid="B53-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Especially, the excellent flexibility of polymers enables the high elasticity of polymer 3D-PMs. The elastic 3D-PMs can be compressed and recycled under a certain pressure to discharge the adsorbed oil by compression, which simplifies the separation process [
 <xref rid="B65-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-polymers-11-00806" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. Therefore, polymers have been widely used in developing 3D-PMs and polymeric 3D-PMs have become one of the research hotspots in oil/water separation. The published articles on superwetting polymeric oil/water separation 3D-PMs (from 2011 to February 2019) are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="polymers-11-00806-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>, indicating that polymeric 3D-PMs have undergone rapid development. Interfacial superwetting 3D-PMs are mainly divided into four categories according to their surface wettability and their functions in dealing with different types of oil/water mixtures: (i) superhydrophobic-superoleophilic 3D-PMs are used to absorb oil; (ii) superhydrophilic-underwater superoleophobic 3D-PMs are used to eliminate the layered oil/water mixture and oil-in-water emulsions; (iii) superhydrophilic-superoleophobic 3D-PMs are used to remove water from oily wastewater and eliminate water from water-in-oil emulsion; (iv) 3D-PMs with switchable super-wettability, which can change wettability and remove oil or water by responding to the external stimulation. In this feature article, firstly, the theoretical mechanism of oil/water separation of super-wetting 3D-PMs is reviewed. Then, the design routes, techniques, the applications in different oil/water mixtures treatment, the current challenges existed in 3D-PMs oil/water separation such as oil contamination, relatively weak mechanical robust under certain pressure, difficulties in oil-desorption, and the adsorption or separation efficiency, were also discussed. Finally, the perspective of the future development on fabrication 3D-PMs to meet the practical requirements is briefly discussed.
</p>
