<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As just mentioned, anticancer treatment is the foundation of anti-metastatic osteolysis but inadequate without specific distribution in the osteolytic part or synergy with anti bone resorption drugs. Optimized targeted delivery systems usually rely on NPs which could target metastatic bone and carry anticancer or anti-osteolysis drugs efficiently via targeting ligands. 
 <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> listed the collected targeted drug delivery systems. Through systemic administration methods like intravenous injection, targeted delivery systems narrow the drug’s distribution to the bone, tumor, or osteolytic site. The ligands like BP, tetracycline, chelating compounds, salivary proteins, Alizarin Red S, and oligopeptides (oligo-aspartic acid) have an affinity to bone (de Miguel et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Chang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0100" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Stapleton et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0109" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In the affinity assay for HA 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, 77.5% of alendronate (ALN, Ald, or Alen) bound to HA powder (Ryu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0100" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Zol exhibited 20-fold increased targeting of bone metastatic lesions than other major tissues (Hatami et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). BP was used mostly to modify the designed NPs which encapsulated anticancer drugs. With BP, NPs can target bone and release anticancer drugs to inhibit cancer cells and suppress osteoclasts. Loaded drugs can be chemically conjugated to the nanocarriers or physically encapsulated or adsorbed and released by diffusion, erosion of carriers or the break of chemical bonds (Zeng et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0145" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The physicochemical property of these targeted nanocarriers makes a difference in their application (Danaei et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The size of nanocarriers cannot exceed 400 nm in order to escape from macrophage and renal clearance and are preferably less than 200 nm (Perez-Herrero &amp; Fernandez-Medarde, 
 <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Smaller NPs can help them through the openings of the bone’s sinusoidal capillaries (10–70 nm). Small neutral NPs (about 150 nm) were also 7-fold more effective in localizing in bone marrow than large NPs (about 320 nm; Adjei et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Nanocarriers between 70 and 100 nm were often used to target bone for their extended blood circulating time (Adjei et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The nanocarriers with hydrophilic, neutral, or slightly anionic surfaces are more prone to localize in the bone marrow and escape from the macrophage attack by avoiding plasma proteins. A neutral surface charge is achieved by modulating the surface-associated emulsifier composition. Hydrophilic surface can be obtained by decoration with hydrophilic polymers like poly(ethylene glycol) (PEG) or amphiphilic polymers like synthetic copolymers of polyethylene oxide (hydrophilic block) and propylene oxide (hydrophobic block) (Perez-Herrero &amp; Fernandez-Medarde, 
 <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Suk et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0113" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Targeted drug delivery systems have been developed based on polymer NPs, micelles, liposomes, Silica NPs, inorganic compounds (HA nanocrystal, calcium phosphates NPs, etc.), or organometallic compounds. Polymer NPs were used most frequently in drug release systems for their good biocompatibility and biodegradability and drugs were released through NPs erosion. Related synthetic polymers include polyglutamic acid, polyglycolic acid (PGA), PEG, polycaprolactone (PCL), polylactic acid (PLA), poly aspartate (PAA), poly(D, L-lactide-co-glycolic) acid (PLGA), and N-(2-hydroxypropyl)-methacrylamide copolymer (HPMA) Ulbrich et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0122" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Natural polymers include chitosan (CS), alginate, dextran, heparin, albumin, gelatin, and collagen (George et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
