<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-insects-09-00025" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Larvicidal and Pupaecidal Activities of Essential Oils and Their Constituents</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of in vitro assays demonstrated the larvicidal activity of essential oils against 
  <span class="italic">C. quinquefasciatus</span> (Diptera: 
  <span class="italic">Culicidae</span>), since all oils tested were able to eliminated 100% of larvae at 75 µg/mL. The essential oils of Mexican oregano and anise display the highest larvicidal activity with LC
  <sub>50</sub> of 6.21 and 4.62 µg/mL, respectively. Pupae are more resistant than larvae, since more than 100 µg/mL of essential oil were needed to reach LC
  <sub>50</sub>; the same effect has been reported before [
  <a rid="B28-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-insects-09-00025">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-insects-09-00025" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-insects-09-00025">29</a>]. 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="insects-09-00025-t002" href="#insects-09-00025-t002">Table 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="insects-09-00025-t003" href="#insects-09-00025-t003">Table 3</a> show lethal concentrations LC
  <sub>50</sub> and LC
  <sub>90</sub> of the essential oils and their constituents studied against larval stage III and pupae of 
  <span class="italic">C. quinquefasciatus</span> after 24 h exposure.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As observed, 
  <span class="italic">t-</span>Anethole, which is the main compound of anise essential oil, proved to be efficient against larvae as well as pupae, with LC
  <sub>50</sub> of 7.4 and 28.6 µg/mL, respectively. Carvacrol also showed efficient activity against larvae and pupae, while thymol showed lower activity, with an LC
  <sub>50</sub> of 23.4 µg/mL against larvae and 100.5 µg/mL against pupae. Eugenol and eucalyptol show larvicidal activity with a LC
  <sub>50</sub> of 23.04 and 24.83 µg/mL, respectively. None of the aforementioned compounds had significant activity against pupae. Percentage of 
  <span class="italic">Culex quinquefasciatus</span> larvae mortality upon exposure to water contaminated by LC
  <sub>50</sub> doses is shown in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="insects-09-00025-t004" href="#insects-09-00025-t004">Table 4</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
