<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Butein. Research regarding the biological properties of butein highlighted a wide range of effects, that indicated a potential of use in chronic conditions due to anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, antidiabetic, neuroprotective and anticancer effects (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Padmavathi et al., 2017</xref>). The effects of this compound correlate with the medicinal properties reported in ethnopharmaceutic and pharmacological studies. Its anti-ulcerative activity was evaluated in mice with gastric ulcer induced with indomethacin and the administration of butein (10, 20, 40 mg/kg) reduced inflammatory parameters, increased PGE2 (prostaglandin E2) concentrations and reduced ulcer areas (
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr">Ugan and Un, 2020</xref>). Butein exerts preventive effects against functional β-cell damage, slowing the progression of type 1 diabetes mellitus. This effect was studied in cytokine-induced β-cell damage. The chalcone blocked cytokine-induced NO production, the expression of iNOS, the translocation of NF-κB and inhibited insulin secretion stimulation by glucose (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Jeong et al., 2011</xref>). Butein has a significant anti-inflammatory effect, inhibiting the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines, matrix metalloproteinases, expression of enzymes involved in inflammation such as COX-2; in experimentally induced osteoarthritis it has been shown to reduce cartilage erosion and synovitis (
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2017</xref>). Several studies have evaluated the cytotoxic effects of butein on cell lines including human cervical cancer (C-33A, SiHa) (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">Yang J. et al., 2018</xref>), breast cancer MCF7 and T47D (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2020</xref>), non-small-cell lung cancer (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Di et al., 2019</xref>), human oral squamous cancer (SAS, KB) (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Bordoloi et al., 2019</xref>) and many other. The compound induces apoptosis by activating the Bax-caspase-3-PARP pathway, it induces the arrest of the cell cycle at the G2/M transition, blocks telomerase activity, reduces angiogenesis and has anti-metastatic properties (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Jayasooriya et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
