<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The extracts of 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic>, 
 <italic>M. esculenta</italic>, and 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> also showed good anti-FIV-RT activity. They could inhibit FIV-RT at a similar strength (IC
 <sub>50</sub> values ranging from 29.73±12.37 to 81.41±17.10 μg/mL, which were approximately 10-fold higher IC
 <sub>50</sub> values than those of 
 <italic>I. obliquus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. igniarius</italic>). The extract of 
 <italic>G. lucidum</italic> showed a broad spectrum of antiviral activity against various viruses such as 
 <italic>Enterovirus</italic> 71, hepatitis B virus, HIV-1, HSV-1, and vesicular stomatitis virus. These antiviral activities were mainly from polysaccharides and triterpenes [
 <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. esculenta</italic> also exhibited wide range of pharmacological properties including antiviral, antimicrobial, antioxidant, antitumor, anti-inflammatory, and immune regulation [
 <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Research on the antiviral activity of 
 <italic>C. sinensis</italic>, has been conducted. In addition, Ohta 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] found that acidic polysaccharide (APS) extracted from 
 <italic>Cordyceps militaris</italic> could reduce influenza A titer in infected mice. APS could also modulate the immune function of macrophages and increase mice survival rate. Cordycepin, adenosine analog (3′-deoxyadenosine), and its derivatives showed anti-influenza, plant, HIV, murine leukemia, and Epstein–Barr viruses activity [
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In the case of 
 <italic>M. esculenta</italic>, the study on antiviral activity of this mushroom is limited. To the best of our knowledge, antiviral activity of 
 <italic>M. esculenta</italic> has not been previously reported. This study was the first on the antiviral property of 
 <italic>M. esculenta</italic> extract. Further research is also required to separate and identify bioactive compounds responsible for anti-FIV-RT properties.
</p>
