<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Comparison of the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of these mushroom extracts and anti-HIV drug EFV revealed that the IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of mushroom extracts were much higher than that of EFV. However, this study clearly showed the anti-FIV potential of these mushroom extracts through inhibition of the RT enzyme which is important for viral infection. Further study is needed to investigate whether the anti-FIV activity is due to a specific component or the combined effect of various individual constituents. As mushroom extracts have been shown to possess antioxidant activity, they can be used as a tonic to reduce oxidative stress during acute FIV infection [
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Moreover, mushrooms have been reported to show immunomodulating activity. They could be used in combination with drugs to initiate and support immune responses [
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Synergism between a mushroom extract and antiviral drug has also been reported [
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It is noteworthy that extraction with nonpolar solvents (hexane and ethanol) gave extracts with great inhibitory activity against FIV-RT. The chemical constituents in these extracts might be hydrophobic compounds. NNRTIs are small hydrophobic molecules with diverse structures. Thus, these mushroom extracts may contain novel NNRTIs. The water extract also showed good anti-FIV-RT activity. It has been reported that some proteins and polysaccharides extracted from mushrooms showed antiviral potential [
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table-2</xref>). Thus, the experimental design to obtain the anti-FIV compounds (e.g., type of inhibitor, solvent used, and purification method) should be taken into account in further studies and clinical applications.
</p>
