<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Candidiasis is a cosmopolitan fungal infection associated with yeasts of the genus Candida. It is one of the most common opportunistic infections in tropical areas, with a frequency ranging from 33 to 47% in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In recent decades, their prevalence has been steadily increasing, especially among patients in intensive care and with the advent of HIV/AIDS infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. They affect all types of tissues and mainly mucous membranes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. It is reported that 25% of urinary tract infections were related to Candida spp. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. 50 to 75% of women of childbearing age developed vulvovaginal candidiasis annually and 5 to 8%, or about 75 million women, can be affected at least four times in a year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Oral infections are common but are found in children and immune compromised people [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Ten million cases of oral candidiasis and 2 million esophageal candidiasis are reported annually in people living with HIV. Most seriously, invasive fungal infections are reported to kill more than tuberculosis and malaria and in 90% of fungal deaths, candidiasis ranks second behind cryptococcosis and ahead of aspergillosis and pneumocystis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. They are fatal in 40% of hospital sepsis cases according to letter No. 72 from the Pasteur Institute [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and are the leading nosocomial fungal disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Their therapeutic management requires the use of antifungals to which 
 <italic>Candida spp.</italic> strains are increasingly resistant [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Indeed, high levels of 
 <italic>Candida spp</italic>. resistance to fluconazole have been identified in several countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Candida spp. resistance even extends to amphotericin B [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], one of the last used antifungals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. This emergence of strains resistant to common molecules is, like the emergence of bacterial resistance to antibiotics, of a great public health concern for which sustainable alternative solutions must be found very quickly. In African countries, these alternative solutions involve the use of medicinal plants. Indeed, the use of plants to treat diseases is an old practice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] and endogenous to populations. According to several authors, in Africa and Asia, 80% of the population continues to use traditional medicines rather than the so-called modern medicines for primary health care for various reasons [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Today, with the support of WHO [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], many research focuses on plants to look for active compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In this sense, some research carried out on plants has shown in vitro their antifungal potential [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and could thus constitute new sources of bioactive molecules [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].
</p>
