<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pickering emulsions, which have been extensively studied and implemented in numerous applications during the last century, are excellent candidates for single cell encapsulation, given their high colloidal stability and controllable droplet size.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13" class="xref">13</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup> Pickering emulsions are stabilized by nanoparticles (NPs) that are self-assembled at the oil/water interface and act as a physical barrier.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup> Pickering emulsions come in the form of oil-in-water (o/w) or inverse (water-in-oil) emulsions. Inorganic NPs such as silica, clays, hydroxyapatites, and organic NPs can act as stabilizers for Pickering emulsions.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup> At the interface, the wettability of the particles determines their localization in the water and the oil phase.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> The diameter of the droplets is dictated by the particle size and the composition of the system (o/w ratio and NP content).
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19" class="xref">19</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup> Cell encapsulation by Pickering emulsions has become useful for various applications, such as encapsulation of microbial cells to protect from pH changes,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup> developing biopesticide formulations based on 
 <italic class="italic">Bacillus thuringiensis</italic> (Bt),
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup> platform for enzymatic reaction,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref24" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup> cellular capsules based on liquid marbles,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup> and encapsulation of adherent cells in water-in-water emulsions for tissue engineering.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
