<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The biological interpretation of proteins involved in stress conditions mediated by 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with ME and SE was assessed by STRING. 2D-DIGE was used to identify the critical proteins (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acsomega.0c04047/suppl_file/ao0c04047_si_001.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Table S1</ext-link>), which were charted in the protein network. There was high protein interaction within all expressed protein groups. A total of 15 networks were generated from the identified proteins whose expression changed significantly in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> after treatment with extracts: carbon metabolism, pyruvate metabolism, metabolic pathways, ribosome, microbial metabolism in diverse environments, citrate cycle (TCA cycle), biosynthesis of antibiotics, glycolysis/gluconeogenesis, biosynthesis of secondary metabolites, purine metabolism, pyrimidine metabolism, RNA polymerase, butanoate metabolism, propanoate metabolism, and oxidative phosphorylation. Connections among identified proteins offer new information about the reactions of bacterial cells under the stress conditions elicited by extracts. Metabolic pathways contained the most affected proteins from which the expression of 15 proteins was upregulated and the expression of 29 proteins was inhibited significantly in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> treated with ME and SE, respectively. In general, most expressed proteins showed an excess in microbes treated with ME and an inhibition in microbes treated with SE, which might suggest higher antimicrobial activity for SE. Furthermore, the last phase in glycolysis is the pyruvate metabolism (to provide acetyl-CoA) and the TCA cycle (to provide energy). The proton-motive force is a result of the enhancement of the TCA cycle via an increase in the level of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>
 </sup> The proton-motive force enhances antibiotic uptake.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>
 </sup> Our results showing variations in metabolic pathways (including the TCA cycle) could be an antibiotic-resistance approach which might explain upregulation of the expression of some metabolic-pathway proteins in extracts having a lower effect on 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> in contrast to extracts showing higher activity even though the expression of their proteins was downregulated. Analysis of the comprehensive protein–protein network of 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> under extract stress might extend our knowledge on the extract mechanism as antimicrobial agents (
 <xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">15</xref>
 </xref>).
</p>
