<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. In Vivo Evaluation of Gel Formulations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ability of SLNs and NLCs to increase drug skin permeation has been attributed to different factors such as occlusive properties, specific drug-carrier interactions with the skin and close contact with the skin’s outermost layers due to their small size [
  <a rid="B34-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-pharmaceutics-09-00048">34</a>,
  <a rid="B35-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-pharmaceutics-09-00048">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-pharmaceutics-09-00048">36</a>]. After topical application, SLNs and NLCs form a continuous and dense film on the cutaneous surface that prevents or decreases water loss from the skin, thus increasing skin hydration and, hence, drug skin permeation [
  <a rid="B37-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-pharmaceutics-09-00048">37</a>]. Wissing and Müller [
  <a rid="B38-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-pharmaceutics-09-00048">38</a>] performed an investigation on human volunteers, studying the hydrating and viscoelasticity effects of an O/W cream containing SLNs in comparison with the same vehicle without SLNs. The results of this study showed that the cream containing SLNs provided a higher increase in skin hydration than the conventional formulation, while skin elasticity was not significantly affected after a 28-day treatment with these formulations, likely owing to the young age of the volunteers enrolled in the study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, in this work, the effects of rosemary EO-loaded lipid nanoparticles on skin hydration and elasticity from gel vehicles was assessed using a gel containing unloaded SLNs as a control.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We chose gel formulations as a vehicle for rosemary EO-loaded NLCs in order to avoid the interactions between vehicle components and NLCs, which may occur in complex vehicles such as emulsions and could interfere with the ability of NLCs to affect skin hydration and elasticity.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of in vivo tests on skin hydration were expressed as hydration difference (Δ hydration) between baseline values and values recorded after a one-week treatment with the gels under investigation. As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pharmaceutics-09-00048-f005" href="#pharmaceutics-09-00048-f005">Figure 5</a>, topical treatment with gel A, which did not contain the active ingredient or lipid nanoparticles, did not lead to any change in skin hydration. Gels B and B1, incorporating 1.5% and 3.0% 
  <span class="italic">w</span>/
  <span class="italic">w</span> free rosemary EO, respectively, enhanced skin hydration but no significant difference (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05) was observed between Gel B and B1, thus suggesting that an increase in rosemary EO concentration in the vehicle was not effective in further improving skin hydration. Topical application of gel C, containing only unloaded SLN, resulted in a hydration improvement similar to that obtained from gel B and B1, thus confirming the ability of SLNs to act as a skin-hydrating factor. After a one-week treatment, rosemary EO-loaded NLCs in gel vehicles (gels D and D1) provided Δ hydration values greater than those observed for gels B, B1 and C, but no significant difference (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &gt; 0.05) was observed between gels containing different percentages of rosemary EO-loaded NLC. These results highlight the usefulness of loading rosemary EO into lipid nanoparticles, supporting the findings of previous studies on rosemary extracts that reported an increase in activity upon loading these extracts into nanoparticles [
  <a rid="B39-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-pharmaceutics-09-00048">39</a>,
  <a rid="B40-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-pharmaceutics-09-00048">40</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pharmaceutics-09-00048-f006" href="#pharmaceutics-09-00048-f006">Figure 6</a> shows that skin treatment with gels A, B and B1 did not alter elasticity values, while all the gels containing lipid nanoparticles provided a slight but significant increase in skin elasticity (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 for all comparisons between gels containing lipid nanoparticles and gels without nanoparticles). However, it is interesting to note the all subjects showed high elasticity values before the treatment with the gels under investigation. Therefore, only moderate increases of this parameter could be expected. Analogously to skin hydration data, no significant difference was observed between elasticity values obtained from gels D and D1 (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05). In addition, our data showed a moderate effect on skin elasticity of the gel containing unloaded SLNs (gel C), which contrasts with the results reported by Wissing and Müller [
  <a rid="B38-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-pharmaceutics-09-00048">38</a>], who did not find any change in this parameter upon topical application of SLNs. The effect of unloaded SLNs on skin elasticity observed in our work could be attributed to the older age of volunteers enrolled in this investigation. However, gel C provided a significantly lower increase in skin elasticity than gels D and D1 (
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 for both comparisons), thus proving better activity from lipid nanoparticles loading rosemary essential oil.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the results of this study pointed out that in vivo topical application of rosemary essential oil from gel vehicles showed a hydrating effect that remarkably increased upon rosemary EO loading into lipid nanoparticles. A slight but significant effect on skin elasticity could be detected only after topical application of gel vehicles containing unloaded SLNs or rosemary EO-loaded NLCs. Therefore, loading rosemary essential oil into lipid nanoparticles seems to be a promising strategy to improve its topical benefits and for designing topical formulations for the treatment of cutaneous alterations involving loss of skin hydration and elasticity.</p>
</sec>
