<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec2dot1-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Materials</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polyoxyethylene-20-oleyl ether (Brij 98
   <span class="sup">®</span>, Oleth-20) was bought from Sigma-Aldrich (Milan, Italy). Methylchloroisothiazolinone and methylisothiazolinone (Kathon CG
   <span class="sup">®</span>), and Imidazolidinyl urea (Gram 1
   <span class="sup">®</span>) were kindly supplied by Sinerga (Milan, Italy). Carbopol Ultrez 21
   <span class="sup">®</span> (Carbopol), Cetyl Palmitate (CP), Glyceryl Oleate (GO) and Triethanolamine (TEA) were bought from ACEF (Fiorenzuola D'Arda, Italy). Solubilisant Gamma 2428
   <span class="sup">®</span> (octoxynol-11, PEG-40 hydrogenated castor oil, polysorbate 20; Solubilisant) was a kind gift of Gattefossé Italia (Milan, Italy). Rosemary oil (Rosmarinus officinalis flower oil, EO) was a kind gift of Exentiae (Catania, Italy). According to the data sheet provided by the manufacturer, rosemary oil contained 1,8-cineol (25–60%), alpha-pinene (8–20%), beta-pinene (2–10%), beta-caryophyllene (4–10%), camphor (7–8%), camphene (3–8%), limonene (2–3%), myrcene (1–2%), terpinolene (0.2–0.5%), 3-carene (0.15–0.5%).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot2-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Lipid Nanoparticles Preparation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unloaded SLNs and EO-loaded NLCs, whose composition is reported in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pharmaceutics-09-00048-t001" href="#pharmaceutics-09-00048-t001">Table 1</a>, were prepared using the phase inversion temperature (PIT) method [
   <a rid="B27-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-pharmaceutics-09-00048">27</a>]. The aqueous phase (double distilled water containing 0.35% (
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>) imidazolidinyl urea and 0.05% (
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>) methylchloroisothiazolinone and methylisothiazolinone as preservatives) and the oil phase (cetyl palmitate, emulsifier and co-emulsifier, different percentages 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span> of EO) were separately heated at 85 °C. Two series of NLCs were prepared: NLCs BEO1–4 were obtained using a constant amount of lipid phase (7% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>) with different ratios solid lipid/liquid lipid, while NLCs CEO1–3 contained a constant amount of solid lipid (7% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>) and different percentages of liquid lipid.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When both phases were at the same temperature, the water phase was slowly added to the oil phase while being stirred and then the resulting colloidal system was cooled to room temperature, under constant agitation. The turbid mixture turned into a clear system at the phase inversion temperature (PIT), whose value was determined using a conductivity meter, model 525 (Crison, Modena, Italy).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot3-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Nanoparticles Characterization</div>
  <sec id="sec2dot3dot1-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1. Transmission Electron Microscopy</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For negative-staining electron microscopy, 5 µL of lipid nanocarriers dispersions were placed on a 200-mesh formvar copper grid (TAAB Laboratories Equipment, Berks, UK) and allowed to be adsorbed. Then the surplus was removed by filter paper. A drop of 2% (
    <span class="italic">w</span>/
    <span class="italic">v</span>) aqueous solution of uranyl acetate was added over 2 min. After removing the surplus, the sample was dried at room temperature before imaging it with a transmission electron microscope (model JEM 2010, Jeol, Peabody, MA, USA) operating at an acceleration voltage of 200 kV.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot3dot2-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2. Size and Zeta Potential Measurements</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean particle size and size distribution were determined in double distilled water by a dynamic light scattering (DLS) using a Zetasizer NanoZS (ZEN 3600, Malvern, Germany).</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the samples were diluted at 1:5 (sample/water) and thermostated at 25 °C for 2 min prior to the measurement. The instrument performed particle sizing by means of a 4 mW laser diode operating at 670 nm. Using the same instrument, ζ potential was determined by the technique of laser Doppler velocimetry, after diluting the sample with KCl 1 mM (pH 7.0), according to a procedure already reported [
    <a rid="B28-pharmaceutics-09-00048" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-pharmaceutics-09-00048">28</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each measurement was performed in triplicate and values were expressed as mean ± standard deviation (S.D.).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec2dot3dot3-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3. Stability Tests</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples of lipid nanoparticles were stored in airtight jars, and then kept in the dark and at room temperature for two months.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At fixed intervals (24 h, one week, two weeks, one month and two months after their preparation), the particle size and polydispersity index of the samples were measured.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot4-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Gel Preparation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gel formulations were prepared using Carbopol Ultrez 21 as a gelling agent and TEA for neutralization, and their compositions are reported in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pharmaceutics-09-00048-t002" href="#pharmaceutics-09-00048-t002">Table 2</a>. The rheological additive (0.8% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>) was carefully dispersed in the aqueous phase, under mild agitation. The aqueous phase consisted of deionized water (gel A), deionized water containing EO and Solubilisant Gamma 2428 (gel B and B1), SLN A (gel C), NLC CEO3 (gel D and D1). As rosemary essential oil was poorly water soluble, we added a solubilizing compound to obtain aqueous gels containing different percentages of EO. All gel formulations were prepared using deionized water containing 0.35% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span> imidazolidinyl urea, 0.05% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span> methylchloroisothiazolinone and methylisothiazolinone as preservatives. The resulting mixture was left in the dark at room temperature for 24 h, to allow complete polymer hydration. Then, TEA (0.8% 
   <span class="italic">w</span>/
   <span class="italic">w</span>) was added drop by drop under slow agitation, to prevent the formation of air bubbles, until the gel was formed. All formulations were stored in airtight jars, and kept in the dark and at room temperature until use.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec2dot5-pharmaceutics-09-00048" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5. In Vivo Evaluation of Gel Formulations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This experiment has been designed to assess the in vivo activity of rosemary oil-loaded lipid nanoparticles in comparison with unloaded SLNs and free rosemary oil in gel vehicles after topical application for one week. Investigations were carried out following the rules of the Declaration of Helsinki of 1975, revised in 2008. The local ethics committee declared that no approval was needed for this type of study, due to the nature of the study and the safety of the ingredients used in the formulations under investigation. Ten healthy female volunteers (average age 53 ± 4), without dermatological diseases and with normal/moderate dry skin were enrolled in the study, after giving their informed consent. Young healthy subjects were not included in this study as they showed high hydration skin levels that made them unsuitable for the evaluation of the effects of skin hydrating treatments. Freshly prepared gel samples were presented in similar containers labeled with four-digit code numbers and the study was performed in double blind. In the first part of the study, subjects were given four out of the six different gels. The volunteers were explained how to pick up and apply the samples and were instructed to apply the product (about 2 mg) onto two different areas over the back of their hands, twice a day (morning and evening) for a period of one week.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements of skin hydration and elasticity were performed at baseline (prior to the treatment) and after one week of treatment. Measurements were taken under controlled temperature (22 ± 1 °C) and humidity (35 ± 5%) conditions, after 30 min of acclimatization. The volunteers were requested not to apply the gels the morning before the final measurement. The use of other products was not allowed throughout the study, apart from normal hygiene treatment. Skin analyses were performed using specific probes of the instrument Soft Plus (Callegari Srl, Parma, Italy). These probes determined skin hydration by capacity measurements in the range 0–100 u.c. (arbitrary units) with a resolution of 1 u.c. and 5% precision, while stress/deformation of skin by suction application allowed measurements of skin elasticity in the range 0–50 u.c. with a resolution of 1 u.c. and 10% precision. Each measurement was performed in triplicate.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second part of the study, after a one-month wash-out, the same subjects were requested to apply the remaining two gels and the test was performed in the same conditions and using the same procedures and instrumental analyses described above.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis of the results was performed using Students’ 
   <span class="italic">t</span> test (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
