<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The application of bioplastics has been limited because of their low mechanical strength [
 <xref rid="B12-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Numerous studies have demonstrated that synthetic fibers, such as glass and carbon fibers, are commonly used as reinforcements in bioplastics due to their strong mechanical properties. However, the synthetic fibers also cause serious problems to the environment owing to their non-biodegradable characteristic in the environment [
 <xref rid="B14-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Recently, a wide range of attractive and alternative materials that can replace synthetic fibers such as lignocellulosic fibers are increasingly being utilized as environmentally friendly materials which can reduce the widespread dependence on fossil fuels and enhance the environment and economy simultaneously [
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. In comparison to synthetic fibers, lignocellulosic fibers are biodegradable, renewable and widely available; moreover, they have low density, competitive specific mechanical properties and a relatively low cost [
 <xref rid="B6-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Lignocellulosic fibers such as sugar cane bagasse [
 <xref rid="B20-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], wheat straw [
 <xref rid="B19-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], rice straw [
 <xref rid="B1-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>], forest wood [
 <xref rid="B21-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], flax [
 <xref rid="B22-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], hemp [
 <xref rid="B12-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], kenaf etc. [
 <xref rid="B23-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] have been widely used as reinforcements in bioplastics. Several reviews of lignocellulosic fibers and biopolymers in bioplastics have already been conducted [
 <xref rid="B4-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>].
</p>
