<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Along with a number of benefits as reinforcements, there are some drawbacks associated with these lignocellulosic fibers. A significant number of studies focus on improving the compatibility between the lignocellulosic fibers and other biopolymers [
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The hydrophilicity and strong crosslinking of lignocellulosic fibers prevent the compatibility with biopolymer matrices, leading to poor interfacial adhesion and mechanical properties [
 <xref rid="B25-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. These bioplastics possess limited dimensional stability when exposed to moisture [
 <xref rid="B25-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Therefore, surface modifications are widely employed to enhance the performance of lignocellulosic fibers and to promote better adhesion between the natural reinforcement and the polymeric matrix [
 <xref rid="B27-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Today, most of the surface modifications are based on cellulose by removing the complicated lignin. As a consequence, lignin commonly changes into a waste in the residuals, while cellulose is used in the attempt to make bioplastics [
 <xref rid="B9-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Although the surface treatment can attain better performance, but removing lignin requires considerable energy input and produces much wastewater [
 <xref rid="B16-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. From a technical point of view, the process removing lignin is demanding technically and profitable impractically [
 <xref rid="B11-polymers-11-00751" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
