<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Plant tissue culture has become a promising alternative strategy for the sustainable and industrial-scale production of secondary metabolites. There are multiple advantages of medicinal plant tissue culture. (i) It is not affected by environmental or geographic conditions. (ii) It can strictly control production and quality and (iii) shorten the growth cycle compared to that of the intact plant. (iv) It avoids taking land resources. In fact, some plant secondary metabolites have been produced using this method, such as shikonin
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>, ginseng saponins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> and paclitaxel
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>, over the past decades. Based on this strategy, some elicitors have been widely used to enhance secondary metabolite production in many plant species. For example, methyl jasmonate (MJ) treatments were found to enhance the production of camptothecin in 
 <italic>Ophiorrhiza mungos</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup> and the content of olide A, withanolide A, withanone, and withaferin A in 
 <italic>Withania somnifera</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, salicylic acid (SA) can increase the accumulation of secondary metabolites in 
 <italic>Salvia miltiorrhiza</italic> cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> and 
 <italic>Daucus carota</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, wounding responses have always occurred. For example, wind, hail, sand and cuts can increase the secondary metabolite production of plants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, some researchers have to enhance SAN in 
 <italic>Argemone Mexicana</italic> by MJ, 
 <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> homogenates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, the sequential application of MJ, SA and YE also can increase the SAN content over 9 times in 
 <italic>A. Mexicana</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. Although the continuous treatment of MJ, SA and YE also can increase SAN 5.5 times in 
 <italic>Eschscholtzia californica</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. However, another research found that the effect of MJ treatment was better
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, manganese chloride is also used to try to increase BIAs in 
 <italic>E. californica</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. However, there still is no report available regarding the elicitor or mechanical damage effect on BIA production in the tissue culture of 
 <italic>M. cordata.</italic>
</p>
