<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The bioautography followed by TLC separation has been useful to determine antimicrobial activity of essential oils and to isolate the active compounds. A bioautography study with five aromatic plants (
 <italic class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Lavandula angustifolia</italic> Chaix, 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus globulus</italic> Labill., 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha spicata</italic> L., and 
 <italic class="italic">Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> Blume) against five bacteria (
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomonas syringae</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Xanthomonas campestris</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">S. saprophyticus</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic>) allowed to attribute the activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Thymus vulgaris</italic> essential oil to thymol, comparing to a pure standard, as well as the activity of 
 <italic class="italic">C. zeylanicum</italic> essential oil to eugenol, by the same principle [
 <xref rid="B29-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. A bioautography assay with 
 <italic class="italic">Mentha</italic> x 
 <italic class="italic">piperita</italic> L. essential oil against 
 <italic class="italic">Candida albicans</italic>, followed by TLC separation of the active fraction, indicated that menthol was responsible for this activity [
 <xref rid="B25-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Also, Guerrini et al. [
 <xref rid="B3-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] detected α-cadinol, α-muurolol, τ-muurolol, and linalool in the active fraction with antibacterial activity against 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> using High Performance Thin Layer Chromatography (HPTLC) plates for separation of 
 <italic class="italic">H. sprucei</italic> essential oil. In our study, the bioautography methodology indicated curzerene as the main compound for the active band found at R
 <sub class="sub">f</sub>’s 0.67 and α-terpineol, α-eudesmol and ferula lactone I for the active band at R
 <sub class="sub">f</sub> 0.12 (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00055-t002" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). The 
 <italic class="italic">H. brasiliense</italic> leaf essential oil collected at Santa Catarina (Brazil) presented antifungal activity and it was also rich in curzerene (8.9%) and α-terpineol (10.2%) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="medicines-04-00055-f004" class="xref">Figure 4</xref> A,B) [
 <xref rid="B25-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], supporting our results. 
</p>
