<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The antioxidant activity of essential oils is already well known [
 <xref rid="B34-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. According to Karadag et al. [
 <xref rid="B38-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], the antioxidant potential is related to compounds capable of protecting a biological system against the potentially harmful effect of reactive oxygen species. The results of a single-assay can give only a narrow view of the essential oil antioxidant properties. Therefore, the antioxidant potential of 
 <italic class="italic">H. brasiliense</italic> essential oils was determined by two different mechanisms of action: DPPH free radical scavenging, that works as electron transfer, and β-carotene/linoleic acid assay, measuring the suppression of lipoperoxides. In the DPPH assay, the IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> values for all the oils ranged from 2516.18 to 3783.49 μg/mL (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00055-t002" class="xref">Table 2</xref>), indicating a weak electron transfer capacity for the oils when compared to the positive controls quercetin and 
 <italic class="italic">G. biloba</italic> extract, that presented IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> values of 2.5 and 13.5 μg/mL, respectively. These results are comparable to those obtained for 
 <italic class="italic">Salvia tomentosa</italic> Mill. essential oils [
 <xref rid="B36-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>], which was rich in β-pinene (39.7%), α-pinene (10.9%) and camphor (9.7%), and it was not considered effective as antioxidant by DPPH and β-carotene/linoleic acid assay. Similarly, the essential oils of seven 
 <italic class="italic">Artemisia</italic> spp. were tested by the same methods and showed weak activities, as their composition were markedly rich in non-phenolic components [
 <xref rid="B39-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. The antioxidant capacity of essential oils, by the DPPH method normally, is not very high when compared with that obtained for extracts and fractions rich in phenolic compounds. The major antioxidative plant phenolic compounds known are eugenol, carvacrol, thymol, menthol, and safrole, among others [
 <xref rid="B34-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. In a test with 98 pure essential oil components for their antioxidant activity, phenols, such as thymol and carvacrol, were the most active compounds, followed by alcohols mono- and sesquiterpenes and ketones α,β-insaturated, however hydrocarbons presented very low antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B40-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. On the other hand, our results indicated that the essential oils of 
 <italic class="italic">H. brasiliense</italic> were much more active in the β-carotene bleaching assay, presenting IC
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">50</sub> values from 71.12 to 180.71 μg/mL (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00055-t002" class="xref">Table 2</xref>), indicating their ability in destroying the conjugated diene hydroperoxides, the end products of linoleic acid peroxidation. In this way, the low radical scavenging activity observed for the 
 <italic class="italic">H. brasiliense</italic> essential oils might be explained by the low amounts of phenolic compounds present in the oil, only 1.11 to 3.63% of thymol, and the high amounts of mono- and sesquiterpene hydrocarbons (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="medicines-04-00055-t001" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Since antioxidant activity of the entire oil is the result of the interaction of all constituents [
 <xref rid="B41-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>], it is hard to attribute the essential oils activity to a single compound, as other oil components may contribute exhibiting synergistic or antagonistic effects [
 <xref rid="B42-medicines-04-00055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. 
</p>
