<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_HLY6128 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><?FILEsi1 svg ?><?FILEsi2 svg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7903315</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2405-8440(21)00233-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06128</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e06128</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mosquitocidal activity of twenty-eight plant essential oils and their binary mixtures against <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus,</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Mahanta</surname><given-names>Sudarshana</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Khanikor</surname><given-names>Bulbuli</given-names></name><email>khanikorbulbuli@yahoo.co.in</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Zoology, Gauhati University, Guwahati, 781014, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>khanikorbulbuli@yahoo.co.in</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Postal Address: Department of Zoology, Gauhati University, Guwahati, Assam, India, 781014. Contact no. +91&#x02013;9365644187.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e06128</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Mosquito control programme using synthetic insecticides has been facing the challenges of resistance development. However, synergistic combinations of plant essential oils (EOs) having different modes of actions and potent lethal toxicity may further negate the concern of resistance development.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>In this study, the toxicity of 28 EOs and the two synthetic insecticides, Temephos and Malathion were evaluated individually and based on the performance, binary combinations of effective EOs were prepared and tested against the larval and adult stages of <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>. Mixtures were prepared by blending LC10 or LD10 concentration/doses of candidates at different volume ratios.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Results demonstrated that among 155 numbers of combinations of different volume ratios, 1:1 ratio of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) L.+<italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels) Macfd. (AsB + CpP) was found to be the most potent against adults, whereas, 1:1 volume ratio of <italic>Allium sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (leaves) (AsB + CpL) was found to possess highest activity against larvae after considering its dose and synergistic interaction. GC-MS analysis revealed the presence of diallyl trisulfide, diallyl disulfide, beta-citronellol, ocimene as major constituents of AsB + CpP combination and diallyl disulfide, linalool, citronellal, caryophyllene oxide etc. in AsB + CpL combination.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Therefore, the said mixtures of the plant essential oils and or mixtures of the constituent compounds can be used as effective control agents for the control of the filarial vector, <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Essential oils; Binary mixtures; Synergism; <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Essential oils</kwd><kwd>Binary mixtures</kwd><kwd>Synergism</kwd><kwd><italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Medical science and entomologists have been facing a diverse set of challenges to protect humans and domesticated animals from harmful mosquitoes. Considering the increasing populations of vector mosquitoes and cases of mosquito borne diseases, quick and proper counter measures are needed at the present time to improve the effectiveness of a vector control strategy. Prompting the adoption of effective mosquito control strategies has resulted in an urge to look for a highly potent, eco-friendly and cost-effective plant-based product. And the current study was aimed to establish low-dose plant essential oil-based synergistic combinations that would be effective against the larval and adult stages of the filarial vector, <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>.</p><p id="p0015">In recent years, researchers are giving more emphasis on developing mixtures to contribute a new dimension to prevent resistance evolution in the vector control strategy. A mixture of compounds or essential oils exerts either synergistic effect, antagonistic effect or no effect. Plant essential oil mixtures employing synergistic actions are considered to have a higher and longer lasting effect than pure organic compounds alone and therefore they are gaining more attention. Synergistic combinations of two or more agents can overcome side effects associated with high doses of single one by decreasing the risk of resistance development, sparing doses on each compound, or accessing context-specific multi-target mechanisms (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Lehar et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Youssefi et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). There have been fewer records of the use of essential oil mixtures as mosquitocidal, although few synergistic activity of mixtures of essential oils with synthetic insecticides have been reported against field crop pests and stored product pests (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Suwannayod et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). Moreover, the study on the potentiality of combinations purely made up of plant essential oils against mosquitoes is rare. In the current investigation, 155 numbers of binary mixtures are prepared from the selected essential oils. All total, twenty-eight essential oils are extracted from twenty-five numbers of plants to study their mosquitocidal activities which are selected based on traditional knowledge and literature review (Table&#x000a0;S1). Among these, some plants are already explored and some are investigated for the first time against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus.</italic> Based on their efficacy in terms of sublethal concentration, effective plant essential oils are selected for combination study to find out synergistic combinations. To compare the toxicity of synthetic insecticides with the plant essential oils, the larval and adult stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> are also treated with two commercially available WHO recommended synthetic organophosphates namely Temephos and Malathion respectively.</p><p id="p0020">Aiming to reduce the dose of synthetic insecticides to be released in the environment and to prevent resistance occurrence, combinations of synthetic organophosphates with the effective plant oils are also attempted to get synergistic interactions in any mixtures. The constituent profile of EOs of a plant species may vary in different regions. However, insight on constituents in combination may further help to develop efficient mixtures by adding its ingredient irrespective of geographical barrier etc. Therefore, to understand the constituent profile of the best combinations which are proved as the most effective against larval and adult stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> in the study, GC-MS analysis is carried out and analysed.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Results</title><p id="p0025">P- Diallyl disulfide, Q- Citronellal, R- Diallyl trisulfide, S- Caryophyllene oxides.</p><p id="p0030">The oil yield percentage of the selected essential oils is mentioned in Table&#x000a0;S7. The highest oil yield was recorded for the peel part of the plant <italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic>. On the other hand, the EOs from <italic>Homalomena aromatic</italic> (leaves) and <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic> (leaves) yielded the lowest amount. While recording the larvicidal activity of the selected essential oils, fourteen numbers of oils were found to possess no larvicidal activity since they did not cause any mortality even at the highest concentration (1000 ppm) (Table&#x000a0;S2). LC50 values were determined for the rest of the fourteen EOs. Among the effective EOs, the LC50 value was found lowest in case of <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) oil with LC50 value of 2.31 ppm. The remaining candidates were found to possess LC50 values at a range of 18.23&#x02013;275.66 ppm (Table&#x000a0;S3). The highest larvicidal activity was exhibited by Temephos with LC50 concentration of 0.7 ppm. No mortality was recorded in the positive and negative control. In case of the bioassay against the adult stage, results demonstrated that some of the essential oils like <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs), <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves), <italic>C.&#x000a0;aurantifolia</italic> (peels) and <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) possessed strong adulticidal activity (Table&#x000a0;S4). LD50 values could be calculated for seven numbers of plant essential oils. Among these, the lowest LD50 dose was recorded in case of <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil (0.35 &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>), which was followed by essential oil of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs). For Malathion, the recorded LD50 value was 0.3 &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>. In positive and negative control, no adult mortality was recorded.</p><p id="p0035">Based on the individual toxicity of the selected essential oils and the two organophosphates, the effective oils were selected for the preparation of binary mixtures to study their joint - activity against the larval and adult stages of the same target species. Six numbers of EOs and temephos were short-listed for the preparations of binary mixtures against the larval stage. Against the adult stage, four numbers of EOs and the organophosphate malathion were selected for the preparations of binary mixtures. Initially, blending of LC50 concentrations of the selected candidates were considered, but the results demonstrated 100% mortality in each case (Table&#x000a0;S5). As a result, it was difficult to underscore the most potent binary mixtures as all the mixtures had caused 100% observed mortality. Finally, the concentration was reduced to LC10 (against larvae) or LD10 (against adults) and binary mixtures were prepared at different volume ratios by mixing LC10 or LD10 concentrations/doses of each candidate present in the mixtures. It is obvious that if such results would be obtained even after reducing the concentration then it would be a better mosquito control agent from the point of cost, dose and toxicity towards the non-target organisms. For larvicidal activity, 83 numbers possessed synergistic effect in case of larvicidal activity. Four binary mixtures with antagonistic effect and eighteen numbers with no effect were also recorded (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Most of the temephos-based combinations were found to have synergistic interaction. Maximum numbers of <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) essential oil-based combinations were found to cause 100% larval mortality except <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) +<italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves) mixture at 2:1 volume ratio. The lowest larval mortality (3.3%) was observed in <italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves) +Temephos (1:1) and <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)+ <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) (1:1) mixtures. Fifty numbers of binary mixtures were tested against the adult stage of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>, out of which 14 combinations were found to exhibit synergistic interaction with observed mortality at the range of 53&#x02013;100% (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Malathion-based combinations were found to show antagonistic or no effect except in <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels)+Malathion (All volume ratios) and <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+Malathion (1:1) mixtures. However, fourteen numbers of mixtures were found to act antagonistically against the target individuals.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Larvicidal activity of binary mixtures of different volume ratios against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> after 24 Hours.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Volume ratios</th><th>Oil A</th><th>Oil B</th><th>LC10 (A)<break/>(Percent mortality)</th><th>LC10 (B)<break/>(Percent mortality)</th><th>Expected mortality</th><th>Observed mortality</th><th>Chi-square</th><th>Effect</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="21"><italic>1:1</italic></td><td rowspan="6"><italic>Allium sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>11.6</td><td>27.8</td><td>100</td><td>187.51</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>5</td><td>22.4</td><td>96.6</td><td>245.78</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Citrus grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>18.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>25.1</td><td>26.6</td><td>0.089</td><td>No Effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>20.9</td><td>55</td><td>55.64</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Mentha piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>25.1</td><td>6.6</td><td>13.63</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>18.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>20.75</td><td>96.6</td><td>277.26</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>5</td><td>16.02</td><td>100</td><td>440.24</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>8.3</td><td>18.9</td><td>45</td><td>36.04</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>11.6</td><td>8.3</td><td>18.9</td><td>96.6</td><td>319.43</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>3.3</td><td>13.67</td><td>100</td><td>545.20</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>11.6</td><td>3.3</td><td>13.67</td><td>100</td><td>545.20</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>11.3</td><td>86.6</td><td>501.77</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>15.9</td><td>38.3</td><td>31.56</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>5</td><td>12.9</td><td>51.6</td><td>116.1</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>8.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>10.76</td><td>12.67</td><td>0.33</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>3.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>11.3</td><td>28.3</td><td>25.57</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>3.3</td><td>5</td><td>8.1</td><td>48.3</td><td>199.51</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>5.91</td><td>3.3</td><td>1.28</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>5</td><td>8.3</td><td>12.9</td><td>3.3</td><td>7.14</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>5</td><td>3.3</td><td>7.85</td><td>9.5</td><td>0.34</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Temephos</td><td>8.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>10.76</td><td>12.3</td><td>0.22</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="21"><italic>1:2</italic></td><td rowspan="6"><italic>A.sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>5</td><td>22.1</td><td>100</td><td>273.53</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>3.33</td><td>20.7</td><td>51.67</td><td>46.33</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>18.3</td><td>1.67</td><td>19.61</td><td>25</td><td>1.48</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>0</td><td>18.3</td><td>61.67</td><td>102.78</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>3.33</td><td>20.7</td><td>10</td><td>5.53</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>18.3</td><td>0</td><td>18.3</td><td>25</td><td>2.45</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>3.33</td><td>13.6</td><td>100</td><td>548.89</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>3.33</td><td>13.6</td><td>100</td><td>548.89</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>11.6</td><td>1.67</td><td>12.42</td><td>100</td><td>617.57</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>0</td><td>11.6</td><td>100</td><td>673.67</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>11.6</td><td>0</td><td>11.6</td><td>100</td><td>673.67</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>100</td><td>1013.12</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>3.33</td><td>10.76</td><td>100</td><td>740.13</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>3.33</td><td>10.76</td><td>41.67</td><td>88.79</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>8.3</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>93.3</td><td>870.48</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.33</td><td>5.91</td><td>31.67</td><td>112.28</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.33</td><td>5.91</td><td>31.67</td><td>112.28</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>3.3</td><td>0</td><td>3.3</td><td>100</td><td>2833.60</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>5</td><td>3.33</td><td>7.85</td><td>11.67</td><td>1.85</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>5</td><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>100</td><td>1805</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Temephos</td><td>3.3</td><td>0</td><td>3.3</td><td>100</td><td>2833.60</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="21"><italic>2:1</italic></td><td rowspan="6"><italic>A.sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>11.6</td><td>11.6</td><td>100</td><td>673.67</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>100</td><td>1805</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>11.6</td><td>1.31</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>60</td><td>974.20</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>16.67</td><td>8.44</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>0</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>18.33</td><td>68.45</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>9.75</td><td>100</td><td>835.39</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>5</td><td>8.3</td><td>12.6</td><td>100</td><td>606.25</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>5</td><td>8.3</td><td>12.6</td><td>100</td><td>606.25</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>5</td><td>3.3</td><td>7.85</td><td>11.67</td><td>1.85</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>5</td><td>11.67</td><td>15.45</td><td>100</td><td>462.70</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>1.67</td><td>3.3</td><td>18.96</td><td>36.67</td><td>16.54</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>1.67</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.87</td><td>88.33</td><td>711.82</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>1.67</td><td>5</td><td>5.95</td><td>36.67</td><td>158.60</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>1.67</td><td>11.67</td><td>11.89</td><td>100</td><td>652.38</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>25</td><td>33.60</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>11.67</td><td>8.89</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>0</td><td>11.67</td><td>11.67</td><td>96.67</td><td>619.10</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>3.33</td><td>8.3</td><td>10.76</td><td>13.33</td><td>0.61</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>3.33</td><td>11.6</td><td>13.67</td><td>100</td><td>545.20</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Temephos</td><td>3.33</td><td>11.6</td><td>13.67</td><td>100</td><td>545.20</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="21"><italic>1:3</italic></td><td rowspan="6"><italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>21.7</td><td>35.22</td><td>100</td><td>119.21</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>13.3</td><td>28.67</td><td>46.67</td><td>11.41</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>18.3</td><td>18.3</td><td>32.76</td><td>18.3</td><td>638.25</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>0</td><td>18.3</td><td>19.1</td><td>0.40</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>5</td><td>22.1</td><td>19.1</td><td>0.40</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>18.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>20.46</td><td>31.67</td><td>6.14</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>13.3</td><td>22.57</td><td>100</td><td>265.63</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>5</td><td>15.45</td><td>100</td><td>462.69</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>11.6</td><td>18.3</td><td>27.02</td><td>100</td><td>197.12</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>11.6</td><td>0</td><td>11.6</td><td>100</td><td>673.67</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>11.6</td><td>3.3</td><td>13.67</td><td>100</td><td>546.80</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>95</td><td>905.65</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>5</td><td>12.6</td><td>18.3</td><td>2.57</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>8.3</td><td>13.3</td><td>19.96</td><td>16.7</td><td>0.532</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>8.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>10.76</td><td>91.67</td><td>608.41</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>3.3</td><td>5</td><td>7.85</td><td>26.6</td><td>44.78</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>3.3</td><td>13.3</td><td>15.61</td><td>28.3</td><td>10.31</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>5.91</td><td>100</td><td>1497.95</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>9.7</td><td>35</td><td>51.26</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>5</td><td>3.3</td><td>7.85</td><td>100</td><td>1081.74</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Temephos</td><td>8.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>11.06</td><td>100</td><td>715.22</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="23"><italic>3:1</italic></td><td rowspan="6"><italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>11.6</td><td>11.6</td><td>100</td><td>673.67</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>76.67</td><td>1027.31</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>6.67</td><td>0.32</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>53.3</td><td>757.57</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>14.2</td><td>4.1</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>0</td><td>3.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>25</td><td>142.69</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>21.67</td><td>5</td><td>24.95</td><td>100</td><td>225.75</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>21.67</td><td>8.3</td><td>27.32</td><td>100</td><td>193.35</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td>21.67</td><td>8.3</td><td>27.32</td><td>100</td><td>193.35</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>21.67</td><td>3.3</td><td>23.37</td><td>100</td><td>251.27</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>21.67</td><td>3.3</td><td>23.37</td><td>100</td><td>251.27</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>20.46</td><td>23.3</td><td>0.39</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>24.56</td><td>98.3</td><td>221.40</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>18.3</td><td>5</td><td>22.1</td><td>15</td><td>2.28</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Temephos</td><td>18.3</td><td>3.3</td><td>20.46</td><td>32.1</td><td>6.62</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4"><italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>8.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>20</td><td>16.49</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td>0</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>15</td><td>20</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Temephos</td><td rowspan="2">0</td><td rowspan="2">3.3</td><td rowspan="2">3.3</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2">2833.60</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>13.3</td><td>8.3</td><td>19.96</td><td>16.67</td><td>0.54</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Temephos</td><td rowspan="2">13.3</td><td rowspan="2">3.3</td><td rowspan="2">15.61</td><td rowspan="2">100</td><td rowspan="2">456.22</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Temephos</td><td>5</td><td>3.3</td><td>7.85</td><td>100</td><td>1081.73</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Adulticidal activity of binary mixtures of different volume ratios against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> after 24 Hours.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Volume ratios</th><th>Oil A</th><th>Oil B</th><th>LC10(A)<break/>(Percent mortality)</th><th>LC10(B)<break/>(Percent mortality)</th><th>Expected mortality</th><th>Observed mortality</th><th>Chi square</th><th>Effect</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="10"><italic>1:1</italic></td><td rowspan="4"><italic>A.sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>6.6</td><td>6.6</td><td>12.7</td><td>100</td><td>600.1</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aegle marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>15</td><td>20.6</td><td>16.6</td><td>0.78</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Eucalyptus maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>15</td><td>20.6</td><td>53.3</td><td>51.90</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>6.6</td><td>6.6</td><td>11.64</td><td>100</td><td>670.75</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>15</td><td>6.6</td><td>20.6</td><td>56.6</td><td>62.91</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>15</td><td>15</td><td>27.75</td><td>33.3</td><td>1.1</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>15</td><td>6.6</td><td>20.1</td><td>22.3</td><td>0.24</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>15</td><td>20.6</td><td>13.3</td><td>2.58</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>6.6</td><td>6.6</td><td>11.64</td><td>100</td><td>670.75</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Malathion</td><td>15</td><td>6.6</td><td>20.1</td><td>25.3</td><td>1.34</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10"><italic>1:2</italic></td><td rowspan="4"><italic>A.sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>6.6</td><td>20</td><td>24.8</td><td>100</td><td>228.02</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>53.3</td><td>55.82</td><td>93.33</td><td>25.17</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>50</td><td>53</td><td>63.33</td><td>2.001</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>6.6</td><td>13.3</td><td>18.22</td><td>21.2</td><td>0.48</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>15</td><td>20</td><td>32</td><td>10</td><td>16.1</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>15</td><td>50</td><td>57.5</td><td>23.33</td><td>20.30</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>15</td><td>13.3</td><td>26.05</td><td>28.2</td><td>0.17</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>50</td><td>53</td><td>63.33</td><td>2.001</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>6.6</td><td>13.3</td><td>18.22</td><td>100</td><td>367.06</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Malathion</td><td>15</td><td>13.3</td><td>26.05</td><td>29.1</td><td>0.35</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10"><italic>2:1</italic></td><td rowspan="4"><italic>A.sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>96.67</td><td>6.6</td><td>96.24</td><td>100</td><td>.15</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td>96.67</td><td>15</td><td>96.67</td><td>96.67</td><td>0</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>96.67</td><td>15</td><td>96.67</td><td>56.67</td><td>16.56</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>96.67</td><td>6.6</td><td>96.24</td><td>73.33</td><td>5.45</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>53.33</td><td>6.6</td><td>98.82</td><td>30</td><td>47.93</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>53.33</td><td>15</td><td>60.05</td><td>56.67</td><td>0.19</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>53.33</td><td>6.6</td><td>98.82</td><td>100</td><td>0.014</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>20</td><td>15</td><td>32</td><td>26.67</td><td>28.40</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>20</td><td>6.6</td><td>24.8</td><td>96.67</td><td>208.27</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Malathion</td><td>50</td><td>6.6</td><td>53</td><td>57.2</td><td>0.33</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10"><italic>1:3</italic></td><td rowspan="4"><italic>A.sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>6.6</td><td>66.67</td><td>68.04</td><td>60</td><td>0.07</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>80</td><td>81.2</td><td>100</td><td>4.35</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>63.33</td><td>65.22</td><td>63.33</td><td>0.06</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>6.6</td><td>30</td><td>34.2</td><td>41.3</td><td>1.47</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>15</td><td>66.67</td><td>80.01</td><td>26.67</td><td>35.50</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>15</td><td>63.33</td><td>68.55</td><td>46.67</td><td>6.98</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>15</td><td>30</td><td>40.5</td><td>28.67</td><td>3.45</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>6.6</td><td>63.33</td><td>65.22</td><td>96.67</td><td>15.16</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>6.6</td><td>30</td><td>34.2</td><td>96.67</td><td>114.10</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Malathion</td><td>15</td><td>30</td><td>40.5</td><td>43.2</td><td>0.18</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="10"><italic>3:1</italic></td><td rowspan="4"><italic>A.sativum</italic> (bulbs)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>93.33</td><td>6.6</td><td>93.42</td><td>83.33</td><td>1.09</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td>93.33</td><td>15</td><td>94.05</td><td>40</td><td>31.06</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>93.33</td><td>15</td><td>94.05</td><td>46.67</td><td>23.87</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>93.33</td><td>6.6</td><td>93.42</td><td>93.33</td><td>0.0001</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3"><italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)</td><td><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td>80</td><td>6.6</td><td>81.2</td><td>63.33</td><td>3.94</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>80</td><td>15</td><td>83</td><td>46.67</td><td>15.90</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>80</td><td>6.6</td><td>81.2</td><td>85.3</td><td>0.20</td><td>No effect</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>C.paradisi</italic> (peels)</td><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>66.67</td><td>15</td><td>71.1</td><td>100</td><td>11.74</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td>Malathion</td><td>66.67</td><td>6.6</td><td>68.04</td><td>96.67</td><td>12.05</td><td>Synergistic</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves)</td><td>Malathion</td><td>63.33</td><td>6.6</td><td>65.52</td><td>41.2</td><td>9.02</td><td>Antagonistic</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0040">Based on the dose of the essential oils present in the mixtures and its effect in terms of observed mortality, the most effective binary combinations were selected which were <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) against adults and <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) against larvae respectively. Besides this, the availability of the selected essential oils, their high yielding nature and environmental and health safety attributes were also taken into account for selection of combination. It is worthwhile to mention that both the plants considered for combinations are edible plants and locally available as well as cultivated commercially for their edible parts.</p><p id="p0045">A number of compounds are found to be present in it and based on its area percentages, probable major constituents are reported. From GC-MS analysis, the constituent profile of <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) combination showed the presence of diallyl trisulfide, diallyldisulfide, beta citronellol, ocimene as probable major constituents of the combination (Figures <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, in the binary mixture of <italic>A. sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>C. paradisi</italic> (leaves), the major constituents identified were diallyldisulfide, citronellal, diallyltrisulfide, caryophyllene oxide etc. The MS, molecular weight, retention index, area percentage and retention time are mentioned below (Figures <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Tables <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The constituent profile of individual essential oils selected in the present study was mentioned in Table S6.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>MS of the constituent compounds of the binary mixture of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixture.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>MS of four major constituent compounds of the binary mixtures (1:1 volume ratio) of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixture. A-Diallyltrisulfide, B- Diallyl disulfide, C- Beta citronellol, D- Ocimene.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>MS of the constituent compounds of the binary mixtures of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil mixture.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Figure&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>MS of four major constituents of the binary mixture (1:1 volume ratio) of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil mixture. P- Diallyl disulfide, Q- Citronellal, R- Diallyl trisulfide, S- Caryophyllene oxides.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Figure&#x000a0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Constituent compounds of the binary mixture (1:1 volume ratio) of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixture.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Component</th><th>Molecular weight</th><th>Retention index</th><th>Chemical formula</th><th>Area (percent)</th><th>Retention time (minute)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Diallyl trisulfide</td><td>178</td><td>1350</td><td>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>10</sub>S<sub>3</sub></td><td>34.98</td><td>11.93</td></tr><tr><td>Diallyl disulfide</td><td>146</td><td>1099</td><td>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>10</sub>S<sub>2</sub></td><td>32.15</td><td>6.27</td></tr><tr><td>Beta citronellol</td><td>156</td><td>1179</td><td>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>20</sub>O</td><td>12.21</td><td>4.15</td></tr><tr><td>Ocimene</td><td>136</td><td>976</td><td>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>16</sub></td><td>3.24</td><td>37.4</td></tr><tr><td>Beta- terpinyl acetate</td><td>196</td><td>1348</td><td>C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>20</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td>3.07</td><td>39.26</td></tr><tr><td>Linalool oxide</td><td>170</td><td>1164</td><td>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>18</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td>2.40</td><td>34.75</td></tr><tr><td>Terpinene-4-ol</td><td>154</td><td>1137</td><td>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>18</sub>O</td><td>1.67</td><td>11.93</td></tr><tr><td>Alpha terpinol</td><td>154</td><td>1143</td><td>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>18</sub>O</td><td>1.51</td><td>20.94</td></tr><tr><td>Oxalic acid</td><td>256</td><td>1738</td><td>C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>24</sub>O<sub>4</sub></td><td>1.47</td><td>5.17</td></tr><tr><td>Cycloheptatriene</td><td>92</td><td>786</td><td>C<sub>7</sub>H<sub>8</sub></td><td>0.70</td><td>7.78</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Constituent compounds of the binary mixture (1:1 volume ratio) of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil mixture.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#x000a0;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Component</th><th>Molecular weight</th><th>Retention index</th><th>Chemical formula</th><th>Area (percent)</th><th>Retention time (minute)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Diallyl disulfide</td><td>146</td><td>1099</td><td>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>10</sub>S<sub>2</sub></td><td>32.75</td><td>4.51</td></tr><tr><td>Citronellal</td><td>154</td><td>1125</td><td>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>18</sub>O</td><td>23.64</td><td>10.23</td></tr><tr><td>Diallyl trisulfide</td><td>178</td><td>1350</td><td>C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>10</sub>S<sub>3</sub></td><td>16.45</td><td>13.83</td></tr><tr><td>Caryophyllene oxide</td><td>220</td><td>1507</td><td>C<sub>15</sub>H<sub>24</sub>O</td><td>8.24</td><td>4.16</td></tr><tr><td>Linalool</td><td>154</td><td>1082</td><td>C<sub>10</sub>H<sub>18</sub>O</td><td>3.62</td><td>8.63</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0050">In the present investigation, as larvicides essential oil of <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves), <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulb), <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves), <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves), <italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels) and <italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves) are found to be highly effective against the target species. However, treated larvae are found to be moderately responsive to the oil of <italic>C.&#x000a0;aurantifolia</italic> (leaves), <italic>C.&#x000a0;linearis</italic> (leaves), <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves), <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves), <italic>C.&#x000a0;sinensis</italic> (leaves) and <italic>L.&#x000a0;alba</italic> (leaves). Treated adults are found as highly responsive toward the oils of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs), <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels), <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs), <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels), <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) respectively but with higher LD50 dose in comparison to larvae. The result of the current study revealed that in some cases, the same plant essential oil acted differently against the different developmental stages of the same target species, <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>. These differential toxic effects might be due to their difference in the levels of penetration and persistence in different life stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). However, in some other cases, the same plant oil is found effective against both the larval and adult stages and therefore such oils can be applied to control this mosquito species irrespective of their developmental stages. In the present investigation, the larval and adult stages of the target species are found to be vulnerable to <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil. The larvicidal activity of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil is in conformity with the findings of <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Muturi et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> where they observed biocidal activity of the garlic oil against <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> and mentioned the constituent compound, allyl disulfide as the responsible factor. It seems that garlic oil is comparatively less volatile because it contains constituent molecules having higher weight with thiol groups than commonly occurring terpene compounds of other essential oils and thereby strongly affecting every developmental stage of the target species due to its high persistence<bold>.</bold> Like <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil, <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) oil is also found toxic against larvae and adults of the target species. The reported major constituents of the <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) oil are eucalyptol and eudesmol which are individually found to be effective against <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> in earlier studies (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>) and the same compounds may be responsible for the biocidal activity of the oil against the life stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> in the present case. In our previous study, we have reported <italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (peels) oil as potent larvicide for the first time against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>, where eudesmol, nootkatone etc. are found as the major constituent compounds which may be the possible factors for its toxicity against larvae (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Mahanta et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Besides these, <italic>C.&#x000a0;grandis</italic> (leaves) and <italic>C.&#x000a0;aurantifolia</italic> (leaves) oils are also found as effective larvicides in the current study. Two of the selected plant oils namely <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) and <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves) oils are found efficient only against the larval stage of the target species. The presence of aromatic rings and both the endocyclic and exocyclic double bonds in its constituent profiles [limonene and carvone in <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) and eugenol and methyl eugenol in <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)] may play the pivotal role for the larvicidal effect (<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Pandey et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, the <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil is found as a strong larvicidal agent with LC50 value of 22.18 ppm against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> for the first time in our investigation. Earlier it was reported as potent ovicide and larvicide against <italic>Aedes</italic> and <italic>Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes respectively (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Dosoky and Setzer, 2018</xref>). Sabinene, beta-ocimene, gamma-terpinene, beta pinene etc. are some of the reported major constituents of this oil which may be responsible for the strong larvicidal activity of the plant oil (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Paoli et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil is also found as an adulticide for the first time in our investigation which may be due to the activity of its constituent compounds like limonene, linalool, pinene etc (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Ivoke et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). In addition to <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) and <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oils, <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves) and <italic>C.&#x000a0;aurantifolia</italic> (peels) oils are also found to act as adulticides but with relatively higher LD50 dose in comparison to their early life stage.</p><p id="p0055">In the present study, some of the plant essential oils like <italic>L.&#x000a0;camara</italic>, <italic>F.&#x000a0;benghalensis</italic>, <italic>Z.&#x000a0;officinale</italic>, <italic>M.&#x000a0;koengii, C. fistula</italic> etc. are found to be ineffective against the target species, though these candidate oils were reported to possess insecticidal activities in previous studies (<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Rahuman et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Govindarajan, 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Rajan and Varghese, 2017</xref>). Differences in the constituent profile of plant essential oils may affect its toxicity. Climatic condition, geographic location, method of extraction, time of harvesting, soil properties are some of the factors which determine the constituent compounds of an essential oil (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Mahanta et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Differences in susceptibility of the treated individuals to the different oils are due to differential rates of uptake, penetration through the chorion which is dependent on the exposure period, detoxification and failure of the toxicant to reach the target (<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Ramar et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). The constituent profiles of each of the selected essential oils are mentioned here (Table&#x000a0;S6). Some of the reported compounds (e.g. limonene from <italic>P.&#x000a0;alba</italic>, alpha pinene from <italic>E.&#x000a0;odoratum</italic>, Eugenol from <italic>C.&#x000a0;fistula</italic>, 1,8- cineol from <italic>C.&#x000a0;linnearis</italic> etc.) of these plants are found to possess insecticidal activities against mosquitoes (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Pavela, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>) though they are not able to cause mortality in the present study whenever tested as crude oils against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>. This may be due to the interference of some other minor compounds present in the crude essential oils. Again, the role of the environmental temperature in differential performance of EOs and their constituents cannot be overruled. It has already been established that the same plant oil or constituent show different biocidal activities in different environmental temperatures. <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Pavela and Sedlak (2018)</xref> experimentally proved higher efficacy of <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> EO and its constituents carvacrol and thymol at the lower temperature (15 &#x000b0;C) in comparison to the higher temperature (30 &#x000b0;C) against larvae of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>. However, in the present study almost uniform laboratory temperature range is maintained during the experimental period. It is also reported in literature that some plant EOs may not show prominent acute toxicity at sublethal concentrations but the treatment may impact on fertility and vitality in the next generation (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Pavela, 2012</xref>). In a recent study <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Pavela et&#x000a0;al. (2020)</xref> showed noticeable reduction of fertility, lower hatching abilities as well as lower vitalities in houseflies in response to the treatment of the sublethal concentration of EO of <italic>Carlina acaulis</italic> and its constituent carlina oxide. Though, in the current study the effect of plant EO on fertility and vitality in the next generation was not studied, further work in this line may enrich information on efficacy of plant EO on this aspect.</p><p id="p0060">Plant essential oils usually present defences as a suite of compounds, not as individual ones. It is thought that a mixture of different constituent compounds, both major and minor constituents cumulatively act to offer plant defence against herbivory and pathogens through a variety of mechanisms. Therefore, in the present investigation, after observing the individual toxicity of the selected plant oils, 155 numbers of binary mixtures were prepared and tested against two developmental stages of the same target species in order to enhance the efficiency and to reduce the dose of a particular essential oil present in the mixture.</p><p id="p0065">In the current study, after applying the prepared binary mixtures, we observed synergistic interaction with a high percentage of observed larval mortality in most of the cases. A total of 83 numbers of mixtures are found to act synergistically against the treated larvae. Interestingly, 100% observed mortality is recorded in case of <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil-based binary mixtures-treated larvae. It is for the first time we have reported the <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil as a strong candidate against the larval stage of the filarial vector. The major as well as the minor compounds present in this essential oil may act cumulatively to induce the activity of the other plant oils present in the mixture. The possible explanation for the increased toxicity of binary mixtures would be that one candidate might have interfered with the enzymatic detoxification of the second one, thereby enhancing its total toxicity (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Perumalsamy et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>). The garlic oil-based combinations are also found to have synergistic interaction against the larval stage of the target species. The variety of major constituent compounds like sulfur compounds (from the garlic oil), monoterpenes or monoterpenoides (limonene, carvone, eugenol, nootkatone etc. from <italic>Citrus</italic>, <italic>Mentha</italic>, <italic>Ocimum</italic> oils) may share different mode of action and thereby increasing its final lethal activities (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Pavela, 2015</xref>). At 1:1 volume ratio, out of 21 numbers, only two combinations i.e. <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) and <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)+ <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) are found to act antagonistically which may be due to the same mode of actions of the constituent compounds present in the candidate oils. Such kind of antagonism can be supported by the findings of <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> where they mentioned the antagonistic interaction between carvone [one of the major constituents of <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) oil] and the sulfur compound [one of the major constituents of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil]. However, the antagonistic effect observed in case of <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves)+ <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) mixture treated larvae has a disagreement with the results reported in their investigations as the mixtures of eugenol [one of the constituents of <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves) oil] with carvone as well as limonene have manifested synergism against the larval stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>. The antagonistic interaction may be due to the involvement of some other minor constituent compounds present in <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> (leaves) and <italic>M.&#x000a0;piperita</italic> (leaves) plant essential oils. In other volume ratios of these two combinations whenever the amount of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> and <italic>O.&#x000a0;sanctum</italic> oils are increased, the mixtures have shown synergistic activities. From this an assertion could be made that the <italic>Mentha</italic> oil is not so effective in combination though it is found to be the most effective one when tested alone. Finally, the most effective binary combination proposed in the current study against the larval stage is 1:1 volume ratio of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves). The co-activity of the monoterpenes [major constituents of <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil and organosulfur compounds major constituents of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) oil] may lead to the synergy in the larval stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>.</p><p id="p0070">The susceptibility status of the adult stage of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> towards the prepared binary mixtures is also studied in the present investigation. Most of the combinations of 1:1 volume ratio has shown synergistic effect except the mixtures of essential oil of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves); <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) and <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels)+ <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves). Similarly, at 1:3 volume ratio, when the volume of <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) oil is increased upto three times than its original LC10 concentration, <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels)+ <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) mixture is found to possess synergism. However, <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) mixture is not able to act synergistically despite the testing of its different volume ratios against the adult individuals. The synergistic interaction with 100% observed mortality is recorded in case of the mixture of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixture. However, 1:3 and 3:1 volume ratios of these mixtures are found to show no effect. From such findings, a conclusion can be drawn that the mixtures may act synergistically at an optimum volume ratio of the particular essential oil present in the mixture. Below or above the volume range, they may lose their synergistic interaction. Moreover, the mixture of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>E.&#x000a0;maculata</italic> (leaves) and <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixtures are also found to act synergistically only at 1:1 volume ratio. These oils may act at different target sites for which synergism occurs. The minor compounds may also interact due to which synergistic effect is observed even at the LC10/LD10 concentration/dose. Some of the <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil-based combinations like 1:1 volume ratio of <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) and <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixtures are found to possess synergism. The co-toxicity of different major constituents viz. sulfur compounds from <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs), limonene from <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil, beta-terpinyl acetate from <italic>A.&#x000a0;marmelos</italic> (leaves) oil with different mode of actions may be the possible reason for their synergistic interaction. Against the adult stage, 1:1 volume ratio of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs)+ <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) oil mixture is considered as the most effective combination.</p><p id="p0075">In case of larvae and adults, some of the binary combinations consisting of temephos or malathion are not found to bear synergistic interaction though they are individually effective as larvicides and adulticides. The possible explanation for such effect is that the synthetic insecticides possess high hydrophobicity and affinity with the essential oils due to which the molecules of the synthetic insecticides get dispersed in the essential oil and as a result bioavailability is decreased (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">Suwannayod et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). However, in some cases the synergistic interaction is also recorded in the temephos or malathion-based combinations. Such outcomes may provide new information that the recommended doses of some of the synthetic organophosphates can be reduced whenever applied as a mixture with plant essential oils. In addition, the rate of susceptibility towards the prepared binary mixtures is found to differ among the different developmental stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>. Larvae are found to be the most susceptible as in most of the cases synergistic interaction is recorded which can be supported by the findings of <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Fox et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</xref> as they mentioned that the larval stage was more responsive to any physical and chemical stresses than the other developmental stages. From the findings it can be concluded that the mixture of essential oil of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> and <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> is found to be effective against larval and adult stage of the filarial vector. The only difference is in case of the larval stages where the effective combination was <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sativum</italic> (bulbs) and <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) oils and in other cases <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) and <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (peels).</p><p id="p0080">In the current study, GC-MS analysis is carried out to highlight the constituent profile of the two most effective binary mixtures i.e. <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulb) + <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) and <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) + <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels). The nature and the structure of the constituent compounds like the presence of hydrocarbon chains besides a phenyl ring, and exocyclic double bonds are some of the responsible factors for the efficacy of essential oil constituents (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Benelli et&#x000a0;al., 2017a</xref>). Here, the constituent profile has shown the presence of diallyl trisulfide, diallyldisulfide, beta citronellol, ocimene as probable major compounds in <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) + <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) combination. Again, in the mixture of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) + <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves), probable major constituents are diallyldisulfide, citronellal, diallyltrisulfide, caryophyllene oxide, linalool. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Deng et&#x000a0;al. (2020)</xref> and <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Sarma et&#x000a0;al. (2019)</xref> proposed the chemical composition of <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> and <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> essential oil where they found some of the compounds similar (like ocimene, linalool, citronellal, caryophyllene oxide for <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> and diallyldisulfide, diallyltrisulfide for <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> respectively) to our findings in this investigation. Most of the probable major constituents of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) + <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) oil mixture viz. sulfur compounds, citronellal, linalool is found to possess no effect in binary combinations as proposed by <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Pavela (2015)</xref>. Therefore, it is important to mention that other major compounds of this particular mixture viz. caryophyllene oxide may be responsible for its synergistic effect along with some other minor constituents. Moreover, caryophyllene oxide is already reported as a larvicidal compound by some of the authors against mosquitoes (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Hung et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>). One of the major compounds of <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) + <italic>C.&#x000a0;paradisi</italic> (leaves) combination, linalool was found to exhibit less larvicidal activity against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> which was established by <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Benelli et&#x000a0;al. (2017b)</xref>. They stated that the insecticidal activity of an essential oil depends not only on its main molecules, but it is an interaction among all the constituent components. Here in the present case, linalool may act as a synergist whenever present in mixture with some other compounds against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> larvae. Moreover, the major constituent compounds present in the <italic>A.&#x000a0;sativum</italic> (bulbs) + <italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> (peels) mixture like sulfur compounds, citronellol, ocimene, terpinyl acetate are already found to be reported to possess insecticidal activities against different pests including mosquitoes (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Chu et&#x000a0;al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Liu et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bossou et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Tabari et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). In these combinations, if we consider the area percentages of the constituents, sulfur compounds and monoterpenes occupy maximum areas and therefore an assumption can be made that the presence of these two types of constituent compounds may be responsible for their synergistic interaction even at a low concentration against <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>.</p><p id="p0085">It is already proved that the presence of a penetration-enhancing effect in the synergistic combination is the primary mechanism of synergy. The synergy in botanical insecticides would be based on the activation of multiple-target sites, interaction with resistance mechanisms and pharmacokinetic effects that improve solubility (<xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Tak and Isman, 2017</xref>). Therefore, such findings could promote a new direction towards the establishment of binary mixtures of plant essential oils which are effective at a very low concentration against different life stages of the filarial vector, <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>. In the present study, the profound effect of prepared combinations on the target species even at LC10/LD10 is the major finding. Bio availability of active compounds at these optimum concentrations in prepared mixtures might be the probable cause for such outcomes (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Mahanta et&#x000a0;al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0090">This experiment provides us a product of binary mixture of the same plant essential oils that acts equally against two developmental stages of this particular mosquito species. Such findings are expected to provide promising alternative measures for reducing the use of synthetic insecticides, which might be effective in terms of cost, toxicity and resistance development. Plant essential oils generally are nontoxic to mammals and other vertebrates. Botanical insecticides developed on the basis of EO are gaining importance because of their environmental and health safety attributes. They are considered to be safe, and eco-friendly alternatives to the synthetic chemicals, although a few studies raise questions about the safety of certain plant essential oils and their constituent compounds. In fact, the most important issue to be considered for the application of essential oils is their rapid degradation under the impact of air and light. Their direct and indirect effects on the other non-target organisms and the economic aspects must be considered before commercialization.</p><p id="p0095">In the present investigation, after testing of 28 EOs and its selected binary mixtures against larval and adult stages of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>, finally it gives some potential mixtures consisting of garlic oil and <italic>Citrus</italic> oil. To the best of our knowledge, this is for the first time we have tested 155 numbers of binary mixtures comprising of only plant crude oils or the mixtures of plant oils plus synthetic insecticides and proposed some profoundly effective combinations of a very low concentration of LC10/LD10 [earlier some authors have reported the joint-toxicity of binary mixtures by using LC50 or LC25 concentrations basically taking the constituent compounds of plant oils (<xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Pavela, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Youssefi et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>)] and their constituent profiles against larvae and adults of the filarial vector, <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Rearing of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic></title><p id="p0100">Egg rafts of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> were collected from Regional Medical Research Centre (RMRC- ICMR), Dibrugarh, Assam, India. The collected eggs were reared in an insect culture room, Dept. of Zoology, Gauhati University and the colonies were maintained between 25 &#x02013; 29 &#x000b0;C temperature and 80&#x02013;90% relative humidity following the method described by <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Arivoli and Tennyson (2011)</xref>. The egg rafts were kept in plastic trays containing 1000 ml of tap water and they were fed on finely powdered dog biscuits and yeast powder (3:1). After the fourth instar larval stage, pupae emerged. The pupal stage was transferred to a disposable cup half filled with water and kept in wooden netted cage of size measuring (1 &#x000d7; 1 &#x000d7; 1 m), where they finally metamorphosed in to the adult stage within 1&#x02013;3 days. No food was provided to the pupal stage. The adult colony was provided with 10% glucose solution soaked in cotton kept in the glass petri-dishes. After 3&#x02013;4 days of adult emergence, an albino rat was provided for blood-feeding. Gravid females after 1&#x02013;2 days of blood feeding laid eggs on the plastic cups containing water.</p><p id="p0105">The Institutional Animal Ethical Committee, Gauhati University gave the permission for using mosquitoes as experimental animals via Reference Number IAEC/Per/2019/RF/2019-021.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><label>4.2</label><title>Collection of plant material</title><p id="p0110">All of the selected plant species (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>) were collected from Guwahati city (Kamrup District, Assam) and the species were identified by the curator, Department of Botany, Gauhati University.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><label>4.3</label><title>Essential oil extraction</title><p id="p0115">After washing, collected parts of the plants (500 g) were cut into small pieces and the essential oil was extracted through hydro distillation method using Clevenger's apparatus following the method described by <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</xref>. The chopped plant materials were placed in 5 L round bottom flask containing 2&#x02013;3 L of water and allowed to heat over heating mantle for about 5&#x02013;6 h which softens the plant materials and allows the release of essential oil in volatile form. The thermostat of the heating mantel was set at 50 &#x000b0;C for extraction of essential oil. The essential oil vapours were condensed and formed a two layered mixture having essential oil in the top layer at the recuperating container. Essential oils were collected and stored in clean glass vials after removing water traces with the help of micropipette and stored at 4 &#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><label>4.4</label><title>Larvicidal assay</title><p id="p0120">To investigate the larvicidal activity, the standard World Health Organization procedure was followed with little modification. 20 numbers of third instar larvae were transferred to the disposable cups (depth 5&#x02013;10 cm) having 100 ml of water where 100 and 1000 ppm concentrations were applied as mentioned above. Based on the results of the pilot test of the essential oil at 100 and 1000 ppm of concentrations, a wide range of concentrations (1 ppm, 5 ppm, 10 ppm, 25 ppm, 50 ppm, 100 ppm, 250 ppm, 500 ppm, 750 ppm, 1000 ppm) of essential oils were prepared using equal amount of dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO) as emulsifying agent. For Temephos, three more concentrations (0.1ppm, 0.5 ppm and 1ppm) were applied. Twenty numbers of 3rd instar larvae were transferred to each replica of each concentration. The mortality was recorded after 24 h by observing larval death. The LC50 and LC10 concentrations were calculated after 24 h of treatment. Each concentration was assayed in triplicate along with one negative control group in water without any treatment and one positive control group treated with equal concentration of DMSO. Larvae which did not respond to any mechanical stimulus were considered as dead, while those which did not show any kind of swimming movement were considered moribund. The moribund larvae which were unable to revive for next 24 h were considered as dead (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). The mortality in the control groups if occurred between 5-10% then, the mortalities of treated group was corrected by using Abbot<sup>'</sup>s correction formula as follows<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg" alttext="Equation 1."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mortality&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Where<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><p id="p0125">A = percentage survival in control group</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><p id="p0130">B = percentage survival in treated group</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><label>4.5</label><title>Adulticidal assay</title><p id="p0135">Impregnated filter paper method was followed by <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Ramar et&#x000a0;al. (2013)</xref> to study the adulticidal activity of the selected essential oils against the target species. Initially two concentrations (10 &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> and 1 &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>) of each selected essential oil were prepared in 2 ml of acetone and applied on Whatman no.1 filter papers (size 12 &#x000d7; 15 cm<sup>2</sup>). 10 numbers of 4&#x02013;5 days old non blood fed adult female mosquitoes were selected for each replication. Three replications were set for each concentration. Based on the results of pilot study of the essential oil, a wide range of concentrations (0.01&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup>) of essential oils was prepared. For positive control, filter papers were treated with 2 ml of acetone alone and placed in exposure tubes (depth 10 cm). After the evaporation time of acetone (5 min), ten numbers of 3&#x02013;4 days old sugar-fed female mosquitoes were released into the tubes. One control group with acetone was placed for each of the oils tested. Adults were considered dead if they did not move when disturbed repeatedly with a soft brush. The LC50 and LC10 concentrations were calculated after 24 h of exposure by probit analysis and finally expressed in microgram/cm<sup>2</sup>. If the recorded mortality percentage was found to exceed 20% in the control batch, the experiment was repeated. However, if mortality in the controls was found more than 5%, the recorded data were corrected using Abbott's correction formula<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg" alttext="Equation 2."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mortality&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Where<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0020"><p id="p0140">A = the percentage mortality in the treated group</p></list-item><list-item id="u0025"><p id="p0145">B = the percentage mortality in the control.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0150">No mortality was recorded at the control groups of larvae and adults.</p><p id="p0155">Bioassays were performed maintaining a constant temperature (25&#x02013;29 &#x000b0;C) relative humidity (80&#x02013;90%) and photoperiod (12 h L: 12 h D).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><label>4.6</label><title>Preparation of binary combinations</title><p id="p0160">Considering the LC50 (Or LD50) concentration/dose of each of the selected plant oils (below 100 ppm for larvae; below 6 &#x003bc;g/cm<sup>2</sup> for adults) effective oils were short listed and they were further studied to explore the joint toxicity in mixtures at different volume ratios. Initially, the pilot study was performed taking 1:1 volume of LC50/LD50 concentration/dose of each of the candidate oil (Table&#x000a0;S5) following the same method described above. However, each of the prepared binary mixtures comprising of LC50 concentration (Or LD50) of each candidate oil is found to cause cent percent mortality among the treated mosquitoes and hence the concentration was reduced to LC10 or LD10 and the rest of the combinations of oils were prepared based on LC10 concentration against the larval stage and LD10 dose against the adult stage of <italic>C.&#x000a0;quinquefasciatus</italic> to find out the best effective combinations.</p><p id="p0165">Mixtures of different volume ratios like 1:1, 1:2, 2:1, 1:3, and 3:1 of LC10 concentrations against larvae and LD10 dose against adults were prepared and applied against the respective developmental stages. DMSO was used as positive control in larvicidal activity and acetone was used as positive control in adulticidal activity of the prepared mixtures. In each bioassay, three replications were set for each combination and three replications for each of the ingredients present in the respective combination. The method of application and condition were kept similar to the methods used for bioassay of essential oil described above.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.7"><label>4.7</label><title>Toxicity of the binary mixtures</title><p id="p0170">The activity of the binary mixtures of essential oils was observed by following the method described by <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Pavela (2015)</xref> with little modifications. Three replications with each replication comprising 20 larvae and adults were tested. Actual mortalities were compared to expected mortalities after 24 h of exposure based on the formula:<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label>E = O<sub>a</sub>+(1-O<sub>a</sub>) O<sub>b</sub></disp-formula></p><p id="p0175">E was the expected mortality and O<sub>a</sub> and O<sub>b</sub> were the observed mortalities of individual treatment at the given concentration or dose. The effects of mixtures were designated as either antagonistic or synergistic by analysis using <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> comparisons. If the chi-square value was greater than the table value at definite degrees of freedom and at the same time, the observed mortality was higher than the expected mortality, then the combination was considered to possess synergism. Again, if the observed mortality was lower than the expected mortality, the mixture was considered to possess antagonistic effect. The combination with chi-square value lower than the table value at definite degrees of freedom, it signified neither synergistic nor antagonistic effect.<disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label>&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = (O<sub>m</sub>-E)<sup>2</sup>/E</disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec4.8"><label>4.8</label><title>GC-MS analysis</title><p id="p0180">GC-MS analysis was carried out to identify the constituents of the most effective essential oil mixtures. Sample of the essential oils was analysed using Gas Chromatography- Mass Spectrometry. GC analysis was carried out on an Agilent GC 7890 A and Mass spectrophotometry in Accu TOF GCv from Jeol instrument. Gas chromatograph equipped with an FID detector and a capillary column (HP5-MS). The carrier gas was helium at a flow rate of 1 ml/min. The splitting program was set as 1:10; 80-1M-5-200-3M-8-275-3M-5-280-E.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.9"><label>4.9</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0185">LC50/LD50 and LC10/LD10 concentrations/doses were calculated from the recorded data of average mortality of larvae and adults by probit analysis using SPSS software 21 (Statistical Package of Social Sciences) and Minitab software. 95% confidence limits of upper confidence limit and lower confidence limit, and chi-square values were also recorded. Standard error was calculated using MS- EXCEL.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0190">Sudarshana Mahanta: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0195">Bulbuli Khanikor: Conceived and designed the experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0200">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs1">University Grants Commission</funding-source> [grant numbers Z/BSR/2015-16/71].</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec5.3"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="p0205">The authors do not have permission to share data.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec5.4"><title>Declaration of interests statement</title><p id="p0210">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.5"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0215">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arivoli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tennyson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal and adult emergence inhibition activity of <italic>Abutilon indicum</italic> (Linn.) (Malvaceae) leaf extracts against vector mosquitoes (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Biopestic.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canale</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cianfaglione</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciaschetti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Senthil-Nathan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehlhorn</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute larvicidal toxicity of five essential oils (<italic>Pinus nigra, Hyssopus officinalis, Satureja montana, Aloysia citrodora</italic> and <italic>Pelargonium graveolens</italic>) against the filariasis vector <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>: synergistic and antagonistic effects</article-title><source>Parasitol. Int.</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Annarelli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrelli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappellacci</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kevin Cianfaglione</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Afshar</surname><given-names>F.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canalea</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergized mixtures of Apiaceae essential oils and related plant-borne compounds: larvicidal effectiveness on the filariasis vector <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> Say</article-title><source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><volume>96</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bossou</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangelinckx</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yedomonhan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boko</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimpe</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and insecticidal activity of plant essential oils from Benin against <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> (Giles)</article-title><source>Parasites Vectors</source><volume>6</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>337</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24298981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and insecticidal activity against <italic>Sitophillus zeamis</italic> of the essential oils derived from <italic>Artemisia giraldi</italic> and <italic>Artemiia subdigitata</italic></article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>1</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>7255</fpage><lpage>7265</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jingyu Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition, antimicrobial, antioxidant, and antiproliferative properties of grapefruit essential oil prepared by molecular distillation</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>25</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>217</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dosoky</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Setzer</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological activities and safety of <italic>citrus</italic> spp. essential oils</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><volume>19</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roff</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairbairn</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Evolutionary Ecology: Concepts and Case Studies</chapter-title><year>2011</year><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal efficacy of <italic>Ficus benghalensis</italic> L. plant leaf extracts against <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> Say, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> L. and <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> L. (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Eur. Rev. Med. Pharmacol. Sci.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20329569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal activity of <italic>cassia fistula</italic> flower against <italic>Culex tritaeniorhynchus</italic> giles, <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> skuse and <italic>Anopheles subpictus grassi</italic> (diptera: culicidae)</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Pure Appl Zool</source><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>121</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Satyal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hietu</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choung</surname><given-names>N.T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquito larvicidal activity of the essential oils of <italic>Erechtites</italic> species growing wild in Vietnam</article-title><source>Insects</source><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>47</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivoke</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogbonna</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekeh</surname><given-names>F.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezenwaji</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atama</surname><given-names>C.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ejere</surname><given-names>V.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of grapefruit (<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> MACF) (Rutaceae) peel oil against developmental stages of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) Asian</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Trop Med Public Health</source><volume>44</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>970</fpage><lpage>978</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warikoo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal, repellent and irritant potential of the seed0derived essential oil of <italic>Apium graveolens</italic> against dengue vector, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> L. (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Front. Public Health</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref93"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition, antifungal and antiautoxigenic activities of Ocimum sanctum L. essential oil and its safety assessment as plant based antimicrobial</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><volume>48</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19909781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borisy</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic drug combinations tend to improve therapeutically relevant selectivity</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>864</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of repellent and insecticidal constituents of essential oil of <italic>Artemisia rupestris</italic> L aerial parts against <italic>Liposcelis bostrichophila</italic> Badonnel</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>18</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>10733</fpage><lpage>10746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24005967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahanta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanikor</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentiality of essential oil from <italic>Citrus grandis</italic> (Sapindales: Rutaceae) against <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> say (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Entomol Zool Stud</source><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>809</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahanta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanikor</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Allium sativum</italic> (Liliales: asparagales) essential oil - based combinations &#x02013; a potential larvicide for <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>int. J.Trop. Inst. Sci.</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muturi</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilkowski</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flor-Weiler</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rooney</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ovicidal and larvicidal effects of garlic and asafoetida essential oils against west nile virus vectors</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Insect Sci.</source><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>43</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tandon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-activity relationships of monoterpenes and acetyl derivatives against <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) larvae</article-title><source>Pest Manag. Sci.</source><volume>69</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1235</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23908002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paoli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocca Serra</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bighelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of the leaf essential oil of grapefruits (<italic>Citrus paradisi</italic> Macf.) in relation with the genetic origin</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Essent. Oil Res.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>271</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sublethal effects of some essential oils on the cotton leafworm Spodoptera littoralis (Boisduval)</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Essen. Oil Bear. Plant.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>156</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute toxicity and synergistic and antagonistic effects of the aromatic compounds of some essential oils against <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> Say larvae</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res.</source><volume>114</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>3835</fpage><lpage>3853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26149532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedlak</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-application temperature as a factor influencing the insecticidal activity of essential oil from Thymus vulgaris</article-title><source>Ind. Crop. Prod.</source><volume>113</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrelli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappellacci</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buccioni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmieri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canale</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outstanding insecticidal activity and sublethal effects of <italic>Carlina acaulis</italic> root essential oil on the housefly, <italic>Musca domestica,</italic> with insights on its toxicity on human cells</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perumalsamy</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>Y.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced toxicity of binary mixtures of larvicidal constituents from <italic>Asarum heterotropoides</italic> root to <italic>Culex pipiens pallens</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Med. Entomol.</source><volume>49</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22308778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahuman</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gopalakrishnan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatesan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geetha</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagavan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mosquito larvicidal activity of isolated compounds from the rhizome of <italic>Zingiber officinale</italic></article-title><source>Phytother Res.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18618523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajan</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varghese</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation on the larvicidal efficacies of aqueous leaf extracts of <italic>Lantana camara</italic> and <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> against mosquito larvae</article-title><source>Int. J. Mosq. Res.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignacimuthu</surname></name><name><surname>Paulraj</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological activity of nine plant essential oils on the filarial vector mosquito, <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> Say (insect: Diptera:Culicidae)</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahanta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanikor</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combinations of plant essential oil based terpene compounds as larvicidal and adulticidal agent against <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>9471</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31263222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref84"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suwannayod</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukontason</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitasawat</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Junkum</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Limsopatham</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic toxicity of plant essential oils combined with pyrethroid insecticides against blow flies and the house fly</article-title><source>Insects</source><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>178</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref86"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabari</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Youssefi</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esfandiari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity of Beta-citrinellol, geraniol and linalool from Pelargonium roseum essential oil against the West Nile and Filariasis vector <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Res. Vet. Sci.</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref87"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tak</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isman</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Penetration-enhancement underlies synergy of plant essential oil terpenoids as insecticides in the cabbage looper, <italic>Trichoplusia ni</italic></article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>72017</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>42432</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref91"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Youssefi</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esfandiari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazemi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moghadamnia</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sut</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of two monoterpenoids, carvacrol and thymol, and their combinations against eggs and larvae of the west nile vector <italic>Culex pipiens</italic></article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>24</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1867</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0235">The following is the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0230">The authors are thankful to the Head, Department of Zoology, Gauhati University; Head, Department of Botany, Gauhati University; Dr. D. R. Bhattacharyya, Scientist RMRC, Dibrugarh; University Grants Commission, New Delhi; SAIF, IIT, Bombay for their valuable help.</p></ack></back></article>