<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plants belonging to the genus 
 <italic>Origanum</italic> (Lamiaceae family) have been known as culinary and medicinal plants. Some species, including 
 <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> L., are rich in essential oils. 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> L. is an aromatic and perennial subshrub and is widely distributed throughout the world. This species is considered extremely variable, both in its morphological characteristics and its chemical composition. The adaptation of 
 <italic>O. vulgare</italic> L. to different edaphological and geographic conditions has given it unique characteristics of biosynthesis of different secondary metabolites depending on the growing environment. Research on new properties of oregano has shown many therapeutic properties: anticancer [
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], antimicrobial [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], antiproliferative [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], antimutagenic [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], hepatoprotective effect [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], antidiabetic activity [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], among others (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02100-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Much of the literature on chemical research on O. vulgare considers its essential oils, and the information on its phenolic compounds is very poor. However, phenolic compounds such as flavonoids and phenolic acids constitute one of the most important pharmacologically active substances that can act as antioxidant, antimicrobial, and anti-inflammatory tools in cells [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and inhibiting low-density lipoproteins’ oxidation [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-26-02100" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The adaptation of O. vulgare to different edaphological and geographic conditions has given it unique characteristics of biosynthesis of different secondary metabolites depending on the growing environment.
</p>
