<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">mNPs can interact with cells involved in innate and adaptive immune response in several organs, altering cytokine production, activation of cell surface receptors and/or cell maturation (including the ability of cells to present antigens)[
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>-
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. Nanoparticles can be recognized as foreign materials and eliminated by the immune system, but they can also trigger an excessive activation of immune responses. This could be useful should NP be used as an adjuvant in vaccinations, but could be detrimental in case of autoimmune disorders. In particular, the binding of gliadin peptides to food NP could represent a way by which these specific antigens can be taken up in great quantity by antigen presenting cells, thus increasing the activation of the autoimmunity process. Several studies have been performed on macrophage-like cell lines to assess the effect of metallic NPs, analyzing the cytotoxicity as well as differences in cytokines production; AgNPs were able to increase the production of IL-8[
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>], which also depended on NP size[
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>] whereas TiO2 NPs increased the secretion of TNF-α and IL-6[
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. Interestingly, Au-NPs induced an alteration in phagocytosis without variation in cytotoxicity or cytokine gene expression[
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>], whereas a similar effect by TiO2 NPs was associated with an inflammatory response[
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">82</xref>]. Transcription profiling on a macrophage cell line treated with different NPs revealed a particular expression pattern, thus suggesting that each metallic NP can trigger a specific response, also depending on the chemical characteristics of the nanoparticle itself[
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>]. Silver NPs have been demonstrated to be able to interact with human monocytes, increasing the production and release of IL-1β, even after the exposure to very low concentrations[
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]. Ag-NP were also able to cause superoxide production, as well as the formation of inflammasome. Metallic NPs also altered the expression of adhesion molecules and chemokine receptor type 4 on the surface of human peripheral lymphocytes[
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]; interestingly, these effects were independent from any sign of cytotoxicity, suggesting that the response to NP exposure can be more subtle and mainly related to gene expression variations. However, NPs can also interact with cells involved in adaptive immune response, and 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> data showed that TiO2 NPs can induce maturation of dendritic cells through the activation of Nf-kB pathway[
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>], a process which is essential for antigen presentation to T helper cells. Again, this process could be important in CeD, since antigen presentation by dendritic cells represents an essential step for the activation of the autoimmune response.
</p>
