<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the most interesting aspects of pomegranate color from academic and practical point of view is the influence of environmental conditions on color accumulation. It is well-known that pomegranate fruit color, like that of other anthocyanin-accumulating plants, such as grapes, red orange, and roses, is sensitive to high temperatures (Lo Piero et al., 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; Ubi et al., 
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Mori et al., 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Ferrara et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). When fruits of evergreen pomegranates that can produce all year round were tested in the Arava desert in Israel during winter and summer, it was found that the content of anthocyanin in the aril juice was inversely related to the sum of heat units accumulated during fruit ripening (Borochov-Neori et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Moreover, it was found that in addition to their effects on the content of anthocyanins, the change of season influenced the level and composition of the anthocyanin derivatives in the juice. Thus, cyanidine molecules accumulated in the hotter season and delphinidin derivatives accumulated in the cooler season (Borochov-Neori et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). It was also noticed that di-glycosidic derivatives mostly accumulated in the hot season, while mono-glycosidic derivatives were mostly accumulated during the cooler season, suggesting that di-glycosidic conjugates of anthocyanins are more stable in higher temperatures (Borochov-Neori et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). The effect of temperature on anthocyanin accumulation was also demonstrated when the content of anthocyanin in 11 different cultivars grown in the Arava desert in Israel was compared to the content of anthocyanin of the same cultivars grown accumulation in aril juice and peel was suggested (Schwartz et al., 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>).
</p>
