<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">SS and SPS play important roles as developmental regulators of C metabolic processes in plants. SS and SPS are important enzymes in C metabolism capacity, and their activity determines primary metabolite enrichment. Salt stress affected the activities of SS and SPS in 
 <italic>Lupinus albus</italic> L.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. In the present study, increases in SS and SPS activity were observed in Si under salt-stressed 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>, with a resulting increase in sucrose content, indicating that Si can buffer fluctuations in carbohydrate contents in response to osmotic stress caused by salt stress. These results indicated that Si further mitigates salt stress by inducing SS and SPS activities in salt-stressed 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>; correspondingly, these enzymes can affect carbohydrate levels. N assimilation is also an important physiological metabolic process, and plants do not absorb inorganic N from soil but change it into organic N through a series of physiological and biochemical reactions, allowing it to be absorbed and utilized by plants. Salt stress not only alters the N absorption of plants but affects the activities of key enzymes in the N assimilation pathway, which causes an imbalance in N metabolism
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies showed that NR activity was reduced in salt-stressed Ethiopian mustard
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. In the present study, salt stress significantly reduced NR activity in 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>, while Si application remarkably enhanced NR activity in salt-stressed 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>. These results indicate that Si can mitigate salinity-induced effects, resulting in an increase in NR activity. GS is vital in plants and is also the major enzyme for ammonium assimilation, and the final form of endogenous inorganic N is ammonium
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. Our results showed that salt stress decreased GS activities in 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>, which is similar to the results in cashews
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. These results indicated that GS activity is strongly limited in plants exposed to saline conditions. However, Si application significantly increased GS activity in salt-stressed 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>, indicating that Si could improve the activities of enzymes to help maintain the N metabolism balance in salt-stressed 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>. Thus, adding Si at an optimal concentration in favor of C and N metabolism can be carried out normally under salt stress and establish a foundation to obtain excellent characteristics of 
 <italic>G. uralensis</italic>.
</p>
