<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Processing of flaxseed has popularly been for their omega-3 fatty acids and lignans content, nevertheless, they also contain a rich amount of carbohydrate, minerals, and protein in abundance. However, the presence of antinutritional factors limits the bioavailability and bioaccessibility of the nutritional value derived therein. Flaxseeds contain antinutrients viz., linatine, protease inhibitors, phytic acids and cyanogenic glycosides (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-23-02444-f005" class="xref">Figure 5</xref>). These compounds affect the bioavailability and bioaccessibility of essential nutrients, as well as triggers life-threatening effects. For instance, the impact of linatine as an antinutritional factor in flaxseeds, causing symptoms of vitamins B
 <sub class="sub">6</sub> deficiency, was observed in fed chicks as early as 1946 [
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-23-02444" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. Nevertheless, the observed negative impact is yet to be observed in humans. Phytic acids act as antinutritional factors in flaxseeds by chelating minerals such as copper, zinc, magnesium, iron, selenium and calcium present, thereby inhibiting their release. Cyanogenic glycosides are nitrogen-containing secondary metabolites which when ingested can be hydrolysed to produce hydrogen cyanide, a highly toxic chemical [
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-23-02444" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. Chronic exposure to hydrogen cyanide toxins leads to defects in the neurological, respiratory, and cardiovascular system as well as the thyroid gland [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-23-02444" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>]. There are four types of cyanogenic glycosides found in flaxseeds, namely; linustatin, neolinustatin, lotaustralin and linamarin [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-23-02444" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-23-02444" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>]. Owing to their toxicity, cyanogenic glycosides are critical antinutritional factors that need to be removed from flaxseeds to enhance their health benefits. 
</p>
