<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By comparing the transcriptome profiles of leaves of linalool and leaves with low oil contents, 3,689 unigenes were identified as DEGs. Among them, expression levels of 
 <italic>AACT-like</italic> and 
 <italic>DXS-like</italic>, catalyzing the first steps toward IPP and DMAPP in the MVA and MEP pathways, were up-regulated in the leaves of linalool type. 
 <italic>DXS</italic> genes are believed to be a significant control point in the MEP pathway (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Wolfertz et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Rohdich et al., 2006</xref>), and manipulation of gene expression levels of 
 <italic>DXS</italic> in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> altered the levels of tocopherols, carotenoids, chlorophylls, abscisic acid, and various other isoprenoids (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Estévez et al., 2001</xref>). However, the contribution of each pathway to the generation of the common precursors for varied terpenoid biosynthesis is still unknown, because crosstalk between the two pathways has been documented in many species including chamomile, 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, tobacco, and snapdragon (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Adam and Zapp, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bick and Lange, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Hemmerlin et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Laule et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Dudareva et al., 2005</xref>). In addition, the expression level of 
 <italic>GGPPS-like</italic> in the “terpenoid backbone biosynthesis” pathway was up-regulated in the comparison, indicating increased supply of precursors for diterpenes biosynthesis. Although the percentage of diterpenes in leaf extracts of linalool-type camphor trees is not high, their oil yield is much higher than trees of low oil yield. Therefore, higher 
 <italic>GGPPS</italic> expression level may simply be correlated with a general increase in oil content. Interestingly, it has been documented that GPP, the precursor for monoterpene, is constitutively and ubiquitously expressed in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Van Schie et al., 2013</xref>), and our results also showed that the level of 
 <italic>GPPS</italic> was indifferent between the groups regardless of different accumulation of monoterpenes.
</p>
