<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Valerian (
  <span class="italic">Valeriana officinalis</span> L. s.l.) is an herbaceous perennial plant with a huge variability regarding habitus, composition of ingredients, and agro-economic traits. The leaves usually are imparipinnate, and the leaflets, weakly to strongly serrated. For blooming, a vernalization is necessary and hence, the first inflorescence usually develops in the second year of cultivation. Valerian occurs on sporadically wet habitats in the temperate zone of the northern hemisphere. This indicates that a secure water supply is necessary for cultivation. Usually, the rootstock forms a dense meshwork of thin roots [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For medicinal purposes, the entire root system including the rhizome is used [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. Preparations based on valerian roots are used against restlessness and sleep disturbances [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. In Germany, the dried root of valerian is a component of about 86 phytopharmaceutical and homeopathic preparations. In North America (USA, Canada, Mexico), due to other admission procedures, more than 1000 products with valerian root are obtainable. In Germany alone, the demand for dried roots amounts to app. 1000 tons, equal to a market size of app. 4 Mio.€ [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To counteract the losses of root mass and secondary compounds during harvesting, cleaning and the further production process of dried valerian roots, breeding was started in 2008 to develop new varieties of valerian with a coarser root-system (thicker adventitious roots) and with high contents of secondary compounds. A coarser root system would probably preserve the secondary compounds, essential oil and valerenic acid [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. According to the European Pharmacopoeia, the minimum content of essential oil must be 4 ml  kg
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and of valerenic acid at 0.17% (m/m) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. The most frequent major constituents of essential oil of 
  <span class="italic">Valeriana officinalis</span> L. s.l. are the monoterpenes borneol and its esters, bornyl acetate and bornyl isovalerate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the abundant analyses of pharmaceutical secondary compounds and their medicinal values, there are relatively few studies related to the physiology and localization within the root. Zacharias [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>] described essential oil to be located in ‘‘[…] the outer exodermis […]’’, whereas Tschirch and Oesterle [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>] found it in the ‘‘[…] single-row hypodermis […]’’. Both authors described one ‘oil droplet’ in a single exodermis cell. Localization of essential oil only in the outer cell layers of the valerian roots would support the two following observations made during the breeding of coarse valerian: (i) Considering 200 selected plants (elites), the essential oil content decreased with the increase of root thickness [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. This behavior is explainable, because with increasing root diameter, the root surface area decreases in relation to the root volume (calculated as cylinder). (ii) After careful hand-harvesting and hand-processing, high essential oil contents were achieved [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Due to careful handling, the surface was not damaged and the essential oil, close to the root surface, still present. The presence of essential oil close to the root surface was confirmed by Holzner-Lendbrandl [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>] und Fridvalszky [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>], who additionally recognized small round bodies named ‘oil sacs’ in the parenchyma of the roots. These ‘oil sacs’ were found predominantly in the outer parenchyma. Violon et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>] identified ‘oil droplets’ also in the inner parenchyma. All previous investigations remain vague about the oil droplet identification and distribution across the cross-section. In addition, they do not give information concerning oil droplets among different varieties, at different root diameters on the same plant, or at different positions along the roots.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The application of various vibrational spectroscopy methods for visualizing secondary metabolites in different plant tissue is already described for e.g. polyacetylenes and carotenoids in carrots, or essential oil components in fennel, chamomile and curcuma [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. The Fourier-transform infrared FITR imaging method allows one to study the occurrence and distribution of a wide range of molecules in cell tissues. However, it has not yet been applied for the essential oil in valerian. The fluorescence-microscopic method is suitable for the visualization and localization of secondary compounds in plant roots, and was used with sunflowers and mountain arnica [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Furthermore, a spectral-sensitive camera could make more oil droplet structures visible, or make chemical differentiation possible, respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our intention was to give a more detailed histochemical description within the valerian roots. The development of an appropriate method to visualize and clearly identify the essential oil droplets required several consecutive steps grouped into two fields: (k) Verification of oil droplets and (kk) generation of an essential oil distribution map. Verification of the oil droplets (k) was done by light-microscopic imaging and subsequent confirmation of the essential oil in the found oil droplets by Fourier-transform infrared (FTIR) imaging. Based on the results of these investigations, fluorescence-microscopic imaging for generating oil droplet maps (kk) could be applied.</p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on this, the study at hand was carried out to better understand the histochemical background of the two observations (i) and (ii). Observation (i) must be well interpreted to assess the achievability of the breeding target of a thick root-system with good essential oil content. Understanding the histological background of observation (ii) may explain why the entire essential oil is not all lost during a more robust, mechanized root harvesting and processing in large-scale valerian field production. We postulated that a great part of the essential oil droplets occur in the inner parts of the valerian root.</p>
</sec>
