<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample preparation and producing of thin root-slices</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From each cloned elite (CE) and root fraction (RF), two well-developed fresh roots with the typical root appearance were chosen and classified into three approximately 60 mm long parts, called horizons (HZ1 to HZ3, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). HZ1 represents the rhizome-near part, which would certainly be harvested after cultivation, and HZ3 represents the rhizome-far part, which probably remains in the ground. Along the whole length of the horizons, several thin-sections were taken and prepared.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The valerian root system components and visualization of the investigated horizons</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13007_2018_309_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cutting of thin root-slices was done by hand with a height adjustable cylinder-microtome. A segment of the respective root diameter fraction and horizon was clamped between a buffer-material, cut out from a carrot root parenchyma. This material has a comparable structure and consistency to the examined valerian roots. Thereby, the fresh valerian roots were well enclosed. With a moderate pressure, a constant velocity and without displacement, a straight metallic blade was moved through the valerian root tissue. The cut was performed in a constant angle of 20°. Through the moveable and height adjustable hanger, thin root-slices of a uniform thickness of 0.2 mm were able to be produced. These root-slices were then placed on top of a drop of water on a microscope slide. From each horizon, 15–20 thin-sections were cut, but just a low number of slices (seven on average) were suitable for the following image processing, analysis and evaluation.</p>
</sec>
