<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The colorless round bodies are filled with essential oil</div>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, FTIR imaging can provide information about the distribution of different plant constituents without destructing the plant constituent containing cell structure. These constituents include lipids, carbohydrates, and lignin, as well as secondary metabolites, e.g. terpenoids [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, the local accumulation of the strong absorbance at 1737 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> tentatively assignable to bornyl acetate indicates an essential oil distribution in distinct cellular structures. As bornyl acetate is a principal component of the essential oil of valerian, the results from FTIR imaging confirms the theory that essential oil is located within the colorless bodies. However, only very few intact oil droplets were found in the thin cryo-sections. The preparation of thin root slides of a thickness below 0.01 mm usually resulted in disruption of the oil bodies and smearing of the essential oil. Therefore, the results of FTIR imaging have to be seen as basic studies combining visual images of the sample with chemical information. The authors’ own previous studies on valerian root sections performed with FT-Raman spectroscopy did not deliver additional information about essential oil distribution. Only the differentiation of various root tissue mainly based on carbohydrate profile was obtained and with the instrument used, the local resolution was limited to around 150 µm (data not shown).
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modern Raman microscopes achieve a local resolution below 1 µm depending on the laser and aperture used. To gather suitable signal intensity, the Raman laser needs to be exactly focused, which demands for the extremely thin root slices. With application of the necessary laser power, the brownish root material often started burning and the spectra showed high fluorescence appearance. A reduction in laser power resulted in a lack of signals. Therefore, if the analytes don’t contain Raman active bonds (e.g. C–C double bonds in carotenoids) and the sample is colored (as the majority of plant derived material is), Raman spectroscopy investigations are technically challenging.</p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent years, another vibrational spectroscopy method gained attention in plant analysis. Hyperspectral (near infrared) spectroscopy imaging can be used for various analytical purposes as species identification, disease detection or nutrient quantification, but is focused on macroscopic samples due to the relatively coarse spatial resolution of several 100 µm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taking into account the above described characteristics of each method, FTIR imaging in combination with subsequent staining to affirm the preliminary results, seems to be the most favorable analytical strategy. The resulting FTIR distribution maps showing the strong C = O vibration at 1737 cm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> confirm the results of staining experiments and fluorescence-microscopy.
 </p>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the failed repeatability of the FTIR imaging of oil droplets, the more robust method of fluorescence-microscopy was chosen to visualize the oil droplets.</p>
</sec>
