<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">Our health and wealth are highly influenced by a number of viruses. Dengue is one of them having a global influence in absence of vaccines and antiviral. WHO suggested that the morbidity of dengue is increasing more than 6 times from 0.5 million in 2010 to over 3.34 million in 2016, following a sharp increase in 2019. The aim of the present study is to check the in vitro and in silico anti-dengue activity of 
  <italic>Cyamopsis tetragonoloba</italic> supercritical extract in cell lines. The optimum yield of supercritical extract was obtained 0.13 g/10 g (1.3% w/w) at 40 °C temp and 15 MPa pressure and further characterized by GC–MS. The antiviral assay was performed on C6/36 cell lines with 100 copies of dengue-2 virus and maximum non-toxic dose (31.25 µg/ml) of supercritical extract and their effect was detected by real-time RT-PCR. This study revealed that 
  <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic> supercritical extract inhibited the dengue-2 virus (99.9%). GC–MS analysis of 
  <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic> supercritical extract showed the presence of 10 compounds. The major compounds identified were Hexadecanoic acid, 15-methyl–methyl ester (24.498%); 9,12-octadecadienoyl chloride, (
  <italic>z</italic>,
  <italic>z</italic>)- (23.718%); methyl dodecanoic acid (13.228%); methyl-stearate (8.696%); Tridecanoic acid, 12-methyl-, methyl-ester (8.426%), dodecanoic acid (6.102%). The study reveals that 
  <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic> can be exploited to develop an effective, inexpensive, and specific anti-dengue. The molecular docking study demonstrated the binding energy of 1,2-benzenedicarboxylic acid, bis(2-methylpropyl) ester (− 4.1 kcal/mol), 9,12-octadecadienoyl chloride (
  <italic>z</italic>,
  <italic>z</italic>) (− 4.0 kcal/mol) ligands were higher than others. It is concluded that 
  <italic>C. tetragonoloba</italic> can play a major role to inhibit dengue-2 virus.
 </p>
</abstract>
