<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Through competitive exclusion, native species with superior fitness may limit the establishment and spread of non‐native species. However, competitive exclusion is not widely applied to control invasive plants (Byun &amp; Lee, 
 <xref rid="ece36938-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). We found that plant traits such as seed germination, seedling growth speed, biomass accumulation, branching, plant height, photosynthetic efficiency, and the direction and magnitude of phytochemical effects, all played a significant role in the competitive exclusion of 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> by 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic>. Evidently, 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic> can outperform 
 <italic>Mikania</italic>, modulated by priority effects and strong competition. Although 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic> is regarded as an invasive species elsewhere (Bentley &amp; Mauricio, 
 <xref rid="ece36938-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Kartzinel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36938-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), it is a valuable native plant in China. The starch‐rich roots of 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic> are valued as a food source and for medicinal purposes. Thus, planting 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic> is a promising approach to reduce the extent of 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> invasion in tropical and subtropical agroforestry systems that are suitable for 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic> cultivation, simultaneously providing weed management and economic benefits. Overall, this study provided promising strategies for species selection for restoration. Specifically, restoration will benefit from (a) the selection of highly competitive native species that have high niche overlap with invasive species, (b) the selection of native species that show strong priority effects (e.g., early emergence, rapid germination, and seedling growth), (c) selecting economically valuable native legumes that can improve restored soils through nitrogen fixation. Our study also provides a valuable framework that may be applied to other invaded ecosystems and species.
</p>
