<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several plant products have been investigated previously for direct treatment or as prophylaxis for infectious diseases (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Dietary supplements such as vitamins C, D and E are primarily antioxidants and are known to improve the immunity. The duration and severity of common cold has been shown to be reduced by a high dose of vitamin C and D supplements in patients (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). Vitamin C has been included in at least 20 clinical studies to evaluate its efficacy in treating COVID-19 patients (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Another ongoing trial is assessing the efficacy of vitamin A, B, C, D and E supplements on the improvement and mortality in COVID-19 patients (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Vitamin E supplementation was found to improve cellular and humoral immunity and provides protection against infections (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>); although, the degree of resistance is unclear. A clinical trial on elderly subjects revealed that long-term supplementation of vitamin E enhanced the resistance to mild respiratory viral infections, such as common cold (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). A large number of phytopharmaceuticals have been investigated for their beneficial effects in several diseases and many of them exerted significant immunomodulation properties. For example, resveratrol, an active constituent from grapevine, red wine, and peanuts, was found to show immunomodulation activity primarily through the inhibition of TNF-α or lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-mediated macrophages, NF-kB in phorbol 12-myristate acetate (PMA), dendritic cells, and myeloid (U-937) (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Epigallocatechin-3-gallate (EGCG), a polyphenol constituent from green tea, reportedly exhibited immunomodulation activity primarily by blocking NF-kB activation. It also down-regulated nitric oxide (NO) production in macrophages and the expression of monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), which is dependent on NF-kB inhibition (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). The squeezed sap of 
 <italic>Echinacea purpurea</italic> showed nonspecific immunomodulation for use against mild to moderate respiratory infections, such as the common cold (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Alkylamides are the principal active constituents, which act upon stimulation by the phagocytosis of macrophages and inhibition of inflammatory cytokine release such as TNF-α. It also increases circulating leukocytes, stimulates NK cells and possesses antiviral activity. Polysaccharide constituents were found to ameliorate the disease progress in mice infected with influenza (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) and were reported to improve the efficacy of influenza vaccine in immunosuppressed mice by activating the dendritic cells (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). Ginsenoside, the active component of ginseng, exhibited significant immunostimulant activity and was successfully used as an adjuvant with influenza vaccine (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). Many of these phytochemicals have shown moderate to good immunomodulating activities in different ways in various 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies. Although, the results have been encouraging and favoring the use of these natural products as immunomodulators, high level systematic clinical studies are still warranted to establish their safety and efficacy. The structures of few important plant bioactive constituents exhibiting immunomodulation activity along with their sources are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2</bold>
 </xref>.
</p>
