<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the ABTS assay, the method in reference [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-26-00403" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-26-00403" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] was adopted with some modifications. The stock solutions included 2.6 mM potassium persulfate solution and 7.4 mM ABTS solution. The working solution was prepared by mixing the two stock solutions in equal quantities and allowing them to react for 12 h at room temperature in the dark. Then, the solution was diluted by mixing 1 mL of ABTS solution with 42 mL of methanol to obtain an absorbance of 0.777 units at 734 nm. The ABTS solution was newly prepared for each experiment. The extracts of sunflower receptacles with different concentrations (The final concentration were 500, 250, 125, 62.5, 31.25, 15.63, 7.81, 3.91, 1.95, 0.97, 0.48, 0.24 ug/mL, 0.5 mL each) were allowed to react with 2 mL of the ABTS solution. After 6 min, the absorbance at 734 nm was recorded. The ABTS scavenging capacity of the extracts were compared with BHT (0.5 mL each), and percentage inhibition was calculated as the ABTS radical scavenging activity. All measurements were made in triplicate (
 <italic>n</italic> = 3). Using Equation (2): 
 <disp-formula id="FD2-molecules-26-00403">
  <label>(2)</label>
  <math id="mm2">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>ABTS</mi>
     <mtext> </mtext>
     <mi>radical</mi>
     <mtext> </mtext>
     <mi>scavenging</mi>
     <mtext> </mtext>
     <mi>activity</mi>
     <mtext> </mtext>
     <mrow>
      <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mfrac>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mrow>
         <mi>ABTS</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mi>control</mi>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <msub>
        <mrow>
         <mi>ABTS</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mi>sample</mi>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mrow>
         <mi>ABTS</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mi>control</mi>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where ABTS
 <sub>control</sub> represents the absorbance without sample. ABTS
 <sub>sample</sub> represents the absorbance with samples. BHT was used as the reference for comparison.
</p>
