<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition, microminerals such as iron, manganese, zinc and copper have been reported in different yam species, hence, contributing toward the RDA of these nutrients in the body of consumers. Iron is crucial for the formation of hemoglobin in red blood cells that bind and transport oxygen in the body. Bashiri et al. [
 <xref rid="B118-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>] reported the importance of iron in respiration and energy metabolism processes. It also plays a very important role in the immune system and has been implicated in the amalgamation of collagen and neurotransmitters. Otegbayo et al. [
 <xref rid="B99-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] reported a range between 1.1 and 3.9 mg per 100 g of iron content in different species of yam, with 
 <italic>D. dumetorum</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>D. alata</italic>&gt; 
 <italic>D. cayenensis</italic> &gt; 
 <italic>D. rotundata</italic>. Although the iron content of different species of yam has been reported to be low as compared to cereals (maize, rice and wheat), Mohan and Kalidass [
 <xref rid="B38-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] observed very high values of iron (103 mg/100 g) in 
 <italic>D. pentaphylla</italic>. Importantly, the range at which iron is found in a majority of the yam species meets the RDA (11–18 mg/day) of iron. Copper, zinc and manganese are components of numerous enzymes and have also been reported in different species of yam tubers, with values in wild yam being as high as 13.3 mg/100 g (
 <italic>D. pentaphylla</italic>), 7.1 mg/100 g (
 <italic>D. remotiflora</italic>) and 9.4 mg/100 g (
 <italic>D. bulbifera</italic>), respectively [
 <xref rid="B51-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-foods-09-01304" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. While yam contributes immensely to the nutritional requirement of consumers, the non-nutritional components and benefits will be discussed herein.
</p>
