<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medicinal plants enhance the glucose uptake by GLUT4 translocation and were proven by the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> glucose model. The L6 and 3T3-L1 cell lines are the best-characterized cellular model origin to study glucose uptake and GLUT4 translocation. The selection of cell line was based on the involved in the mechanism of action in the uptake of glucose where adipose tissue and skeletal muscle are now well established as a primary target site in glucose metabolism as well as regulation in whole-body glucose homeostasis and main targets for insulin-stimulated glucose uptake to control hyperglycaemia
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref>. Skeletal muscle cell acts as a major primary site that was responsible for postprandial glucose uptake. In the skeletal muscle, insulin increases glucose uptake by increasing functional glucose transport molecules in the plasma membrane
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref>. Furthermore, it is the most abundant tissue in the whole body and thus, the proper function of skeletal tissue is important to maintain normal blood glucose levels. In fact, L6 cells represent a good model for glucose uptake because they have been used extensively to elucidate the mechanisms of glucose uptake in muscle, have an intact insulin signalling pathway and express the insulin-sensitive GLUT4
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref>. Based on our findings showed that root extract displays a better activity with the increased stimulation of the 2- NBDG uptake in both of the cell lines as compared with fruit extract. We can observe that the 2- NBDG uptake increased as the dose concentration of the sample increase. This is in agreement with previous studies, which have addressed the increment of 2- NBDG uptake in 3T3-L1 and L6 cell lines along with the increase in the sample treatments
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref>. The presence of polyphenols including berberine, flavonoid glycoside (phlorizin), isoflavonoid (mundulone and scandenin) and cinnamic acid derivative (dimethyl caffeic acid) that containing in the extracts, contribute in promoting glucose absorption that can arise from their synergistic or complementary interactions with multiple targets in order to exercise their pharmacological behaviour. Firstly, berberine is shown to mediate its action by encouraging translocation of GLUT4 and increased activity of AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) in L6 myotubes and mediating anti-diabetic properties
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref>. Besides, cinnamic acid derivatives precisely activate proteins phosphoinositide 3-kinase (P13K) pathway and exert its anti-diabetic effect by substantially enhance the uptake of glucose
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref>. The finding from previous studies suggests that the introduction of a hydroxyl group on the benzene ring of cinnamic acid at the meta- and/or para-position increases the ability to stimulate glucose uptake in the cells
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref>.
</p>
