<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In September of 2017, we established two 20‐m transects within the Cedar Point National Wildlife Refuge, in Ohio USA (Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece36811-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="ece36811-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). The transects were established where large, dense native and non‐native 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> co‐occur and intermix. Exact age of each transect location is unknown, but based on historical aerial imagery, stands appear to be &gt;10 years old at the time of sampling. Each transect contained a high‐density zone of non‐native 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> dominance, a mixed zone containing both native and non‐native, and a high‐density zone of native 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> dominance. Each lineage's high‐density dominant zone was a near monoculture (i.e., included few other plant species at low abundance and did not include the opposite lineage); they will hereafter be referred to as monocultures. Samples were collected within 0.5 × 0.5 m plots at 2‐m intervals in the monoculture zones of both transects. In the mixed zones, samples were collected at 0.5‐m intervals in Transect 1 and 1.0 m intervals in Transect 2 (Transect 1 had 44 total sampling locations; 21 native, 23 non‐native; Transect 2 had 25 total sampling locations; 12 native, 13 non‐native. See Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece36811-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="ece36811-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> for more details). Within each plot, we assessed plant species composition by counting the stems of each 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> lineage, identifying other plant species, and estimating total percent plant cover. One 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> ramet of each lineage was collected within each plot (1 sample in monoculture; 2 in mixed plots). Paired bulk and rhizosphere soils were collected as described above; bulk soils were collected adjacent to the plot in a zone of low stem density to avoid root influence. In addition, the entire root ball with adhering soil particles (rhizoplane soils) from the selected ramet was also collected and returned to the lab on ice.
</p>
