<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our previous research proved that translational Brownian motion may be a promising method in micro-volume viscosity measurement [
 <xref rid="B30-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] and other applications [
 <xref rid="B31-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Considering that Brownian motion is simply driven by thermal effects, it is independent of external power. The diffusivity of translational Brownian motion is inversely proportional to the suspended bead diameter according to the Stokes–Einstein relation [
 <xref rid="B36-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. By contrast, the diffusional signal can be further improved when rotational Brownian motion is dominant. According to the Stokes–Einstein–Debye relation [
 <xref rid="B37-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>], the diffusivity of rotational Brownian motion is inversely proportional to the cubic bead diameter. Therefore, the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) can be further enhanced by rotational Brownian motion [
 <xref rid="B38-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Unlike microrheometry [
 <xref rid="B39-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] that can measure the viscoelasticity of materials, our diffusometer dealt with only viscosity due to simple targets (Newtonian fluids) investigated in the study. Nevertheless, the diffusometer can be extended to cope with viscosity and elasticity by performing frequency-related shear forces to liquids [
 <xref rid="B29-sensors-19-01217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. In the present study, Janus microbeads were fabricated by coating a thin layer of gold film on the surface of fluorescent polystyrene (PS) microbeads. After resuspending the Janus microbeads in a test medium, the cross-correlation algorithm was used to analyze consecutive changes in particle images over time. A characteristic correlation time was then derived from the exponential curve fitting of the time-elapsed correlation intensity. The correlation time increased with viscosity due to slow translational and rotational Brownian motion. A calibration curve was obtained by measuring glycerol–water mixtures with 1%–100% (
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">v</italic>) water content. As a proof of concept, five frequently used oil products, including lubricant oil, baby oil, food oil, olive oil, and motor oil, were investigated with the proposed diffusometer, and results were compared with those measured by a rotational viscometer. Good agreement in trend between our diffusometer and the commercial viscometer was obtained. Another test was conducted by heating food oil and olive oil at a high temperature for 10 min to intentionally downgrade their quality. The viscosities of both oils tended to increase after heat treatment, thereby implying degradation. Between the oils, olive oil showed a lesser characteristic correlation time shift, indicating better durability against heat processing. Finally, the rotational diffusometer with Janus microbeads achieved measurement from 0.8 cP to 574.8 cP with a volume of only 2 μL per run. The limit of detection was as low as 0.8 cP. The proposed rotational diffusometer provides a generally promising alternative to current devices for micro-volume viscosity measurement.
</p>
