<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>P. aculeata</italic> is invasive in Australia across an extraordinarily broad geographic range (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g001">Fig. 1</xref>), from upland to wetland habitats and from arid to tropical climates 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-vanKlinken2" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0032323-vanKlinken3" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. Its life-cycle consists of several life-stages (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g002">Fig. 2</xref>): seed bank (
 <italic>SB</italic>), seedlings (
 <italic>Sg</italic>), juveniles (
 <italic>Juv</italic>) and adults (
 <italic>Ad</italic>). Tree growth, the number of seeds produced, and seed germination (
 <italic>Germ</italic>) predominantly occurs in the warm to hot months of the year. Indehiscent pods (containing 1 to 9 seeds) fall directly under the parent tree and release most seeds by the end of summer. 
 <italic>SB</italic> was defined to include all live seeds present in both the soil and the litter layers. Seeds have hard-seeded dormancy from which they are released by wet, warm to hot conditions. Most are released from dormancy and either germinate or die within the first 1–2 years. Germination resulted in seedlings (&lt;20 cm tall) that become small juveniles (20–100 cm tall) by the first winter census. Seedling survival rates (
 <italic>S
  <sub>sg</sub>
 </italic>), i.e. the proportion of new seedlings that survived and established as juveniles by their first winter census, was included within the transition rate between 
 <italic>SB</italic> and 
 <italic>Juv</italic>. Small juveniles became large juveniles (100–150 cm tall) before becoming adults (&gt;150 cm tall). After establishment, juveniles take at least one year to mature. Adults grow continuously to over 7 m in height and 10 m in width, with total seed production increasing proportionally with canopy volume, but they rarely live longer than 30 years under natural conditions. Adults were stratified into seven sub-stages 
 <italic>i</italic> (defined by canopy volume 
 <italic>V</italic>: see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0032323-g003">Fig. 3</xref>) to provide better resolution of size-dependent fitness components such as annual growth rate (
 <italic>G
  <sub>Vi</sub>
 </italic>), survival rate (
 <italic>S
  <sub>Vi</sub>
 </italic>) and total number of seeds produced (the fecundity rate 
 <italic>f
  <sub>Vi</sub>
 </italic>).
</p>
