<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Litter influences micro-environmental conditions, effects nutrient cycling and can have effects on seedling germination and growth via mechanical and chemical effects [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Positive litter effects are due to higher soil humidity and a lower amplitude of diurnal temperature fluctuations beneath a low litter cover [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Still the size of litter effects on seedling germination and establishment do also depend on the amount of litter present. If litter layer gets thicker, it reduces the amount of light that reaches the seeds. However, seeds of ragwort depend on a certain light amount to germinate [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. On the other side germination of ragwort was facilitated under light sand cover compared to no cover [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In addition, thick litter layers that preserve a relative high humidity can facilitate the spread of mould that may cause decay of seeds [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. After germination seedlings can be hampered in their growth or even die if litter amounts are too high. Thus Van der Meijden and van der Waals-Koi found significantly fewer seedlings in pots with high vegetation cover [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Litter may also exert chemical effects by nutrient immobilization, depletion of oxygen in the soil or toxicity of carbon dioxide produced by decomposers or by releasing phytotoxins [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Through these mechanisms litter potentially influences community organization via delaying and reducing or facilitating seedling emergence or seedling growth [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
