<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hypothetically conspecific litter may facilitate the establishment of conspecific seeds compared to heterospecific litter that may inhibit the growth of other species through allelopathic effects [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Yet, as intraspecific competition can be more intense than interspecific competition [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], inhibiting effects of conspecifics may also be expected. While many studies have shown facilitating effects of adult plants on conspecific seedlings [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], particularly in weed species [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], there are also studies demonstrating the opposite [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In line with the latter, studies on ragwort showed the negative autotoxic potential of ragwort litter and soil near to ragwort plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Also, Bezemer et al. 2006 and Van de Voorde et al. 2011 found a negative intraspecific plant-soil-feedback for ragwort, which they assumed is probably driven by pathogens that accumulate in the soil community [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Under these circumstances, negative effects of ragwort litter and ragwort conditioned soil on ragwort performance (e.g. lower biomass) may either be additive or not. However, the influence of litter during seedling emergence might be stronger than during seedling growth, since at the latter stage impacts of competition are of higher importance than direct litter effects [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Thus, if litter reduces seedling density through self-thinning, surviving seedlings might have an advantage later on, as intraspecific competition would be reduced [
 <xref rid="pone.0246459.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
