<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, alcoholism has become a major social problem in public health. More than 80% of heavy drinkers have a fatty liver to a certain extent, of which 10%–35% can develop into alcoholic hepatitis (AH), and 10%–20% of them will develop liver cirrhosis (AC) [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The latest WHO statistics show that drinking to excess kills 2.5 million people a year, which is one of the common high-risk factors of four major types of noncommunicable diseases. Alcohol was associated with 6.2% of male deaths and 1.1% of female deaths [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. One-time heavy drinking can cause acute alcoholism. According to statistics, cardio-cerebrovascular disease, acute pancreatitis, and acute alcoholism are the three diseases with the highest incidence in holidays [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Acute alcoholism may cause central nervous system depression and metabolic abnormality, and severe patients may suffer from respiratory and circulatory failure and even death [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. On the one hand, how to avoid and prevent alcohol damage when drinking is a prominent research question, but currently there is no effective and safe drug to prevent AAI. On the other hand, first aid measures generally taken for severely poisoned patients include prohibition of alcohol, reducing central depression, promoting the excretion of alcohol in the digestive tract, and dissolving and removing alcohol metabolites. Current treatment methods mainly focus on blocking the inhibitory effect of excessive ethanol on the central nervous system and accelerating the metabolism of alcohol, but they have no direct effect on the pathogenesis of acute alcoholism. Based on the above two points, it is particularly important to find safe drugs to prevent and treat acute alcoholism. In China, the application of traditional Chinese medicine has a long history in the prevention and treatment of alcoholism and anti-inebriation [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In addition, natural drugs present wide pharmacological spectra on various targets and facilitate the recovery of physical conditions without toxic effects. The compound turmeric recipe used in this study comes from the hangover recipe of Professor Xiao-yu Hu. The prescription includes 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>, 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic>, 
 <italic>Pueraria lobata</italic>, 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic> flower, and 
 <italic>Hovenia dulcis</italic> Thunb. Regarding these Chinese medicines included in the prescription, Curcumin, the main active component of 
 <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>, has various pharmacological effects such as antitumor, lipid-lowering, and antimicrobial effects, especially in antioxidation, scavenging free radicals, anti-inflammation, and protecting the liver [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Curcumin can inhibit the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and scavenge oxygen free radicals produced in the process of oxidation [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]; Curcumin alone can also improve the antioxidant activity and reduce liver damage in acute alcoholism mice [
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Ginsenoside, the main active component of 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic>, has anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Ginseng extract reduces the concentration of alcohol in rat plasma [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and increases the blood alcohol clearance rate of humans [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. 
 <italic>Panax ginseng</italic> has a protective effect on acute alcoholism mice [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The extract of 
 <italic>Pueraria lobata</italic> can reduce the harm of ethanol and its metabolites by promoting lipid metabolism and increasing the activities of antioxidant enzymes in the liver [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], inhibit the increase of intestinal permeability induced by ethanol, and improve the intestinal barrier dysfunction caused by ethanol [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The extract of 
 <italic>Pueraria</italic> flower can increase the elimination rate constant of blood acetaldehyde and promote the elimination of acetaldehyde, but has no effect on blood ethanol concentration [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Intragastric administration of Puerarin or intraperitoneal injection of its metabolites can reduce the blood alcohol concentration and mortality of ethanol poisoned rats [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. 
 <italic>Hovenia dulcis</italic> Thunb. has a preventive effect on alcoholic liver injury caused by excessive drinking in mice [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The compound turmeric recipe combines the above Chinese herb medicines playing an active role in this study. RU-21 produced by American Psychiatrics Co., Ltd., is effective against drunkenness, and all its ingredients have been confirmed as safe by the US Food and Drug Administration. The mechanism of detoxification is as follows: its active ingredients can effectively reduce the oxidation of ethanol into acetaldehyde, accelerate the decomposition of acetaldehyde, and quickly and effectively reduce the content of acetaldehyde in the blood to detoxify. In this experiment, RU-21, a drug with sobering effect that is recognized to be safe and effective and to have nontoxic side effects, was selected as the positive drug to observe the sobering effect of Compound Turmeric Recipe.
</p>
