<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0200">In another research, the cytotoxicity activity of green silver nanoparticles synthesized product of 
 <italic>M. pinnata</italic> (L.) Panigrahi flower extract was evaluated of particular concentration using brine shrimp lethality assay where the LD
 <sub>50</sub> value was 36.41 μg/mL. This revealed the presence of toxic constituents in green silver nanoparticles synthesized product which links a mechanism towards an anticancer activity as the nanoparticles are a good substitute for a cancer drug. Anticancer activity is due to the presence of flavonoid which is chemopreventive in nature and plays an important role in the cell signalling (i.e. cell proliferation and angiogenesis phase). It is the fact that phytoconstituents from flavonoid group may show potent anticancer activity (
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Rajakumar et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <italic>Pongamia piñata</italic> (synonym of 
 <italic>M. pinnata</italic> (L.) Panigrahi) was reported earlier for its sub-acute toxicity of its isolated compound “Pongamol” using long Evan’s rats at a dose of 300 μg/kg/day for a period of 14 days. Different parameters like biochemical, haematological, body weight and histopathology were evaluated in both the control and experimental group. It was found that Pongamol is safe for clinical trial as it showed no significant changes in any parameters (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Baki et al., 2007</xref>). Again, the acute oral toxicity study of this same plant was also evaluated by using female Wistar rat. A dose of 2000 mg/kg/day of crude extract were administrated to the animals (100–120 gm, 4–8 week old) for 14 days. As a result, there were no toxicity signs and death found in any groups (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Aneela et al., 2011</xref>). Later, another isolated compound known as “Karanjin” was also isolated from the methanol extract of the same plant and evaluated for its toxicity. Male Wistar rats (180–200 gm) were administered at a dose of 20 mg/kg/day of Karanjin for a time period of 14 days. The result showed no major changes in the biochemical profile indicating no lethal effect (
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Vismaya et al., 2011</xref>). Different solvent extracts like ethanol, aqueous, chloroform, and petroleum ether of 
 <italic>Pongamia piñata</italic> (synonym of 
 <italic>M. pinnata</italic> (L.) Panigrahi) was evaluated for acute oral toxicity for a dose range of 50–5000 mg/kg/day for a period of 14 days. It was observed that there is no significant change in the toxicity parameters of all the extracts (
 <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Sikarwar and Patil, 2010</xref>).
</p>
