<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0195">Quantifying the phytochemicals such as total phenolic, flavonoid and tannin contents serve as the background information for some of the bioactivities. Previously many studies claimed that phenolic compounds are one of the responsive factors for antioxidant activity of medicinal plants [
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Flavonoids are also physiologically active constituents that have been traditionally utilized to treat different human diseases especially cardiovascular disease [
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Tannins are and attributed to antioxidant, antimicrobial, anti-mutagenic, and other health-promoting activities [
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Therefore, as evident from our study, the presence of a high quantity of phenol as well as flavonoid and tannin can be credited as contributing factors to the medicinal values of these flowers. Shabir et al. reported the total phenolic and total flavonoid content in 80% methanolic extract of 
 <italic>Delonix regia</italic> flower as 2.24 g/100 g dry extract and 0.81 g/100 g dry extract respectively [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. P. Siddhuraju et al. reported the total phenolic content of 90% methanolic extract of 
 <italic>Cassia fistula</italic> flower as 6.52 g/100 g extract [
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Irshad et al. reported total phenolic and flavonoid content of 
 <italic>Cassia fistula</italic> fruit pulp extract as 114.23 mg/g and 74.65 mg/g respectively. They also quantified the total phenolic and flavonoid content in seed extracts as 109 mg/g and 67.78 mg/g respectively [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. A study conducted by Kesavanarayanan et al. reported the total phenolic, flavonoid, and tannin content in methanolic extract of leaves of 
 <italic>Lagerstroemia speciosa</italic> as 300.11 μg/mg, 53.12 μg/mg and 118.90 μg/mg respectively [
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
</p>
