<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Baicalein has also been investigated for its inhibitory effects against glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) brain cancer by Kang et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The research group extracted crude compounds from 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> leaves using binary extraction system composed of a combination of petroleum ether and methanol solvents to generate crude extract with 15% of baicalein content. In order to further enhance the baicalein content in the crude extract, it was subjected to an enrichment fractionation chromatography composed of Diaion HP20 resin column and methanol solvent which successfully increased the baicalein content by nearly two-fold (from 15% to 29%). The baicalein enriched extract obtained after the fractionation chromatography not only contained higher baicalein concentration, it also possessed higher antioxidant activity as well as enhanced efficiency to inhibit GBM cancerous cell growth (IC
 <sub>50</sub> baicalein-enriched fraction = 36 μg/mL vs. IC
 <sub>50</sub> crude extract = 92 μg/mL). Therefore, it can be logically hypothesized that the major phytochemical of 
 <italic>O. indicum</italic> that confers the anti-GBM medicinal benefits is the baicalein. The fascinating effects of the baicalein active compound on GBM cell inhibitory could be due to its major capacities to inhibit nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-kB), a multifunctional transcriptional nuclear factor which involves extensively in cancer development and progression [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Attenuation of the NF-kB pathway has long been linked to inhibit various types of cancers such as ovarian cancer [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], gastric cancer [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and breast cancer [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Moreover, baicalein also has been proved to induce apoptosis by activating caspase-9/-3 and to inhibit tumor invasion and metastasis by reducing the expression of matrix metalloproteinase-2/-9 (MMP-2/-9) [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In addition, baicalein possesses a unique feature to cross blood-brain barrier (BBB), enabling its distribution over a wide range of brain area after oral administration [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-25-05677" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. This feature has significantly supported its therapeutic potential for brain and central nervous system (CNS) diseases, including the brain cancer.
</p>
