<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7461802</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01489</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diversity and Bioactivity of Endophytes From <italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> in China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xin-Guo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/864274/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Si-Jia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Wen-Na</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Guo-Xing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Guo-Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Xiao-Di</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Life Sciences and Engineering, Lanzhou University of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Lanzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Screening and Processing in New Tibetan Medicine of Gansu Province</institution>, <addr-line>Gansu</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Rajesh Jeewon, University of Mauritius, Mauritius</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Vijay Kumar Sharma, Kunming University of Science and Technology, China; Kathrin Blumenstein, University of G&#x000f6;ttingen, Germany</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xin-Guo Zhang, <email>biodrug@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>This article was submitted to Fungi and Their Interactions, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1489</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Zhang, Guo, Wang, Wei, Ma and Ma.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhang, Guo, Wang, Wei, Ma and Ma</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Plant seeds are not merely reproductive organs, they are also carriers of microorganism, particularly, inherent and non-invasive characteristic endophytes in host plant. Therefore, in this study, the endophytic diversity of <italic>Angelica</italic> seeds was studied and compared with endophytes isolated from healthy leaves, stems, roots, and seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> using 20 different media. The metabolites of endophytic strains were evaluated with six different methods for their antioxidant activity and the paper disc diffusion method for antimicrobial activities. As a result, 226 endophytes were isolated. Compared with the biodiversity and abundance of uncultured fungi from <italic>Angelica</italic> seed, the result showed that the most frequent endophytic fungi were <italic>Alternaria</italic> sp. as seen in artificial media; moreover, compared with artificial media, the pathogenic fungi, including <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp. and <italic>Pseudallescheria</italic> sp., were not found from the <italic>Angelica</italic> seed, the results suggested it may not be inherent endophytes in plants. In addition, bacteria from seven phyla were identified by high-throughput sequencing, while five phyla of endophytic bacteria were not isolated on artificial media including <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>, <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>, <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, <italic>Microgenomates</italic>, and <italic>Saccharibacteria</italic>. Furthermore, the sample JH-4 mycelium displayed the best antioxidant activity, and the active constituent may be a flavonoid as determined by total phenol and flavonoid content. Moreover, YH-12-1 mycelium had strong inhibitory activity against the five tested strains and the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) against <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> was found to be 25 &#x003bc;g/mL. Our results confirm that plant endophytes are rich in biodiversity and contain important resource of many uncultured microorganisms.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Angelica sinensis</italic></kwd><kwd>endophytes</kwd><kwd>diversity</kwd><kwd>secondary metabolite</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial activity</kwd><kwd>antioxidant activity</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="79"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Endophytes, including endophytic bacteria and endophytic fungi, are microorganisms that asymptomatically live in different healthy tissues of plants during the whole or part of their lifetime (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Promputtha et al., 2005</xref>). Compared with the external dynamic environment of plants, a relatively stable environment can be obtained for microbial population adapted to endogenous life from the interior of the plant (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Farrar et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Siqueira et al., 2016</xref>). There are about 300,000 terrestrial host plant species distributed in temperate regions and tropical rain forests, each of which has one or more endophytes, and the biodiversity of these naturally occurring endophytes is very great (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Doilom et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>). Accumulating evidence has demonstrated that endophytes are hyperdiverse and abundant (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Zimmerman and Vitousek, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Afzal et al., 2019</xref>). All plant species, such as angiosperms, non-vascular plants, conifers and ferns, are considered to be symbiotic with endophyte (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Rosenblueth and Martinez-Romero, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Venugopalan and Srivastava, 2015</xref>). Studies have shown that endophytes provide some advantages to their host, including protection against insects/pests and pathogens (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Rosenblueth and Martinez-Romero, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Siqueira et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Deshmukh et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2016</xref>), conferring their host plant with an ability to adapt to stresses such as tolerance to heat, metals, drought, disease, herbivory and salinity, and also promote growth via plant hormone biosynthesis and nutrient acquisition (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Rosenblueth and Martinez-Romero, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Venugopalan and Srivastava, 2015</xref>).</p><p>Although endophytes have been studied for a long time, they were found to be able to mimic the secondary metabolite repertoire of host plants only in the last two decades (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">Venugopalan and Srivastava, 2015</xref>). Endophytes can produce biologically active compounds, which are very important for increasing the adaptability of endophytes and their host plants, including tolerance to biotic and abiotic stresses (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Rai et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Golinska et al., 2015</xref>). More importantly, many compounds with unique structures and highly biologically active secondary metabolites were isolated from endophytes. An increasing number of novel compounds are being isolated from endophytic fungi and actinomycetes, including alkaloids, peptides, steroids, terpenoids, quinones, flavonoids, aliphatic compounds, and phenols (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Strobel and Daisy, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Golinska et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Deshmukh et al., 2018</xref>). These compounds have been proved to have the biological activities previously shown, including antimicrobial, antiviral, larvicidal, antimalarial, anti-tumor and antidiabetic (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Strobel and Daisy, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Golinska et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Matsumoto and Takahashi, 2017</xref>). Therefore, isolation of endophytes from medicinal plants may provide new opportunities to discover diverse species and natural products using for medicine, agriculture, and industry (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Aly et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Ding et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Golinska et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Jeewon et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Bibi et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p><italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> is a perennial herb of the Umbelliferae family and is widely planted in the western part of China. Radix <italic>Angelica sinensis</italic> (RAS) named as &#x0201c;<italic>Danggui</italic>&#x0201d; in China is one of the most important traditional Chinese medicine (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2014</xref>, <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). RAS is used to act on uterine smooth muscle for the treatment of irregular menstruation, to improve coronary circulation and atherosclerosis for the treatment of cardiovascular diseases (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2013</xref>). Phthalides compound, organic acids and their esters and polysaccharides have been shown to be major chemical constituents associated with RAS&#x02019;s high potency of pharmaceutical activity. In addition, the extracts of <italic>Angelica</italic> also have other pharmacological actions including radiation resistance, anti-inflammatory analgesia, anti-oxidation, anti-aging, and anti-psoriasis (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Armstrong and Peterson, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bandara et al., 2006</xref>). Therefore, RAS is accepted by the ministry of health of China for use in health food raw materials, such as a daily tonic; furthermore, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> can be described as an edible Chinese traditional herb with a medicinal function (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Tang, 2002</xref>).</p><p>As a traditional Chinese medicine material, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> is well documented for its various medicinal attributes and is clinically widely used. In view of the medicinal value of the host, in this study, we selected <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> as a source plant to examine the diversity of the endophytic community with 20 different media. We also studied the diversity of endophytes in the seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> using high-throughput sequencing. Finally, endophytes were isolated from healthy leaves, stems, roots and seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>, and the metabolites of endophytic strains were evaluated with six different methods for their antioxidant activity and the paper disc diffusion method for antimicrobial activities. Our research will aid in the search for new and effective biologically active ingredients from endophytes associated with this medicinal plant and pave the way for future approaches to examining medicinal plants for their endophytes and systematically studying product isolation and characterization of bioactive compounds.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2.SS1"><title>Plant Materials</title><p>Healthy <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> plants were collected from Min county, Gansu Province in September 2015. Seeds were obtained from Zhang county, Gansu Province, China in October 2015. All samples were placed in ice boxes and immediately sent to the laboratory for further research.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS2"><title>Chemicals and Reagents</title><p>The reference standard of rutin and gallic acid were purchased from Aladdin (purity &#x0003e; 98%, Shanghai, China). The 1,1 diphenyl 2-bitter hydrazine (purity <bold>&#x0003e;</bold> 97%) were purchased from Tokyo Chemical Industry. All other analytical chemicals were obtained from Kebaite Technology (Lanzhou, China).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS3"><title>Tested Strains</title><p>Two strains of gram-negative bacteria (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>) and three strains of gram-positive bacteria (<italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>) were used. These tested microbes were kindly provided by school of Basic Medical Sciences, Lanzhou University in China.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS4"><title>Separation and Purification of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> Endophytes</title><p>The seed, leaves, stems and roots of fresh <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> were rinsed thoroughly with running water for 10 min. They were soaked in 75% ethanol for 45 s. Then soaked in 2% NaClO for 4, 5, and 6 min, respectively, then the surface sterilizing agents were removed by rinsing 6 times with sterile distilled water. The last rinse was collected to evaluate the effect of sterilization (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2016</xref>, <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>). The surface sterilized plant samples were aseptically processed in an ice bath and plated on 20 different media shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. As described <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Grum-Grzhimaylo et al. (2016)</xref>, emerged fungal isolates were purified and pre-identified by morphological characters. To avoid redundancy, in few cases of joint isolations from different media, the co-isolated strains were discarded down to a minimum number of morphotypes (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Grum-Grzhimaylo et al., 2016</xref>). All endophyte strains were kept in store at 4 &#x000b0;C and selected for further study.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Twenty different media for endophyte isolation.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ingredient</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potato 200 g, Dextrose 20 g, 15 g agar 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 PDA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted media I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rose Bengal medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 g peptone, 10 g glucose, 1 g potassium dihydrogen phosphate, 0.5 g magnesium sulfate, 15 g agar, 0.03 g Rose Bengal, 0.1 g chloramphenicol, 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2 (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017a</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 Rose Bengal medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted media III</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czapek&#x02013;Dox Medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 g NaNO<sub>3</sub>, 0.1 g K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 0.5 g KCl, 0.5 g MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.01 g FeSO<sub>4</sub>, 30 g sucrose, 15 g agar and 1000 mL distilled water</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 Czapek&#x02013;Dox Medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted media V</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast extract medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 g yeast extract, 20 g sucrose, 15 g agar 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VIII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 Yeast extract medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted media VII</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yam medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yam 200 g, Dextrose 20 g, 15 g agar 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">X</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 Yam medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted media IX</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IX</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carrot medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carrot 200 g, Dextrose 20 g, 15 g agar 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 Carrot medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted media IX</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lily medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lily 200 g, Dextrose 20 g, 15 g agar 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 Lily medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted medium XIII</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweet potato medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweet potato 200 g, 20 g Dextrose, 15 g agar 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XVI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 Sweet potato medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted medium XV</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XVII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">beef extract peptone medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 g beef extract, 10 g peptone, 15 g agar, 5 g NaCl, 1000 mL distilled water, pH 7.2 (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017a</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XVIII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 beef extract peptone medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted medium XVII</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIX</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-vitamins medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4 g yeast extract, 4 g Dextrose, 3.75 mg multi-vitamins, 1 mL/L trace salt, 15 g agar, 1000 mL distilled water</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XX</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/100 multi-vitamins medium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 times diluted medium XIX</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multi-vitamins</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 mg vitamin B<sub>1</sub>, 1 mg vitamin B<sub>6</sub>, 1 mg vitamin B<sub>2</sub>, 1 mg Nicotinic acid, 1 mg Phenylalanine, 1 mg vitamin H, 0.3 mg Alanin</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trace salt</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 g MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>0, 0.1 g MnCl<sub>2</sub>&#x022c5;4H<sub>2</sub>0, 0.1 g ZnSO<sub>4</sub>&#x022c5;7H<sub>2</sub>0, 100 mL water</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S2.SS5"><title>Identification Based on Morphology and DNA Sequence Data</title><p>Morphological observation combined with molecular biology identification are widely used for taxonomic studies of strains (<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2016</xref>). The isolated fungi were grown on PDA medium and bacteria were grown on beef extract-peptone medium. Characterization of cell morphology included their mycelium color, pigment, morphology of spore producing structure, presence or absence of sporulation and spore morphology, and were described and surveyed using a microscope (Motic E220, China).</p><p>Ezup Column Genome DNA Extracting Kit (Sangon Biotech, Shanghai, China) was used to extract genomic DNA from high activity strains according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. The 16S rDNA from the extracted DNA was amplified by PCR using primer 27F (5&#x02032;-AGAGTTTGATCC TGGCTCAG-3&#x02032;) and primer 338R (5&#x02032;-TGCTGCCTCCCGTAGGAGT3&#x02032;) (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017a</xref>); Moreover, 18S rDNA from the extracted DNA was amplified by PCR using primer EF3 (5&#x02032;-TCC TCTAAATGACCAAGTTT-3&#x02032;) and primer EF4 (5&#x02032;-GGAAGGGRTGTATTTATTAG-3&#x02032;).</p><p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) were performed using our previously reported method (<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2017b</xref>). Reaction mixtures contained 5 &#x003bc;L 10 &#x000d7; PCR buffer, 4 &#x003bc;L 2.5 mmol/L dNTPs, 1 &#x003bc;L 5 &#x003bc;mol/L forward primer, 1 &#x003bc;L 5 &#x003bc;mol/L reverse primer, 0.5 &#x003bc;L Taq enzyme, 1 &#x003bc;L Template DNA and was add ddH<sub>2</sub>O to 50 &#x003bc;L. The thermal cycling conditions were: denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 3 min, followed by 32 cycles of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C for 30 s, annealing at 56&#x000b0;C for 30 s and an extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 50 s. At the end of the cycles, the reaction mixture was kept at 72&#x000b0;C for 7 min and then cooled to 4&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Gutell and Fox, 1988</xref>). The gel electrophoresis (1%) was used to detect PCR products and the result were analyzed by Sangon Biotech (Shanghai, China).</p><p>The 16S rDNA or 18S rRNA gene sequences were subjected to BLAST search against the GenBank database. The sequences determined and reference sequences downloaded from GenBank were aligned using multiple-sequence alignment software CLUSTAL X version 1.81. Phylogenetic trees were constructed with the molecular evolutionary genetics analysis software MEGA 5.0 program.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS6"><title>Diversity of Endosphere of Seeds in <italic>A. sinensis</italic></title><p>According to the instruction manual, E.Z.N.A.DNAKit (Omega Bio-tek, Norcross, GA, United States) was used to extract microbial DNA from the seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>, furthermore, determination of DNA concentration and purification were performed by using NanoDrop 2000 UV-vis spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Wilmington, United States), and the gel electrophoresis (1%) was used to evaluate the quality of extracted DNA (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2018</xref>). The 27F_338R hypervariable (V1-V2) regions of the bacteria 16S rRNA gene were amplified with primers 27F (5&#x02032;-AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG-3&#x02032;) and 338R (5&#x02032;-TGCTGCCTCCCGTAGGAGT-3&#x02032;) (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Ravel et al., 2011</xref>) by PCR using a GeneAmp 9700 PCR system (ABI, United States). The TS1F_ITS2R hypervariable regions of the fungi 18S rRNA gene were amplified with primers ITS1F (5&#x02032;-CTTGGTCATTTAGAGGAAGTAA-3&#x02032;) and ITS2R (5&#x02032;-GCTGCGTTCTTCATCGATGC &#x02212;3&#x02032;) by PCR. PCR reactions were performed using previous method (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>) as follows: denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 3 min, followed by 27 cycles of denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 30 s, annealing at 56&#x000b0;C for 30 s and extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 45 s, and a final elongation at 72&#x000b0;C for 10 min (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). 2% agarose gel was used to extract the resultant PCR products, and further AxyPrep DNA Gel Extraction Kit (Axygen Biosciences, Union City, CA, United States) was used to purify and QuantiFluor-ST (Promega, United States) was used to quantify according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2018</xref>). According to Majorbio Bio-Pharm Technology Co., Ltd. Standard protocol (Shanghai, China), Sequencing and analysis of the purified amplicons was performed on an Illumina MiSeq platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA, United States).</p><p>The Illumina reads of raw fastq files were demultiplexed and quality-filtered using Trimmomatic v0.36 (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Bolger et al., 2014</xref>). Overlapping paired-end reads were merged using FLASH (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Magoc and Salzberg, 2011</xref>) according to specific criteria as reported by <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2018)</xref>. Chimeric sequences were identified and removed using UCHIME (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Edgar et al., 2011</xref>). Sequences with 97% sequence similarity were clustered into Operational Taxonomic Units (OTUs) using UPARSE (version 7.1; <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Edgar, 2013</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="footnote1">1</xref></sup>. The taxonomy assignment of each OTU sequence was analyzed using the RDP Classifier algorithm<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="footnote2">2</xref></sup> against the Silva 16S rRNA database and Unite ITS fungi with a confidence threshold of 70% (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Hao et al., 2017</xref>). The reference database used was Silva (Release 126)<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="footnote3">3</xref></sup>. Rarefaction curves and alpha diversity containing the Chao1 index, ACE index, Shannon estimator and Simpson estimator were determined as described previously (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS7"><title>Preparation of Endophytic Metabolite Extraction</title><p>Each fungal strain was inoculated into 200 mL potato dextrose broth (PDB) medium at 200 rpm on a rotary shaker at 28&#x000b0;C for 7&#x02013;10 days. The fungal broth was filtered using Whatman No. 5 filter paper, and then the protein in filtrate was removed by the sevage method (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Kusaikin et al., 2010</xref>). The mycelia was dried and then extracted twice with 95% ethyl alcohol (1:2/V:V) by circumfluence extraction (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2015</xref>). The bacteria was inoculated in beef extract-peptone medium at 200 rpm on a rotary shaker at 37&#x000b0;C for 48&#x02013;72 h. All the extracting solution was concentrated in a rotary evaporator at 60&#x000b0;C and further was removed by evaporation under 40&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS8"><title>Antioxidant Activity Assay</title><sec id="S2.SS8.SSS1"><title>DPPH Radical Scavenging Activity Assay</title><p>The DPPH radical scavenging activity of endophytic metabolite extracts was measured according to the method of <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Du et al. (2013)</xref>. 2.0 mL of different concentrations of the test sample (0.02, 0.04, 0.06, 0.08, and 0.1 mg/mL) which was added to a tube containing 2 mL of DPPH solution (0.05 mg/mL in ethanol). The reaction mixture was shaken well and incubated in the dark for 30 min at room temperature. Then, absorbance was measured at 517 nm. In this study, distilled water (negative) and ascorbic acid (positive controls) were used and the absorbance at 517 nm was measured. The following formula is used to calculate DPPH free radical scavenging activity (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2013</xref>):</p><p>Scavenging rate (%) = (1&#x02013;A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub><sub>/</sub>A<sub>0</sub>) &#x000d7; 100%</p><p>Where A<sub>0</sub> is the absorbance value of the control, A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub> is the absorbance value of the samples and ascorbic acid. IC<sub>50</sub> is the amount of antioxidant necessary to decrease by 50% the initial DPPH concentration.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS8.SSS2"><title>Hydroxyl Radical Scavenging Activity Assay</title><p>The hydroxyl radical scavenging activity of the endophytic metabolite extracts was measured following a method by <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">Smirnoff and Cumbes (1989)</xref>. 2.0 mL of different concentrations of the tested sample (0.02, 0.04, 0.06, 0.08, and 0.1 mg/mL) was added into a tube containing 1.0 mL FeSO<sub>4</sub> (6.0 mmol/L), salicylic acid-ethanol (6.0 mmol/L) and 0.1% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> reaction mixture, and cultured in a 37&#x000b0;C constant temperature water bath for 30 min. The absorbance of the reaction mixture was read at 510 nm. The hydroxyl radical-scavenging rate was calculated using the following formula:</p><p>Hydroxyl radical-scavenging rate (%) = [1 &#x02013; (A<sub>1</sub>&#x02212; A<sub>2</sub>)/A<sub>0</sub>] &#x000d7; 100% (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2013</xref>)</p><p>In the above formula, A<sub>0</sub> represents OD<sub>510</sub> of the blank control, A<sub>1</sub> represents OD<sub>510</sub> of the sample and positive (ascorbic acid), and A<sub>2</sub> represents OD<sub>510</sub> of the sample and the positive control with distilled water containing 2 mL instead of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> aqueous (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS8.SSS3"><title>Ferric Cyanide Reducing Power Assay</title><p>Ferric cyanide reducing power (FRAP) of the endophytic metabolite extracts was determined by the method of <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2012)</xref>. Reaction mixtures were prepared by adding 2.5 mL of phosphate buffer (0.2 M, pH 6.6), 2.5 mL potassium ferricyanide (1%) and 2.5 mL varying concentrations (0.02, 0.04, 0.06, 0.08, and 0.1 mg/mL) of tested samples and incubating reaction mixtures at 50&#x000b0;C for 30 min, allowing to cool at room temperature (28&#x000b0;C), and adding 2.5 mL of 10% TCA (Trichloroacetic acid) to each reaction mixture, followed by centrifugation at 5000 rpm for 5 min. Five milliliter of the supernatant was added to 4 mL of distilled water and 1 mL of 1.0% FeCl<sub>3</sub> in a test tube, and the absorbance was measured at 700 nm after reacting at room temperature for 10 min. Ascorbic acid solution was used as a standard.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS8.SSS4"><title>Total Antioxidant Capacity Assay</title><p>The total antioxidant capacity of the endophytic metabolite extracts was determined using the phosphomolybdate method as described by <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Naima et al. (2012)</xref>. 0.5 mL of different concentrations (0.02, 0.04, 0.06, 0.08, and 0.1 mg/mL) of tested sample and 5.0 mL of reagent solution (0.6 M sulfuric acid, 28 mM sodium phosphate, 4 mM ammonium molybdate) were mixed in a tube and placed at 95&#x000b0;C for 90 min. After the mixture cooled to room temperature, the absorbance of 765 nm was noted as A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>. 5.0 mL blank control containing reagent solution and the appropriate volume of solvent was incubated under the same conditions. Ascorbic acid as a standard control was noted as A<sub>0</sub>. The total antioxidant capacity was calculated by the following formula:</p><p>Total antioxidant capacity (%) = (A<sub>0</sub> &#x02212; A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>)/A<sub>0</sub> &#x000d7; 100%.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS8.SSS5"><title>Hydrogen Peroxide Radical (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) Scavenging Assay</title><p>The hydrogen peroxide scavenging of the endophytic metabolite extracts was determined using the method previously reported by <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Ruch et al. (1989)</xref>. The reaction mixture was prepared by adding hydrogen peroxide solution (2 mM) to 50 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.4). 0.5 ml of different concentrations (0.02, 0.04, 0.06, 0.08, and 0.1 mg/mL) of tested sample was placed into the test tube and diluted with phosphate buffer to 2.0 mL. Subsequently, 3.0 mL hydrogen peroxide solution was added to the mixture, and the absorbance of 230 nm was measured after 10 min. The hydrogen peroxide scavenging activities were calculated by the following formula:</p><p>Hydrogen peroxide scavenging activities (%) = (A<sub>0</sub>&#x02212;A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>)/A<sub>0</sub>) &#x000d7; 100%,</p><p>Where A<sub>0</sub> and A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub> was the absorbance values of ascorbic acid and the samples, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS8.SSS6"><title>Superoxide Anion Radical Scavenging Assay</title><p>The superoxide anion scavenging activity of the endophytic metabolite extracts was measured by following the method of <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Nishikimi et al. (1972)</xref> and <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Kaur and Arora (2010)</xref>. One milliliter nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT) solution (156 &#x003bc;M NBT in 100 mM phosphate buffer, pH 8.0), 1 mL NADH solution (468 &#x003bc;M in 100 mM phosphate buffer, pH8.0) and 1 mL of different concentrations (0.02, 0.04, 0.06, 0.08, and 0.1 mg/mL) of the tested sample were mixed. 60 &#x003bc;M of phenazine methyl sulfate (PMS) was dissolved in pH 8.0, 100 mM phosphate buffer, and further 100 &#x003bc;l PMS was added to start the reaction. After the reaction was carried out at 25&#x000b0;C for 5 min, the absorbance values of 560 nm were measured. The capability of scavenging super oxide radicals was calculated using the following formula (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Kaur and Arora, 2010</xref>):</p><p>Capability of scavenging super oxide radicals (%) = (A<sub>0</sub>&#x02212;A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>)/A<sub>0</sub> &#x000d7; 100%.</p><p>Where A<sub>0</sub> and A<sub><italic>x</italic></sub> was the absorbance of the positive control (ascorbic acid) and the samples, respectively. The solution containing NBT, NADH, and PMS without the sample was used as a blank.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S2.SS9"><title>Determination of Total Flavonoid Content</title><p>The total flavonoid content of the endophytic metabolite extracts was determined using the method previously reported by <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Park et al. (2008)</xref>. 1.0 mL of tested sample (0.1 mg/mL) was mixed with 2 mL of distilled water, after which 0.5 mL NaNO<sub>2</sub> (0.5 M) and 0.5 mL Al(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub> (0.3 M) solution were added to the mixture. After 6 min, 0.5 mL NaOH solution (1.0 M) was added to the mixture and cultured for 30 min at room temperature. Absorbance of 510 nm was determined with rutin as a standard compound.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS10"><title>Determination of Total Phenolic Content</title><p>Total phenolic acid content was determined by the Folin-phenol method (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2003</xref>). One milliliter of tested sample (0.1 mg/mL) and 1 mL Folin-ciocalteu reagent were added to a flask and mixed thoroughly. After 3 min, 3 mL of sodium carbonate (2%) was added and the mixture incubated at 23&#x000b0;C for 90 min with intermittent shaking. The absorbance was measured at 750 nm versus water blank with gallic acid as a standard compound.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS11"><title>Determination of Antibacterial Activity</title><p>Antimicrobial activity of the secondary metabolite of endophytes was evaluated using the paper disc diffusion method, as described by <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Doughari (2006)</xref>. For determination of antibacterial activity, all bacterial strains were suspended in nutrient broth and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C, after which they were adjusted to approximately 10<sup>5</sup> colony forming units/mL with sterile saline (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute, 2002</xref>) and 200 &#x003bc;L of suspensions was spread over nutrient agar (beef-oxoid) plates (diameter: 9 cm). Extracts were dissolved in 10% aqueous dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) and sterilized by filtration through a 0.22 &#x003bc;m membrane filter. Under aseptic conditions, empty sterilized discs (diameter: 6 mm) were impregnated with 10 &#x003bc;L of extract dilutions (10 mg/mL) and placed on the previously-seeded agar surface. Paper discs impregnated with 10 &#x003bc;L of penicillin (5 mg/mL) and 10 &#x003bc;L of DMSO were used as positive and negative controls, respectively. All plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 18 h. Antimicrobial activity was determined by the apparent zone clear zones of inhibition around the paper discs. For each extract, three replicates were performed against each organism (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS12"><title>Determination of the Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC)</title><p>The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of the secondary metabolites of the endophytes was determined by the paper diffusion method, as described by <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Shafi (1975)</xref>. Ten microliter of varying concentrations of the extracts (0.01, 0.05, 0.5, 1.0, 2.0, 4.0, 6.0, 8.0, and 10.0 mg/mL) were placed on the agar surface previously seeded using the above-mentioned method. Paper discs impregnated with 10 &#x003bc;L of a solution of 5 mg/mL of penicillin as a standard antimicrobial were used for comparison. All petri dishes were sealed with sterile laboratory parafilm to avoid eventual evaporation of the test samples. Inoculated plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 18 h. Inhibition of bacterial growth on the plates containing the test samples was determined by comparison with growth on the blank control plates. The MIC of each test sample was determined as the lowest concentration to completely inhibit the growth of each organism (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Shafi, 1975</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Delaquis et al., 2002</xref>). The MIC was repeated for each of the test organisms in triplicate (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Shafi, 1975</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS13"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>All experimental data are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD from three separate observations. The data analyzed by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Duncan&#x02019;s multiple range tests using the SPSS19.0 software. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was used to define statistically significant differences between the control and experimental groups.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3.SS1"><title>Isolation and Identification of Endophytes</title><p>Many studies have confirmed that endophytes have obvious distribution diversity in different tissue of host plants (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Hyde, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">Rosenblueth and Mart&#x000ed;nez-Romero, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Promputtha et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Jeewon et al., 2013</xref>). Therefore, in this study, different tissue of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>, including roots, stems, leaves, and seeds, are used for the isolation of endophytes. A large number of endophytes were isolated from different tissues of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>, including leaves, stems, roots and seeds, all of which showed that endophytes are very abundant and diverse in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. After inoculation and culturing for more than 1 week, 226 endophyte strains with distinct morphology were isolated from the roots, stems, leaves and seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> samples. All tissues showed a variation in the colonization frequency of endophytes. Among the tissues sampled, maximum colonization frequency was found in seed (29%), followed by leaf (26%) and lastly in stem and root with 23 and 22%, respectively. The molecular identification of 47 typical strains combined with morphology is shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The maximum nucleotide identity of the 16S DNA sequences of endophyte compared with those available in GenBank ranged from 99 to 100% (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">W&#x00229;&#x0017c;owicz et al., 2014</xref>). The 16S rDNA-based phylogenetic tree provides a more detailed synopsis of the relationship between the different species of endophytes obtained from different parts of each plant (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Kusari et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). The tree shows two major groups, which comprise 13 isolates belonging to <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>, and includes <italic>Brevibacillus</italic> sp., <italic>Pantoea</italic> sp., <italic>Erwinia</italic> sp., <italic>Enterobacter</italic> sp., <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp., <italic>Bacillus</italic>, and <italic>Serratia</italic> sp. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>, a phylogenetic tree was built from 18S rDNA sequences of endophytic fungi. The tree shows two major groups, which comprises 34 isolates belonging to <italic>Ascomycota</italic> and <italic>Deuteromycetes</italic>, and corresponds to <italic>Penicillium</italic> sp., <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp., <italic>Trichothecium</italic> sp., <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp., and <italic>Alternaria</italic> sp.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Endophytes isolated from different tissues of <italic>A. sinensis.</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endophytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum identity (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZC-5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria burnsii</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487761</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZC2-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria alternata</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487762</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZC2-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487763</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZC2-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria tenuissima</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487764</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZHLB-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487765</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZDF-6-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus awamori</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487766</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZG-6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pantoea</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492013</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZG-10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Erwinia gerundensis</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492014</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZG-8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492015</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZG-7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pantoea agglomerans</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492016</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZG-LB-3-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterobacter cloacae</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT505514</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZDF-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Trichothecium roseum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487767</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZH-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus safensis</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492017</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZH2-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria burnsii</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT488301</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZH2-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fusarium</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT563084</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZH2-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Fusarium acuminatum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487768</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZH2-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT498091</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZH2-5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria alternata</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487769</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZP4-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487770</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZP4-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria tenuissima</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487771</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZPP-2-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus sojae</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487772</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZSY-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487773</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZSY-2-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria alternata</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487774</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZSY-5-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Brevibacillus</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492018</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZSY-5-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487775</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZSY-6-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Penicillium</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487776</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZSY-7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487777</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZT-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus methylotrophicus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492019</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZT-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alternaria</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487778</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZW-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492020</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZW-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterobacteriaceae bacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492021</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZWD-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487779</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YC-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudallescheria</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT563085</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YH-8-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487780</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YH-8-2-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487781</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YH-8-2-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487782</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YH-12-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus oryzae</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487783</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YS-1-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus terreus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487784</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YS-1-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487785</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YT-2-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Penicillium polonicum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487786</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YT-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus niger</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487787</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JC-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus thuringiensis</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492022</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487788</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JC-1-2-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus terreus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487789</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GT-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Serratia</italic> sp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT505513</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GT-5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus cereus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT492023</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GT-6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MT487790</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree of partial sequence of endophytes from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> (<bold>A</bold>, bacteria; <bold>B</bold>, fungi).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-11-01489-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS2"><title>Biodiversity and Abundance of Bacteria and Fungi With Non-culture</title><p>A total of 252,400 fungi sequences and 362,404 bacterial sequences were obtained from 4 seed samples of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. The length of these valid sequences was approximately 280&#x02013;340 bp for bacteria and 220&#x02013;260 for fungi, accounting for 99% of the total valid sequences. The mean length of these valid sequences was nearly 290 bp for bacteria and 250 bp for fungi. The rarefaction curves of sequence data showed clear asymptotes in the number of observed species, demonstrating that bacterial and fungal communities from each seed sample of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> were well-covered by pyrosequencing (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>).</p><p>Using a 97% similarities sequence cutoff value, the valid sequences were further clustered into 152 OTU for bacteria and 83 OTU for fungi. Furthermore, a Community Diversity index, including Ace, Sobs and Chao, and a Community richness estimator, including Shannon and Simpson, were further analyzed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). No significant differences between the Community Diversity index and Community richness estimator could be observed for bacteria and fungi, suggesting that the difference in the diversity of bacteria and fungi, in the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> seeds, is not obvious and that as previously reported, bacterial and fungal diversity in the rhizosphere around the plants are similar (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2013</xref>). Moreover, the coverage shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref> was almost the same (from 99.95 to 100.0%), which was consistent with the demonstration of the rarefaction curve (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>; <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2016</xref>).</p><p>The relative ratio of bacteria to fungi composition at the phylum level is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>, bacterial sequences were classified into 7 phyla. the main phyla in the four biological samples were <italic>Cyanobacteria</italic> (65.45&#x02013;90.4%), <italic>Proteobacteria</italic> (7.64&#x02013;33.23%), and <italic>Firmicutes</italic> (0.04&#x02013;1.46%). The relatively low abundance (0.24&#x02013;1.24%) of <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>, <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, <italic>Microgenomates</italic>, and <italic>Saccharibacteria</italic> was also detected in a most biosamples. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>, fungi from two phyla were detected, the main phylum in the four biosamples was <italic>Ascomycota</italic> (98.15&#x02013;99.56%). The relatively low abundance (0.44&#x02013;1.85%) of <italic>Basidiomycota</italic> was also detected in most biosamples.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Mean relative abundance of the abundant phyla, orders, genera, and species in bacteria <bold>(A,C,E,G)</bold> and fungi <bold>(B,D,F,H)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-11-01489-g002"/></fig><p>The relative ratio of bacteria to fungi composition at the order level is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Relative abundance analysis showed 26 orders of bacteria and 17 orders of fungi from each seed sample of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. As demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>, the dominant bacteria order with abundance larger than 1% (the main order with abundance larger than 1%) in the four biosamples was <italic>norank_c__Cyanobacteria</italic> (65.45&#x02013;90.4%), <italic>Rickettsiales</italic> (0.47&#x02013;17.45%), <italic>Pseudomonadales</italic> (0.09&#x02013;15.87%), <italic>Enterobacteriales</italic> (0.07&#x02013;1.53%), and <italic>Bacillales</italic> (0.01&#x02013;1.2%). The relatively low abundance (0&#x02013;1.0%) of <italic>Lactobacillales</italic>, <italic>Burkholderiales</italic>, <italic>Sphingobacteriales</italic>, <italic>Rhodospirillales</italic>, <italic>Rhizobiales Micrococcales</italic>, <italic>Cytophagales</italic>, and <italic>Streptomycetales</italic> were also detected in most biosamples. As demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>, the dominant fungi order with abundance larger than 1% (the main order with abundance larger than 1%) in the four biosamples was <italic>Pleosporales</italic> (17.34&#x02013;87.57%), <italic>Capnodiales</italic> (3.28&#x02013;79.6%), <italic>Erysiphales</italic> (0.00&#x02013;1.67%), <italic>Helotiales</italic> (0.01&#x02013;1.49%), and <italic>Tremellales</italic> (0.01&#x02013;1.26%). The relatively low abundance (0&#x02013;1.0%) of <italic>Unclassified_c__Dothideomycetes</italic>, <italic>Cystofilobasidiales</italic>, <italic>Eurotiales</italic>, <italic>Dothideales</italic>, <italic>Xylariales</italic>, and <italic>Pleosporales</italic> were also detected in most biosamples.</p><p>The relative ratio of bacteria to fungi composition at the genus level is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Relative abundance analysis showed that 88 genera of bacteria and 44 genera of fungi were found in each seed sample of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. As demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>, the dominant bacterial genus with abundance larger than 1% (the main order with abundance larger than 1%) in the four biosamples were <italic>norank Cyanobacteria</italic> (65.45&#x02013;90.4%), <italic>Rickettsiales</italic> (0.47&#x02013;17.45%), <italic>Pseudomonadales</italic> (0.09&#x02013;15.87%), <italic>Enterobacteriales</italic> (0.07&#x02013;1.53%), and <italic>Bacillales</italic> (0.01&#x02013;1.2%). The relatively low abundance (0&#x02013;1.0%) of <italic>Lactobacillales</italic>, <italic>Burkholderiales</italic>, <italic>Sphingobacteriales</italic>, <italic>Rhodospirillales</italic>, <italic>Rhizobiales Micrococcales</italic>, <italic>Cytophagales</italic>, and <italic>Streptomycetales</italic> were also detected in most biosamples. As demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F</xref>, in the four biosamples, the dominant fungi order with abundance larger than 1% (the main order with abundance larger than 1%) were <italic>Alternaria</italic> (16.79&#x02013;79.28%), <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic> (2.27&#x02013;45.5%), <italic>Unclassified Davidiellaceae</italic> (0.12&#x02013;32.46%), <italic>Unclassified norank Pleosporales</italic> (0.21&#x02013;4.94%), <italic>Monographella</italic> (0.0&#x02013;3.03%), <italic>Plenodomus</italic> (0.1&#x02013;2.27%), <italic>Septoria</italic> (0.2&#x02013;2.57%), <italic>Gibberella</italic> (0.01&#x02013;2.16%), <italic>Erysiphe</italic> (0.78&#x02013;1.67%), <italic>Unclassified Sclerotiniaceae</italic> (0.01&#x02013;1.47%) and <italic>Cystofilobasidium</italic> (0.0&#x02013;1.4%). The relatively low abundance (0&#x02013;1.0%) of <italic>Unclassified Capnodiales</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Dothideomycetes</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, <italic>Cryptococcus</italic>, <italic>Stagonosporopsis</italic>, <italic>Stemphylium</italic>, <italic>Cladosporium</italic>, <italic>Trichothecium</italic>, and <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic> was also detected in most biosamples.</p><p>The relative ratio of bacterial and fungal composition at species level is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Relative abundance analysis showed 125 species of bacteria and 60 species of fungi from each seed sample of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. As demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2G</xref>, the dominant bacterial genera with an abundance higher than 1% (the main order with abundance larger than 1%) in the four biosamples were <italic>Unclassified norank Cyanobacteria</italic> (65.44&#x02013;90.38%), <italic>Unclassified norank Mitochondria</italic> (0.47&#x02013;17.44%), <italic>Unclassified Pseudomonas</italic> (0.01&#x02013;15.22%), and <italic>Izhakiella capsodis</italic> (0&#x02013;1.15%). The relatively low abundance (0&#x02013;1.0%) of <italic>Unclassified Asaia</italic>, <italic>Uncultured bacterium Hymenobacter</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Oxalobacteraceae</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Massilia</italic>, <italic>Uncultured bacterium Variovorax</italic>, <italic>Ethylobacterium adhaesivum</italic>, and <italic>Methylobacterium</italic> were also detected in most biosamples. As demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2H</xref>, the dominant fungal species with abundance larger than 1% (the main order with abundance larger than 1%) in the four biosamples were <italic>Unclassified Alternaria</italic> (16.74&#x02013;79.26%), <italic>Mycosphaerella_tassiana</italic> (0.59&#x02013;45.5%), <italic>Unclassified Davidiellaceae</italic> (0.12&#x02013;32.46%), <italic>Unclassified norank Pleosporales</italic> (0.21&#x02013;4.94%), <italic>Monographella cucumerina</italic> (0.0&#x02013;3.03%), <italic>Unclassified Plenodomus</italic> (0.1&#x02013;2.15%), <italic>Unclassified Septoria</italic> (0.2&#x02013;2.57%), <italic>Unclassified Gibberella</italic> (0.01&#x02013;2.16%), <italic>Erysiphe polygoni</italic> (0.78&#x02013;1.67%), <italic>Unclassified Sclerotiniaceae</italic> (0.01&#x02013;1.47%), and <italic>Cystofilobasidium</italic> (0.0&#x02013;1.4%). The relatively low abundance (0&#x02013;1.0%) of <italic>Unclassified Capnodiales</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Dothideomycetes</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, <italic>Cryptococcus</italic>, <italic>Stagonosporopsis</italic>, <italic>Stemphylium</italic>, <italic>Cladosporium</italic>, <italic>Trichothecium</italic> and <italic>Mycosphaerella</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Rachicladosporium</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Capnodiales</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Rachicladosporium</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Penicillium</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Cryptococcus</italic>, <italic>Unclassified Ascomycota</italic>, and <italic>Unclassified Capnodiales</italic> were also detected in most biosamples.</p></sec><sec id="S3.SS3"><title>DPPH Free Radical Scavenging</title><p>In the current study, the antioxidant activity of 190 endophytic metabolite extracts was evaluated using the DPPH scavenging method. The primary results of the DPPH radical scavenging assay are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> (scavenging rates &#x0003e; 70%). As can be seen, scavenging rates between 0 and 70%, 70 and 80%, 80 and 90%, and 9 and 100% were found in 49 (46.23%), 13 (12.26%), 21 (19.81%), and 1 (0.94%) isolates, respectively (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The DPPH radical scavenging rate of ZP4-3 fermentation, JH-4 mycelia, JH-4 fermentation and GT-2 fermentation exceeded 85%, indicating significant antioxidant activity, with the highest values observed for ZP4-3 fermentation (95.21 &#x000b1; 1.131%).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Number of endophytes with different DPPH radical-scavenging rates.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPPH radical scavenging</td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Number of endophytes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stem</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Root</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0223c;70%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0223c;80%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.26</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0223c;90%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.81</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0223c;100%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Moreover, the antioxidant activities of these four samples were further determined using different methods at different concentrations. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3A&#x02013;F</xref>, our results showed that four tested samples exhibited antioxidant activity in a dose-dependent manner within a concentration range of 0.02&#x02013;0.1 mg/mL. Similar to the standard V<sub><italic>C</italic></sub>, over a certain concentration range radical scavenging ability increased before reaching a plateau (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3A&#x02013;F</xref>). Furthermore, the IC<sub>50</sub> of the four samples of DPPH radicals, hydroxyl radical, reducing power, total antioxidant capacity, hydrogen peroxide and superoxide anion are determined and summarized in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Antioxidant activities of different samples. <bold>(A)</bold> DPPH radical scavenging activity. <bold>(B)</bold> Hydroxyl radical scavenging activity. <bold>(C)</bold> Reducing power. <bold>(D)</bold> Total antioxidant capacity. <bold>(E)</bold> Hydrogen peroxide radical activity. <bold>(F)</bold> Superoxide anion scavenging activity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-11-01489-g003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>TABLE 4</label><caption><p>IC<sub>50</sub> value from five antioxidant activity assays from four extracts of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="5" rowspan="1">IC<sub>50</sub> value (mg extract per mL)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPPH radical</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydroxyl radical</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total antioxidant capacity</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrogen peroxide radicals</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superoxide anion</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH-4 mycelium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057 &#x000b1; 0.002<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061 &#x000b1; 0.002<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062 &#x000b1; 0.004<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068 &#x000b1; 0.002<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071 &#x000b1; 0.006<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JH-4 fermentation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056 &#x000b1; 0.006<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104 &#x000b1; 0.006<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060 &#x000b1; 0.003<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072 &#x000b1; 0.009<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073 &#x000b1; 0.004<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GT-2 fermentation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057 &#x000b1; 0.002<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073 &#x000b1; 0.003<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071 &#x000b1; 0.008<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074 &#x000b1; 0.008<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088 &#x000b1; 0.007<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZP4-3 fermentation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053 &#x000b1; 0.002<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084 &#x000b1; 0.007<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067 &#x000b1; 0.002<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086 &#x000b1; 0.003<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090 &#x000b1; 0.003<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V<sub><italic>C</italic></sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054 &#x000b1; 0.005<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053 &#x000b1; 0.002<sup><italic>e</italic></sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053 &#x000b1; 0.003<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052 &#x000b1; 0.005<sup><italic>e</italic></sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056 &#x000b1; 0.007<sup><italic>e</italic></sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup><italic>a</italic>&#x02013;<italic>e</italic></sup>significant differences between different groups (p &#x0003c; 0.05).</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, the results show that no significant difference between the IC<sub>50</sub> of the four samples of DPPH radicals (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05) (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>), indicating that the antioxidant activity of the tested samples was similar to the V<sub><italic>C</italic></sub> standard. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3B&#x02013;F</xref> and <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, compared with Vc, the IC<sub>50</sub> of the four samples for hydroxyl radical, reducing power, total antioxidant capacity, hydrogen peroxide and superoxide anion was significantly lower (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). However, the IC<sub>50</sub> of the JH-4 mycelium for the hydroxyl radical, hydrogen peroxide radicals and superoxide anion were significantly higher compared with the other three samples (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). The JH-4 mycelium IC<sub>50</sub> for DPPH radicals, hydroxyl radical, reducing power, total antioxidant capacity, hydrogen peroxide and superoxide anion was 0.057 &#x000b1; 0.002, 0.061 &#x000b1; 0.002, 0.062 &#x000b1; 0.004, 0.068 &#x000b1; 0.002, and 0.071 &#x000b1; 0.006 mg/mL, respectively, all of which suggest that the antioxidant activity of JH-4 mycelia was the strongest.</p></sec><sec id="S3.SS4"><title>Estimation of Total Flavonoid and Total Phenol Content</title><p>The method of estimation of total flavonoid content and total phenol content was developed in the present study, the result of which is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. The standard curve of the rutin standard and gallic acid show a good linearity (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x0003e; 0.99) over the concentration range of 0&#x02013;1.2 mg/mL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4A,C</xref>). The results suggests that the method is applicable for the determination of total flavonoid content and total phenol content (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute, 2002</xref>). The total phenolic content in JH-4 fermentation, JH-4 mycelium, GT-2 fermentation and ZP4-3 fermentation were estimated to be 0.164 &#x000b1; 0.008 mg/mL, 0.142 &#x000b1; 0.009 mg/mL, 0.148 &#x000b1; 0.004 mg/mL, and 0.229 &#x000b1; 0.008 mg/mL, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>). The total flavonoid content in JH-4 fermentation, JH-4 mycelium, GT-2 fermentation and ZP4-3 fermentation were estimated to be 0.156 &#x000b1; 0.004 mg/mL, 0.173 &#x000b1; 0.003 mg/mL, 0.044 &#x000b1; 0.004 mg/mL, and 0.084 &#x000b1; 0.006 mg/mL, respectively, of which the highest total content of flavonoids was found in the JH- 4 mycelium, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4D</xref>.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>FIGURE 4</label><caption><p>Estimation of total flavonoid and total phenol content. <bold>(A)</bold> Rutin standard curve. <bold>(B)</bold> Total flavonoid content. <bold>(C)</bold> Gallic acid standard curve. <bold>(D)</bold> Total phenol content.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-11-01489-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS5"><title>Determination of Antimicrobial Activity and MIC Assay</title><p>This study also aimed to obtain isolates with high antimicrobial activity from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. We found that some sample of 190 crude extracts of endophytes from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> mostly displayed inhibitory activity against one or more of the five indicator bacteria. The primary screening results also showed that the mycelia extracts displayed higher antimicrobial activity than those of the filtrates. Furthermore, the MIC of four extracts (ZHLB-3 mycelium, ZWD-1 mycelium, YS-1-2 mycelium, and YH-12-1 mycelium) with high antimicrobial activity from the 190 endophytic metabolite extractions were determined, and the results are shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. As we can see, YH-12-1 mycelium exhibited good inhibitory activity against the five test strains, including <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, <italic>Bacillus licheniformis</italic>, <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>. In particular, the MIC value against <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> was 25 &#x003bc;g/mL, and MIC value against <italic>B</italic>. <italic>licheniformis</italic> was 30 &#x003bc;g/mL. Compared with the MIC of ampicillin against <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> of 8 and 6 &#x003bc;g/mL, this strain showed very good potential for further research.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>TABLE 5</label><caption><p>Determination of Minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) (&#x003bc;g/mL).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bacillus licheniformis</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZHLB-3 mycelium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZWD-1 mycelium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YS-1-2 mycelium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YH-12-1 mycelium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e; 50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Endophytes are widely distributed in plant tissues as well as the interior of plant tissues. Endophytes with different morphologies and functions are isolated from various plant species in natural ecosystems (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Tejesvi et al., 2011</xref>), and play an important role in host life cycles (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>). Western China, especially in Gansu Province, has a unique alpine climate and is a suitable place for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> planting. Some areas are called as &#x0201c;the homeland of Chinese <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>,&#x0201d; and its production of artificially cultivated <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> constitutes 70% of China&#x02019;s total production (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2016</xref>). Therefore, in the present study, fresh <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> plants from Min County of Gansu province were used to isolate endophytes using a tissue homogenate method.</p><p>The biosphere is microbially rich. However, after nearly 200 years of microbiology discovery research, we still know very little about the microbial diversity around us (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 2013</xref>). Most microorganisms in the natural environment are difficult or impossible to obtain pure culture by traditional culture separation methods. Traditionally, microbiologists try to increase the separation of microorganisms by changing the nutrient composition and culture conditions of these classic media (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Achtman and Wagner, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 2013</xref>). In this study, to isolate as many endophytes as possible and simulate the artificial environment as much as possible, 20 different media, including oligotrophic media, were used along with the conventionally diluted media. Generally, PDA medium is the most commonly used medium for the isolation of endophytes, in which, potato extract is the main natural complex component that affects the isolation of endophytes, and artificial medium cannot fully match. The potato as a tuber plant was used as a natural medium, therefore, other tuber plants such as lily, sweet potato, yam and carrot were also used as natural medium components for the separation of endophytes in here. However, the above natural medium is sufficiently nutritious, and rapid growth of dominant strains would inhibit the growth of other non-dominant strains, resulting in a decrease in the number and abundance of endophytes. Studies have shown that by reducing the nutrient concentration of traditional medium to prepare the oligotrophic state, and appropriately extending the incubation time, some microorganisms that cannot be separated from the classical medium can be obtained (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Davis et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 2013</xref>). Therefore, a variety of oligotrophic media were prepared with 100-fold diluted natural medium and were used in the experiment to isolate the endophytes. The results showed that the separation efficiency of the 100-fold diluted natural medium was higher than that of the original medium, which 100-fold diluted yam medium was the highest.</p><p>With 20 different media used, the results showed there are many endophytes in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>, which have abundant biodiversity. Furthermore, 226 representative strains were isolated and distributed in at least 13 genera belonging to 4 phyla. For endophytic fungi, the most frequent genera were <italic>Alternaria</italic> sp. and <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. The results also agreed with other previous reports that members of a variety of common fungal genera, such as <italic>Alternaria</italic> sp., <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp., <italic>Penicillium</italic> sp., and <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp., are usually isolated from a variety of plants around the world (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">W&#x00229;&#x0017c;owicz et al., 2014</xref>). In addition, organ specificity of endophytes were observed (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Kusari et al., 2013</xref>). For example, in the present study, <italic>Serratia</italic> sp. preferred to colonize the roots and <italic>Pseudallescheria</italic> sp. inhabited only the leaf. However, <italic>Brevibacillus</italic> sp., <italic>Erwinia</italic> sp., <italic>Enterobacter</italic> sp., and <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. inhabited only the seed. Compared with the MiSeq sequencing method, a minority of endophytes were identified from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. This indicates that there are still some defects in the traditional approaches. Therefore, different cultivation methods, such as diffusion box cultivation <italic>in situ</italic>, still need to be carried out in future.</p><p>We live in a world surrounded by microbes, the endophyte in a plant includes both the endogenous bacteria that are inherent to the plant and the inter-endogenous bacteria that coexist between the plants. As a class of microbes coexisting with host plants, endophytes have become an increasingly good resource for finding new active compounds. Plant seeds are not merely reproductive organs or important tools in agricultural production, they are also carriers of both pathogens and beneficial endophytes, particularly, inherent and non-invasive characteristic endophytes in host plant. However, in comparison to the well-studied endophytic fungi of roots, stems and leaves in those plants, little is known about microbes associated with plant seeds, in particular, the true knowledge of endophytic diversity in medicinal plant seeds.</p><p>Genetic evidence suggests that uncultured microorganisms account for a high percentage of environmental microbial communities in natural ecosystems, and yet the accessible (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Rapp&#x000e9; et al., 2002</xref>), cultivable fraction is less than 1% (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Epstein, 2013</xref>). Therefore, this study used metagenomics to analyze endophytic diversity in the seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> and compared with endophytes isolated from healthy leaves, stems, roots and seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> using 20 different media. The results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) showed that the most frequent endophytic fungi were also <italic>Alternaria</italic> sp. as seen in artificial media; moreover, our results showed that endophytic fungi obtained through artificial cultivation are mainly phyla <italic>Ascomycota</italic>, among which none of the endophytes isolated from the <italic>Angelica</italic> seed belonged to <italic>Pseudallescheria</italic> sp. and <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp., as seen in the diversity analysis by high-throughput sequencing. Correspondingly, the microorganisms of <italic>Basidiomycetes</italic> were not isolated on artificial media. The results suggest that pathogenic fungi, including <italic>Fusarium</italic> sp. and <italic>Pseudallescheria</italic> sp., may not be inherent endophytes in plants, but are formed by transfection from the environment during plant growth. As such, the microorganisms inherent in those plants, rather than the microorganisms obtained from the outside world, may be true endophytes. In addition, the endophytic bacteria obtained by artificially separating the medium are mainly divided into two phyla, <italic>Firmicutes</italic> and <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>. Furthermore, the endophytes in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> seed contained seven phyla isolated with the high-throughput sequencing of microorganisms, and five phyla of endophytic bacteria, including <italic>Proteobacteria</italic>, <italic>Actinobacteria</italic>, <italic>Bacteroidetes</italic>, <italic>Microgenomates</italic>, and <italic>Saccharibacteria</italic>, were not isolated on artificial medium. Therefore, we believe the endophytes in the roots, stems and leaves of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> possibly derived from the seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>, and changes in individual dominant strains of roots, stems and leaves of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> may be due to changes in growth environment of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. Our results also suggested that seeds of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> is a good material for studying the endophytes of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. Moreover, in another study, in order to simulate the natural environment as much as possible, we used plant extract as the medium for the microorganisms cultured. However, we found that this medium was too difficult to culture the fungus and further added potato extract as a growth factor (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Beever and Bollard, 1970</xref>), which significantly increased the fungal colony rate (data not shown). This result also indicates that different separation methods are necessary if more intrinsic endophytic bacteria and endophytic fungi are to be isolated.</p><p>Reactive oxygen species (ROS), generated by triplet state oxygen reacting with other molecules, such as superoxide radicals, hydroxyl radicals, and hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), is the major sources of primary catalysts that initiate oxidation <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2013</xref>). When these species are produced in excess due to pathophysiological processes or environmental interference, ROS can promote tissue damage and result in disease. Antioxidants are known to prevent those reactions caused by free radicals (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Goodman et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Marson Ascencio et al., 2014</xref>). In this paper, six antioxidant activity assays, including DPPH, hydroxyl radical scavenging assay, FRAP assay, total antioxidant capacity assay, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> scavenging assay and superoxide anion radical scavenging assay, were used to comprehensively evaluate the antioxidant activities of endophytic metabolites. The results showed that the sample JH-4 mycelium displayed the best antioxidant activity. Furthermore, total phenols and total flavonoids are known as the main components of antioxidant activity, and their contents are determined. Phenolic compounds are known to have very important biological activities, such as preventing hormone-related cancers, and as potent antioxidant agents (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Pise et al., 2010</xref>). The antioxidant activity of phenolic compounds is mostly derived from their redox actions, neutralizing free radicals, quenching singlet and triplet oxygen, or decomposing peroxides. Flavonoids are widely distributed polyphenolic compounds and have recently received extensive attention due to their important antioxidant properties (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Pietta, 2000</xref>). Flavonoids probably showed antioxidant activities because of their high total number of OH groups (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Firuzi et al., 2005</xref>). According to the current results, we found a significant correlation between flavonoid content and radical scavenging effect, but the correlation between total phenolics content and antioxidant activity was relatively weaker. The results further suggest that antioxidants in the bacteria may be flavonoids. The results obtained in this study also agree with those published previously in the literature (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Moein et al., 2008</xref>). In addition, there were few studies on the activity of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> endophytes besides (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2013</xref>). The antimicrobial activity of isolated endophytes from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> were detected using the paper disc diffusion method with five tested strains, including <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>, <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic>, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>licheniformis</italic>, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic>Str</italic>. <italic>pneumoniae</italic>. Our study showed that YH-12-1 mycelium had a strong inhibitory effect on <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic>, with a MIC of 25 &#x003bc;g/mL, which also indicates that further research is necessary.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In the present study, with 20 different media, 226 endophytes were isolated from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic> and identified based on morphological characteristics and molecular biology. This study was the first of its kind to study the diversity of endophytes in the seeds of medicinal plants. Compared with high-throughput sequencing, a minority of endophytes were isolated from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>. Furthermore, results of bioactivity evaluation showed that JH-4 mycelia and YH-12-1 mycelia have good antioxidant and inhibitory activity. All of our results showed that endophytes were highly abundant in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>sinensis</italic>, and indicated that their metabolites are potential viable sources for exploring many novel active compounds. Further exploration of endophytic isolation methods to obtain as many microbial resources as possible is still necessary.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/ <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors listed have made a substantial, direct and intellectual contribution to the work, and approved it for publication.</p></sec><sec id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This research was supported by the program of National Natural Science Foundation of China under (Grant No. 31860004), Gansu Province Natural Science Fund (No. 17JR5RA128), and the Fundamental Research Funds for Key Laboratory of Drug Screening and Deep Processing for Traditional Chinese and Tibetan Medicine of Gansu Province (No. 20180802).</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn id="footnote1"><label>1</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drive5.com/uparse/">http://drive5.com/uparse/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="footnote2"><label>2</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/">http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="footnote3"><label>3</label><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arb-silva.de">http://www.arb-silva.de</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><sec id="S9" sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2020.01489/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2020.01489/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="DS1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Achtman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Microbial diversity and the genetic nature of microbial species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>431</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>440</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1872</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18461076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18461076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinwari</surname><given-names>Z. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sikandar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Plant beneficial endophytic bacteria: mechanisms, diversity, host range and genetic determinants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Microbiol. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>221</volume>
<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2019.02.001</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30825940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30825940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debbab</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Proksch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Fungal endophytes: unique plant inhabitants with great promises.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>1829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1845</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-011-3270-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21523479?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21523479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The interface between the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus <italic>Glomus intraradices</italic> and root cells of <italic>Panax quinquefolius</italic>: a Paris-type mycorrhizal association.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mycologia</italic></source>
<volume>94</volume>
<fpage>587</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>595</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15572536.2003.11833187</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21156532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21156532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandara</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seneviratne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulasooriya</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Interactions among endophytic bacteria and fungi: effects and potentials.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Biosci.</italic></source>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>645</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>650</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bf02708417</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17301503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17301503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beever</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollard</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>The nature of the stimulation of fungal growth by Potato extract.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Gen. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>279</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-60-2-273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokhan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahomoodally</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Fungal endophytes associated with mangroves &#x02013; Chemistry and biopharmaceutical potential.</article-title>
<source><italic>South Afr. J. Bot.</italic></source></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>2114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2120</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24695404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Bacterial community shift and improved performance induced by in situ preparing dual graphene modified bioelectrode in microbial fuel cell.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioresour. Technol.</italic></source>
<volume>238</volume>
<fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2017.04.044</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28454001?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28454001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.-D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.-T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.-N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Parasutterella, in association with irritable bowel syndrome and intestinal chronic inflammation.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Gastroenterol. Hepatol.</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>1844</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1852</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jgh.14281</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29744928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29744928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab> (<year>2002</year>). <source><italic>Methods for Dilution Antimicrobial Susceptibility Tests of Bacteria that Grow Aerobically.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Pittsburgh, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Diversity and antioxidant activity of culturable endophytic fungi from alpine plants of <italic>Rhodiola crenulata</italic>, <italic>R. angusta</italic>, and <italic>R. sachalinensis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>:<issue>e0118204</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118204</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25768014?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25768014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Effects of growth medium, inoculum size, and incubation time on culturability and isolation of soil bacteria.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>826</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>834</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.71.2.826-834.2005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15691937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15691937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delaquis</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanich</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of individual and mixed fractions of dill, cilantro, coriander and eucalyptus essential oils ?.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Food Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0168-1605(01)00734-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deshmukh</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Endophytic fungi: a source of potential antifungal compounds.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Fungi</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>:<issue>77</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof4030077</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29941838?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29941838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deshmukh</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verekar</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhave</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Endophytic fungi: a reservoir of antibacterials.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>715</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2014.00715</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25620957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25620957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Isolation and characterization of endophytic fungi from <italic>Camptotheca acuminata</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>1831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1838</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11274-013-1345-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23579767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23579767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doilom</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manawasinghe</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeewon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayawardena</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibpromma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hongsanan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Can ITS sequence data identify fungal endophytes from cultures? A case study from Rhizophora apiculata.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mycosphere</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>1869</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1892</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5943/mycosphere/8/10/11</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doughari</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of <italic>Tamarindus indica</italic> Linn.</article-title>
<source><italic>Trop. J. Pharm. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Chemical analysis and antioxidant activity of polysaccharides extracted from <italic>Inonotus obliquus</italic> sclerotia.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>691</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>696</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2013.10.016</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24145301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24145301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>UPARSE: highly accurate OTU sequences from microbial amplicon reads.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nat. Methods</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>996</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>998</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2604</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23955772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quince</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detection.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>2194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr381</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21700674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The phenomenon of microbial uncultivability.</article-title>
<source><italic>Curr. Opin. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>636</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>642</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2013.08.003</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24011825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24011825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Copeselby</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Understanding and engineering beneficial plant&#x02013;microbe interactions: plant growth promotion in energy crops.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Biotechnol. J.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>1193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1206</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12279</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25431199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25431199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Firuzi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacanna</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrucci</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrosu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saso</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of the antioxidant activity of flavonoids by &#x0201c;ferric reducing antioxidant power&#x0201d; assay and cyclic voltammetry.</article-title>
<source><italic>BBA Gen. Subj.</italic></source>
<volume>1721</volume>
<fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2004.11.001</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15652192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15652192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golinska</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wypij</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarkar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathod</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahm</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Endophytic actinobacteria of medicinal plants: diversity and bioactivity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</italic></source>
<volume>108</volume>
<fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-015-0502-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26093915?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26093915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bostick</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kucuk</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Clinical trials of antioxidants as cancer prevention agents: past, present, and future.</article-title>
<source><italic>Free Radic. Biol. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>1068</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1084</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2011.05.018</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21683786?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21683786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grum-Grzhimaylo</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgieva</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondarenko</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debets</surname><given-names>A. J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilanenko</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>On the diversity of fungi from soda soils.</article-title>
<source><italic>Fungal Divers.</italic></source>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13225-015-0320-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutell</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>A compilation of large subunit RNA sequences presented in a structural format.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nucleic Acids Res.</italic></source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>r175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>r269</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/16.suppl.r175</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 3368328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3368328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakovli&#x000e6;</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Succession and fermentation products of grass carp (<italic>Ctenopharyngodon idellus</italic>) hindgut microbiota in response to an extreme dietary shift.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>1585</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01585</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28871246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28871246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeewon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ittoo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahadeb</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaufeerally-Fakim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.-K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A.-R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>DNA based identification and phylogenetic characterisation of endophytic and saprobic fungi from <italic>Antidesma madagascariense</italic>, a medicinal plant in Mauritius.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Mycol.</italic></source>
<volume>2013</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/781914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeewon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luckhun</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhoyroo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadeer</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahomoodally</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rampadarath</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <source><italic>Pharmaceutical Potential of Marine Fungal Endophytes.</italic></source>
<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>H.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A friendly relationship between endophytic fungi and medicinal plants: a systematic review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>906</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00906</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27375610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27375610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Superoxide anion radical scavenging activity of <italic>Bauhinia purpurea</italic> and <italic>Bauhinia galpinii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Chinese Clin. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>255</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant capacity of phenolic phytochemicals from various cultivars of plums.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>326</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0308-8146(02)00423-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D. S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Biodiversity and tissue-recurrence of endophytic fungi in <italic>Tripterygium wilfordii</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Fungal Divers.</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusaikin</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ermakova</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shevchenko</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isakov</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorshkov</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vereshchagin</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Structural characteristics and antitumor activity of a new chrysolaminaran from the diatom alga <italic>Synedra acus</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chem. Nat. Comp.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10600-010-9510-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusari</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiteller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kayser</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Endophytic fungi harbored in <italic>Cannabis sativa</italic> L.: diversity and potential;as biocontrol agents against host plant-specific phytopathogens.</article-title>
<source><italic>Fungal Divers.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>151</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13225-012-0216-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalhais</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>C. M. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Inner plant values: diversity, colonization and benefits from endophytic bacteria.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>2552</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.02552</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29312235?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29312235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magoc</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>FLASH: fast length adjustment of short reads to improve genome assemblies.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bioinformatics</italic></source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>2957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2963</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr507</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21903629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21903629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marson Ascencio</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ascencio</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimenta</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Chemical assessment and antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of endophytic fungi extracts isolated from <italic>Costus spiralis</italic> (Jacq.) Roscoe (Costaceae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Evid. Based Complement. Alternat. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>2014</volume>:<issue>190543</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Endophytic actinomycetes: promising source of novel bioactive compounds.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Antib.</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>519</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ja.2017.20</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28270688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28270688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moein</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moein</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadizadeh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Radical scavenging and reducing power of Salvia mirzayanii subfractions.</article-title>
<source><italic>Molecules</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>2804</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2813</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules13112804</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19015620?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maria</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activity, total phenolic and total flavonoid contents of whole plant extracts <italic>Torilis leptophylla</italic> L.</article-title>
<source><italic>BMC Complement. Alternat. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>12</volume>:<issue>221</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6882-12-221</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23153304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23153304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishikimi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Appaji</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1972</year>). <article-title>The occurrence of superoxide anion in the reaction of reduced phenazine methosulfate and molecular oxygen.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</italic></source>
<volume>46</volume>
<fpage>849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>854</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0006-291x(72)80218-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4400444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arancibia-Avila</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Antioxidants and proteins in ethylene-treated kiwifruits.</article-title>
<source><italic>Food Chem.</italic></source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>640</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>648</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2007.08.070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pietta</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Flavonoids as antioxidant.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Nat. Prod.</italic></source>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>1035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1042</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10924197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pise</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jena</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maharana</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaikwad</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagtap</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Free radical scavenging, reducing power, phenolic and biochemical composition of <italic>Porphyra</italic> species.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Algal Biomass Utilization</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Promputtha</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeewon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumyong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Ribosomal DNA fingerprinting in the identification of non sporulating endophytes from <italic>Magnolia liliifera</italic> (Magnoliaceae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Fungal Divers.</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Promputtha</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lumyong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>K. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeewon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>A phylogenetic evaluation of whether endophytes become saprotrophs at host senescence.</article-title>
<source><italic>Microb. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>590</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-006-9117-x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17410394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17410394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathod</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarkar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brestic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastore</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Fungal growth promotor endophytes: a pragmatic approach towards sustainable food and agriculture.</article-title>
<source><italic>Symbiosis</italic></source>
<volume>62</volume>
<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13199-014-0273-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapp&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Connon</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergin</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Cultivation of the ubiquitous SAR11 marine bacterioplankton clade.</article-title>
<source><italic>Nature</italic></source>
<volume>418</volume>
<fpage>630</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>633</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00917</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12167859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12167859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gajer</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcculle</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Vaginal microbiome of reproductive-age women.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>108(Suppl. 1)</volume>
<fpage>4680</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4687</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Fungal endophytes: diversity and functional roles.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytologist</italic></source>
<volume>182</volume>
<fpage>314</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>330</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02773.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19236579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19236579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenblueth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Romero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Rhizobium etli maize populations and their competitiveness for root colonization.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arch. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>181</volume>
<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>344</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-004-0661-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15024554?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenblueth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Romero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Bacterial endophytes and their interactions with hosts.</article-title>
<source><italic>Mol. Plant Microbe Interact.</italic></source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>837</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/mpmi-19-0827</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16903349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16903349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruch</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klaunig</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Prevention of cytotoxicity and inhibition of intercellular communication by antioxidant catechins isolated from Chinese green tea.</article-title>
<source><italic>Carcinogenesis</italic></source>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>1003</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1008</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/carcin/10.6.1003</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 2470525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2470525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shafi</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1975</year>). <article-title>Determination of antimicrobial MIC by paper diffusion method.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Clin. Pathol.</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>989</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>992</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jcp.28.12.989</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 812889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">812889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>K. A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brissow</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J. L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>E. G. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Endophytism and bioactivity of endophytic fungi isolated from <italic>Combretum lanceolatum</italic> Pohl ex Eichler.</article-title>
<source><italic>Symbiosis</italic></source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28066124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>V. M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>J. M. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza-Motta</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Endophytic fungi from the medicinal plant <italic>Lippia sidoides</italic> Cham. and their antimicrobial activity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Symbiosis</italic></source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13199-011-0113-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smirnoff</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cumbes</surname><given-names>Q. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Hydroxyl radical scavenging activity of compatible solutes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Phytochemistry</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>1057</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1060</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9422(89)80182-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daisy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Bioprospecting for microbial endophytes and their natural products.</article-title>
<source><italic>Microbiol. Mol. Biol. Rev. MMBR</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>502</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mmbr.67.4.491-502.2003</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 14665674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14665674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The Ministry of Health announces the list of food and food homologous items that can be used for health food items.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chinese Arch. Traditional Chinese Med.</italic></source></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tejesvi</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kajula</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattila</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirttil&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Bioactivity and genetic diversity of endophytic fungi in <italic>Rhododendron tomentosum</italic> Harmaja.</article-title>
<source><italic>Fungal Divers.</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>97</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13225-010-0087-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venugopalan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Endophytes as in vitro production platforms of high value plant secondary metabolites.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biotechnol. Adv.</italic></source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>873</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>887</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2015.07.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26225453?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26225453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Antioxidant activities potential of tea polysaccharide fractions obtained by ultra filtration.</article-title>
<source><italic>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>558</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>564</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2011.12.028</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22230610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22230610</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>W&#x00229;&#x0017c;owicz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozp&#x00061;&#x00327;dek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnau</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The diversity of endophytic fungi in Verbascum lychnitis from industrial areas.</article-title>
<source><italic>Symbiosis</italic></source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>147</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13199-015-0312-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Bacterial communities in the rhizospheres of three mangrove tree species from beilun estuary, China.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>:<issue>e0164082</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0164082</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27695084?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27695084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.-X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Advances in studies on rhizospheric microorganism of medicinal plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Chinese Traditional Herb. Drugs</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>504</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Study on angelica sinensis endophytic fungi and its antibacterial activity.</article-title>
<source><italic>Adv. Mater. Res.</italic></source>
<volume>641-642</volume>
<fpage>816</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>819</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4028/www.scientific.net/amr.641-642.816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Cervical microbiome is altered in cervical intraepithelial neoplasia after loop electrosurgical excision procedure in china.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>4923</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Z-ligustilide extracted from Radix Angelica Sinensis decreased platelet aggregation induced by ADP ex vivo and arterio-venous shunt thrombosis in vivo in rats.</article-title>
<source><italic>Yakugaku Zasshi J. Pharm. Soc. Jpn.</italic></source>
<volume>134</volume>
<fpage>855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>859</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1248/yakushi.129.855</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19571521?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19571521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>K. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Chemical and biological assessment of angelica roots from different cultivated regions in a chinese herbal decoction danggui buxue tang.</article-title>
<source><italic>Evid. Based Complement. Alternat. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>2013</volume>:<issue>483286</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Study on effects of endophytes on growth and production of Z-Ligustilide and ferulic acid in <italic>Angelica sinensis</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Braz. J. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40415-015-0245-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q. Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017a</year>). <article-title>Antitumor activity of a <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. Lut0910 isolated from polluted soil.</article-title>
<source><italic>Tumour Biol. J. Int. Soc. Oncodev. Biol. Med.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>:<issue>1010428317711661</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017b</year>). <article-title>A novel enzyme-assisted approach for efficient extraction of Z-ligustilide from Angelica sinensis plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>7</volume>:<issue>9783</issue>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Bacterial diversity in the feces of dogs with CPV infection.</article-title>
<source><italic>Microb. Pathog.</italic></source>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.04.043</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29709688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29709688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>X. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Diversity, distribution and biotechnological potential of endophytic fungi.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ann. Microbiol.</italic></source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>542</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13213-015-1153-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>N. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitousek</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Fungal endophyte communities reflect environmental structuring across a Hawaiian landscape.</article-title>
<source><italic>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</italic></source>
<volume>109</volume>
<fpage>13022</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13027</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1209872109</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22837398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22837398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>