<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Melis et al. recently reported on a series of quinoline-triazole Ir(III)Cp* conjugates, shown to inhibit the growth of NF54 and K1 strains of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic>, with activities ranging between 0.25–2.34 μM and 0.65–3.06 μM, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-05276-f004">Figure 4</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-25-05276" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Most notably, the activities of the complexes are substantially superior to those of the corresponding uncoordinated ligands, against the NF54 strain, with the activity, in some cases, exceeding that of the ligand by over 20-fold. This result highlights the potential benefits of metal incorporation, within drug design, offering an opportunity to enhance the pharmacological efficacy of organic compounds upon complexation. The cationic 
 <italic>N^N</italic>-coordinated pyridyl complex 
 <bold>18</bold> was the most active in the series, against both the sensitive and resistant strains, with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.25 ± 0.11 and 0.63 ± 0.06 μM, respectively. Furthermore, the selectivity indices for the tested complexes (
 <bold>17a</bold>–
 <bold>e</bold>, 
 <bold>18</bold>, and 
 <bold>20</bold>) suggest that they are not cytotoxic toward the CHO-cell line, and thus display increased selectivity for the parasite, with complex 
 <bold>18</bold> almost 500 times more selective toward parasitic cells than the mammalian cell-line. It was also noted that the incorporation of hydrophobic substituents did not seem to influence the antiplasmodial activity of the metal-based compounds. Furthermore, coordination at the quinoline nitrogen atom (
 <bold>19</bold>) was found to be unfavourable for activity. Finally, preliminary mechanistic studies suggested a dual mode of action by the compounds, involving inhibition of the hemozoin pathway and perturbation of the NAD
 <sup>+</sup>/NADH biochemical process by intracellular catalysis, which will be discussed in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec7-molecules-25-05276">Section 7</xref>.
</p>
