<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par65" class="p">Essential oils (EOs) extracted from aromatic plants and their main components have been described as broad-spectrum antimicrobial agents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>], with significant anthelmintic and antiprotozoal activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>]. Some terpenes of these oils such as citral (
 <italic class="italic">Lippia alba</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Cymbopogon citratus</italic>), caryophyllene oxide (
 <italic class="italic">Aframomum sceptrum, Achillea millefolium,</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Piper var brachypodon</italic>), and limonene (
 <italic class="italic">L. origanoides</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">L. pedunculosa</italic>) have demonstrated efficient trypanocidal activity on extra and intracellular forms of 
 <italic class="italic">T. cruzi</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>]. In addition, these terpenes have been found to exhibit other interesting biological properties, such as being anti-inflammatory immunomodulators, selective antioxidants, and cytoprotectors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>]. The presence of citral, caryophyllene and limonene has been identified in EOs isolated from two chemotypes (Citral and Carvone) of the aromatic shrub 
 <italic class="italic">Lippia alba</italic> (Miller) N.E. Brown (Verbenaceae), that grows in the Colombian province of Santander [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> represents the seventh species most cited in traditional Brazilian medicine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. The “healers” use their leaves as an infusion to treat health problems such as hypertension, digestive, colds and local wound healing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. In the state of Boyacá, Colombia, it is frequently used as an analgesic, for digestive (diarrhea, stomach pain) and respiratory problems (flu and cough) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]
 <italic class="italic">.</italic> Previous screening studies with these oils evidenced selective inhibition and cytotoxicity against trypanosomatid parasites, in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. Taking into consideration their numerous functions, 
 <italic class="italic">L. alba</italic> EOs and their bioactive terpenes are a promising platform for development of holistic therapies to combat Chagas Disease. This kind of approach could allow for a selective eradication of the parasite, with less toxicity (even with chemoprotection), and for controlling the host immune response, through a possible synergistic interaction of the compounds involved [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>].
</p>
