<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, compounds 3a–4i did not display any anticancer activity, whereas compounds 4a–4i exhibited potent antiproliferative activity against theSW620, MD468, and MD468-2 colon cancer cell lines. This implied that after PEGylation, the anticancer activity enormously increased in multiples of 469- to 11896-fold. PEGylated 1-H-pyrazol (3 and 4b) and quinolin-6-amine (4h) exhibited the highest activity against the SW620, MD468, and MD468-2 colon cancer cell lines and had IC50 values of 8.5 nM/mL and 9.3 nM/mL, respectively, for the corresponding cell lines. Compound 4i had an IC50 value of 7.8 nM/mL and also possessed the highest anticancer activity against the SW620 colon cancer cell line. Compounds 4g and 4b showed lower activity among compounds 4a–4i against MD468, MD468-2, and SW620, respectively, with IC50 values of 49.8 nM/mL and 39.3 nM/mL. However, compounds 4a–4f displayed moderate activity when the IC50 values of all of the compounds were compared with those of standard drugs like Camptothecin (IC50:10 nM) and Paclitaxel (IC50: 10 nM). Doxorubicin (IC50: 250 nM) and Oxaliplatin (IC50: 2000 nM) were also suited as reference cytotoxic agents. A comparative investigation of the IC50 concentrations of compounds 4a–4i with those of Doxorubicin (IC50: 250nM) and Oxaliplatin (IC50: 2000nM) was conducted. The anticancer activity displayed at an IC50 concentration ranging from 7.8 nM/mL to 49.8 nM/mL indicated that all of the synthesized compounds exhibited incredibly higher potency than those of Doxorubicin (IC50: 250 nM) and Oxaliplatin (IC50: 2000 nM). The results summarized in Table 3 suggested that the potency of each compound as an anticancer agent was irrespective of its substituents and showed high selectivity and more specificity towards the binding targeted sites. Compound 4h proved to be a highly-potent candidate against the SW620, MD468, and MD468-2 colon cancer cell lines than the existing armory of anticancer drugs attributable to the ring annulations with fused pyrazole nucleus.</p>
