<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The worldwide growing consumption of proteins for human and animal nutrition has drawn a considerable amount of attention to insect rearing; sector stakeholders focus on insect potential to convert organic material of low quality into high quality food and feed. Using insects, and in particular black soldier fly (BSF), 
 <italic class="italic">Hermetia illucens</italic>, larvae to transform waste into feed cannot be considered as an original idea. In their exhaustive review, Wang and Shelomi [
 <xref rid="B1-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] clearly stated that the practice of rearing insects on human-inedible wastes and using these Arthropods as a protein source for domestic animals is more environmentally friendly than using the land, water, and energy resources that could otherwise be employed to produce food for humans [
 <xref rid="B2-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. However, to avoid possible conflicts with the EU legislation and FDA (Food and Drug Administration) in the USA, potential biohazardous wastes such as animal manure and household waste cannot be used as substrates for insect rearing. The main substrates currently used in the European insect production include former foodstuffs not containing meat and fish, and co-products from the primary production of food of non-animal origin [
 <xref rid="B3-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Among the substrates categorized by the European Food Safety Authority (EFSA), in addition to animal feed materials included in the EU catalogue [
 <xref rid="B4-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], food waste of non-animal origin from food for human consumption was also considered. In particular, by-products of crops or leftovers of fruit and vegetable discarded from markets might represent a good substrate for rearing insects, which could be then used to feed domestic animals for human consumption. The use of food/waste by-products is not only a means to generate proteins for animals and man. Food waste is an issue of global importance directly linked to environmental, economic, and social impact. Different studies showed that between 1/3 and 1/2 of the world food production is wasted [
 <xref rid="B5-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. The European Parliament adopted the resolution of 19th January 2012 [
 <xref rid="B7-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] to point out the necessity of avoiding food wastage. Sectors that contribute to food waste are: primary production, processing, wholesale and logistics combined with retail and markets, food service, and household. The purpose of the present research was to demonstrate that it is possible to properly reduce food waste generated from fruit and vegetable markets by transforming this organic material into products that enter a circular value chain. According to the European Commission’s Circular Economy Package of 2015 “the transition to a more circular economy, where the value of products, materials and resources is maintained in the economy for as long as possible, and the generation of waste minimized, is an essential contribution to the EU’s efforts to develop a sustainable, low carbon, resource efficient, and competitive economy” [
 <xref rid="B8-animals-09-00278" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. 
</p>
