<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Beyond the rational refactoring of plant natural product pathways for microbial biosynthesis of natural alkaloids, synthetic biologists are taking inspiration from medicinal chemistry campaigns investigating small-molecule drug leads, with the objective of expanding the repertoire of medicinal plant alkaloids by including their unnatural derivatives. Bioactive natural products often proceed from lead to licensing without undergoing significant modification (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Ganesan, 2008</xref>). However, there is evidence that the derivatives of plant alkaloids possess new or improved pharmaceutical activities (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Leggans et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Sears and Boger, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Gautam et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>). This will be of interest for (i) finding drugs against therapeutic targets that are currently considered “undruggable,” such as B-class GPCRs (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Barker et al., 2013</xref>), and ii) finding improved variants against current targets—for example, 10-fluorovinblastine, 10-fluorovincristine (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Sears and Boger, 2015</xref>), and halogenated noscapine variants (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">DeBono et al., 2015</xref>) have demonstrated improved inhibition of tumor growth relative to the natural variants. Yet, the sparsity of derivatized natural products occurs because the same complexity that bedevils total synthesis of natural products also hinders systematic chemical modification. The high number of reactive oxygenic groups makes it difficult to chemically modify specific positions without also modifying others, creating a complex product mixture. Consequently, large collections of discrete natural product derivatives are not readily available for bioactivity screening (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Dandapani and Marcaurelle, 2010</xref>). It has been often hypothesized that a biological approach could generate relatively pure lead compound derivatives by harnessing the intrinsically high substrate and product specificity of enzymes. Accordingly, a number of studies have investigated the natural promiscuity of the biosynthetic pathways for medicinal plants alkaloids by feeding building block analogs or expressing building-block modifying enzymes (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">McCoy et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">Yerkes et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Runguphan et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">McDonald et al., 2019</xref>). However, the slow growth rate, relatively sparse molecular toolbox, and complex regulatory systems of plants have prevented systematic engineering of the pathway as a whole, and generally limited the biological exploration of chemical space to what is achievable with the natural promiscuity. Thus, while the refactoring of these pathways into microorganisms, as described above, holds great potential to yield valuable production workhorses for existing pharmaceuticals in the near future, microbial synthesis may furthermore facilitate the engineering of natural product pathways to open up entirely novel regions of chemical space that are currently inaccessible.
</p>
