<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sixteen cannabinoids (
 <bold>31</bold>–
 <bold>46</bold>) were classified as CBG-type cannabinoids (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02774-f003">Figure 3</xref>). In 1964, cannabigerol ((
 <italic>E</italic>)-CBG, 
 <bold>31</bold>) was isolated from cannabis resin, using florisil chromatography; the chemical structure of (
 <italic>E</italic>)-CBG (
 <bold>31</bold>) was confirmed through synthesis [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Cannabigerolic acid (CBGAA, 
 <bold>32</bold>) and the monomethyl ether of CBGAA (CBGAM, 
 <bold>34</bold>) were isolated in 1975, proving that CBGA (
 <bold>32</bold>) is the first cannabinoid synthesized in the biosynthetic pathway of Δ
 <sup>9</sup>-THCAA (
 <bold>2</bold>) [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The monomethyl ether of (
 <italic>E</italic>)-CBG (CBGM, 
 <bold>33</bold>) was isolated from a benzene extract of hemp by heating the extract with toluene for seven hours and purifying using column chromatography (silica-gel column) with benzene as the eluent [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Cannabigerovarin (CBGV, 
 <bold>35</bold>) and cannabigerovarinic acid (CBGVA, 
 <bold>36</bold>) were isolated from a benzene extract of “Meao variant” cannabis from Thailand; the chemical structures for CBGV (
 <bold>35</bold>) and CBGVA (
 <bold>36</bold>) were determined through IR, NMR, and UV spectroscopies [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In 1995, cannabinerolic acid ((
 <italic>Z</italic>)CBGA, 
 <bold>37</bold>) was isolated from an acetone extract of the leaves of a Mexican strain of 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic>, using silica-gel column chromatography. The chemical structure of (
 <italic>Z</italic>)CBGA (
 <bold>37</bold>) was determined through FAB-MS and NMR spectroscopies and confirmed by the synthesis of the cannabinoid [
 <xref rid="B30-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Another cannabinoid derivative, 5-acetyl-4-hydroxy-cannabigerol (
 <bold>38</bold>), was isolated from the buds of high potency 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> using normal phase HPLC of the polar fractions [
 <xref rid="B31-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Two esters of CBGA (
 <bold>32</bold>), γ-eudesmyl-cannabigerolate (
 <bold>37</bold>) and α-cadinyl-cannabigerolate (
 <bold>38</bold>), were also isolated from high potency 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic>, using chiral HPLC and their chemical structures were established by GC/MS, HRESIMS, 1D NMR, and 2D NMR [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In 2008, four epoxy cannabigerol derivatives, (±)-6,7-
 <italic>trans</italic>-epoxycannabigerolic acid (
 <bold>41</bold>), (±)-6,7-
 <italic>cis</italic>-epoxycannabigerolic acid (
 <bold>42</bold>), (±)-6,7-
 <italic>cis</italic>-epoxycannabigerol (
 <bold>43</bold>), and (±)-6,7-
 <italic>trans</italic>-epxoycannabigerol (
 <bold>44</bold>), were isolated from high potency 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> (grown in Mississippi) by the application of various chromatographic techniques (VLC, flash chromatography, and HPLC). The chemical structures of the four epoxy cannabigerol derivatives (
 <bold>41</bold>–
 <bold>44</bold>) based on NMR and HRESIMS spectroscopic analyses [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The polar dihydroxycannabigerol derivative (camagerol, 
 <bold>45</bold>) was isolated from the aerial parts of a 
 <italic>C. sativa</italic> strain, Carma, using reverse-phase (C
 <sub>18</sub>) silica-gel column chromatography, followed by normal-phase silica gel column chromatography and, finally, normal phase (NP)-HPLC. The wax of the aerial parts of the Carma strain was hydrolyzed and purified, using silica and alumina column chromatography, resulting in waxy and non-waxy fractions. The farnesyl prenylogue of cannabigerol (sesquicannabigerol, 
 <bold>46</bold>) was isolated from one of the waxy fractions. Its structure was established on the basis of NMR spectroscopic analysis (
 <sup>1</sup>H-NMR, 
 <sup>13</sup>C-NMR) and semisynthesis from cannabigerol (
 <bold>31</bold>) [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-26-02774" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The CBG type cannabinoids are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-02774-f003">Figure 3</xref>.
</p>
