<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For the disease detection in agriculture product, a fruit sorting machine is used to detect the citrus canker at 730 and 830 nm with a bandpass filter installed in the scanning camera [
 <xref rid="B172-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">172</xref>]. A real-time image processing and classification algorithm is developed based on a two-band ratio (R830/R730) approach, which achieves a detection accuracy of 95.3% for 360 citrus samples. Next, a shortwave infrared hyperspectral imaging system is used to detect the sour skin in onion based on the suitable reflectance spectrum from 1070 to 1400 nm [
 <xref rid="B173-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">173</xref>]. Two image analysis approaches are utilized based on the log-ratio images at two optimal wavelengths of 1070 and 1400 nm. A global threshold of 0.45 is integrated to segregate sour onion skin infection areas from log-ratio images. With Fisher’s discriminant analysis, the detection accuracy of 80% is achieved. The second image analysis approach is the incorporation of three parameters; max, contrast and homogeneity of the log-ratio images as the input features for the SVM. Subsequently, the Gaussian kernel generates higher detection accuracy as 87.14%. Apart from that, the tumorous chicken is detected by the combination of a CCD camera and imaging spectrograph from 420 to 850 nm [
 <xref rid="B174-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">174</xref>]. Within the wavelength bands, the PCA select the three useful wavelengths of 465, 575, and 705 nm from the tumorous chicken image. Based on the images from 60 tumorous and 20 normal chicken, multispectral image analysis generates the ratio images, which are divided into ROI classified either as tumorous or normal chicken. The image features from ROI such as coefficient of variation, skewness and kurtosis are extracted as the input for the Fuzzy classifier, which generates the detection accuracy of 91% for normal chicken and 86% for tumorous chicken. To detect the nematodes in coffee cultivation, hyperspectral data is used in band simulation of the RapidEye sensor to determine the most sensitive spectral ranges for pathogen discrimination in coffee plants [
 <xref rid="B176-molecules-24-02025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">176</xref>]. Multispectral classification identifies the spatial distribution of healthy, moderately infected, and severely infected coffee plants with an overall accuracy of 71%. Apart from the four main applications with the spectral imaging technique in agriculture products, more applications with different scanning methods and various wavelengths are tabulated in 
 <xref rid="molecules-24-02025-t007" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 7</xref>. 
</p>
