<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lignans can be produced in cell cultures [
 <xref rid="B444-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">444</xref>] and hairy root cultures [
 <xref rid="B445-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">445</xref>]. Hairy root cultures are particularly attractive for genetic engineering of secondary metabolism in crops recalcitrant to genetic transformation. Hairy roots are adventitious roots genetically transformed with 
 <italic>Agrobacterium rhizogenes,</italic> which harbors the root inducing (Ri) plasmid and 
 <italic>rol</italic> (root loci) genes that trigger hairy root growth. Compared to 
 <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic>-mediated genetic transformation, 
 <italic>A. rhizogenes</italic> mediated transformation is more efficient; no regeneration of transformed tissue is needed; and the transformed organ (root) proliferates fast. The fact that cell and hairy root cultures can be grown under controlled conditions independently of the season and climate over the whole year [
 <xref rid="B446-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">446</xref>] compensates for the high costs of facilities for in vitro production, as compared to growing plants in the field. For instance, sesame seeds contain 100 times more sesamin than transgenic cells of 
 <italic>Forsythia</italic>; however, transgenic cells multiplied 10-times in two weeks [
 <xref rid="B433-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">433</xref>], and they can be cultivated without seasonal interruptions. External factors such as light can be optimized in order to maximize sesamin production in cell cultures [
 <xref rid="B447-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">447</xref>,
 <xref rid="B448-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">448</xref>]. Culturing conditions exert tremendous effect on the metabolic productivity of tissues and cells. For instance, the same hairy root culture of 
 <italic>S. indicum</italic> accumulated certain metabolites in a bioreactor, while these metabolites were essentially missing when the roots were grown in flasks [
 <xref rid="B223-molecules-26-00883" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>].
</p>
