<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Terminalia chebula</italic> is the most widely used herb and commonly consumed traditional medicine of India [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It is well-documented traditional medicine to treat several diseases and infections [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> belongs to Combretaceae family and is found all over India and its fruit is considered as the “King of medicines”. This herb has achieved considerable development for its medicinal applications concerning several biological activities. Based on its unique natural components and products, it has been considered as a valuable source in developing medicines against infections and diseases [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> fruit is rich in phytochemical constituents like sterols, resin, amino acids, flavonoids, tannins etc., its content varies depending upon the geographical variation [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This plant is rich in tannins and the major chief polyphenol components of tannins are corialgin, chebulic acid, ellagic acid and gallic acid [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Further, the fruit extract of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> has a antimicrobial activity as it was found to be very effective in both gram-negative and gram-positive bacteria, similar to 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>, 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. It also has an excellent antioxidant, anticarcinogenic, antidiabetic, antiaging activities [
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> can also act as antiviral agent by activating the macrophage/monocyte of the system and also helps in the release TNF and interferon in the host cells [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> has been reported to be cytotoxic against cancer cell lines at higher concentrations. In a study conducted by Ravi Shankara et al. (2016), ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> leaf gall was found to effectively inhibit the growth of human lung cancer (A-549) and human breast adenocarcinoma (MCF-7) cell lines. The reported IC
 <sub>50</sub> values against A-549 and MCF-7 were 208.16 ± 3.7, and 643.13 ± 4.2 µg/mL, respectively [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Furthermore, the aqueous extract of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> was found to induce apoptosis in A-549 cell line via mitochondria-mediated pathway controlled by the Bcl-2 family members, Bcl-2, Bcl-xI and Bax proteins [
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Similarly, in an in vivo study conducted by Ahuja et al. (2013), it was concluded that the ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> significantly reduced the tumor growth in mice, with EAC induced cancer, apart from increasing their lifespan and restoring the haematological homeostasis [
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-05042" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. To the best of knowledge, limited research has been conducted in understanding the anti-breast cancer potential of 
 <italic>T. chebula</italic> owing to its selective cytotoxicity.
</p>
