<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For each GloNAF region, we collected a range of variables which are assumed to relate to current RRN (= number of naturalized species relative to native species number) and RRI (= number of invasive species relative to native species number). Each GloNAF region was assigned to one of nine continents of the TDWG continental scheme (further referred to as TDWG continents; 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Brummit 2001</xref>). We calculated the area of each region while considering only the ice sheet-free areas of each region, ranging from 0.03 to 4 331 903 km
 <sup>2</sup> (median: 28 836 km
 <sup>2</sup>). In addition, each GloNAF region was uniquely classified as belonging to a continental landmass (= mainland) or island, assigned to a hemisphere, Old/New World and the predominant broad climatic regime (zonobiome) to which the dominant vegetation type is closely associated (according to the Köppen-Geiger climate classification system; 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Kottek 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Peel 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2007
 </xref>). Spatial heterogeneity positively influences the number of niches available, which in turn may be colonized by alien plants. We thus used topographic heterogeneity of the region, calculated as the standard deviation of the mean elevation of each grid cell (size: 30 × 30 geographic seconds, corresponding to c. 1 × 1 km at the equator; taken from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/srtm/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/srtm/</ext-link>) belonging to the respective region, as a proxy for environmental heterogeneity. Variation in elevation is closely related to variation in climate, geology, geomorphology and land use, and therefore it is a useful measure of a region’s heterogeneity (
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Kerr and Packer 1997</xref>).
</p>
