<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With regards to the difference in response evoked by coconut oil supplementation between pre-clinical and clinical studies, it is prudent to consider the distinctions inherent to each experimental model that was used in each study. The two studies involve specimens with different structure and metabolism and also with different experimental conditions. In the preclinical study, the dose of coconut oil administered was 2 mL per day for animals weighing between 200–300 g. Based on this dosage, if this was extrapolated for use in adult humans (average weight 70 Kg), an amount that would exceed 500 mL of EVCO per day would be necessary [
 <xref rid="B33-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The dose used in this study (10 mL/day) was based on the study by [
 <xref rid="B17-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] which proved to be safe, with no adverse effects recorded. [
 <xref rid="B34-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] demonstrated that virgin coconut oil (1.4 mL/kg weight) prevents blood pressure elevation in rats fed palm oil. The experiment used 32 male Sprague-Dawley rats and measurements were performed every four weeks for a total period of 16 weeks by tail-cuff method. It is not clear that the beneficial effects attributed to coconut oil obtained in animal studies can be extended to humans. For example, Khaw et al. [
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] compared three types of diets: EVCO, extravirgin olive oil and unsalted butter. The participants incorporated 50 g of the respective fats into their usual diet for a period of four weeks. These authors did not report any difference in pressure levels after the experimental period. On the other hand, Perona et al. [
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] observed a reduction in systolic blood pressure levels in elderly hypertensive patients after using 60 g/day virgin olive oil for four weeks. Indeed, unlike what is observed in relation to coconut oil, Massaro et al. [
 <xref rid="B35-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], through a distinguished review work, showed that there is relative similarity of effects between pre-clinical and clinical studies addressing the use of olive oil to treat hypertension. Summarizing, Wallace [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-13-00798" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] performed a systematic review on the effects of coconut oil and concluded that the available evidence is sufficient only to encourage new studies with more methodological robustness. Another important aspect that deserves consideration is that, in order to avoid the confounding effects of medication, we opted for stage 1 hypertensive patients. Whether coconut oil may exert some beneficial effect on blood pressure of patients with higher blood pressure levels remains to be elucidated.
</p>
