<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In tomato, its characteristic sweet-sour taste is due to a combination of the sugars and organic acids, and positive correlations between perceived sweetness, reducing sugar content, and soluble solids have been found [
 <xref rid="B162-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. Therefore, to define what compounds are more critical to flavour is more complex than expected. Moreover, when vegetables are harvested, a catabolic process starts due to the disruption of plant tissues, affecting their aroma and transforming their key flavours into different compounds. Some of them may even turn into a new biologically active compound. For example, in brassica vegetables, operations such as cutting, chewing, and cooking have an uncontrolled effect on volatile compounds, due to the mixture of enzymes. The brassica vegetables’ typical odours and tastes are mainly due to the presence of glucosinolates, which when in contact with the enzyme myrosinase (EC 3.2.1.147, thioglucoside glucohydrolase) hydrolyse into new groups of breakdown products such as isothiocyanates, organic cyanides, oxazolidinethiones, and thiocyanate [
 <xref rid="B162-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>], affecting their aroma and transforming their key flavour into a different one. A similar situation occurs with 
 <italic>Allium</italic> species, such as onion, shallot, garlic, leek, and others, have in common the presence of the sulphur-based 
 <italic>S</italic>-alk(en)ylcysteine sulfoxide (alliin, I) in their composition. In damaged or disrupted tissue transformation into several other compounds, via alliinase occurred [
 <xref rid="B163-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. The initial hydrolysis products are ammonia, pyruvate, and an alk(en)ylthiosulphinate (allicin, II), and can undergo further nonenzymatic reactions to yield a variety of compounds such as thiosulphate [III] and di- and trisulphides [IV] [
 <xref rid="B146-foods-10-00106" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>], which gives to 
 <italic>Allium</italic> species their typical odour of a sulphur-like smell.
</p>
