<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Diabetes mellitus (DM) is the most common chronic and metabolic disease, which affects a large number of populations in the world. Currently, more than 150 million people are suffering from diabetes, and this number is expected to reach 300 million by 2025 [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is characterized by an elevated blood glucose level due to defects in insulin secretion and insulin resistance, or both. DM is associated with eye, renal, cardiovascular, and neurological complications in the long term and is also associated with symptoms such as polyuria, fatigue, weight loss, delayed wound healing, blurred vision, increases in plasma and urine glucose levels [
 <xref rid="B2-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Generally, DM can be categorized into two types; type 1 and type 2. Many synthetic medicines like insulin and oral hypoglycemic drugs available on the market are used to treat type 2 diabetes, but the long term use of insulin therapy and oral synthetic medicines may cause severe side effects [
 <xref rid="B5-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Furthermore, oral anti-diabetic drugs are costly; hence, it is very difficult for low and middle-income people to continually use these medications [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Taking into account the side effects of synthetic anti-diabetic drugs, the interest in herbal medicinal products for DM treatment is growing [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Several phytochemical constituents, including flavonoids, phenolic, coumarins, and other compounds that are plentiful in medicinal herbs have been evaluated as being capable of lowering blood glucose levels [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The capability of medicinal plants in treating DM relates to their ability to improve the action of pancreatic tissue by increasing insulin secretion or reducing intestinal glucose absorption [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Decreasing postprandial hyperglycemia is a therapeutic approach used for the treatment of DM. This goal can be achieved by inhibiting the carbohydrate hydrolyzing enzyme, 
 <italic>α</italic>-glucosidase (AG). The AG enzyme plays a vital role in carbohydrate metabolism by breaking starch and disaccharides into glucose [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-05885" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, inhibition of AG is an effective therapeutic approach for the management of DM.
</p>
