<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Six isonitrogenous (45% crude protein) and isolipidic (8% crude lipid) experimental diets were formulated to meet the nutrient requirements of swimming crab juveniles based on NRC recommendations (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). The major fatty acid compositions of experimental diets containing different lipid sources (% total fatty acids) are presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>. FO diet contained 7.94% EPA and 7.42% DHA of TFA (total fatty acids), KO diet contained 8.71% EPA and 7.54% DHA of TFA, PO diet contained 29.42% C16:0 of TFA, RO diet contained 38.45% C18:1n-9 of TFA, SO diet contained 42.93% C18:2n-6 of TFA, and LO diet contained 27.73% C18:3n-3 of TFA, respectively. All experimental diets were sealed in vacuum-packed bags and stored at -20°C until used to maintain good quality for the feeding trail. Disease-free and similar sized swimming crab juveniles were obtained from Xiangshan crab field (Ningbo, China). The feeding trial was conducted in Ningbo Marine and Fishery Science and Technology Innovation Base (Ningbo, China) located at (121.7784°E, 29.6481°N). Prior to the start of the feeding trial, swimming crab juveniles which caught from the pond were acclimated in the cement pool for 1 week and fed with a commercial diet (45% crude protein, 80% crude lipid, Ningbo Tech-Bank Feed Co., Ltd., Ningbo, China). A total of 270 swimming crab juveniles with an initial weight of 5.43 ± 0.03 g were randomly divided into six diets. Each diet had three replicates, each consisted of 15 crabs. Each crab juvenile was assigned to an individual rectangle plastic basket (35 cm × 30 cm × 35 cm) in the cement pool (6.8 m × 3.8 m × 1.7 m, length × width × depth). The plastic basket had two compartments, one section filled with sand (diameter, &lt;0.5 mm; thickness, 5.0–7.0 cm) to mimic the habitat of swimming crab and the other section as the feeding area. Fifteen plastic baskets were placed in a line next to each other in the cement pool provided with continuous aeration through an air stone to maintain dissolved oxygen levels near saturation levels. All of the crabs were fed experimental diets once daily (daily ration was about 6–8% of wet weight) at 17:00 h. Crab in each plastic basket was weighted once every 2 weeks and the feed’s daily ration was adjusted accordingly. Feces and uneaten feed were removed and about 60% of seawater in the cement pool were daily exchanged to maintain water quality every morning. Seawater temperature in the cement pool was entirely consistent among all individual rectangle plastic basket used for the experiment. Seawater temperature in the cement pool gradually decreases from 32.3 to 26.2°C with the conduct of feeding trial (8 weeks, from July 25th to September 11th). The variation of 6°C referred to the natural temporal variation of temperature over the duration of the experiment. The salinity ranged between 25.5 and 28.6 g/L, pH was 7.3–7.9, ammonia nitrogen was lower than 0.05 mg/L, and dissolved oxygen was not less than 6.0 mg/L during the feeding trail. Salinity, pH, ammonia nitrogen and dissolved oxygen were measured by YSI Proplus (YSI, Yellow Springs, OH, United States). The feeding trial lasted for 8 weeks.
</p>
