<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">Yeast (
 <italic class="italic">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) has become a regular ingredient in the food industry. Some of the most outstanding ingredients now used for natural flavouring in process flavours are yeast extract-based products and yeast autolysates (In et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2005</xref>), particularly when a meaty aroma is required (Lin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">2014</xref>). These enhance the food flavour by imparting cheesy, meaty or savoury notes, but can also be used as texturizers, stabilizers and thickeners (Sucan and Weerasinghe 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" class="xref">2005</xref>). Yeast extracts are also known for their nutritional benefits as they have a relatively high content of protein, vitamins (B1, B2 and nicotinic acid) and minerals (Sucan and Weerasinghe 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" class="xref">2005</xref>). In addition, they can be used for salt reduction in processed food without compromising the ‘saltiness sensation’ of the food product (Batenburg and van der Velden 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2011</xref>). By varying the autolytic conditions used in yeast processing, such as temperature and time, different meaty and savoury notes can be obtained to suit different industrial purposes (Ames 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">1994</xref>; Münch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">1997</xref>; Mahadevan and Farmer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2006</xref>). Components can be either already present in the starting materials or they are formed as a result of the processing strategy used (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). Cooked foods develop characteristic flavours and colours, which are formed through complex series of reactions mainly related to Maillard reactions, lipid oxidation, and thermal degradation (Parker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">2015</xref>). These reactions and their importance to flavour development are explained in detail throughout this review.
</p>
