<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In vitro anti-arthritic activity</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Protein denaturation is a process in which proteins lose their tertiary structure and secondary structure. It is one of the causes of arthritic disease and inflammation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. Mechanism of denaturation probably involves alteration in electrostatic, hydrogen, hydrophobic and disulphide bonding [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. In vitro anti-arthritic activity of studied oil samples was evaluated with bovine serum albumin (BSA) denaturation and egg albumin denaturation methods. Our study reveals that the milk thistle oil is capable to inhibit the denaturation of protein (Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>). The oil extracted from mature seeds showed inhibition of denaturation of BSA and egg albumin by 72.49% and 59.89%, respectively. This result suggested that milk thistle oil might prevent denaturation of protein in rheumatoid arthritis and could be used as a potential anti- arthritic agent. Previously published studies examined the anti-arthritic activity of various plant extracts. The ethanolic extract of 
  <span class="italic">Oryza sativa</span> inhibited the egg albumin and bovin serum denaturation by 84.15% 60.47%, respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The methanolic stem extract of 
  <span class="italic">Cuscuta pedicellata</span> also exhibited strong inhibition of protein denaturation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. Kamble et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>] indicated that ethanolic extract of leaves of 
  <span class="italic">Vitex negundo</span> and Punica granatum showed potential anti-arthritic activity as compared to aqueous extract.
  <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Effect of milk thistle oil on egg albumin and BSA denaturation, during seed maturation</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Maturation stage</th>
      <th>% of inhibition
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </th>
      <th>% of inhibition
       <span class="sup">b</span>
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Immature</td>
      <td>59.89 ± 1.4</td>
      <td>72.49 ± 1.3</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Intermediate</td>
      <td>78.46 ± 1.2</td>
      <td>85.32 ± 1.0</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Mature</td>
      <td>86.36 ± 1.5</td>
      <td>92.53 ± 1.2</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Values were expressed as means ± SD of triplicate experiments</p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">a</span>% of inhibition of egg albumin denaturation
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="sup">b</span>% of inhibition of bovine serum albumin (BSA) denaturation
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results showed that the anti-arthritic activity of oil samples was affected by the seed maturity stage, as shown in Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>. The maximum inhibition of BSA denaturation (92.53%) and egg albumin denaturation (86.36%) were exhibited by the oil extracted from the immature seeds. Throughout seed maturation, the total policosanol content of milk thistle oil was highly correlated with the inhibition of BSA denaturation (0.774) and egg albumin denaturation (0.901) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>).Therefore, the anti-arthritic activity of oil can be attributed, in part, to the policosanol content. Kumari et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>] reported that the anti-arthritic activity of methanolic extract of 
  <span class="italic">Rhizophora mucronata</span> might be due to the presence of active principles such as polyphenolic content, triterpenoids, alkaloids and flavanoids. Though present in small amounts, the minor constituents of dietary oils may supplement the dietary therapies for rheumatoid arthritis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>].
  <div id="Tab4" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Correlation coefficients (r) between policoanol content, antioxidant and anti-arthritic activities of milk thistle oil, during seed maturation</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th>Correlation coefficient</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>TPC-DPPH effect</td>
      <td>0.952</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>TPC-ABTS effect</td>
      <td>0.899</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>TPC- % of inhibition of EAD</td>
      <td>−0.901</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>TPC- % of inhibition of BSA</td>
      <td>0.774</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">TPC</span> Total Policosanol content
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="italic">DPPH</span> 1,1-diphenyl-2-picrylhydrazyl radical
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="italic">ABTS</span> 2,2′-azino-bis (3-ethyl-benzthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid)
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="italic">EAD</span> egg albumin denaturation
    </p>
    <p>
     <span class="italic">BSA</span> bovine serum albumin denaturation
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
