<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Policosanol composition</div>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aliphatic alcohols fraction of the milk thistle oil was submitted to the GC-MS analysis. Nine aliphatic alcohols were identified in the oil samples and they range from C
  <sub>22</sub> to C
  <sub>32</sub> (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). The dominant policosanols in the mature seed oil were Octacosanol (75.44%) and triacontanol (8.61%), however the other aliphatic alcohols detected including C
  <sub>22</sub>, C
  <sub>23</sub>, C
  <sub>24</sub>, C
  <sub>26</sub>, C
  <sub>27</sub>, C
  <sub>29</sub>, and C
  <sub>32</sub> were present in amounts ranging from 1.52 to 3.34%. Milk thistle oil extracted from mature seeds could serve as natural source of octacosanol, which has been shown to exhibit various beneficial effects such as anti-parkinsonian, antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effects [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Octacosanol is also the single most abundant policosanol in sugar cane wax (60–70%) and perilla seeds (55.93%) with a minor quantity of many other policosanols [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. The policosanol composition in vegetable oils was greatly source dependent [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. In the commercial green tea leaves, octacosanol (29.9–42.7%) and triacontanol (27.4–41.5%) were the main policosanol components [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Olive oil was characterized by the predominance of hexacosanol, tetracosanol and octacosanol [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. Harrabi et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>] reported that dotriacontanol (30.1–35.5%) was the major policosanol in whole corn kernel, followed by triacontanol (17.7–24.8%) and tetracosanol (15.2–25.7%). However in wheat, tetracosanol was the most abundant compound, followed by docosanol and hexacosanol [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>].
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Policosanol composition of milk thistle oil extracted from mature seeds</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Policosanol (Chemical formula)</th>
      <th>Percent</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Docosan-1-ol (C
       <sub>22</sub>-OH)
      </td>
      <td>1.52 ± 0.24</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Tricosan-1-ol (C
       <sub>23</sub>-OH)
      </td>
      <td>2.12 ± 0.39</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Tetracosan-1-ol (C
       <sub>24</sub>-OH)
      </td>
      <td>2.02 ± 0.50</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Hexacosan-1-ol (C
       <sub>26</sub> -OH)
      </td>
      <td>2.50 ± 0.16</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Heptacosan-1-ol (C
       <sub>27−</sub>OH)
      </td>
      <td>1.90 ± 0.25</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Octacosan-1-ol (C
       <sub>28</sub>-OH)
      </td>
      <td>75.44 ± 2.41</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Nonacosan-1-ol (C
       <sub>29</sub>-OH)
      </td>
      <td>2.55 ± 0.62</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Triacontan-1-ol (C
       <sub>30</sub>-OH)
      </td>
      <td>8.61 ± 1.20</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Dotriacontan-1-ol (C
       <sub>32</sub>-OH)
      </td>
      <td>3.34 ± 0.56</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Values were expressed as means ± SD of triplicate experiments</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> shows that the percentages of octacosanol, triacontanol and dotriacontanol were largely influenced by seed maturity stages. In immature seeds, the dominant alcohol was C
  <sub>30</sub> (40.25%), followed by C
  <sub>28</sub> (30.42%) and C
  <sub>32</sub> (16.36%). During seed maturation, the percentage of octacosanol increased rapidly, while those of triacontanol and dotriacontanol decreased. The levels of the other detected compounds were relatively constant, as the seed developed. In agreement to our present trends, the level of triacontanol was also found to decrease during corn kernel development [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. Immature seeds are rich in triacontanol which is essential for their development. In fact, triacontanol has been reported to stimulate plant growth, increase dry weight, prevent oxidative stress and act as an inhibitor of lipid peroxidation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. The variation in the policosanol composition might be due to the physiological changes that accompany ripening of seeds. Triacontanol exhibited anti-inflammatory action in animals and has been suggested to be an effective anti-inflammatory drug [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. Thus, immature milk thistle seeds could be exploited as a natural source of this bioactive compound.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Changes in octacosanol, triacontanol and dotriacontanol levels in milk thistle oil during seed maturation</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12944_2018_682_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
