<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">Allelopathy is ubiquitously existing among plant species, generally being tested with the effects on the plant seedling growth
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Common native species, for instance 
 <italic>pueraria lobata</italic> and 
 <italic>paederia scandens</italic>, depressed growth of 
 <italic>Ipomoea cairica</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Allelochemicals inhibited protein synthesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup> and cell division and elongation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>, consequently affecting plant growth and development. However, the study of allelopathy mainly focuses on the allelopathy of invasive plants to native plants, while the opposite study may become a new way to control invasive weeds. The present study identified an inhibitory allelopathy effect of a native plant species 
 <italic>H. scandens</italic> on 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>, being revealed by the fact that three chemical extracts of HR inhibited the seedling growth of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> (
 <italic>SE</italic> &lt; 0, Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Inhibition of shoot growth of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> was previously identified as well with extracts, residues and allelochemicals from different plants and fungi
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Biomass is one of the main important factors controlling the spread of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. The regrowth capacity of alligator weed was weakened by removing and destroying its above- and below-ground biomass
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. An inhibited aboveground biomass, belowground biomass, total biomass and the leaf area of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> were found in our study with exposure to ethyl acetate extract of HR (
 <italic>RI</italic> = − 0.67, − 0.72, − 0.68, − 0.83, respectively). Allocation indicates the investment of plants in resource utilization. Therefore, the reduced biomass of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> would likely reduce the ability of this invasive plant to absorb nutrients and capture light energy.
</p>
