<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Under optimal conditions, the balance between reactive oxygen species (ROS) formation and consumption is tightly controlled by antioxidant enzymes and redox metabolites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. However, allelochemicals were able to induce cell membrane permeability (for example, of saccharomycetes, sugar beet, maize and so on)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup> and oxidative stress
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. In the present study, an increased POD activity in the leaves of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> with the treatment of PE and NE extracts (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A) indicated an accelerated H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> stress that was potentially induced by the extracts of HR. Phenolic compounds caused oxidative damage in peanut seedlings and increased the contents of catalase (CAT) and peroxidase (POD) in leaves compared with the control, which is mutually confirmed by this study
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. MDA is one of the lipid peroxidation products of biofilm system
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. The higher the content of MDA in the plant, the more obvious the degree of injury
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. An increased MDA content could damage the membrane system of leaves and consequently inhibit the growth of seedlings
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, compared with Ck, MDA content in leaves of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> treated with three extracts (PE, EE and NE) increased significantly (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C), and EE treatment reached the highest. In conclusion, 
 <italic>H. scandens</italic> may release allelochemicals, which may have negative effects on the ROS of 
 <italic>A. philoxeroides</italic> leaves, thus inhibiting its normal growth.
</p>
