<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">There are many studies on the chemical constituents of 
 <italic>H. scandens</italic>, more in the field of traditional Chinese medicine. Compounds β-sitosterol, carotene, apigenin, daucesterol, stigmast-3,6-dione, n-hexadecanoic, linoleic acid and stigmasterol were isolated and identified from the whole plant of 
 <italic>H. scandens</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. Compounds were obtained from the ethyl acetate fraction of methanol extract stems of 
 <italic>H. scandens</italic> and identified as cis-N-p-coumaroyltyramine, N-cis-feruloyltyramine, trans-N-p-coumaroyltyramine, Vomifoliol
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, 5 compounds were isolated from 
 <italic>H. scandens</italic> root extracts for the first time, which were dibutyl phthalate, stigmasta-3,5-diene, 2,6-Di-tert-butylphenol campesterol, and neophytadiene. And n-hexadecanoic acid exists in all three extracts. The compound “stigmasta-3,5-diene” is used in medical research and has biological activity against certain inflammatory diseases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. Some scholars utilized GC–MS to separate from Solidago Canadensis the compounds 2,6-Di-tert-butylphenol
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>, which showed certain allelopathy to the growth of the 
 <italic>Solanum melongena</italic> L. seedings
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. Compound campesterol shows various degrees of allelopathic activity on common weeds, such as red chilli and legumes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. Compound dibutyl phthalate has certain allelotoxicity to tobacco seedlings and the growth of Microcystis aeruginosa
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
