<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although not the best-known medicinal mushrooms, the 
 <italic>Pleurotus</italic> species also have proven biological and effects. Several studies have been carried out to assess their antioxidative, antimicrobial, antidiabetic, anticancer, anti-inflammatory, immunomodulatory, antihypercholesterolemic, antihypertensive, antimicrobial, hepatoprotective, and antiaging properties, although the mechanisms underlying these effects have often not been elucidated, nor have the metabolites responsible been identified or characterized. The immunomodulatory and antitumor activities of 
 <italic>Pleurotus ostreatus</italic> (Jacq.) P. Kumm. were reported by Sarangi et al. [
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] by assaying, in vitro and in vivo, the effect of water-soluble proteoglycan fractions extracted from 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>ostreatus</italic>, or oyster mushroom, on a sarcoma-180-bearing mouse model. Treatment with the mushroom resulted in a quantitative reduction of tumor cells and their arrest in the pre-G0/G1 phase of the cell cycle, increased cytotoxicity of NK cells, and the stimulation of macrophages to produce nitric oxide. In a study by Jedinak and Sliva [
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] comparing the impact of different medicinal mushrooms on the growth of breast and colon cancer cells, 
 <italic>P</italic>. 
 <italic>ostreatus</italic> (PO) proved to be the most effective, suppressing cell proliferation via the p53-dependent and p53-independent pathways. More specifically, the methanolic extract of the mushroom induced the suppression of the proliferation of the human breast cancer cell lines MDA-MB-231 and MCF-7 and colon cancer cell lines HCT-116 and HT-29, and caused cell cycle arrest in the G0/G1 phase in MCF-7 and HT-29 cells. Furthermore, in MCF-7 cells, it induced the expression of the tumor suppressor p53 and the cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p21(Cip1/Waf1) and inhibited phosphorylation of the retinoblastoma protein Rb; the upregulation of p21 expression and inhibition of Rb phosphorylation was also observed in HT-29. A few years later, Jedinak et al. [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-22-00634" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] demonstrated the anti-inflammatory properties of PO by testing a mushroom concentrate in vitro on the RAW264.7 murine macrophage cell line and murine splenocytes, in the absence or presence of lipopolysaccharide (LPS) or concanavalin A (ConA), and in vivo on Balb/c mice with LPS-induced inflammation. PO suppressed the LPS-induced secretion of TNF-α, IL-6, and IL-12 from macrophages and inhibited the LPS-induced production of prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) and nitric oxide (NO) through, respectively, the downregulation of the expression of COX-2 and iNOS, the suppression of the LPS-dependent activation of AP-1 and NF-κB, the suppression of the secretion of TNF-α and IL-6 in mice challenged with LPS in vivo, and the inhibition of ConA-induced splenocyte proliferation and the production of IFN-γ, IL-2, and IL-6.
</p>
