<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Common carp (
 <italic class="italic">Cyprinus carpio</italic>) juveniles (9.7 ± 0.1 g), the diet of which was supplemented with SeNPs (0.7 mg Se/kg), showed the highest weight gain of 97.2 ± 10.8% and feed efficiency ratio 42.4 ± 0.8%, the highest serum hemolytic activity, total immunoglobulin, and total protein and Alb contents as well as the lowest serum total cholesterol and LDL levels after 8 weeks of feeding compared to the carp fed with Na
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>SeO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, Se-Met, and the control. Carps fed with SeNPs or Se-Met showed also pronouncedly higher activities of serum glutathione peroxidase (GPx) and SOD and an increase in white blood cell counts, neutrophil percentage, and serum lysozyme activity compared to the control group and the Na
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>SeO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> group [
 <xref rid="B265-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">265</xref>]. Dietary treatments of crucian carp, 
 <italic class="italic">Carassius auratus gibelio</italic>, with SeNPs and Se-Met showed higher Se levels in muscle (16.42 ± 1.07 μg/g and 13.52 ± 1.31 μg/g, respectively) compared to carps fed with basal feed (6.10 ± 0.78 μg/g). Although the survival rate and the feed conversion ratio were not affected by the dietary treatments, GPx activities in Se-treated carp plasma and liver differed significantly from those of the control [
 <xref rid="B266-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">266</xref>]. Dietary SeNPs supplementation at the dose of 0.68 mg/kg to juvenile mahseer (
 <italic class="italic">Tor putitora</italic>) considerably increased red blood cell count, hemoglobin level, hematocrit values, and lysozyme activity as well as serum GH levels, tissue total protein content, and GPx activity in liver and muscle tissues of 
 <italic class="italic">T. putitora</italic> [
 <xref rid="B267-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">267</xref>]. Chinese mitten crabs (
 <italic class="italic">Eriocheir sinensis</italic>) fed with a diet containing 0.2 mg/kg SeNPs in a 60 d feeding trial had a considerably higher weight gain rate and a reduced feed coefficient. When juvenile Chinese mitten crabs were kept under the condition of hypoxia, the up-regulative effects of SeNPs on antioxidant capacity, hemocyte counts, and hemocyanin expression were further amplified. Hypoxia exposure increasing mortality in crabs infected with 
 <italic class="italic">A. hydrophila</italic> bacteria was also alleviated when crabs received a diet containing 0.2 mg/kg SeNPs, suggesting the importance of dietary SeNPs in regulating the immunity and disease resistance in crabs kept under hypoxia stress [
 <xref rid="B268-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">268</xref>]. Naderi et al. [
 <xref rid="B269-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">269</xref>] who investigated the impact of dietary SeNPs (1 mg/kg), vitamin E (500 mg/kg), and their combination on the humoral immune status and serum parameters of rainbow trout under high-density condition (80 kg/m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>) reported that the positive effects observed in the performance following the combine treatment may be due to vitamin E alone, because supplementation with SeNPs did not markedly affect the performance in rainbow trout under high-density conditions. In addition, the immuno-protective role of biologically synthesized dietary SeNPs applied at the dose of 1 mg/kg against multiple stressors (Pb level of 4 ppm, high temperature of 34 °C) in 
 <italic class="italic">Pangasinodon hypophthalmus</italic> was reported by Kumar et al. [
 <xref rid="B270-nanomaterials-09-00296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">270</xref>].
</p>
