<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Acute alcoholism (AAI) is a common emergency. Currently, there is a lack of preventive and therapeutic drugs with superior safety and efficacy. 
  <italic>Curcuma longa</italic>, 
  <italic>Panax ginseng</italic>, 
  <italic>Pueraria lobata</italic>, 
  <italic>Pueraria</italic> flower, and 
  <italic>Hovenia dulcis</italic> Thunb., which are the components of compound turmeric recipe (CTR), are, respectively, used in China as adjuvant therapeutic agents for AAI and alcoholic liver injury, respectively. The purpose of this research was to investigate the effect of traditional compound turmeric recipe in anti-inebriation treatment and to identify its underlying mechanisms. The mice were administered with CTR mixture, and ethanol was subsequently given to mice by gavage. The effects of CTR on the righting reflex, 24-hour survival, drunken behavior, blood ethanol concentration, and pathological changes of liver are depicted. The activities of serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and alkaline phosphatase (ALP) were detected. Besides, the activities of tumor necrosis factor-
  <italic>α</italic> (TNF-
  <italic>α</italic>), interleukin-8 (IL-8), alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH), aldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH), cytochrome P450 (P450), superoxide dismutase (SOD), and malondialdehyde (MDA) in the liver and the levels of 
  <italic>β</italic>-endorphin (
  <italic>β</italic>-EP) and leucine enkephalin (LENK) in the brain were also measured. Our results demonstrated that CTR can increase the activities of ADH, ALDH, P450, and SOD and decrease the contents of TNF-
  <italic>α</italic>, IL-8, and MDA in the liver. In addition, it can decrease the activities of ALT, AST, and ALP in serum and 
  <italic>β</italic>-EP and LENK activities in the brain. CTR showed effects on prevention of acute alcoholism, promoting wakefulness, and alleviating alcoholic liver injury, which were likely mediated by the above mechanisms.
 </p>
</abstract>
