<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Purpose:</bold> The objective of this study was to exploit a novel methotrexate (MTX)-loaded solid self-microemulsifying drug delivery system (SMEDDS) with enhanced bioavailability and photostability.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Materials and methods:</bold> The optimized liquid SMEDDS was composed of castor oil, Tween
  <sup class="sup">®</sup> 80, and Plurol
  <sup class="sup">®</sup> diisostearique at a voluminous ratio of 27:63:10. The solid SMEDDS was formulated by spray drying liquid SMEDDS with the solid carrier (calcium silicate). Particle size analyzer, scanning electron microscopy (SEM), differential scanning calorimetry (DSC), powder X-ray diffraction (PXRD), and Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy experiments characterized the physiochemical properties of the MTX-loaded solid SMEDDS. These properties include a z-average diameter of emulsion around 127 nm and the amorphous form of the solid SMEDDS. Furthermore, their solubility, dissolution, and pharmacokinetics in Sprague-Dawley rats were analyzed in comparison with the MTX powder.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Results:</bold> The final dissolution rate and required time for complete release of solid SMEDDS were 1.9-fold higher and 10 min shorter, respectively, than those of MTX powder. Pharmacokinetic analysis demonstrated 2.04- and 3.41-fold increments in AUC and Cmax, respectively in comparison to MTX powder. The AUC and C
  <sub class="sub">max</sub> were significantly increased in solid SMEDDS. Finally, the photostability studies revealed the substantially enhanced photostability of the MTX-loaded SMEDDS under the forced degradation and confirmatory conditions.
 </p>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Conclusion:</bold> This solid SMEDDS formulation could be an outstanding candidate for improving the oral bioavailability and photostability of MTX.
 </p>
</abstract>
