<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">Many clinical studies confirmed the safety of quercetin as a supplement and supported its addition to the dietary diet. This molecule was added as a supplemental ingredient to the Food and Drug Administration's Generally Recognized as Safe list (GRAS) (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Dabeek and Marra, 2019</xref>). The study of (
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Harwood, 2007</xref>) and his collaborators reviewed the genotoxic and mutagenic effects of quercetin on several animal and human models. The results confirm the safety of quercetin and the absence of 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> toxicity and carcinogenic effects. Quercetin had interesting protective effects due to its large spectrum of biological activities. This secondary metabolite limits the cardiotoxic effects of bisphenol-A (
 <xref rid="bib147" ref-type="bibr">Vanani et al., 2020</xref>) and prevents the hepatotoxicity induced by paracetamol, 5-fluorouracil, sodium fluoride, and thioacetamide in rats (
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">El Faras and Elsawaf, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Gelen et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Nabavi et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">De David et al., 2011</xref>). Moreover, this molecule is potentially effective for the treatment of chronic kidney disease due to its antioxidant, diuretic and nephroprotective activities (
 <xref rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr">Shebeko et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, quercetin exerts a significant protective action against the reproductive toxicity induced in several models (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Aziz et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">Mi et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Farombi et al., 2012</xref>). Rutin had no acute or chronic toxicity (
 <xref rid="bib160" ref-type="bibr">Wilson et al., 1947</xref>). Indeed, this molecule was reported to assess many protective effects on several vital organs. It had protective effects against CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-induced hepatotoxicity, nephrotoxicity, and reproductive toxicity due to its antioxidant and antidyslipidemic activities (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Elsawy et al., 2019</xref>). The pretreatment with rutin significantly attenuated pirarubicin-induced cardiotoxicity in rats (
 <xref rid="bib155" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>), blood toxicity and fluoride-induced oxidative stress-mediated cardiotoxicity (
 <xref rid="bib143" ref-type="bibr">Umarani et al., 2015</xref>). Jahan and his collaborators (2018), reported that the cotreatment with rutin ameliorates the infertility of animals and reduces testicular toxicity signs (
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Jahan et al., 2018</xref>). Also, rutin was reported to attenuate intestinal toxicity induced by methotrexate due to its significant anti-inflammatory, antioxidant and antiulcer properties (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Gautam et al., 2016</xref>). Quercetin and rutin had cardioprotective effects in ischemia-reperfusion-induced myocardial infarction in both normal and diabetic rats (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Annapurna et al., 2009</xref>). Rutin had many kidney protective activities tested in several models including oxonate-induced hyperuricemia and potassium bromate-induced nephrotoxicity and possess protective effects on lung tissue in cases of acute lung injury by the prevention of polymorphonuclear granulocytes infiltration in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid and the reduction of the inflammatory response (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Ganeshpurkar et al., 2017</xref>). Myricetin was found to be non-toxic in several 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> models (
 <xref rid="bib127" ref-type="bibr">Semwal et al., 2016</xref>). This molecule had a protective effect against tert-butylhydroperoxide (t-BHP) induced oxidative stress in human erythrocytes (
 <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">Pandey et al., 2009</xref>) and possessed antigenotoxic and hepatoprotective properties against pyrogallol-induced toxicity in mice (
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Matić et al., 2013</xref>). The pretreatment with myricetin notably reduced the cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity in mice (
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Hassan et al., 2017</xref>). Myricetin protects cardiomyocytes against inflammatory injury and possesses cardioprotective, anti-hypertensive, antihyperglycemic, and antihyperlipidemic effects (
 <xref rid="bib119" ref-type="bibr">Qiu et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib137" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2019a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib138" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2019b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib156" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2019</xref>). There are controversial reports regarding the safety of kaempferol. Indeed, various 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies demonstrated the genotoxic and the carcinogenic effects of kaempferol. However, it is supposed that the low oral bioavailability of kaempferol prevents it 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> toxicity (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Devi et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Calderon-Montano et al., 2011</xref>). In addition, no human or animal trials reported the potential toxicity of kaempferol (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Dabeek and Marra, 2019</xref>). However, this metabolite attenuates nephrotoxicity and prevent renal injury induced by mercuric chloride (
 <xref rid="bib150" ref-type="bibr">Vijayaprakash et al., 2013</xref>) and had significant 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> protective effects on hepatotoxicity induced by alcohol and drugs (Isoniazid and Rifampicin) (
 <xref rid="bib153" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib132" ref-type="bibr">Shih et al., 2013</xref>). Kaempferol derivatives like kaempferol-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-rutinoside and kaempferol-3-
 <italic>O</italic>-glucoside possess hepatoprotective effects against CCl
 <sub>4</sub>-induced oxidative liver damage (
 <xref rid="bib154" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015b</xref>). Several 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies documented the cardioprotective effects of kaempferol (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Dabeek and Marra, 2019</xref>). Furthermore, kaempferol protects pancreatic beta cells from 2-deoxy-
 <italic>D</italic>-ribose-induced oxidative damage through the attenuation of lipid peroxidation inducing the decrease of type II diabetes progression (
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2010</xref>).
</p>
