<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Larrea tridentata,</italic> depicted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-24-01786-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref> is a plant species whose extracts could be used as an antioxidant for biodiesel. It belongs to the Zygophyllales order and the Zygophillaceae family. It is a green bush of medium height with leaflets of 15 × 8 mm and has brightly yellow-colored solitary flowers of up to 2.5 cm in diameter that bear oval white velvety fruits. 
 <italic class="italic">L. tridentata</italic> is located in the arid zones of northern Mexico and the southern U.S., at an altitude of up to 1800 m above mean sea level. Its most noted characteristics are its resistance to desiccation and intense odor, along with its ability to displace other species by aggressive competition and a nearly complete absence of natural enemies. It has been commonly named creosote bush and gobernadora in Spanish, due to its abundance in desert areas, mainly in Baja California, Mexico [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Preceding studies have proven the antimicrobial and antioxidant properties, as well as many applications in Native American medicine [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] of 
 <italic class="italic">L. tridentata</italic>. Just as in other species from the same genus, the presence of diverse compounds such as lignans, flavonoids and terpenes has been found [
 <xref rid="B28-molecules-24-01786" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>].
</p>
