<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this review, we systematically went through the chemical composition and biological activities of halophytic grasses up to now. The identification of 300 compounds was summarized and present; among them, several chemical families were revealed (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-20-01067" class="xref">Table S1</xref>). Nonetheless, research on halophytes from Poaceae is still in its infancy and needs to be supplemented with further investigation on chemical composition, since only 14% of the diversity of the 
 <italic class="italic">taxa</italic> was studied regarding this aspect. Moreover, the available information regarding some of the studied species is still scarce. This is evidenced by the different degree of compounds identified among the 
 <italic class="italic">taxa</italic> so far, but also in the number of chemical classes described. For instance, in 
 <italic class="italic">B. dactyloides</italic>, only cinnamic, benzoic and other short chain carboxylic acids and derivatives were described. Similarly, in 
 <italic class="italic">H. mucratom</italic>, only fatty acids and derivatives were reported and in 
 <italic class="italic">S. pyramidalis</italic> solely carbohydrates. 
 <italic class="italic">C. dactylon</italic> is the only species with far more detailed characterization of its chemical composition (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-01067-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>) with 11 chemical families reported. In addition, from a chemical point of view, most of the studies lack a structural identification by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR). Even with scarce studies, it is evident that halophytic grasses exhibit a wide range of chemical families, as well as a great diversity of compounds (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-20-01067" class="xref">Table S1</xref>), some of them being recognized for their biological activities with importance in pharmaceutical and nutritional areas. Nonetheless, only in-depth work on the phytochemical profile using modern chromatographic techniques such as high-performance liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (HPLC-MS) and gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) as well as the isolation and characterization of the compounds will allow further speculation on their application in pharmaceutical and/or agrifood industry. Another important aspect considering the potential application of halophytic grasses in the food industry is the solvent used in the extraction process. For instance, carbon tetrachloride was used in the extraction of 
 <italic class="italic">S. spontaneum</italic> and although in high yield, this solvent is considered highly carcinogenic leading to the formation of DNA adducts due to lipid peroxidation products formed during its metabolism [
 <xref rid="B222-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">222</xref>]. Furthermore, it is also considered an environmental hazard since it contributes to the destruction of the ozone layer [
 <xref rid="B223-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">223</xref>]. In food and pharmaceutical processing, only non-toxic solvents should be taken into consideration [
 <xref rid="B224-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">224</xref>]; therefore, carbon tetrachloride has been banned in several countries, especially for use in consumable products [
 <xref rid="B225-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">225</xref>]. It is also important to note that some of the reported compounds can be of fungal origin. Plant-associated microorganisms such as fungal endophytes are well described in grasses [
 <xref rid="B226-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">226</xref>] and play important roles in the enhancement of salt stress resistance among halophytic species [
 <xref rid="B227-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">227</xref>]. For instance, the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Epichloe</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Neotyphodium</italic> are well reported in the Poaceae [
 <xref rid="B228-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">228</xref>] and several studies have associated the production of biological active compounds to these fungi [
 <xref rid="B227-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">227</xref>] such as the case of ergot and lindole alkaloids and indole-diterpenes [
 <xref rid="B229-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">229</xref>]. This is a point that needs to be taken into consideration while studying the chemical composition of halophytic grasses. For instance, 
 <italic class="italic">C. dactylon</italic> present ergonovine (
 <bold class="bold">262</bold>) and ergonovinine (
 <bold class="bold">263</bold>) [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-20-01067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>], two ergot alkaloids that might be produced by endophyte fungi association with this host.
</p>
