<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">It is very important to study the change in the amount of essential oil of medicinal plants because it is related to the change in their nutritional, medicinal, and antioxidant properties. Scientists believed that the chemical composition of essential oil and production of secondary metabolites are related to the physiology of the plant, developmental stage, plant species, and various treatments such as various light sources (Yu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2005</xref>; Fernandes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2013</xref>; Mashkani et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2018</xref>). Content and composition of plant’s essential oil are influenced by many factors, including environmental conditions (Fernandes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2013</xref>; İzgı et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2017</xref>), light period, light intensity (Shafiee-Hajiabad et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2016</xref>), and light spectrum (Li and Kubota 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2009</xref>). The light spectrum acts a significant function in controlling morphology, growth processes, and photosynthesis activities in plants (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2016</xref>). Besides, most plant species can promote acclimation systems to cope with different lights, including changing their content of essential oil, which could be one of the mechanisms that plants respond to stress (Zhang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2003</xref>). Ivanitskikh and Tarakanov (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2014</xref>) stated that changes in the light spectrum can be utilized for the biosynthesis of material in plants including essential oils. The light intensity can also alter essential oil production by the stimulation of photo-sensitive enzymes required for the mevalonic acid pathway. Thus, irradiance can directly affect the generation of essential oils, or indirectly, through the increase in plant biomass (Pegoraro et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2010</xref>). Increasing the number of leaves and trichomes (Fernandes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2013</xref>), the effect of light on the expression of genes affecting essential oil synthesis (Urbonavičiūtė et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2008</xref>), and increasing the number of intermediates involved in essential oil biosynthesis such as IPP (Selmar and Kirinwächter 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2013</xref>) are some other mechanisms that show the role of natural light in increasing essential oils. Recently, there is a global trend in arid regions of the world including Iran to use greenhouses and indoor facilities instead of the field for growing medicinal species due to the shortage in irrigation water (Mesgaran and Azadi, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2018</xref>). In these conditions, LEDs can be used as a supplementary light or sole source of light for boosting photosynthesis and increasing metabolites accumulation. As Darko et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2014</xref>) stated, LED lights can mimic the effects of natural light, and therefore, it is not unreasonable to expect that LED lights can also increase these compounds by mechanisms similar to what is interpreted about the effect of natural light on increasing the amount of essential oils in plants.
</p>
