<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0051">PAKs belong to mammalian kinases family also known as RAC/CDC42-activated kinases that have been came into existence since decades. Amid, these classes PAK1 is most prominent category of "pathogenic kinases" that can cause a plethora of diseases like cancer, inflammation, malaria, dengue, immuno-suppression and many antiviral diseases, if behave abnormally (
 <xref rid="bib0144" ref-type="bibr">Maruta, 2020</xref>). Strikingly, PAK1-blockers (naturally existing) such as caffeic acid, its esters, bee-product propolis have been observed to inhibit RAC that directly activates PAK1 (
 <xref rid="bib0251" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2005</xref>). However, previous studies reported that chloroquine a drug active against malaria also suppressed the incidence of SARS/Coronavirus infection, but its mode of action still remains unknown (Vinecent, 2005). Later, it was reported that this drug induced CDK inhibitor (p21) to inhibit PAK1 activity (
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">Maruta, 2014</xref>). In line of forging argument, a recent study depicted that tumor-repressed phosphatase PTEN, mainly involved in impeding PAK1 also inhibited the coronavirus-curbed LLC2-linked fibrosis (
 <xref rid="bib0128" ref-type="bibr">Lu, 2020</xref>). Moreover, LLC2 expression has been observed to correlate with ACE2, a coronavirus receptor and CK2/RAS-PAK1-AP1 signaling cascade (
 <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2010</xref>). Henceforth, through all these assumptions we can deduce the PAK1-reliance of corona pathogenesis and a suggestion of using PAK1-blockers for treating pandemic COVID-19 outbreak (
 <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> ). Albeit, PAK-1 have a direct link with suppressing the immune system of the hosts, yet, PAK-1 blockers behave as antiviral vaccines in elevating the immune responses (
 <xref rid="bib0087" ref-type="bibr">Huynh et al., 2017</xref>). Peeping into the previous studies, it was found that rabies vaccine developed in 1885 was active against myriad of viral diseases but it usually took 12-18 months for actual resistance development. Apparently, a fast-track approach of therapeutics in the form of natural PAK-1 blockers are predominantly making its position nowadays to act against prevailing viral diseases like coronavirus.
</p>
