<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some endophytic bacteria can enhance the resistance of host plants to abiotic stresses, such as heavy metals and salinity (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Sheng et al., 2011</xref>). Salinity primarily inhibits the growth of plants by lowering soil osmotic potential, forcing the plant to lower its own water potential in an effort to obtain and conserve water. Host plant survival under such conditions may be enhanced by mechanisms such as phytohormone modulation that alleviate osmotic stress impacts (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Hasanuzzaman et al., 2014</xref>). One experiment demonstrated that the presence of 
 <italic>Achromobacter xylosoxidans</italic> reduced ethylene levels in 
 <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> and increased the content of antioxidant enzymes such as ascorbate peroxidase, catalase, and superoxide dismutase under saline conditions (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Karthikeyan et al., 2012</xref>). Moreover, endophytic bacteria stimulated the growth of plants through increasing the nutrient absorption capacity of rhizosphere and enhancing photosynthesis. In a study of 
 <italic>Cicer arietinum</italic>, inoculation with 
 <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> facilitated the synthesis of photosynthetic pigments and enhanced the plants’ contents of calcium, magnesium, nitrogen, and potassium (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Abd_Allah et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <italic>Silene vulgaris</italic> with 
 <italic>P. helmanticensis</italic> H16, 
 <italic>Proteus vulgaris</italic> H7, or 
 <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. H15 treatment had higher fresh shoot biomass under Cd and Zn stress than controls (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Płociniczak et al., 2019</xref>). These mechanisms of abiotic stress tolerance are through production of antibiotics, enzymatic and non-enzymatic antioxidants, and phytohormones (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Khare et al., 2018</xref>). Future studies are needed on the interactions among the environment, host plants, and endophytic bacteria, particularly on mechanisms by which endophytic bacteria help their hosts resist environmental stress.
</p>
