<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plants in xenobiotics-contaminated soil naturally recruit endophytes possessing essential genes to degrade the contaminants (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">Siciliano et al., 2001</xref>). In fact, the genes for degradation of nitro-aromatic compounds were found more prevalent in endophytic strains in the fields with nitro-aromatic contaminations than in rhizospheric or soil microbial communities (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Ryan et al., 2008</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Barac et al. (2004)</xref> described an application of bacterial endophytes possessing substantial biotechnological potentials, who demonstrated that engineered 
 <italic>Burkholderia cepacia</italic> G4 increased plant tolerance toward toluene and decreased the transpiration of toluene to atmosphere (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Barac et al., 2004</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Newman and Reynolds (2005)</xref> summarized the potential advantages of applying endophytic microorganisms for improving xenobiotic remediation, the major of which is the required genetic engineering of a xenobiotic degradation pathway, while gene manipulation is more easily accomplished in bacteria than in plants (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Newman and Reynolds, 2005</xref>). Moreover, quantitative expression of pollutant catabolic genes in the endophytic populations could serve as a valuable monitoring tool to assess the efficiency of the process of remediation. The unique niche of interior plant environment provides xenobiotic-degradation strains with larger sizes of population attributed to reduced competition. Furthermore, toxic xenobiotics taken up by plants might be degraded in the planta, thereby reducing phytotoxic effects and preventing potential toxicity on herbivorous fauna residing near or on the contaminated sites. Understanding relevant mechanisms that enable the interactions between these endophytic bacteria and the host plants is essential for fully achievement of their biotechnological potentials for various applications. One of the promising areas of future research is to develop endophytic bacteria that enhance the sustainable production of biomass and bioenergy crops as well as soil contaminant phytoremediation.
</p>
