<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Currently, there is a growing interest in the use of medicinal plants as a group of natural substances that could be a good source for managing of disorders. Considerable attention has been invested in the positive effects of natural medication on alleviating stress-related neuropsychiatric disorders, such as depressive disorders (
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>). The Lamiaceae family is among the largest and most distinctive families of flowering plants. It has about 220 genera and almost 4000 species worldwide (
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>). Labiatae are best known for the essential oils of many family members. 
 <italic class="italic">Origanum vulgare L.</italic> “Oregano” as an aromatic plant is rich in phenolic compounds with therapeutic actions widely distributed throughout Asia, including Iran. Oregano is the herb widely used in cooking and natural medicine. It has applied for the treatment of respiratory and hypoglycemic diseases and microorganisms inhibition (
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>). Previous studies have shown that oregano oil contains thymol, γ-terpinene, carvacrol, cis-terpinene, p-cymene, linalool, terpinen-4-ol, and sabinene hydrate as the main components (
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>). It has been reported that thymol exhibit significant anti-anxiety activity in rat (
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>). Moreover, in the plus maze test, anxiolytic effects are presented by carvacrol (5-isopropyl-2-methylphenol) (
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>), which is one of the major components of the essential oil of oregano (
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>).
</p>
