<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Free radicals and ROS are produced by physiological and biochemical processes in the human body [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. A number of chemically reactive radicals, i.e., superoxide, hydroxyl radicals, and H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, are derived from oxygen during ROS generation [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It is well documented that overproduction of such free radicals can cause serious damage to biomolecules such as DNA, RNA, proteins, and lipids, which leads to pathogenic conditions to human [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. ROS play the most important character in the pathogenesis of diverse physiological conditions, such as cellular damage, neurodegenerative, diabetes, hepatic, and cardiovascular diseases [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Endogenous antioxidant enzymes, e.g., glutathione peroxidase, superoxide dismutase, and catalase are accomplished of neutralizing free radicals, and hence, sustaining optimum cellular activities [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Nonetheless, under high ROS production and oxidative stress, these endogenous antioxidant enzymes may not be adequate to maintain optimum cellular activities. Thus, the dietary antioxidants may be essential. Natural products or plants have always been used to treat and cure various diseases since ages [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Plants produced various secondary metabolites, for example alkaloids, terpenoids, flavonoids, and vitamins, that take part in the neutralization of free radicals and delay chronic ailments caused by ROS and oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Natural antioxidants from plant materials play a vigorous part in the production against the action of free radicals [
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Numerous studies have shown that consumption of plant seeds and leaves with strong antioxidant potential and are capable to lower the causation of different chronic diseases like cancer [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. 
 <italic>Anethum graveolens</italic> (family: Apiaceae) is known for medicinal and therapeutic purposes since long in the conventional system of medicine [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. graveolens</italic> has been described for its biological potential and pharmacological potential, e.g., antioxidant [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], anti-inflammatory [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], antidiabetic [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], antimicrobial [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and anticancer [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] activities. Ethanolic and acetonic extracts of 
 <italic>A. graveolens</italic> flowers and leaf [
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and essential oil of 
 <italic>A. graveolens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] have been shown to possess high antioxidant activities. Cancer is the abnormal growth of cells which forms a tumor. These cells are different than normal cells and are not accountable for normal growth controlling mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The cytotoxic/antiproliferative potential of plants and plant-derived components can be measured by different cytotoxic endpoints, such as MTT, neutral red uptake, and cellular morphological analyses, using various cancer cell lines [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The available treatment for cancer is chemotherapy and radiotherapy, but the main disadvantage of current drugs is their side effects [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Plants encompass rich number of effective constituents with less toxicity [
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Thus, nowadays, the attempts are being made to search an anticancer agent from plant origin which can prevent and reverse the development of cancer [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Hence, this study was aimed at investigating the antioxidant and anticancer efficacies of 
 <italic>A. graveolens</italic> (AG-ME) against different human cancer cells (MCF-7, A-549, and HeLa).
</p>
