<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7445301</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">70889</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-70889-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impregnation of pectin-cedarwood essential oil nanocapsules onto mini cotton bag improves larvicidal performances</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>Smriti</given-names></name><address><email>smritikl16@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sogan</surname><given-names>Nisha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>Amrish</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Jitendra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.482456.9</institution-id><institution>Formulation Division, </institution><institution>Institute of Pesticide Formulation Technology (IPFT) (Ministry of Chemicals and Fertilizers, Government of India), </institution></institution-wrap>Gurugram, Haryana 122016 India </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417967.a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0558 8755</institution-id><institution>Center for Rural Development Technology (CRDT), </institution><institution>Indian Institute of Technology (IIT) Delhi, </institution></institution-wrap>Delhi, 110016 India </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419641.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9285 6594</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Malaria Research (NIMR), </institution></institution-wrap>Delhi, 110077 India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>14107</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The use pesticide is one of the indispensable means to combat mosquito borne diseases. However, the repeated use of synthetic pesticides has induced resistance in the vector pest along with undesirable impact on the environment. The biodegradability, non-persistent and user&#x02019;s safety are the root cause to prefer plant-derived pesticides to synthetic ones. The botanical based pesticides tend to degrade rapidly under the influence of several environmental factors. For the feasible application as pesticides, the plant products are formulated either as liquid or as purely solid. Despite well-established formulation technology in pesticide delivery, their handling trouble is being ignored. There is difficulty in liquid formulation of pesticide products, as they are prone to splashing and spillage, resulting in contamination, wastage and direct exposure to skin; whereas a solid formulation tends to produce dust. In the present work, cedarwood (<italic>Cedrus deodara</italic>) essential oil embedded pectin nanocapsules were produced. The nanocapsules were characterized according to their morphology, size, encapsulation efficiency and thermal stability. Furthermore, the nanocapsules were impregnated onto mini cotton tea bags to be employed as RTU (ready to use) formulation for treating the breeding sites of mosquitoes. The larvicidal activity of the bags treated with pectin-cedar wood nanocapsules was assessed against malaria vector, <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic> and 98% mortality was recorded till 4&#x000a0;weeks, this suggests its potential and hassle free applications in controlling mosquito vector.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Nanobiotechnology</kwd><kwd>Techniques and instrumentation</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Global health threats, primarily due to mosquito borne diseases can devastate communities in social and economic terms and hinder development progress<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Among the various vector borne diseases, malaria is the major public health issue, which transmits through the bite of <italic>Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. According to the World Health Organization (WHO) 2019 report, malaria causes 228 million morbidity cases and 405,000 number of mortality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic> is alone accountable for 60&#x02013;65% of the malaria burden<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. A Mosquito-borne disease remains a challenge since there is no vaccine, and further drug resistance is an increasing threat. Under these circumstances, vector control plays a vital role and often remains the only way to prevent disease outbreaks.</p><p id="Par3">The control of malaria vector, <italic>Anopheles,</italic> relies upon indoor residual spray (IRS) and insecticide treated nets (ITN)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Several other control tools have also been proposed including; nano pesticides, microbial pesticides (that are natural occurring bacteria, fungi and viruses) and pesticides of plant origin, which may act as repellents, oviposition deterrents and larvicides etc.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. A new generation biotechnological tool in mosquito control program, based on genetically modified mosquitoes and sterile Insect Technique (SIT) is also being considered<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Despite significant progress so far, further investigations are needed to determine if genetically modification based strategies can be an effective method of mosquito control. These facts point out that the use of pesticides may be probable approach to be considered for the reasonable mosquito targeting.</p><p id="Par4">The tackling of the mosquito at the immature stage has been considered more convenient, since the insect is most vulnerable. Moreover, the pesticide application is on selected and defined area, therefore, the contamination and wastage due to pesticide applications could be minimized. In the current scenario the synthetic pesticides are extensively used to control larval stages, which is resulting in resistance development, persistence and toxicity to non-target. In this context, plant derived pesticides may preferred on account of their non-persistent and biodegradability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The recent advancements have extensively focused on plants based bio-pesticides as an efficient larvicide against <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic>. In particular few of botanical pesticides, such as Neem (<italic>Azadirachta indica</italic>) oil, bio-waste of Cashew nut (<italic>Anacardium occidentale</italic>), leaf and seed extracts of castor (<italic>Ricinus communis)</italic>, Paracress <italic>(Spilanthes acmella), Yellow berry night shade (Solanum xanthocarpum), Clove (Syzygium aromaticum</italic>)<italic>,</italic> Shisham <italic>(Dalbergia sissoo</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> have shown significant larvicidal activity . Although the use of plant-derived botanical pesticides (essential oil and crude plant extract) has occupied key space in pest management yet the application of botanicals is limited due to poor water solubility and further feasibility of the plant-based product is not assured because of volatility, degradation, and stability. Consequently, the potential use of plant material in large-scale applications is not considered as realistic. To overcome these drawbacks bioactive plant products may be formulated; using polymers, plasticizers, stabilizers and biodegradable additives<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The additives in formulating a plant product may include; polymers, emulsifying agents, surfactants, solvents, stabilizers, de-foamers which ensure the stability, adherence and controlled release of the bioactive compounds, depending on the type of formulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Himalayan Cedar (<italic>Cedrus deodara</italic>) is large evergreen coniferous tree, found abundantly grown throughout the western Himalayas regions of India. The essential oil of cedar wood (CWO) has been reported to possess insecticidal activities against stored pests, houseflies and lepidopteran insects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The extraction method is one of prime factors that determine the quality of essential oil since; inappropriate extraction procedure can lead to the damage or alter the constituents of essential oil. Extraction of essential oils can be carried out by various means, as solvent extraction, supercritical extraction and steam distillation. In the present study steam distilled oil was used. Although steam distillation (SD) is the most popular one due to low-cost and easy operation, it would be beneficial to conduct investigation on, the effect of extraction technique on the phyto-constituents of essential oil. The promising results obtained in the preliminary examination with the steam distilled essential oil of cedar wood; against the larva of <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic> has encouraged us to use it further.</p><p id="Par7">In recent years, there has been an increased interest in nanotechnology as a means of improving the effectiveness of pesticide, while at the same time minimizing their environmental impacts. Several studies have described the use of nanostructure systems that offer better efficacy as a mosquito larvicide. Some of the most promising nanostructured systems that can be used as larvicides are based on polymeric encapsulation, followed by nanoemulsions and nanogels, etc. Nanoemulsions that can be formulated within the droplet size range of 20&#x02013;200 nm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>, and, nanogel that are hydrogel particles in the nanometer range, loaded with <italic>Lippia sidoides</italic> oil has been described as an efficient mosquito larvicide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Among all the nanostructure systems, nanoencapsulation is one of the well-documented strategies, which can contribute towards sustainable vector management program. It has attracted attention due to the potential for assisting in reduced doses of pesticides while at the same time improving stability and offering controlled release along with decreased water contamination, and less risk to the consumers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Pectin is an inexpensive, non-toxic polysaccharide extracted from citrus peels or apple pomaces, and has been used as a food additive, a thickening agent and gelling agent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Pectin is also used as an encapsulating agent leading to release of encapsulated material at the desired site<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">While earlier studies have shown the potential of nano bio-pesticides in different connections, however, the studies describing the convenient way of application by which, pesticides are delivered to their biological targets have not exemplified. Since, the most of the larvicidal products described are liquid based; nano/micro- emulsions and encapsulated suspensions, etc. (Supplementary Fig <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The liquid formulation of pesticide products may affect the extent of exposure, as they are prone to splashing and occasional spillage, resulting in direct skin contact or indirect contact through clothing contamination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Moreover, the solid formulation tends to produce dust. In the recent years, there has been considerable interest in developing biodegradable, easy to use and effective pesticide delivery systems.</p><p id="Par9">The above evidence provides the rationale behind this study that aimed to devise a technique to get the better of liquid preparation, through the concept of the nanocapsules impregnated mini bag. The impregnation of cotton fabric with the nanocapsules and microcapsules has been reported for long-lasting mosquito repellent and antibacterial effects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. However, such an approach may certainly be used to larvicidal control program on account of its sustainability. Cotton is made up of cellulose and, therefore, it is easily biodegradable. The cotton based tea bags, therefore, can be used to impregnate pectin-cedar wood nanocapsules.</p><p id="Par10">The study is intended to hypothesize the comparative evaluation on the long-lasting larvicidal efficacy of CWO nanocapsules impregnated bags with that of non-encapsulated bags. The study, therefore, explores a new approach for a safe way of pesticide application, employing botanical and nanoparticles. Here, we present a report describing, design and synthesis of nanocapsules impregnated bag to target immature stages of mosquitoes (illustration-Supplementary Fig <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Further, we also described long lasting efficacy of nano-encapsulted bag against mosquito larvae. The cured tea bags, impregnated with pectin-cedarwood nanocapsules, could be a RTU (ready to use) formulation to treat mosquito-breeding sites. Such an approach can be effortless and may provide long lasting effects. The nanocapsules impregnated bags may be preferred on account of their safety with respect to reduced direct exposure to the pesticides along with convenience in handling and prolonged effectiveness. This reduces application of pesticides to the target, which may cut costs of the active ingredient used for spray applications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Composition of CWO oil&#x02014;GC&#x02013;MS</title><p id="Par11">A total of 49 compounds from the cedarwood essential oil were identified, which accounted for 100% of its total composition. The GC&#x02013;MS identified several main chemical compounds in the CWO. The peak area correlated to concentration and was greater for &#x003b2;-himachlene (19.8%-RT-retention time 30.7) followed by &#x003b1;-himachlene (15.38%-RT 28.5), Atlantone (14.0%-RT 41.0), Longifolene (7.4%-RT 29.6), Deodarone (4.63%-RT 38). The other compounds detected as an average percentage included; several other sesquiterpenes and monoterpenes. The gas chromatogram of CWO oil is presented in Supplementary Fig <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref> and composition percentage of major and average constituents along with RT is given in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The <italic>Cedrus deodara</italic> is generally rich in sesquiterpenes-himachalene, which was observed as the most abundant constituent of cedar wood essential oil. The results of our findings are in agreement with the previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> where, similar trends in oil composition of <italic>Cedrus</italic> were reported. However, variation in abundance of constituents was observed in the essential oil, which may differ according to the part of the plant used for the oil extraction and varies according to the geographical zones, the harvest period and the age of the plant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Plants synthesize several secondary metabolites as bio-actives including terpenes and terpenoids. The essential oils of <italic>Cedrus deodara</italic> from the present investigation is therefore identified as a complex mixture of hydrocarbon terpenes and terpenoids, the majority of the first group consists of monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes, and the second group may consists of oxygenated derivatives of hydrocarbon terpenes i.e. terpenoids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Terpenoids are responsible for notable bioactivity properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and furthermore, the insecticidal activity of essential oils is reported probably due to terpenes and terpenoids content present in the oil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. The major identified constituents sesquiterpenes i.e. &#x003b2;-himachalene and &#x003b1;-himachalene, present in oil were reported to possess insecticidal activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. From the above discussion, it may be deduced that the larvicidal activities of CWO essential oil can be because of the high concentrations of himachalene present in the oil, however, the observed larvicidal activity may also be attributed to the synergy between various components of essential oil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Therefore, the phyoto-constituents analysis briefs about the probable compounds responsible for larvicidal efficacy.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Constituents of cedar wood essential oil identified by GC&#x02013;MS.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">S/N</th><th align="left">Compound identified</th><th align="left">RT</th><th align="left">Mol.Wt</th><th align="left">Composition (%)</th><th align="left">S/N</th><th align="left">Compound identified</th><th align="left">RT</th><th align="left">Mol.Wt</th><th align="left">Composition (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="9"><bold>Major components</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x00391;lpha Himachalene</td><td align="left">28.5</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">15.38</td><td char="." align="char">26</td><td align="left">Bergamotene</td><td align="left">27.8</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left"><p>Longifolene</p><p>- (V4)</p></td><td align="left">29.6</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">7.4</td><td char="." align="char">27</td><td align="left">Cadina-1,4-Diene</td><td align="left">28.02</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Beta Himachalene</td><td align="left">30.7</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">19.88</td><td char="." align="char">28</td><td align="left">Geranyl-.Alpha.-Terpinene</td><td align="left">28.7</td><td char="." align="char">272</td><td char="." align="char">0.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">Deodarone</td><td align="left">38</td><td char="." align="char">236</td><td char="." align="char">4.63</td><td char="." align="char">29</td><td align="left">8 Cedren-13-Ol Acetate</td><td align="left">29.08</td><td char="." align="char">262</td><td char="." align="char">0.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Atlantone Trans-, Alpha</td><td align="left">41</td><td char="." align="char">218</td><td char="." align="char">14.0</td><td char="." align="char">30</td><td align="left">Beta Chamigrene</td><td align="left">29.2</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left" colspan="9"><bold>Average components</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Himachelene 1,4 Diene</td><td align="left">29.7</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">1.74</td><td char="." align="char">31</td><td align="left">AmorphaneCis 4,10 epoxy</td><td align="left">29.9</td><td char="." align="char">222</td><td char="." align="char">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">Neoisolongifolene, 8,9-Dehydro-</td><td align="left">31.5</td><td char="." align="char">202</td><td char="." align="char">1.36</td><td char="." align="char">32</td><td align="left">Alpha Ylangene</td><td align="left">30.2</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">Himachalene Oxide</td><td align="left">34.7</td><td char="." align="char">220</td><td char="." align="char">1.43</td><td char="." align="char">33</td><td align="left">Alpha DehydroHimachalene</td><td align="left">30.9</td><td char="." align="char">200</td><td char="." align="char">0.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">Himachalol</td><td align="left">36.3</td><td char="." align="char">222</td><td char="." align="char">1.59</td><td char="." align="char">34</td><td align="left">Isolongifolen, 4,5-Dehydro-</td><td align="left">31.1</td><td char="." align="char">202</td><td char="." align="char">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">Dihydroatlantone</td><td align="left">37</td><td char="." align="char">220</td><td char="." align="char">2.41</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td align="left">Ar-Himachalene</td><td align="left">31.7</td><td char="." align="char">202</td><td char="." align="char">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">(Z)-Gamma-Atlantone</td><td align="left">37.7</td><td char="." align="char">218</td><td char="." align="char">5.08</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td align="left">Bisabolene (Z)-, Alpha-</td><td align="left">32.1</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">1.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">(E)-Gamma-Atlantone</td><td align="left">38.2</td><td char="." align="char">218</td><td char="." align="char">5.39</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td align="left">Spathulenol</td><td align="left">32.7</td><td char="." align="char">220</td><td char="." align="char">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">Atlantone&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;(Z)-Alpha-&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;</td><td align="left">38.7</td><td char="." align="char">218</td><td char="." align="char">3.44</td><td char="." align="char">38</td><td align="left">Cis-Nerolidol</td><td align="left">33</td><td char="." align="char">222</td><td char="." align="char">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">Thujopsan-2-Alpha-Ol</td><td align="left">36.8</td><td char="." align="char">222</td><td char="." align="char">1.24</td><td char="." align="char">39</td><td align="left">OxidoHimachalene</td><td align="left">33.2</td><td char="." align="char">218</td><td char="." align="char">0.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">Alpha-Pinene</td><td align="left">6.5</td><td char="." align="char">136</td><td char="." align="char">0.06</td><td char="." align="char">40</td><td align="left">1H-Inden-1-One, 3a,4,5,6,7,7a-Hexahydro-4,4,7a-Trimethyl-</td><td align="left">33.5</td><td char="." align="char">178</td><td char="." align="char">0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Limona Ketone</td><td align="left">14.6</td><td char="." align="char">138</td><td char="." align="char">1.34</td><td char="." align="char">41</td><td align="left">Juniperol</td><td align="left">34.3</td><td char="." align="char">222</td><td char="." align="char">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">Terpeniol</td><td align="left">17.7</td><td char="." align="char">154</td><td char="." align="char">0.03</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td align="left">Caryophyllene Oxide</td><td align="left">35</td><td char="." align="char">220</td><td char="." align="char">1.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">Alpha Longipinene</td><td align="left">24.1</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.14</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td align="left">Alpha-Bisabolol</td><td align="left">35.4</td><td char="." align="char">222</td><td char="." align="char">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">2-Ethyl-3,4-Dimethyl-5-Phenyl-1,2-Oxaborolane</td><td align="left">25.7</td><td char="." align="char">202</td><td char="." align="char">0.56</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td align="left">Bergamotene Alpha-, Cis-</td><td align="left">35.5</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">Sibirene</td><td align="left">26.4</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.16</td><td char="." align="char">45</td><td align="left">Thujopsanone 3-Iso</td><td align="left">35.7</td><td char="." align="char">220</td><td char="." align="char">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">Longifolene</td><td align="left">26.5</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.90</td><td char="." align="char">46</td><td align="left">Alpha.-Ylangene</td><td align="left">36.1</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">Vestitenone</td><td align="left">26.7</td><td char="." align="char">178</td><td char="." align="char">0.37</td><td char="." align="char">47</td><td align="left">Bisabolene</td><td align="left">36.5</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">Himachala 2-Diene</td><td align="left">27.3</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.86</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td align="left">Acorenol Beta</td><td align="left">39.1</td><td char="." align="char">222</td><td char="." align="char">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">4,5-Dehydro-Isolongifolene</td><td align="left">27.4</td><td char="." align="char">202</td><td char="." align="char">0.12</td><td char="." align="char">49</td><td align="left">Dihydroatlantone (E)</td><td align="left">41.5</td><td char="." align="char">220</td><td char="." align="char">0.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">Alpha.-Ylangene</td><td align="left">27.6</td><td char="." align="char">204</td><td char="." align="char">0.20</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>S/N</italic> serial number; <italic>RT</italic> retention time; <italic>Mol.wt</italic> molecular weight.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Preparation and encapsulation efficiency of pectin-CWO nanocapsules</title><p id="Par12">Essential oils are highly effective as pesticide, but inherent volatile and degradable nature limits their applicability. Nanoencapsulation, which involves coating of active within a polymer, can be a favorable approach to prevent the volatility of essential oil and increase their efficacy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Several studies attempted to formulate effective pesticide using the nanoencapsulation technique; the nanoencapsulation of essential oils of thyme and dill with copper nanoparticles improved antifungal activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, essential oil from&#x000a0;<italic>Zanthoxylum rhoifolium</italic>&#x000a0;leaves encapsulated in PCL (polycaprolactone) against <italic>B. tabaci</italic>&#x000a0;showed that nanoencapsulation is an effective protector of the active-ingredient<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Moreover, the enhanced efficacy of garlic essential oil as a pesticide, loaded in PEG nanocapsules was described as compared to free garlic oil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. However, the utilization of natural polysaccharides such as chitosan, sodium alginate, starch, pectin, etc. has become more popular due to their non-toxic, biodegradable and biocompatible properties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Pectin is safe and an environment friendly polymer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> as a pesticide carrier, therefore, the use of the pectin to load cedarwood essential oil, is acceptable. The CWO nanocapsules were produced via ionic gelation method. Ionic gelation involves the interactions of an ionic polymer with oppositely charged ion to produce hydrogel beads also called as gelispheres, which are spherical cross-linked hydrophilic polymeric entity capable of swelling in water and the release of active is controlled by the polymer relaxation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Pectin forms electrostatically stabilised gel networks i.e. gelispheres with divalent metal cations, usually calcium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. The addition of cedar wood oil in pectin solution, during the emulsification process followed by addition of CaCl<sub>2</sub> at constant mixing produced pectin nanocapsules containing cedarwood oil.</p><p id="Par13">The percent encapsulation efficiency (EE %) i.e. the amount of CWO enclosed into the pectin matrix was determined by the UV&#x02013;Visible spectrophotometry. The average encapsulation efficiency of 60% was obtained under the optimized conditions and concentration (polymer solution with 1% w/v pectin, cross-linker with 0.5 w/v CaCl2). Since, the encapsulation improves the stability of an essential oil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, the obtained value of EE represents an attracting value from the industrial point of view. High encapsulation efficiencies of 87.6&#x02013;90.6% for sunflower oil encapsulated by ionic gelation using pectin have been previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The encapsulation efficiency may vary and affected by many factors such as, the nature of the oil, polymer concentration and oil polymer ratio, stirring speed, etc<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Together, the obtained results and evidences from prior literature, confirmed that the use of pectin for nano-encapsulation can be helpful in enhancing efficacy of bioactive by volatility reduction and also controlled targeted delivery of bioactive<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, which was further proved from the long-lasting residual effects as observed in larvicidal bioassay.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Size and morphology</title><p id="Par14">Size of the nanocapsules in raw state was observed by Transmission electron microscope (TEM). The TEM image of non-encapsulated emulsion shows the droplets with out any wall coating (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). However, TEM images of the pectin nanocapsules loaded with CWO demonstrate regular distribution and spherical shape with size distributed between the ranges of 40 and 80&#x000a0;nm (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The in-depth morphology of the outer surface of the nanocapsule was perceived which shows the clear presence of the encapsulating-carrier agents having smooth surfaces without any cracks or pores. Since, the essential oils are inherently volatile in nature and the absence of cracks or pores on the surface may signify that the oil-volatiles is protected against degradation and volatility, this is in agreement with the result published by Ali et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>TEM micrographs of (<bold>A</bold>) non-encapsulated cedarwood; (<bold>B</bold>) encapsulated: CWO-loaded pectin nanocapsules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Fourier transform-infrared (FT-IR) spectroscopy</title><p id="Par15">The FTIR spectra of pectin, blank pectin nanoparticles, CWO loaded pectin nanoparticles, and CWO is presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. The pectin shows one of the characteristic peaks at 1741 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which refers to the CH stretching of carboxyl groups (COOH) and another peak at 1542cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> attributed to amide group II was observed which is also supported by previous findings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In pectin nanoparticles, the new peak introduces at 1632&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1,453&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1,334&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, this might be probably due to intermolecular interaction, which is due to complex formation by electrostatic interaction between pectin and divalent metal cation calcium chloride, the statement is in agreement with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. FTIR spectra of CWO showed quite similar general features, with most of the peaks characteristic of oil as reported by Shen et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Peaks at 1,375 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 1455&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> are attributed to the methyl, methylene and CH stretch from CWO terpenes. The peaks at 1617&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> due to C=C stretching, and 2,915 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> due to CH<sub>2</sub> symmetrical and asymmetrical stretching. After loading of CWO in pectin nanoparticles, in addition to the characteristic peaks of pectin nanoparticles, the peaks of CWO also appear thereby indicating no modification occurs after loading of oil. This change led to an assumption that CWO might be present into the pectin nanoparticles and molecular compatibility between the CWO constituents&#x02019; and pectin nanoparticles could exist.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>FTIR spectra of (1) pectin powder (2) Blank pectin nanocapsules (3) CWO loaded nanocapsules (4) CWO.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Thermal properties (DSC)</title><p id="Par16">DSC aids in providing in depth information about the thermal behavior of various materials, such as melting and crystallization performances<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. When a molecule interacts with the polymer its melting, boiling or sublimation point generally shifts to a different temperature or disappears within the range<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. DSC (differential scanning colorimeter) thermograms of pectin, blank pectin nanoparticles, and CWO loaded pectin nanoparticles are presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. The DSC thermogram of the pectin powder showed a broad endothermic peak at 79&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C which is ascribed to its glass transition temperature and second peak at 158&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C corresponding to its melting point, this is in accordance with previous literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. A broad peak at 122&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C was observed in pectin cross-linked with CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The shifting of the peak at high temperature in cross-linked matrices of pectin revealed high thermal stability compared to their individual components, the statement is in agreement to the previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. After the loading of cedarwood oil in pectin nanocapsule, the peak further shifts to higher temperature at 131&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. DSC results obtained here indicated that the CWO was stable in pectin nanocapsules, which was produced by crosslinking with CaCl<sub>2</sub>. The comparable result was reported previously by Chattopadhyay et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, who used DSC tool to study the compatibility between the polymer, active and other components of the formulations. In both the cases, the shift towards higher temperature was observed in the thermogram of the polymer loaded with active content. Furthermore the thermal stability of nanocapsules at 131&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C after loading with CWO oil points out that the bags can be cured at 100&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the statement is consistent with the previous reports published by Liu et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>DSC thermograms of (1) pectin powder (2) blank pectin nanocapsules (3) CWO loaded nanocapsules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Coating of capsules on tea bag</title><p id="Par17">The mechanism of adhesion of the pectin nanocapsules on the cotton bag surface in the presence of acrylate may be attributed to surface modification of cotton fibers, illustrated in a supplementary figure (Supplementary Fig <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). During curing the process at 100&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, there might be an interaction between &#x02013;OH group of cellulose (Cell-OH) and &#x02013;COOH group of acrylate, which may lead to formation of ester linkage. The statement is according to previous reports <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. The ester linkage might be responsible for deposition of pectin -CWO nanocapsules on cotton-bag fibers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Surface morphology of coated bags</title><p id="Par18">The surface morphology of the bag impregnated with nanocapsules was investigated by SEM. The comparative SEM images of bags before and after impregnation with nanocapsules are presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. The untreated bag (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a) shows blank fibers, whereas, the impregnated bag shows clear presence of nanocapsules onto cotton fibers (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). In addition, the nanocapsules were fixed in the spacing of fibers this may be because of the esterification reaction occurred between acrylate and cellulose during the curing process. The SEM result indicates that the capsules were successfully impregnated on the fibers of bags. A previous study also suggested that the successful impregnation of nanocapsules onto cotton fabric can be carried out using polymeric binder or resin and further its confirmation by SEM imaging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Surface morphology of (<bold>A</bold>) blank bag (<bold>B</bold>) bag impregnated with CWO loaded nanocapsules.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Residual larvicidal assay</title><p id="Par19">The results of larvicidal bioassay are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. In the larvicidal bioassay; the larvae treated with the encapsulated bag initially exhibited lower larval mortality, which was recorded at 70% (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The reason for initial lower mortality may be due to slow release of oil contents as owned by pectin nanocapsules. Generally, the release of active from swellable polysaccharides like pectin occurs by either single or by a combination of three different mechanisms: an osmotically driven force, a diffusion mechanism, or erosion or degradation of the polymer. Here in this case the release from pectin nanocapsules probably governed by a diffusion mechanism which includes several phases; penetration of water into the capsule, resulting in swelling of the matrix followed by conversion of the polymer into a rubbery swollen matrix, resulting in release of the active from the swollen matrix, the statement is supported by previous literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. The initial low mortality rate may be attributed to the ascribed slow release mechanism involving diffusion. However, after complete swelling is achieved, the pectin nanocapsules shows burst release, which is justified by increased release of CWO components resulting in increased mortality rate and 90% reduction in larval population up to 2&#x000a0;weeks followed by 98% mortality up to the fourth week. The results may be attributed to the successful encapsulation and the impregnation of CWO nanocapsules on the fiber of the bag, which offered slow release. Contrast to this the bag coated with free emulsion (non encapsulated), there was a constant decline in mortality rate after 2&#x000a0;weeks, which may be due to the free oil that got completely released from the bag initially. However, no mortality was observed in control (distilled water&#x02009;+&#x02009;surfactants). The difference in bioassay of the encapsulated bag and non-encapsulated bag may be because of the thermodegradation and volatility of bioactives of CWO, which may be responsible for losses of oil components in non-encapsulated bag. However, the losses due to the similar factors seem to be prevented by encapsulation process in the encapsulated bag. It has been stated previously that essential oils are volatile and sensitive to environmental factors, nanoencapsulation may prevent their degradation and volatility<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>, hence the long-term efficacy was attained up to 4&#x000a0;weeks with 98% mortality rate may be attributed to nanoencapsulation. There have been evidences indicating the nanoencapsulation process-enhancing efficacies of essential oils<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref></sup>. Oregano&#x000a0;essential oil loaded-chitosan nanoparticles produced thermally stable nanocapsules that showed more effectiveness against fungus <italic>Alternaria alternate</italic> which causes great damages to the post-harvest crops<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup> and zein (corn protein) nanoparticles&#x000a0;loaded with neem oil was found more effective and safe to the non-target organisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>. Our findings are corroborated by these previous literatures. Further, the results point out that the nanocapsules impregnated bags may be suitable to achieve long-term effect for targeting the breeding sites of mosquitoes.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparative efficacy of encapsulated bag and non-encapsulated bag formulation showing percentage mortality with residual effect on <italic>Anopheles </italic>(&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD standard deviation).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Days</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Nano encapsulated</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Free oil ( non-encapsulted)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Mean No. of dead larva (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th align="left">Reduction in larval population (%)</th><th align="left">Mean No. of dead larva (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th align="left">Reduction in larval population (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td char="." align="char">14.00 b</td><td char="." align="char">70.00 b</td><td char="." align="char">19.33 a</td><td char="." align="char">96.67 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char">15.33 b</td><td char="." align="char">76.67 b</td><td char="." align="char">19.67 a</td><td char="." align="char">98.33 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td char="." align="char">18.00 a</td><td char="." align="char">90.00 a</td><td char="." align="char">16.67 b</td><td char="." align="char">83.33 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td char="." align="char">19.33 a</td><td char="." align="char">96.67 a</td><td char="." align="char">9.67 c</td><td char="." align="char">48.33 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">21</td><td char="." align="char">19.33 a</td><td char="." align="char">96.67 a</td><td char="." align="char">8.33 c</td><td char="." align="char">41.67 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left">28</td><td char="." align="char">19.67 a</td><td char="." align="char">98.33 a</td><td char="." align="char">2.33 d</td><td char="." align="char">21.67 d</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values (means of 3 replicates). Means (&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD) followed by the same letters (a&#x02013;d) within columns indicate no significant difference (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) from each other in a (Duncan&#x02019;s multi-range test).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Histopathological alterations in larva tissues</title><p id="Par20">Histopathological alterations in the midgut of larva post exposure to bioactive contribute to a better understanding in the possible mode of action of particular bio-pesticide against a larva<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. Since, the midgut is composed of muscle (M), Adipose tissue (AT) and epidermal cells. (EC). EC is responsible for the production of enzymes and cuticular oxidation process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup> and have several diverse functions, such as ionic and osmotic regulation, lipid and carbohydrate storage, midgut lumen pH control, digestive enzyme secretion and nutrient absorption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. The 4th instar larvae of <italic>An. culicifacies</italic> exposed to nano-CWO showed severe morphological deformities. CWO-nanocapsules directly acted upon, muscle (M), Adipose tissue (AT) and epidermal cells (EC) and displayed completely damaged epithelial cell, muscles and adipose tissue (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). In contrast, LS examination of the control larval tissues displayed intact and undamaged assembly of epithelial cell, muscles and adipose tissue (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). The results are in accordance with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. The toxicity of the plant essential oil (EO) as an insecticide mainly depends on penetration rate of EO into the insect body, their interaction with specific target enzymes and the detoxification ability of the mosquito at each developmental stage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. In the present study, the 4th instar larvae <italic>of An. culicifacies</italic> exposed to nano-CWO showed severe morphological deformities. Some earlier researchers have also reported the morphological aberrations induced by nano based botanical pesticide on mosquito larvae<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup>. The comparatively severe damage occurred in the larval midgut cells treated with nano-CWO may attributed to the remarkable feature of nanoparticles; larger surface and smaller size, which can promote easy penetration into the larval body and disturb their normal cycle of life by interrupting the intake of feed, cell division and breathing, the statement is supported by previous literature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Cytomorphology of midgut of larva (<bold>A</bold>) Control (<bold>B</bold>) CWO nanocapsules, magnification 40&#x000d7;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Chemicals and materials</title><p id="Par21">Pectin (30,000&#x02013;10,0000&#x000a0;MW) and Calcium chloride were purchased from SRL chemicals, India. Tween80 and Span 20 were purchased from SDFCL India. Cedar wood essential oil and Cotton tea bags were purchased from local supplier. Acrylate (Thickener/Binder aqueous emulsion of acrylic polymer) obtained from Lamberti, Italy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Methodology</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Chemical composition of cedarwood oil-(GC&#x02013;MS)</title><p id="Par22">The major components of cedar wood essential oil were identified through GC&#x02013;MS (Shimadzu QP 2010 74707 Plus) equipped with an FID and capillary column (0.32&#x000a0;mm i.d., length: 30&#x000a0;m, film thickness 0.25&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m). Injection volume was 1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l, oven temperature was programmed with 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (hold time 5&#x000a0;min), which was increased at the rate of 10&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C/min to 300&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C (hold time 5&#x000a0;min). Injection temperature was 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, with a split ratio of 10. The chemical constituents of oil were identified using GC&#x02013;MS by comparing the individual mass spectra with the database of National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST12 or NIST62-) libraries.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Preparation and encapsulation efficiency of CWO loaded pectin-nanocapsule</title><p id="Par23">Pectin nanoparticle was prepared via ionic gelation method using calcium chloride as cross-linker, a method described previously with slight modification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Briefly, 1% solution of pectin was prepared, Tween 80 (5): Span80 (2) was added to the solution and was stirred in magnetic stirrer at 1500&#x000a0;ppm. While stirring cedar wood oil was poured to the solution and it was further stirred for 10&#x000a0;min. Finally 0.5% w/v added drop-wise as a cross-linker.</p><p id="Par24">The total content of encapsulated cedarwood essential oil (CWO) was determined spectrophotometrically according to previously described method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Briefly, a fixed weight of microcapsules (200&#x000a0;mg) was taken and diluted with ethanol. The mixture of ethanol and sonicated for 15&#x000a0;min to allow complete breakage of nanocapsules followed by centrifugation for 5&#x000a0;min. The supernatant was collected and the total amount of encapsulated cedarwood essential oil was determined by UV&#x02013;Vis spectrophotometer at a wavelength of 326&#x000a0;nm using a Labomed UVD 2960 spectrophotometer. For standard curve several dilutions of oil was prepared and curve was constituted. The trend line was obtained by linear regression with standard equation (<italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;18.75<italic>X</italic>&#x000a0; &#x02212; 0.0019) and&#x000a0;<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;value (0.99852). The amount of CEO was calculated by appropriate calibration curve of free CEO in ethanol (R<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.999). The encapsulation efficiency of cedarwood essential oil into pectin&#x02010;nanocapsules was calculated by using the following equation.<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$EE \left(\%\right)=\frac{\left(WT-WS\right)\times 100 }{\left(WT\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>(where WT&#x02009;=&#x02009;the total amount of cedarwood used in the encapsulation, WS&#x02009;=&#x02009;and the remaining cedarwood essential oil in the supernatant after centrifugation).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Characterization of nanoparticle</title><p id="Par26">The size distribution of the nanocapsules was measured and observed by TEM (Jeol 1011, Japan) at a magnification of 100000&#x000d7;.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR)</title><p id="Par27">FTIR analyses for pure pectin, pure CWO and pectin nanoparticles (loaded or unloaded with CWO) were recorded from wave number 500&#x02013;4000&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> by FTIR spectrometer (Burker Tensor 37, Germany) using ATR transmittance mode. Sixteen scans were obtained at a resolution of 4&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Thermal properties</title><p id="Par28">The physicochemical compatibility between the cedar wood essential oil and encapsulated polymer were evaluated by DSC analysis. The DSC thermograms (DSC Satarum, France) obtained for oil, encapsulated oil and pectin powder. Samples were heated at a temperature range between 50 and 250&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C at a heating rate of 10&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Coating of capsules on mini bag</title><p id="Par29">Cotton tea bag procured from local supplier (specifications as; fine and lightweight bleached 100%plain-weave 135&#x000a0;g/m<sup>2</sup>, 80 ends per inch &#x000d7; 78 picks per inch) was used for coating. The tea bag was treated according to previously described method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. The bag was immersed in nanoencapsulated suspension containing (0.01% W/v) acrylate as binder agent. The mixture containing immersed bags was heated at 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h. The bags, dried at 50&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min and cured at 120&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min. Similar concentration (10%) of control and nonencapsulated samples was used to treat bags which was used as reference.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Surface morphology of coated bag</title><p id="Par30">To study the morphology of bags, SEM imaging was performed. A part of treated bag was mounted on aluminum stubs using a conductive carbon tape and gold palladium sputtered for a conductive coating. A SEM Tescan Vega 3, Czech Republic, was used at 20&#x000a0;kV accelerating voltage to image the surface of the bag. Untreated bag was also imaged for reference.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Collection and maintenance of <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic></title><p id="Par31">The Laboratory reared larvae of <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic> were obtained from National Institute of Malaria Research (NIMR), Insectary Delhi. The larvae were maintained in the standard condition of 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and humidity 85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5% kept in tap water in an enamel bowl. Larvae were fed on mixture of dog biscuit and yeast powder in the (3:1) ratio.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Dose response bioassays on <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic></title><p id="Par32">The comparative larvicidal bioefficacy of coated bag 1(Nanoencapsulated cedarwood in pectin) and bag 2 (Cedar wood nonencapsulated) was evaluated against 3rd instar larvae of <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic> following WHO standard larval susceptibility test method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. The coated bags were introduced in water (250&#x000a0;mL). Larvae (20 individual) were released into each test container containing. A set up containing water, Tween 80:Span 20 (4:1) served as control. Each experiment was carried out in three replications. The number of deceased larva was counted in the exposed population during the exposure period of 24&#x000a0;h. Corrected mortality was calculated using formulae (WHO 2009).<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$Mortality \left(\%\right)=\frac{\left(X-Y\right)\times 100 }{\left(100-Y\right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mfenced></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>(where <italic>X</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;Percentage mortality in treated sample, <italic>Y</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;Percentage mortality in control sample).</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Histopathology alterations in larva induced by CWO nanocapsules</title><p id="Par34">To study the mode of action of cedar wood nanoencapsulated on larva, the treated dead larva of Anopheles was studied through histopathology. The mortal larvae was removed from the treated solution and stored in buffered formalin reagent (pH 7.2). The larva was dehydrated by passing through graded ethanol series and embedded in paraffin wax<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. A thin longitudinal section (LS) of the larva stained with Hematoxylin and Eosin (Hi-Media labs) was cut using microtome (Leica, Germany) and mounted on glass slide. The LS of the midgut region were examined under an Upright Olympus microscope. A setup containing tween, span and water served as control was also performed for reference.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par35">The results of mortality calculated here are means of three replicates. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed on the data and means were compared using Duncan&#x02019;s multi- range test with SPSS 10.0 software. The significance level was p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par36">The pectin-based nanocapsules loaded with cedar wood essential oil was developed and characterized. The nanocapsules were impregnated on to mini cotton bag producing ready to use (RTU) formulation to treat mosquito-breeding sites. An important feature of the nanocapsules impregnated bag in larvicidal control program is greater effectiveness with long lasting efficacy and comparative simplicity to the existing control methods. The devised technique may contribute in minimizing risk of dustiness and contamination as the bag can be directly placed in mosquito breeding sites. Moreover, the incorporation of botanical pesticide in the nanocapsules may have added advantages of dose reduction, associated risks due to synthetic pesticides and the long-lasting residual effect. The promising results obtained in the larvicidal bioassays provides basis for the future research under realistic field conditions. Therefore, the technique devised in this work could potentially to be used as an effective larvicide in the mosquito management program, which may contribute towards sustainable vector control strategies and combating against mosquito-borne diseases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec26"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_70889_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary file1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p> is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41598-020-70889-z.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This article does not utilize any fund from any of the external sources/Agencies/Organizations.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>S.K. designed experiments, performed experimental work, wrote manuscript. N.S. performed larvicidal bioassays experiments. S.N.N. provided guidance and support in experimental studies. A.A. provided guidance in formulation development. J.K. provided guidance in experimental studies.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All the relevant data are provided in this paper and in Supporting Information files.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par37">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations Development Programme (UNDP). A Socio-Economic Impact Assessment of the Zika Virus in Latin America and The Caribbean. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/hiv-aids/a-socio-economic-impact-assessment-of-the-zika-virus-in-latin-am.html">https://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/hiv-aids/a-socio-economic-impact-assessment-of-the-zika-virus-in-latin-am.html</ext-link>. Assessed 11 Nov 2109 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarwar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defeating malaria with preventative treatment of disease and deterrent measures against anopheline vectors (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>RRJPTS</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>4</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. World Malaria Report 2019. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/feature-stories/detail/world-malaria-report-2019">https://www.who.int/news-room/feature-stories/detail/world-malaria-report-2019</ext-link>. Assessed 3 Mar 2020 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal activity of the extracts extracts from different parts of the plant <italic>Solanum xanthocarpum</italic> against important mosquito vectors in the arid region</article-title><source>J. Environ. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20121022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20121022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization.<italic> Guideline for Malaria Vector Control.</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/malaria/policy-guidance/vector-control">https://www.who.int/malaria/policy-guidance/vector-control</ext-link>. Assessed 28 Feb 2020 (2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furnival-Adams</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Indoor use of attractive toxic sugar bait in combination with long-lasting insecticidal net against pyrethroid-resistant <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>: An experimental hut trial in Mb&#x000e9;, central C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-019-3095-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31910831?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31910831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benellia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current vector control challenges in the fight against malaria</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>2017</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2017.06.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28684267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Das</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A synergistic transcriptional regulation of olfactory genes drives blood-feeding associated complex behavioral responses in the mosquito <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic></article-title><source>Front. Physiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>577</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2018.00577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29875685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biopesticides: Formulations and delivery techniques</article-title><source>Nat. Remed. Pest Dis. Weed Control</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-819304-4.00018-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Patanjali</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sogan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neem oil water dispersible tablet as effective larvicide, ovicide and oviposition deterrent against <italic>Anopheles culicifacies</italic></article-title><source>S. Afr. J. Bot.</source><year>2019</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2019.03.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kala</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nanoemulsion of cashew nut shell liquid bio-waste as a potential larvicide in mosquito management: Insights on possible mode of action</article-title><source>S. Afr. J. Bot.</source><year>2019</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sajb.2019.10.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sogan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal activity of <italic>Ricinus commmunis</italic> extract against mosquitoes</article-title><source>J. Vec. Borne Dis.</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>4</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavela</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant extracts for developing mosquito larvicides: From laboratory to the feild, with insights on the modes of action</article-title><source>Act. Trop.</source><year>2019</year><volume>193</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2019.01.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal and repellent actions of <italic>Dalbergia sissoo</italic> Roxb. (<italic>F. leguminosae</italic>) oil against mosquitoes</article-title><source>Biores. Technol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-8524(99)00180-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formulation of botanicals for the control of plant&#x02013;pathogens: A review</article-title><source>Crop Prot.</source><year>2018</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cropro.2018.04.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent developments of safer formulations of agrochemicals</article-title><source>Environmentalist</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10669-007-9045-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tewary</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and larvicidal activities of the Himalayan cedar, <italic>Cedrus deodara</italic> essential oil and its fractions against the diamondback moth, <italic>Plutella xylostella</italic></article-title><source>J. Insect Sci.</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1673/031.011.15701</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22239128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22239128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of nanoencapsulation on volatile constituents, and antioxidant and anticancer activities of Algerian <italic>Origanum glandulosum</italic> Desf essential oil</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2812</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-59686-w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 32071359?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32071359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anna</surname><given-names>EMF</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Essential oil from&#x000a0;Pterodon emarginatus&#x000a0;as a promising natural raw material for larvicidal nanoemulsions against a tropical disease vector </article-title><source>Sustain. Chem Pharm.</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scp.2017.06.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundararajan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Moola</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>BDR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formulation of nanoemulsion from leaves essential oil of <italic>Ocimum basilicum</italic> L. and its antibacterial, antioxidant and larvicidal activities (<italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic>)</article-title><source>Microb. Pathog.</source><year>2018</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.10.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30340015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30340015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fl&#x000e1;via</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan/cashew gum nanogels for essential oil encapsulation</article-title><source>Carbohyd. Polym.</source><year>2012</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>1282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.04.048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson do</surname><given-names>ESP</given-names></name><name><surname>Halley</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardo</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymeric nanoparticles as an alternative for application of gibberellic acid in sustainable agriculture: A field study</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>7135</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-43494-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31073210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavanke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review on ionotropic gelation method: Novel approach for controlled gastroretentive gelispheres</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm. Pharm. Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonassen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Treves</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kj&#x000f8;niksen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smistad</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiorth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of ionically cross-linked pectin nanoparticles in the presence of chlorides of divalent and monovalent cations. dx</article-title><source>Biomacromol</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3523</fpage><lpage>3531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bm4008474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christos</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Eleftherohorinos</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pesticide exposure, safety issues, and risk assessment indicators</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source><year>2011</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>20</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smriti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan-acrylate nanogel for durable anti mosquito finishing of cotton fabric and its dermal toxicity profiling on Swiss albino mice</article-title><source>Coll. Surf. B</source><year>2019</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colsurfb.2019.06.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotresh</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Csiszar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of antimicrobial cotton fabrics using herb loaded nanoparticles</article-title><source>Carb. Pol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.08.064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ainane</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Khammour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Charaf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elabboubi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkouali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Benhima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherroud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ainane chemical composition and insecticidal activity of five essential oils: <italic>Cedrus atlantica</italic>, <italic>Citrus limonum</italic>, <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic>, <italic>Syzygium aromaticum</italic> and <italic>Eucalyptus globules</italic></article-title><source>Mater Today Proc.</source><year>2019</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>474</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matpr.2019.04.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouquillon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauconnier</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Encapsulation of essential oils for the development of biosourced pesticides with controlled release: A review</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2539</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24142539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Br&#x000fc;gger</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bioactivity of the <italic>Cymbopogon citratus </italic>(poaceae) essential oil and its terpenoid constituents on the predatory bug, <italic>Podisus nigrispinus</italic> (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae)</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>8358</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-44709-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31175321?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31175321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal activity of eucalyptus oil nanoemulsion with karanja and jatropha aqueous filtrates</article-title><source>Int. Biodeter. Biodegr.</source><year>2014</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibiod.2013.11.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mosquito larvicidal activity of the essential oils of erechtites species growing wild in Vietnam</article-title><source>Insects</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/insects10020047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osanloo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nano-encapsulated tarragon (<italic>Artemisia dracunculus</italic>) essential oil as a sustained release nano-larvicide</article-title><source>J. Contemp. Med. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weisany</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of the antifungal activity of thyme and dill essential oils against <italic>Colletotrichum nymphaeae</italic> by nano-encapsulation with copper NPs</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2019</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.02.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christofoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal effect of nanoencapsulated essential oils from <italic>Zanthoxylum rhoifolium</italic> (Rutaceae) in <italic>Bemisia tabaci</italic> populations</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><issue>70</issue><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural characterization of nanoparticles loaded with garlic essential oil and their insecticidal activity against <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> (Herbst) (Coleoptera: Tenebrionidae)</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>57</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>10156</fpage><lpage>10162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf9023118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19835357?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19835357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nuruzzaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Naidu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanoencapsulation, nano-guard for pesticides: A new window for safe application</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food Chem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>64</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1447</fpage><lpage>1483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.5b05214</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26730488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26730488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morri</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amil K&#x000f6;k</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polysaccharide drug delivery systems based on pectin and chitosan</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Genet. Eng. Rev.</source><year>2010</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02648725.2010.10648153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21415901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwivedy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Encapsulation in chitosan-based nanomatrix as an efficient green technology to boost the antimicrobial, antioxidant and in situ efficacy of <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> essential oil</article-title><source>Int. Bio. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.04.070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protein adsorption onto alginate-pectin microparticles and films produced by ionic gelation</article-title><source>J. Food Eng.</source><year>2015</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfoodeng.2014.12.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chitosan microspheres as a potential carrier for drugs</article-title><source>Int. J. Pharm.</source><year>2004</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2003.12.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15072779?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15072779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pectin polymers as wall materials for the nano-encapsulation of bioactive compounds</article-title><source>Trends Food Sci. Technol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2019.05.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balik</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Argin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagaron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres-Giner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation and characterization of electrospun pectin-based films and their application in sustainable aroma barrier multilayer packaging</article-title><source>Appl. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5136</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app9235136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farahmandghavi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two-step method for encapsulation of oregano essential oil in chitosan nanoparticles: Preparation, characterization and in vitro release study</article-title><source>Carbohyd. Polym.</source><year>2013</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2013.02.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamdem</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of sugar beet lignocellulose films containing tung oil and cedarwood essential oil</article-title><source>Cellulose</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2703</fpage><lpage>2715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10570-015-0679-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formation of curcumin nanoparticles via solution-enhanced dispersion by supercritical CO<sub>2</sub></article-title><source>Int. J. Nanomed.</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>3171</fpage><lpage>3181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IJN.S80434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro&#x000a0;and&#x000a0;in vivo&#x000a0;evaluation of oxatomide&#x000a0;&#x003b2;-cyclodextrin inclusion complex</article-title><source>J. Pharm.</source><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/629593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In Situ gelling ophthalmic drug delivery system: Formulation and evaluation</article-title><source>J. Appl. Polym. Sci</source><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/app.39788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minhas</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of biodegradable hydrogels for oral delivery Of 5-fluorouracil targeted to colon: screening with preliminary in vivo studies</article-title><source>Adv. Pol. Technol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adv.21659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ultra low concentration deltamethrin loaded patch development and evaluation of its repellency against dengue vector <italic>Aedes (S) albopictus</italic></article-title><source>Parasit. Vectors</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>284</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-284</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24289656?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Study on the grafting of chitosan&#x02013;gelatin microcapsules onto cotton fabrics and its antibacterial effect</article-title><source>Coll. Surf. B</source><year>2013</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colsurfb.2013.03.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheriaa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baffoun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of cross linkers combination, for three dimensional effects, on denim garment properties</article-title><source>Fibers Polym.</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12221-015-1150-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kashyap</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan nanoparticle based delivery systems for sustainable agriculture</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2015.02.039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chouhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Guleria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of some essential oils&#x02014;present status and future perspectives</article-title><source>Medicines</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>58</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/medicines4030058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eykia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Encapsulation of <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> essential oils in chitosan&#x02013;cinnamic acid nanogel with enhanced antimicrobial activity against <italic>Aspergillus flavus</italic></article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2014</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2014.01.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashemib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Masoud</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chitosan nanoparticles loaded with <italic>Cinnamomum zeylanicum</italic> essential oil enhance the shelf life of cucumber during cold storage</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2015.08.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guerra-Rosas</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of nanoemulsions containing essential oils and high methoxyl pectin during long-term storage</article-title><source>Food Control</source><year>2017</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.02.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Electrospraying method for fabrication of essential oil loaded-chitosan nanoparticle delivery systems characterized by molecular, thermal, morphological and antifungal properties</article-title><source>Innov. Food. Emerg.</source><year>2019</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ifset.2018.12.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascoli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neem oil based nanopesticide as an environmentally-friendly formulation for applications in sustainable agriculture: An ecotoxicological perspective</article-title><source>Sci. Total Environ.</source><year>2019</year><volume>677</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2019.04.345</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31051383?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31051383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amutha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mosquito-larvicidal potential of metal and oxide nanoparticles synthesized from aqueous extract of the seagrass, <italic>Cymodocea serrulata</italic></article-title><source>J. Clust. Sci</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10876-019-01542-7.pdf</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Histology and ultrastructure of aedes albopictus larval midgut infected with <italic>Bacillus Thuringiensis</italic> Var. Israelensis</article-title><source>Microsc. Res. Tech.</source><year>2008</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jemt.20605</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18567013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18567013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Perumalsamy</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Young-Joon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity and possible mechanisms of action of honokiol from <italic>Magnolia denudata</italic> seeds against four mosquito species</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>411</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-36558-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30674912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30674912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahanta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanikor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combinations of plant essential oil based terpene compounds as larvicidal and adulticidal agent against <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>9471</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-45908-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31263222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31263222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nanoformulation of poly(ethylene glycol) polymerised organic insect repellent by PIT emulsification method and its application for Japanese encephalitis vector control</article-title><source>Colloids Surf. B</source><year>2015</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colsurfb.2015.02.034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrandiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenollar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Balart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and characterization of bioactive alginate microcapsules with cedarwood essential oil</article-title><source>Flavour Fragr. J.</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ffj.3373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization<italic>. Laboratory and Field-Testing of Mosquito larvicides</italic> (CDS/WHOPES/GCDPP/05.13). Geneva. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/whopes/resources/who_cds_whopes_gcdpp_2005.13/en/">https://www.who.int/whopes/resources/who_cds_whopes_gcdpp_2005.13/en/</ext-link>. Assessed 11 Sept 2019 (2005)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Mekhlafi</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larvicidal, ovicidal activities and histopathological alteration induced by (Apiaceae) extract against Pipiens (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Saudi. J. Bio. Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2017.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29379357</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>