<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">The other most cited plants across the country were 
 <italic>Steganotaenia araliacea</italic> Hochst., 
 <italic>Heteromorpha trifoliata</italic> (Wendl.)Eckl. &amp; Zeyh., 
 <italic>Kigelia africana</italic> (Lam.) Benth., 
 <italic>Bulbinella floribunda</italic> (Thunb.) T. Durand &amp; Schinz., 
 <italic>Solanum incanum</italic> L., 
 <italic>Pseudolachnostylis maprouneifolia</italic> Pax [Agg]. and 
 <italic>Burkea africana</italic> Hook. as indicated in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. This implies that these medicinal plant species have better use-value than the other plants cited only once in this study. The list of plants obtained and their traditional uses can be compared with what came out of other studies that concentrated on the cytotoxicity of certain medicinal plant extracts. For example, 
 <italic>Kigelia africana</italic> (Lam.) Benth.
 <bold>
  <italic>,</italic>
 </bold> highlighted by some practitioners in this study’ has been found from other studies to be useful for skin ailments (eczema, psoriasis, fungal infection, boils), diarrhoea, haemorrhoids, fever, malaria, diabetes as well as having anti-cancer properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The bioactive constituents found to be present in all the plant parts include iridoids, naphthoquinones, flavonoids, terpenes and pheneylethanoglycosides [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. The stem bark and fruit extracts were found to be cytotoxic against cancer cell lines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Another study revealed anticancer activity of the fruit extract against cervical and colorectal cancer cell lines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. 
 <italic>Hibiscus sabdariffa</italic> L. and 
 <italic>Pseudolachnostylis maprouneifolia</italic> Pax [Agg]. have been reported for their use as cytotoxic agents, among other activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. The high polyphenol content in dried leaf extract of 
 <italic>Hibiscus sabdariffa</italic> L. have been linked to its activity against leukaemia and gastric carcinoma [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Studies have also shown 
 <italic>Hibiscus sabdariffa</italic> L. leaf extract-induced apoptosis in human prostate cancer cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Other medicinal plants that have been reported for their actual or potential anti-cancer activities include 
 <italic>Hypoxis hemerocallidea</italic> Fisch.&amp;C.A.Mey [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]., 
 <italic>Sutherlandia frutescens</italic> (Lam.)R.BR [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. as well as 
 <italic>Solanum incanum</italic> L. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. 
 <italic>Hypoxis hemerocallidea</italic> Fisch.&amp;C.A.Mey.
 <italic>,</italic> also referred to as the miracle plant [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>], apart from other documented activities such as hypoglycaemic and antioxidant properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]; has been shown to have activity against cancerous and premalignant cancer cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The herbal extract of 
 <italic>Solanum incanum</italic> L. has been found to possess anticancer, antinociceptive, antipyretic, antispasmolytic, oretic, hypoglycemic and antimicrobial activities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Notable active components thought to be responsible for the anticancer activity are glycoalkaloids; which include solamargine, solasodine and solasomine. Solarmagine was found to act by inducing cancer cells apoptosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Cancer bush, 
 <italic>Sutherlandia frutescens</italic> (L.)R.Br
 <italic>,</italic> is native to South Africa and has been traditionally used in the treatment and prophylaxis of cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. An in-vitro study demonstrated a concentration-dependent inhibition of several tumour cell lines as well as antioxidant activity in reducing free radical cations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. 
 <italic>Lantana rugosa</italic> (camara) Thunb. root and leaf extracts were shown to have activity against cancer cell lines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] and the plant has been used in folklore medicine for its antipyretic, antimalarial and antimutagenic antitumor, analgesic, antimicrobial and anti-eczema properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. 
 <italic>Prunus persica</italic> (L.) Batsch. roots, bark, fruits, leaves and flowers found uses in treating haemorrhoids, diarrhoea and the common cold [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Its glycosides bioactive constituents were reported to have activity in the inhibition of tumour growth as well as chemoprevention [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Other plants highlighted by traditional medicine practitioners in the study that also had anticancer uses or activities reported in elsewhere include 
 <italic>Moringa oleifera</italic> Lam., 
 <italic>Heteromorpha trifoliata</italic> (Wendl)Eckl. &amp; Zeyh., 
 <italic>Ximenia caffra</italic> Sond., 
 <italic>Ricinus communis</italic> L., 
 <italic>Steganotaenia araliacea</italic> Hochst.
 <italic>,</italic> as shown in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Some plants were not reported for their anticancer activities in literature but were being used to treat cancer by practitioners in this study. Such plants include 
 <italic>Duranta erecta</italic> L., 
 <italic>Asparagus africanus</italic> Lam., 
 <italic>Bulbinella floribunda</italic> (Thunb.) T. Durand &amp; Schinz. and 
 <italic>Burkea africana</italic> Hook. These plants’ pharmacological significance could be due to the presence of phytoconstituents such as flavonoids, saponins, phenolics, glycosides, alkaloids and tannins in the extracts; which have been found to confer activity against cancer cells. The findings from the present study, therefore, relate to some of the plants’ uses that have been reported by other researchers as demonstrated above. This could be an indication of a strong primary health care provision offered by these TMPs using medicinal plants.
</p>
