<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the soil where neither bactericide nor fungicide was applied, 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> had a higher level of root colonization by AM fungi (58%) (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35407-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d) than 
 <italic>Coix</italic> (38%) (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35407-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). These results are counter to the notion that exotic plants are less likely than native plant species to associate with AM fungi (Bunn et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Klironomos, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Pringle et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Although invasive plants may leave behind coevolved mutualists in the native range (Kowalski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), as the density, range, and time‐since‐invasion increase, the plants may acquire novel microbial mutualists (the host‐jumping hypothesis; Shipunov, Newcombe, Raghavendra, &amp; Anderson, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Kowalski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). For instance, 
 <italic>Cyperus rotundu</italic>s that invaded the U.S. Gulf coast region harbored a fungal mutualist 
 <italic>Balansia cyperi</italic> that was native to the region (Stovall &amp; Clay, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">1988</xref>). The fungus likely jumped from a native 
 <italic>Cyperus</italic> host to 
 <italic>C. rotundus</italic> (Kowalski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Invasive plants may also reunite with native‐range mutualists through cointroductions (the cointroduction hypothesis; Shipunov et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). For instance, communities of endophytic fungi were similar between invaded and native ranges of 
 <italic>Centaurea stoebe</italic>, suggesting multiple cointroductions of different fungal species (Shipunov et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). 
 <italic>Pinus contorta</italic> coinvaded New Zealand with its ectomycorrhizal fungal communities (Dickie et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Several Australian ectomycorrhizal fungi were found in plantations of Australian 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> species in the Iberian Peninsula, further supporting the idea of cointroductions (Díez, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). In the Iberian Peninsula, the Australian 
 <italic>Acacia longifolia</italic> harbored symbiotic nitrogen‐fixing bacteria that are native to Australia (Rodríguez‐Echeverría, 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Whether 
 <italic>Mikania</italic> that has been present in China for close to 100 years (Holm et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35407-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">1977</xref>) has acquired new microbial symbionts and/or reunited with those in its native range remains an area of further study.
</p>
