<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To understand the relative influence of patch scale, management, abiotic factors, and landscape factors on assembling plant communities, we conducted principal components analyses (PCAs), variation partitioning, and redundancy analyses in R 3.0.2 (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team, 2013</xref>) using package vegan 2.2-1 (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen et al., 2015</xref>). For these analyses, we used data from all herbicide treated plots (27 total plots; 12 large scale, 15 small scale) from 2015, the year following the last herbicide treatments. We removed rare species and used a Hellinger’s transformation on our plant community data. Hellinger’s transformations on community datasets with large numbers of zeros enable the use of linear methods such as redundancy analysis (RDA) (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Legendre and Gallagher, 2001</xref>). We transformed some univariate predictor variables and response variables to best meet the assumptions of normality. We log-transformed abiotic variables phosphorus, nitrogen, average water depth (across all monitoring years), and 2015 water depth (depth during the year selected for analysis). We log-transformed landscape variables including the length of canals, length of roads, and distance to the nearest discharge. We arcsine-square-root-transformed the proportion of development, proportion of agriculture, and cover of surrounding native perennials. We square-root-transformed the distance to nearest water diversion variable. We logit-transformed the response variables 
 <italic>Phragmites</italic> cover and native perennials cover. We then reduced local abiotic and landscape disturbance variables in separate PCAs in order to reduce redundant variables and address collinearity (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Graham, 2003</xref>). For the landscape category, we excluded the proportion of surrounding emergent marsh (1 km) and percent cover of native perennials in the surrounding area from the PCA. These variables were less related to landscape disturbance and were more reflective of surrounding marsh conditions. They were included as separate variables in further analysis.
</p>
