<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">
 <italic>Akebia trifoliata</italic> (Thumb.) Koidz. subsp. 
 <italic>australis</italic> is a perennial woody plant that belongs to the genus 
 <italic>Akebia</italic> (Lardizabalaceae) and is mainly distributed in East Asia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>australis</italic> (abbreviated as 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic> hereafter) as well as 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic> subsp. 
 <italic>trifoliata</italic> and 
 <italic>A. quinata</italic>, which are two other members of the genus 
 <italic>Akebia</italic>, are listed in the Chinese Pharmacopoeia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> and have been used as traditional herbal medicines for &gt;2000 years. An example is “Akebiae Fructus”, which is made from the dry fruit of 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic>, including seeds, peel, and flesh
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Experimental and clinical studies have demonstrated that 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic> possesses anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, antioxidative, and anticancer properties
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. Lu et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> reported that the ethanol extract of 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic> seeds has antimetastatic potency against hepatocellular carcinoma cells. The pharmacological properties of 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic> are attributed to numerous bioactive compounds, including triterpenoid saponins, triterpenes, and flavonoids, in dried fruits, stems, leaves, and seeds of 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. The content of oleanane-type triterpenoids, especially oleanolic acid, is high in the dry fruit of 
 <italic>A. trifoliata</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. These natural bioactive compounds with minimal or no side effects have attracted attention from chemists and pharmacologists due to their complex structural features and multiple biological effects.
</p>
