<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Castanospermine, an alkaloid derived from black bean (
 <italic>Castanospermine australe</italic>), was investigated against all serotypes in vitro via plaque-forming assay using BHK-21 cells and in vivo using A/J mice. The compound inhibited all serotype infections in vitro at the level of secretion and infectivity, but could only inhibit DENV-2 in vivo and prevented mouse mortality [
 <xref rid="B120-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. These findings suggest that not all compounds that are active in in vitro studies would give similar outcomes in in vivo studies, more so in clinical studies. The percentage of inhibitory activity of these compounds ranged from 20–70%, with phenolics and flavonoid glycosides and derivatives exhibiting the highest activity. Many of the compounds are selective in their anti-dengue activity against different serotypes. Most of them displayed activity against DENV-2. Quercetin and quercetirin obtained from the ethyl acetate fraction of 
 <italic>H. cordata</italic> aerial leaves displayed anti-DENV-2 effects with median inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) of 176.76 µg/mL and 467.27 µg/mL, respectively, showing a bigger virucidal effect of quercetin than its glycoside, quercetirin. However, the quercetin was more cytotoxic (CC
 <sub>50</sub> = 155.38 µg/mL) than the quercetirin [
 <xref rid="B108-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. In another study, four constituents from the ethyl acetate fraction of the same plant—chlorogenic acid, hyperoside, quercetin, and quercetirin—were tested against the NGC strain of DENV-2 using the plaque reduction assay individually displayed certain degrees of activity, while their combination yielded greater antiviral effects [
 <xref rid="B109-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. The main phenolic constituents of 
 <italic>Spondias mombin</italic> and 
 <italic>Spondias tuberosa</italic>—rutin, quercetin and ellagic acid—showed antiviral effects at 500 µg/mL and inhibited viral replication by 68.42%, 50%, and 25.02%, respectively in C6/36 cells. Rutin was the most active [
 <xref rid="B85-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Among the compounds purified from the methanol extract of yellow rhizomes of 
 <italic>Boesenbergia rotunda</italic> and tested against DENV-2, four compounds exhibited anti-DENV activity. These compounds were chalcone derivatives: 4-hydroxypanduratin A, panduratin A, pinostrobin, and cardamonin. The first two compounds exhibited good competitive inhibitory activity toward DENV NS3 protease, while the last two compounds demonstrated non-competitive inhibitory activity [
 <xref rid="B37-biomolecules-11-00042" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
