<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fungal infections account for nearly 1.6 million deaths worldwide, thus presenting a huge socio-economic burden, frequently neglected by public health authorities [
 <xref rid="B1-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Most fungal infections affect mucous membranes, especially vaginal and mouth membranes [
 <xref rid="B2-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and, despite being primarily superficial, mycosis can rapidly evolve into systemic infections, especially in immunocompromised individuals. These type of infections are mainly caused by 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, nevertheless other 
 <italic>Candida</italic> species are becoming important etiological agents such as 
 <italic>C. krusei</italic>, 
 <italic>C. parapsilosis</italic> and 
 <italic>C. tropicalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B3-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Several features contribute to 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. virulence including yeast-to-hypha morphological transition and biofilm formation [
 <xref rid="B4-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The first, starts with germ tube formation that develop into hypha promoting tissue penetration and immune avoidance, thus resulting in a more effective infection. In addition, this transition is necessary for biofilm formation [
 <xref rid="B5-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These complex structures can be formed in both biological and artificial surfaces and constitute a major clinical burden due to their higher resistance to antifungal drugs [
 <xref rid="B6-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In fact, for most conventional antifungals, the minimal inhibitory concentration necessary to inhibit biofilms is 100-fold higher than the concentrations needed to inhibit planktonic cells [
 <xref rid="B7-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Fungal infections can also be caused by other yeast such as 
 <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> which affects the central nervous system and by dermatophytes of the 
 <italic>Trichophyton</italic>, 
 <italic>Microsporum</italic> and 
 <italic>Epidermophyton</italic> genera. Dermatophytes are able to colonize keratinized structures, such as hair, skin and nails. Furthermore, filamentous fungi from the 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> genus, especially 
 <italic>A. fumigatus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic> and 
 <italic>A. niger</italic>, are also important agents in the development of bloodstream systemic infections as well as pulmonary and allergic infections [
 <xref rid="B8-antibiotics-10-00592" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
