<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the flora of Uzbekistan, this genus is represented by 18 species (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00132-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Taxa of the genus 
 <italic>Lagochilus</italic> basically occur throughout the territory of Uzbekistan, starting from the deserts to Tian-Shan and Pamir-Alay mountain systems. The majority of species can be found in the Pamir-Alai Mountain, south-west of Tian-Shan and Turanian lowland [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Species from the genus 
 <italic>Lagochilus</italic> belong to the most vulnerable plant species from the Lamiaceae family. Out of the existing 18 
 <italic>Lagochilus</italic> species in the flora of Uzbekistan, four are included in the Red Book of the Republic of Uzbekistan [
 <xref rid="B14-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]: 
 <italic>L. vvedenskyi</italic>, 
 <italic>L. olgae</italic>, 
 <italic>L. proskorjakovii</italic>, and 
 <italic>L. inebrians</italic>. The main population of these species grows in Nuratau and Kyzylkum deserts. On the basis of occurrence, these Red List plant species belong to category I (disappearing) and II (rare species). In addition, the natural distribution of other species from this genus, such as 
 <italic>L. gypsaceus</italic> and 
 <italic>L. acutilobus,</italic> are also limited across the country [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In the territory of South Kazakhstan, 10 species of 
 <italic>Lagochilus</italic> were found, and the areas of these species are located in Karatau, Karzhantau, and Aksu-Zhabagly [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In the Flora of China, there are 14 
 <italic>Lagochilus</italic> species distributed wildly in the northwest region. One of the species, 
 <italic>L. ilicifolius</italic>, grows in the desert (sandy land) and steppe in northwestern China (Neimeng, Gansu, Shanxi, and Ningxia provinces), whereas the other 13 species are distributed mainly in the Xinjiang region [
 <xref rid="B3-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The Flora of Iran comprises six species, and four of them (
 <italic>L. macranthus</italic> Fisch and C.A. Mey., 
 <italic>L. quadridentatus</italic> Jamzad, 
 <italic>L. lasiocalyx</italic> (Stapf) Jamzad, and 
 <italic>L. aucheri</italic> Boiss.) are endemic to Iran [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Three species of 
 <italic>Lagochilus</italic> are found in Mongolian flora, and they are widely distributed in the Khangai, Mongolian Altai, Middle Khalkha, Depression of Great Lakes, Valley of Lakes, East Gobi, Gobi-Altai, Transaltai Gobi, Alashan Gobi regions (
 <xref rid="plants-10-00132-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B20-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-plants-10-00132" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].
</p>
