<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Minerals such as potassium, calcium, iron sodium, magnesium, phosphorus, manganese, zinc, and copper are crucial for normal body development and maintenance (Haruna et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). They help in sustaining and improving the functions of the
 <strike>,</strike> muscles, heart, and brain as well as the production and maintenance of strong bones and teeth (Jequier and Constant 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Magnesium is required in the plasma and extracellular fluid to maintain osmotic equilibrium. It also functions in many biochemical reactions including oxidative phosphorylation, glycolysis, and protein synthesis (Gröber et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Thomas et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). Phosphorus plays a vital role in energy generation, maintenance of bones, teeth and muscles, and cell growth and also provides the structural framework for DNA and RNA (Gharibzahedi &amp; Jafari, 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). It also functions in regulating blood sugar levels and contraction of the heart (Achi et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Potassium is crucial in maintaining normal cell functions, regular muscle contraction, and regulation of blood pressure. Calcium is required for bone and muscle formation, synaptic nerve impulse transmission and blood coagulation (Ozan and Akbulut 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). High intake of calcium is highly recommended especially for children and pregnant women (Insel et al. 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Zinc functions in normal body development, protein synthesis, and wound healing. It also forms an important part of many enzymes in the human body (Afolayan &amp; Jimoh, 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). However, excessive consumption of zinc is dangerous to human health (Ogundola et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Sodium is involved in the regulation of acid–base balance, normal cell function, transport of metabolites, nerve impulse transmission, and maintaining blood pressure (Unuofin et al., 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Iron is essential for hemoglobin formation; energy metabolism, and oxygen transport (Gaeta and Hider 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; WebMD, 
 <xref rid="fsn31978-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).
</p>
