<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fresh leaves of reference plants (~60 mg) were used for DNA extraction, the DNA was isolated using the Invisorb
 <sup>®</sup> Spin Plant Mini Kit (Stratec biomedical AG) following the protocol of the producer. The weighed plant material was shock-frozen in liquid nitrogen and homogenized in reaction tubes with steel beads (QiagenTissueLyser) for 2 min. The isolated DNA was evaluated by spectrophotometry (Nanodrop, Peqlab) for quality and quantity, and DNA concentration was diluted to 50 ng/µl as template for genomic PCR. A reaction volume of 30 µl containing 20.4 µl nuclease free water (Lonza, Biozym), 1-fold Thermopol Buffer (New England Biolabs), 1 mg/ml bovine serum albumin, 200 µM dNTPs (New England Biolabs), 0.2 µM of forward and reverse primers (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 2</bold>
 </xref>), 100–150 ng DNA template, and 3 units of Taq polymerase (New England Biolabs) was used to amplify the marker sequences. The 
 <italic>psbA-trnH intergenic spacer</italic> region was amplified in a thermal cycler by initial denaturation at 95°C for 2 min; followed by 33 cycles at 94°C for 1 min, annealing at 56°C for 30 s, and elongation at 68°C for 45 s; ending with an extension of 68°C for 5 min. The PCR amplicons were evaluated by agarose gel electrophoresis using NEEO ultra-quality agarose (Carl Roth, Karlsruhe, Germany). The DNA was visualized using SYBRsafe (Invitrogen, Thermo Fisher Scientific Germany) under blue light excitation (Invitrogen, Safe Imager λ = 470 nm). A 100-bp size standard (New England Biolabs) was used to determine the fragment size of the products. The amplicons were purified for sequencing using the MSB
 <sup>®</sup> Spin PCRapace kit (Stratec). Sequencing was conducted by Macrogen Europe (Netherlands) or GATC (Germany), and the quality of the obtained sequences was tested by FinchTV Version 1.4.0 (
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://digitalworldbiology.com/FinchTV" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://digitalworldbiology.com/FinchTV</uri>). The marker region was sequenced from two directions to get a robust result. The resulting two sequences were merged for each accession by aligning the forward read with the reverse complemented backward read. For sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis, the program MEGA7 (Version 7.0.14) with the integrated tree explorer was used. The sequences were aligned using the Muscle algorithm of MEGA7. Alignments were trimmed to the first nucleotide downstream of the forward primer and the nucleotide preceding the reverse primer. With the same software, the phylogenetic relationships were inferred by using the neighbor-joining algorithm with a bootstrap value that was based on 1,000 replicates. The species 
 <italic>Melissa officinalis</italic> was chosen as an outgroup. Additional 
 <italic>psbA-trnH intergenic spacer</italic> sequences for the use in molecular phylogeny were obtained from GenBank using a BLAST tool in combination with the Taxonomy View tool.
</p>
