<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The worldwide spreading of plant species outside their native range [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] is becoming an expansive phenomenon [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Invasive alien species (IAS) are one of the greatest threats to global biodiversity and the sustainable functioning of ecosystems [
 <xref rid="B4-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and, for this reason, are subject to a strict policy regulation such as the EU Regulation 1143/2014 on invasive alien species [
 <xref rid="B5-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ailanthus altissima</italic> is one of the most important IAS in Europe, also due to its wide presence [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In the recent commission implementing regulation (EU), 2019/1262 of 25 July 2019 [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] the list of IAS of Union concern was updated and 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> was inserted following a process of risk assessment. This species was first introduced in Europe from China, in the 1740s, in Paris, used as ornamental plants in cities and for afforestation [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Nowadays, it shows a wide diffusion in urban and peri-urban areas, but also in the agro-forest environment [
 <xref rid="B8-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In Italy, it appeared in 1760 when it was introduced at the Botanical Garden of Padua [
 <xref rid="B12-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], and now it is considered as invasive in all Italian administrative regions [
 <xref rid="B13-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], exerting an ecological impact on plant communities and Natura 2000 habitats [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The expansions of 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> is due to its pioneer characteristics such as the efficacy in gamic reproduction and dissemination [
 <xref rid="B16-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], agamic reproduction with strong sprouting ability also through radical activity [
 <xref rid="B18-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and extremely rapid growth [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] that can easily outcompete the forest native species, e.g., [
 <xref rid="B21-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. There is a species-specific mechanism in the invasion of recipient habitats. 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> colonization probabilities are higher in hardwood forests that are dominated by the trees of the genera 
 <italic>Fraxinus</italic>, 
 <italic>Quercus,</italic> and 
 <italic>Ulmus</italic> in the floodplains and hill positions and in dry conditions [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Moreover, the production of allelopathic substances (e.g., ailanthone) from the cortex and leaves that accumulate in the soil can inhibit the germination of native species [
 <xref rid="B24-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> spontaneous secondary stands also have impacts on soil properties and nutrient cycling, which are fundamental components of ecosystem functioning and processes. 
 <italic>A. altissima</italic> can modify carbon and nitrogen cycling [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] thanks to the decomposition rates of the leaf litter [
 <xref rid="B29-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], and alter the soil pH, even though the mechanisms are elusive [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Although its wide distribution all over the Mediterranean and temperate Europe, where it is mainly confined to cities at northern outposts of its range [
 <xref rid="B19-plants-09-01404" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], there is a lack of floristic-vegetational studies along with ecological studies in a paired comparison with the reference forest in its meridional range in sub-Mediterranean and Mediterranean bioclimates.
</p>
