<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">Yogurt is produced from coagulated milk after fermentation of lactic acid in milks by Lactobacillus bulgaricus and 
 <italic>Streptococcus thermophilus</italic>. It is known to all that yogurt is a highly efficient immune-modulatory food product. Many studies reported that immune-stimulatory and potential therapeutic effects of yogurt are due to their capability to change the gastrointestinal micro ecology (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Bourlioux and Pochart, 1988</xref>), where increased the number of beneficiary bacteria suppresses the growth of pathogenic bacteria which contributes to reduce infection. Some studies conducted in human have showed that yogurt consumption increases cytokine production, antibody production, phagocytic activity and T cell function, and natural killer (NK) cell activity, which ultimately boost up immune system to prevent any diseases (
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Meydani &amp;Woel-Kyu, 2000</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Choi et al. (2009)</xref> reported that yogurt containing probiotics have strong anti-viral efficacy against RNA virus like enterovirus 71, which also reduce the impact of influenza virus-induced respiratory infections. Furthermore, research articles published in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI), consumption of probiotics is a more feasible way to reduce the incidence of respiratory tract infections in children. The findings of systematic reviews and randomized controlled trials revealed that various probiotics, especially lactobacilli and bifidobacteria significantly reduced the incidence and severity of upper and lower respiratory tract infections (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Calder, 2020</xref>). Although the effectiveness of probiotics in reducing COVID-19 infected patients has not yet been scientifically established, however, the prophylactic benefits for improving the immune system are supportive for their long term use. A recent study showed that the improved gut microbiota profile has a significant role in preventing COVID-19 in older and high-risk persons having negotiated immune systems (
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Dhar and Mohanty, 2020</xref>).
</p>
