<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In vascular smooth muscle cell membrane, the opening of potassium channels (K
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>) enhance an increase in K
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> efflux, provoking membrane potential (
 <italic class="italic">Em</italic>) hyperpolarization and subsequent closure of voltage-activated calcium (Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>) channels, causing a decrease of intracellular Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> mobilization followed by a vasodilation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" class="xref">92</xref>]. In our experiments, the treatment of aorta with potassium channels blockers did not change the vasodilator action induced by AcEO, which suggests that the observed effect is potassium channel-independent. Besides K
 <sup class="sup">+</sup> channels, Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> channels contribute to the relaxant effect of resistant vessels. The Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> influx into vascular smooth muscle have two preponderant pathways: one is an L-type Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> channel and the other is a store-operated Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> channel (STOC). L-type calcium channels are the main gate of Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> mobilization from extracellular space during cell excitation. The Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> influx through L-type Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> channels is the determinant of intracellular calcium level in the vascular smooth muscle and hence the key parameter of contraction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" class="xref">93</xref>]. Hence, the calcium antagonism via L-type calcium channel is a recognized as a mechanism of vasorelaxation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">94</xref>]. A decrease in Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> levels into sarcoplasmic reticulum (SR) triggers refilling of cytoplasmic Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> in the SR Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> store through sarco/endoplasmic reticulum Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> ATPase (SERCA) pump and decreasing Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> influx from STOC, which consequently decreases intracellular Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> and enhance the vasorelaxation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>]. We performed separate experiments with the blockers of SERCA pump (thapsigargin) and L-type calcium channels (verapamil). As result, we found that AcEO-vasorelaxation induced was decreased by 50% with both drugs. In addition, AcEO inhibited KCL-induced contraction, and subsequently reduced the Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>-induced contraction in aortic rings exposed to KCl, and this effect was similar to that observed with increasing doses of verapamil, a known calcium channel blocker and a vasorelaxant drug, which confirms that AcEO acts by blocking the L-type calcium channels. However, 
 <italic class="italic">A.campestris</italic> L. oil also inhibited Phen-induced contraction, suggesting that it attenuated Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> influx through receptor-operated Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> channels as well.
</p>
