<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">As observed in Rosenzweig et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>, attributing climatic changes to natural systems requires special treatment through ‘joint attribution’. It seems clear that the recent reports of increased abundance of whiteflies and cassava diseases are not due simply to natural variation (internal variability). Cassava has been grown in the region for a long time prior to the recent reports of disease pandemics, and there have been a range of native whiteflies present in the region
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. By using the CLIMEX model of 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> MEAM1
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>, we have satisfied the second and third criteria for climate change attribution. The CLIMEX model was fitted using long-term average historical climate data and experimental data on MEAM1 response to climate variables (cross-checked with SSA responses), thus satisfying the plausibility criterion. When we applied the time-series climate data (
 <italic>natural forcing</italic>), the resulting pattern of statistically significant changes in climate suitability matched the observed patterns of changes in whitefly abundance and cassava disease. The trend was clearly sustained throughout the 39 years of the study, and was apparent despite the substantial inter-annual variability in climate suitability; further supporting the notion that it was not due to internal variability in the system, nor due to shorter-term variability in climate (e.g. inter-decadal)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. The null hypothesis for climate change is in-effect the baseline CLIMEX model for 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> MEAM1, applied to the historical climate dataset centred on 1995. By drawing upon a process-oriented model such as CLIMEX in this manner, we are essentially utilizing a variant of the ‘end-to-end’ method of climate change attribution
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
