<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NF-κB is a transcription factor that plays an important role in the transcription of genes, which are involved in immune and inflammatory responses. It was recently observed that Toll-like receptor 7 contributes to neuropathic pain by activating NF-κB in primary sensory neurons and subsequently induced the release of inflammatory mediators in immune cells [
 <xref rid="B118-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. NF-κB is released from a complex with I-κB and migrates to the nucleus where it binds to the κB enhancer element and induces transcription of its target genes, such as COX-2, iNOS, TNF-α, IL-1β, and IL -6, chemokines and adhesion molecules [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Treatment with an 
 <italic>E. speciosa</italic> methanol extract (ESLE) induced a significant reduction in the immunoexpression of NF-κB, COX-2, iNOS, and the pro-inflammatory marker, TNF-α in doses of 50–100 mg/kg. Additionally. Additionally, it increased the levels of GSH and catalase. This study concludes that ESLE exerted a gastroprotective effect through the synergistic anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activity of its various compounds, such as flavonoids (orientin, isoorientin, vitexin, isovitexin, and luteolin), alkaloids (hypaphorine), and saponins [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. It has been seen that an oxidative environment produces a positive regulation of cytokines and macrophages, increasing the inflammatory response mediated by COX-2. The cytokines released can act directly on the primary afferent sensory neurons increasing the permeability of sodium (Na
 <sup>+</sup>) sensitizing the capsaicin receptors (TRPV1). These effects facilitate peripheral sensitization. Likewise, the oxidative environment can activate brain regions that transmit pain signals from other brain regions, which are responsible for nociceptive processing, such as the rostral ventrolateral medulla (RMV) [
 <xref rid="B119-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. The methanolic extract from the leaves of 
 <italic>E. senegalensis</italic> has recently been seen, it showed a protective effect against oxidative stress in SC-1 fibroblasts and THP-1 macrophages. Observing the highest antioxidant activity against free radicals (IC50 = 44.86 μg/mL [ABTS]; 291.1 μg/mL [DPPH]) and intracellular ROS induced by 2,2′-Azobis (2-amidinopropane) dihydrochloride (AAPH) in macrophages. This effect was comparable to that of the positive control, Trolox [
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The presence of compounds such as kaempferol, rutin, and rotenone is suggested as possible, responsible for the effect, however, confirmation of the finding is required [
 <xref rid="B85-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. However, neobavaisoflavone (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-00248-f001">Figure 1</xref>), an isoflavone previously isolated from the root of 
 <italic>E. senegalensis</italic> and 
 <italic>E. excelsa</italic> [
 <xref rid="B120-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>] and found in 
 <italic>Psoralea corylifolia</italic> L., has been shown to have significant anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B121-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-ijms-22-00248" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>].
</p>
