<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results confirmed the antimicrobial activity of the three essential oils tested independently of the microorganisms used: in fact, Grădinaru and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B32-molecules-23-02818" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] reported anti-
 <italic class="italic">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 25923 activity of the green cardamom oil at a concentration of 6.25 mg/mL. While, the methicillin-resistant clinical isolates of 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> (MRSA) were most susceptible to 1,8-cineole (MIC = 1.25 mg/mL) as compared to the cardamom oil (MIC = 6.25 mg/mL). Additionally, we have previously reported that the green cardamom essential oil was active against a large panel of Gram-positive bacteria (mean diameter= 21.77 mm), cariogenic bacteria (mean diameter= 19.51 mm) and fungi (mean diameter= 39.5 mm), with MICs values ranging from 0.023 to 0.046 mg/mL for all bacterial and fungal strains tested [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-23-02818" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Recently, Teneva and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B33-molecules-23-02818" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] reported that the green cardamom oil (chemotype α-terpinyl acetate 39.03 %, eucalyptol 31.53 %) was active against pathogenic 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> ATCC 25922, 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> ATCC 8739, 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> sp., 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> ATCC 6538P, and 
 <italic class="italic">P. vulgaris</italic> strains with a diameters of inhibition zones between 8 and 10 mm and MICs values from 60 to &gt;600 ppm. In 2017, Mutlu-Ingok and Karbancioglu-Guler [
 <xref rid="B34-molecules-23-02818" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] reported that the green cardamom oil (chemotype α-terpinyl acetate 43.4%, eucalyptol 29.2%) was active against 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter coli</italic> with a diameter of growth inhibition zone ranging from 24.75 mm to 25.58, respectively. The MICs and MBCs values were low for the two 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> strains tested (0.025 µL/mL).
</p>
