<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The inhibition halo technique is often used to assess antibacterial activity of vegetal extracts and essential oils [
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Our results on the antimicrobial activity confirm that the behavior of an antimicrobial agent can be not only species-specific but also strain-specific [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. The available literature reports several studies ascertaining the antibacterial activity of the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">L. nobilis</italic> against different pathogens [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. The Algerian laurel essential oil versus 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ps. aeruginosa</italic> produced an inhibition halo of 13.73 mm and 10.73, respectively. The oil produced an inhibition halo of 13.03 mm when assayed versus 
 <italic class="italic">S. aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. In our experiments, the antimicrobial activity resulted higher than that of the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">L. nobilis</italic> collected in Turkey, if tested against 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> O157:H7 [
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Considering the chemical composition of the essential oil, we could hypothesize a synergistic action at least of the main compounds present in, specifically monoterpenes and oxygenate monoterpenes, which have per se low antimicrobial activity when used as single compounds [
 <xref rid="B21-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Other terpenes—such as α-pinene, β-pinene, γ-terpinene δ-3-carene, (+)-sabinene, and α-terpinene—showed a very low or no antimicrobial activity against 25 genera of bacteria [
 <xref rid="B22-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. These in vitro tests confirm that terpenes show ineffective antimicrobial activity when used as single compounds [
 <xref rid="B23-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">L. nobilis</italic> essential oil showed different antifungal activity (
 <xref rid="molecules-22-00930-t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>) respect to previous studies: in fact, our results indicate a marked antifungal activity, superior, for example, respect to that observed by Simic and co-workers both against 
 <italic class="italic">Aspergillus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Penicillium</italic> spp., in spite of its high content of 1,8-cineole [
 <xref rid="B24-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Therefore, the diameter of the halo produced by 1,8-cineole against the fungi was less evident. For this reason, we hypothesize a synergistic effect among the different components of the 
 <italic class="italic">L. nobilis</italic> EO, which, in a certain sense, cancel out the weakness demonstrated by the individual components. The remarkable effectiveness exhibited by the studied essential oil may be interesting for example in the manufacturing and food processing, which, as is known, is increasingly directed to the use of green technologies able to safeguard the quality food, the environment, and especially the health of the consumer [
 <xref rid="B25-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Therefore, the comforting results obtained using the essential oil of 
 <italic class="italic">L. nobilis</italic> indicate that such oil could be used as an antimicrobial agent, also for health and food purposes. The use of this essential oil prolonged the shelf life of modified atmosphere-packed (MAP) fish fillets [
 <xref rid="B26-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. The laurel essential oil was also used to safeguard the quality and safety of fresh sausages, prolonging their shelf life too and also avoiding the problems related to fat oxidation [
 <xref rid="B27-molecules-22-00930" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>].
</p>
