<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Applications of polymeric materials in mineral processing and metallurgy are determined by their pyrolysis products, bonding capacity with metal oxides as the alloying material and the super affinity to the water. In this context, this section discusses the relevant aspects of thermoplastics, thermosets, silicones and super absorbent gels. High-temperature pyrolysis of plastics is particularly advantageous in connection with metallurgical processes running at very high temperatures, e.g., the Corex process, the blast furnace, the recycling of the automotive wastes, the HTK Process (Hochtemperatur-Konversionsverfahren, aka High-Temperature Conversion Process) of VOEST-ÖMV, and the Thermoselect process [
 <xref rid="B5-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. This paper considers following applications of EOL and virgin plastics:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Energy and fuel: Plastics have a high calorific value when compared with other materials (as they are essentially made from crude oil), making them a convenient energy source.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Reductant: The CH
    <sub class="sub">4</sub>, CO, H
    <sub class="sub">2</sub> and the char produced during the pyrolysis of the plastics can replace the coal-based coke as a reducing agent in blast furnace applications.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Binder: Virgin thermoset polymers and inorganic silicones are adhesives and adhesion promotors (coupling agents). They form strong interfacial chemical bonds with transition metal oxide and impart high strength in the pellets using these thermosets as the binder. While epoxy thermoset resins lend high compression strength, the silicones, on the other hand, are easily compressible; nevertheless, they form stronger bonds with metal oxide and do not crumble. In addition, they also offer other advantages of the plastics as an energy source and as the reductants. They offer energy savings, better mechanical properties compared to the conventional binders, such as bentonite, which due to the high silica content, adds to the slag burden. Thermoset polymers offer high strength to the pellets under ambient conditions and can replace the conventional binders, such as bentonites, and organic binders in palletisation process [
    <xref rid="B7-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Alloying material: Virgin thermoset polymers and inorganic silicones also act as alloying agents in ferrosilicon and silicon carbide, and iron carbide. Silicones can substitute coke and quartz in iron alloy (ferrosilicon) production [
    <xref rid="B8-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. The viscous nature of the virgin thermosets provides for solid–liquid–gas reactions promoting good wetting between the reactants. This promotes the elemental silicon in silicones to react with the hematite to form ferrosilicon at much lower than the conventional temperatures. Similarly, the fillers in the epoxy resins easily form alloys with the hematite to produce SiC and FeC
    <sub class="sub">8</sub> with nano- and microstructures.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Carbon sequestration: Virgin thermosets can completely consume the carbon dioxide produced in a high carbon footprint reaction, such as magnesia and magnesium and clinker production, greatly reducing the global warming potential by up to 99%. This is achieved through the use of thermosets for carbon sequestration in the thermal decomposition of magnesite [
    <xref rid="B9-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Application in dewatering of coal: High moisture content in coal, in addition to detrimentally impacting the calorific value, also attracts high transportation tariffs and energy penalties when evaporating techniques are employed for dewatering. Superabsorbent polymers (SAPs) offer ambient dewatering of low-grade coals, greatly improving their calorific values and reducing the transport tariffs. Use of SAPs to dewater fine black coals, brown coals and tailings has been reported [
    <xref rid="B10-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
    <xref rid="B11-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
    <xref rid="B12-materials-12-00655" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
