<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2662-7671</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7290070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-020-02982-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Altitude impact on the chemical profile and biological activities of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L. essential oil</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1957-2127</contrib-id><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>Noha</given-names></name><address><email>noha.hassan@fue.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El-Jalel</surname><given-names>Lamya</given-names></name><address><email>lamyaeljalel26@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yousif</surname><given-names>Miriam</given-names></name><address><email>miriam.fouad@fue.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonaid</surname><given-names>Mariam</given-names></name><address><email>mariam.hussein@fue.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.440865.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0377 3762</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Pharmaceutical Sciences and Pharmaceutical Industries, </institution><institution>Future University in Egypt, </institution></institution-wrap>Cairo, 11835 Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Natural Resources and Environmental Sciences, Omar Al-Moukhtar University, 991, Albayda, Libya </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>186</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Several agricultural or environmental factors affect plants&#x02019; chemical and pharmacological properties.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">In this study, the essential oil of Libyan <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> was isolated from plants collected during two successive years at two different altitudes; Wasita (WEO) and Safsaf (SEO), 156 and 661&#x02009;m above sea level, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">GC/MS allowed the identification of 21 and 23 compounds, respectively. Thymol prevailed in WEO (26.69%), while carvacrol prevailed in SEO (14.30%). Antimicrobial activity was tested by agar-well diffusion method, and MIC/MLC values were determined by broth dilution method. Values of MIC/MLC were 0.125/0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml for SEO against <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> and <italic>K. pneumonia</italic> and for WEO against <italic>B. subtilus</italic>. It was observed that plants growing at lower altitude in Wasita locality had better antifungal activity, while those growing at higher altitude at Safsaf locality had better antibacterial activity. Both essential oils had a better anthelmintic activity than the standard piperazine citrate against a tested earthworm. However, SEO oil had a significantly higher anthelmintic activity than WEO. Cytotoxicity of the oils tested using SRB assay on human breast cancer (MCF-7) and colon cancer cell lines (HCT-116) showed better activity for SEO, especially against HCT-116 with IC<sub>50</sub> 2.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">Thus, altitude is an important factor that should be considered as it affected the yield, composition and biology of the plant extracts.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Altitude</kwd><kwd>Anthelmintic</kwd><kwd>Antimicrobial</kwd><kwd>Cytotoxic</kwd><kwd>Essential oil</kwd><kwd><italic>Satureja</italic></kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par50">The Libyan flora is spread over a diversity of geomorphologic regions which in return gives rise to a variety of climatic conditions suitable for the growth of different types of plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. One of the widespread plants in Al Jabal Al Akhdar region in Libya are members of family Lamiaceae like <italic>Satureja</italic> genus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. <italic>Satureja</italic> comprises more than 200 species of popular herbs or shrubs that are often aromatic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In Al Jabal Al Akhdar, two main species of <italic>Satureja</italic> dominate, <italic>S. thymbra</italic> and <italic>S. fortii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L.<italic>,</italic> known as pink savory, is an aromatic plant with oregano-like smell that is endemic to the Mediterranean region. The main chemical classes identified in the essential oil include monoterpene hydrocarbons such as <italic>p</italic>-cymene and &#x003b3;-terpinene, oxygenated monoterpenes, especially phenolic constituents as thymol and carvacrol. Also, sesquiterpene hydrocarbons were detected as &#x003b2;-caryophyllene and &#x003b1;-humulene as well as oxygenated sesquiterpenes such as caryophyllene oxide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The plant is also rich in other phenolic constituents like flavonoids and flavonoid glycosides as well as tannins, acids and exudates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Due to the presence of these compounds, <italic>S. thymbra</italic> L. has been evaluated as antibacterial, antifungal and antiviral agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. <italic>The essential</italic> oil proved an antimicrobial activity against several bacteria and fungi like <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic>, <italic>Shigella sonnei</italic>, <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and some resistant strains such as <italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>, <italic>S. maltophilia</italic>, and <italic>Chryseomonas luteolaas</italic> as well as the yeast <italic>Candida albicans</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The essential oil of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> (1%) has also been reported to possess a strong bactericidal activity against bacterial biofilms formed on stainless steel by some pathogenic bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The oil has also shown an in-vitro inhibitory activity against SARS-CoV and HSV-1 replication by visually scoring of the virus-induced cytopathogenic effects post-infection with a high selectivity index (SI) against HSV-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The oil also had a high SI when tested for its cytotoxicity in Vero cells using MTT assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Essential oil of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> has also been reported to possess an insecticidal activity against the mosquito <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> biotype <italic>molestus</italic>, acaricidal effect against <italic>Hyalomma marginatum</italic>, genotoxic activity against <italic>Drosophila</italic> as well as insecticidal activity against three stored-product insects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Other reported activities for the oil included improving circulation and thus being used in the treatment of arthritis, rheumatism, as a wound healing promoter and in painful joints and muscles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Being evaluated for cholinesterase inhibitory and antioxidative effects, the essential oil is suggested to treat amnesia and Alzeheimer&#x02019;s diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Traditionally, it has been used in food flavoring, perfumery and in local home remedies as antiseptic and diuretic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par51">Plants&#x02019; essential oil content and composition, and in-turn, its biological activity, has proved to be related to several factors including altitude, genetic, climate, topography, genotype, growing conditions and harvest time. Also, different chemotypes have been described for a number of medicinal plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Moreover, studies have shown that the different characteristics of medicinal plant may be affected by a variety of ecological factors such soil composition, temperature, humidity and other climatic conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Consequently, these changes in content and composition would definitely affect the pharmacological activity of the essential oil. Specifically, several studies show that chemical metabolic profile of Lamiaceae plants is strongly affected by environmental conditions such as geographical cultivation area, cultivation and harvesting period as well as local ecological conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. For example, altitude is one of the factors that affect plant metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Previous reports revealed that phenol-rich Lamiaceae species have shown that the great diversity in the content of thymol and carvacrol in the essential oils is associated with climatic factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Altitude affected the quantity and quality of the essential oil of several studied plants like <italic>Thymus kotschyanus</italic> (Lamiaceae), <italic>Teucrium hyrcanicum</italic> (Lamiaceae), <italic>Cymbopogon olivieri</italic> (Poaceae), <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> (Lamiaceae), <italic>Tanacetum polycephalum</italic> (Asteraceae), <italic>Ziziphora clinopodioides</italic> (Lamiaceae) and <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> (Lamiaceae) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. To further investigate the effect of altitude on the Libyan-growing medicinal plant; <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic>, the present work aimed at studying the impact of two different altitudes (Wasita and Safsaf in Al Jabal Al Akhdar region in Libya), on the chemical profile, antimicrobial, anthelmintic and cytotoxic activity of the essential oils of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> aerial parts collected during fall 2017 and 2018.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant material</title><p id="Par52">Samples of aerial parts of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> were obtained from two different localities (50 plants from random locations in each locality), during fall 2017 and fall 2018 from plants in Al-Jabal Al-Akhdar in Libya, from Wasita locality (32&#x000b0;52&#x02032;30.68&#x02033;N, 13&#x000b0;11&#x02032;14.86&#x02033;E) at 150&#x02009;m above sea level and from Safsaf locality (32&#x000b0;78&#x02032;19.51&#x02033;N, 21&#x000b0;95&#x02032;23.92&#x02033;E) at 661&#x02009;m above sea level. The plant is not endangered, so no permission was needed for its collection. Plants identity was authenticated by staff members of the Plant Taxonomy Department of the Faculty of Science at Omar Al Mokhtar University, Al Bydaa, Lybia. Voucher specimens were deposited at the Faculty of Pharmacy, Omar Al-Moukhtar University (STTB-8 and STTB-9). Plants were dried in shade, powdered and refrigerated in closed containers until use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Isolation of essential oils</title><p id="Par53">Samples (100&#x02009;g of dried plant in 500&#x02009;ml distilled water), were separately hydro-distilled with a Clevenger apparatus for 4&#x02009;h. Percentage oil yield was calculated/dry weight using the eq. (W1/W2 &#x000d7;&#x02009;100, where W1 is the weight if the oil in grams and W2 is the total weight of dried plant used). The obtained essential oil was dried over anhydrous sodium sulfate and kept refrigerated in sealed amber vials till analysis. Specific gravity of the obtained essential oils was determined according to the Egyptian Pharmacopoeia (2005).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>GC/MS analysis of the essential oil samples</title><p id="Par54">An Agilent 7890A gas chromatograph (Agilent Technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA) with a capillary column RTX-5MS (30&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.32&#x02009;mm, film thickness 0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) was used for the GC/MS analysis of the essential oils. This was coupled to an Agilent 5975C mass selective detector. The initial oven temperature was 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;min, then it was raised at the rate of 5&#x02009;&#x000b0;C/min until it reached 210&#x000b0;. The injector and detector temperatures were 290 and 300&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, respectively. Helium carrier gas was used at a flow rate of 2&#x02009;ml/min. Manual split mode injection was applied (0.1&#x02009;&#x003bc;l, each). EI mode was used for recording the mass spectra. The range for m/z was 35&#x02013;500. Ionization voltage was 70&#x02009;eV and ion source temperature was set at 230&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. The above conditions were applied for the analysis of a homologous series of n-alkanes to calculate retention index (RI). Identification was based on comparison of KI with literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], in addition to obtained data from Wiley&#x02019;s MS libraries. Authentic compounds (Sigma-Aldrich, Germany) were also used for identification of some compounds (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Gas chromatography/flame ionization detection (GC-FID)</title><p id="Par55">The GC analyses were carried out on a Focus GC&#x000ae; (Thermo fisher scientific&#x000ae;, Milan, Italy) equipped with TR5-MS fused bonded column (30&#x02009;m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;mm&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;m) (Thermo fisher scientific&#x000ae;, Florida, USA) and FID detector; carrier gas was nitrogen (1.5&#x02009;ml/ min); the operating conditions were: initial temperature 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, 1&#x02009;min. Isothermal followed by linear temperature increase till 230&#x02009;&#x000b0;C at a rate of 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C / min. 230&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, then 5&#x02009;min. Isothermal. Detector and injector temperatures were 300 and 220&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, respectively. The split ratio was 1: 20. Chrom-card&#x000ae; chromatography data system ver. 2.3.3 (Thermo Electron Corp.&#x000ae;, Florida, USA) was used for recording and integrating of the chromatograms. Average areas under the peaks of three independent chromatographic runs were used for calculation the % composition of each component.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Antimicrobial activity of the essential oils</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Source of microbial cultures</title><p id="Par56">Standard reference strains (American Type Culture Collection &#x0201c;ATCC&#x0201d; for bacteria and fungi) were used for assessing the antimicrobial activity of the essential oils. Gram positive bacteria: <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (ATCC 6538), <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> (ATCC 6051). Gram negative bacteria: <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (ATCC 8739), <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC 9027), <italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic> (ATCC 7002), <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (ATCC 13883). Fungal microorganisms: <italic>Candida albicans</italic> (ATCC 10231), <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> (ATCC 16888). Microbial inoculate of bacterial and fungal cultures were prepared as suspensions in Roux bottles using Trypticase soy agar (TSA) and Sabouraud dextrose agar (SDA) media according to the directions of the manufacturer (Sigma, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Agar-well diffusion method</title><p id="Par57"><italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> essential oils were prepared as an emulsion (10% w/w) using Tween 80. Sterilization of the obtained emulsion was achieved using a 0.45&#x02009;&#x003bc;m membrane filter. Agar-well diffusion method was performed according to the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The resultant inhibition zones were measured in mm, and the average values were taken. Ampicillin, Ciprofloxacin and Amphotericin B were used as standard antimicrobial agents. A blank prepared from the same concentration of Tween 80 was included.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Determination of minimum inhibitory and lethal concentrations (MIC/MLC) by broth dilution method</title><p id="Par58">Broth dilution method was used for determination of minimum inhibitory and minimum lethal concentrations of the oil (MIC/MLC) against the previously mentioned standard microorganisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Determination was achieved on 96 well culture plates using a microorganism suspension at a density of 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;CFU/ml with Casein Soy Broth (CSB) incubated for 24&#x02009;h at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for bacteria, and Sabouraud Dextrose Broth (SDB) incubated for 48&#x02009;h at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for yeasts. Serial dilutions of essential oils (0.125&#x02013;5&#x02009;&#x003bc;l/ml) were prepared with Brain Heart infusion (BHI) broth medium in test tube and mixed with bacterial suspensions to give a volume of 4&#x02009;ml and a final concentration of bacteria of approximately 5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup>&#x02009;CFU/ml. Final solutions were incubated at the temperatures mentioned earlier. The MIC is the lowest concentration which gave no visible growth, while the MLC was determined by sub-culturing 100&#x02009;<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>l from each negative test tube onto plate count agar (PCA) plates. MLC was defined as the lowest concentration resulting in a negative subculture or giving presence of only one colony after incubation. Negative controls lacking the oil were assayed simultaneously. The experiments were carried out in three replicates.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Anthelmintic activity of the essential oils</title><p id="Par59"><italic>Allolobophora caliginosa;</italic> an adult earthworm, was used to evaluate the anthelmintic activity of the essential oils at different concentrations. To obtain different concentrations of the essential oil (1, 2 and 3% v/v), 3% essential oil was diluted in 1% aqueous tween 80. Anthelmintic assay was carried out by dividing the earth worms into three groups each containing 6 worms (each worm &#x02265;10&#x02009;cm long). A control containing 3% aqueous tween 80 was used. The reference anthelmintic drug piperazine citrate (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) was also prepared in 0.1% solution using tween 80. Time of paralysis was recorded when no movement was observed, while time of death when the worms didn&#x02019;t move after being dipped in warm water (50&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>In-vitro screening of cytotoxic activity</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Human tumor cell lines</title><p id="Par60">The HCT-116 (human colon carcinoma) cell lines and MCF-7 (human breast adenocarcinoma) cells, maintained in the laboratory of Cancer Biology Department of National Cancer Institute, Cairo, Egypt (obtained originally from Sigma-Aldrich, Germany) were used for cytotoxicity assay. Normal hamster lung fibroblasts (V79 cells) were included as control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Cytotoxicity assay</title><p id="Par61">The essential oils at different concentrations (0&#x02013;10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml in 2% DMSO) were tested for cytotoxicity against the fore mentioned human tumor cell lines adopting sulforhodamine B stain (SRB) assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The relation between survivals and the oil concentration was plotted to get the survival curve of each tumor cell line after the application of specific concentration. The results were compared to those of the standard cytotoxic drug; doxorubicin (10&#x02009;mg adriamycin hydrochloride, in 5&#x02009;ml IV injection, Pharmacia, Italy) at the same concentration was used as standard anti-tumor. The dose of the test solutions which reduces survivals to 50% (IC<sub>50</sub>) was calculated as well as selectivity index. A blank prepared from the same concentration of Tween 80 was included.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par62">Tests were conducted in triplicate and values recorded as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. Results were analyzed by GraphPad Prism&#x000ae; v.5 software. Significant differences among means of different samples were analyzed using paired<italic>-t-</italic>test at <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Effect of altitude on essential oil physical properties, yield and composition</title><p id="Par63">Both Wasita essential oil (WEO) and Safsaf essential oil (SEO) were obtained in yellow color with a strong aromatic odor. During fall 2017, WEO had a significantly higher yield and specific gravity (1.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.03%v/w, 0.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04, respectively, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, paired<italic>-t-</italic>test) than SEO (1.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02%v/w and 0.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02, respectively). No significant difference in the results was observed during fall 2018 than those obtained during fall 2017 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Physical properties and percentage yield of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> essential oils obtained from Wasita (WEO) and Safsaf (SEO) localities during two successive years</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Locality</th><th>% EO<break/>(w/v)</th><th>Specific gravity of EO</th><th>Color of EO</th><th>Odor of EO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Wasita W1</td><td>1.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.90&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="4">Yellow</td><td rowspan="4">Strong aromatic</td></tr><tr><td>Wasita W2</td><td>1.55&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td>0.90&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Safsaf S1</td><td>1.44&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02<sup>b</sup></td><td>0.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Safsaf S2</td><td>1.38&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td>0.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are &#x000b1;SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5), different letters in same column denote significant difference at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, paired<italic>-t-</italic>test</p><p>W1 and W2 are plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively. S1 and S2 are plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par64">GC/MS analysis of WEO and SEO allowed the identification of 21 and 23 compounds, representing 88.17 and 93.84% in both oils, respectively during fall 2017 (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Monoterpene hydrocarbons had almost the same percentage in both oils (16.6 and 16.1% in WEO and SEO, respectively) represented mainly by &#x003b1;-thujene and <italic>p</italic>-cymene which had higher percentage in SEO (8.7 and 2.3% in SEO and 3.8 and 7.5% in WEO, respectively). On the other hand, two monoterpene hydrocarbons; &#x003b1;-terpinolene and allo-ocimene were detected in WEO only. Oxygenated monoterpenes was the most prevailing class in both oils (35.6 and 32.1% in WEO and SEO, respectively) represented mainly by the phenolic constituents; thymol and carvacrol. Thymol was the major identified compound in WEO (29.6%), while carvacrol was the major identified compound in SEO (14.3%). Sesquiterpene hydrocarbons were represented mainly by viridiflorine in WEO (3.4%) and &#x003b4;-cadinene in SEO (6.4%). Oxygenated sesquiterpenes had a much higher percentage in WEO than SEO (27.2 and 2.1%, respectively). Iso-spathulenol was the only oxygenated sesquiterpene in SEO (2.1%) which was also the major oxygenated sesquiterpene detected in WEO (13.4%) among other oxygenated sesquiterpenes present. Other classes of compounds were 27.2% in SEO and only 1.1% in WEO, represented by 2-tetra-butyl-4-methyl-phenol, which was completely absent in SEO. Generally, no significant difference in the results was observed during fall 2018 than those obtained during fall 2017.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of altitude on the chemical profile of the essential oils of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> essential oils obtained from Wasita (WEO) and Safsaf (SEO) localities during two successive years</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Compound</th><th colspan="2">Retention index (RI)</th><th colspan="4">Rel. abundance (%)</th><th rowspan="2">Methods of identifications</th></tr><tr><th>Cal.</th><th>Reported</th><th>Wasita W1<break/>(156&#x02009;m)</th><th>Wasita W2<break/>(156&#x02009;m)</th><th>Safsaf S1<break/>(661&#x02009;m)</th><th>Safsaf S2<break/>(661&#x02009;m)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="8"><bold><italic>Monoterpene hydrocarbons</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x003b1;-thujene</td><td>918</td><td>916</td><td>3.82&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.51 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.14 <sup>a</sup></td><td>4.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21 <sup>b</sup></td><td>4.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.18 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td><italic>p</italic>-cymene</td><td>1025</td><td>1023</td><td>7.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.01 <sup>a</sup></td><td>7.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.92 <sup>a</sup></td><td>8.76&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21 <sup>a</sup></td><td>8.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.41 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x003b3;-terpinene</td><td>1052</td><td>1053</td><td>1.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22 <sup>a</sup></td><td>0.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34 <sup>a</sup></td><td>2.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78 <sup>b</sup></td><td>1.96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.98 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;dehydro-<italic>p</italic>-cymene</td><td>1070</td><td>1067</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>0.50&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.11 <sup>a</sup></td><td>0.94&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.22 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x003b1;-terpinolene</td><td>1079</td><td>1082</td><td>1.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.48 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.27&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;allo-ocimene</td><td>1118</td><td>1119</td><td>2.08&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.14 <sup>a</sup></td><td>2.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.94 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td><italic>16.63</italic></td><td><italic>15.12</italic></td><td><italic>16.17</italic></td><td><italic>15.71</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold><italic>Oxygenated monoterpenes</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;thymol</td><td>1291</td><td>1299</td><td>29.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.25 <sup>a</sup></td><td>28.69&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.12 <sup>a</sup></td><td>9.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.44 <sup>b</sup></td><td>8.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.12 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS,AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;carvacrol</td><td>1298</td><td>1302</td><td>2.77&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25 <sup>a</sup></td><td>2.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21 <sup>a</sup></td><td>14.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.55 <sup>b</sup></td><td>14.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.12 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;4,5-dimethyl-2-ethyl phenol</td><td>1305</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.09&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45<sup>a</sup></td><td>2.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.26 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.59 <sup>b</sup></td><td>1.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;2,3,5,6-tetramethyl phenol</td><td>1361</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.33 <sup>b</sup></td><td>3.52&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.97 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;2,3,5,6-tetramethyl,3,4-diethyl phenol</td><td>1296</td><td>1301</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.41 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.02&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.44 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td><italic>35.61</italic></td><td><italic>34.57</italic></td><td><italic>32.18</italic></td><td><italic>31.10</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold><italic>Sesquiterpene hydrocarbons</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td><italic>trans</italic>-&#x003b2;- caryophellene</td><td>1412</td><td>1410</td><td>0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21 <sup>a</sup></td><td>0.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.19 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.57&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.02 <sup>b</sup></td><td>3.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.22 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;aromadendrene</td><td>1427</td><td>1423</td><td>1.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.12 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.09 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.47&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.78&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.23 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x003b1;-humulene</td><td>1441</td><td>1438</td><td>1.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78 <sup>a</sup></td><td>0.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.95 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.06 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.96 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;viridiflorine</td><td>1491</td><td>1487</td><td>3.40&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.18 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.21 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x003b4;-cadinene</td><td>1525</td><td>1521</td><td>1.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.77 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45 <sup>a</sup></td><td>6.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.31 <sup>b</sup></td><td>6.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.96 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td><italic>7.57</italic></td><td><italic>7.32</italic></td><td><italic>13.10</italic></td><td><italic>12.46</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold><italic>Oxygenated sesquiterpenes</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x003b1;-cedrene oxide</td><td>1569</td><td>1566</td><td>3.14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.11 <sup>a</sup></td><td>4.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.01 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;caryophllene oxide</td><td>1570</td><td>1568</td><td>1.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.69 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.79&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;iso spathulenol</td><td>1577</td><td>1585</td><td>13.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.37 <sup>a</sup></td><td>12.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.77 <sup>a</sup></td><td>2.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.05 <sup>b</sup></td><td>2.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.91 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x003b2;-oplopenone</td><td>1607</td><td>1603</td><td>0.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.33 <sup>a</sup></td><td>0.49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;caryophyllenol</td><td>1645</td><td>1648</td><td>3.84&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.04 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.47 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;valerenol</td><td>1706</td><td>1711</td><td>4.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.25 <sup>a</sup></td><td>4.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.05 <sup>a</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td><italic>27.2</italic></td><td><italic>26.69</italic></td><td><italic>2.18</italic></td><td><italic>2.44</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold><italic>Diterpenes</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;cembrene</td><td>1948</td><td>1941</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.97&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.72 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.55 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold><italic>Others</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;2-tetra-butyl-4-methyl-phenol</td><td>1513</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.45 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.78 <sup>b</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td><italic>p</italic>-anisaldehyde</td><td>1277</td><td>1279</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.37&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.56 <sup>a</sup></td><td>2.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.77 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS, AT</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;1,2-diethyl-3,4-dimethyl-benzene</td><td>1075</td><td>1076</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.22&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.44 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.62 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ethyl-tetra-methyl-cyclo penta-diene</td><td>1082</td><td>1085</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4.04&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.47 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.94&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.66 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;4, methoxy-6-methyl-2(3&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-dimethoxy benzyl) benzoic acid</td><td>1685</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.22 <sup>a</sup></td><td>1.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.36 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;1,2,3,1&#x02032;,2&#x02032;,3&#x02032;-hexamthyl-bicyclopentyl 2,2&#x02032;-diene</td><td>1122</td><td>1126</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>6.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.58 <sup>a</sup></td><td>5.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.98 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;2-hydroxy-3,4,6,7-tetra methoxy phenanthrene</td><td>1975</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.01&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.03 <sup>a</sup></td><td>2.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.65 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;1.8-dimethoxy-3-methylanthracene,9,10-dione</td><td>2035</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.66 <sup>a</sup></td><td>3.24&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.25 <sup>b</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;benzie-&#x003b1;-pyrone</td><td>2435</td><td>2442</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2.44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.89 <sup>a</sup></td><td>2.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.41 <sup>a</sup></td><td>RI, MS</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td><italic>1.16</italic></td><td><italic>3.29</italic></td><td><italic>27.24</italic></td><td><italic>23.08</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><italic>Total number of identified compounds</italic></td><td><italic>21</italic></td><td><italic>21</italic></td><td><italic>23</italic></td><td><italic>23</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><italic>Total percentage of identified compounds</italic></td><td><italic>88.17</italic></td><td><italic>86.99</italic></td><td><italic>93.84</italic></td><td><italic>87.80</italic></td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>MS: Identification based on mass spectral data; RI: identification based on retention index relative to standard <italic>n</italic>-alkanes; AT: Identification based on co-chromatography with authentic samples, (&#x02212;)&#x02009;=&#x02009;not detected. Values are &#x000b1;SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3), means followed by different letters in same row denote significant difference at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, paired<italic>-t-</italic>test</p><p>W1 and W2 are plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively. S1 and S2 are plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Effect of altitude on antimicrobial activity of the essential oils</title><p id="Par65">Testing of antimicrobial activity of the oils by agar-well diffusion method revealed that highest inhibition zone was observed for SEO collected during fall 2017 (55.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7&#x02009;mm) against the gram-negative <italic>K. pneumonia</italic>, while the weakest activity was observed for WEO collected during the same season, against <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> with inhibition zone 11.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2&#x02009;mm (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Both oils had significantly (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, paired<italic>-t-</italic>test) higher activity than ampicillin against the tested gram-positive bacteria. SEO had significantly higher activity than WEO against <italic>B. subtilus</italic> with inhibition zones 49.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1&#x02009;mm and 39.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5&#x02009;mm, respectively. However, the difference in activity between both oils against <italic>S. aureus</italic> was not significant. Also, activity of both oils was significantly higher than ciprofloxacin against all tested gram-negative bacteria, except for SEO against <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, which had the same activity as ciprofloxacin, while WEO had significantly lower activity than ciprofloxacin. Antibacterial activity of WEO was significantly higher than SEO against <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>P. mirabilis</italic>. WEO had significantly higher antifungal activity than SEO; however, both oils&#x02019; antifungal activity was significantly higher than the standard amphotericin B against <italic>C. albicans</italic>, but significantly lower than the standard amphotericin B against <italic>A. niger</italic>.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effect of altitude on the antimicrobial activities of the essential oils of S. thymbra essential oils obtained from Wasita (WEO) and Safsaf (SEO) localities during two successive years</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Test Organisms</th><th colspan="6">Inhibition Zone (mm)</th></tr><tr><th>Blank</th><th>WEO (W1)</th><th>WEO (W2)</th><th>SEO (S1)</th><th>SEO (S2)</th><th>Standard</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>Gram positive organisms</italic></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>Ampicillin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 6538</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>26.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>25.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.0 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>27.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>28.0&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.1 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>12.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 <sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> ATCC 6051</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>39.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.5 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>39.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.5 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>49.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>49.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>27.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7 <sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Gram negative organisms</italic></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>Ciprofloxacin</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 8739</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>46.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>46.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>37.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>38.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>23.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 <sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 9027</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>11.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>11.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.5 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>19.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>18.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.3 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>20.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2 <sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>atcc 7002</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>31.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>30.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>30.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>29.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.5 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>19.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6 A</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 13883</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>55.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>53.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>55.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.7 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>56.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>22.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 A</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Fungi</italic></td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>Amphotericin B</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Candida albicans</italic> ATCC 10231</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>35.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.2 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>36.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.1 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>34.6&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.9 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>34.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>25.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 A</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> ATCC 16888</td><td>(&#x02212;)</td><td>20.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.2 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>21.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>17.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.4 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>16.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.6 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>23.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2 A</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are &#x000b1;SEM (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3), means followed by different letters in same row denote significant difference at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, paired<italic>-t-</italic>test. Lowercase letters compare means of WEO with SEO, uppercase letters compare means of sample with the standard antibiotic</p><p>W1 and W2 are plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively. S1 and S2 are plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par66">Determination of MIL/MLC for the essential oils was performed using broth dilution method (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The results showed variable effects of the oils against the tested microorganisms. Highest bacteriostatic and bactericidal effects were observed for SEO against <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> and <italic>K. pneumonia</italic> with MIC/MLC 0.125/0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml, while lowest activity was for both oils against <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and the fungi <italic>A. niger</italic> with MIC/MLC ranging 1-&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml. SEO collected during fall 2018 had also better effect against <italic>B. subtilus</italic> with MIC/MLC 0.125/0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml. WEO had better bacteriostatic and bactericidal activity than SEO against <italic>E. coli</italic>, while no significant effect was observed between the activity of both tested samples against <italic>C. albicans</italic>.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effect of altitude on the MIC/MLC of the essential oils of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> essential oils obtained from Wasita (WEO) and Safsaf (SEO) localities during two successive years</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Test Organisms</th><th colspan="4">Minimum inhibitory and bactericidal concentrations (MIC/MLC, &#x003bc;g/ml<sup>a</sup>)</th></tr><tr><th>WEO (W1)</th><th>WEO (W2)</th><th>SEO (S1)</th><th>SEO (S2)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="5"><italic>Gram positive organisms</italic></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 6538</td><td>0.25/0.313</td><td>0.188/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> ATCC 6051</td><td>0.313/0.375</td><td>0.25/0.313</td><td>0.188/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><italic>Gram negative organisms</italic></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ATCC 8739</td><td>0.25/0.25</td><td>0.188/0.25</td><td>0.25/1</td><td>0.25/1</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 9027</td><td>1/&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5</td><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5/&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5</td><td>1/1</td><td>1/&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic> ATCC 7002</td><td>0.188/0.25</td><td>0.188/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 13883</td><td>0.125/0.375</td><td>0.125/0.375</td><td>0.125/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><italic>Fungi</italic></td></tr><tr><td><italic>Candida albicans</italic> ATCC 10231</td><td>0.125/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td><td>0.25/0.25</td><td>0.125/0.25</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> ATCC 16888</td><td>1/1</td><td>1/1</td><td>1/&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5</td><td>1//&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Values are mean resuts of three replicates</p><p>W1 and W2 are plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively. S1 and S2 are plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Effect of altitude on anthelmintic activity of the essential oils</title><p id="Par67">The essential oils collected from cuttings of two successive years from two different altitudes had a strong anthelmintic activity against the tested earthworm which was significantly higher than the standard piperazine citrate used. SEO had a slightly higher anthelmintic activity with shorter time recorded for the paralysis and death of the tested worms (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effect of altitude on the anthelmintic activity of essential oils of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> obtained from Wasita (WEO) and Safsaf (SEO) localities during two successive years</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Test</th><th>WEO (W1)</th><th>WEO (W2)</th><th>SEO (S1)</th><th>SEO (S2)</th><th>Piperazine citrate (Standard)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="5">Time for paralysis (min.)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1% EO</td><td>4.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.45 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>4.01&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.57 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>3.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.35 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>3.03&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.35 <sup>bB</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="3">9.77&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.78 <sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td>2% EO</td><td>3.51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.52 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>3.66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.39 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>2.15&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.25 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>2.59&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05 <sup>aB</sup></td></tr><tr><td>3% EO</td><td>2.37&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.24 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>2.66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>1.75&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.15 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>1.36&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.21 <sup>bB</sup></td></tr><tr><td/><td align="center" colspan="5">Time for death (min.)</td></tr><tr><td>1% EO</td><td>6.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.66 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>5.99&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.85 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>5.58&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.42 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>5.61&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.36 <sup>aB</sup></td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char" rowspan="3">13.58&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.95 <sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td>2% EO</td><td>4.65&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.49 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>4.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.41 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>4.22&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>4.26&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.45 <sup>aB</sup></td></tr><tr><td>3% EO</td><td>3.89&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.42 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>3.63&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.43 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>2.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.19 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>2.41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.74 <sup>bB</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are &#x000b1;SEM (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3), means followed by different letters in same row denote significant difference at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, paired<italic>-t-</italic>test. Lowercase letters compare means of WEO with SEO, uppercase letters compare means of sample with the standard antibiotic</p><p>W1 and W2 are plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively. S1 and S2 are plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Effect of altitude on cytotoxic activity of the essential oils</title><p id="Par68">Both WEO and SEO had a strong cytotoxic activity (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml) on both breast and colon cancer cell lines, with significantly higher activity and better selectivity index observed for SEO (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effect of altitude on the cytotoxic activities of the essential oil of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> obtained from Wasita (WEO) and Safsaf (SEO) localities during two successive years</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Test</th><th>Breast tumor cell line MCF-7</th><th>Selectivity index</th><th>Colon cancer cell line HCT-116</th><th>Selectivity index</th></tr><tr><th>IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/ml)</th><th colspan="2">IC<sub>50</sub> (&#x003bc;g/ml)</th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Wasita (W1)</td><td>3.69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.51 <sup>aA</sup></td><td>3.66</td><td>3.91&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>3.25</td></tr><tr><td>Wasita (W2)</td><td>3.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22 <sup>aA</sup></td><td>3.15</td><td>3.12&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14 <sup>aB</sup></td><td>3.04</td></tr><tr><td>Safsaf (S1)</td><td>2.75&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>4.15</td><td>2.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.21 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>4.69</td></tr><tr><td>Safsaf (S2)</td><td>3.01&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>4.82</td><td>2.99&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.21 <sup>bB</sup></td><td>4.78</td></tr><tr><td>Doxorubicin</td><td>3.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12 <sup>A</sup></td><td/><td>0.40&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.19 <sup>A</sup></td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are &#x000b1;SEM (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3), means followed by different letters in same column denote significant difference at p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, paired<italic>-t-</italic>test. Lowercase letters compare means of WEO with SEO, uppercase letters compare means of sample with the standard antibiotic. Selectivity index was calculated as the ratio of the IC<sub>50</sub> values on V79 cells to those in the tested cancer cell lines. SI&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3 indicates a promising activity</p><p>W1 and W2 are plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively. S1 and S2 are plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>In-vitro cytotoxic activity of S. thymbra oil obtained from Wasita and Safsaf localities on the tested cell lines. Significant differences among means of different treatments were separated using Bonferroni posttests at <italic>P</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3) with all treatments compared to the control; doxorubicin. *: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, ***: <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001. W1 and W2 are plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively. S1 andS2 are plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017 and 2018, respectively</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_2982_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par69">At higher altitudes<bold>,</bold> average temperatures are lower than those at the base of the mountains. Elevation plays a great role in the health and growth of plants. The type and amount of sunlight, amount of water that plants can absorb and the nutrients that plants receive differ at different altitudes. The main difference observed in the composition of the essential oils was in the major identified compound which was thymol in WEO and carvacrol in SEO. It was also observed that the percentage of total phenolic constituents of WEO is 36.77% while that of SEO is 32.18%. Present results are in agreement with the previously identified compounds in <italic>S. thymbra</italic> essential oil (thymol and carvacrol as well as their precursors; <italic>p</italic>-cymene and &#x003b3;-terpenene) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Several studies showed that a variation in the essential oil composition occurred in <italic>S. thymbra</italic> plants due to the effect of different factors such as different ecological conditions and even harvesting time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Other studies showed that altitude affects the chemical composition of the essential oils of several plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Essential oil of <italic>S. hortensis</italic> gave a higher yield of carvacrol at higher altitude [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], which is the case in this present work. Qualitative and quantitative variation in secondary metabolites may be due to several other different environmental, agricultural and genetic factors such as temperature, humidity, amount of rainfall, amount of sunlight, variety of the plant, collection season and even collection timing through the day as well as method of drying and extraction of the plant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. It is thus interesting to study the composition and biological activity at different geographical areas in order to choose the optimum source of possible drug.</p><p id="Par70">The tested essential oils gave a promising antimicrobial activity against bacteria and fungi. This was evidenced by larger inhibition zones given by the oils compared to the standard antimicrobial agents used, especially against <italic>S. aureus, B. subtilus, E. coli, P. mirabilis, K. pneumonia</italic> as well as <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Values of MIC/MLC were 0.125/0.25&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml for SEO against <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>P. mirabilis</italic> and <italic>K. pneumonia</italic> and for WEO against <italic>B. subtilus</italic>. It was observed that plants growing at lower altitude in Wasita locality had better antifungal activity, while those growing at higher altitude at Safsaf locality had better activity antibacterial activity. Compared with other studies, <italic>S. thymbra</italic> essential oil proved to be an available and natural antimicrobial agent that could be used in food industry to prevent the growth of food borne bacteria or to increase the shelf life of different processed foods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. A study showed that the oil of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> showed bacteriostatic activity at 0.001&#x02013;0.1&#x02009;mg/ml and was bactericidal at 0.002&#x02013;0.2&#x02009;mg/ml and fungistatic effects at 0.001&#x02013;0.025&#x02009;mg/ml and fungicidal effects at 0.001&#x02013;0.1&#x02009;mg/ml, while the oil main constituents thymol and carvacrol e also showed strong antimicrobial activity and antifungal activity that was even higher than the commercial fungicide bifonazole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The oil is active against certain microbial strains like <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>S. aureus</italic>, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic>C. albicans</italic> and <italic>Moniliophthora perniciosa</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. This strong antimicrobial activity may be attributed to the phenolic constituents: thymol and carvacrol which proved to interfere with the cell wall enzymes of bacteria and fungi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Studies also revealed that thymol&#x02019;s antimicrobial effect, especially against <italic>S. aureus</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> could be due to the perturbation of the lipid fraction of the bacterial plasma membrane resulting in the leakage of intracellular materials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Also data show that both carvacrol and thymol had desired antimicrobial effect on <italic>E. coli</italic>, possibly due to their ability to permeabilize and depolarize the cytoplasmic membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. A study showed that at higher altitudes, plants are exposed to extreme environmental conditions, which stimulate the accumulation of secondary metabolites that causes a further enhancement in the medicinal activity including the antimicrobial effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Results of the anthelmintic studies augmented that of the antimicrobial results. In literature, the essential oil of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> is well recorded for its anthelmintic, larvicidal, acaricidal and genotoxic activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par71">Previously, it has been reported that the essential oil of <italic>S. thymbra</italic> possesses a moderate anti proliferative and concentration dependant inhibition of viability of C32 (human amelanotic melanoma cell line) and ACHN (renal cell adenocarcinoma) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Cytotoxicity of the essential oils of other <italic>Satureja</italic> species were evaluated on several cell lines such as J774 macrophage, 5637, KYSE, Fem-X Human Malignant Melanoma, Vero, SW480, MCF7, JET3, A549, THP-1 and HT29/219 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par72">In conclusion, altitude may influence the chemical composition and biological activity due to a collection of conditions like temperature and climate changes. In this study, <italic>S. thymbra</italic> plants collected during two successive years, growing at a lower altitude gave a better essential oil yield, higher yield of thymol as well as better antifungal activity. However, plants growing at higher altitudes gave better yield of carvacrol, improved antibacterial, anthelmintic activity and better cytotoxic activity against colon and breast cancer cell lines. Therefore, altitude at which the plant grows should be considered according to its intended use. Moreover, further studies on samples collected from more altitudes, as well studying the effect of other different environmental factors at these altitudes, such as temperature, humidity and amount of sunlight, should be employed in order to augment the results of this study.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term><italic>A. niger</italic></term><def><p id="Par5"><italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ACHN</term><def><p id="Par6">Renal cell adenocarcinoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AT</term><def><p id="Par7">Identification based on co-chromatography with authentic samples</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATCC</term><def><p id="Par8">American Type Culture Collection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>B. subtilus</italic></term><def><p id="Par9"><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BHI</term><def><p id="Par10">Brain heart infusion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>C. albicans</italic></term><def><p id="Par11"><italic>Candida albicans</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>C32</term><def><p id="Par12">Human amelanotic melanoma cell lines</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFU</term><def><p id="Par13">Colony forming unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSB</term><def><p id="Par14">Casein soy broth</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMSO</term><def><p id="Par15">Dimethyl sulfoxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>E. coli</italic></term><def><p id="Par16"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC/MS</term><def><p id="Par17">Gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC-FID</term><def><p id="Par18">Gas chromatography/flame ionization detection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCT-116 </term><def><p id="Par19">Human colon carcinoma cell lines</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>hrs.</term><def><p id="Par20">Hours</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSV-1 </term><def><p id="Par21">Hepres simplex virus 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IC<sub>50</sub></term><def><p id="Par22">Half maximal inhibitory concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>K. pneumonia</italic></term><def><p id="Par23"><italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MCF-7</term><def><p id="Par24">Human breast cancer cell lines</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIC/MLC</term><def><p id="Par25">Minimum inhibitory and lethal concentrations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic></term><def><p id="Par26"><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>P. mirabilis</italic></term><def><p id="Par27"><italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCA</term><def><p id="Par28">Plate count agar</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RI</term><def><p id="Par29">Retention index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>S1</term><def><p id="Par30">Plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2017</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>S2</term><def><p id="Par31">Plants collected from Safsaf during fall 2018</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>S. aureus</italic></term><def><p id="Par32"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>S. fortii</italic></term><def><p id="Par33"><italic>Satureja fortii</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>S. hortensis</italic></term><def><p id="Par34"><italic>Satureja hortensis</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>S. maltophilia</italic></term><def><p id="Par35"><italic>Stenotrophomonas maltophilia</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>S. thymbra</italic></term><def><p id="Par36"><italic>Satureja thymbra</italic>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SARS-CoV </term><def><p id="Par37">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDA</term><def><p id="Par38">Sabouraud dextrose agar</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDB</term><def><p id="Par39">Sabouraud Dextrose Broth</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SEM</term><def><p id="Par40">Standard error mean</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SEO</term><def><p id="Par41">Safsaf essential oil</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SI</term><def><p id="Par42">Selectivity index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SRB</term><def><p id="Par43">Sulforhodamine B stain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TSA</term><def><p id="Par44">Trypticase soy agar</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>v/v</term><def><p id="Par45">Volume/volume</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>V79</term><def><p id="Par46">Normal hamster lung fibroblasts</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>W1</term><def><p id="Par47">Plants collected from Wasita during fall 2017</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>W2</term><def><p id="Par48">Plants collected fromWasita during fall 2018</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WEO</term><def><p id="Par49">Wasita essential oil</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Authors would like to acknowledge Dr. Kamel A. El-Ghareeb, at the Microbiology Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, Al-Azhar University, Cairo, Egypt; for his help during performance of the antimicrobial studies.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Conception and design of the study was proposed by M.Y. and M.G. Acquisition of data was carried out by N.K. and L.E. Interpretation of data, statistical analysis and drafting of the article was carried out by N.K. and L.E. Revising the article critically was carried out by N.K., M.Y. and M.G. Final approval of the version to be submitted was carried out by N.K., L.E, M.Y. and M.G. All authors have read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All obtained data have been included into the manuscript.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par73">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par74">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par75">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jafri</surname><given-names>SMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group><source>Flora of Libya</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Libya</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Al Faateh University, Faculty of Science, Department of Botany</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abusaief</surname><given-names>HMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakhil</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Mogasby</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altitudinal and rocky habitats of the flora eastern and western sides of the Al Jabal Al Akhdar in Libya</article-title><source>Am J Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tepe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cilkiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A pharmacological and phytochemical overview on <italic>Satureja</italic></article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>54</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25955956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25955956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jafri</surname><given-names>SMH</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Gadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Flora of Libya</source><year>1985</year><publisher-loc>Tripoli</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Al Faateh University, Faculty of Science, Department of Botany</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giatropoulos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimbaris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaelakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Papachristos</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Polissiou</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmanouel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and assessment of larvicidal and repellent capacity of 14 Lamiaceae essential oils against <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>117</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1953</fpage><lpage>1964</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29717370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29717370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitsiou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Anestopoulos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chlichlia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Galanis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourkoutas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Panayiotidis</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and Antiproliferative properties of the essential oils of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> and <italic>Satureja parnassica</italic> and their major constituents</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>36</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5757</fpage><lpage>5763</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27793897?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27793897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chorianopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Evergetis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallouchos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalpoutzakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nychas</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haroutounian</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the essential oil volatiles of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> and <italic>Satureja parnassica</italic>: influence of harvesting time and antimicrobial activity</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3139</fpage><lpage>3145</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16608243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16608243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giweli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzamic</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ristic</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of essential oils of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> growing wild in Libya</article-title><source>Molecules (Basel, Switzerland)</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>4836</fpage><lpage>4850</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Economou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Panagopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarantilis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalivas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotoulas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Travlos</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Polysiou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Karamanos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variability in essential oil content and composition of <italic>Origanum hirtum L., Origanum onites L., Coridothymus capitatus</italic> (L.) <italic>and Satureja thymbra</italic> L. populations from the Greek island Ikaria</article-title><source>Ind Crop Prod</source><year>2011</year><volume>33</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>241</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsimogiannis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Choulitoudi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bimpilas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitropoulou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourkoutas</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Oreopoulou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploitation of the biological potential of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> essential oil and distillation by-products</article-title><source>J Appl Res Med Aromat Plants</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choulitoudi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bravou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bimpilas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsironi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsimogiannis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Taoukis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Oreopoulou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and antioxidant activity of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> in gilthead seabream fillets edible coating</article-title><source>Food Biopro Process</source><year>2016</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>570</fpage><lpage>577</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goren</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Topcu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilsel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilsel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of essential oil of Satureja thymbra by hydrodistillation, thermal desorber, and headspace GC/MS techniques and its antimicrobial activity</article-title><source>Nat Prod Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14984095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14984095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarac</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ugur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activities of the essential oils of <italic>Origanum onites</italic> L., <italic>Origanum vulgare</italic> L. subspecies <italic>hirtum</italic> (link) Ietswaart, <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L., and <italic>Thymus cilicicus</italic> Boiss. &#x00026; Bal. growing wild in Turkey</article-title><source>J Med Food</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18800908?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18800908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;rkc&#x000fc;oglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Satil</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Can Baser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x000fc;men</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> antimicrobial activity and chemical composition of some <italic>Satureja</italic> essential oils</article-title><source>Flavour Fragr J</source><year>2005</year><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>591</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baydar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa&#x0011f;di&#x000e7;</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d6;zkan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Karado&#x0011f;an</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity and composition of essential oils from <italic>Origanum</italic>, <italic>Thymbra</italic> and <italic>Satureja</italic> species with commercial importance in Turkey</article-title><source>Food Control</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>172</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chorianopoulos</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Giaouris</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Skandamis</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Haroutounian</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nychas</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disinfectant test against monoculture and mixed-culture biofilms composed of technological, spoilage and pathogenic bacteria: bactericidal effect of essential oil and hydrosol of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> and comparison with standard acid-base sanitizers</article-title><source>J Appl Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>104</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1596</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18217930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18217930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loizzo</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Saab</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tundis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Statti</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Menichini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampronti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cinatl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemical analysis and in vitro antiviral activities of the essential oils of seven Lebanon species</article-title><source>Chem Biodivers</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18357554?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18357554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saab</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampronti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Finotti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgatti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Esseily</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vitro</italic> evaluation of the biological activity of Lebanese medicinal plants extracts against <italic>Herpes simplex</italic> virus type 1</article-title><source>Minerva Biotecnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>121</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cilek</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Oz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Deveci</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanikoglu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acaricidal activity of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L. essential oil and its major components, carvacrol and gamma-terpinene against adult <italic>Hyalomma marginatum</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>Vet Parasitol</source><year>2010</year><volume>170</volume><issue>3&#x02013;4</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20303667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20303667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karpouhtsis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardali</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Feggou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokkini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scouras</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavragani-Tsipidou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal and Genotoxic activities of oregano essential oils</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>1115</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayvaz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagdic</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Karaborklu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal activity of the essential oils from different plants against three stored-product insects</article-title><source>J Insect Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>21</fpage><?supplied-pmid 20578885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20578885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michaelakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Theotokatos</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koliopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chorianopoulos</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oils of Satureja species: insecticidal effect on <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> larvae (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title><source>Molecules (Basel, Switzerland)</source><year>2007</year><volume>12</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2567</fpage><lpage>2578</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Beyrouthy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Delelis-Dusollier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants used as remedies antirheumatic and antineuralgic in the traditional medicine of Lebanon</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2008</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18809483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18809483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d6;zt&#x000fc;rk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anticholinesterase and antioxidant activities of Savoury (<italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L.) with identified major terpenes of the essential oil</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>134</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamidpour</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamidpour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamidpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahlari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohraby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Summer savory: from the selection of traditional applications to the novel effect in relief, prevention, and treatment of a number of serious illnesses such as diabetes, cardiovascular disease, Alzheimer's disease, and Cancer</article-title><source>J Tradit Complement Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25161917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25161917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Saikia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanotiya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity, essential oil composition, and in vitro antioxidant and antimicrobial activity of <italic>Curcuma longa</italic> L. germplasm collections</article-title><source>J Appl Res Med Aromat Plants</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0015e;anli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karado&#x0011f;an</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographical impact on essential oil composition of endemic Kundmannia anatolica hub.-Mor. (Apiaceae)</article-title><source>Afr J Tradit Complement Altern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28480390?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28480390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satyal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McFeeters</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Kaf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Setzer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotypic characterization and biological activity of <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic></article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>20</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pourohit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Medicinal plants cultivation</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Jodhpur</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Agrobios Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozturk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Duru</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Harmandar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Topcu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of temperature on the essential oil components of <italic>Salvia potentillifolia</italic> obtained by various methods</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1020</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19731615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19731615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aboukhalid K, Al Faiz C, Douaik A, Bakha M, Kursa K, Agacka-Moldoch M, Machon N, Tomi F, Lamiri A. Influence of Environmental Factors on Essential Oil Variability in <italic>Origanum compactum</italic> Benth. Growing Wild in Morocco. Chem Biodivers. 2017;14(9):1&#x02013;17.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapposelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Melito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barmina</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Foddai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Azara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarpa</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between soil and essential oil profiles in <italic>Salvia desoleana</italic> populations: preliminary results</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1615</fpage><lpage>1618</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26594772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26594772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahdavi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouri</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoudi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezazadeh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahzooni-Kachapi</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating the altitude effect on the quantity and quality of the essential oil in <italic>Tanacetum polycephalum</italic> Sch.-Bip. <italic>polycephalum</italic> in the Baladeh region of nour, Iran</article-title><source>Chin J Nat Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24359783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24359783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demasi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Caser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cioni</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scariot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Latitude and altitude influence secondary metabolite production in peripheral Alpine populations of the Mediterranean species <italic>Lavandula angustifolia</italic> mill</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>983</fpage><?supplied-pmid 30026754?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30026754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleta-Soriano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Villellas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptation of the long-lived monocarpic perennial <italic>Saxifraga longifolia</italic> to high altitude</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>172</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>775</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27440756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27440756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimmalek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malekpoor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in antibacterial activity, thymol and carvacrol contents of wild populations of <italic>Thymus daenensis</italic> subsp. <italic>daenensis</italic> Celak</article-title><source>Plant Omics</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>214</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karousou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Koureas</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kokkini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential oil composition is related to the natural habitats: <italic>Coridothymus capitatus</italic> and <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> in NATURA 2000 sites of Crete</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>66</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>2668</fpage><lpage>2673</lpage><?supplied-pmid 16289149?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16289149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aminzadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>AZARNIVAND</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abedi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of evaluation for quality and quantity of essential oil <italic>Thymus kotschyanus</italic> (Damavand-tar)</article-title><source>J Med Plants</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Identification of essential oil components by gas chromatography/quadrupole mass spectroscopy, vol. 1, 4th edn</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Illinois</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Allured Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CLSI</collab></person-group><source>Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Disk Susceptibility Tests, Approved Standard, 7th edn. Pennsylvania 19087, USA</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Wayne</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute, 950 West Valley Road, Suite 2500</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dkhil</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-coccidial, anthelmintic and antioxidant activities of pomegranate (<italic>Punica granatum</italic>) peel extract</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2639</fpage><lpage>2646</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23609599?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23609599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skehan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Storeng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scudiero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Monks</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vistica</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokesch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New colorimetric cytotoxicity assay for anticancer-drug screening</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>1990</year><volume>82</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>1112</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2359136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2359136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glamo&#x0010d;lija</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vukojevi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Milenkovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Griensven</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antifungal activities of essential oils of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L. and <italic>Salvia pomifera</italic> ssp. calycina (Sm.) Hayek</article-title><source>J Essent Oil Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piras</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Falconieri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Porcedda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marongiu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Frau</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaleiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgueiro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of the volatile oil from <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> by supercritical carbon dioxide extraction: chemical composition and biological activity</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1526</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22164799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22164799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Beyrouthy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold-Apostolides</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Najm</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abou Jaoudeh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Labaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhifi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Abou Kais</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of the aerial parts of <italic>Satureja thymbra</italic> L. essential oil growing wild in Lebanon</article-title><source>ActaHortic</source><year>2013</year><volume>997</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadjafi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Asareh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezadoost</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological and yield related traits, essential oil and oil production of different landraces of black cumin (<italic>Nigella sativa</italic>) in Iran</article-title><source>Sci Hort</source><year>2018</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kacar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayta&#x000e7;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;ksu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Erba&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Telci</surname><given-names>&#x00130;</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmasta&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological variation of yield and aroma components of summer savory (<italic>Satureja hortensis</italic> L.)</article-title><source>J Appl Res Med Aromat Plants</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zidorn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altitudinal variation of secondary metabolites in flowering heads of the Asteraceae: trends and causes</article-title><source>Phytochem Rev</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>203</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djouahri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudarene</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meklati</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of extraction method on chemical composition, antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities of essential oil from the leaves of Algerian <italic>Tetraclinis articulata</italic> (Vahl) masters</article-title><source>Ind Crop Prod</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ricciardi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bubenik</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricciardi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dellacassa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental effect on essential oil composition of <italic>Aloysia citriodora</italic> from Corrientes (Argentina)</article-title><source>Nat Prod Commun</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1711</fpage><lpage>1714</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22224294?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22224294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nazzaro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fratianni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Martino</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>De Feo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of essential oils on pathogenic Bacteria</article-title><source>Pharmaceuticals</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1474</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24287491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24287491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trombetta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarpietro</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Venuti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cristani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniele</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saija</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzanti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisignano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of antibacterial action of three monoterpenes</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2474</fpage><lpage>2478</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15917549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15917549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The antibacterial mechanism of carvacrol and thymol against <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Lett Appl Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><?supplied-pmid 19552781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19552781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gulzar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawchoo</surname></name><name><surname>Yaqoob</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A study on variation of phytochemical constituents with altitude and <italic>In vitro</italic> antimicrobial potential of two species of <italic>Ajuga</italic> L</article-title><source>Adv Biomed Pharm</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>