<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Mentha piperita</italic> essential oil (MPE) is commonly known as peppermint. Leaves of mint plant are aromatic perennial herb cultivated in most part of the world. It is used as folk medicine and frequently used in herbal tea and for culinary purpose to add flavor and aroma. The essential oil of 
 <italic>M. piperita</italic> rich in menthol, l-menthone, pulegone, piperitone, menthol acetate, piperitenone menthone, carvone, menthofuran, isomenthone, menthyl acetate, isopulegol, menthol, 3-octanol, pulegone; hence, it also used as natural antioxidants.[
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] MPE have shown potent inhibitory activity against several microorganisms such as 
 <italic>Penicillium digitatum</italic>, 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic>, 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic>, 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, 
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>
 <italic>Mucor</italic> spp., and 
 <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>,[
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] further MPE reported as antifungal agent for several mycotoxigenic speceies by Silva 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 2012;[
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] 
 <italic>A. flavus</italic> and 
 <italic>A. parasiticus</italic>, Freire 
 <italic>et al</italic>., in 2012[
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] reported against 
 <italic>Aspergillus ochraceous</italic>, 
 <italic>Colletotrichum gloeosporioides</italic>, 
 <italic>Colletotrichum musae</italic>, 
 <italic>F. oxysporum</italic>, 
 <italic>Fusarium semitectum</italic>. Currently, it has been widely used in cosmetic, food and pharmaceutical industries no studies of which we are aware have reported the effects of MPE on 
 <italic>F. sporotrichioides</italic>. Therefore, the present study was undertaken to evaluate the effects of MPE against the growth of 
 <italic>F. sporotrichioides</italic>. Morphological alteration was investigated by scanning electron microscopy.
</p>
