<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Global-scale modelling studies on 
 <italic>Lantana</italic> have predicted its widespread distribution in India, perhaps due to broad geographic scale and lack of sufficient occurrence points in India (
 <xref rid="PLU052C4" ref-type="bibr">Bhagwat 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C58" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Kumar 2012</xref>). 
 <italic>Lantana</italic> distribution models for Australia found that temperature (i.e. limiting low temperature, limiting high temperature) and soil moisture (i.e. soil drainage type) play key roles in its current and potential distribution pattern. Similarly in China, models were built using temperature, precipitation and elevation variables due to their importance in eco-physiological activities (
 <xref rid="PLU052C32" ref-type="bibr">Lüi 2011</xref>). In contrast, our model was developed based on the widely distributed occurrence points in India, which are expected to encompass heterogeneous environmental regimes, thus promising better predictive power than the previous models. The potential distribution map reflected its moderate-to-high country-wide distribution potential, except in the western desert and the northern Himalayan regions, and this is well supported by available literature as well as field observations (
 <xref rid="PLU052C61" ref-type="bibr">Thakur 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 1992
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C24" ref-type="bibr">Kannan 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>). The pattern becomes clearer with a binary distribution map based on minimum presence points. The model revealed preference towards variables like temperature seasonality (Bio4), altitude and land-cover patterns which share a similarity with findings from elsewhere (
 <xref rid="PLU052C32" ref-type="bibr">Lüi 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C58" ref-type="bibr">Taylor and Kumar 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="PLU052C59" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Grossly, the favourable areas have higher seasonality values in comparison with the non-favourable ones, indicating species tolerance to harsh climatic conditions, except in the western desert region as revealed in other studies (
 <xref rid="PLU052C5" ref-type="bibr">Broughton 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="PLU052C6" ref-type="bibr">Day 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2003
 </xref>). Similarly, altitude plays an important role as the distribution almost discontinues near the Himalayan foothill area and different parts of central Indian highlands. However, the Western Ghats, one of the major biodiversity hotspots, is found to be moderately favourable for its spread as reported previously (
 <xref rid="PLU052C24" ref-type="bibr">Kannan 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>).
</p>
