<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Med Ther</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary Medicine and Therapies</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2662-7671</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7325256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3001</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-020-03001-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of in-vivo antidiarrhoeal and in-vitro antibacterial activities of the root extract of <italic>Brucea antidysenterica</italic> J. F. Mill (Simaroubaceae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7089-421X</contrib-id><name><surname>Zewdie</surname><given-names>Kaleab Alemayehu</given-names></name><address><email>kalxy2919@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8198-3376</contrib-id><name><surname>Bhoumik</surname><given-names>Dayananda</given-names></name><address><email>drdbhoumik@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1127-6443</contrib-id><name><surname>Wondafrash</surname><given-names>Dawit Zewdu</given-names></name><address><email>davaniye@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2847-1392</contrib-id><name><surname>Tuem</surname><given-names>Kald Beshir</given-names></name><address><email>kalizad2003@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.30820.39</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 1539 8988</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, School of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Mekelle University, </institution></institution-wrap>1871 Mekelle, Ethiopia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>201</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Diarrhoea has been the major cause of death especially in children of developing countries. <italic>Brucea antidysenterica</italic> is one of the several medicinal plants used traditionally for the treatment of diarrhoea in Ethiopia. Hence, the present study was undertaken to investigate the antidiarrhoeal and antibacterial activities of the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Plant material was extracted by maceration technique using 80% methanol. The antidiarrhoeal activity was tested using castor oil-induced diarrhoea, castor oil-induced charcoal meal test, and castor oil-induced enteropooling models in mice. Whilst, the antibacterial activity of the crude extract was evaluated using agar well diffusion and broth microdilution methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The 80% methanolic crude extract significantly delayed the diarrhoeal onset at the two higher doses (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and it has also inhibited the number and weight of faecal output at all tested doses as compared with the negative control. Moreover, it showed a significant anti-motility effect (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) at all tested doses. Whereas it displayed a significant reduction in the weight and volume of intestinal contents at the doses of 200 and 400&#x02009;mg/kg (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01). The highest concentration (800&#x02009;mg/mL) of test extract showed maximum zone of inhibition in all tested standard strains of bacteria (18.3&#x02009;mm&#x02013;22&#x02009;mm). While MIC and MBC values (0.39&#x02009;mg/mL and 1.56&#x02009;mg/mL) showed that <italic>S. flexneri</italic> was the most susceptible pathogen for test extract.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">The study revealed that the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> has antidiarrhoeal and antibacterial activities.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Antidiarrhoeal</kwd><kwd>Antibacterial</kwd><kwd>Castor oil</kwd><kwd>Agar well diffusion</kwd><kwd><italic>Brucea antidysenterica</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100009402</institution-id><institution>Mekelle University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>PG/MSc/MU-NMBU/CHS/27/2011</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Zewdie</surname><given-names>Kaleab Alemayehu</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par11">Diarrhoea is a loss of watery stool at least three times a day [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], or more frequent bowel movements with a volume or weight of greater than 200&#x02009;mL or 200&#x02009;g in 24&#x02009;h duration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Although diarrhoea is a preventable condition, it affects almost all global population and accountable for 5% of health defects and 4% of all deaths worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Globally, about 2.2 million people died each year and most are due to bacterial-induced diarrhoea. Several bacterial pathogens including <italic>Vibrio cholera</italic>, <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic>, <italic>Shigella</italic> species, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> species causes various forms of diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. According to the Centre for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and WHO report in 2017, 1 in 9 child death was reported worldwide, which makes diarrhoea the second leading cause of death for under-five children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Moreover, diarrhoea kills 2195 children each day which is greater than malaria, measles and AIDS combined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par12">Since primaeval times, humans used natural products to relieve and treat diseases for themselves and their livestock. Different traditional plants have been used as a source of modern medicine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition, numerous traditional plants were scientifically reported for their antidiarrhoeal activity:- including <italic>Myrtus communis</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]<italic>, Lantana camara</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]<italic>, Croton macrostachyus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]<italic>, Carissa carandas</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]<italic>, Zehneria scabra</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]<italic>, Ajuga remota</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]<italic>, Discopodium penninervum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] and <italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par13"><italic>Brucea antidysenterica</italic> J. F. Mill (Family: Simaroubaceae) belongs to genus <italic>Brucea</italic>. It is a small tree, widely distributed in tropical America and Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The family Simaroubaceae comprises about 25 genera, 120 species and in the genus <italic>Brucea</italic> about 10 species are found in Africa, Asia, and Australia. <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> is mostly found in Ethiopia and well-known for its medicinal uses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. It has been reported for several ethnomedicinal uses such as malaria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], bacterial infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], dysentery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] and amoebicidal effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">The anti-diarrhoeal claims of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> were stated in numerous works of literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The bark, fruit, and roots of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> have been used by traditional society against dysentery, as an anthelmintic and for treatment of fever. The seed, leaf and roots are used as a remedy for diarrhoea, indigestion, and stomach-ache [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The present study was investigated to assess the antidiarrhoeal and antibacterial activities of the 80% hydro-methanolic root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> in laboratory-based studies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Drugs and chemicals</title><p id="Par15">Castor oil (Amman Pharmaceutical industries CO, Jordan), activated charcoal (Research-Lab fine Chem industries, Mumbai, India), loperamide (Daehwa Pharmaceuticals, Republic of Korea), distilled water (Dallul Pharmaceuticals PLC, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia), methanol (Alpha Chemika, Mumbai, India), ciprofloxacin 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/disc (Becton, Dickinson and Company, Sparks, USA), ceftazidime 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/disc (Oxoid Ltd., Basingstoke, England), muller hinton agar (MHA) (HiMedia Laboratories Pvt. Ltd., India), muller hinton broth (MHB) (HiMedia Laboratories Pvt. Ltd., India) and nutrient agar (Micro master lab, India) were used during the study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>List of materials</title><p id="Par16">The following materials were used for the study. Electrical grinder (Shanghai Yuan Wo industrial and trade CO. LTD, Shanghai city), orbital shaker (Stuart S01, UK), drying oven (M200CFL, England), vortex mixer (Assistant Reamix 2789, Germany) and Bio-safety Cabinet (Bio- II- A/P, Telstar Company, Italy).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Collection and authentication of plant material</title><p id="Par17">The roots of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> were collected from one of the claimed areas &#x02018;<italic>Lumame</italic>&#x02019;, in Gozamin Wereda, east Gojjam zone of Amhara region, Ethiopia in November 2018. Identification and authentication of the plant material was done by Professor Sileshi Nemomissa, an authorized botanist at the National Herbarium, College of Natural and Computational Sciences, Addis Ababa University, and the sample were deposited for future reference with voucher specimen number 1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Preparation of crude extract</title><p id="Par18">The collected root was washed gently and dried at room temperature under shade. It was then chopped manually and ground with an electrical grinder. The extraction was done by maceration technique with 80% methanol solvent, in the 1:6 solute-solvent ratio. The extraction was facilitated by intermediate manual shaking and occasional quivering with an orbital shaker at 120&#x02009;rpm. After 72&#x02009;h, the macerate was filtered with a double-layered muslin cloth and Whatman number 1 filter paper. The marc was re-macerated twice with fresh solvent for exhaustive extraction. The combined extract was dried under 40&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in a drying oven. After drying, the percentage yield of plant extract was determined and it was 6.26% w/w. Finally, the dried crude extract was stored in the refrigerator at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C until use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Experimental animals</title><p id="Par19">Healthy Swiss albino mice of either sex (weighing 25&#x02013;35&#x02009;g and age of 6&#x02013;8&#x02009;weeks) were used for the experiment. The animals were obtained from and maintained in the laboratory of Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, School of Pharmacy, Mekelle University. All animals were housed in plastic cages at room temperature in an air-conditioned room of 12-h light/dark cycle with accesses of pellet diet and clean water ad libitum. Before any experiment was started animals were allowed a week of acclimatization to the experimental environment and all the experiments were carried out according to the internationally accepted laboratory animal care and use guideline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The protocol approval letter was obtained from the Health Research Ethics Review Committee (HRERC) of College of Health Sciences, Mekelle University and registered as ERC 1537/2018 protocol number on December 11, 2018.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Acute Oral toxicity test</title><p id="Par20">Acute oral toxicity test was performed based on the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) guideline, number 425. All animals were observed continuously for toxicities like diarrhoea, decrease of appetite, hair erection and loss, lacrimation, convulsion, salivation, lethargy, paralysis, and mortality for the first 1 hour continuously and intermittently for the next 3 hours and periodically for 24&#x02009;h and later cage side observation continued for 14&#x02009;days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Grouping and dosing of animals</title><p id="Par21">Mice were randomly assigned into five groups of six animals each to perform antidiarrhoeal activity using three models. The negative control groups were treated with distilled water (DW) (10&#x02009;mL/kg), positive control groups received the standard drug loperamide (3&#x02009;mg/kg) in all models. The three tested doses were selected based on the result of acute toxicity study. Based on that 100, 200 and 400&#x02009;mg/kg were considered as low dose, middle dose and high dose, respectively. A volume of 1&#x02009;mL/100&#x02009;g was administered orally based on individual mouse body weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The duration of administration was depending on the type of test and it was described along with the respective models.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Determination of anti-diarrhoeal activity</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Castor oil induced Diarrhoea model</title><p id="Par22">This model was conducted according to Degu et al., and Sisay et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Animals were fasted for 18&#x02009;h and placed individually in a cage, in which the bottom floor was lined with blotting paper and was replaced every hour. Then animals received either vehicle or treatment samples as described in section 2.7 based on their fasting weight. Diarrhoea was induced by administering 0.5&#x02009;mL of castor oil per oral route to each mouse just 1&#x02009;h after the previous treatments. The observation was continued for a period of 4&#x02009;h. Time of onset of diarrhoea, a total number of faecal outputs (frequency of defecation) and weight of faeces excreted by the animals were recorded. Finally, the percentage of diarrhoeal inhibition, percentage weight of wet faecal output and percentage weight of total faecal output were determined with respect to their formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].
<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{Inhibition}=\frac{\mathrm{Average}\ \mathrm{number}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{WFC}-\mathrm{Average}\ \mathrm{number}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{WFT}}{\mathrm{Average}\ \mathrm{number}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{WFC}}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Average number of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>WFC</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Average number of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>WFT</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Average number of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>WFC</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par23">Where, WFC&#x02009;=&#x02009;average number of wet faeces in the control group and</p><p id="Par24">WFT&#x02009;=&#x02009;average number of wet faeces in the test group.
<disp-formula id="Equb"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{Wet}\ \mathrm{faecal}\ \mathrm{output}=\frac{\mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{weight}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{wet}\ \mathrm{faces}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{each}\ \mathrm{group}\ }{\mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{weight}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{wet}\ \mathrm{faces}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{the}\ \mathrm{control}}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>Wet</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>faecal output</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mean weight of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>wet</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>faces of each group</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mean weight of</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>wet</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>faces of the control</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equb.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equc"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{Total}\ \mathrm{faecal}\ \mathrm{output}=\frac{\mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{faecal}\ \mathrm{weight}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{each}\ \mathrm{group}}{\mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{weight}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{the}\ \mathrm{control}}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>of Total faecal output</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>Mean faecal weight of each group</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>Mean weight of the control</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equc.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Castor oil induced charcoal meal test</title><p id="Par25">Gastrointestinal motility test by using activated charcoal was done in accordance with Sisay et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Mice of either sex were fasted for 18&#x02009;h with free access to water and treated with the vehicle, standard drug and plant extract according to their respective group as described in section 2.7 based on their fasting weight by oral gavage. After 1 hour of test/ vehicle compound administration, 0.5&#x02009;mL castor oil was administered by oral gavage then 1&#x02009;mL of 5% charcoal suspension was administered orally 1 hour after castor oil treatment. After 1 hour of the charcoal meal, animals were sacrificed by cervical dislocation and the small intestine was dissected out and later the total length covered by a charcoal indicator from the pylorus to cecum was measured and calculated as a percentage of the total length of the small intestine. Finally, the Peristalsis index and proportion of inhibition were calculated by using the following formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].
<disp-formula id="Equd"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{Peristaltic}\ \mathrm{index}=\frac{\mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{distance}\ \mathrm{travelled}\ \mathrm{by}\ \mathrm{charcoal}\ \mathrm{meal}\ }{\mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{length}\ \mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{small}\ \mathrm{intestine}}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:mtext>Peristaltic index</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mean distance travelled</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>by</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>charcoal meal</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Mean length of small intestine</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equd.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Eque"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \%\mathrm{of}\ \mathrm{inhibition}=\frac{\mathrm{PIC}-\mathrm{PIT}}{\mathrm{PIC}}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mtext>of inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>PIC</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>PIT</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>PIC</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Eque.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par26">Where, PIC&#x02009;=&#x02009;Peristaltic index of control; PIT&#x02009;=&#x02009;Peristaltic index of the test group</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Castor oil induced Enteropooling model</title><p id="Par27">The intraluminal fluid accumulation (enteropooling) was carried out based on a method described by Sisay et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Mice were grouped as described earlier and fasted for 18&#x02009;h prior to the experiment. Then the test compound and vehicle were given according to their grouping based on their fasting weight by oral gavage 1 hour prior to castor oil administration. After 1 hour all mice were sacrificed by cervical dislocation, and then the small intestine was isolated and tied with thread at the pyloric end and the ileocaecal junction. Then the weight of filled intestine was measured and the content was drained into a graduated cylinder and volume was measured, later the weight of empty intestine was re-measured again and the change in the full and empty intestine was calculated. Finally, the percentage reduction of intestinal discharge (volume) and weight of intestinal content were calculated by comparing with a negative control by the following formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].
<disp-formula id="Equf"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{Percentage}\ \mathrm{volume}\ \mathrm{inhibition}=\frac{\mathrm{MVICC}-\mathrm{MVICT}\ }{\mathrm{MVICC}} \times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mtext>Mean Percentage volume inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>MVICC</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>MVICT</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>MVICC</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equf.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par28">Where, MVICC is the Mean volume of the intestinal content of the control group</p><p id="Par29">MVICT is the Mean volume of the intestinal content of the test group.
<disp-formula id="Equg"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{Mean}\ \mathrm{Percentage}\ \mathrm{weight}\ \mathrm{inhibition}=\frac{\mathrm{MWICC}-\mathrm{MWICT}\ }{\mathrm{MWICC}}\times 100 $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mtext>Mean Percentage weight inhibition</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>MWICC</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>MWICT</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>MWICC</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equg.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par30">Where, MWICC is the Mean weight of the intestinal content of the control group</p><p id="Par31">MWICT is the Mean weight of the intestinal content of the test group.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>In vivo anti-Diarrhoeal index</title><p id="Par32">The in vivo anti-diarrhoeal index (ADI) was determined by combining three parameters taken from the above-mentioned models. It was then expressed according to the following formula developed by Aye-than et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].
<disp-formula id="Equh"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{ADI}=\sqrt[3]{Dfreq\ X\  Gmeq\ X\  Pfreq} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16" display="block"><mml:mi>ADI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mroot><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">Dfreq</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">Gmeq</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">Pfreq</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mroot></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equh.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par33">Where, Dfreq is the delay in defecation time as a percentage of negative control,</p><p id="Par34">Gmeq is the gut meal travel reduction as a percentage of negative control.</p><p id="Par35">Pfreq is the reduction in purging frequency in the number of wet stools as a percentage of the negative control.
<disp-formula id="Equi"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ \mathrm{Dfreq}=\frac{\mathrm{MODTG}-\mathrm{MODCG}}{\mathrm{MODCG}} $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18" display="block"><mml:mtext>Dfreq</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>MODTG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>MODCG</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>MODCG</mml:mtext></mml:mfrac></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Article_Equi.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par36">Where, MODTG is Mean onset of diarrhoea in the test group</p><p id="Par37">MODCG is Mean onset of diarrhoea in the control group</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Antibacterial activity test</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Media preparation and inoculum standardization</title><p id="Par38">The standard bacterial medium was prepared and used according to the manufacturers&#x02019; guidelines. According to the Clinical and Laboratory Standard Institute (CLSI), the bacterial turbidity of each species was prepared and standardized. The turbidity of the inoculum tube was adjusted visually by the naked eye against a 0.5 McFarland turbidity equivalence with white background and contrasting black lines in the presence of adequate light by either adding colonies or sterile normal saline solution. It is assumed to contain a bacterial concentration of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL. Then, the standardized suspension was used within 15&#x02009;min of its preparation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Agar well diffusion method</title><p id="Par39">The antibacterial activity of the crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> was done according to Umer et al., and Molla et al., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. It was performed on both American type cell culture (ATCC) and clinical isolates of selected intestinal pathogens obtained from Ayder comprehensive specialized hospital, which were considered as a major cause of diarrhoea such as <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic> (<italic>S. flexneri</italic>) (ATCC-12022), <italic>Salmonella typhi</italic> (<italic>S. typhi</italic>) (ATCC-13062), <italic>Salmonella</italic> species (clinical isolate), <italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC-25922), <italic>E. coli</italic> (Clinical isolate) and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC-27853).</p><p id="Par40">Three test concentrations of plant extract (800&#x02009;mg/mL, 400&#x02009;mg/mL and 200&#x02009;mg/mL), vehicle and standard antibiotic disc were used for determining zone of inhibition. Ceftazidime (30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ disc, for <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>) and ciprofloxacin (0.005&#x02009;mg/disc, for the remaining bacteria) were used as a standard drug and distilled water was used as a negative control. The standard antibacterial discs were selected based on the susceptibility of bacterial species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The antibacterial activity was evaluated by measuring the zone of inhibition against the test organisms by using vernier calliper and then compared with the reference as well as the control. Each procedure was done in triplicates and average values were being taken for further use [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Determination of the minimum inhibitory concentration</title><p id="Par41">Microdilution broth method was used for determining minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. MIC was performed for the test extract that showed acceptable (&#x0003e;&#x02009;7&#x02009;mm) antibacterial activity in agar well diffusion assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The plant extract concentration was ranged from 50&#x02009;mg/mL to 0.0975&#x02009;mg/mL for <italic>S. flexneri</italic> and from 200 to 0.39&#x02009;mg/mL for the remaining bacteria in a descending order from first to tenth column.</p><p id="Par42">The 96 well plates were used for resazurin-based microtitre dilution assay. The lowest concentration of test extract at which no colour change occurred was recorded as the MIC value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Each procedure was carried out in triplicates and average values were taken. In this experimentation, each microtiter plate had a set of two controls. One of the controls was growth control (colour contrast control) which contained all solution except the plant extracts (11th column). It was used to determine the growth of bacteria. The other control was sterility control which was the 12th column contained media and resazurin solution. The sterility control was used to know the sterility of the procedure (the media and resazurin solution). Finally results were compared with reference drug in the CLSI guideline and other literatures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Determination of minimum bactericidal concentration</title><p id="Par43">The minimum bactericidal concentration (MBC) was determined by sub-culturing the contents of wells from the MIC results for individual bacterium as done by previous literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In this method, the contents of all wells resulting in MIC and all concentrations above MIC were streaked using a sterile wire loop on MHA. Then it was incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 24&#x02009;h. The lowest concentration of the extract which showed no bacterial growth was distinguished and verified as the MBC. All procedures were conducted in triplicates and the average value was taken for the MBC of test material against each bacterium.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Preliminary phytochemical screening</title><p id="Par44">The qualitative phytochemical screening for the crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> were done by using standard chemical tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par45">Results were expressed in mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error of the mean (SEM) and comparisons were made between negative control, positive control and treatment groups of various doses using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by <italic>posthoc</italic> Tukey&#x02019;s test using statistical package for the social sciences (SPSS) version 20.0. All data were analyzed at 95% confidence interval and <italic>P</italic>-values less than 0.05 was considered as statistically significant. Coefficient of determination (linear regression analysis) (R<sup>2</sup>), was also determined by using Microsoft excel 2013. The analyzed data were presented using tables and figures.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec23"><title>Acute Oral toxicity test</title><p id="Par46">After a single oral administration of limit dose (2000&#x02009;mg/kg), animals did not show any change in motor activity, lacrimation, diarrhoea, convulsion, and coma. In addition, no physical, behavioural and neurological changes were recorded. During the total period of acute toxicity study, none of the animals show any change in weight and appetite (food and water intake). No mortality was also recorded during the total 14&#x02009;days of the observation period.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Anti-diarrhoeal activity</title><sec id="Sec25"><title>Effects on Castor oil induced Diarrhoea in mice</title><p id="Par47">The crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> showed a dose-dependent response in prolonging the onset of diarrhoea. As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref><bold>,</bold> the onset of diarrhoea was significantly protracted at doses of 200 and 400&#x02009;mg/kg as compared to the negative control (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). In addition, the largest test dose has shown maximum prolongation in diarrhoeal onset as compared to the standard drug loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg. Moreover, all test doses of the crude root extract significantly decreased (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) the average number and weight of wet faces as compared to the negative control.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The Antidiarrhoeal effects of the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> on castor oil-induced diarrhoeal model in mice</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Dose Administered</th><th>Onset of Diarrhoea (Min)</th><th>No of wet faeces</th><th>Total No of faeces</th><th>Average weight of wet faeces (gm)</th><th>Average weight of total faeces (gm)</th><th>% Reduction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5"><bold>80% BAE</bold></td><td>DW 10&#x02009;mL/kg</td><td>76.17 &#x000b1; 2.07</td><td>7.5 &#x000b1; 0.43</td><td>8.17 &#x000b1; 0.48</td><td>0.76 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td>0.83 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>166.33 &#x000b1; 6.97<sup>a3c3</sup></td><td>1.33 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup>a3c3</sup></td><td>2.67 &#x000b1; 0.42<sup>a3c2</sup></td><td>0.14 &#x000b1; 0.03<sup>a3c2</sup></td><td>0.23 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>a3c2</sup></td><td>82.22%</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 100&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>89.50 &#x000b1; 2.50<sup>b3d3e3</sup></td><td>3.5 &#x000b1; 0.22<sup>a3b3d3e3</sup></td><td>4.83 &#x000b1; 0.31<sup>a3b2e2</sup></td><td>0.38 &#x000b1; 0.04 <sup>a3b2d1e3</sup></td><td>0.50 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>a3b2e2</sup></td><td>53.33%</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 200&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>151.00 &#x000b1; 3.17<sup>a3c3e2</sup></td><td>1.33 &#x000b1; 0.21<sup>a3c3</sup></td><td>3.33 &#x000b1; 0.33<sup>a3</sup></td><td>0.18 &#x000b1; 0.03 <sup>a3c1</sup></td><td>0.31 &#x000b1; 0.04<sup>a3</sup></td><td>82.22%</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 400&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>172.67 &#x000b1; 3.48<sup>a3c3d2</sup></td><td>0.83 &#x000b1; 0.31<sup>a3c3</sup></td><td>2.17 &#x000b1; 0.40<sup>a3c2</sup></td><td>0.11 &#x000b1; 0.04 <sup>a3c3</sup></td><td>0.19 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>a3c2</sup></td><td>88.89%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data&#x02019;s are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6); <sup>a</sup> compared with negative control values; <sup>b</sup> compared with loperamide; <sup>c</sup> compared with 100&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>d</sup> compared with 200&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>e</sup> compared with 400&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>1</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup>2</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup>3</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; <italic>DW</italic> Distilled water, <italic>BAE B. antidysenterica</italic> extract</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par48">As presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref><bold><italic>,</italic></bold> the dose-dependent decrement in percentage weight of wet faecal output and percentage weight of the total number of faecal outputs were recorded. The largest dose showed the highest inhibition of defecation (88.89%), the lowest percentage of mean wet faecal output (14.07%) and a total number of faecal output (22.79%) as compared with all tested doses of the extract and positive control (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Percentage weight faecal output inhibition of the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> in castor oil-induced model. LD, low dose; MD, middle dose; HD, high dose; ** <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2020_3001_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Effects on Castor oil induced intestinal transit in mice</title><p id="Par49">Results from the charcoal meal intestinal transit model revealed that the crude extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> showed significant inhibition of intestinal transit at all test doses. The maximum antimotility effect was recorded in the highest dose of test extract 400&#x02009;mg/kg (67.59%), which is comparable with the standard drug loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg (67.35%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The effects of root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> on gastrointestinal transit in mice</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Extract</th><th>Dose Administered</th><th>Length of small intestine (cm)</th><th>Distance covered by charcoal meal (cm)</th><th>Peristaltic index (%)</th><th>% Inhibition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5">80% BAE</td><td>DW 10&#x02009;mL/kg</td><td>57.50 &#x000b1; 0.43</td><td>50.33 &#x000b1; 0.84</td><td>87.56 &#x000b1; 1.61</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>57.83 &#x000b1; 0.83</td><td>16.50 &#x000b1; 0.76<sup>a3c3d3</sup></td><td>28.59 &#x000b1; 1.50 <sup>a3c3d3</sup></td><td>67.35</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 100&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>57.83 &#x000b1; 0.79</td><td>30.83 &#x000b1; 0.67<sup>a3b3d3e3</sup></td><td>53.30 &#x000b1; 0.67 <sup>a3b3d3e3</sup></td><td>39.13</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 200&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>58.33 &#x000b1; 0.54</td><td>22.83 &#x000b1; 0.84<sup>a3b3c3e3</sup></td><td>39.11 &#x000b1; 1.18 <sup>a3b3c3e3</sup></td><td>55.34</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 400&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>56.83 &#x000b1; 0.48</td><td>16.17 &#x000b1; 1.19<sup>a3c3d3</sup></td><td>28.38 &#x000b1; 1.87 <sup>a3c3d3</sup></td><td>67.59</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data&#x02019;s are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6); <sup>a</sup> compared with negative control values; <sup>b</sup> compared with loperamide; <sup>c</sup> compared with 100&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>d</sup> compared with 200&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>e</sup> compared with 400&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>1</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup>2</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup>3</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; <italic>DW</italic> distilled water, <italic>BAE B. antidysenterica</italic> extract</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Effects on Castor oil induced Enteropooling</title><p id="Par50">The 80% hydro-methanolic crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> showed a significant reduction in both average weight and volume of intestinal contents as compared with the negative control. Significant inhibition of intestinal milked volume was recorded on 200&#x02009;mg/kg (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and 400&#x02009;mg/kg (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) test dose relative to the negative control group. The highest dose of test extract 400&#x02009;mg/kg showed comparable result (37.76%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) as of standard drug Loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg (39.80%, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The effects of the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> on gastrointestinal fluid accumulation in mice</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Extract</th><th>Dose Administered</th><th>Volume of intestinal contents (mL)</th><th>% Inhibition</th><th>Weight of intestinal contents (gm)</th><th>% Inhibition</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5">80% BAE</td><td>DW 10&#x02009;mL/kg</td><td>0.82 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1.07 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>0.49 &#x000b1; 0.04<sup>a3c2</sup></td><td>39.80</td><td>0.71 &#x000b1; 0.03<sup>a2</sup></td><td>34.31</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 100&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>0.71 &#x000b1; 0.03<sup>b2e2</sup></td><td>13.27</td><td>0.90 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td>16.25</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 200&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>0.57 &#x000b1; 0.05<sup>a3</sup></td><td>30.61</td><td>0.78 &#x000b1; 0.06<sup>a1</sup></td><td>27.82</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 400&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>0.51 &#x000b1; 0.02<sup>a3c2</sup></td><td>37.76</td><td>0.72 &#x000b1; 0.06 <sup>a2</sup></td><td>32.56</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data&#x02019;s are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6); <sup>a</sup> compared with negative control values; <sup>b</sup> compared with loperamide; <sup>c</sup> compared with 100&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>d</sup> compared with 200&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>e</sup> compared with 400&#x02009;mg/kg; <sup>1</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, <sup>2</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <sup>3</sup><italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; <italic>DW</italic> distilled water, <italic>BAE B. antidysenterica</italic> extract</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par51">The other parameter recorded in this model was percentage inhibition in the average weight of intestinal contents. As shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, significant inhibition were recorded in 200 and 400&#x02009;mg/kg dose of test extract with percentage inhibition of 27.82% (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) and 32.56% (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) respectively. The highest level of intestinal fluid reduction was recorded in the standard drug loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg (34.31%), which is comparable with the highest dose of test extract.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>In vivo anti-diarrhoeal index</title><p id="Par52">As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref><bold>,</bold> 32.04, 73.22 and 87.6% were recorded as in vivo ADI for 100, 200 and 400&#x02009;mg/kg dose of test extract. The 400&#x02009;mg/kg dose showed the highest in vivo anti-diarrhoeal index, which is comparable to the standard drug loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg dose (83.07%).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>In vivo antidiarrhoeal index of the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Extract</th><th>Dose Administered</th><th>Delay in defecation time (Dfreq)<break/>(%)</th><th>Gut meal travel distance (Gmeq) (%)</th><th>Purging frequency in number of wet stools (%)</th><th>In vivo Anti-diarrhoeal Index (ADI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5">80% BAE</td><td>DW 10&#x02009;mL/kg</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Loperamide 3&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>118.37</td><td>67.35</td><td>82.22</td><td>83.07</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 100&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>17.50</td><td>39.13</td><td>53.33</td><td>32.04</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 200&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>98.24</td><td>55.34</td><td>82.22</td><td>73.22</td></tr><tr><td>BAE 400&#x02009;mg/kg</td><td>126.69</td><td>67.59</td><td>88.89</td><td>87.60</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>BAE B. antidysenterica</italic> extract, <italic>DW</italic> distilled water</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Antibacterial activity</title><sec id="Sec30"><title>Antibacterial zone of inhibition</title><p id="Par53">The concentration-dependent effect (R<sup>2</sup>) values were calculated for each bacterial species accordingly, R<sup>2</sup> of 80% methanolic extract was 0.873, 0.890, 0.930 and 0.987, for ATCC strain of <italic>S. typhi, E. coli, P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>S. flexneri</italic> respectively. The maximum average zone of inhibition was recorded at 800&#x02009;mg/mL concentration of test extract as 22.0, 20.7, 19.3 and 18.3&#x02009;mm for ATCC strains of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic>S. flexneri</italic>, <italic>S. typhi</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> respectively. On the contrary, no bacterial growth inhibition was observed in all concentrations of 80% methanolic extract against clinical isolates of <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>Salmonella</italic> species.</p><p id="Par54">In Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>, the mean comparison of different concentrations of extract within a group and with the standard antibacterial disc was presented. As shown in the table, all concentrations of plant extract showed a statistically significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) as compared with the positive control in all standard bacteria. In addition, the 200&#x02009;mg/mL concentration of extract had significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) for <italic>S. typhi</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 for <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> as compared with 400&#x02009;mg/mL of crude extract. It had also a <italic>p</italic>-value &#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 as compared with 800&#x02009;mg/mL concentration for <italic>S. typhi</italic>, <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> while, the p-value is less than 0.01 for <italic>S. flexneri</italic>. In addition, the 400&#x02009;mg/kg concentration of test extract showed a significant difference (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) as compared with 800&#x02009;mg/mL for <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, while <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 for <italic>S. flexneri</italic>.
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Zone of inhibition for the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> against selected diarrhoea causing bacteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Extract</th><th>Concentration</th><th><italic>S. flexneri</italic> (ATCC-12022)<break/>(mm)</th><th><italic>S. typhi</italic> (ATCC-13062)<break/>(mm)</th><th><italic>Salmonella Spp.</italic> (CI)<break/>(mm)</th><th><italic>E. coli</italic> (ATCC-25922)<break/>(mm)</th><th><italic>E. coli</italic> (CI)<break/>(mm)</th><th><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (ATCC-27853)<break/>(mm)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3">80% BAE</td><td>BAE 200&#x02009;mg/mL</td><td>14.7 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3d2</sup></td><td>14.7 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3c2d3</sup></td><td>NA</td><td>14.0 &#x000b1; 0.00 <sup>a3c2d3</sup></td><td>NA</td><td>16.7 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3c3d3</sup></td></tr><tr><td>BAE 400&#x02009;mg/mL</td><td>17.3 &#x000b1; 0.67 <sup>a3d1</sup></td><td>17.7 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3b2</sup></td><td>NA</td><td>16.7 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3b1d2</sup></td><td>NA</td><td>19.7 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3b3d2</sup></td></tr><tr><td>BAE 800&#x02009;mg/mL</td><td>20.7 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3b2c1</sup></td><td>19.3 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3b3</sup></td><td>NA</td><td>18.3 &#x000b1; 0.33 <sup>a3b1c3</sup></td><td>NA</td><td>22.0 &#x000b1; 0.00 <sup>a3b3c2</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Standards</td><td>Cipro <italic>5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g</italic>/disc</td><td>29.3 &#x000b1; 1.20</td><td>34.3 &#x000b1; 0.67</td><td>18.0 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>32.3 &#x000b1; 0.33</td><td>NA</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Cefta 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/disc</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>10.3 &#x000b1; 0.33</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are expressed as Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3), <sup>a</sup> compared to positive control; <sup>b</sup> compared to 200&#x02009;mg/mL; <sup>c</sup> compared to 400&#x02009;mg/mL; <sup>d</sup> compared to 800&#x02009;mg/mL; <sup>1</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <sup>2</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.01, <sup>3</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;0.001. The negative control has shown no antibacterial activity. The positive controls: <italic>BAE Brucea antidysenterica</italic> extract, <italic>Cipro</italic> Ciprofloxacin, <italic>Cefta</italic> Ceftazidime, <italic>NA</italic> No Activity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Minimum inhibitory concentration and minimum bactericidal concentration of crude extract against bacterial species</title><p id="Par55">According to the result obtained from 96 well microtiter plate microdilution test, the minimum inhibitory concentration of the crude extract against the tested species were less than or equal to (&#x02264;) 3.13&#x02009;mg/mL for all tested bacteria species. As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, the lowest MIC of the crude root extract was recorded as 0.39&#x02009;mg/mL for <italic>S. flexneri</italic> and the highest is for <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> with a concentration of 3.13&#x02009;mg/mL.
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Minimum inhibitory concentration and minimum bactericidal concentration of 80% methanolic root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Bacterial species</th><th colspan="3">80% methanolic BAE</th></tr><tr><th>MIC (mg/mL)</th><th>MBC (mg/mL)</th><th>MBC/MIC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><italic>S. flexneri</italic></td><td>0.39 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>1.56 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>4.00</td></tr><tr><td><italic>S. typhi</italic></td><td>1.56 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>3.13 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>2.00</td></tr><tr><td><italic>E. coli</italic></td><td>2.08 &#x000b1; 0.52</td><td>8.33 &#x000b1; 2.08</td><td>4.00</td></tr><tr><td><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic></td><td>3.13 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>200 &#x000b1; 0.00</td><td>63.89</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are expressed as Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3); <italic>BAE B. antidysenterica</italic> extract</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par56">As presented in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, the MBC values ranged from 1.56&#x02009;mg/mL (<italic>S. flexneri</italic>) to 200&#x02009;mg/mL (<italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec32"><title>Bacteriostatic/ bactericidal/ nature of the crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic></title><p id="Par57">The bacteriostatic and bactericidal nature of the plant extract was also evaluated to assess its potential against bacterial strains. There are certain circumstances where cidal agents are preferable over static agents and vice versa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Antibacterial substance is said to be bactericidal if the ratio of MBC/MIC is &#x02264;4 and bacteriostatic if MBC/MIC &#x0003e;&#x02009;4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. As presented in Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, except <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, the crude plant extract showed bactericidal activity. Moreover, extracts with MICs values between 0.1 and 0.625&#x02009;mg/mL had moderate activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Phytochemical constituents</title><p id="Par58">As presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab7" ref-type="table">7</xref>, the phytochemical analysis of the crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> indicates the presence of different bioactive components.
<table-wrap id="Tab7"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Phytochemical composition of the crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Metabolites Tested</th><th>80% methanolic BAE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Alkaloids</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Saponins</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Tannins</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Polyphenols</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Terpenoids</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Flavonoids</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td>Anthroquinones</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par59"><italic>BAE B. antidysenterica</italic> extract, +: Present, &#x02212;: Absent</p></sec><sec id="Sec34"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par60">Diarrhoea is characterized by rapid and frequent passage of semisolid or liquid faecal material. It involves decreased in absorption of fluid, increased motility of the intestinal tract and increased secretions. In addition, diarrhoea leads to loss of electrolytes particularly sodium (Na<sup>+</sup>) and water, and finally end up with dehydration and death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">80% methanol was used as a macerating solvent for plant extraction and it was similar with other laboratory works done on <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In general, hydro-alcoholic co-solvents such as 80% methanol seem to possess the optimum solubility characteristics for initial crude extraction and provide high extraction yield [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. However, despite the several works interests in the polyphenols extraction, there is no single solvent which may be considered standard because it is usually different for different plant matrices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par62">Castor oil-induced diarrhoeal model is the first model to assess the ability of test extract towards its antidiarrhoeal activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. It causes an imbalance between the secretary and absorptive processes in the small intestine by producing inflammation and local irritation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. After oral administration, &#x0201c;ricinoleic acid&#x0201d; the active constituent of CO, is released by intestinal lipases. Consequently, it activates intestinal smooth-muscle cells via endothelial prostanoid receptors (EP<sub>3</sub>). Then it induces fluid and electrolyte secretion secondary to stimulation of an active anion secretory process, which is mediated by cAMP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Therefore, the use of castor oil as diarrhoea inducer for all models is reasonable since it resembles the pathophysiologic processes and ensures the actual diarrhoeal (secretory and inflammatory diarrhoea) diseases in humans.</p><p id="Par63">Results in this experiment verified that the crude root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> showed a dose-dependent response by prolonging the onset of diarrhoea on mice. The highest activity was seen in the two higher doses of test extract while the lower dose was devoid of significant prolongation. This might be associated with the smallest dose of test extract has not sufficient ability to prolong the onset of diarrhoea. As explained by other reports doses having lower antimotility and/or antisecretory effects are less likely to address all the parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">The root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> also significantly decrease the average number and weight of wet faces in the castor oil-induced diarrhoea model. Studies proved that an increase in stool frequency and volume showed the severity of diarrhoea and also a decreased in wet faces was used as a sign of recovery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. According to Degu et al, a decrease in stool frequency was associated with antisecretory and antimotility mechanisms, by which it decreases the number and weight of wet stool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In addition, a study done by Lakshmanan et al, stated that the decreased in stool volume was mediated either by an antisecretory mechanism, reduction in intestinal muscle tone and/or decreased peristalsis of the gastrointestinal tract, which can slow the movement of faecal matter through the GI tract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p><p id="Par65">Gastrointestinal motility was significantly decreased at all test doses of crude extract. Different studies confirmed that the peristalsis in the GI system was increased in case of diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The reduction of GI peristalsis is one of the mechanisms by which antidiarrhoeal agents can act. For example, the standard drug (loperamide) used in this study acts by activation of &#x003bc; receptors that inhibit the release of acetylcholine to enhance phasic colonic segmentation and inhibit peristalsis, thus increasing intestinal transit time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The report was compared with similar reports done by Degu et al and Sisay et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. All the test doses of plant extracts showed a significant decrement in peristaltic movement.</p><p id="Par66">The third model in this study was castor oil-induced enteropooling model, which is aimed to assess the potential inhibition of secretory components in the gastrointestinal tract after castor oil administration for the induction of diarrhoea. Outcomes in this model proved that the 80% methanolic extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> showed a dose-dependent reduction in both average weight and volume of intestinal contents at all test doses as compared with the negative control. Even though the maximum effect was seen in the standard drug, the highest dose of plant extract exhibit a comparable effect. As described in Beubler, the gastrointestinal secretions secondary to castor oil administration are related to ricinoleic acid, which activates the nitric oxide pathway and induces nitric oxide (NO) dependent gut secretion along with prostaglandin synthesis. So that the possible mechanism is illustrated as inhibition of the nitric oxide pathway, by that it halts GI secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>].</p><p id="Par67">The combined effect of antidiarrhoeal agents was generally investigated by calculating ADI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. As presented in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, ADI values showed the dose-dependent nature of each parameter. The highest dose of the crude extract showed highest ADI as compared with corresponding doses and also better than the standard drug. This might be due to its better potential in prolongation of onset of diarrhoea, decrement of peristaltic movement and halting of purging frequency in the GI system as compared with the standard drug and respective doses.</p><p id="Par68">Different mechanisms are hypothesized as a mechanism for the antidiarrhoeal effect of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic>. Compounds inhibiting prostaglandin inhibition has an ability to prevent diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Similarly, a study done by Tessema et al, showed that <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> has an anti-inflammatory effect, which might be attributed to inhibition of castor oil-induced prostaglandin synthesis and prevention of diarrhoea by inhibiting stimulation of intestinal secretions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].</p><p id="Par69">The other activity done in this study was the determination of antibacterial activity for selected diarrhoea causing bacteria. Based on the results obtained the highest antibacterial activity was observed in the highest concentration (800&#x02009;mg/mL) of crude extract. The maximum zone of inhibition was recorded for ATCC strain of <italic>P. aeruginosa.</italic> Although the test extract has a smaller zone of inhibition as compared with the positive control in the case of <italic>S. flexneri, S. typhi</italic> and <italic>E. coli,</italic> it has better zone of inhibition for <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. This finding was inline with a study done on the leaf extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]<italic>.</italic> According to Fentahun et al, the chloroform leaf extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> has showed highest (11&#x02009;mm) zone of inhibition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Other results done on different plants against <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> showed that the zone of inhibition was ranging between 9 and 21&#x02009;mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. This may indicate that the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> has been promising activity against <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and important to tackle diarrhoea secondary to chronic diseases.</p><p id="Par70">The MIC and MBC results from this experiment showed that the root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> has the ability to inhibit and kill bacteria. The MIC of an extract is regarded as good if the values are less than 0.1&#x02009;mg/mL, moderate if it is between 0.1 and 0.625&#x02009;mg/mL and weak when it is above 0.625&#x02009;mg/mL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Based on this, the MIC of 80% hydro-methanolic crude extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> was ranged from moderate to weak against the tested bacteria strains. This might be related with their zone of inhibition during agar well diffusion assay. According to CLSI (2015a), compounds having a higher zone of inhibition has an ability to inhibit bacterial growth with a smaller concentration as compared with compounds having a low zone of inhibition. In addition, MBC of plant extract were one or more dilution factor greater than MIC values for each bacteria except for <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. It may indicate the sensitivity of test extract for those common diarrhoea causing bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. However, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> is known to utilize its high level intrinsic and acquired resistance mechanisms to counter most antibiotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. In addition, recent finding showed that biofilm-mediated resistance and formation of multidrug-tolerant persister cells are responsible for recalcitrance and relapse of infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. On the other hand, the promising activity of plant extract against <italic>S. flexneri, S. typhi and E. coli</italic> might be used for treatment of bloody diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], inflammatory induced diarrhoea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], traveller diarrhoea and food poisoning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] respectively.</p><p id="Par71">Results of phytochemical screening also support some of the aforementioned mechanisms listed above. According to similar studies done on different plants suggested that the presence of tannins and flavonoids increase colonic water and electrolyte reabsorption. Tannins are known for making intestinal mucosa more resistant by reducing secretion, normalizing deranged water transport and reduction of intestinal transit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Other secondary metabolites like terpenoids and saponins also have the ability to inhibit the release of autacoids like prostaglandins and histamines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Phytochemicals such as phenolic compounds and alkaloids also inhibit intestinal motility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. In addition, flavonoids are also found to display a wide range of biological activities including inhibition of enzymes such as prostaglandin synthase, cyclooxygenase and lipoxygenase that might mainly contribute to its anti-diarrhoeal activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].</p><p id="Par72">The bioactive components, especially tannins and flavonoids, exert a major role on antibacterial activity. Different mechanisms are postulated for the action of these bioactive components. For example, tannins produce antibacterial activity by inactivating numerous enzymes, microbial adhesion, and cell envelope transport proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Other active components like saponins have been reported to possess antibacterial activity, which could be attributed to their ability to form a complex with extracellular proteins, soluble proteins, and bacterial cell walls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Other previous antibacterial studies also proved that the presence of these secondary metabolites has an important role in the inhibition of bacterial growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec35"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par73">Based on this study, the 80% hydro-methanolic root extract of <italic>B. antidysenterica</italic> had promising anti-diarrhoeal and antibacterial activities. The overall antidiarrhoeal activity of the studied plant extract was associated with inhibitory effects on castor oil-induced gastrointestinal motility and fluid secretion. In addition, it has bactericidal activity against most of the studied bacteria. Further studies for solvent fractions, isolation of active principle (s), chemical standardization and elucidating the possible mechanism of action are recommended.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ATCC</term><def><p id="Par5">American type of cell culture</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFU</term><def><p id="Par6">Colony-forming unit</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CLSI</term><def><p id="Par7">Clinical and laboratory standard institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MBC</term><def><p id="Par8">Minimum bactericidal concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MIC</term><def><p id="Par9">Minimum inhibitory concentration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SPSS</term><def><p id="Par10">Statistical package for the social sciences</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Professor Sileshi Nemomissa for authenticating the plant material. We also thank Ethiopian Food and Drug Authority (EFDA), for providing active loperamide.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>KAZ developed the proposal, conducted the experimental activities, analyzed the data, and drafted the manuscript. KBT, DB, DZW, and KAZ contributed to topic selection, design of the study, and data analysis and revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. All authors have read and approved the manuscript and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors thank School of Graduate Studies, Mekelle University for granting sponsorship to the first author. We also thank Norad small research project office for partly supporting the study financially. Funding bodies did not involve in the study design and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets generated and/or analyzed during the study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par74">The protocol approval letter was obtained from the Health Research Ethics Review Committee (HRERC) of College of Health Sciences, Mekelle University and registered as ERC 1537/2018 protocol number on December 11, 2018. In addition, to avoid animal suffering at each stage of the experiment, the internationally accepted laboratory animal care and use guideline was used.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par75">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par76">The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><source>Key facts Scope of diarrhoeal disease. World Heal Organ / Centers Dis Control Prev</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sweetser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating the patient with diarrhea: a case-based approach</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc</source><year>2012</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22677080?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22677080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reintam Blaser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fruhwald</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diarrhoea in the critically ill</article-title><source>Curr Opin Crit Care</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25692805?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25692805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">GBD. Estimates of global, regional, and national morbidity, mortality, and aetiologies of diarrhoeal diseases: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2015. Lancet Infect Dis. 2017;17:909&#x02013;48.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centre for Disease Control and Prevention. Diarrhea: Common Illness, Global Killer. Centers Dis Control Prev. 2012;1&#x02013;4. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/healthywater/pdf/global/programs/globaldiarrhea508c.pdf">https://www.cdc.gov/healthywater/pdf/global/programs/globaldiarrhea508c.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shane AL, Mody RK, Crump JA, Tarr PI, Steiner TS, Kotloff K, et al. 2017 Infectious Diseases Society of America Clinical Practice Guidelines for the Diagnosis and Management of Infectious Diarrhea. Clin Infect Dis. 2017;65:e45&#x02013;80. 10.1093/cid/cix669.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupont</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ACG Clinical Guideline : Diagnosis , Treatment , and Prevention of Acute Diarrheal Infections in Adults</article-title><source>Am J Gastroenterol</source><year>2016</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ajg.2016.126</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27068718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27068718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Traditional Medicine - Sharing Experience from the Field. first. Seohak-Ro, Wansan-Gu, Jeonju, Republic of Korea</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Traditional Medicine and Modern Medicine from Natural Products</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sisay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Engidawork</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibeshi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the antidiarrheal activity of the leaf extracts of Myrtus communis Linn (Myrtaceae) in mice model</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Engidawork</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengistu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the anti-diarrheal activity of the aqueous stem extract of Lantana camara Linn ( Verbenaceae ) in mice</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Engidawork</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibeshi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the anti-diarrheal activity of the leaf extract of Croton macrostachyus Hocsht . ex Del . ( Euphorbiaceae ) in mice model</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26729470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasmal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In-vivo evaluation of anti-diarrhoeal activity of Ethanolic fruit and root extracts of Carissa carandas Linn. (Apocynaceae)</article-title><source>Int J Drug Dev Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>221</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailu</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurmu</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mechesso</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental assessment of antidiarrheal and antisecretory activity of 80% methanolic leaf extract of Zehneria scabra in mice</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24383621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yacob</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibeshi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidiarrheal activity of 80% methanol extract of the aerial part of Ajuga remota Benth (Lamiaceae) in mice</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1277-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26729470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derebe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdulwuhab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wubetu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the Antidiarrheal and Antimicrobial Activities of 80% Methanolic Leaf Extract of Discopodium Penninervum (Hochst.) . Evidence-Based Complement</article-title><source>Altern Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehmood</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkharfy</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on antidiarrheal and antispasmodic activities of Lepidium sativum crude extract in rats</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22006354?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22006354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tadesse H. Phytochemical Investigation on the Seeds of Brucea antidysenterica. Addis Ababa Univ; 2005. p. 1&#x02013;53. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://etd.aau.edu.et/bitstream/handle/123456789/1963/Haregewine%20Tadesse.pdf?sequence=1&#x00026;isAllowed=y">http://etd.aau.edu.et/bitstream/handle/123456789/1963/Haregewine%20Tadesse.pdf?sequence=1&#x00026;isAllowed=y</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ablat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Awang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shilpi</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of antidiabetic and antioxidant properties of Brucea javanica seed</article-title><source>Sci World J</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><fpage>786130</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kefe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Erko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimalarial properties of crude extracts of seeds of Brucea antidysenterica and leaves of Ocimum lamiifolium</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1098-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26729470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Giday</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Animut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activities of selected medicinal plants in traditional treatment of human wounds in Ethiopia</article-title><source>Asian Pac J Trop Biomed</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2221-1691(11)60082-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23569795?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fentahun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilkal</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Amsalu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemayehu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amsalu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial evaluation and phytochemical analysis of selected medicinal plants against some pathogenic enteric Bacteria in Gozamin District, Ethiopia</article-title><source>Aust J Pharm</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayele</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Regasa</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Delesa</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial and antagonistic activity of selected traditional medicinal plants and herbs from east Wollega zone against clinical isolated human pathogens</article-title><source>Sci Technol Arts Res J</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>179</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillin</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Suffness</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bruceantin , a Potent Amoebicide from a Plant , Brucea antidysenterica</article-title><source>Antimicrob AGENTS Chemother</source><year>1982</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><?supplied-pmid 6100431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6100431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current developments in the discovery and Design of new Drug Candidates from plant natural product leads</article-title><source>J Nat Prod</source><year>2004</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14987069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14987069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teklehaymanot</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnobotanical study of knowledge and medicinal plants use by the people in Dek Island in Ethiopia</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol J</source><year>2009</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Amsalu N, Bezie Y, Fentahun M, Alemayehu A, Amsalu G. Use and Conservation of Medicinal Plants by Indigenous People of Gozamin Wereda, East Gojjam Zone of Amhara Region, Ethiopia: An Ethnobotanical Approach. Evidence-Based Complement Altern Med. 2018;2018:1&#x02013;23. 10.1155/2018/2973513.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Getaneh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Girma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ethnobotanical study of medicinal plants in Debre Libanos Wereda, Central Ethiopia</article-title><source>African J Plant Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>379</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woldeab</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Regassa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Megersa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal plants used for treatment of Diarrhoeal related diseases in Ethiopia</article-title><source>Evid Based Complement Altern Med.</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ILAR</collab></person-group><article-title>The 1996 Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</article-title><source>ILAR J</source><year>1996</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ilar.38.1.41</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>OECD</collab></person-group><article-title>Acute oral toxicity&#x02013;up-and-down-procedure (UDP)</article-title><source>OECD Guidel Test Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tekewe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidiarrhoeal and antimicrobial activity of Calpurnia aurea leaf extract</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23280361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Than</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hmone</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tha</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-diarrhoea1 Eflicacy of Some Burmese Indigenous Drug Formulations in Experimental Diarrhoea1 Test Models</article-title><source>Int J Crude Drug Res</source><year>1989</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>200</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CLSI</collab></person-group><article-title>M07-A10: Methods for Dilution Antimicrobial Susceptibility Tests for Bacteria That Grow Aerobically</article-title><source>Approved Stand</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Alemayehu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibeshi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the in vitro antibacterial activity of the solvent fractions of the leaves of Rhamnus prinoides L &#x02019; Herit ( Rhamnaceae ) against pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-016-1279-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26729470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CLSI</collab></person-group><source>M100-S25 performance standards for antimicrobial</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Wayne</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harborne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>A guide to modern techniques of plant analysis</source><year>1998</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Asmerom D, Hailu GS, Yimer EM, Bitew H, Kahsay G. Antimicrobial evaluation of latex and TLC fractions from the leaves of Aloe adigratana Reynolds. Evid Based Complement Altern Med. 2020;2020. 10.1155/2020/8312471.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kon&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Atindehou</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Terreaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hostettmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dosso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional medicine in north C&#x002c6; ote-d &#x02019; Ivoire : screening of 50 medicinal plants for antibacterial activity</article-title><source>J Ethnopharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15182903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15182903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avoiding pitfalls in determining antimicrobial activity of plant extracts and publishing the results</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-019-2519-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30606178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bafna</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herbal Antidiarrhoeals : a review</article-title><source>Int J Res Pharm Biomed Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>649</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmi</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dioso</surname><given-names>R(II)P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of Diarrhoeal Diseases Among Children under Five Years in East African Countries from 2012&#x02013;2017</article-title><source>Asean J Sci Technol Dev</source><year>2017</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>51</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thouri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chahdoura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>El Arem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Omri Hichri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Hassin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Achour</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of solvents extraction on phytochemical components and biological activities of Tunisian date seeds (var. Korkobbi and Arechti)</article-title><source>BMC Complement Altern Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kritika</surname><given-names>HEM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants used for treatment of diarrhea : an Ayurvedic prospective plants used for treatment of diarrhea : an ayurvedic prospective</article-title><source>Innovare J Ayurvedic Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Racusen</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ricinoleic acid stimulation of active anion secretion in colonic mucosa of the rat</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1979</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><?supplied-pmid 220281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">220281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Van Tonningen MR. Gastrointestinal and antilipidemic agents and spasmolytics. In: Drugs During Pregnancy and Lactation. 2nd ed: Elsevier B.V; 2007. p. 94&#x02013;122. 10.1016/B978-044452072-2/50009-4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tunaru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Althoff</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusing</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Diener</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Offermanns</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Castor oil induces laxation and uterus contraction via ricinoleic acid activating prostaglandin EP3 receptors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>9179</fpage><lpage>9184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1201627109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22615395?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22615395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harig</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute diarrhea in adults</article-title><source>Postgrad Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00325481.1989.11704502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakshmanan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazumder</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasmal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganguly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis, antispasmodic and antidiarrheal activities of some 1-substituted imidazole derivatives</article-title><source>Acta Pharma</source><year>2011</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>236</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardi</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Semrad</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Surawicz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannella</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gastro 2013 APDW/WCOG Shanghai working party report: chronic diarrhea: definition, classification, diagnosis</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24117999?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24117999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Antidiarrhoeal drugs as adjunctive therapies for acute Diarrhoea in children</article-title><source>Int J Pediatr</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beubler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Domschke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of Prostaglandins in Intestinal Fluid Secretion</article-title><source>Prostaglandins and Leukotrienes in Gastrointestinal Diseases</source><year>2011</year><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>47</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunaydin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilge</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs at the molecular level</article-title><source>Eurasian J Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5152/eurasianjmed.2018.0010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30002579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30002579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tessema</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Makonnen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Debella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Molla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of in vivo wound healing and anti-inflammatory activity of crude extract of the fruits of Brucea antidysentrica in mice</article-title><source>Wound Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.wndm.2018.05.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mummed B, Abraha A, Feyera T, Nigusse A, Assefa S. In Vitro Antibacterial Activity of Selected Medicinal Plants in the Traditional Treatment of Skin and Wound Infections in Eastern Ethiopia. Biomed Res Int. 2018;2018:1&#x02013;8. 10.1155/2018/1862401.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yemata</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetene</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro evaluation of the antibacterial activity of some medicinal plant extracts against Xanthomonas campestris pv. musacearum</article-title><source>Ethiop J Sci Technol</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>17</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Famuyide</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aro</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasina</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Eloff</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcgaw</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial activity and mode of action of acetone crude leaf extracts of under- investigated Syzygium and Eugenia ( Myrtaceae ) species on multidrug resistant porcine diarrhoeagenic Escherichia coli</article-title><source>BMC Vet Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30606179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adlard</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirov</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa as a cause of infectious diarrhoea</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><year>1998</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9747778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9747778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Raudonis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Glick</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance in Pseudomonas aeruginosa : mechanisms and alternative therapeutic strategies</article-title><source>Biotechnol Adv</source><year>2019</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2018.11.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30500353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30500353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlos</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saniel</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etiology and epidemiology of diarrhea</article-title><source>Phil JMicrobiol Infect Dis</source><year>1990</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>53</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cooke</collab></person-group><article-title>Causes and management of diarrhoea in children in a clinical setting</article-title><source>S Afr J Clin Nutr</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diemert</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention and self-treatment of traveler &#x02019; s diarrhea</article-title><source>Am Soc Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>594</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakare</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Magbagbeola</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Akinwande</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Okunowo</surname><given-names>OW</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antidiarrhoeal activity of aqueous leaf extract of <italic>Momordica charantia</italic> in rats</article-title><source>J Pharmacogn Phyther</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palombo</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytochemicals from Traditional Medicinal Plants used in the Treatment of Diarrhoea : Modes of Action and Effects on Intestinal Function</article-title><source>Phytother Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>724</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>724</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary supplementation of green tea by-products on growth performance , meat quality , blood parameters and immunity in finishing pigs</article-title><source>J Med Plants Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2458</fpage><lpage>2467</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>