<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fenofibrate is a cholesterol-lowering drug with a high lipophilicity, whose oral bioavailability in hard gelatin capsules is about 60%, but highly variable among individuals [
 <xref rid="B111-nutrients-11-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>]. Wei et al. [
 <xref rid="B112-nutrients-11-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>] investigated the oral bioavailability of fenofibrate formulated with SEDDSs, consisting of TPGS1000 and Tween 20 or Tween 80 as surfactants. Fenofibrate release from the SEDDSs was complete within 30 min, but release from the commercial product (Tricor
 <sup class="sup">®</sup>) was limited. A pharmacokinetic study of healthy volunteers examined the effect of different forms of oral fenofibrate at a dose of 54 mg. Tricor
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> had the greatest AUC (87 μg∙h mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>), followed by SEDDSs containing Tween 20 (53 μg∙h mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) and SEDDSs containing Tween 80 (52 μg∙h mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). Consumption of water with oral SEDDSs and the agitation of GI tract may be insufficient to enhance the self-emulsifying process that is necessary for in vivo dissolution. Another study examined the oral absorption of SEDDSs (droplet diameter: 205 to 379 nm, depending on the oil:surfactant ratio) loaded with fenobribrate that were composed of Myritol (oil phase) and TPGS1000 (surfactant) [
 <xref rid="B113-nutrients-11-00068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]. These researchers then selected two optimized SEDDSs for analysis of the pharmacokinetics in healthy subjects receiving oral fenofibrate containing Tween 80 or with a high oil:surfactant ratio. The t
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> was greatest for Tricor
 <sup class="sup">®</sup> (2.8 h), followed by Tween 80 SEDDSs (2.0 h) and high-oil SEDDSs (1.8 h). The bioavailability was also 1.2-fold greater for high-oil SEDDSs than Tricor
 <sup class="sup">®</sup>. However, loading fenofibrate into Tween 80 SEDDSs reduced the AUC. 
 <xref rid="nutrients-11-00068-t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref> summarizes the pharmacokinetic parameters of oral drug delivery assisted by TPGS-containing SEDDSs that were designed to increase bioavailability.
</p>
