<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As Ec.Chf was the most active fraction in α-glucosidase inhibition and antioxidant assays, so it was subjected to 
 <italic>in-vivo</italic> and GC-MS analysis for preliminary identification of bioactive compounds. The GC-MS resulted in the identification of 60 compounds. Out of these, 15 compounds were found to represent the major peaks of the spectrum. Several compounds identified in the GC-MS data were found active in terms of anti-diabetic and antioxidant potentials as evident from their reported literature. In anti-diabetic context, these include thymol, nerolidol, neophytadiene, falcarinol, linolenic acid, palmitic acid, pyrrolidione derivative etc. Briefly, the thymol a monoterpene isolated from 
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic> and reported to possess antioxidant and anti-diabetic potentials (Hyun et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Nerolidol and neophytadiene are terpenes found in many plants, for example, it has been found recently in the extract of 
 <italic>Achillea ligustica</italic> and in the extract was also assayed for its anti-radical and anti-diabetic potentials with excellent results (Conforti et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Similarly, falcarinol, a known pesticide which is also found in some plant extracts along with anti-diabetic activity (An et al., 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In the same way, linolenic acid has also been reported to possess anti-diabetic potential (Kato et al., 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). Palmitic acid has also been proven to be an excellent candidate in type-2 diabetes mellitus (Chae et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Correspondingly, the pyrolidone derivative has been proven to possess strong α-glucosidase inhibitory and anti-inflammatory properties (Trapero and Llebaria, 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Jan et al., 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Moreover, several antioxidant compounds identified in the GC-MS spectrum have been reported to scavenge the free radicals effectively. Some of which include thymol, tocopherol, palmitate, phytol, triacontane, cyclohexene, 3-(1,5-dimethyl-4-hexenyl)-6-methylene etc. The thymol has been verified previously to possess strong antioxidant potential (Braga et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The vitamin E is also an excellent antioxidant compound used in various diseased conditions (Müller et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In the same way, ascorbyl palmitate has been reported to possess antioxidant properties (Hra et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). The antioxidant activity of phytol has been demonstrated by several investigators (Santos et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Likewise, the 16-hydroxy-18-Triacontane and 4-hydroxy-triacontane-16,18-dione has been isolated as a natural antioxidant from Eucalyptus leaf (Osawa and Namiki, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>). The cyclohexene, 3-(1,5-dimethyl-4-hexenyl)-6-methylene was previously identified in the Karungkuravai (a type of medicinal rice) and assayed for antioxidant activity with positive results (Krishnanunni et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). All the putative bioactive compounds identified in the Ec.Chf are shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. The identification of numerous bioactive compounds in the Ec.Chf and the current investigational studies shows the role of 
 <italic>E. caeruleum</italic> in the management of oxidative stress and diabetes mellitus.
</p>
