<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To further test the hypothesis, we examined whether another group of parasitic plants also exhibit the interfamily plant-grafting capability. We used 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic>, the holoparasitic plants in Convolvulaceae, for the test. The host range of 
 <italic>Cuscuta campestris</italic>, a species of 
 <italic>Cuscuta</italic> genus, is broad, allowing the haustorium to invade the host stem tissues and connect the vascular xylem bundles (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1a,b</xref>). We grafted 
 <italic>C. campestris</italic> onto 
 <italic>Vinca major</italic> (Apocynaceae). Since 
 <italic>V. major</italic> was a good interfamily grafting partner for 
 <italic>P. japonicum</italic> and the stem thickness was comparable to that of 
 <italic>C. campestris, V. major</italic> could be a suitable plant to be examined. As expected, 
 <italic>C. campestris</italic> scions grafted onto 
 <italic>V. major</italic> also survived more than 4 weeks (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1c–e</xref>). After grafting, the scion of 
 <italic>C. campestris</italic> continued to grow and formed lateral branches on the stems. This observation again supports our idea that ability of parasitism is related to grafting. Another interesting phenomenon was observed when we grafted 
 <italic>C. campestris</italic> onto 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, which shows a high affinity to 
 <italic>Nicotiana</italic> and 
 <italic>P. japonicum</italic> in interfamily grafting and can serve as a host of 
 <italic>C. campestris</italic>. The 
 <italic>C. campestris</italic> scions adhered their tissues to 
 <italic>A. thaliana</italic> rootstock, but only lived for 3 weeks after grafting. A possible explanation for the better viability of parasitism than in grafting is that parasitism may have become more optimized during the evolutionary process. In addition, their growth was inferior to the case of grafting onto the 
 <italic>V. major</italic> stock. This difference could reflect the amount of biomass or graft-compatibility of the stock plants. Asking this causal effect will provide further information about the vigor and compatibility of the graft.
</p>
