<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hepatic and renal function are crucial, with one being used for the metabolism of ingestion and the other for excretion of the waste product, respectively [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. To evaluate the toxicity of any new compound, it is essential to know the state of these two vital organs, which can be verified by biochemical estimation [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In this study, liver function and renal function tests were performed. Protein profile and metabolic biomarkers were also measured. Serum levels of three enzymes (ALT, AST, and ALP) are commonly used as clinical biochemistry markers associated with liver damage [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Among these enzymes, serum levels of ALT and AST of the groups 500, 1000, and 2000 mg/kg/bw were statistically lower when compared to the control. Besides that, all the values found are within the normal range for the species [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Therefore, the variations found are not attributed to the clinical significance or the toxic effect of the HS extract. Significant changes in other liver function markers such as ALP were observed in HS extract treatment groups. The subacute exposure of rats to the higher doses (1000 and 2000 mg/kg) of the HS extract produced a significant increase in ALP (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05; 
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Thus, these increase is known to be in response to biliary obstruction [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A previous study demonstrates that the elevated serum phosphatase in bile duct obstruction originates in the liver and that its rise in serum is due to the induction of this enzyme within the liver [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Moreover, there was a significant increase in triglycerides in rats receiving the HS extract orally at doses of 1000 and 2000 mg/kg, as compared to the control group of rats. An elevation in its level may lead to liver metabolic dysfunction [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In contrast, the data showed that there were no significant differences in urea, creatinine, and albumin levels of the groups treated with HS water extract (500 mg/kg, 1000 mg/kg, and 2000 mg/kg) compared to the control. Hence, HS water extract did not alter the kidney function of the rats.
</p>
