<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In plants, the isoprenoid precursors for the biosynthesis of sesquiterpenes, triterpenes and sterols has generally been assumed to be provided from the mevalonic acid (MVA) pathway in cytosol. In plastids, the 1-deoxy-D-xylulose-5-phosphate (DXP) or known as methylerythritol phosphate (MEP) pathway provides precursors for the production of monoterpenes, diterpenes, and carotenoids (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rohmer, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dong et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singh and Sharma, 2015</xref>). These two pathways biosynthesise C5 homoallylic isoprenoid precursor, that is isopentenyl pyrophosphate (IPP) and its electrophilic allylic isomer dimethylallyl pyrophosphate (DMAPP). An exchange of IPP and DMAPP was observed to happen in between plastids and cytosol even with the spatial partitioning of the two pathways (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dong et al., 2015</xref>). The production of IPP and DMAPP precursors from pyruvate and acetyl-CoA involves a series of enzymes according to the respective pathway (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">Figure 4</xref>). The genes encode for these enzymes have been identified from 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic> species through transcriptome sequencing analysis (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ye et al., 2016</xref>). These C5 isoprene units will later be channeled into the generation of C15 farnesyl pyrophosphate (FPP) by sequential condensation reactions in the presence of FPP synthase (FPS) (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rohmer, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yang et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ye et al., 2016</xref>). The FPS is one of the key-limiting enzymes responsible for the sesquiterpene biosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gaffe et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yang et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu X. M.et al., 2017</xref>). The genes encode for FPS have been cloned from 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria microcarpa</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">Am-FaPS-1</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenmotsu et al., 2011</xref>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria sinensis</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">AsFPS1</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yang et al., 2013</xref>). The transcript level of 
 <italic class="italic">AsFPS1</italic> was reported to be higher in stem and roots than the leaves, suggesting that sesquiterpene synthesis in 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic> species tends to be tissue-specific. Besides, the expression of 
 <italic class="italic">Am-FaPS-1</italic> was shown to be up-regulated upon exposure to methyl jasmonate (MeJA), yeast extract and Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup>-ionophore A23187, indicating that the two former chemicals are effective to initiate the sesquiterpene biosynthesis pathway whereas Ca
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> can act as signaling molecule during the activation process (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kenmotsu et al., 2011</xref>). This provides clues for the artificial induction of agarwood formation via exogenous chemically induced approaches by triggering the sesquiterpene biosynthetic pathway in 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic> trees.
</p>
