<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the final stage of sesquiterpenes production, the enzymes accountable for the diversification of sesquiterpene mainly come from the classes of sesquiterpene synthases (SesTPs) and cytochrome P450 dependent mono-oxygenases (P450s). The SesTP enzymes are responsible to catalyze the formation of multicyclic scaffold complexes from FPP, followed by oxidative functionalization of the resulting scaffolds by cytochrome P450 enzymes. The added hydroxyl groups by P450s can serve as molecular handles for further modifications, such as alkylations, esterifications and the addition of sugar residues (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pateraki et al., 2015</xref>). In addition, the P450 enzymes which carry out stereospecific hydroxylation on the hydrocarbon backbones, that is important for the novel chiralities and further modifications of the sesquiterpene molecules, have never been reported from 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic> species thus far. Similarly, the NADPH-dependent cytochrome P450 oxidoreductases (POR) in 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic> that act as redox partners of P450s catalysis activity are basically unexplored. Several studies have been reported to isolate genes encode for SesTPs from 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic>, which can be considered as the early attempts to study SesTPs involved in the agarwood formation (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kumeta and Ito, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al., 2013</xref>). In the study of 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kumeta and Ito (2010)</xref>, five genes encode for sesquiterpene synthases which shared highly similar amino acid sequences have been isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria crassna</italic>. Three out of these genes have been successfully expressed in 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and enzymatically converted FPP into δ-guaiene as their major product. Besides, three other sesquiterpene synthase genes (
 <italic class="italic">ASS1</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">ASS2</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">ASS3</italic>) identified from 
 <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> via transcriptome sequencing have been revealed to encode enzymes that produce δ-guaiene as well (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xu et al., 2013</xref>). The isolation of 
 <italic class="italic">SesTP</italic> genes was also described in 
 <italic class="italic">A. malaccensis</italic> where the temporal and spatial expression of the two 
 <italic class="italic">SesTP</italic>s reported in the study, i.e., the guaiene (
 <italic class="italic">AmGuaiS1</italic>) and sesquiterpene synthase (
 <italic class="italic">AmSesTPS1</italic>), was elucidated (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Azzarina et al., 2016</xref>). The 
 <italic class="italic">AmSesTPS1</italic> was found to be highly expressed after 6 h of wounding while 
 <italic class="italic">AmGuaiS1</italic> was induced after 2 h of wounding at a magnitude of 18- and 5.5-fold higher than unwounded control, respectively. Recently, a novel sesquiterpene synthase gene (
 <italic class="italic">As-sesTPS</italic>) was isolated from 
 <italic class="italic">A. sinensis</italic> where the recombinant As-sesTPS catalyzed FPP into nerolidol (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ye et al., 2018</xref>). Expression analysis showed that the transcript level of 
 <italic class="italic">As-sesTPS</italic> was much higher in agarwood than the healthy wood, implying that the gene can be participated in the agarwood formation. Despite the fact that many sesquiterpene compounds have been discovered from the agarwood, the corresponding SesTPs responsible for their production have yet to be reported from 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic>. For that reason, the sesquiterpene biosynthesis pathways involve in the functionalization of terpenes in 
 <italic class="italic">Aquilaria</italic> is urged for further clarification.
</p>
