<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Backgrounds</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">Oils of fish origin are a very rich source of Omega − 3 and Omega − 6 fatty acids. They have been suggested to provide numerous health benefits for humans involving antimicrobial properties. 
   <italic class="italic">Chrysichthys nigrodigitatus</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">Hepsetus odoe</italic> are two fishes well known in Cameroon. The chemical composition and the antibacterial activity of these fishes derived oils are unknown. The study was designed to valorise 
   <italic class="italic">C. nigrodigitatus</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">H.s odoe</italic> oils activity against food poisoning bacteria.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">Oils were extracted by pressing and maceration methods. Their quality was assessed by analysing quality indexes including peroxides, acid, iodine, anisidine and thiobarbituric acid values. Chemical analysis was established by gas chromatography coupled to flame ionization detector. Antibacterial activity was evaluated by broth microdilution method.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">
   <italic class="italic">C. nigrodigitatus</italic> oil obtained by maceration exhibited highest acid (7.33 ± 0.00 mg KOH/g), anisidine (34.5 ± 1.84) and thiobarbituric acid (7.50 ± 0.30 μmol MDA/Kg) values compared to that obtained by pressing method (9.13 ± 0.64 and 6.72 ± 0.34 μmol MDA/Kg) respectively. 
   <italic class="italic">H. odoe</italic> oil obtained by pressing method showed highest peroxide value (6.22 ± 1.31 meq O
   <sub class="sub">2</sub>/kg). Oil chemical analysis revealed long chain polyunsaturated fatty acids of the ω-3 family: linolenic acid (C18:3); eicosapentaenoic acid (C20:5) and docosahexaenoic acid (C22:6) and ω-6 family; arachidonic acid (C20:4). In addition, 
   <italic class="italic">C. nigrodigitatus</italic> oil obtained by pressing and maceration methods showed Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (MIC) values ranging from 32 to 64 mg/ml. 
   <italic class="italic">H. odoe</italic> oil obtained by pressing method revealed MIC values ranging between 8 and 64 mg/ml.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4" class="p">
   <italic class="italic">C. nigrodigitatus</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">H. odoe</italic> oils have activity against food poisoning bacteria, due to their chemical composition.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
