<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Today, bacterial resistance represents a critical problem for human health and the care of patients with numerous diseases, thus urgently calling for the immediate development and use in therapy of drugs against multi-resistant pathogens [
 <xref rid="B1-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This has encouraged the research and investigation of various drug discovery approaches: one of them is drug repurposing, which is a strategy to establish new applications for approved or investigational drugs, aside from the original medical indications. Drug repurposing is becoming more appealing because it allows for overcoming the restrictions related to the expense and delay of the discovery and development of new drugs [
 <xref rid="B2-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In the last twenty years, humans have encountered five pandemic diseases, severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS), Avian flu, Ebola, Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) [
 <xref rid="B4-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) [
 <xref rid="B5-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Recently, a new variant of COVID-19 was also described [
 <xref rid="B8-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. It has been reported that the disease prognosis of COVID-19 is largely influenced by multi-organ involvement. The multi-organ dysfunction is characterized by acute lung and liver failure, acute kidney injury, cardiovascular disease, and a wide spectrum of hematological abnormalities and neurological disorders. The most important mechanisms are related to the direct and indirect pathogenic features induced by SARS-CoV2. Moreover, organ failure may be induced by the cytokine storm, as a result of increased levels of inflammatory mediators, endothelial dysfunction, coagulation abnormalities, and the infiltration of inflammatory cells into the organs [
 <xref rid="B9-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Medical treatment options for COVID-19 include antiviral drugs, chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine, antibiotics, beta-blockers, steroidal and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and some others [
 <xref rid="B11-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In this framework, new multitarget molecules could be useful to counteract the effects of the virus at various levels and in different ways. The repositioning of anticancer diarylureas for new indications, such as antimicrobial [
 <xref rid="B13-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], antiviral, and anti-inflammatory, could be a very interesting option for obtaining multitarget agents useful for the treatment or prevention of pandemics. Diarylureas or bis-arylureas are generally known as anticancer agents [
 <xref rid="B14-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], for instance sorafenib, regorafenib, linifanib, tivozanib, and ripretinib, which have been recently reviewed by our research group [
 <xref rid="B15-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Nevertheless, it is reported that they have also a lot of different and important biological activities [
 <xref rid="B16-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Indeed, they are antimicrobials, particularly active in schistosomiasis and malaria [
 <xref rid="B18-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], anti-inflammatory, antiplatelet, and antiviral agents [
 <xref rid="B21-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and allosteric modulators of the cannabinoid CB1 receptor [
 <xref rid="B23-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], VLA-4 integrin antagonists [
 <xref rid="B24-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and EGFR inhibitors [
 <xref rid="B25-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Taking into account the multiple factors involved in the pathogenesis of COVID-19, all the activities of diarylureas make them promising tools for the treatment of this disease. It is known that the novel coronavirus pneumonia is closely associated with inflammatory storms. Indeed, the patients with severe COVID-19 have a “cytokine storm” syndrome, given the high-levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines found in these patients [
 <xref rid="B26-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Moreover, there is an increasing recognition of a prothrombotic state in COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B27-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and neuropsychiatric diseases such as depression and anxiety [
 <xref rid="B28-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The expression levels of angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), acetylcholinesterase (AChE), interleukin-6 (IL-6), based on their involvement in both environmental responses and comorbid conditions, such as hypertension and type 2 diabetes mellitus, may substantially raise the respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) mortality [
 <xref rid="B29-antibiotics-10-00092" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In this review, we summarize the recent research on diarylureas with antimicrobial and antiviral activities and other properties related to pandemics. The literature data reported herein make these molecules attractive in this area.
</p>
