<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reactive oxygen species (ROSs) are various forms of activated oxygen. A disproportion of the reactive oxygen species and the absence of their scavenge systems in cells lead to oxidative stress and increases the risk of several human chronic diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. ROS contributes to the development of various diseases such as diabetes, atherosclerosis, cancer, neurodegenerative diseases, liver cirrhosis and the aging process [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. The liver plays a central role in the maintenance of systemic lipid homeostasis and is especially susceptible to ROS damage. CCl
  <sub>4</sub> is now of greatest concern as an environmental contaminant [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. It was reported that CCl
  <sub>4</sub> was one of the most commonly used toxins in the experimental study of liver diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. Abraham et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>] showed that the nephrotoxic effects of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> were also associated with free radical production.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To prevent the damage caused by ROS, living organisms have developed an antioxidant defense system that includes the presence of non-enzymatic antioxidants and enzymes such as catalase (CAT), superoxide dismutase (SOD) and glutathione peroxidase (GPx) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]. It has been anticipated that in addition to these natural antioxidants, other synthetic or natural ROS scavengers may reduce the incidence of free radical-mediated diseases. The use of antioxidants in the prevention and cure of various diseases is intensifying, and there is considerable interest in the study of the antioxidant activities of molecules such as plant polyphenolic and carotenoid components [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. Antioxidants appear to act against disease processes by increasing the levels of endogenous antioxidant enzymes and decreasing lipid peroxidation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of studies showed that various herbal extracts could protect liver and kidney against CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced oxidative stress by inhibiting lipid peroxidation and enhancing antioxidant enzyme activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. Silymarin, a flavonolignan mixture of milk thistle (
  <span class="italic">Silybum marianum</span>), is one such important herbal hepatoprotective drug. Silymarin exhibits hepatoprotective effects by altering cytoplasmic membrane architecture and, in turn, preventing the penetration of hepatotoxic substances, such as carbon tetrachloride (CCl
  <sub>4</sub>), thioacetamide and D-galactosamine [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The well-known and widely used peppermint (
  <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> L.) (Lamiaceae) is a cultivated natural hybrid of 
  <span class="italic">Mentha aquatica</span> L. (water mint) and 
  <span class="italic">Mentha spicata</span> L. (spearmint). Although a native genus of the Mediterranean region, it is cultivated all over the world for its use in flavor, fragrance, medicinal, and pharmaceutical applications. Peppermint oil is one of the most widely produced and consumed essential oils [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. Besides its uses in food, herbal tea preparations, and confectioneries, the medicinal uses of mint, which date back to ancient times, include carminative, anti-inflammatory, antispasmodic, antiemetic, diaphoretic, analgesic, stimulant, emmenagogue, and anticatharrhal application. It is also used against nausea, bronchitis, flatulence, anorexia, ulcerative colitis, and liver complaints. Mint essential oils are generally used externally for antipruritic, astringent, rubefacient, antiseptic, and antimicrobial purposes, and for treating neuralgia, myalgia, headaches, and migraines [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the experimental and clinical studies performed on 
  <span class="italic">Mentha piperita</span> leaf essential oil (MpEO), it seems that most of its pharmacological actions are due to its antioxidant activity which is mainly due to its ability to scavenge free radicals and/or inhibit lipid peroxidation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. Antioxidants are substances that delay or prevent the oxidation of inter- or intra-cellular oxidizable substrates from oxidative stress. In this study, we report the chemical composition and antioxidant effects of MpEO in several in vitro systems (DPPH and superoxide scavenging activities). Besides, we are interested in determining the possible protective effects of MpEO against oxidative damage of the liver and kidney following an intraperitoneal administration of CCl
  <sub>4</sub>, by assessing the oxidative stress profile and some serum biochemical parameters.
 </p>
</sec>
