<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec28" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chemical composition of the essential oil obtained from MpEO was determined by GC-MS analysis. The compounds, their percentages as well as the retention indices are listed in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. The essential oil is a complex mixture with 26 compounds representing 98.17% of the total oil composition. The major component of the essential oil is menthol (33.59%) followed by iso-menthone (33.00%). In lower amounts we found a variety of compounds including limonene (8.00%), piperitone (3.20%), 1,8-cineole (2.80%), linalool (2.64%), iso-pulegol (2.40%), caryophyllene (1.95%) and pulegone (1.60%). The obtained results are in accordance with previous studies of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> oils from Turkey, Spain (Barcelona), Norway and Poland that also had menthone and menthol as their most important components [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. On the other hand, the composition of the essential oil from Iran is totally different, with α-terpinene (19.70%), isomenthone (10.30%), trans-carveol (14.50%), pipertitinone oxide (19.30%) and β-caryophyllene (7.60%) as the major compounds, and also the oil from the Girona region (Spain) is different, where limonene and 1.8-cineole, eucalyptol are the main compounds (33.37% and 30.75%, respectively) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par64" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These studies showed variable chemotypes of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> L. extracts with various major oil components. Differences in chemical composition observed for essential oils is likely related to abiotic factors such as soil type and climate specific regions of provenance samples and geographical factors [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Furthermore, menthol and iso-menthone, found at relatively high concentrations in the MpEO used in the present study, have been reported to exhibit anti-inflammatory activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>], making MpEO use a promising candidate against oxidative damage of the liver and kidney following an intraperitoneal administration of CCl
  <sub>4.</sub> To be noted: working with natural extracts, the antioxidant activity is considered to be primary related to the major active compounds in the essential oil such as menthol and its derivatives [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. However the antioxidant activity could also come from a minor compound interacting in a synergistic or antagonistic way, to create an effective system against free radicals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], this has to be realized when evaluating different MpEO preparations.
 </p>
 <p id="Par65" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Liver injury after CCl
  <sub>4</sub> exposure is characterized by the elevated levels of serum hepatic marker enzymes indicating the cellular leakage and loss of functional integrity of hepatic membrane architecture. High levels of ALT, AST, ALP, LDH and γGT activities are sensitive indicators of liver cell injury and are most helpful in recognizing hepatic diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-treated rats show increased activities of these enzymes, reflecting damage to the liver cells or changes in the cell membrane permeability leading to leakage of enzymes from cells to the circulation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. In the present study increased levels of serum hepatic markers suggested that an extensive liver injury was occasioned by CCl
  <sub>4</sub> due to increased lipid peroxidation which had the ability to cause membrane damage. It is now generally accepted that CCl
  <sub>4</sub> hepatotoxicity is the result of reductive dehalogenation, which is catalyzed by its specific isoenzyme of cytochrome P450 2E1, and which forms the highly reactive free radical. Hence, the suppression of P450 2E1 could result in reduced levels of reactive metabolites, and thus decreased tissue damage [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par66" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The liver plays a fundamental role in the metabolism of lipids. Injection of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> caused a significant increase in the triglyceride, total cholesterol, and LDL levels and decrease in HDL level. Increase in the cholesterol levels might be due to the increased esterification of fatty acids, inhibition of fatty acid β-oxidation, and decreased excretion of cellular lipids [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. CCl
  <sub>4</sub> stimulates the transfer of acetate into liver cells (probably by increasing access to acetate) and leads to an increase in cholesterol synthesis. It also increases the synthesis of fatty acids and triglyceride from acetate and enhances lipid esterification [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. The accumulation of triglyceride in liver might occur due to the inhibition of lysosomal lipase activity and VLDL secretion [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par67" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The administration of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> induced also renal toxicity evidenced by an elevation of serum creatinine and urea [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. These pathological changes can also be attributed to damages touching the structural integrity of nephrons [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>], which is consistent with reports confirming that the level of serum creatinine increases only if at least half of the kidney nephrons are already damaged [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par68" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Treatment of rats with MpEO prior to CCl
  <sub>4</sub> exposure resulted in a dramatically protective effect against acute hepato and renotoxicity and oxidative stress, which was further also confirmed by the hepatic histopathological examinations. The stimulation of hepatic regeneration makes the liver more resistant to damage by the toxin [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. Treatment with silymarin (50 mg/kg) or MpEO (40 mg/kg) significantly decreased the elevated levels of ALT, AST, ALP, LDH, γGT, total cholesterol, triglycerides, LDL urea and creatinine and increased of HDL level as compared to CCl
  <sub>4</sub> group. Pharmacological studies have shown that essential oil derived from various plant materials possesses anti-inflammatory activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>] Knowing that sesquiterpenes have excellent anti-inflammatory activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>], the anti-inflammatory activity of 
  <span class="italic">M. piperita</span> L. leaf essential oil could be partly explained by the presence of sesquiterpenes, such as spathulenol, cadinene, caryophyllene and caryophyllene oxide. The ethanolic extract of parsley leaves also showed significant anti-inflammatory [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>] and antioxidant activities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>] which may contribute to its hepatoprotective action. Furthermore, menthol and iso-menthone, found at relatively high concentrations in the MpEO used in the present study, have been reported to exhibit anti-inflammatory activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par69" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, the two fold increase in the TBARS levels and reduce activity of SOD, CAT and GPx observed in liver and kidney homogenate of CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-intoxicated rats. Silymarin significantly reversed CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced TBARS levels elevation but values obtained with MpEO at the highest dose was comparable in attenuation of TBARS levels in liver and kidney. Silymarin reversed CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced SOD, CAT and GPx activities decrease but values obtained with MpEO at the highest dose (40 mg/kg) was comparable in attenuation of SOD, CAT and GPx activities in liver and kidney.
 </p>
 <p id="Par70" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These results suggested that MpEO could exert its antioxidant and/or radical scavenging activities thus preventing the formation of the carbon free radicals originated from CCl
  <sub>4</sub> metabolism as well as ROS and peroxidation products. This hypothesis is supported by the recent findings on the in vitro antiradical and antioxidative activities of MpEO [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. Previous studies showed that menthol and its derivatives were the major compounds responsible for antioxidant activity of MpEO [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par71" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, the rats of group 2 served as CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-hepato and renotoxicity control and rats of groups 3, 4, 5 and 6 were injected with 1 ml/kg BW of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> and olive oil mixture on day seven (a single intraperitoneal injection). It has already been shown that a single dose of CCl
  <sub>4</sub> initiates lipid peroxidation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>] that results in the disruption of cellular and organelle membrane integrity and subsequent leakage of cellular contents into the blood [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>]. CCl
  <sub>4</sub> is further well known to induce fibrosis of the hepatic tissue that may further progress to cirrhosis if the stimuli persists [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>]. Thus, a single CCl
  <sub>4</sub> injection in mice can be used as an attractive and highly reproducible model of liver regeneration after toxic injury. The first appearance of histological fibrosis and scarring fibers is usually observed after repeated CCl
  <sub>4</sub> treatment for 2 to 3 weeks, depending on the dosage and mouse strains used [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>]. In the present work, the hepatic histoarchitecture of the CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-treated rats resulted large numbers of inflammatory cells such as lymphocytes along with hepatic sinusoidal inflammation, hepatocyte necrosis and devastating liver architecture The highest dose of MpEO (40 mg/kg) or silymarin (50 mg/kg) significantly attenuated the damaged liver depicting marked focal regenerative changes which are illustrated by presence of actively dividing cells with a prominent nucleolus. The administration of MpEO reducing the histological alterations in liver provoked by CCl
  <sub>4</sub> was quite noticeable. In fact, the histological changes seen in the kidney of rats treated with CCl
  <sub>4</sub> were characterized by some nephrotoxic lesions, as evidenced by the glomerular and tubular necrosis. Our results confirmed previous findings of Ozturk et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>] who had found degenerative changes in kidney of rats exposed to CCl
  <sub>4</sub>. The results suggest that MpEO treatment prior to CCl
  <sub>4</sub> intoxication could prevent the CCl
  <sub>4</sub>-induced alterations in kidney tissues of treated animals.
 </p>
</sec>
