<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Increased secretion of mucus in intestine triggered by compounds that originate from plants precludes the possibility of bacterial and fungal adhesion to the epithelium in the intestine of poultry [
 <xref rid="B90-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>]. EOs also reduce the effects of pathogenic bacteria by direct antibiotic effects and growth promotion of probiotic microflora. Although in vitro active antibiotic concentrations of EOs are higher than doses of EOs that animals would accept [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], some studies proved that in vivo efficacy. However, in vivo effects of essential oils and aromatic plants on the microflora in swine and poultry can be different and even contradictory [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. However, studies proving the clear effect of PFA in controlling of pathogenic flora should not be underestimated. Studies on broilers challenged with 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Clostridium perfrigens</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Eimeria</italic> sp. showed that the number of pathogens decreased with the addition of EOs [
 <xref rid="B91-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. Evidence has also showed that plant-based products can control 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> population in the ileum of pigs [
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">94</xref>] and 
 <italic class="italic">L. intracellularis</italic> in pig feces [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>]. Most of the studies demonstrated that EOs have a stimulating effect on probiotic microflora growth in pigs and poultry [
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>], but some reports neglected the effects of EOs on probiotic microflora [
 <xref rid="B88-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>] or even causing bactericidal effects on these desirable microbiota [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-23-01717" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>].
</p>
