<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par70">I/R injury is associated with several serious clinical manifestations, including acute heart failure, gastrointestinal dysfunction, myocardial hibernation, cerebral dysfunction, systemic inflammatory response syndrome, and multiple organ dysfunction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]; the last condition is associated with an extraordinarily high mortality rate and requires timely treatment to protect the brain from injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. Inflammation is a critical feature of cerebral I/R injury. The specifics associated with the inflammatory response determine the extent and nature of the brain damage that may ensue; these factors are connected with several signaling pathways, including the MAPK and the Toll-like receptor 4 (TLR4)/NF-κB signaling pathways, among others. Therefore, it is critical to suppress the inflammatory response associated with I/R. Toward this end, the results of several studies revealed that the administration of PA could reduce infarct volume and alleviate the ensuing blood–brain barrier dysfunction in a model of obese mice with cerebral I/R injury. Levels of protein and mRNA encoding TNF-α and IL-1β were diminished in response to the administration of PA, together with diminished phosphorylation of JNK and p38; these results demonstrate that PA can provide protection against cerebral I/R injury by its capacity to inhibit inflammatory responses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Interestingly, cell apoptosis and oxidative stress also contributed to the development and progression of I/R injury. In addition to its capacity to alleviate inflammation by inhibiting TLR4/NF-κB signaling, pretreatment with β-PAE also results in a significant suppression of cellular apoptosis in I/R injury in rats, largely by decreasing the Bax/Bcl-2 expression ratio and limiting the induction of caspase-3 activity. Elevated levels of glutathione peroxidase (GSH-PX) and SOD were detected, while superoxide generation and MDA levels were reduced [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>].
</p>
