<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Main active ingredients of 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> Var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil
 </div>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As interaction between small molecule and protein plays a critical role in modulating the intrinsic biological processes, the information related to protein targets and small molecule has been highly valued by biomedical and pharmaceutical sciences. Target proteins are often those important ones in the development of specific diseases within the organism. Perturbing their functions by druggable molecules will help to cure the disease or relieve the symptoms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Therefore, more attention was paid to highly connected ingredients of 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil in this study.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to explore key nodes of the network, degree values of all nodes were ranked in a descending order (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Among all the 44 ingredients, eugenol (
  <span class="italic">k</span> = 106) and geraniol (
  <span class="italic">k</span> = 96) had most connections with target proteins, and were screened as key ingredients of 
  <span class="italic">O. fragrans</span> var. 
  <span class="italic">thunbergii</span> essential oil. Eugenol and geraniol were reported to exert multiple pharmacological actions. For instance, eugenol exhibited potential to inhibit ehrlich ascites and solid carcinoma [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Immunomodulatory and anti-inflammatory effects of eugenol were also found in clove extract [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Geraniol in essential oil of plants was reported to modulate DNA synthesis and potentiates 5-fluorouracil efficacy on human colon tumor xenografts [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Experimental evidences showed the therapeutic or preventive effects of geraniol on other different types of cancer, such as breast, lung, pancreatic, and hepatic cancer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. Geraniol could also inhibit prostate cancer growth by targeting cell cycle and apoptosis pathways [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. In addition, geraniol in plant essential oil also exhibited anti-microbial activity against many microorganisms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>], which might be induced by causing leakage of K
  <span class="sup">+</span> and Mg
  <span class="sup">2+</span> ions from microorganism cells through changes in the compositions of the cell membranes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Degree values (
     <span class="italic">k</span>) of all nodes in the ingredient-target-pathway network, shown in descending order
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12918_2017_523_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
