<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">Plants have the ability to synthesize aromatic substances such as phenolic and nitrogen containing compounds vitamins, terpenoids and some other endogenous metabolites, which are active against herbivores, insects, bacteria and fungi (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Bharathi et al., 2011</xref>). It is known that as a result of extensive use and in addition misuse of antibiotic and antifungal agents led to multi drug resistance (MDR). Thus, there is a need to discover novel antibacterial and antifungal agents from different sources and plants are one of them (
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Karaman et al., 2003</xref>). It was previously proposed that bryophytes are good candidates to discover potential active compounds (
 <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2006</xref>). Some bryophytes have ethnobotanical uses against several diseases, such as skin infections (
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Veljić, et al., 2009</xref>). There are several results regarding the antibacterial and antifungal activities of bryofite extracts in the literature (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Singt and Rawat, 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Vidal et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Bukvički et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Onbasli et al., 2019</xref>). In this study, antimicrobial activity of the extracts was identified by determining the minimum inhibitory concentrations (MIC) and MIC values identified for each microorganism were ≥ 125 µg.mL
 <sup>−1</sup>. Previously the antibacterial and antifungal activity of 
 <italic>BC</italic> methanol extract were tested against 
 <italic>Bacillus megaterium</italic>, 
 <italic>Shigella flexneri</italic>, 
 <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serotype 
 <italic>Typhimirium</italic> SL 1344, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> ETEC LM 63,083 and 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> ATCC 26,555 by MIC. They were found that the methanol extract of this bryophyte was active against 
 <italic>S. flexneri</italic> and 
 <italic>B. megaterium</italic> and the MIC values were 20 mg.mL
 <sup>−1</sup> for both microorganism. However, the ethanol extract of 
 <italic>Cratoneuron filicinum</italic> presented antibacterial activity against six bacteria with a MIC value ranging between 1.56 and 3.12 μg.mL
 <sup>−1</sup> and antifungal activity with a MIC value of 3.12 μg.mL
 <sup>−1</sup> (
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Singt and Rawat, 2006</xref>). In addition, ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Octoblepharum albidum</italic> was previously tested for its antibacterial activity against six microorganisms by MIC test and an activity against 
 <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> ATCC 33,018 and 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> ATCC 25,922 was observed with a MIC value of 512 μg.mL
 <sup>−1</sup> (
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Vidal et al., 2012</xref>). 
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Onbasli et al. (2019)</xref> were tested 
 <italic>Hypnum andoi</italic> extracts against skin pathogens, because bryophytes have ethnobotanical uses against several diseases, such as skin infections (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Bukvički et al., 2012</xref>). Antimicrobial activity of 
 <italic>BC</italic> is higher than 
 <italic>Hypnum andoi</italic>. Our study is supported by the studies present in the literature.
</p>
