<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Natural glycosides of xanthones demonstrate several biological activities in which the glycosidic moiety showed an important role [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In our group, an acetylated xanthone glycoside (
 <bold>60</bold>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-26-00431-f015">Figure 15</xref>) obtained by synthesis was recently shown to have a potent inhibitory effect on glioma cells growth [
 <xref rid="B119-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Acetylated xanthonoside 
 <bold>60</bold> and its parent non-acetylated xanthonoside were first evaluated for their in vitro growth inhibitory effect on A375-C5 (IL-1 insensitive malignant melanoma), MCF-7 (breast adenocarcinoma), and NCI-H460 (non-small-cell lung cancer) cell lines. Acetylated xanthonoside 
 <bold>60</bold> exhibited potent growth inhibitory activity in MCF-7 and NCI-H460 cell lines with GI
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.46 and 0.19 μM, respectively, while the non-acetylated xanthonoside was not able to reach 50% of cell growth inhibition. These results put forward the role of the acetyl groups in the potent cell growth inhibitory activity of xanthone 
 <bold>60</bold>. After this promising results, glioblastoma cell lines (U251, U373, and U87MG) growth was also studied in the presence of xanthone 
 <bold>60</bold> and a potent inhibitory activity was found with this xanthone against the referred three lines (GI
 <sub>50</sub> values between 0.42–0.55 μM). Association of acetyl groups with inhibition of growth of glioma cell lines had been reported in the natural 
 <italic>O</italic>-acetylated ganglioside GD1b neurostatin, present in the mammalian brain, which showed strong inhibition of astroblast and astrocytoma division and in a previous work of our regarding an acetylated flavonoid glycoside [
 <xref rid="B120-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Acylation is expected to increase the penetration through the cell membrane. However, as acetylated compounds are likely to present poor water solubility and to suffer hydrolysis by esterases, the encapsulation of this acetylated xanthonoside in nanosystems was planned as possible strategy to overcome these limitations. Xanthone 
 <bold>60</bold> was successfully incorporated by us in liposomes while maintaining the inhibitory activity against glioblastoma cell lines [
 <xref rid="B119-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. New formulations and/or drug carriers to fight glioma growth with this promising xanthone are being studied by our group.
</p>
