<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mangiferin was selected for sulfation as part of our top priority of developing new molecules derived by molecular modifications of known drugs, for several reasons as follows. Modification of molecules that have already been used in human therapy leads to compounds with more predictable and less complex pharmacokinetics, lower incidence of side effects, and less demanding clinical studies. The wide use of mangiferin by humans for many years suggests low toxicity not only for mangiferin but also for their metabolites and analogues. Protective effects of mangiferin with regard to cardio, renal, liver, and brain toxicity are well documented [
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Because aryl 
 <italic>C</italic>-glycosides are stable analogues of 
 <italic>O</italic>-glycosides, resistant to metabolic processes, the 
 <italic>C</italic>-glycoside mangiferin emerged as an interesting derivative to be sulfated. Starting from commercial mangiferin, sulfation was performed with triethylamine sulfur trioxide adduct in dimethylacetamide at 65 °C for 24 h. Depending on the loading of sulfur trioxide adduct, mangiferin tetrasulfate (
 <bold>57</bold>) and mangiferin heptasulfate (
 <bold>58</bold>) were obtained [
 <xref rid="B108-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Due to the sulfate groups, 
 <bold>57</bold> and 
 <bold>58</bold> revealed a better solubility in water than mangiferin. Both derivatives exhibited anticoagulant activity when tested in vitro in human plasma, with the heptasulfate mangiferin (
 <bold>58</bold>) being more potent. Enzymatic in vitro assays to elucidate coagulation targets of 
 <bold>58</bold> demonstrated that this sulfated mangiferin was a selective direct inhibitor of factor Xa. This work inspired Q. Rashid et al. to explore by in silico studies the binding mode of several sulfated and non-sulfated xanthones on coagulation proteases [
 <xref rid="B110-molecules-26-00431" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>].
</p>
