<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The electrospinning process is a simple and versatile method used to fabricate nanofibers with a diameter in the range of the submicron to the nanometer scale [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Nanofibers can be processed from various materials, such as synthetic and natural polymers, ceramics, and/or composites [
 <xref rid="B10-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Compared to ceramics and/or their composites, polymers’ benefit is that they can be formed into nanofibers using various nontoxic solvents, or can be electrospun after blending with other polymers (owing to appropriate viscosity) [
 <xref rid="B59-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The ultrafine fibers fabricated by electrospinning have drawn much attention due to their prominent properties, such as high porosity and large surface-to-volume ratio. This has resulted in superior mechanical properties if we compare the nanofiber mats with polymeric films of the same thickness [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. These nanofibers have enormous applications in tissue engineering, drug delivery, stem-cell differentiation, and wound dressing because of their aforementioned versatile nature and exceptional qualities [
 <xref rid="B61-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Generally, drug-filled nanofibers using a drug and a polymer solution are considered sufficient; however, the release of the drug from the nanofiber is problematic due to the initial burst release. Therefore, the use of a core-sheath-shaped nanofibers fabricated by coaxial electrospinning offers a promising method of managing the initial burst release [
 <xref rid="B64-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. In brief, in the electrospinning process, as illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-22-04017-f002">Figure 2</xref>, one end of the electrode is attached to the spinneret’s tip, and the other end is connected to the high-voltage power supply. This power supply generates a positive charge that is attached with the spinneret using an alligator clip (typically more than 5–40 kV). The collector (flat or round exterior) is grounded with a negative charge with high voltage. When the charges generated inside the polymer solution reach a critical point, the solution forms a Taylor cone at the capillary tip and is forced out from its end [
 <xref rid="B65-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The polymeric solution’s jet loop becomes longer and thinner when heading close to the oppositely charged collector. Eventually, it solidifies while depositing on the collector due to solvent evaporation during its travel. The collector onto which fabricated micro- or nanofibers are deposited are placed some distance away (usually 5–20 cm) from the spinneret [
 <xref rid="B66-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The polymers used for electrospinning must be soluble in a desirable solvent. A single-phase homogenous solution is attained, which is very important for forming defect-free fibers. By appropriately controlling the solution parameters, such as conductivity, viscosity, dielectric constant, and surface tension; and the processing parameters, such as flow rate, polymer concentration, the distance between the tip and collector, temperature, and humidity, fibers with desirable morphologies and diameters can be produced [
 <xref rid="B67-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The solution concentration should be proper (not too high or too low) to form smooth and properly defect-free fibers. A lower flow rate generally results in thin nanofiber preparation because the jet gets sufficient time to elongate and polarize. However, for fiber formation without dripping and beads, i.e., smooth fibers, a maximum distance between a collector and spinneret tip is usually desired [
 <xref rid="B59-ijms-22-04017" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
</p>
