<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cheese is one of the major fermented dairy products. Dairy products are an excellent source of high-quality protein and milk fat desirable for human health. It has fat-soluble vitamins along with vital mineral, calcium, and phosphorous and concentrated source of energy [
 <xref rid="ref180" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">180</xref>]. A study was performed in cottage cheese, a traditional Mexican Cheese, to investigate the antioxidant properties of peptides produced during the course of 6 months ripening period. Peptides were characterized by high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC); results showed that peptides with antioxidant activity were produced during the ripening period of 6 months. 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH), free radical scavenging activity of 6-month-old cheese, was 98% [
 <xref rid="ref181" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">181</xref>]. Cheddar cheese was prepared using 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic> as starter culture, changes in antioxidant characteristics of cheddar were monitored for 6 months, and different antioxidant assays were used as indicators of antioxidant activity. DPPH and superoxide free radical scavenging activities of cheese increased up to 4 months of ripening; the increase in antioxidant activities was attributed to the production of water-soluble peptides. Antioxidant activity and extent of water-soluble peptides were strongly correlated [
 <xref rid="ref182" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">182</xref>]. Antioxidant activity of white brined prepared from overheated milk (90°C, for 10 min) was investigated, antioxidant activity of water-soluble and water-insoluble fraction of cheese was increased during the ripening period, and antioxidant activities were correlated with degree of proteolysis [
 <xref rid="ref183" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">183</xref>]. Rashidinejad 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref184" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">184</xref>] worked on full-fat cheeses to investigate the effect of antioxidant properties of green tea catechin. Full-fat cheeses were added with green tea extract (GTE) at 250, 500, and 1000 ppm. Cheeses were ripened for 90 days at 8°C. The compositional analysis of cheeses such as pH, total protein content (TPC), and antioxidant activity on storage days of 0, 30, and 90 was analyzed. The determination of GTE catechins from the ingesta and concentrations in the curd of ripened cheeses were assessed using HPLC. The resulted data showed that pH of whey and curd significantly decreased after addition of GTE during manufacturing of cheese and ripening period; however, no significant changes were recorded on fat, moisture, and protein contents of the cheese. The study further revealed that TPC and antioxidant activity also increased in all concentrations after GTE addition, but the manner was non-linear. Branciari 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref185" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">185</xref>] studied pecorino cheese for total phenolic content and antioxidant activities after the supplementation of rosemary leaf in the diet of sheep. Two dietary groups were assigned after random collection of 324 sheep, which were kept on lucerne hay and concentrate (400 g/day) at recommended level. Thus, 2.50% dried rosemary leaves were supplemented to one group in the form of concentrate. The time period for the said study was 7 weeks. Cheese was prepared at 3, 5, and 7 weeks before the trial started. The supplementation of rosemary leaves showed good results because of the increase in the total phenolic content and antioxidant properties of the cheese and decreased lipid oxidation of pecorino cheese. Rashidinejad 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref186" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>] studied that the addition of catechin has no effect on low-fat hard cheese composition and increased total phenolic content and antioxidant activities. Cheese was analyzed for 90-day ripening period at temperature of 8°C [
 <xref rid="ref187" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">187</xref>]. According to this study, there was a significant increase in both the TPC and antioxidant activity during the ripening period of 90 days. Fernandes 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ref188" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">188</xref>] evaluated cream cheese oxidation and fermentative stabilities using oregano and rosemary essential oils which were added as a natural antioxidant in cream cheese. Peroxidase and anisidine value of treated cheese was estimated. Cheese treated with oregano and rosemary essential oils showed more stability, lower PV, and lower acidity with higher pH and also reduced the total viable count on 35 days of storage. The study showed that cheese treated with oregano had more acidic pH which is 4.68, less total viable count 2.35 CFU/g than rosemary essential oil [
 <xref rid="ref189" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">189</xref>]. Hence, protective effect of oregano and rosemary essential oils has been shown on cheese against lipid oxidation. The study was conducted using rosemary extract (RE). RE was added into the soft cheese, which was made from UF milk having 1.5% milk fat. RE was added in the concentration of 1-5%, and cheese was stored in cold storage for 30 days. The study showed that addition of RE had increased the total phenolic content and antioxidant capacity of cheese. Pasteurization had increased the total phenolic content and antioxidant capacity of cheese supplemented with RE. Addition of salt up to 3% had decreased the total phenolic content and antioxidant activity. The study showed that 1% RE had more total phenolic content and had more antioxidant activity, while 5% of RE tends to improve the nutritional value and had better acceptability, better flavor, texture, and more antioxidant activity during 30 days of storage [
 <xref rid="ref190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">190</xref>]. Catechins were added in the low-fat hard cheese to evaluate its antioxidant and total phenolic content. Cheese was analyzed for 90 days of ripening at 8°C. Cheese curd showed retention of catechins in the range of 0.63-0.75. Catechins decreased the pH of cheese and did not affect protein, fat, and moisture content of the cheese. During 90 days of ripening, both total phenolic content and antioxidant activities were increased [
 <xref rid="ref186" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">186</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Foeniculum vulgare</italic> (Fennel) was added into the cottage cheese. The extract is rich in the phenolic content. Fennel antioxidant and antimicrobial potential were determined. The study showed that fennel extract has phenolic compounds in it. Fennel was added in the cottage cheese, to increase the shelf life of the cottage. In control cheese (where no fennel was added), no effects on nutritional profile up to 7 days of storage were observed. After 14 days of storage, it showed a decrease in the lactose content in treated cottage cheese. Only control cheese showed the signs of deterioration after 14 days. Fennel (phenolic-enriched extract) cottage cheese increased the shelf life up to 14 days through its antioxidant property [
 <xref rid="ref93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. Another study was carried out on four different plant essential oils (bay, cinnamon, clove, and thyme), which were added in the soft cheese in low-fat and full-fat cheese as a natural preservative. The plant essential oils were added at the concentration of 0.1, 0.5, and 1%, and its antimicrobial effect was evaluated on 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> and Salmonella for 14 days at two different 4°C and 10°C storage temperatures. All these oils at 1% concentration were equally effective in reducing the activity of 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria</italic> in low-fat cheese. However, in case of full-fat cheese, only clove oil achieved this reduction. The study also showed that thyme oil has no effect on Salmonella in full-fat cheese [
 <xref rid="ref191" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">191</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Matricaria recutita</italic> L. (chamomile) was added into the cottage cheese as a natural antioxidant and to also improve its nutritional value. The study showed that the antioxidant activity was limited for 7 days only. The aqueous plant extract has microencapsulation, so it is added to the cottage cheese to increase the bioactivity. Cottage cheese functionalized with chamomile extract showed a higher value of antioxidant activity for 7 days only, but it did not affect the nutritional value of cottage cheese [
 <xref rid="ref93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. The study was conducted to check the antimicrobial and nutritional effect of 
 <italic class="italic">Moringa oleifera</italic> leaf ethanolic and ether extracts which were added into the West African soft cheese in different concentration (1, 2, and 3%). The study showed that the highest antimicrobial effect was shown by the 2 and 3% of ethanol extract of 
 <italic class="italic">M. oleifera</italic>. The addition of 1% ethanol showed the highest crude protein and moisture. As compared to ether extract, ethanol extract tends to improve nutritional and microbial safety of West African soft cheese [
 <xref rid="ref192" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">192</xref>].
</p>
