<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another stilbene of considerable medicinal interest is combretastatin A-4 (
 <bold>35</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f009">Figure 9</xref>, together with related structures (such as combretastatin A-1 and B-1) [
 <xref rid="B104-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. It is found in the bark of the bushwillow tree (
 <italic>Combretum caffrum</italic>; Combretaceae) native to the Cape region of South Africa. Combretastatins have a structure similar to that of resveratrol, however, they differ in substitution pattern and in that, the double bond has a 
 <italic>cis</italic>-configuration, although combretastatins exist in a number of different isoforms. Combretastatins exert strong cytotoxic activity by binding to the colchicine site on tubulin and preventing its polymerization into microtubules. Combretastatin A-4 is structurally similar to colchicine, a strong antimitotic poison, and thus has attracted interest as a potential anticancer drug with similar mechanism of action as other commonly used antimitotic drugs such as analogues of vincristine [
 <xref rid="B105-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>], and it appears that they have selective toxicity toward tumour vasculature. Combretastatin A-4 provided the template for the synthesis of the water-soluble phosphate pro-drug combretastatin A-4 phosphate (CA4P; 
 <bold>36</bold>), 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-25-03846-f009">Figure 9</xref>. Based on its specific mode of action, CA4P stands as the lead drug of a novel class of depolymerising compounds known as vascular-targeting agents (VTAs). CA4P appears to specifically target established tumour blood vessels and rapidly reduce blood flow in the tumour, which results in potent anticancer activity [
 <xref rid="B107-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. This compound demonstrated promise in clinical trials as an anticancer agent against various solid tumours such as phase II/III ovarian cancer [
 <xref rid="B110-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>], but it is still in clinical development. Another combretastatin A-4 derivative with VTA-activity is ombrabulin. Nevertheless, it failed in the phase III clinical trial and the company that was developing this compound ceased further research [
 <xref rid="B111-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Numerous analogues based on the combretastatin structure have been developed, and many of these have demonstrated significant anticancer activity in preclinical settings [
 <xref rid="B86-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-molecules-25-03846" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>].
</p>
