<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pectin is a complex macromolecule in nature, and main structural element in plant’s cell walls. It can be used as raw material for the buildup of galacturonic acid as its main chain (homogalacturonan) consists of galacturonic acid units, with α-D connector (1–4) esterified with methyl groups and/or acetylated [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-26-01547" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Rehman et al. [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-26-01547" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] recently reviewed the perspective of pectin as a carrier in different nanoencapsulation techniques (nanocomplex, nanohydrogel, nanoliposomes and nanoemulsion), with a focus on its applications for encapsulating natural bioactive ingredients. The authors reflected that pectin is a promising carrier for nanoencapsulation of bioactive ingredients such as vitamins, saffron and D-limonene, allowing its controlled release in the body. In addition, its use as complex with proteins and lipids allows to improves its beneficial effects in terms of stability and controlled release rate. In this regard, Lopes et al. [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-26-01547" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] found that nanoliposomes coated with pectin or polygalacturonic acid can be used for lysozyme and nisin encapsulation, controlling effectively bacterial pathogens in a real food system such as Ultra-High Temperature (UHT) milk. Mohammadi et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-molecules-26-01547" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] achieved the nanoemulsion of olive leaf phenolic compounds with a whey protein concentrate–pectin complexes. The results were satisfactory since a high stability (96.64%) and slow controlled release (8.1%) of the encapsulated compounds by transport of the entire inner droplets were obtained. The results showed that nanoencapsulation technique around oil particles have a significant influence on the release of inner components. Moreover, double layers had more elasticity and aggregations than single-layers, resulting in a high stability [
 <xref rid="B52-molecules-26-01547" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Positive effects were also found when citrus peel pectin was combined with bovine serum albumin to form a nanohydrogel with vitamin C [
 <xref rid="B53-molecules-26-01547" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. As a result, a stable food system with an EE of 65.31%, an enhanced vitamin C retention (73.95%) and a release in two distinct stages (burst release and sustained release) were obtained.
</p>
