<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ability of the extracts to prevent biofilm formation by bacteria (
 <italic>S. aureus, E. coli</italic> and 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>) was evaluated at concentrations of 1, 1/2, 1/4, 1/8, and 1/16 (MIC) using the microplate antibiofilm method [
 <xref rid="B29-foods-09-01768" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Tryptose-Soy Broth (TSB) containing 0.25% glucose were filled into wells with or without extracts, and 200 μL of 1% overnight bacterial cell cultures (5 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> CFU/mL) were added and incubated at 37 °C for 48 h. The negative control wells contained only TSB and bacterial cells. The planktonic bacteria were washed after incubation, and the remaining bacteria were stained with 0.1% crystal violet solution and allowed to sit for 10 min. The dye was washed out carefully with distilled water, after which 200 μL of ethanol or 33% glacial acetic were filled into the wells of the microplates. Next, 125 μL of the resulting solution were transferred using a pipette into sterile tubes and the total volume was made up to 1 mL by adding distilled water. The optical density of each tube was read at 550 nm, and the equation below was used to calculate the percentage inhibition of the biofilm formation. Each experiment was done three times. 
 <disp-formula id="FD1-foods-09-01768">
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi>Biofilm</mi>
      <mo> </mo>
      <mi>inhibition</mi>
      <mo> </mo>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mo>%</mo>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mo> </mo>
     <mfrac>
      <mrow>
       <mi>O</mi>
       <mi>D</mi>
       <mo> </mo>
       <mn>550</mn>
       <mo> </mo>
       <mi>c</mi>
       <mi>o</mi>
       <mi>n</mi>
       <mi>t</mi>
       <mi>r</mi>
       <mi>o</mi>
       <mi>l</mi>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <mi>O</mi>
       <mi>D</mi>
       <mo> </mo>
       <mn>550</mn>
       <mo> </mo>
       <mi>s</mi>
       <mi>a</mi>
       <mi>m</mi>
       <mi>p</mi>
       <mi>l</mi>
       <mi>e</mi>
       <mo> </mo>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi>O</mi>
       <mi>D</mi>
       <mo> </mo>
       <mn>550</mn>
       <mo> </mo>
       <mi>c</mi>
       <mi>o</mi>
       <mi>n</mi>
       <mi>t</mi>
       <mi>r</mi>
       <mi>o</mi>
       <mi>l</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo>×</mo>
     <mn>100</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
