<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The search for new and more effective molecules from different sources has clearly been focussed on these potential mechanisms, with the goal of preventing oxidation, thus reducing the production of ROS and protecting the tissues
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>. Plants from the genus 
 <italic>Plectranthus</italic>, belonging to the 
 <italic>Lamiaceae</italic> family, are widely distributed across the warm and tropical areas of Africa, Asia and Oceania, and were likely brought to Mediterranean areas in the 16th century during the period of Portuguese discoveries
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>. Rich in essential oils and in mono- and sesquiterpenes
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24–26</sup>
 </xref>, extracts from these plants are widely used in traditional medicine with different ethnopharmacological uses, including antimicrobial, analgesic, antipyretic, anti-inflammatory and antitumoral. Moreover, they have been applied in many skin disorders including wound healing
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25–28</sup>
 </xref>. Diterpenoids (abietane, labdane, kaurane, and clerodane skeleton), together with triterpenoids, phytosterols, phenolic acids, flavonoids and other polyphenolic compounds are the specific compounds of interest within this genus, according to their displayed effects compiled in the literature
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28–30</sup>
 </xref>. Polyphenols, such as rosmarinic acid which is ubiquous to all 
 <italic>Plectranthus</italic> spp., and chlorogenic acid, obtained primarily from 
 <italic>P. saccatus</italic>, and usually present in the aqueous extracts
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31–34</sup>
 </xref>, are powerful antioxidants
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>. Phenol groups in polyphenolic compounds are able to accept an electron to form relatively stable phenoxyl radicals, thereby disrupting radical chain oxidation reactions in cellular components
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref>. Abietane diterpenes from 
 <italic>P. ecklonii</italic>, 
 <italic>P. madagascariensis</italic> and 
 <italic>P. grandidentatus</italic> are able to chelate the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl (DPPH) radical comparably to positive control quercetin, a natural flavonoid 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref>.
</p>
