<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Functional food products, along with its beneficial health effects, also possess some health-related hazards. GM foods are the main concern of public health in terms of environmental safety, labeling, intellectual property rights, food security, and poverty alleviation and consumer choices. Most authorities such as European Commission, India Parliamentary Committee of Agriculture, and FDA consider that specific assessments are necessary for GM food and there is a lack of policies regarding safety testing of foods, regulations, and labeling. All the novel methods and concepts should be well defined which are used for the assessment of GM and conventional foods [
 <xref rid="ref216" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">216</xref>]. The potent issues or health concerns have increased using these foods and the privileges are by changing its chemical nature through biotechnological approaches which disturb the nutritional profile, drug resistance for certain foods, potential toxin production in the functional foods, allergenicity, possible creation of new viruses and toxins, religious/cultural/ethical concerns, concerns of animal rights groups, and fear of the unknown issues [
 <xref rid="ref217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">217</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">218</xref>]. For example, the risks behind recommending the increased dose of chemical compounds such as “isoflavones” may be dangerous because of modulation in the estrogen metabolism and the development of different kinds of tumors in clinical research animals due to genistein, which is a soy phytoestrogen and may act as a “double-edged sword” [
 <xref rid="ref219" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">219</xref>]. The International Food Information Council released a series of the recommendations that are expected to guarantee that research results come about nutritional status, safety of foods, and health risks are conveyed in an unmistakable, balanced, and non-deceiving way [
 <xref rid="ref220" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">220</xref>]. The following recommendations have been made by the General Accountability Office related to the safety of functional foods.
</p>
