<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">LA is a dominant omega-6 PUFA in fish oil. This fatty acid is essential for growth, reproduction, and skin function. It can be metabolized to γ-linolenic acid (GLA), dihomo-GLA, prostaglandin (PG)E1, and arachidonic acid (AA). The eicosanoids, such as PGE2 and leukotriene B4, are derived from AA. These eicosanoids are involved in the inflammation and allergic response in cutaneous tissue [
 <xref rid="B27-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. LA is the richest fatty acid in the epidermal layer. It is also the precursor to ceramide synthesis [
 <xref rid="B29-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Ceramide is a predominant material of the intercellular stratum corneum lipid matrix producing the skin’s permeability barrier. Several omega-3 fatty acids are produced from ALA. These include DHA, EPA, and docosapentaenoic acid [
 <xref rid="B30-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. ALA is largely found in vegetable oils, zooplankton, phytoplankton, and fish oils. ALA is fundamental to visual and brain functions through its effect on membrane fluidity because PUFAs and their derivatives are principally located in the cell membrane phospholipids [
 <xref rid="B31-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. The derivatives of ALA can modify the immune response of the epidermis via affecting the T cells, acting on Toll-like receptors, and stimulating caspase cascades that relieve inflammatory dermatoses such as acne, psoriasis, dermatitis, lupus, and skin cancers [
 <xref rid="B32-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. The mechanisms of ALA and the derivatives for inflammation inhibition are based on barrier function maintenance, stratum corneum maturation, stratum corneum differentiation, proinflammatory eicosanoid inhibition, lamellar body formation, lipoxygenase inhibition, and cytokine suppression [
 <xref rid="B33-marinedrugs-16-00256" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>].
</p>
