<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cytosolic enzyme hCA III is specifically found to be present in liver, adipocytes, and skeletal muscle
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>. The hCA III is comparatively inefficient in catalysing CO
 <sub>2</sub> hydration (≈300-fold less than hCA II)
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>. However, hCA III has been found to be involved in the contraction of skeletal muscle and protection of cells from reactive oxygen species (ROS) and oxidative stress
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22–25</sup>
 </xref>. The hCA III also facilitates the regulation of adipogenesis in relation to peroxisome proliferating-activated receptor-gamma 2 (PPAR-γ2)
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref>. Furthermore, hCA III is found to be a valuable biomarker in various diseases like neuromuscular disease, sarcopenia, and hepatitis B and C infections and liver carcinoma
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27–29</sup>
 </xref>. It should be noted that most important classes of hCAIs contain sulphonamide (R-SO
 <sub>2</sub>NH
 <sub>2</sub>), sulphamide (R-NH
 <sub>2</sub>-SO
 <sub>2</sub>NH
 <sub>2</sub>), sulphamate (R-OSO
 <sub>2</sub>NH
 <sub>2</sub>) functional groups which are found to be insensitive towards hCA III
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30–32</sup>
 </xref>. Recently, an ureido-substituted benzene-sulphonamide (SLC 0111) has been reported to have potent hCA inhibitory activity (selective towards hCA IX/XII against hCA I and II), which is currently under Phase Ib/II clinical trials investigation for the treatment of metastatic breast cancer
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref>, but, this study did not explore the selectivity profile against hCA III isoform. Thus, several heterocyclic hCA III inhibitors from natural and synthetic origin with different mechanism as compared to sulphonamides have been discovered and are currently being investigated as potential therapeutic agents for the treatment of diabetes and hyperlipidaemia
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref>. In particular, Supuran et al. reported hCA III inhibition profile of diverse sulphonamide containing molecules including 2-aminothiadiazoles
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref>. Same group of researchers further reported that most potent inhibitors of hCA-III are mainly anions like carbonate, cyanate, cyanide, thiocyanate, etc.
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref>. In continuation of these observations, Alzweiri et al. reported promising hCA-III inhibitory activities of carboxylic acid containing analogues of benzoic acid and nicotinic acid
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref>. Interestingly, vanillic acid showed more potent hCA-III inhibitory activity as compared to the acetazolamide
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref>. Therefore, it was our thought of interest to synthesise and evaluate a novel series of 2,4,5-trisubstitutedthiazole derivatives with 5-aryl group, 4-carboxylic acid/ester moiety, and 2-amino/amido/ureido functional groups as possible hCA-III Inhibitors.
</p>
