<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">FI-ISK invasion risk predictions available for crayfish present in the Dutch aquarium trade range from medium (
 <italic>C. puer</italic>, 
 <italic>C. quadricarinatus</italic>, 
 <italic>P. virginalis</italic>) to high (
 <italic>C. destructor</italic>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>Cambarellus puer</italic> has a small size and produces lower numbers of eggs, resulting in a low risk of invasion for the Netherlands. Due to widespread presence of North American species potentially carrying crayfish plague, the susceptible 
 <italic>C. quadricarinatus</italic> and 
 <italic>C. destructor</italic> seem unlikely candidates for widespread invasion in the Netherlands. This notion is supported by the apparent mismatch between their climate tolerance and the Dutch climate. The combination of these traits also excludes the other 
 <italic>Cherax</italic> spp. in this study. Although not currently found in the wild in the Netherlands, both 
 <italic>P. virginalis</italic> and 
 <italic>P. alleni</italic> are clustered with the very successful invader 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic>, suggesting they also possess those traits necessary to become invasive. However, these 
 <italic>Procambarus</italic> species and 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> differ in their climate tolerance too, with only the latter being adapted to a colder climate. 
 <italic>Procambarus virginalis</italic> is adapted to a humid subtropical and temperate climate but can survive water temperatures lower than 8 °C and even below 2 °C for several weeks
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. Here, climate change could make a difference in the near future. Furthermore, both 
 <italic>F. limosus</italic> and 
 <italic>P. virginalis</italic> can reproduce parthonegetically, increasing chances of establishing populations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>, but 
 <italic>P. alleni</italic> has not been reported to be capable of this. Tricarico et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> predicted 
 <italic>P. virginalis</italic>’ invasion risk in Italy to be medium, but caution against its release into the wild. Chucholl
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> found that higher human population density and availability of lentic water can increase the likelihood of 
 <italic>P. virginalis</italic> releases. 
 <italic>Procambarus virginalis</italic> has established wild populations in Germany, Italy, and Slovakia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup> and has already been recorded once in the Netherlands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. However, no subsequent sightings have been reported. In contrast, no established populations of 
 <italic>P. alleni</italic> have currently been identified in Europe
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup> and no sightings have been reported in the Netherlands. Due to availability in the Dutch aquarium trade, its functional traits with high invasive potential and invasion history in Europe, 
 <italic>P. virginalis</italic> is most likely to become the next successful invader in the Netherlands.
</p>
