<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">The second largest group of vernacular names had a Tupi origin. Names like 
 <italic>cajú</italic>, 
 <italic>tapereba</italic>, 
 <italic>buçu</italic>, 
 <italic>sicuriju</italic>, 
 <italic>jambu</italic>, and 
 <italic>tauari</italic> reflect an acquisition of indigenous words in the Brazilian lexicon for living organisms found in the natural world, also evidenced by the native and especially Amazonian plants that were sold at the market. Portuguese-speaking people have inhabited the Belém area since the seventeenth century, and their language gradually became the official language [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Nevertheless, Tupinambá indigenous people were still present around Belém during the turn of the twentieth century [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>], and Tupi, Tupinambá, and 
 <italic>língua geral</italic> (a mix of Tupi and Portuguese which served as lingua franca in the region) were spoken in Pará up until the nineteenth or twentieth centuries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>], alongside various other spoken languages also belonging to the Tupi-Guarani language family [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. This indicates that while the Portuguese-speaking peoples that inhabited the area mainly used Portuguese words to describe the natural world, they also relied upon indigenous Tupi names to some degree. This indigenous influence is not only reflected in the vernacular plant names at the VOP and the number of native species, but also in medicinal and religious plant uses. For example, the thin papery inner bark of 
 <italic>Couratari guianensis</italic> (
 <italic>tauari</italic>), whose presence in Belém and surroundings was not previously documented, is used during Amazonian indigenous and Afro-Brazilian ceremonies as tobacco paper to roll ritual cigars [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. We also found combinations of Tupi and Portuguese names, such as 
 <italic>pião-paje</italic> (
 <italic>Jatropha podagrica</italic> Hook.) and 
 <italic>jurema preta</italic> (
 <italic>Mimosa tenuiflora</italic> (Willd.) Poir.). These are prime examples of names shaped by cultural exchange among people from different cultural and linguistic backgrounds in the area.
</p>
