<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Inflammation is a host response to infections or tissue injury that occurs throughout a complex set of interactions among soluble factors and cells. In normal conditions, the inflammatory response is self-limiting. However, prolonged inflammation can cause many diseases [
 <xref rid="B45-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. There was a strong relationship between long-term inflammation and the development of colon cancer. Colitis-associated cancer (CAC) is a subtype of colorectal cancer linked to inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). Chronic inflammation in CAC is responsible for oxidative damage to DNA, resulting in p53 mutations observed in tumor cells and the inflamed but nondysplastic epithelium [
 <xref rid="B46-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Therefore, searching for natural anti-inflammatory agents without or with low toxic effects seems necessary. There are numerous studies indicating that mushroom polysaccharides, including β-glucans, possess immunomodulatory or anti-inflammatory activities [
 <xref rid="B47-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Inducible cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) and 5-lipooxygenase (5-LOX) are among the best known inflammatory biomarkers produced in the human body. Previous research revealed that a non-aqueous fraction from 
 <italic>S. crispa</italic> extract inhibited the production of PGE
 <sub>2</sub> via the downregulation of the expression of COX-2 [
 <xref rid="B48-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. A study conducted by [
 <xref rid="B49-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] revealed that the water extract of 
 <italic>S. crispa</italic> suppressed mast cell-mediated allergic inflammation by regulating calcium, MAPK, and NF-κB. Moreover, several phthalides from cauliflower mushroom exerted an inhibitory effect on LPS-stimulated NO and PGE
 <sub>2</sub> production by RAW264 cells [
 <xref rid="B50-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. It was demonstrated that a branched β-glucan from 
 <italic>S. crispa</italic> induced macrophages to produce several mediators, including the inflammatory cytokines interleukin-1 (IL-1), IL-6, tumor necrosis factor-a (TNF-a), and nitric oxide (NO) [
 <xref rid="B51-nutrients-13-00161" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Our study demonstrates the anti-inflammatory potential of CPS in the direct inhibition of pro-inflammatory enzymes such as COX-2 and LOX. Further studies are necessary to establish whether there are any additional mechanisms of the anti-inflammatory activity of 
 <italic>S. crispa</italic> polysaccharides.
</p>
