<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7593253</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2020.587414</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Introduced Populations of an Invasive Tree Have Higher Soluble Sugars but Lower Starch and Cellulose</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wenrao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1038805/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Luwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1102728/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Baoliang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1042425/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Jianqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/749759/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>Evan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/745802/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Crop Stress Adaptation and Improvement, School of Life Sciences, Henan University</institution>, <addr-line>Kaifeng</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Biosciences, Rice University</institution>, <addr-line>Houston, TX</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Henrik Hartmann, Max Planck Institute for Biogeochemistry, Germany</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Jianwen Zou, Nanjing Agricultural University, China; Shishir Paudel, Phipps Conservatory and Botanical Gardens, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jianqing Ding, <email>jding@henu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>This article was submitted to Functional Plant Ecology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>587414</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Li, Wang, Tian, Ding and Siemann.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li, Wang, Tian, Ding and Siemann</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Native and introduced plant populations vary in leaf physiology, biochemistry, and biotic interactions. These aboveground traits may help invasive plants in competition for resources with co-occurring native species. Root physiological traits may affect invasive plant performance because of the roles of roots in resource absorption. The aim of this study was to test this prediction, using invasive Chinese tallow tree (<italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>), as a model species. Here we examined carbohydrate (soluble sugar, sucrose, fructose, starch, and cellulose) concentrations and the mass of roots, stems, and leaves, along with root water potential and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) colonization of soil-cultured <italic>T. sebifera</italic> seedlings from 10 native (China) and 10 introduced (United States) populations in a common garden. Introduced populations had a significantly greater stem and leaf mass than native populations but their root masses did not differ, so they had lower R:S. Introduced populations had higher soluble sugar concentrations but lower starch and cellulose concentrations in their leaves, stems, and roots. Introduced populations had more negative root water potentials and higher AMF colonization. Together, our results indicate that invasive plants shift their carbohydrate allocation, leading to faster growth and a greater aboveground allocation strategy. Higher AMF colonization and more negative water potential in invasive plants likely facilitate more efficient water absorption by the roots. Thus, such physiological variation in root characteristics could play a role in plant invasion success.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chinese tallow tree</kwd><kwd>soluble sugars</kwd><kwd>starch</kwd><kwd>cellulose</kwd><kwd>root water potential</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="38"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Successful invasive plants often optimize their performance and competitive ability by improving resource acquisition and use in their introduced ranges (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Zou et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Petruzzellis et al., 2019</xref>). However, nearly all studies of variation among native and introduced populations of invasive plants focus on foliar ecophysiology, while knowledge of the roles of root ecophysiological traits in facilitating biological invasion is still limited. Roots play a vital role in determining plant growth, development, and adaptation via water uptake, nutrient acquisition and carbon storage and exudation (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">McCormack et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Erktan et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000fc; et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Petruzzellis et al., 2019</xref>). Whether plants from introduced populations have different root physiological traits compared with congeneric native populations, and whether these differences contribute to the faster growth of invasive plants are largely unexplored.</p><p>Furthermore, invasive plant root growth and functioning are affected by the synthesis, allocation, and storage of carbohydrates. Carbohydrates in plant tissues are usually classified as structural or non-structural carbohydrates according to their chemical structure and function in plants (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Dietze et al., 2014</xref>). Structural carbohydrates, as non-storage components, are long-chained molecules and mainly include polymerized compounds, such as cellulose which confers mechanical strength to cells, playing important roles in maintaining or changing plant tissue density (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Dumas et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Miedes et al., 2014</xref>). Thus, low cellulose concentrations in roots may reduce defense against natural enemies, but facilitate arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) penetrating into roots, increasing AMF colonization. AMF establish symbioses with most terrestrial plants, assisting plants to obtain water and nutrients from the soil by forming a large composite network of root hyphae to expand the absorption area of the host plant roots and increase the root length, and by inducing greater aquaporin expression (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Simard et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz-Lozano and Aroca, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000fc; et al., 2018</xref>). Studies have shown some introduced populations of plants can have higher AMF colonization than native ones (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Nijjer et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2015a</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). However, it remains unknown whether cellulose concentrations differ between introduced and native populations despite the potential for this difference to play a role in invasion success.</p><p>Non-structural carbohydrates include soluble sugars (such as glucose, sucrose, or fructose) and starch, which serve different physiological functions. Starch is a long-term carbon storage pool because of its osmotic inactivity (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Hartmann and Trumbore, 2016</xref>), while soluble sugars are used directly for cellular metabolism, as the substrates of cellular respiration or osmolytes for maintaining plant growth (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Rosa et al., 2009</xref>), and provide the energy for AMF colonization (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000fc; et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Caballero et al., 2018</xref>). Non-structural carbohydrates can undergo frequent transformations including the conversion of soluble sugar to starch for storage or the conversion of starch to soluble sugar for metabolism. Therefore, tissue soluble sugar and starch maintain a dynamic trade-off between growth (defense, osmoregulation, and symbiosis) and storage (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Dietze et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Hartmann and Trumbore, 2016</xref>), which represent different adaptation strategies to various environments. <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Hinman and Fridley (2018)</xref> found that native species have higher root soluble sugar concentrations and employ a grow-first strategy prioritizing allocation to new structural biomass over carbon storage, but invaders tended to store more root starch for new root growth in spring. A cross-continental comparison of sycamore maple (<italic>Acer pseudoplatanus</italic>) showed trees from native populations had higher foliar glucose and fructose concentrations than invasive population trees but their sucrose and starch concentrations were similar (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Shouman et al., 2017</xref>). To date, however, there are few reports examining the root structural and non-structural carbohydrate traits of introduced and native populations of invasive plants (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2018</xref>). Testing such differences may reveal whether invasive plants shift their root physiological strategies after they are introduced from their home range.</p><p>Here we examined the mass and carbohydrate concentrations of roots, stems, and leaves as well as root water potential and AMF colonization in a common garden experiment with plants of Chinese tallow trees (<italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>) from China (native range) and USA (introduced range). Specifically, we asked the following questions: (1) How do soluble sugars, starch, and cellulose concentrations vary among leaves, stems, and roots of introduced and native populations? (2) How do their AMF colonization and root water potential differ? We predict that, relative to native populations, introduced populations have a greater allocation to soluble sugars vs. starch and cellulose, higher AMF colonization and more negative root water potentials.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="S2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2.SS1"><title>Experimental Set-Up</title><p>Chinese tallow tree (<italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>) is native to China and was introduced to the United States in the late 18th century where it has become invasive throughout the southeast (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Pile et al., 2017</xref>). Relative to native conspecifics, introduced populations of <italic>T. sebifera</italic> have more rapid growth, larger leaf area or specific leaf area, greater photosynthetic rates (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Zou et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2015b</xref>), higher rates of AMF association (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2015a</xref>,<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Pei et al., 2020</xref>), and greater plasticity of functional and fitness-related traits under salt stress (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2015a</xref>). Previous studies have also reported that plants of Chinese tallow tree had higher AMF colonization than several native plant species in the introduced areas (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Nijjer et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Paudel et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>In the fall of 2016, we hand collected seeds from trees in 10 populations across the native range and 10 populations across the introduced range (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). We collected mature seeds (pods had dehisced to expose seeds) from 6 to 10 widely spaced, haphazardly selected adult trees. We pooled seeds from separate trees within each population. The introduced populations included those descended from the two historically recorded major introduction events (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Pile et al., 2017</xref>) along with likely source populations as identified in a microsatellite study (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">DeWalt et al., 2011</xref>). The Georgia populations are descended from the original introduction in 1772, which was most likely from a Guangdong province population and the rest of the US populations are descended from a later introduction around 1900 most likely from a Jiangsu province population (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">DeWalt et al., 2011</xref>).</p><p>We removed the seeds&#x02019; waxy coats (by soaking them in water with detergent then scrubbing), surface sterilized them (HgCl<sub>2</sub> [0.1%] for 1 min) and rinsed them repeatedly with distilled water. Then we put them in moist sand at 4&#x000b0;C for &#x0223c;30 days. Following this, we sowed &#x0223c;300 seeds of each population in a tray filled with a mixture of vermiculite and commercial topsoil that we placed in an unheated greenhouse.</p><p>We conducted our experiments in Kaifeng, Henan, China. Due to logistical constraints related to measuring root water potentials, we split the experiment into two-time blocks. We filled PVC tubes (24.5 cm high, diameter 6.3 cm; 32 tubes in July and 64 tubes in August 2017) with 630 g of soil and vermiculite (volume 2:1). We collected soil from a field left fallow for three years. We separately collected soil for the July (1.0 g kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> total nitrogen, 9.2 mg kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> available phosphorous, 178.8 mg kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> available potassium, 5.0 g kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> organic carbon) and August (1.4 g kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> total nitrogen, 14.7 mg kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> available phosphorous, 173.7 mg kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> available potassium, 10.6 g kg<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> organic carbon) blocks to avoid storing soil.</p><p>We planted one seedling (three-leaf stage) into each PVC tube. At each time block we transplanted four seedlings for a population (eight for GL) for mass, carbohydrate and root water potential measurements and another set of four seedlings (eight for GL) in August only for AMF measurements. We randomly arranged tubes in a mesh-sided greenhouse, watered them daily, and changed their positions every other day. Light and temperature approximated ambient conditions. At the beginning of the experiment, all seedlings used were similar in size. We allowed seedlings to grow from July 12 to August 24, 2017 or from August 12 to October 4, 2017.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS2"><title>Root Water Potential</title><p>We placed each tube individually into a pressure chamber (Model: 3005, Soil moisture Equipment Corp., CA, United States), then we removed their leaves and clipped their stems slightly (&#x0223c;2.5 cm) above ground level. We sealed the pressure chamber lid around the stem and raised the pressure in the chamber until tiny droplets appeared on the cut surface. The pressure point indicates root water potential.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS3"><title>Mass</title><p>After measuring root water potential, we clipped the remaining stem at ground level. Then we washed roots out of the soil. We dried the leaves, stems and roots and weighed them. The dry weight of every organ was defined as leaf, stem, and root mass, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS4"><title>Carbohydrate Content</title><p>We separately ground each plant&#x02019;s roots, stem, and leaves (excluding petiole) using a ball mill (Retsch-MM400, Retsch, Haan, Germany). The tissue total soluble sugar, sucrose, and fructose concentrations as well as starch and cellulose concentrations were determined using Comin Biochemical Test Kits (Comin Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Suzhou, China) per the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. For a complete measurement of soluble sugar and starch concentrations, the sample was extracted three times and then the supernatant was used for soluble sugar determination and the residue was used for starch measurement.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS5"><title>AMF</title><p>We examined AMF on the fine root samples from the other set of plants. We stored each AMF root sample in a histocassette in ethanol until we processed them following the methods of <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Nijjer et al. (2004</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2008)</xref>. We cleared and bleached the roots. Then we acidified and stained them (trypan blue), and slide-mounted 30 1-cm fragment of fine roots (PVA mount). We examined the slides (400&#x000d7; magnification) and recorded the number of 300 grid intersection points at which mycorrhizal hyphae were present.</p></sec><sec id="S2.SS6"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>We used a series of ANOVAs (PROC GLM, SAS 9.4) with time block, population origin, population nested in origin and their interactions as fixed factors to examine the variation in mass and carbohydrates of roots, stems and leaves as well as root water potential. We used the variation among populations to test for a significant origin effect and we used the interaction of populations and time block to test for a significant origin by block effect. We conducted an additional ANOVA without any time block terms to examine AMF colonization (only measured in August block).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3.SS1"><title>Mass</title><p>Plants from introduced populations had a significantly greater stem and leaf mass than those from native populations but their root masses did not differ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>); thus, they had lower root to shoot ratio (R:S) (introduced: 0.162 &#x000b1; 0.007; native 0.192 &#x000b1; 0.007; <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>,<sub>18</sub> = 5.2, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0344). Similarly, leaf and stem masses varied with population(origin), but root mass did not (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). From visual inspection, there were no apparent effects of introduction event of an introduced population on any mass variables (GA1 and GA3 vs. rest of introduced populations, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Plants were larger in the August block (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) but there were no significant interactions between the origin and time block or population(origin) and time block (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, the incomplete, unbalanced design to populations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) provided little power to examine the interaction of origin or population(origin) with time block.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>The dependence of root <bold>(A)</bold>, stem <bold>(B)</bold>, and leaf <bold>(C)</bold> mass on population origin (light fill is native, dark fill is introduced). Each point is the means &#x000b1; SE of a population (abbreviations from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) in the July (triangle) or August (circle) time block. ** indicates <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 for the main effect of population origin (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for full results). <italic>N</italic> = 4 except for population GL (<italic>N</italic> = 8).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-11-587414-g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>The dependence of mass, physiological, and chemical properties of <italic>T. sebifera</italic> plants (roots, stems, and leaves) on population origin, population nested in origin, experimental block and their interactions as fixed effects.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Origin</bold><hr/></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Pop(origin)</bold><hr/></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Block</bold><hr/></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Origin &#x000d7; block</bold><hr/></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Pop &#x000d7; block(origin)</bold><hr/></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Variable</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>F<sub>1</sub>,<sub>18</sub></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>F<sub>1</sub>,<sub>73</sub></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>F<sub>1</sub>,<sub>73</sub></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>F<sub>1</sub>,<sub>1</sub></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>F<sub>1</sub>,<sub>73</sub></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>P</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Roots</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4203</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0021</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>497.6</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6639</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2431</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total soluble solids</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52.5</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4181</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>14.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0003</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8996</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4072</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>15.2</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0011</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1214</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3134</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2517</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>14.0</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0015</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.9</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0321</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16.2</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5128</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6030</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>15.6</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0009</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.0</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0072</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0772</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7104</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellulose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10.2</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0050</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.8</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0491</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.9</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0062</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7629</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5304</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water potential</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.3</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0146</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8965</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>37.9</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8416</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0218</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Stem</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11.9</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0029</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.2</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0002</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>177.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5965</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1853</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total soluble solids</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18.3</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0005</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1130</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10.0</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0022</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8829</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.3</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0086</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0438</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8152</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4782</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5393</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6.0</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0168</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0030</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1173</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>31.1</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4154</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6464</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0660</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0176</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>77.9</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1115</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9652</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellulose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>21.8</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0002</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6293</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0927</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0965</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8081</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>Leaves</underline></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mass</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9.6</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0061</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.1</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0135</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>61.8</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0847</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9710</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total soluble solids</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>31.4</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.9</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0317</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6332</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2412</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>47.2</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c; 0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9439</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1939</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7532</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1499</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>13.5</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0018</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.9</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0285</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1206</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2529</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5488</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starch</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12.3</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0025</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1183</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0072</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6348</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3081</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cellulose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0022</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.1</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0003</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0072</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>782.7</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.0227</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9117</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>The imbalanced design (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) resulted in little power to test for effects of Origin &#x000d7; block or Pop &#x000d7; block(origin). Significant results indicated in bold.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S3.SS2"><title>Carbohydrate Content</title><p>Introduced populations had higher concentrations of total soluble sugars, fructose [except stems], and sucrose but lower concentrations of starch and cellulose in their leaves, stems and roots than native populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Populations varied in some of these characteristics with an especially significant variation for root starch and leaf cellulose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Some of the variables depended on the time block. In August, sugars were significantly higher, but cellulose was lower in roots and stems, while leaf sugar and starch concentrations were higher and cellulose was lower. Only leaf cellulose depended on origin &#x000d7; time block with a larger difference between native and introduced populations in July than August (+ 55 vs. + 47 mg/g, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>The dependence of root <bold>(A,D,G,J,M)</bold>, stem <bold>(B,E,H,K,N)</bold>, and leaf <bold>(C,F,I,L,O)</bold> carbohydrates (Fructose, <bold>A&#x02013;C</bold>; Sucrose, <bold>D&#x02013;F</bold>; Total soluble sugar, <bold>G&#x02013;I</bold>; Starch, <bold>J&#x02013;L</bold>; Cellulose, <bold>M&#x02013;O</bold>) on population origin (light fill is native, dark fill is introduced). Each point is the mean &#x000b1; SE of a population (abbreviations from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) in the July (triangle) or August (circle) time block. * indicates <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, ** indicates <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, *** indicates <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001, **** indicates <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001 for the main effect of population origin (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for full results. <italic>N</italic> = 4 except for population GL (<italic>N</italic> = 8).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-11-587414-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="S3.SS3"><title>Root Water Potential and AMF Colonization</title><p>Introduced populations had more negative root water potentials and higher rates of AMF colonization (<italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub>,<sub>13</sub> = 4.8, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0483) than native populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Both root water potential and AMF colonization did not significantly vary with population (origin) (AMF: <italic>F</italic><sub>13</sub>,<sub>49</sub> = 1.4, <italic>P</italic> = 0.2085; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Root water potentials were less negative in the July block (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) but there were no significant interactions between population origin and time block or population(origin) and time block.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>The dependence of AMF colonization <bold>(A)</bold> and root water potential <bold>(B)</bold> on population origin (light fill is native, dark fill is introduced). Each point is the mean &#x000b1; SE of a population (abbreviations from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="TS1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>) in the July (triangle) or August (circle) time block. * indicates <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 for the main effect of population origin (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for full results. <italic>N</italic> = 4 except for population GL (<italic>N</italic> = 8).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-11-587414-g003"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Several studies have compared leaf morphological, physiological, and biochemical traits of plants from native and introduced populations (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Angelo and Pau, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Petruzzellis et al., 2019</xref>) but root physiological traits are largely neglected. Root carbohydrate allocation is closely related to plant growth, resource storage, and defense. Here, we found that <italic>T. sebifera</italic> roots of plants from native and introduced populations varied in water potentials, AMF colonization and carbohydrate contents. These findings indicate the differences in those root traits in the introduced range may play a role in the more rapid shoot growth of plants from introduced populations, which helps to better understand the invasion success of this species and likely other plant species.</p><p>In this study, the greater concentrations of soluble sugars together with lower concentrations of starch and cellulose in <italic>T. sebifera</italic> plants from introduced populations suggest a shift from storage and defense to more rapid metabolism in the introduced range. Our results also support a trade-off between the allocation to soluble sugars and starch, given starch and sugar are often in a dynamic conversion state. Soluble sugars are strongly positively associated with more active tissue metabolism and rapid growth (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Dietze et al., 2014</xref>), while starch is the most common storage carbohydrate (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Hartmann and Trumbore, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Thalmann and Santelia, 2017</xref>). Therefore, when the plants had a strong demand to grow, less starch will be synthesized for decreasing energy store, and more sugar will be synthesized for increase metabolic energy. In part, these changes reflect that, for <italic>T. sebifera</italic> plants from introduced populations in this study, more soluble sugar might be associated with the decreasing tissue water potential (i.e., more negative) (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Tardieu et al., 2018</xref>). Similarly, cellulose is a macromolecular polysaccharide composed of glucose such that higher cellulose concentrations limit allocation to other types of carbohydrates. The lower cellulose for lower tissue density perhaps also reflects less need for physical defense or lower risk of tissue loss with low enemy abundance in the introduced range (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Hartley et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Petruzzellis et al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, the patterns we found for carbohydrates could reflect selection for increased soluble sugars for more active metabolism (such as to allow more rapid growth) by decreasing starch for storage at least during the seedling stage in our study.</p><p>Although there were no significant interactions between time block and population origin, the strong effect of time block on water potential motivates the additional study of possible phenological differences between introduced and native populations in attributes such as growth vs. storage. Phenological variation in carbohydrates may also be critical for linking our results to plant strategies. Other factors could simultaneously affect multiple carbohydrates such as increased soluble sugars to provide nutrients to AMF (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">L&#x000fc; et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Caballero et al., 2018</xref>) and lower cellulose to decrease root surface resistance to AMF infection. Of course, AMF can help plants enhance water absorption by promoting the expression of aquaporins (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz-Lozano and Aroca, 2017</xref>). The greater surface area of AMF hyphae than that of plant roots may also increase the absorption of water and nutrients. Higher AMF colonization might play important role for <italic>T. sebifera</italic> invading into the new areas (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Nijjer et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Paudel et al., 2014</xref>). Higher AMF colonization in introduced <italic>T. sebifera</italic> compared to native populations also had been reported by <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al. (2015a)</xref>. However, it is more difficult for them to cause these same changes in carbohydrates that we found for roots to also occur in leaves and stems.</p><p>The patterns of soluble sugars, starch, and cellulose in roots, stems, and leaves in this study indicate that there may be a general functional advantage of a higher metabolic rate, lower storage, and/or physical defense in the introduced range for <italic>T. sebifera</italic>. We found similar root mass and higher leaf and stem mass (and so lower R:S) in introduced populations than in native ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). This indicated that relatively more photosynthetic products were allocated to the shoots for the introduced populations and relatively more mass was allocated to root growth for the native populations. A lower R: S may provide an advantage in the competition for aboveground resources (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Reynolds and Pacala, 1993</xref>) which shows a greater importance for aboveground resource acquisition and competition in the introduced range that has been found for other species (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">van Kleunen et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Petruzzellis et al., 2019</xref>). The more negative root water potential of plants from introduced populations may reflect their higher solute (soluble sugars) concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) that improve the ability of root system to absorb water from the soil because of soluble sugar&#x02019;s osmotic regulation role (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Woodruff and Frederick, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, <italic>T. sebifera</italic> trees from introduced populations are more able to tolerate conditions of osmotic stress such as salinity (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2015b</xref>).</p><p>Overall, our results support a scenario in which <italic>T. sebifera</italic> in its introduced range has shifted to a strategy of faster growth, greater aboveground allocation, and more efficient root water absorption potential in part from more positive AMF interactions and more negative water potential. Significantly higher seedling biomass in introduced <italic>T. sebifera</italic> plants suggests that AMF more benefit introduced populations of <italic>T. sebifera</italic> relative to its native populations. The changes in carbohydrates from lower starch and cellulose to higher soluble sugars are consistent with greater resource investment to the growth rate in the introduced range. Because several invasive plant species have such a pattern of more rapid growth in introduced populations (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">van Kleunen et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Petruzzellis et al., 2019</xref>), such changes in carbohydrates may also have occurred in those invasive plants. This extends our knowledge of physiological variation in root characteristics between ranges for an invasive plant species, though further studies on changes in the belowground structure and function are needed to fully unveil mechanisms involved in the genetic variation of root ecophysiology in invasive plants.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>All datasets presented in this study are included in the article/<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Material.</xref></p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>WL and JD planned and designed the research. WL and LW performed the experiments and conducted the field work. ES analyzed the data. WL, JD, and ES wrote the manuscript. BT and ES collected the seeds. All authors have read and approved the submitted manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The reviewer JZ declared a past co-authorship with one of the authors, ES, to the handling Editor.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by the National Key Research and Development Program (2017YFC1200100 to JD) and National Science Foundation (NSF)-China (31770414 to JD and 31971565 to WL).</p></fn></fn-group><sec id="S8" sec-type="supplementary material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2020.587414/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpls.2020.587414/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="TS1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.DOC"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="DS1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.XLS"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angelo</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Root functional diversity of native and nonnative C3 and C4 grass species in Hawai&#x02019;i.</article-title>
<source><italic>Pac. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2984/71.2.2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiu</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Conspecific plasticity and invasion: invasive populations of Chinese tallow (<italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>) have performance advantage over native populations only in low soil salinity.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e74961</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074961</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24040366?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24040366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeWalt</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Geographic distribution of genetic variation among native and introduced populations of Chinese tallow tree. <italic>Triadica sebifera</italic> (<italic>Euphorbiaceae</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. J. Bot.</italic></source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>1128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1138</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1000297</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21730337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21730337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietze</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sala</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Czimczik</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantooth</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Nonstructural carbon in woody plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>687</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-050213-040054</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24274032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24274032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaulin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Esquerr&#x000e9;-Tugay&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Cellulose-binding domains: cellulose associated-defensive sensing partners?</article-title>
<source><italic>Trends Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2008.02.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18329320?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18329320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erktan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roumet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Frontiers in root ecology: recent advances and future challenges.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>424</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-018-3618-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The invasive plant <italic>Alternanthera philoxeroides</italic> was suppressed more intensively than its native congener by a native generalist: implications for the biotic resistance hypothesis.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e83619</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0083619</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24386236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24386236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Y. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valiente-Banuet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Evolutionary tradeoffs for nitrogen allocation to photosynthesis versus cell walls in an invasive plant.</article-title>
<source><italic>PNAS</italic></source>
<volume>106</volume>
<fpage>1853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1856</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0808434106</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19171910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19171910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Comparisons of arthropod assemblages on an invasive and native trees: abundance, diversity and damage.</article-title>
<source><italic>Arthropod Plant Int.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11829-010-9105-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trumbore</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Understanding the roles of nonstructural carbohydrates in forest trees - from what we can measure to what we want to know.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>211</volume>
<fpage>386</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>403</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13955</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27061438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27061438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinman</surname><given-names>E. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fridley</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>To spend or to save? Assessing energetic growth-storage tradeoffs in native and invasive woody plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oecologia</italic></source>
<volume>188</volume>
<fpage>659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>669</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-018-4177-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29882168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29882168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Ollas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>I. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Long-distance ABA transport can mediate distal tissue responses by affecting local ABA concentrations.</article-title>
<source><italic>J. Integr. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jipb.12605</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29052969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29052969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klinkhamer</surname><given-names>P. G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrieling</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Evolutionary changes in growth, regrowth and carbohydrate storage in an invasive plant.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci Rep.</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>14917</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-33218-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30297825?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30297825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Higher photosynthesis, nutrient- and energy-use efficiencies contribute to invasiveness of exotic plants in a nutrient poor habitat in northeast China.</article-title>
<source><italic>Physiol. Plantarum.</italic></source>
<volume>160</volume>
<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>382</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ppl.12566</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28321883?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28321883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Relationship between arbuscular mycorrhizas and plant growth: improvement or depression?</article-title>,&#x0201d; in <source><italic>Root Biology</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>464</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-75910-4_18</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickie</surname><given-names>I. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eissenstat</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Redefining fine roots improves understanding of belowground contributions to terrestrial biosphere processes.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>207</volume>
<fpage>505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>518</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.13363</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25756288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25756288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miedes</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanholme</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boerjan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The role of the secondary cell wall in plant resistance to pathogens.</article-title>
<source><italic>Front. Plant Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>5</volume>:<issue>358</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2014.00358</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25161657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25161657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nijjer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The effects of soil biota and fertilization on the success of <italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Appl. Soil Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsoil.2007.08.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nijjer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>The effect of mycorrhizal inoculum on the growth of five native tree species and the invasive Chinese tallow tree (<italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic>).</article-title>
<source><italic>Tex. J. Sci.</italic></source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>368</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pct053</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23574701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23574701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paudel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (AMF) and success of <italic>Triadica sebifera</italic> invasion in coastal transition ecosystems along the northern Gulf of Mexico.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>378</volume>
<fpage>337</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-014-2026-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>Y. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Root flavonoids are related to enhanced AMF colonization of an invasive tree.</article-title>
<source><italic>AoB Plants</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>:<issue>laa002</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aobpla/plaa002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 32071712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32071712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petruzzellis</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonet</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacaro</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Less safety for more efficiency: water relations and hydraulics of the invasive tree <italic>Ailanthus altissima</italic> (Mill.) Swingle compared with native <italic>Fraxinus ornus</italic> L.</article-title>
<source><italic>Tree Physiol.</italic></source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/treephys/tpy076</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29982793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29982793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pile</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stovall</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabler</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Mechanisms of Chinese tallow (<italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>) invasion and their management implications&#x02013; A review.</article-title>
<source><italic>For. Ecol. Manag.</italic></source>
<volume>404</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacala</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>An analytical treatment of root-to-shoot ratio and plant competition for soil nutrient and light.</article-title>
<source><italic>Am. Nat.</italic></source>
<volume>141</volume>
<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/285460</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19426022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19426022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Caballero</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caravaca</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rold&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The unspecificity of the relationships between the invasive <italic>Pennisetum setaceum</italic> and mycorrhizal fungi may provide advantages during its establishment at semiarid Mediterranean sites.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sci. Total Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>630</volume>
<fpage>1464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1471</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.02.321</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29554765?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29554765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Podazza</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Interdonato</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilal</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Soluble sugars: metabolism, sensing and abiotic stress: a complex network in the life of plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Signal. Behav.</italic></source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>388</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>393</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/psb.4.5.8294</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19816104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19816104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz-Lozano</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aroca</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Plant aquaporins and mycorrhizae: their regulation and involvement in plant physiology and performance</article-title>,&#x0201d; in <source><italic>Plant Aquaporins, Signaling and Communication in Plants</italic></source>, <role>eds</role>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Chaumont</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyerman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-49395-4_15</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shouman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>N. W. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kichey</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clossetkopp</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heberling</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobeissi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Functional shift of sycamore maple (<italic>Acer pseudoplatanus</italic>) towards greater plasticity and shade tolerance in its invasive range.</article-title>
<source><italic>Perspect. Plant Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ppees.2017.11.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beiler</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deslippe</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Philip</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teste</surname><given-names>F. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Mycorrhizal networks: mechanisms, ecology and modeling.</article-title>
<source><italic>Fungal. Biol. Rev.</italic></source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fbr.2012.01.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tardieu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thierry</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The physiological basis of drought tolerance in crop plants: a scenario-dependent probabilistic approach.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</italic></source>
<volume>69</volume>
<fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>759</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042817-040218</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 29553801?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29553801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thalmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santelia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Starch as a determinant of plant fitness under abiotic stress.</article-title>
<source><italic>New Phytol.</italic></source>
<volume>214</volume>
<fpage>943</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>951</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14491</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 28277621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28277621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Kleunen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A meta-analysis of trait differences between invasive and non-invasive plant species.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecol. Lett.</italic></source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>245</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2009.01418.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20002494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20002494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodruff</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederick</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Water stress, shoot growth and storage of non-structural carbohydrates along a tree height gradient in a tall conifer.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Cell Environ.</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1920</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1930</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3040.2011.02388.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21722142?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21722142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015a</year>). <article-title>Positive and negative biotic interactions and invasive <italic>Triadica sebifera</italic> tolerance to salinity: a cross-continent comparative study.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oikos</italic></source>
<volume>124</volume>
<fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/oik.01552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015b</year>). <article-title>The effects of fertilization on plant-soil interactions and salinity tolerance of invasive <italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>.</article-title>
<source><italic>Plant Soil</italic></source>
<volume>394</volume>
<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11104-015-2520-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Chinese Tallow Trees (<italic>Triadica sebifera</italic>) from the invasive range outperform those from the native range with an active soil community or phosphorus fertilization.</article-title>
<source><italic>PLoS One</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>:<issue>e74233</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074233</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24023930?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24023930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWalt</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>The effect of Chinese tallow tree (<italic>Sapium sebiferum</italic>) ecotype on soil&#x02013;plant system carbon and nitrogen processes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Oecologia</italic></source>
<volume>150</volume>
<fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-006-0512-2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 16917777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16917777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Differences in morphological and physiological traits between native and invasive populations of Sapium sebiferum.</article-title>
<source><italic>Funct. Ecol.</italic></source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>730</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2435.2007.01298.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>