<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Furthermore, our results indicated that pigs fed with RPA exhibited the highest ADFI and the backfat thickness in 10th rib but the lowest ATTD of CP of pigs. In normal diets, chlortetracycline has been widely added to feed as the growth promoter to increase growth rate and feed conversion of pigs [
 <xref rid="B31-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Recent studies have shown that the activity of antibiotics was affected by dietary protein supply [
 <xref rid="B15-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, there is little data available investigating the effects of chlortetracycline supplementation in reduced-protein, amino acid-supplemented diets on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, and carcass traits of growing-finishing pigs. In the current study, with similar ATTD of gross energy, RPA treatment significantly increases feed intake of pigs, which in turn causes excess energy to eventually lead to deposition of fat at the 10th rib. Similarly, Cho et al. [
 <xref rid="B32-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] have pointed that exposure of mice to subtherapeutic doses of antibiotics also increased total and relative body fat mass. However, further research is needed to clarify the underlying mechanism of RPA leading to increased feed intake. Our data also suggest that subtherapeutic doses of chlortetracycline supplementation in reduced-protein diet may have no significant effect on improving growth performance of growing-finishing pigs. Additionally, the RPA-fed pigs had a lower population of 
 <italic class="italic">Lactobacillus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> in ileal digesta compared with the RPD-fed pigs. These results are consistent with those of Allen et al. [
 <xref rid="B33-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] and Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-08-00159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], who reported that that population of 
 <italic class="italic">E. coli</italic> in intestine is decreased in chlortetracycline-treated pigs and broilers, respectively. These results suggest that RPA treatment broadly reduces the population of 
 <italic class="italic">Escherichia coli</italic> and probiotic bacteria. 
</p>
