<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Considering the origin of n-3 LC-PUFA in the marine environment it is therefore no surprise that fish and seafood, traditionally from capture fisheries, have been the source of virtually all the EPA and DHA in our diet. It is well documented that capture fisheries around the world are either at or beyond their sustainable limits, plateauing at around 90 million tonnes per annum for the last decade or so and there is no prospect of this increasing in the future [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. However, with an ever-growing global population, demand for fish and seafood has constantly increased and aquaculture has increasingly filled this demand with over half of all fish and seafood now being farmed [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. However, there is a problem. While fish vary in the amount of n-3 LC-PUFA they can contain, depending largely upon whether oily or lean, they produce very little or none themselves, again dependent upon species. Therefore, essentially all the EPA and DHA they contain is derived from their diet, the natural prey organisms in wild-captured food fish or the manufactured feeds for farmed fish [
 <xref rid="B2-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Consequently, the only way to ensure farmed fish contained high levels of EPA and DHA was to include these fatty acids in the feed and, until now, the only way to do this was to use large amounts of fish oil and fishmeal, themselves derived from marine fisheries that are similarly finite and limiting [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. This, then, is the paradox. While aquaculture has increasingly become the major source of EPA and DHA for the burgeoning human population, it has also, at the same time, become the greatest consumer of the world’s available supply of EPA and DHA [
 <xref rid="B27-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] and, consequently, the sector most proactive in ensuring adequate future supplies [
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-00089" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>].
</p>
