<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>
  <italic>Anopheles stephensi</italic> with three different biotypes is a major vector of malaria in Asia. It breeds in a wide range of habitats. Therefore, safer and more sustainable methods are needed to control its immature stages rather than chemical pesticides. The larvicidal and antibacterial properties of the 
  <italic>Pelargonium roseum</italic> essential oil (PREO) formulations were investigated against mysorensis and intermediate forms of 
  <italic>An</italic>. 
  <italic>stephensi</italic> in laboratory conditions. A series of nanoemulsions containing different amounts of PREO, equivalent to the calculated LC
  <sub>50</sub> values for each 
  <italic>An</italic>. 
  <italic>stephensi</italic> form, and various quantities of surfactants and co-surfactants were developed. The physical and morphological properties of the most lethal formulations were also determined. PREO and its major components, i.e. citronellol (21.34%), L-menthone (6.41%), linalool (4.214%), and geraniol (2.19%), showed potent larvicidal activity against the studied mosquitoes. The LC
  <sub>50/90</sub> values for mysorensis and intermediate forms were computed as 11.44/42.42 ppm and 12.55/47.69 ppm, respectively. The F48/F44 nanoformulations with 94% and 88% lethality for the mysorensis and intermediate forms were designated as optimized formulations. The droplet size, polydispersity index, and zeta-potential for F48/F44 were determined as 172.8/90.95 nm, 0.123/0.183, and -1.08/-2.08 mV, respectively. These results were also confirmed by TEM analysis. Prepared formulations displayed antibacterial activity against larval gut bacteria in the following order of decreasing inhibitory: LC
  <sub>90</sub>, optimized nanoemulsions, and LC
  <sub>50</sub>. PREO-based formulations were more effective against mysorensis than intermediate. Compared to the crude PREO, the overall larvicidal activity of all nanoformulations boosted by 20% and the optimized formulations by 50%. The sensitivity of insect gut bacteria may be a crucial factor in determining the outcome of the effect of toxins on target insects. The formulations designed in the present study may be a good option as a potent and selective larvicide for 
  <italic>An</italic>. 
  <italic>stephensi</italic>.
 </p>
</abstract>
