<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A key premise of this paper is that existing hypotheses that predict invasion success can be effectively complemented by the Human Release Hypothesis ( 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). Our own data, of course, focused only on one species – which is enough to pose a hypothesis, but far too little to test its general usefulness. We want to emphasize that our hypothesis is complementary and acknowledge the fact that multiple interacting mechanisms often contribute to invasions 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>
 </sup>. To this end, we endorse integrated testing of hypotheses, to identify if Human Release is the main driver of high abundance of invasive species. While Human Release could also be manipulated via experiments, we recommend to investigate on-site land use patterns via direct field studies, or at a global scale, drawing on appropriate land use proxies (e.g. anthropogenic biomes, human appropriation of net primary production, population census data). As demonstrated with this case study and recommended by Catford 
 <italic>et al.</italic> (2009) 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 </sup>, integrated hypothesis testing could follow the PAB framework in an incremental approach. To that effect, a top down approach, starting with the most complex scenario (PAB + HR) and then gradually eliminating non-plausible explanations, could serve to identify under what circumstances Human Release is an important driver. Furthermore, to draw universal conclusions, case studies on a single study species should be designed with multi-site sampling, as well as case studies in certain environments be conducted on multiple species 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 </sup>. Ideally, the hypothesis should be tested by comparing the same species in its native and invasive range on ecological similar abandoned and maintained sites. However, such comparisons could be difficult since we state that land abandonment is rare in the native range of a species. If comparable sites are not available, these differences in land use between ranges can also provide insights on the validity of the Human Release Hypothesis. Studies should then focus on long-term monitoring of populations in both ranges to quantify if they are being diminished by land use practice.
</p>
