<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39" class="p">Label-free and non-targeted techniques have gained importance in recent years, since they avoid such labelling related limitations and allow to study biological samples in a way that more closely reflects their native environment. The use of Raman spectroscopy in microscopy enables label-free and chemically selective imaging (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Molecular identification originates from the specific frequencies of molecular vibrations appearing in a Raman spectrum [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. A drawback is that spontaneous Raman scattering is a very weak optical effect compared to fluorescence or elastic light scattering. Approximately only one of 10
 <sup class="sup">6</sup> photons or less of scattered light undergoes an energy loss or gain, so-called Stokes and anti-Stokes Raman scattering (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>) through interaction with the molecular vibrations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. The imaging of a typical biological sample with Raman microscopy is not always suitable as it requires very long image acquisition times, even when intense laser beams are used [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>]. In contrast, Coherent anti-Stokes Raman scattering (CARS) is a nonlinear optical technique (for details see Methods section) delivering a Raman equivalent signal of distinctively higher intensity which allows much shorter acquisition times. CARS is therefore highly suitable for imaging applications, especially for the fast, non-destructive imaging of biological samples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>] and has been used e.g. for monitoring the differentiation state of stem cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>] or the detection of lipids by assessing the strong C-H vibration at a single-band frequency [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>].
</p>
