<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In hypersaline solutions, cells must maintain the water activity of their cytoplasm higher than that of the surrounding brine to avoid loss of water (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Csonka, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown, 1990</xref>). Moreover, in order to generate cell turgor pressure, which is considered to be the driving force for cell extension, growth, and division, the cells need to maintain an intracellular osmotic pressure that is somewhat greater than that of the growth medium (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Csonka, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown, 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oren, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Welsh, 2000</xref>). Microbial strategies to cope with osmotic stress include maintenance of high intracellular salt concentrations and/or a range of low-molecular-weight organic solutes, including trehalose, glycine betaine, or glutamate, that are compatible with biological function of the cells (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown, 1976</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oren, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B217" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Welsh, 2000</xref>). Such organic compounds can either be taken up from the environment or synthesized by the organisms. Halophilic sulfate-reducing bacteria appear to have the ability to synthesize trehalose and to uptake glycine betaine, with the ability to accumulate glycine betaine from the environment being energetically more favorable than the synthesis of trehalose, which requires a significant investment of both energy and fixed carbon (
 <xref rid="B218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Welsh et al., 1996</xref>). Bacterial sulfate reduction, including sulfate reduction coupled to AOM, is sustained at high salinities such as in deep hypersaline basins from the Mediterranean Sea (
 <xref rid="B206" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">van der Wielen et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B207" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">van der Wielen and Heijs, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Borin et al., 2009</xref>), Gulf of Mexico (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lloyd et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B230" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhuang et al., 2016</xref>), Gulf of Cadiz (
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Maignien et al., 2013</xref>), in a hypersaline Dead Sea aquifer (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Avrahamov et al., 2014</xref>), and the Great Salt Lake in Utah (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kjeldsen et al., 2007</xref>). A consequence of the energetically costly adaptation to osmotic stress is that with increasing salinity, metabolic reactions that yield little energy, such as the oxidation of acetate coupled to sulfate reduction, are no longer carried out (
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oren, 1999</xref>). It can be speculated that in such cases, other organisms may use acetate. Candidates could be so far uncultivated bacterial phyla that have been widely detected in anaerobic environments (BD1-5, OP11, and OD1), who are likely to play important yet unrecognized roles in hydrogen production, sulfur cycling, and fermentation of refractory sedimentary carbon (
 <xref rid="B226" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wrighton et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kantor et al., 2013</xref>). There is evidence that these organisms are present at hydrocarbon seeps and in deep-sea anoxic brine lakes (
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pachiadaki et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Antunes et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aoki et al., 2014</xref>). Acetoclastic methanogenesis is negatively impacted by high salinity (
 <xref rid="B212" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Waldron et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B228" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al., 2017</xref>). However, due to high salinity, glycine betaine and dimethylsulfoniopropionate (DMSP) and their degradation products trimethylamine and dimethyl sulfide (DMS) become available to microbes inhabiting hypersaline environments (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">King, 1984</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oren, 1990</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lai and Gunsalus, 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B218" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Welsh et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lai et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B229" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhuang et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B230" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Such methylated compounds serve as substrate for methanogenesis in hypersaline environments (
 <xref rid="B230" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhuang et al., 2016</xref>), which highlights the possibility that there is a link between the formation of zero-valent sulfur and carbon cycling via methanogenesis in hypersaline, sulfidic environments such as the Urania deep-sea basin.
</p>
