<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phytochemicals (primary and secondary metabolites) are well known for their vast medicinal benefits to plants and human [
 <xref rid="B100-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. The primary metabolites—such as carbohydrate, proteins, chlorophyll, lipids, nucleic, and amino acids [
 <xref rid="B101-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]—are responsible for plants’ biochemical reactions such as respiration and photosynthesis [
 <xref rid="B102-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. The secondary metabolites are majorly alkaloids, phenols, terpenoids, flavonoids, saponins, steroids, tannins, and glycosides, which play important roles in protecting the plants against damages and improving plant aroma, coloration and flavor [
 <xref rid="B101-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>], The phytochemicals are present in various parts of the plants especially in the three major parts viz. the leaves, stems and roots. Their percentage composition in each plant may vary depending on environmental conditions, variety and processing methods [
 <xref rid="B101-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Previous studies have shown that phenolic compounds are the most abundant and widely distributed phytoconstituents (45%), followed by steroids and terpenoids (27%), and alkaloids (18%) [
 <xref rid="B101-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Alkaloids, flavonoids, tannins, and phenolic compounds are the most common constituents that have been studied in phytochemistry [
 <xref rid="B104-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-ijms-22-00618" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Several compounds from these classes have been identified and investigated from 
 <italic>Parkia</italic> plants for various pharmacological activities. Despite the enormous reports on the phytochemical screening of different species from the genus 
 <italic>Parkia</italic>, structure identification and purification of compounds from these species are scarcely reported compared to other genera. The compounds were identified using high-performance liquid chromatography with diode-array detector (HPLC-DAD), liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LCMS), flow analysis-ionization electrospray ion trap tandem mass spectrometry (FIA-ESI-IT-MS), gas chromatography time-of-flight mass spectrometry (GC/ToF-MS), high-performance liquid chromatography-electrospray ion mass spectrometry (HPLC-ESI-MS), and chromatographic purification from the fraction and characterization through nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR).
</p>
